hey so getting started together I want to say that I appreciate
the um community that uh forms in the little
chat I um I do see that I don't see it while I'm teaching really because it's
too much but I do um check it out as we're coming in and I was appreciate the
warmth and friendliness and that many of you know each other and if any of you are new to today you're completely
welcome into our little online chat community so this week we are connecting
with various wholesome qualities as a support for our meditation so bringing
them in at the beginning and then allowing them to kind of just flavor their practice that we do and I hope
you'll see over the course of the week that this is a skillful thing to do and you're free to do it in whatever way
works for you if you find it valuable so the quality for today is
generosity such as sharing our care in the chat with each
other and let's settle in now for sitting so finding a posture that's
comfortable giving your body some
care maybe you're sitting maybe you're lying
down or something else and just allowing the attention to
come
inward feeling how the body is from the
inside not an idea or what you think it would look like in the mirror but what
it feels like to be in this body right now
whether it's comfortable or not however much energy there
is and just settling into to that
softening maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths
in and on the exhale letting the body settled into its
posture perhaps finding as you settle out the obvious tensions there's an
internal strength or energy that you can touch
into I find the body kind of naturally wants to be upright
perhaps feeling that contact points where you're sitting your weight is
resting on something and feeling those pressure points and softening into them
allowing yourself to be supported
giving your weight over to what you're sitting
on connecting in with the simple feelings of
breathing in and out so that we have kind of
a simple rhythmic connection to the
present natural breath
and in this sitting we'll again begin with a a simple use of the mental aspect of
the mind to deliberately bring in a
memory of a time when you did an act
that I'm going to call clean generosity so it means it was simple and
direct and easy nothing complex that you had to arrange
or debate about whether you were doing just something that was so easy
like as simple as holding the door for someone or
um petting a dog that looked like it wanted
petting handing somebody uh the change that they couldn't find in their wallet
at the checkout and saying here I've got
that something really simple like that and just take into the body what it
feels like to recall that moment allowing it to register
breathing with it maybe allowing it to get distributed through the cells the
way the breath does and not to be grandiose or put a
self into it it was just staying with the
feeling and then switch to recall a time when you received
someone else's generosity again in a really simple
way maybe it wasn't even somebody that you
knew how does it feel in the body to recall that
situation so really taking that in also
then letting go of this mental activity
of bringing up memories and coming back into the fully into the
present moment feeling the body sitting the
breath and maybe really tuning in to the energetic side of the
body flow of Life Force in the
body and then also including the emotional side the
heart allowing those to
integrate it's fine if in the present moment we have some difficult emotions
or pain in the body that's all part of the
field Maybe will remember that feeling of simple generosity and just allow
those to be
there and then gently relaxing even further in just taking
up the
mindfulness the flow of occurrences in the body in
minded perhaps with a focus like the breath perhaps more open
awareness just letting that flow
on
e
e e
can there be a sense in our way of meeting
experience of generosity of giving the wholesome
States our full attention or appreciation sometimes we skip over our
wholesomeness and for the UNH wholesome more giving them space to be
there but not get further entrenched let's say
so having a sense of how to guide ourselves with the normal flow of
recurrences such that the Mind stays fresh and free and on
track we can bring in the other qualities we've worked with like
clarity about what is helpful and what is not
and then having a very open and yet clear attitude about how to
be with whatever is arising for
us like a good guide for
ourselves
e
e e
a deeper aspect of generosity really just a deepening and
a spreading of it is Letting Go it's the same movement of
mind that gives and that lets [Music]
go so allowing the mind to continually
release what is arising generously taking it in seeing
it and then letting it go to turn to the next
thing resting in the sense of Letting Go
that allows experience to keep flowing
e
e e
one of the fruits of meditation practice is to begin to meet
experience with a generosity of spirit generosity of heart if you
prefer and that can begin internally with
the willingness to greet and be with whatever
arises it's not all Pleasant it's not all
wholesome but to have a generosity of spirit okay this is
here and then further to appreciate and really let register what is wholesome
what is beautiful because there's a lot of that too starting to become able to tolerate
the fullness of experience the fullness of this being human and for some it's a big process to
release the resistance the holding the oh I don't know about that kind of
feeling I think it's quite ongoing for us to keep opening that
way and it then can spill outward and start to come into our life in certain
ways meeting other people with a generosity of
heart seeing them as the complex beings that they are having seen our own
complexity and so affording them some flexibility in our
response some generosity and Imagining the possibilities for
them some willingness to release or reactivity that might come
up so less often meeting the world with a sense of grasping or
fear or resistance or attack or dulling out Turning
Away more and more having the width and breadth of heart that we can
meet what is arising in some
way and find a skillful approach to it there isn't just
one so we'll each find our way but this generosity of heart and
spirit can be felt by others and it even if they don't know what it is quite
consciously it's a feeling that's brought and it tends to bring out the possibilities for
others so the world needs this kind of energy and it can't be faked but the
degree to which our practice cultivates it we can become aware of it and let it
express so may there be just a sliver more of the generosity part as you go
out into into the world today
so we'll continue on with these 10 uh
attributes or epithets of the Buddha's mind which we'll talk about nine of them
in detail and we've seen up to now uh that the Buddha's mind was free of all
defilements and he was able to manifest that in his behavior and way way of
meeting life and then furthermore he turned that liberated mind toward seeing
clearly How the Universe operates how it is for people with their minds and
bodies and Karma and life and death he he was willing to take in the whole
picture the beautiful The Not So Beautiful uh he saw and understood all
of that and was not couldn't be thrown off by any of that so these are captured
in these epithets we've talked about so far AR
S V Charo sug and Loca
Vu and that could be the end of the story you know he had complete knowledge
inner and outer and those two aren't so separate for a Buddha um but it isn't
the end of the story actually because the Buddha chose to act and specifically
he chose to teach so the two attributes or epithets for today are about the
Buddha's skill in teaching he was a great teacher and we are all the
beneficiaries of that still learning his teachings to this
day so remember that we're meant to you know reflect on these qualities and turn
them over in our mind and when we
consider this great teaching of the Buddha we can be uplifted and inspired
by that we might also see that some of how we train and teach ourselves is
there we've learned something from the teachings about how to guide ourselves
skillfully I mean nobody's there with you on the cushion and kind of my voice comes in sometimes but um you know it's
you and your mind so you know how are we training and teaching ourselves
throughout the day guiding ourselves and then third um reflecting
on the Buddha's teaching qualities can can prompt us to consider our qualities
as students also so these are some of the things I want to bring in today as we talk about the the two attributes
that relate to to teaching so the first is a longish one it's ano porad
sarti and sarti is a trainer it's literally was the name of a profession
like an elephant trainer or a horse trainer you know back in the Buddhist time and anuo means unexcelled there's
no one better and Puris sadama is an interesting word um pora means person
and then uh dhama has to do with taming it's not to be confused with dhma d h m
m a that's the Dharma this is dhma d m ma a it's a different word and it has to
do with taming so porad is usually translated as persons To Be Tamed so the
full phrase um is usually trans ated as unexcelled trainer of persons To Be
Tamed so the Buddha teaches those who are
trainable it's interesting right um so I find myself when I reflect on this so
the Buddha is the unexcelled trainer of persons To Be Tamed first of all we have
to um admit that there are parts of us that would probably do well to Be
Tamed and um so we can think about how okay this is the the side of the Buddha
that can meet what is unskillful or UNH wholesome in the world and find a way to
kind of put that more on track you know to train it to train it up so that it's
not wandering around and causing problems so one question for us is are
we willing to Be Tamed or trained and there's some some room for humility uh
it's important to admit that we really are under the sway of greed hatred and
delusion sometimes we go too far and see ourselves as only possessing those qualities but sometimes we also have an
idea that we you know that we don't in some way I actually had to kind of
explicitly admit early in my practice that I wanted to be trained it's not
that I thought I was perfect but somehow the admission mattered like I remember a
moment where I decided you know what I really I want to submit myself for training here maybe like in 12 step or
something you have to have that moment where you say yeah this is a problem uh
this mind could use a little training you know and we're you know why
is it that sometimes we don't you know why is it that we need to make this admission kind of
conscious we're not free because we have ignorance in the mind that's kind of the
root problem and in English the word ignorance suggests something kind of passive like
we we just don't know something um but in Buddhism AA is actually an active
Turning Away something in our mind doesn't want to see and so we look away
and that's actually why it takes effort to train our mind you know why our mind keeps wanting to go back it doesn't
really there's a part of it that doesn't really want to wake up um so working
with that is part of you know like working with training an animal and
maybe it's not only our own effort you know our willful effort so I see this quality
of the Buddha also as a practice where we offer ourselves up for training it's
not a task for me to do but more like an offering up yeah to the Buddha um yes I
I submit myself for training I will follow these instructions because I know that my mind
will benefit from that so that's one side of the teaching then we get to kind
of the inspirational side which is uh the term is
SATA Manus okay and sat is a teacher satar is
the root word and DEA manusana means of deavas and humans gods and humans so the
Buddha is the teacher of gods and humans so this is I think um similar to
the training but you know the trainer part is like he's kind of you know working with an
animal um that need you know that needs to be guided to some kind of good
behavior but then there's the the teaching part the actual imparting of
Knowledge and Skills the supporting of what is wholesome in us we're not just
like an animal being trained actually we have the capacity to understand the
process to learn the principles of the Dharma to be touched in the Heart by the
teachings of the Dharma it's not quite the same way a dog is touched by our
training right it's a there's a more elevated side of the Buddhist teaching
also so um for us then there can be the inspirational side the practical
question are we being intelligent students are we using all of our
beautiful amazing capabilities of mind and heart to bring the Dharma into our
lives and let it flower do we listen to the Dharma do we ask questions so that
we can understand you know the dog doesn't ask questions about why it's being trained a certain way this or that
you know but we're meant to participate and bring in our understanding our engagement or
enthusiasm and then put that into practice and use it to to feed um
practice I think that's why it's said specifically gods and humans those are
in the Buddhist cosmology those are the higher Minds higher forms of mind um
ones that can really understand and uh participate in their training so a SAT a
teacher more than a trainer is someone who empowers us who grows the good in us
for our own benefit so that eventually we can become our own teacher we have
the capability gods and humans have the capability to also take on qualities of
being teachers and it's said at the first stage of Awakening um in this practice
that we become what's called independent in the Dharma so we become able to walk
the path ourselves stand our own two feet if you would so
that's really a beautiful thing um as a student uh we have a choice about how we
navigate how we uh have relationships with teachers and I would suggest that
we look for teachers who want us to be strong be smart be beneficial in the
world teachers who want us to discover our own inner
wealth and teachers who have the qualities that the Buddha named in those
who teach the Dharma actually a few months ago gild did one of these five day series on the qualities of a teacher
the ud suta there are five of them um at least in one of these lists so I'll just
review them briefly but it might be interesting to look back on that week so
a teacher should teach uh step by step in a progressive understanding so that you can move toward greater and greater
good greater and greater wholesomeness a teacher should speak uh giving reasons understand helping you
understand what you're doing and why a teacher should teach with care
with love with concern with tenderness um not with cruelty and so
forth and beating you into shape but with care and kindness
teachers are teaching not for profit but for the intrinsic goodness of the Dharma
wanting to share it with people and also not teaching in a way that aises
themselves and disparages others so even if they have a distinct teaching style
they simply teach that as the embodiment of how they teach without claiming that
others aren't doing it right or so forth so
teaching being a student and finding a teacher finding qualities of the teacher
within ourselves this too is part of the awakened mind and The Awakening mind
that we have so one upshot maybe of reflecting in this way is to have gratitude for our
great Fortune of having encountered the teachings and also amazement maybe at
the Buddha's generosity and compass passion to teach and also to the long
line of practitioners and other teachers who have kept this Dharma alive over the
centuries so that it comes to us and we can still learn and benefit from it
everyone here has seen the benefit of the Dharma in some way and thank goodness that we that it was taught and
that we heard it and that we had the opportunity and that we're even having the opportunity to practice it
so the amazing teaching of the Buddha is still echoing today 2600 years later and
we can embody that through being a sincere and engaged student of our own
Humanity letting that flower forth and become most of what we can
be so thank you for that for doing that in your own unique special way and for this
chance to be together today and tomorrow there's even yet more about the
Buddha take care