good morning good
day just happy to see the streaming chat
messages yeah
and just all take a moment to kind of gather here uh maybe Savor a little sense of
being in community together as the people Gathering
here in this online virtual space
so happy to be with you all everyone uh we're coming to the last um morning or
last day of this a sequence that I've been uh hopefully taking you through um
as a sort of a nature guide um doing a nature within
ourselves and so this week um we did opening to
the uh aspect of Earth elements
grounding and uh enlivening through being with our breath
and enriching our experiences by being with um our
emotions and thoughts and then the we also included
spaciousness yesterday kind of really like this mountain Inner Mountain a life Mountain
surrounded by nature and the space And So today we're coming to
the um piece of
um um of clarifying or seeing clearly
knowing clearly I kind of have been preparing ourselves um along the way and
so today we'll be uh going through the sequence um but then also open to clear
seeing and clear knowing so okay we'll begin
[Music]
pausing pausing to start
start from where we are and start from how we
are just as it is
releasing demands for things to be
otherwise releasing expectations
Here and
Now what is the felt sense of here in this
place and this time
feeling and sensing the global sense of a body
sitting lying down standing however your posture is
like arting your attention to wherever the body makes a
contact with the floor Earth
chairs beds
sensing
contact pressure
weight temperature
allow this earthy body resting into the contact
maybe there is a sense of a resting down or resting
back allow the contact to
become as big as it likes to or as
deep as it likes to
a sense of a rootedness
grounded steady quiet
sitting like a quiet Mountain Within
quiet
breath quiet aliveness
you may not have a words for them and that's totally okay
sensing and feeling a quiet
flow of the
breath enlightening the whole
body e
you may be rhythmic in and
out up and
down or it may be not
a sense of a wonder and awe may come in
the movements of the emotions can
enrich in Rich this very sense of Being Human
sensing and the [Music] feeling the spaciousness
all around or
[Music]
within e
releasing stories
ideas and conceptual overlays
allow the knowing and
seeing to be emerging from the felt sense
Let each breath slow freely
Let each sensation
dance fre
Let each thought
float
freely
e
for e
[Music]
[Music] so we finished
um this sikaya 22.11
uh that Ed the three similes of the sutta to um highlight or kind of
describe some overarching characteristics of the
practice and today um I feel like I have more to say
about the sua and that is um I like to
Circle back to the opening statement of the suta and this is let me read this line
that I say that the destruction of the tins is for one who knows and
sees not for one who does not know and
does not see and so this sense of um knowing and
the see seeing is a very important uh kind of um
aspect of our cultivation you know using the similes
of the chicken and eggs and hatching and
um the Oz handle being worn off and and
the rope that ties the uh ship rots away
um and they uh what they also offer is
that this layers layers of beliefs of fixed
ideas and our conceptual overlays are shedded are kind of put
down or uh let go of and when this happens um
um there is a increasing degrees of knowing and seeing little by little and
they become more and more available to us and this kind of knowing and seeing
is very different from um the you know reading the book and getting some sense
and that is one aspect of um a knowing
but it's not uh the complete aspect of the knowing and so
when we're only counting on conceptual level of understanding and to want to
manage our way through the conceptual lenses often we shut down so much of
ourselves that can know can see
differently the part of ourselves that knows and sees don't always speak
English or Chinese or Spanish you know
so um you know our body knows maybe through the responses in the nerve
systems or responses in our cellular kind of a feeling or uh in the movements
of the breath our heart knows uh that may manifest as
a certain kind of a felt sense in our heart
space and so much of our training is to begin to
open to this wide range of ways of a Being Human that is able to know and
[Music] sense in this um Rich ways when we allow
this a wide ranged way of knowing and then seeeing and Things become more more
clear and so today I'm kind of wanted to bring yet another simile this this is a
week of uh simile from the sutta it's not from the same sutta but I think it's
relevant to this notion of uh knowing and seeing and this Su is
from maim nikaya and 39 it's a Simo of um a clear Mountain
Lake and I like to kind of expand a little bit because you know in order to
get to a clear Mountain Lake and I would imagine you have to kind of you know get
on a high Bing Trail and and walk um to
get to the mountain lake and so for
me uh this part that was not actually you know hiking and walking the mountain
trail is not part of the the sutta but for me uh it evokes something in me that
is um the person in order to get to the Clear Mountain
Lake um has to take the path has to walk kind of like us having to
practice um walk the Noble eight-fold Path and as we engage in this as we hike
in this Mountain Trails uh we put down a lot of
preoccupations that we have in our mind about things um
uh we want to do or projects we need to manage and we're more and more present
on the trail in the Mountain Trails and maybe we'll have a sense of a
slowing down and maybe a sense of a life Mountain comes
in and so the Chatters in our mind might quiet quiet
down and so that's the process of the practice a so we put down a lot of uh inner
Chatters or preoccupations and when we get to the
mountain lake um can our mind and heart feels
more clear I want to read you this um Mountain Lake Sim here it
says practitioners it's like a Lake in a mountain range transparent clear and
undisturbed standing on the shore a person with eyes could see oysters
shells Stones Pebbles and a fish moving
about and holding still that person would think this is a
transparent clear and un Disturbed Lake here there are oysters shells
Stones Pebbles and a fish moving about and a holding
still practitioners in the same way a
practitioner understands the Dua as it is and so on it goes through all the
four noble truths and knows this clear clearly just like seeing through um the
clear transparent undisturbed Mountain
Lake can see things moving around and see
things um without the filters that we put on
without the filters of our own judgments
beliefs and without out all the act reactivities that may be
operating and so that becomes available and possible to
us and one thing I'd like to highlight that um in the sutta that we went
through this week that we know that this seeing and
knowing becomes available available to us
naturally uh when the uh kind of stings faded
away and also I'd like to say that the cl Clarity uh sense of being really
clear they don't have to come all at once you know it's not like a big band
you know kind of big switch or something that you just turn on but
rather um the felt sense with the similes and this hiking the mountain
trail the mind gets more and more clear uh it feels more at least to me it
feels more like things become increasingly clear little by little
little by little and gradually and so for most of us
that's the process of um our practice it's a gradual
process little by little we're less caught by the habitual
reactivities or little by little uh that we begin to experience a kind of a
well-being or joy to whatever degree that may be
available to us and little by little we chipping away
the Tendencies underlying
Tendencies and I would also say that um for most of us and that the uh there are
also times that the things get very very
difficult and the invitation is that we practice with a kind and Compassionate
Heart as best as we are able and this phrase as best as we are able is very
important because that's the truth of how we can practice we can't practice
more than what we're able and surely we'll get lost on the
path and whenever we're able we come back
and period we come back that's it releasing kind of blaming judging
shaming criticizing we know those are just extra
um burden that we had to carry and so even though I'm using this
mountain hike um as a a way to illustrate this
uh but the path we're undertaking is a Inner Path in fact so
much of the training is about us staying where we are how we are right here and
we stop trying to fix ourselves up and fix
others and so we make ourselves available to uh different possibilities
I like to end uh with a quote from uh
windberry and this says the world cannot be discovered by a
journey of Miles no matter how long but
only by a spiritual journey or journey of 1
inch very arduous and a humbling and the
joyful by which we arrive at the ground
at our feet and learn to be at
[Music]
home thank you dear may we all learn to be at home