Hello friends Hello friends good morning good afternoon good
evening um wherever you are whatever time zone you're on it's uh lovely
to be with you and and feel your presence um on the
channel in uh let's turn this down here we go okay to see your presence on um on
YouTube there you are yeah nice lovely to see your um yeah feel your presence
very sweet um so um I'm Nikki
murri um and uh have been away for a while
traveling in Asia delighted to be back and supporting the S and offering
teachings this morning so so for the theme of this week um I'd like to
um actually let's let's just sit together I'll introduce the theme afterwards how's that I think that's
better let's just sit and I'll introduce it through this uh um dra our s together
so let us let us land let us
land let us land in our bodies in this moment in time wherever
we
are arriving and settling here arriving settling
here feeling the connection of our feet
with the earth I am
here letting ourselves feel the connection of our sit
bones with the cushion the
chair just as the Buddha touched the Earth on the
night of his enlight Enlightenment we're touching the Earth
We're touching the Earth with our bodies this Earth that we're
on allowing to feel how our body is on the earth supported by gravity allowing
our body to relax the muscles to relax
feeling supported by gravity there is a sense of trust that here we
can can let go of the muscles and soften relax into our chair into our
cushion our seat and gravity is here we're not going to
go flying into the space like on a spaceship traveling even though we are
traveling through the universe and at astounding speeds and yet gravity
there's a sense of trust that yes the heart can
relax and connect with the breath this breath here
letting the INB breath and the out
breath blow flow through the body
it's not so much that we are consciously breathing or controlling the
breath and if there is this subtle control of the breath no need let that
go and really let the breath be
free calming soothing settling the mind and heart
we show up we show up again and again to our
practice to our meditation practice to to this moment
at this moment being aware lovingly kindly aware
of the breath of the body of this mind
states with a sense of trust
that that we are planting seeds this practice Works in some way we
may not understand and be able to articulate
even it's okay but in some
way it works in some
way and letting this
[Music] knowing be a sense of settling
confidence stability as perhaps the mind wanders to
thoughts and it's okay Minds do
that inviting inviting awareness bag to settle not
with judgment or anger self- disappointment oh here you go again none
of that none of that not NE it even if very subtle so subtle
sometimes sense of
confidence confidence uprightness in how you're sitting how you're sitting in
your posture sitting like a
Buddha allowing your inner Buddha to be known to be
seen one breath that is
time
e
e e
and if you find at any point that the mind has wandered into a story and
is lost remember feel the Earth feel the Earth
with your feet with your sit bones or even touching perhaps the Earth
or your cushion or your chair it's really your it's um it's a reminder I'm here
I'm here I'm on this Earth a sense of stability uprightness
trust
connecting connecting again and again
remember that this reconnecting is always available we might forget and
feel lost and it's so simple to turn our
attention to it so simple to just turn our attention to
it when when we
remember and it's
okay it's okay we all get lost sometimes we all do don't judge
yourself the more we judge it becomes heavier and harder
regaining connection with the body with the breath with the
Earth
e
e e
here here
here connecting through your feet with the Earth your sit bones
here here stabilizes the heart and mind
here just here sweetheart
here not the past not the future here just here simply here
if today especially the mind is busy as Monday can
be feel your feet on the earth
stabilize connect here
here
e
e e
as we turn slowly to bring the sitting period
to a [Music]
close I'm aware of how you might be feeling a little
different than when you arrived tiny bit different perhaps maybe
a little more subtle perhaps the mind is just a bit
calmer the heart
maybe very subtle perhaps
perhaps you feel a sense of connection with your feet to the Earth your sit
[Music] Bones the breath moving through more than you did before they're more
available just a tiny bit more
available and let these sh shifts tiny
shifts ways that the heart and mind can [Music] settle and resources of stability become
a little more available just tiny bit more Let It Be a source of confidence
and Trust yes
yes yes planting SE seeds anding
seeds and may our practice of planting seeds of growing in trust and
confidence for the possibility of change more peace more
trust more ease may this support us and support
others with whom we
interact and those they interact
with radiating out May this support May our
practice support all beings
everywhere may they have sense of confidence and Trust in the midst of doubt and
confusion support them may all beings
everywhere have ease may all beings everywhere have
well-being all beings everywhere be free including myself
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
and it take a moment to swap recordings for the next piece
I had forgotten how sweet it is to be with the morning s and or the 7 a.m. s
okay California time and and and see all your um Reflections all your yeah the
names scrolling by yeah very sweet worldwide so many
places in this world a so sweet oh my heart is
[Music] warmed yeah
great so so the theme for today as you might have gathered um
actually the theme for this week is um is
confidence trust the word in poly is uh
Sada and um wait where's where are my notes hold
on a second I'm having technical difficulty my so many windows open hold
on here where did my notes go here we go I can always riff but it's better to
have notes Here we go there they are great okay great
lovely so so Sada the word in poly Sada s a d d
ha a Sada I'm sure one of you will write it
uh in chat Sada and um s Sada actually
Sada I should say it right Sada because there is a um um elongation that the a
at the end is long Sada Sada Sada yeah that's better better poly pronunciation
poly being the language of the Buddha Sada so so the word Sada um translated
as trust confidence and sometimes faith and and um it is a very significant
uh concept and not just so much concept but in our practice I mean Buddhist is
not so much conceptual I I take I take this practice to be really practical and when I started practicing uh years and
years ago I was um I just wanted to practice I just wanted to to um I
actually said on let's uh it's said you know what I'm going to put in the chat s eyes yeah there you go Henry Henry
that's the yeah that's it Henry and J me thank you and you even got the yeah the the um uh diacritics right on the a
thank you I love this song we all support each other I love it this is so sweet so um yeah there's a little bit of
a delay between the zoom and the YouTube so it takes like 30 seconds after you put the um something in chat for me to
acknowledge it you know this already I know you know anyway so um so yeah I was saying that
when I started practicing uh decades ago I was just interested in meditating and practicing and and the concepts and and
the teachings only I became interested later so the uh this is copied and paste
it from Wikipedia love it very sweet um so so Sada so it's interesting because
um some people um come to practicing meditation mindfulness or become
interested in Buddhism um from being um not interested in faith faith-based
religion somehow there's a sense of this faith in uh that we associate with um
with theistic religions with with having to have a faith in God as a uh entry to
the religion as uh and unless you have that ticket you can't enter
um and where and and come to the practice of mindfulness Buddhism
with because it doesn't require any beliefs it doesn't require believing anything you don't have to believe in
rebirth you don't have to believe in the but you don't have to believe in anything you don't have to believe you practice and through your practice oh
yeah I'm a little Kinder I'm a little gentle with gentler with myself or I'm a little more peaceful yeah okay oh this
this kind of works maybe I'll do more of it that it's that that kind of confidence or faith or trust that really
um we uh it's it's part of Buddhism it's not Blind Faith it's it's uh it's a
trust and confidence and faith that comes through verifying um the the results of the
practice and and also to say that um also some people come to the practice of
mindfulness and and and Buddhism also having faith in in Divinity in God in in
um you know being being Christian being Muslim being uh Jew and and also uh
practicing and and being a Buddhist and that's that's all good too that's all fine it's it's again there are no uh
there are no requirements tickets that any particular Faith or belief needs to be held it's just what what is helpful
what is wholesome what is supportive for your Humanity for your wisdom and kindness really wisdom and compassion
the two wings of the bird um how can we practice in a way that we can grow in
those for uh in those beautiful qualities for our sake and the sake of the world so the other beliefs can can
be there you can be practicing you know chakras energies and be doing this practice
so so now the idea of trust and confidence and and and Sada Sada say it
right Sada in in in Buddhism um it's an essential quality yeah that's
it not concept it's an essential quality for anyone anyone beginning to practice
or or continuing practice on this path there has to be some level of trust in
this practice and and the um at the beginning
of the practice the trust is often borrowed
trust so what is borrowed trust borrowed trust um I know for me for example
borrow trust was this friend of mine years and years ago I'm still grateful for when I was very sick very ill and
and she had uh done meditation Retreats she had done um practice meditation
practice and she said you know this might support this might support not necessarily physically but might be
supportive in some ways and so I had trust in my friend that this is a good friend I had borrowed trust I borrowed
her trust to start practicing and go on my first 10day Meditation Retreat
because of that borrowed trust there's also borrowed trust when
we um have not just good friends but also
teachers and people that we respect and we see that oh there's something a little different about them ah I I like
that I want that whatever that is a sense of stability confidence kindness
or whatever it is there's something that I I want to cultivate um so so it's a
borrow you're borrowing from their trust like okay there's something they've done works I'm going to borrow from um it's a
borrowed trust that's something they've done works and then when we practice on our
own it becomes verified trust or verified faith we verify it you know
maybe even um through the sit I invited you from the beginning to the end to
notice so are you just a tiny little bit perhaps calmer or more peaceful oh yeah
okay this practice Works something about sitting in silence and and um bringing
awareness and attention to the body and the breath yet there's something about this this toolkit that works oh yeah
verified trust verified Faith verified confidence and you can have more and more and more
and more verified confidence more and more as you see how you change how you
are Kinder so so the this borrowed trust borrow
Sada and then verified uh trust at some point when we keep
practicing it becomes unshakable trust it becomes unshakeable able trust and
confidence um in in these teachings that they really really work they work for me
they work for me so different levels and also there's one more type of Faith or
trust I'll mention sometimes it's bright very bright Faith bright trust maybe we
come to the teachings at the very beginning there's this bright Faith bright trust that uh it's very bright
and then it becomes more verified through our own practice until it becomes unshakable there's a sense of
stability to it trust faith can be particularly
helpful um at the times when we feel unored when we feel lost and we all feel
lost at some point in our lives maybe at times of transition um at times of
difficulty uh we just don't know which way to go what to do there's a sense of
being completely unored perhaps um as if we're we're falling and there's nothing
to hang on to and that that borrowed trust just a little bit of trust in
something little bit of trust in something and it doesn't have to be huge
trust it could just be a little bit of trust for example if if you wake up and you're feeling out of sorts and there's
a lot of Doubt coming that out about
everything finding just something little maybe as I was bringing the meditation
just bringing a sense of trust and confidence in oh my feet are touching
the Earth okay trust confidence and gravity okay
that I can just sit here for a moment just tiny little bits of trust and
confidence and if it's physical embodied it even better even more
supportive to support us through times of uh um yeah lack of trust doubt a lot
of TR um yeah a lot more to say but I realize i' yeah well we have four more
days on the topic so I'll I'll speak about those um one thing I wanted to say
is invitation for the rest of the day to um to notice this to notice areas of
trust to notice areas of trust and also notice areas of lack of trust um where
where there can be trust oh well maybe I don't have trust in this but can I have a little bit of confidence a little bit
of confidence in this yes maybe I feel overwhelmed by this project ah but can I
have trust confidence that I can take this first small little step maybe just
I don't know open this book and just read the first line or or just answer this one email or or
again just breathe and feel my feet on the earth so notice where there is trust
where there is trust because the more you notice trust and confidence the more it grows you notice that yeah it's there
it's really here there's so much of it here okay all right so um thank you all
for your practice thank you so much for your presence all around the world um
and look forward to exploring so many different aspects of trust this was just the introduction of course today dipping
our toes may all beings be well may all beings be
happy have a great day