and so now the invitation is to start to settle
into a posture
acknowledging however you are wherever you are right
now sensing into whatever confidence or trust is there
and meeting back with
appreciation with kindness so I hear the people saying
that you can hear me but it's santam Mushi unfortunately I can't do anything about that um so I'm not sure why it's
different today than yesterday but um hopefully
we will be able to work our way through
[Music] it rooting
yourself in the Integrity of your
posture taking a moment to really notice whether you're sitting standing lying
down [Music]
down entering your weight over your hip points your
feet allowing your head and your spine to be
aligned and with a couple of relaxed more
intentional perhaps deeper breaths
relaxing into that uprightness that
posture softening your [Music]
eyes and letting go releasing offering the exhale
receiving the inhale receiving awareness of this moment here
now allowing the eyes to to be soft the tongue to be
soft then inviting the breath to be natural normal
and for the next few minutes whatever your anchor of attention is breath sound
body the invitation is to give yourself over completely to
it but go into
it being in contact with the moment
you're calling your intention for meditating today for being here
today then allowing body to completely
relax inviting the [Music]
mind to relax
and attentively
completely being with each
moment
e e
if distractions
come the instruction is to meet
the distracted mind with kindness
respect and graciously including that too in this
moment of awareness
returning to your anchor of
attention
e e
stabilizing the
attention by getting interested in each little arising in the
moment
each part of the breath each waiver or change in the
sound each moment of silence or Stillness
if each thing in your experience its own
time listening deeply being with
companioning whatever is present while resting
softly in the
moment
e
e e
Letting Go letting all of Who You
Are release into the attention into the breath into the
moment
resting riding in the flow of
now
e
e e
in the last few moments of our formal meditation together
please consider recollecting these moments of
meditation in an appreciative
way especially recalling every little
glimmer of mindfulness awareness
calm patient
trust and in a wholehearted complete way Gathering
those moments WIS up and savoring them taking them in as
nourishment appreciating respecting the time you've
offered this practice today
and then casting your internal gaze out to the others in your
life and offering them
too the benefits of this practice
may they be safe happy
peaceful and
free then allowing those good wishes to extend even further
out as far or near as they want to
go may all beings be happy
safe peaceful and free May the benefits of our practice
here together Ripple out through our lives all the
lives we touch and all of the lives they
touch is an offering to the
world thank you for the sincerity of your
practice
e
e e
so thank you everyone very much for your practice your presence here
today and um thank you also those of you who
responded about the theme of confidence and Trust
yesterday going to continue today on um with this
exploration of gifts we can offer the Dharma dharmic
reciprocity and how those can resonate and return to us maybe in a slightly
different form and feed the meditation feed need our
um maturity happiness presence in our
lives so today yesterday we talked about I talked about trust confidence
conviction and today we'll explore the benefits of wholehearted
attention respect in the practice the Buddha named these
qualities is Gifts of a good person and this obscure little discourse one of the
things I'm drawing on riffing on this week gifts of a good person a person who
offers with integrity and the language itself to me
suggests that he's talking about the attitude of the person as well as the
process of giving itself wholehearted
attention is was experienced as Respect by
others and recently I I heard an anecdote about this um a letter written
by the famed abolitionist Frederick Douglas sort of Civil War era person and
in this letter he recalled with be being deeply impressed by meeting Abraham
Lincoln and even though he and Lincoln were on the same side of the abolition kind of
perspective they differed in their approaches and in some ways Douglas had been a big critic of Lincoln but dougas
when they met was moved by how completely Lincoln paid attention met
him wholeheartedly completely respectfully where he
was I was moved by that there are accounts too of the
Buddha himself offering this kind of resp respect through wholehearted attention the Buddha paid close
attention to all kinds of people who came to ask questions debate receive teachings regardless of their point of
view or their cast back in Ancient India there's this story um of a leper
who came to the outskirts of a large Gathering where the Buddha was teaching and he'd initially come hoping
there would be food there he was hungry and and then he heard the Buddha
teaching and decided to stay and just listen to the teachings and the Buddha scanned the
crowd and attentively noticed that this man was there and that he was ready and
he offered the teachings specifically tailored to
him and the man reached full Awakening so rather than casting the
person out or ignoring him because he I mean lepers didn't look very good and
they were kind of reviled the Buddha met him where he
was this kind of wholehearted attention respect doesn't just benefit people on a
relational level it also applies kind of seamlessly in my own experience to the
practice of meditation itself
wholehearted attention complete attention to the most ordinary moments
of practice has this resonance it begins to increase interest in the
moment it's not giving to get gaining mind they call it in this scene that
doesn't work rather giving of one's self and one's attention so completely so
whole wholeheartedly with such
respect it's like an offering a deep listening that naturally inspires a
response and that invites more gifts of the
practice some of those are that gradually mindfulness mindful awareness
can come become more continuous stable awareness itself becomes more
resilient less thrown off by momentary distractions there's a deeper presence
and then the heart and mind begin to receive all kinds of benefits of gifts from that
more continuous attention Joy can arise For No Good
Reason good good news is that setting all of this in motion
including the joy can be cultivated through this kind of completeness this giving
over to being in the moment to attending closely with respect and here's some
ways that can work first it can be really helpful to set a
resolve an aspiration to get in interested to be
attentive this includes getting interested in interest and its opposite
interested in boredom which is often got an element of
aversion in it another way that can help is having a
respectful unhurried attitude towards whatever is coming up to give it its own
time turn to it
completely and just like with deep attentive listening you don't have to agree with what's there it just it still
helps to offer
respect and speaking of respect it can be incredibly
beneficial to offer yourself self internal respect for doing this practice
no matter how it's turning out respect for everything that's coming up
everything you meet when I served as a hospital
chaplain I would go into rooms all day long with people from different walks of life all kinds of
backgrounds and I soon discovered very early on that offering this kind of
complete attention and respect opened the door to much more interesting
conversations it served them better and it served me better too it felt better
in the moment and this was especially true when encountering
difference getting interested in someone who didn't seem all that open at first
or had a very different way of being often revealed not obvious but
very important points of contact between us or feelings thoughts World Views that
would open into a deeply satisfying even loving
conversation with wholehearted attention can also feel like
love doing this even improved my own resiliency
so this is equally true of being in rapport with our own experience just as
an attentive listener can help the words and ideas and feelings to flow the
conversation to flow complete wholehearted attending to the
moment that also opens things up and opens a possibility for a whole range of
experience that might not normally be available at all but metabolizing
emotions and obvious thoughts stories that's just the beginning an
important beginning and a powerful moment in
practice there's also taking a wholehearted learning
mindset towards the tiniest foots of the beginning of a thought the beginnings of
sensation sound can all become apparent and this
supports a whole another level of freedom in relationship with the
moment the simplest objects the simplest
experiences can become beautiful with the sense of wonder and
awe for the ordinary so
notice notice these simple moments the
satisfaction that can be there and all of this feeds a
flexible fluid continuity of mindful awareness which in
itself feeds contentment opens the
possibility for a deeper more subtle way of seeing and
being in other words if you offer yourself give yourself over completely to the
practice the gifts received can include intrinsic interest and beauty of the
ordinary there's a resonance between the offering and the
receiving the gifts we receive Echo but aren't identical
necessarily to the gifts we offer and these benefits open the heart and mind to still other beautiful experiences
well including ining the kind of trust and confidence we talked about
yesterday so wholehearted unwavering complete
attention respectful attention in my own experience opens the gates of the Dharma
practice wide in a sense it echoes a very famous teaching by aan cha one of the root
teachers in this tradition the Tha Forest tradition
he said if you let go a little you will have a little
peace if you let go a lot you will have a lot of peace and if you let go
completely you will have complete Peace So this friends is an invitation
to wholeheartedly let go into the darma into your
practice thank you for your kind
attention and the invitation between now and tomorrow morning or tomorrow whatever time it is
for you is to notice the effect of offering wholehearted attention complete
attention maybe with another person in your life and with yourself
love to hear about it thank you