so hello hello everyone lovely to see you lovely to be with you dear sa these last days of um this year so so
given that towards the end of the year there's always this sense of um looking
forward looking back I wanted to invite us to to reflect um with meta with
kindness with Good Will with with um yeah sense of appreciation looking back
at this year for people for people who have been kind supportive they've had
some um some gift they've given us some gift and also maybe later as as I'm inviting us
in this guided meditation that I will lead in leave in a moment sometimes we can also look back at the year and and
realize that we have grown um through some challenges we've had with some
people so can we have meta and Goodwill and gratitude for them stretching us um
again that's that's not necessary you you don't have to go to that part of the practice but maybe starting where it's
easy starting where the practice is really easy and looking back um the
sense of appreciation and meta Goodwill Goodwill for for those who have uh yeah
been been of support and uh have been part of our path part of our path this
year how's that so so that's the invitation you know all all um uh
sources are coming with top 10 list and this and that and and we do meta we we do retrospective meta for for for
ourselves of course for ourselves and yeah I'd like to invite us to consider meta for ourselves over this past year
there must have might there might must have been challenges we're we're human beings we all have challenges in the
body and and mind and relationships perhaps and and also sharing our care
for ourselves and others in the sense of the the uh looking looking back so so um
yeah with that I want to invite us to uh lean to um yeah lean into our
embodiment leaning into our
embodiment arriving and Landing arriving and landing in our
body In This Moment In Time how is this
body how is this
heart can we arrive and land This Moment In Time in our bodies
feeling the Earth under our
feet feeling grounded feeling our sit Bones on the
chair on the cushion
inviting the body to relax and to receive the breath to
receive the breath in the belly inviting the
breath to be as as it is shallow deep doesn't matter
inviting a sense of relaxation in the
body in our face inviting our face to soften our neck our
shoulders inviting our heart to soften and relax
receiving this breath as if as if a gift because it is a gift that's keeping us
alive the sense of appreciation rej just this breath this
moment letting it be very
simple the mind can settle with the ease
of the nourishment of just receiving this breath let's hang out with this breath
with appreciation and settle like a cocoon cocooning with our
breath in this moment in our
bodies
e
e e
feeling really feeling the breath in our belly filling up our lungs
bringing life a life force appreciating this breath
and can there be appreciation for all the breaths in this body all the breaths
that have come and gone just like this one this one right
here this breath all the breaths that have
supported us nourished us the breaths when we were
happy the breaths we breathed when we were
sad breath we breathed when we were alone or with others friends family
perhaps
whether we were having ease or we're having challenges those
breaths appreciating all those breaths all of them without
discrimination not preferencing the breaths we breathed when we were this way or the other all the breaths all the
breaths appreciating all the
breaths this past year just like this
one and perhaps appreciating this breath and really inhabiting fully this
breath all the previous breaths breathe this past year have brought us to this
one this very one right here thank you
thank you breath thank you life whatever the circumstances ups and
downs the adventure it's always an
adventure e
and with appreciating the breath here in this moment all the previous moments of this
year leading up to this one this breath can we appreciate ourselves all
the versions of ourselves that have showed up and become this past
year through the struggles through the gifts blessings
through the challenges through the joys all the versions of
ourselves can we appreciate them with gratitude with with meta with
good willll thank you dear you've done your best all these versions as
if we're looking into two mirrors that are set in front of one another and
echoing and mirroring lots and lots of versions of ourselves spreading into
this this past year all these versions happy ones sad ones all of them
thank you thank you I love you or perhaps I
appreciate you may you be well I appreciate that you've done your
best I accept you with goodwi whatever version works for you see what works for
you can there be an openness as if we're
embracing these versions of ourselves with open arms
you don't have to necessarily think of them or so that this doesn't become a
thinking meditation but as if we're opening our arms and greeting a whole bunch of say children all these
versions just spreading meta spreading goodwill spreading appreciation
without thinking about scenarios just opening our hearts Opening Our Hearts to all all of
them all of
us see what phrase works for you thank you you I appreciate you or thank you I
accept you or thank you I love you or your own
version
e e
and remember to stay here the present moment your seat of the
presence seat of the present seat of your presence
now if you would like to invite in your heart space into your heart space one or
two people perhaps in this past year who've been
supportive on your path
open the door see who wants to come and receive metan
appreciation maybe there's the image of your opening the door of your heart and they just come in and sit
silently and this room of your heart that's warmed up with good willll and
appreciation and they just receive just sit and
receive as you're sitting and offering Goodwill to yourself and others very
simple
e
e e
Maybe other versions younger versions of you also walk into your heart space and
sit in the room of your heart silently and receive Goodwill
care meta love
all who have entered sitting silently just receiving your
Goodwill appreciation care
love
e
e e
if it feels appropriate perhaps to let someone in
who supported you by stretching you a bit and showing the areas that you can
continue to grow in wisdom and compassion if it feels okay to let them
in if it's not destabilizing do so otherwise no need stay where you are
maybe they've showed you ways that patience can still grow in you it's
okay or feel free to just let it be those who are already present
present your heart's chamber sharing meta
Goodwill e
as we turn to bring this meditation to a close appreciating
yourself or having showed up regardless of what happened or did not happen it's
okay trusting that you're planting seeds of Goodwill
kindness they'll flower in their own
time May the goodness of our practice together may be a cause and condition
for happiness or wisdom for compassion for freedom for all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves everyone thank you for your
practice lovely to sit with you so the invitation today was um
first to stabilize in the body feeling the breath then then I invited you to
feel this Breath Right Here Right Now with sense of appreciation this lifegiving breath and then the
invitation from there was appreciation for all the breaths that have um led up
to this moment all these breaths in this past year no matter what the state of
mind was um and that way perhaps more appreciation came for yourself different
versions of yourself that were doing their best through this year
and cultivating Goodwill kindness appreciation for for ourselves through
this this other this different way this creative way of of seeing these versions of ourselves as if two mirrors were in
front of one another we're seeing like way many many versions and then I invited you to imagine
perhaps that there was a chamber of of in in your heart and and people from
this past year walking in into this space that was filled with care and acceptance and and appreciation that
they were just walking silently and and being this field of meta and then at the
very end I asked you if it felt appropriate not destabilizing to invite someone who perhaps stretched you a bit
this past year challenge you to to see the other there still ways that I can grow in wisdom compassion
forgiveness um patience whatever it might be but not push it if it felt okay
you could invite them and that was the arc that was the entire Arc of our practice together and
um yeah and um I would love to uh after
we come out of the that the small groups um would love to hear your remarks how
your practice went and and maybe I'll share with you um uh my own actually
tell you what I'm going to put the happy hour um uh guide
the the small groups um interaction guide the break breakout room guidance
um maybe I'll go over that before I share my U my practice report so in a
moment as we'll head into the rooms uh again just a reminder for us to
um um practice meta in this in the small group spaces as well embracing
compassion for ourselves for each other staying on topic and the topic the invitation is how was this practice for
you were there spaces that it really opened up for you of the reflection
um where there places that um a perhaps A New Perspective came up
and um if you'd like to share again for the purpose of your own reflection going
deeper in order um when you are held Witness by others our own insights can
can go deeper um and then please taking turns briefly we'll go in reverse alphabetical
order according to first name off offering one nugget or you can also say pass no problem you can say pass um and
um and yeah avoiding cross talk uh not giving each other advice uh maintaining a safe space and
going in order Etc not interrupting Etc practicing meta for yourselves and
for each other and when you go into small groups in the moment please turn on your cameras um for one another um it
it really um having the camera is off it does not support a sense of being you
know the trust in small groups so um so
so yes so back to the topic so the question is did something come up with
some was something about one of the invitations perhaps a perspective that shifted and opened up for you and if not
you can say pass or or um maybe you know the mind was distracted you fell asleep
it's okay no problem it's perfectly fine just being showing up with kindness for
yourself and for one another is really the the Crocs of this practice you can
say I fall fell asleep but it's okay it's all right I'm still showing up in small group so it's all about
cultivating Goodwill um for ourselves and one another so oh yes um I'll share
with you my practice reports so yeah for me it was actually quite interesting as I was leading and I was practicing iing
with you this sense of um you know in this uh the mirror as if I was seeing
lots of different versions of this being who is me this past year and and again not thinking about it but the sense of
the fullness of of so many circumstances and this appreciation of ah great wow
thank you thank you you've done your best thank you I care for you thank you I love you um and and again I was
following as I was giving you The Guidance with with people entering so many people I'm uh grateful for but I
stopped at some point because I didn't want my meditation to get too busy and at the end I did invite someone who's
who's gently stretched me a bit this year to realize oh there's more there's more room to grow of course there's
always more room to grow um in in patience so and so that's my practice
report and I was modeling for what you could be sharing if you wanted to but share like one nugget let somebody else
go um I shareed the whole thing in one go so just because I'm sending you now
to practice to a small groups so the groups are created and um please take
care of yourselves please take care of one another with kindness back welcome back everyone my rooms are closed
everybody's back lovely to see you and um yeah the floor is yours um
any Reflections you want to share for the benefit of each other um sharing your practice
questions complaints everything is welcome so you can use your Zoom hand if
you like also I'm going to open chat so that you can post in chat either to me
privately or to everyone in the group Noella please there
Hi um this isn't necessarily on topic but is like I've really been working on
you know um meta and I'm you know I I have two sons
who sometimes really push back on how much love I want to give them and that
constipates my emotional um my
emotional um River because they they seem to damn it in their own way and I
feel like if they don't receive it it's hard for me to to to pulse it out and I
feel um that it for I just am thinking that for all of you who are sending out
meta I'm receiving it so that you don't get it it that sense of
constipation of of your good will I'm totally receiving it I just want you
guys to know that how much difference it makes for me and how much how undamned
and how how how free flowing my love is
for you just because I'm receiving your love for me and it's just totally a life
practice now so um thank you yeah thank you NOA thank you so much for sharing oh
so beautiful Your your gratitude for the community and this this allowing
allowing of the flow and um yeah it's it's when there is openness when there
is allowing the openness to ex to receiving there's there's more ease both
in the giving and the receiving so actually receiving meta is a gift to and with your sons I wanted to invite you to
consider something if I may here's an invitation and that is um what if you
you accepted and had metap for their resistance because giving meta is
unconditional it's right is is um is
unconditional it's yeah it's it's absolutely
unconditional it's it doesn't have to look a particular way and sometimes if
we if we insist on it looking a particular way and others are not ready
to receive that particular way right then there is resistance but if you say okay I love you no matter what
it's so so bringing more discernment is my invitation to also again this may not
be the case it might be totally off the wall but but um sometimes you know I you
we want to love in our way and people no want to be loved in their way right so
it's it's can you love him in the way they want to be loved which is with
equinity with a lot of equinity uh with no strings attached
absolutely no strengths attached loving is my work of a lifetime
yeah yeah always learning yeah thank you especially being a parent of adult
children a high dose of equanimity is is needed in The Meta which is it's like
this okay spacious like a lot of spaciousness a lot of spaciousness in in
the meta yeah yeah thank you so much NOA thank you also thank you for receiving
it was so beautiful yeah thank you ah Barbara Barbara Barbara Barbara
there um our breakout group liked the cue of of sending meta to all the
aspects of you during you know your year or during the
lifetime and for me it it's so pertinent for now because it's at the end of the
year and tomorrow I'm going to look at my day planner and
look oh I showed up up oh I helped out
oh I volunteered oh I read a book and get a sense
of of ways in which I was following the path that I had set
out and and what was important to me and it still is important to me and by
looking at that and feeling gratitude for this person or you know appreciation
for this person who did those things right it's very nice thank you
Nikky thank you Barbara thank you all these verions of Barbara really lovely
right yeah just look back with the sense of beloved other wow this person really they had these intentions and they
showed up they did these things wow oh dear sweetheart thank you wow right
appreciating earlier versions of ourselves that's lovely thank you Barbara thank you it's very sweet yeah
nice yeah other um other Reflections what worked what what didn't what any
any nugget you like to offer uh from your practice for everyone for
everyone's benefit [Music]
red please and then Maria yeah thanks Nikki uh you to maybe just
State the OB obvious that uh of everybody here the SAA was was one of
the the groups of people that I was so grateful to for you know daily and your
daily support and that's really a lot you know it's there a lot of days in
that we gathered this year and um and that's been really consistent and solid and I just feel really grateful for that
I'm grateful to you too of course thank you thank you Fred thank
you for naming the S wow so powerful right so powerful to be gathering so
many days of this year wow my heart just lights up thanks for naming it it's it's
so obvious that we we sometimes forget it right so um yeah beautiful and and of
course I'm grateful for all of you uh this is a co-creation I wouldn't be here
if you if you weren't showing up if you weren't here so vice versa thank you friend Maria
please hi I
um the thing that came up for me when I considered the growth from somebody who
challenged me this year was my daughter um she's
34 and we have a tendency both of us I think she got it from
me to talk over each other when we're talking and so we both sort of feel
frustrated because we're not really listening well to each other because we have too much to say and so I made a
decision about six months ago um to just be quiet and to listen to her and I even
put on her phone number on my on my contact list instead of her last name it
says her first name which is Miranda and then deep listening a nice when she
calls I get this Trump rand's calling deep listening nice and and it's not
perfect but it's better yeah that's nice
ni beautiful oh yay y That's oh how beautiful to have this
reminder and and you know deep listening is an act of Love is an act of meta it's
an act of just receiving and according to various um theories and when we change
other people change right it's the there are these systems these Dynamics these family systems that we have so sometimes
we want to change the other person and we can change the other but if we change
oh guess what they're going to change and response to that it's like oh wow this person is listening so I don't have
to be as angry or as as whatever talk at them like they're actually listening I can relax it's just magic can Happ so I
just loveing Mar and I just love that you you added that to to the phone number and the name it's brilliant yeah
brilliant thank you a that is just so lovely ah thank you so
lovely very sweet so dear ones um have maybe time
for one more reflection or offering before we close
can also type in chat yeah maybe this feels complete this
feels complete and I'm so inspired actually um as Maria was sharing um yeah
it add I know this might be a bit much for you but I'll share the what what
came up for me so many of you know that I love teaching about mindfulness of mortality that you know this could be
the last time I talked with this person this could be the last time and there's people who are very dear in my life and
and and you know what if I added you know after their name this could be the last conversation right you know just
like oh really just loving them even more appreciating not not to the sense of point of anxiety but just the sense
of yeah I I really care for this person and any conversation could be a last
conversation so just making sure people I care about know that I love them so
with that thank you all thank you for your practice for cultivating good willll and meta for your own sake and
the sake of all beings whose lives yours touches May our practice be a support
cause and condition for all beings being happy being free including
ourselves thanks everyone thank you thank you thank you I'm going to um