so hello and welcome
to the Insight Meditation Cent YouTube meditation
session I'm very happy to sit here with all of you who are
participating so this is the 25th of the
25 sessions introduction to meditation
sessions and um and mindfulness has a lot to do with
noticing what is happening and with that kind of
emphasis it's easy to overlook that one of the things is H that is
happening is the absence of things things disappear and they're no no
longer there suffering disappears and is no longer
there and the absence is significant absence allows for
silence absence allows for Stillness absence allows for
spaciousness and sometimes when we practice mindfulness what stands out as
the predominant experience or what stands out as a significant thing to
take in let register are these absences the absences of
suffering the absence of tension and in that absence there's a
kind of nourishment some goodness there sometimes that you want to take in that
if we go on to the next happening thing we don't take time to register and receive the benefits
of that those absences the absence of noise is silence
the absence of agitation is stillness the absence of contraction is space
spaciousness and um these qualities can always be present to some
degree in some ways and certainly search ing for them
or trying to make them happen is not helpful but sometimes they
support mindfulness as we're paying attention to suffering as we're paying attention to
agitation as we're paying attention to ways where the mind is tight and
contracted there can also be a connection
to silence in the noise there's also
silence important part of music is the the silence between the
notes in the agitation there can be
Stillness probably wouldn't know you were agitated unless there was some reference to
Stillness maybe a subconscious one and the absence of
contraction just on the edges of the contraction edges of
the tightness tension just beyond the edges of our
thoughts there is space so with that as
a introduction maybe during this
sitting you can from time to time know notice if any of these qualities
of Silence Stillness and space is there for you maybe at the end of every
exhale maybe if you let your thoughts drift off away let go of your
thoughts maybe there at the end of the sentence that you're saying end of the
image some of these three qualities are
there maybe mindfulness
itself mindfulness in the middle of everything the mindful the awareness
itself has these
qualities maybe in the middle of awareness there is silence
Stillness spaciousness and that it makes a world of difference to be
aware centered on those qualities then it would be for the
awareness to be also noisy agitated
contracted so we'll sit in silence and allow you to
be your own teacher give yourself your own guidance
for sitting here for these next 20 or so
minutes
for
e
and as we near the end of this sitting
finding where in your body do you feel
softness a soft sense of
being maybe there soft Ness associated with
breathing maybe with a
belly maybe some places on the edge of your body along the skin the
arms the
chest
and is there any softness in the
mind maybe it's easy to find tightness and contraction agitation
but is there also softness in the
mind maybe the softness that is on the edges of the
Mind touching the space and the silence
beyond the
mind maybe a softness in the
heart and if the Heart Is Not So Soft maybe at the center of the
heart inside of the tightness or
protectiveness there's a place a spot of softness
and in whatever softness you have associated with
Maybe Might there also be some sense of
Silence the space of the mind that tends to be filled with words words and
images now has more silence in it than
before a Stillness in the
body as softness as soet with spacious
feeling and sensing within with outside of you the edges
between you and the outer world where there might be
Stillness silence
spaciousness that can hold all all
things that is
soft and in that Stillness and softness
silence can you
feel a
selflessness freedom from self
concern and staying centered in all of
this bring to mind the world of people and events activities you you'll be
involved in today or
tomorrow gaze upon it with Stillness and
quiet
and bring forth whatever well wishing good will love
kindness care you might have for
others and let that be supported by the
softness the Stillness
and wish everyone well may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may the way that you remain soft and
peaceful be a means by which you support this to happen May all beings be
happy
thank
you
e
so I just uh posted in the chat the link for our community meeting
in 15 minutes or so and you'll probably have to uh copy it and paste it
into your we your browser or into
zoom and uh the
um the link is also in uh imc's
homepage in uh bottom right hand corner there's a section called what's
new and you will find it um there also
and I don't think you'll need the password with u how the link is set up but uh if you do need a password the
password is meta and um it'll take me a you know a couple of minutes to log on myself so if
some of you do before 7:45 uh just wait for
me so hello and as I start this uh last talk on
introduction to mindfulness meditation um and considering that this
is the last of 25 I'd like to say that um I plan to
continue with this kind of uh series uh starting next week and maybe we'll call
this uh intermediate mindfulness or introduction to mindfulness part two um but I think that
uh uh there's much more to to say that kind of Builds on what we've done so far and
and all at the heart of mindfulness practice and for today um the in a sense maybe
it's poignant at the very end and also in the end where they this coming to a
conclusion that all things must end that all things come to um uh a time when
they are not there uh except saved on the internet but all things are are not
there and um and that that what follows that the end end of things is an
absence and that absence of course can lead us to loneliness and sadness and
grief all kinds of things when the things come to an end and we miss them or we love
them and there's also something very poignant in absence that uh we can find
sometimes in this practice um maybe it depends on what the absence is but one of the key absences
we're looking for in the Dharma is the absence of suffering and when that absence is there
uh then um uh if that absence is there then uh
that is sweet or that is freeing that's uh very nourishing to feel our existence
without suffering as part of it and so one of the things that we want to be attuned to when we do mindfulness and
recognize is in fact absence um uh there's a very
strong instruction in mindfulness practice to pay attention to what is
happening but what is happening is uh is certainly the you know Central to this
Enterprise but uh what we really want to look at is um not really but we want to
also include um when some things are no longer there so if we're no caught up in
distracted thinking and it just goes on and on and then when it's absent when it stops finally uh don't just don't go on
to the next happening take time to register oh that feels good how it's
good that absence of thinking if you're filled with anger and the anger dissipates and disappears take time to
register the goodness of that absence what's available what it feels like to
have that absence and absence is doesn't make for a very sharp um object of attention uh it's
more amorphous or diffuse or um you know it's uh almost bordering on imagination
you know we know we remember in our imagination memory that something was there not here
now uh there's tension in our bodies that we carry and that if the tension the
tightness in the body dissolves there's the absence of that tension and how does does the body feel then without
it um and um so the
um um so as we sit and meditate for being mindful of what is part of what is
is absence and some of the qualities of absence that uh can stand out sometimes
really loud in a sense really strongly is uh the uh an absence that is uh this
marvelous sense of Silence in the mind the mind is not thinking so much or
thinking at all uh marvelous sense of
Stillness uh I love the image of uh a very still quiet morning Lake before the
sun rises and and there all the animals and birds are quiet and no wind and it's
just so peaceful and still sometimes you can feel that that
inside and sometimes um there's the uh the absence of um of claustrophobic
objects all this stuff happening and Sensations and this and that and there's a sense of spaciousness in
awareness and um a lot of thinking makes the Mind claustrophobic maybe and but
the spacious mind has lots of room and the nourishing part of
Stillness silence and spaciousness I associated with uh when there's softness
as part of it or diffusiveness as part of it um where there's not a lot of
constructs of self and um where there even self self-centeredness self-c
conern drops away there's kind of selfless quality in it and this uh
absence of self-concern a absence of self- referencing a absence of self
constructing itself s being itself self measuring everything according to the self a kind of feeling of experience of
absence of self even uh is also soft and wonderful and
peaceful and and absence has um a quality of um freedom in it and this
absence is uh is uh can be all this all these wonderful absences
can be experienced in mindfulness itself when mindfulness is just kind of a clear
awareness of what is in that clear awareness clear almost like the clarity
itself um you can see is the clarity is absence of of smudges absence of
obstacles to see and in that Clarity then there's ABS absence of noise absence of agitation
absence of contra ction in the clarity of mind that is mindfulness when
mindfulness is really strong and centered um it's it's characterized by
these absences which are almost synonymous with freedom a sense of clear
Independence where mindfulness is knows what's happening
but in knowing it is independent of what is happening not entangled not caught not
reactive and that absence of being caught the absence
of being entangled the freedom of suffering that's there this is one of
the great experiences that mindfulness can bring and what's wonderful about this is
that this kind of Freedom this kind of experience in a certain way is portable
you can bring it with you into the world and when the experience of freedom is
strong enough then you probably always have a reference point maybe it's uh
it's you know we're too busy sometimes to notice it but just to be able to turn
towards it and see ah there's that freedom there's that Refuge of
Stillness spaciousness silence softness this Refuge of freedom right
there here it's with me and uh and then mindfulness becomes a
wonderful nourishment that promotes greater and greater
Freedom so thank you for being part of this 25 session introduction to
mindfulness and I hope this has supported you some of you have probably been practitioners for a long time and
um and maybe um uh either some of you are more
beginners and some of you are experienced beginners either way I hope that the
introductory instructions is useful for everyone so thank you and uh I saw that
I I put the I'll do it again here with the chat for our community meeting the the link and um and somehow that's I I
see that it appeared but um and I saw other people put links too to it so if
you scroll up hopefully you can see it and um but if you don't uh not connected
to uh the chat for YouTube you'll find the link on the IMC uh homepage on the
bottom right there's a section called what's new and there it says uh you know uh you YouTube community meeting and if
you click on that you'll get the you'll see the link there and um and I'll be
there in just a couple of minutes though and for those of you who don't want to go or don't know how to find your way to
the YouTube do the zoom um we'll uh remain here broadcasting on YouTube so
you can just continue uh and um and if we do a breakout group uh for
the zoom people then I'll just stay here and maybe I can chat with a few of you
that are here on on uh YouTube so thank you very
[Music]
much
so it looks like it worked and pretty easily so I see some of you found it and
can you do a thumbs up that you can hear me great so
um so let me check here a little bit more on things
great so I think that I uh still on YouTube
so I think we're set for that yep we're still on YouTube and uh
so for those of you staying then very nice and I'll try to switch back and
forth on my screen between the two and um but now I
will um go to zoom again there we go
okay so wonderful to see you and
uh so maybe people are still
coming and um I so I'll start by saying how grateful I
am for all of you who come to YouTube it's been a wonderful thing to be able
to offer these kinds of teachings and um and uh it was my you know when I first
um decided to dedicate my life to Buddhist Buddhist practice
and uh which was now you know over 40 years ago
uh I um image I had for myself was that uh I would be I was going to be as Zen
priest as and Monk and I'd have the key to a small storefront um Meditation
Center in some City and um that pretty much was just like a room that I had the
key and I'd keep it clean the place and I'd go early in the morning and open up the door and sit and meditate with
whatever whoever came to support their meditation and so this AA of getting up in the morning and sitting with people
uh was something that's always been in my mind as a central part of what you know my life was going to be about and I
do that on Retreats uh certainly I'm very happy I get up for the first sitting and I love sit doing it but here
since the we started this YouTube at in California at 7 a.m. I just delight at
the chance to get up in the morning get ready have breakfast and then come down here and be able to sit with people and
it's not quite a storefront with we have here but um uh I don't know exactly what
this YouTube space is but um it's uh very very satisfying and I'm happy to be
a part of this and to do this and um the
um and the idea I don't I don't can't imagine that we we'll stop doing this YouTube now um you know when I when as
you know when I go away and to do something then I we have this wonderful teachers who come and teach for me and I
can imagine someday in the future that maybe there'll be a transition where I teach less and some of those teachers
teach more but for the time being I have no plans to do things differently um as we're doing it
now and then um uh you know I do I do have some some
concern for how to continue to support those of you who primary connection is through YouTube this way and uh some of
you might might find it very interesting to um some of you already do is that uh
with the pandemic uh We've started to offer Retreats dayong Retreats and longer
Retreats uh res uh um uh on zoom and
some of them are called hybrid where uh participants are some PE participants are in person at our retreat center and
then there's lots of people who can do it more people can do it online on Zoom then or can do it in person and it's not
uncommon for us to have Retreats with 100 people on zoom and 40 people at the
retreat center which is the maximum we can hold and um and then we have day longs
as well on Zoom that uh through IRC I'm doing one I think I'm doing
one maybe in a couple of weeks in a week or so so
um anyway so wanting to support you in some way and so hopefully we do some of
them and and I know that Matthew Bren also wants to have something uh wants to
do offer something for us on YouTube um and I need to be in conversation with
him and how he wants to maybe add an additional thing uh weekly which I think be quite wonderful many of you know him
and find him wonderful and and you know and of course some many of you know that Nikki mapori and now Liz Powell and some
others are also offering happy hour sometimes on YouTube um so there's more
and more available as we go along here so um do you guys have any
questions you'd like to ask maybe from this uh inter meditation series or from
um anything at all that's somehow related to what we're doing here and it would be best if you can raise your hand
your Zoom hand which means that if you don't know how this in the bottom screen of your screen there's a menu in there
it should say reaction and um and now as you finally a chance you're allowed to have a reaction um and
um and and push a button and um to and
I'll see your hand and can call on you so I see p
Padma let's see wait second I have to I see p oh let's see what oh hang on a
minute I have to I have to um uh change some things here I have to
go find the YouTube and and make it
silent
somehow okay so YouTube is now silent
see you see I um I turn off the sound on my laptop
when I do this uh and so then I forget to turn it on and when I do it's confusing so now I think I'm ready let's
let's try again Padma okay can you hear yes thank you thank you Gil thank you
thank you for all your services and U I'm grateful that IMC came into my live
like 7 years ago and it's been nothing but bliss fall um couple of questions um
so you know I attended all these 25 sessions um even though I've been practicing for a while I'm still a
beginner um and you know I do notice it and it's really nice when I notice that
how the mind is going um and uh but my question is that isn't the noticing part
still the mind that's question question number one question number two is completely different which is you know I
had this thought for a while I think I talked to a couple of teachers too it's like I wish IMC has this community
living I want to just live and breathe in the community um so what are your thoughts on that I mean it's like more
like going into the monastery style I guess I don't know but I I think it would be such a great thing to have it
in California and I'm sure I'd love to contribute in any way I can thank thank you very very good questions so the
first one let me see if I can repeat it um we we're practicing mindfulness of
everything mindfulness of the mind but the mindfulness itself the noting itself is the mind and so you're a little
confused about that like how can the Mind know itself or you're kind of stuck in the mind you can't get out of it um
it's not like I'm stuck it is nice I do get that moments of the just whatever you call the quietness Stillness and I
don't even feel my body and it's beautiful you know it's just like a floating Sun and then slowly I'm like is it still my
mind you know um but I'm not stuck there you know I'm just going through the waves still right yeah yes that's nice
yeah so I don't think you should worry about it the um the yes every in a c
certain kind of way everything is mind uh and um and uh sometimes it seems
like we're surfacing to make a note to recognize what's going on and so you just
recognize oh I feel like I'm surfacing and then you uh let make the note maybe
or don't make a note and sometimes you can start feeling yourself surface as you the intention to note come up with a
thought arises and then you say no thank you and then you you settle back in again and uh and just be relaxed about
it all because it's the rhythm of maybe coming up and having a note and then not
being not being ruffled by it and then you settle again and there are times when there's no need to make any note
there's no need for the the the the to to have this active recognition but
that's mostly when things are very very quiet and still and empty and um but
it'll it'll come in and come out and your job is just to be at ease with whatever happens at that
point and so and and part of that ease is uh at this point no need to figure it
out because that's that's that's agitated mind if that's figuring it out
does that does that help yes okay so then with um with the
um um this you know uh retirement kind of uh retirement community or IMC you
know kind of uh place where people can live together um that would be lovely to have
and uh sometimes I've thought it would be nice to uh there's an apartment building next door here here and I don't
know how many units it has maybe 10 units or something I thought wow if we or someone could buy it we could have a
community people living right next door and that would be nice and and you know
people are complicated so it'll have it'll have its other aspects and then
the other is um been many people have asked for is is in fact a kind of
retirement community and um and the San Francisco Zen Center has just opened one
uh that uh took maybe took 15 years of uh or uh uh
planning uh at least 10 years of planning and no maybe maybe almost 20
years um they didn't know what they were doing so one person with uh their the
vice president at a certain time with not a lot of support from the community thought we have to do this and and
researched and planned and created the connections to make it happen and they failed and they started again and then
it worked and now I think it has 200 units and people are now moving in and
some of the people I've I've talked to who moved in there love it up there it's a kind of a Buddhist retirement
community and it's actually a Buddhist Quaker they kind of a partnership with the Quakers which is kind of
special and um so what I've seen from San Francisco Zen Center there's there there's a um model in this country uh
for how to create retirement communities that's supported by some of the churches
some of the big denominations have these these nonprofit Wings this is what they do is they create retirement communities
and the Quakers have a preeminent one they really people they really high quality and caring kind of way of doing
it and other uh and so there's a way of doing it and partnering with people who are in the business of it but um it's a
lot of work uh you know maybe if if one person put their whole full time uh task to it
that could probably be done but um um I can't you know I would love to
see it happen for us but I don't see the volunteer who's going to step forward to make it happen unless you want to do
it thanks again thank
you okay so I see a hand I got looking the wrong place and for that I have to
put on my glasses Mary
Lou well thank you Gil these weeks have been so helpful and I'm glad we're going
to go deeper um in the coming weeks um my question today is about earlier this
week you were discussing the aperture of mindfulness moving close or moving far
away and lately um I've had some oh uh work anxiety concern for another being
and there's not much I can do really about the situation and I have just had waves of
emotion during on the cushion and off the cushion and of course when it happens on the cushion there's a part of
me that's like no I want to be settling and following the guidance but I can't
there is no way it feels like I can step further away um so then I just follow
what I believe is the instruction that if something's predominant you stay there and it EBS and flows you know
comes and goes but I guess so my question is is there a skillful way or
should I or could I be learning to step further away when something like that
happens and what does um widening an aperture even about maybe something not
is is is you know emotional how does that work how does it look to step
further away great wonderful question so it stood out for me that when you talked
about uh you're talking specifically you're talking about um how to be
mindful with it how to be and you know there's other other practices to do like equinity that might be helpful sometimes
but but let's just stay with the mindfulness for now and uh and it struck me that you talked about it being waves
you talked about it the es and flows so you see so there's some freedom in you to be able to just let it pass through
and and and kind of go kind of be there and know that it's passing through as opposed to getting locked into it so
you're already in a good sh good spot one of the things that might be helpful
because of how you're practicing with it uh is to kind of just accept that oh
this is The Human Condition uh people have had this kind of feelings this kind of kind of loss
this kind of concern for people for Millennia this is The Human
Condition and not not to dismiss it or belittle it but to kind of allow
yourself to accept your humanity and you know this is how this is life is hard life is has this part as
part of it and in some sense of course we want to have this capacity to feel sadness and concern because because we
love and this is the this is part of Love um so so then with that kind of
acceptance then very carefully and maybe lovingly uh just allow it to be there
allow it just be and move through you and move through you but pay attention to it until maybe you start seeing oh
look at that there's resistance there look at that there's I'm holding on to something there or look at that there's
a uh uh I'm thinking of myself as a victim of all this and so that e that
you know and so you want to see where the extra is what are you doing that's extra without
disrespecting the basic feeling because it might be you know it's that very normal what you're experiencing but
slowly teas apart what's extra where the attachments are or the clinging is or something or maybe you assign meaning to
it and this assigning a meaning is after while that's extra you know it may just be more simple with
it and that Clarity then might help you to do what you're asking to do to step
away from it um which is and and one way to do that more specifically is um uh is
to use Mental noting so you know I don't exactly what it is but let's call it waves for now
just generic um there's a wave and then you can fe uh just recognize it as wave
but pay attention to the tone of voice in which you're saying it with because the way way that you're relating to it
you're involved with it in might be contained in the voice you know you might be saying you know you might be a
little bit afraid of it and so oh wave coming oh wave you know and you can feel
hear that in the voice or you can or it's anger or you can or confusion or something and see if you can find a
place to use the mental note that's free of that reactivity and that might create the
distance you're looking for the bigger you're looking for then it might be easier to oh okay um now I have this
bigger uh point of view to hold it
in yes thank you so thank
you so then uh is it uh
Zoo how do you pronounce your name Zoo okay you're still
muted maybe I can help you oh with
that there we go got it great okay um so
my question is about my um posture um
I was unable to sit for a very long time so I started lying down with my back on the floor and my legs on a chair um and
I've been doing that for maybe two or 3 years and finally the injury has
resolved itself and I can actually sit again and I find that
um I actually get much deeper lying down and much more relaxed and much more able
to stop uh the mind is much much calmer so now that I sit the meditation
does not go as deep and I'm wondering about that um you know whether
I if it's okay to be lying down or whether I should try sit um sitting
again if if you have an opinion about that would be great great well certainly
uh it's fine to continue the way you were if that worked well for you and
you're learning something very significant from that deep piece that you have there at some point you I hope
that you become interested in uh how to carry some of what you're experiencing in meditation into your daily life the
the line the mind that's in meditation and the mind that's outside meditation is the same mind it's your mind and so
you know there's no you know to limit that possibility of that peace you have in meditation and not the rest of your
life is a you know is unfortunate you why not you know have it be
continuous and so a big part of mindfulness practice at some point is practicing in daily life and uh and uh
bringing this into daily life so one possibility is that um sitting in in the
ight meditation posture is the uh is the uh is the is the intermediary that'll
help you bring it into daily life so you can do one of two things you can
continue with lying on the floor the way you have been for your primary
meditation and then when that finishes if you have time um uh stretch your legs
do something that you know prepares you and then go back and sit uh in upright
position uh but you have the momentum you have the still the the residue of
the earlier meditation that you get to kind of bring that deeper piece there
into that posture because you already prepared yourself and then you get to explore what it's like there with the
idea is at some point you're going to explore what it's like to start bringing some quality of it uh some
characteristic of into your daily life so that's one thing you can do the
other you can do is just say well I've done now a few years of this floor thing
and uh that was uh meditation with u uh training wheels and now I'm want to take
off the training wheels and just jump right into sitting upright and it's going to take a while to get to the same place but that's that that's you know
when you take off the training wheels you're a little wobbly on the bike so you're you know a little bit wobbly
sitting upright and it'll take a while you're so fortunate to have had this reference point this possibility and now
you're going to learn it in upright and that what you learn there will be a great foundation for taking it into life
so those are the two things I suggest thank you so much wonderful
thank you thank you Captain
hi hi girl thanks so much for all these teachings today the softness I think at
the end especially was really helpful and it's kind of related to my question
which is I notice when I'm not today maybe but there's been other dayses
where you've talked about resting your eyes in their sockets and also like relaxing the belly and I find both of
those very challenging um especially
when um sitting upright for my belly I can't quite figure out how to relax it
sometimes and then I think I create stories around it that I'm trying to relax but also I also can't figure out
how to get my eyes it feels like they're just constantly looking and I wondered just if you had any thoughts about that
yeah so with the eyes uh the eyes often most of the time will
be gently moving in the sockets just kind of floating in there so if that's what's
doing just be relaxed that's fine but if it's you're actively kind of more looking you know like every time if
there's a you're left knee hurts and you can see your eyes kind of like go and almost you know your eyes are closed but
you're kind of looking in that direction then you're uh too involved and so the first line of how to practice with that
is um be content just knowing that's the case it's just one more thing to be
mindful of oh look there I'm doing my thing again just that's how it feels this is what how it is now and just
there's something very profound about being relaxed about anything that's going on including something you think
shouldn't be happening um drop this shouldn't be happening just um okay this
is how it is I'm just supposed to be mindful how things is and this is how it is and that kind of that acceptance that
kind of clarity and then really seeing it that itself over time begins to relax
those things so that's one possibility the other possibility is to
spend some time actively relaxing the the eyes at least um feeling where the
tension is maybe spend you know five minutes at the at some point during the sitting doing a a scanning of eye scan
and uh just scan all around the eyes the inside where where's the tension where's the holding what does it feel like to be
looking this way I am my my eyes a little bit popping out of their sockets are they like I'm reaching out
into the world to grab something or is there some emotion that's connected to there oh look some people their eyes are
a manifestation of of anxiety it's oh there's a little bit of apprehension
there that's interesting so then you then it becomes apprehension meditation you know leave the eyes alone and just
connect to the anxiety that might be there um so those are some things you
can do and I don't know if that resonated with you with the eyes with the belly it might be have something to
do with the posture you're sitting in uh so you might see if there's an
other posture that's more upright or I don't know if you use a back rest or not in chair but maybe sit away you know sit
sit in such a way that there's a little curve in the lower back so that you know at least in principle gravity will pull
your your belly forward and um but you know I carried a lot of
tension in my belly when I started meditating and uh it was surprised to me how much and I would relax it I could do
that and it would last for half a second and uh and so I didn't make it
like a constant project but after a while it just became an ordinary everyday kind of thing and meditation
that three four five times in the course of 40 minute meditation I'd relax my
belly and then I didn't worry or wasn't concerned that half a second later it got tied again it was just okay this is
how it is and then after year some years of doing that the belly started to stay
more and more relaxed now I don't know if you have the patience for years but um I didn't mind because I I
wasn't really trying to I didn't have an idea that it should be different and
that was kind of a Saving Grace for me I just okay I'm tense I'll relax nope it
that was nice for a half a second but and then I went on with my meditation while thinking about it for another 10
minutes and then I tried again and so so uh so that kind of ease with it all
usually works well that is so helpful thank you very much
thank you nice to see you nice to see you so Emperor
empero actually this is uh Nate I'm on my mom's Zoom accidentally I thought it was mine
hi hello yeah I've been I've been meditating with you almost I think a
year and three months right I caught Co just to tell you a little I'm not going
to go on and on I caught Co I was having long Co symptoms and um I was told by a
community that had autoimmune disorder to meditate and I can tell you today right now I'm much more active and I'm
much more happier since meditation I really am um but I get a lot of pressure in my
in my scalp here here a lot of lot of pressure ears everything lot of
pressure and um I I just remember you uh saying things
in class breathe into the chaos right and and that's actually helped me a lot
expand and relax great that's yeah very good that sounds
excellent I mean so I mean one of the primary kind of uh aspects of
mindfulness is what I already said now is to in a certain way accept what's
happening don't fight it don't be concerned but be mindful of it uh so you
want to bring your your your mindfulness to that tension and do a guided tour of
your attention like high tension we're friends we've been around for a while and then just kind of scan around feel
where it's happening in your body and then if you can breathe with it or breathe through it and expand with it in
it or with it like you do fantastic so you're on the right you're on the right
track um yeah you know it that's changed my life I no longer have anxiety
depression um it's I used to have really bad I was in the house for like five
years I had gor phobia I I it was so bad and this has allowed me to just sit and
confront I started with Zen meditation and like how you started uhhuh that was really
difficult and I come from a really religious background like I learned my Rosary in Latin and I had an experience
in My Religion but then I've had my experiences with meditation which are all my very personal ones yes fantastic
well I'm very happy to hear this and um one one thing you might consider since
you brought up this topic of the pressure in your head is that for some
people uh that happens when uh they're medit when they're meditating they're
trying too hard yeah I know I know that I read up on this okay am I trying too hard I keep
going and it might not it might not be so but it sounds like you're finding your way very well and I think my job
listening to you is to uh uh celebrate with you how well you're doing and how
well this meditation has worked for you and and how well you're finding your way and uh maybe more than just celebrate
with you maybe I can be your cheerleader thank you I want you to use your strong voice one time though to
you okay meditate
meditate have a good morning man thank you very much great thank
you so
Steve yes I'm amazed that I have this opportunity to speak to you Gil it's
it's um you've been one of my guers um one of my my guides for the last few
years actually I started listening to you in audio DH many years ago so it's really an honor to and I want to course
express my gratitude right now but I do have a Dharma question um I um well it's more of a
psychological or Dharma question it's about um unpleasant emotions and um the
resistance to them I you know I think I through you and other teachers i' I've
I've recognized that there's distinction between the two of them and I've been working with the resistance I really
think I've made some some Headway on that I think there's tightness in my chest and my worry about what I'm
feeling have I I well I've been able to actually the tightest in my chest is is
really vanished through just kind of feeling into it but there's some unpleasant emotions that are still there
that have been refreshed for good reasons because they're unpleasant and especially fear fear is um I I've tried
to um just feel into that but it doesn't work it seems like
it it overwhelms me and I know you've been um you have a great way of of
addressing my personal concerns on on your morning um talks and so you I've
heard you say it before but what if it's overwhelming what can you really do
about fear how do you work with it is it maybe I should use meta or some some
other hack or something because I just can't dive into the fear it overwhelms
me great well thank you this is very important what you're bringing up and it's this is a you know you're not alone
with this kind of concern and so I appreciate the chance to answer this not just for you but for others as well the
um so you know it's it's very personal ideally the answer that the teacher
gives is very personal and really knows a person well because uh fear can be
debilitating and uh and fear can be connected to extremely deep things inside that maybe it's better to work
with a really good therapist uh with this so with so so we have to take a
little bit of a grain of salt what I'm about to say and uh and consider whether it suits you but here I'll tell you I I
am having um I do have a a therapist I'm not sure if it's a really good therapist but I'm not asking for um I do I do just
see the distinction between the two um job descriptions you're but I'm asking
from a Dharma perspective yeah yes yes so um uh I would
uh uh find circumstances where you feel pretty safe
maybe for you it's safest you know if you know you have your therapist later in the day for example or find a
circumstance where you know uh where you don't have to do anything for that day
and you feel like you can kind of you know just be yourself for a while or
recover or uh make sure you know get get you I don't know what anything at all make yourself safe even if it means
getting an extra lock for your door or something whatever it makes your heart your mind feel like okay it's this now
it's safe or have a friend nearby um and then meditate with the
fear and let yourself be
overwhelmed try that and and uh and uh and let it take
its course but the way to do this to let let
let it be overwhelming is have a good meditation posture that you do not
compromise so for example you wouldn't collapse you know or you know or tense up and
start pulling away or you know you would just you know hopefully it's a nice comfortable po enough Co posture but you
you stay in the posture and then whatever overwhelm you're having and
fear you're having compost it in the body let the body hold it let the body
process it just bring it back and feel how it is in the body so compost in the body is the same thing as feeling it in
the body body and just come back feeling the body as opposed to the stories and
the some of the mental reactivity that might be and uh and if you can relax the body around the fear great so you so
really see it through let it overwhelm you overwhelm you with those conditions I just provided and see what happens on
the other side of the overwhelm is there I know this is a
dangerous question for the you asked you mentioned my therapist should be should be helping me as well but is it you're
giving me a you're you're implying that there's a there's good things on the other side yes you give me a faith of
that yes I'm applying there's good things on the other side and uh it's possible to live without
fear and anxiety and so some people will do this on Retreats meditation Retreats
uh because there it's it's very safe and you have the whole day to kind of let it
wind or process and you don't have to go to work you don't have to talk to people and uh so some people find that's good
place and whether it's a right place for you uh it might be something you want to ask your therapist uh and say you know
I'm thinking about doing a retreat or something or um dayong Retreat you can do the one on zoom we're going to have
soon um and um but ask you know ask your therapist because I I don't know you I
don't know how intense it is and what can happen with with uh fear is it there
can you know you know there can be panic attacks it could uh it rather than finding more uh uh
mindfulness uh it triggers more fear and then it kind of spirals out and so if you if if you notice that it's really
spiraling out um you have to be cautious maybe it's not healthy for you but if um
but overwhelm and spiraling out are two different things so so uh so you have to be able
to be Discerning about what's happening but but in principle that's what I recommend you that you uh you just uh
trust it trust the process and and open to it let it be overwhelming and breathe
and stay and stay and if you stayed for a long time 40 minutes 45 minutes with
it then maybe get up and do some walking meditation or walk around the block and then come back and
continue I could go um I know that I don't want to I think this a short question the your the routine of your
Retreats I'm sure other people would be interested in hearing the general
routine because I've been to a Zen Retreat and I kind of know the traditional Zen session format do is
that an appropriate question to answer right now or I could ask a on teacher uh yeah it's fine the we have I think we
have the schedule for our Retreats on our website but the difference between Zen and our Retreats Insight Retreats is
and Zen the schedule is required everyone has to show up and in our Retreats the schedule is a
recommendation and so if you need to take a break it's easy to take a
break and so you know but we have a lot of sitting through the day sitting and walking meditation in Zen the walking
meditation is usually 10 minutes for us it's a 30 to 45 minutes so there's a bigger kind of break between sits in
that way great so then we have
Susan hey folks hi David
um sort of along the same lines I don't have a teacher I don't have
never done Refuge or any of that so but I do read and I study on my own and I've
been coming to these sessions for um quite a
while but one of the things that I'm sort of trying to um figure out
is we are told and Neuroscience tells us that the things that we focus on become
stronger stronger and stronger like rots in your mind whether they're emotions or whether they're thought stories or or
whether they're whatever um and in the Buddhist you
know um interpretation that would be the more you you know more thoughts or um
attitudes you uh have in your mind that's what's going to
become a stronger inclination for your mind for your attitudes and then
eventually I guess becomes part of your character or that's what's built your character so
we are also instructed to when something comes up that's not
particularly helpful wise you know it's um that to sort of sit with it and feel
it even more and more and more and I'm wondering where's that line
between okay it's um what is it desensitization therapy you know letting
the spiders crawl all over you until you're no longer afraid of spiders and when is it um indulging the fear or the
emotion thought even more yes this is a very important question thank you and uh
it's very important that we can start Discerning the difference between participating in difficult States
activities of the mind that reinforces him for example versus uh uh being
mindful of them which is is uh a different uh track in the
mind it's a different activity of the mind that we're trying to reinforce and strengthen not trying to uh strengthen
our neurosis and so the um uh so uh uh but
some people can't it's it's difficult to see the difference between between the two the way that we get involved and
participate and in our NE kind of negative mind States uh is
almost us unconscious and so we bring mindfulness to it and the mindfulness itself is just
more of the same as before and it's we are then reinforcing it and so it's not so healthy so uh one
of the uh instructions I offered uh this last week or two was the idea that um
when you when you're mindful of something like especially it was for thinking thinking mind
is um do it for only three breaths because that might be enough to
kind of uh inter interrupt the usual way in which we're feeding the thinking
mind but we're not uh we're then not likely to keep keep somehow
unconsciously feeding it and then we come back to the breathing and then it might be a few breaths later you go back and notice thinking again but uh but not
just stay on it all the time and that principle might also be true for some emotions that uh if we stay with some
emotions too long like with fear it might be that with fear um there's it's
uh it's almost automatic that some fear is carried in the mindfulness itself
which then maybe subtly is subtly not so subtly is reinforcing the fear but if we do three breaths with fear and then
return to the just breathing for a while and then relax and then three breaths with fear that might support uh this
shifting of the of what's being uh developed in the mind and we are in
Buddhism trying to develop positive states of Mind by their repetition by feeding them and some of the positive
states of Mind are mindfulness so uh Joy uh
Tranquility uh uh concentration or this kind of steadiness of mind
equinity um there's a faith that we want to we want to strengthen um the kind of trust or
confidence we want to strengthen so there are kind of good states of mind
that uh we want to recognize and and um and allow for and but what happens with
the best states of mind that comes with meditation uh they're there because of the absence of other hindrances they're
not there because we're participating in them and so then we're allowing for them we're kind of getting out of the way
we're more like making room for them so they can grow and spread rather than engineering them or trying to push them
to be better or something um so when the when the self is involved with self uh
when uh too much self concern is involved with the mindfulness then chances are we're
feeding the wrong thing when well you bringing up another
the other flip side of it for me in terms of
the kind of difficult
um easy way that you can um subtly shift
things so the idea of the positive states of
Mind At what point are I mean the idea that maybe um shifting in that way is also a
way of suppressing and denying you know okay I'm going to suppress and deny and
allow I can allow certain things to Bubble Up but I have to push something else's you know see what I'm not very
experienced at this so this is what I see my own I worry you know like okay is
this really something that's naturally um it you know sort of
drifting off because I've let it go and something positive is coming up or
really is that subconscious suppression repression um and
then you know grasping after something that has a nice um sound to it you know
like um you know equinity or whatever sure and sort of labeling it so I feel
okay that's okay but in fact it's really um disengagement from something I don't
want to feel and these are all things happening kind of yeah at the margins of
subconscious yes great so the fact that you're uh concerned with this thinking about this is a good sign this is
healthy and appropriate to have this kind of self-reflection these kinds of questions so I appreciate that quite a
bit um the other but uh the fact that you have it I would like to uh suggest
to you that uh that uh you have a Discerning mind you don't have to be actively using
it as much as you're using that uh uh it's there for to support you that what you need to do is
to trust the practice and that everything will be be be revealed over time so if you're
repressing things a you know it's not not a crime to repress things so I
wouldn't you know treat it as a crime it's like you know you know you're you know you're not a bad Buddhist because you're repressing things there might be
good reasons to repress it might be better than the alternative for some people so uh but if you're
mindful um uh and learning to be mindful of the body and with time you get to be
mindful of your reactivity the tensions in your body and sooner or later you'll
start noticing you're repressing you'll see it and feel it and then the practice
becomes self-correcting and don't be don't be ahead of yourself don't guess and worry
that it might be happening if you want just assume it is happening it's okay and um and just keep doing the practice
until it becomes obvious in your experience oh yeah there it is I see it I'm doing it again you don't have to
guess whether you're doing it or not you know you're doing it and you feel the tension and you feel the downside of it
and then you're ready to do a course correction but don't do a course correction until the mindfulness has
revealed its full Glory trust the practice just do the
practice with what's obvious do the practice what's going on and you have the discernment I'm repeating myself you
have the discernment to notice these things so you can now relax just trust the process the practice just be mindful
of how it is don't second guess don't worry about what's not obvious and the
practice of self-correcting over time thanks
Ash thank you Gil um I feel in some ways that that question might have answered
my that answer might have answered my question I had a clear question at the beginning and then now I'm having a
little trouble framing it I've been meditating with you for 20 years now it's 2004 when I started listening to
you and have made felt feel like a lot of progress equinity and um sense of
openness or noticing when I'm contracted and when I can Orient towards an opening
towards what's coming so this is on the cushion as well as in livelihood and in
interactions and I guess um without just uh keep going and begin again you know
what's next ah what's next for you m well uh I
have a clear sense of what's next for next for for you but I don't know if your life life circumstance allows for
this yet so it might be some years away but you're ready to sit some long
Retreats and uh you know minimum a month it could be the two-month at
Spirit Rock it could be longer at IR uh at IMs um so uh that's uh you're ready
for a long real you know in residential long
Retreats yeah I'm oriented towards that opening that space yeah yeah so that
that that's I think I feel like that's what's next for you I mean you know in terms of I don't
know you're you're practicing great as you are so it's not like you're missing out but uh in terms of my you know my
wish for you that's an addition to what you're already doing would be a long
retreat okay thank you and then uh is it Jean or jeie it's
or Genie work um long time listener first time caller um and I'm just so grateful for
this opportunity and um I might get a little choked up because uh like Nate the
um having a practice and having access to insight has absolutely transformed my
life in ways that I never imagined to be possible um and so thank than you um
from all the depths of my heart um for that and thank you to everyone who sits
because you know we perfect in some way by practicing
together um and I think my question is
um related to that because in this world where there's so much suffering and so
much Injustice that it can sometimes feel deeply unfair to even sit and I know
rationally you know the reasons to do it you know both from like literature and then experience but
sometimes just balancing that feeling that by practicing I'm being
unfair um so any thoughts or guidance that you can offer would be most
appreciated ah I'm I'm very touched than appreciative of you saying all of this and with the
question concern that you have and I I probably won't be able to do a good answer for you personally I'll do my
best but uh um well I appreciate first how
meaningful the practice has been for you and so one
possibility is that um you're ready for something different
now and of course I hope you keep practicing you know some every time but maybe it's
time for you to uh do something that responds to the suffering of the world more actively or more fully than what
you do now I don't know what you do now but uh maybe it's time for you to
actually uh bring the practice to something uh and whether it means that
um you know that you go to the Gaza or the Ukraine and try to
help the children there who are suffering so much or whether
you uh you know form a neighbor neighborhood support group for people who are suffering in your neighborhood
you know I don't know what it would be it does doesn't have to be dramatic um you know you're not going to
end some of the wars in the world but uh do something and as you do it and
probably you should start something small uh you know easy to do but do something and uh and as you do it uh
check in with yourself keep keep checking in be honest about how it's going and you might then at some point
because you know what you're capable of uh how much suffering you're capable of having at some point you'll say okay now
I know I need this practice you know now I really need it yes I read the I read all the stories
why you should be practicing and how it helps other people but now it's you know it's true if I don't practice now uh I'm
going to make a mess what I'm trying to do for the world and that might be the phase you're in and you do that for a while and then
you might be uh ready for like with ush go off with ush to a long
retreat is that okay as an answer for now yes that is that's very helpful uh
as an answer for now and and it brought uh additional clarity as well about what is or is not um ready great okay thank
you thank you so maybe we'll do two more and I see two hands up so it's um so
it's uh is it mij yes thank you um thank you yolan s um my question
has to do with um being a senior and an advanced senior and coming to Buddhism
as a practice and finding that many things that I thought were resolved in
my life through a a longtime spiritual practice and also many years of therapy
have opened up and um I um and and I
hear that it takes time for these things to take place and I'm at I'm beginning
at the end so so how does a senior come into uh active Buddhist practice
okay well active Buddhist practice where do you live in in uh San Jose oh San
Jose um so IMC does have a senior sa a group
that meets most I'm doing senior sa I'm doing the eight path okay so you're
doing lots of I I attend I've been attending your um uh meditation practice
for over a year
so you know so I don't really know you maybe we've had one other conversation like before I somehow recognize you so I
apologize for if I don't remember if we met so it's a little bit hard in this context to have a a really deep meeting
with you about this and to be able to offer you something uh if I take a risk with you and with everyone here uh if
that'll be okay that's fine you so you've had a long spiritual practice and so maybe you have you can um brush me
off if I say something which is not helpful um so it's a thought
experiment or it's based on this premise you might already have a very strong
foundation and the question is can you call on your existing
Foundation as a as a as a foundation with which to practice with the
difficult things which are arising now I I do find that helpful and can you
do so in such a way that your the issues you have do not
get resolved is there something more important for you that can that's here
that can be present that uh for you that uh doesn't depend on these issues being
resolved my uh my desire for for coming to Buddhism was to uh face dying
consciously yes so that that was where I was going to go with you so
imagine that you're on your deathbed and you know somehow you
understand you have about five minutes left to be alive that's the circumstance and it's
you're comfortable you know you're dying the best way you could imagine but you you
you have 5 minutes left and um and then you
remember I think I overpaid my credit card I better do something about this
and call my credit card company and try to fix this and would would is that the best way to
spend your last five minutes alive no not for me so so what would be
better to be present to what's happening uh right with me at that that moment and
and why why is that why is that better than uh dealing with money is important right it was you earned it and you
should not lose it and so why is it why being present at that moment is more
important that the money is is of no use to me at
all um it it has no meaning uh at that particular time it's a p it's something
that's over and done with uhhuh okay okay so that's nice I'm happy to hear
this now what about um and then your the last five minutes and uh some fear that
you have that you still carry with you comes up and there's that old friend
your fear so well that's probably a good thing to do for the last five minutes is to really get into it and be afraid and
you know you know it wouldn't wouldn't that be a good use of your
time no um uh I I'll tell you my concern
now is is um uh my children um
uh letting go of of that letting go of them uh letting go of the things that
that were guiding um cares and concerns in my life and joys and opportunity in
my life and being present you know to what's happening with me right so in you
have five minutes left yeah and your your your kids your family is around you
and they they value you so much you've been kind of a teacher a model for them and they're looking to see how you're
going to die do you think clinging to your kids is the final message you want to give no
what is the final message you want to give
um again just being where being in that moment and doing where my the journey
taking the Journey of my life in uh in a peaceful calm accepting way fantastic so
mij so I apologize if some of the things I say were a little B coarse or something but uh but uh you have a
foundation you know something already you know something very profound about the value of being present here in a
peaceful way it's in you already can you call on it more
now why wait I I feel that that's the practice
and what comes up are are things that I thought were resolved for instance i'
I've worked in in counseling with people in death and dying yeah and and being at
this side of it is different uhuh in a way so so so I I I agree with that so
now we come back to what I said in the beginning do you have the ability to be honest about what's coming up for you to
meet it with mindfulness and intelligence and maybe even try to find a way through it in a way but not you
don't need to have it resolved you can breathe and be present
just fine with the issues coming up because you only have five minutes
left maybe you never know you think you I'm trying to offer
you a different perspective on this is this working it is you think you're up
for the challenge yes I am and I would love to
talk to you about it someday or let hear how it's going and if you're in San Jose maybe you'll come up one Sunday morning
when I'm here and you can say hello hello okay thank you thank you mijch so
then the last one is
Charlie hi Gil um hello from uh near
Boulder Colorado and um now that we all
have learned how to die I don't know what else there is to
say well thank you for that and well if you learn if you've learned how to die
then there there is something important to do and that is to live your life
Fully live Li live live your life
compassionately that um that sounds sounds like it's in line with with what
I'm uh trying to do and I just wanted to express a lot of appreciation to you for
the support I've received from joining you for these guided meditations these
past six weeks and um and and a little bit before that I'm um finding a lot of
um it it the
uh there's always been a a tension in my mind about in meditation
between um oh I guess it's a kind spiritual
bypass escapism going away from Life um through silence through being alone
versus connection uh compassion as you're saying the point of life right um and
um it's and so um
it sounds like you know you talk about you talk about both of those things you
know you talk about creating space and distance from aspects of mind and part
of me says No I don't want to do that I want to be with everything I don't want to create space and distance I want to
be connected to myself every part of myself every part of the world I don't want to go away I don't want to escape I
don't want to bypass I don't and then um
then I'll just think and think and think and kind of time goes by and
um there's um I don't know I don't not sure what my
question is in there there's always there's been this tension between being connected allowing everything versus
creating space um distance seeing things
does that make does that sound like a question yeah yeah I understand your question but turns out both are possible
actually if if you do both they both become better for each other so for
example uh do you have this concern about being disconnected from people and
separating yourself and locking yourself out of people's lives when you go take a
shower and close the door
I just imagining inviting everyone to come with me yes no exactly I want to be alone for
that one and and uh and because in principle what we're doing there is getting clean and when we're clean then
people want to connect to us you know if you never took a shower people would probably be you know pulling away but
you're you you you go back clean and refreshed and you're so much better for
making that connection to people that rhythm of going pulling away and locking
the door in the bathroom to shower and coming out clean is a natural
Rhythm meditation the same way we learn to kind of cleanse ourselves by being a
part in meditation closing our eyes so we come back better cleaner Fuller and
what we're looking for in meditation is not to be um apart from people
we're looking to be to avoid being entangled with people and we come together like this
where it's uncomplicated it's clean it's full it's caring not caught up in people with each
other and and and ultimately we we have better better connections when there's a
separation that comes together like this where each person is met in their own wholeness which a lot of people don't
know how to do but to discover your own wholeness your own fullness your own freedom in
meditation then allows so much more to happen when you come together it's actually the relationships become
richer so I I so you can do both and don't set up one against the other they
both support each other like showering and then I would encourage you
so I I love it that you're this way that you have the sensibility you're concerned that you have a practice that
you want to be in the world and connected maybe in a compassionate way
um uh I think you probably have good things to do in the world for the world
and I would encourage you to be uh
courageous thank you um I will do my best great and hope
hope to join you for a retreat and um at IMC soon great I'd love to have
you come that' be very nice and and as long as you're as long as you understand that uh you're it is a kind of it's
wonderful at these Retreats because it's definitely a way of pulling away from your normal life but we have 40 people
in community that's really special so you doing it in a different context so yes you're pulling away from
your normal life but it's not from life itself it's actually life is Fuller on
Retreat for many people it's a way of stepping into life and in the way that you want to really be connected to life
on the retreat there's a way particular way we step into life in a much more Fuller way we can than we ever can do in
some of our daily lives okay great nice nice to talk to
you so so let me put put it back on Galler view so thank you everyone for
being part of this and I had wanted to hope to do a uh you know breakout group
for you so that you could meet each other but we it seemed like it was nice to continue with the questions so I
appreciated the questions I appreciate all of you being here and all this and and um it's my intention to do these
Community meetings more often and uh certainly I'm inspired after today to do it more often um my schedule is such
that you know it's a little hard but um I will uh look for the next
opportunity so thank you all and be well and and uh I'll see many of you I hope
on U Monday or see you I'll you see me more we'll be
together thank you bye-bye thank you Gil thanks
everyone thank you you so much
that was wonderful nice to see you youil have a good day sir appreciate you thank you
s nice to see everybody
byby than thank you Gil for doing this yes you're welcome you're
welcome thank you thank you thank you everyone for their
wonderful questions right thank you so much for the teachings today they were special very
special thank you okay okay bye bye
bye