thing so today I'm going to continue on this topic of the inner critic and
there's a number of different ways we can Define the inner critic but uh I'm
influenced by Roba when he talks about it and he says it's like almost like a
subpersonality inside of us and I'm saying that not being a psychologist so we don't have to read any psychological
meaning into that just a you know Common everyday usage but it's this voice
that's like maybe it's a voice it's a constellation of uh um experiences
that's like constantly putting us down belittling us this voice of negativity
that's blaming ourselves and nagging us and maybe it's accompanied with this
sense of Shame Shame for what we are or how we are or who we are and it has this
climate of harshness and not only that when part of
the way that we might even know that it's there is there's this feeling of
inadequacy I'm not enough whatever I'm doing it's not enough or I'm not worthy
or who I am as a living being is inadequate not enough in some kind of
way yeah OA there's so much pain and Dua
that can be wrapped up and this uh structure we'll
say so for the guided meditation like I did yesterday I'm going to do one that's not the usual guide meditation that we
find in theas um Retreats or instructions it's
not that General one but um to give myself some credibility I want to say
that I learned this from Sharon salsburg somebody who is you know she's a very
influential figure here in the terva Buddhism in the Contemporary West and
part of the reason why I'm choosing this type of a guided meditation is because it kind of like usurps power from the
thinking mind and the inner critic you know kind of co-ops of thinking mind so I want to
use a guided meditation that's not the usual and not only does it maybe
undermine the thinking mind that likes to protest but it also brings a quality of
spaciousness and warmth and that's what's needed so we're
going to do this kind of a guided meditation I recognize that many of you you know are regular meditators and if
not here in the 7 AM for years now which is such a beautiful thing but you know
maybe have your own meditation practice but just give it a go see what it's like
to do a meditation practice that's a little bit different than the usual just
with the idea of bringing some warmth and spaciousness without a whole amount of
you know striving and trying to get there okay so taking a meditation
posture a posture that has some
uprightness and some ease
this a posture that expresses Our intention to
cultivat meditation cultivate spaciousness and
warmth for the next little
bit maybe a few longer exhales just at
the beginning to promote and support a sense
of well-being or relaxation longer
exhales can be a big support for
that then we'll do some loving kindness towards the
body in a simple
way so you can repeat silently after
me and the thinking mind may want to show up and say oh this is different
this is not the way real meditation is done can just bow to the thinking mind
and respect and love it and then continue with the meditation
May the head be
happy may my head be [Music]
peaceful May the eyes be
happy May the eyes be
peaceful May the neck be
happy May the neck be
peaceful
May the shoulders be
happy May the shoulders be
peaceful May the arms be happy
May the arms be
peaceful May the hands be
happy
May the hands be
peaceful May the upper back be
happy May the upper back be peaceful
May the lower back be
happy May the lower back be
peaceful
May the chest be
happy May the chest be
peaceful May the belly be
happy May the belly be
peaceful May the hips be
happy May the hips be
peaceful May the right leg be
happy May the right leg be peaceful
May the right knee be
happy May the right me be
peaceful May the left leg be
happy May the left leg be
peaceful May the left knee be
happy May the left knee be
peaceful May the feet be
happy May the feet be
peaceful we're using the expression May the body part be
happy as an
invitation not as a
demand sending Goodwill and
warmth with well- [Music] wishing
and working our way back up the
body May the left knee be
happy May the left knee be
peaceful May the left leg be
happy May the left leg be
peaceful May the right knee be happy
May the right KNE be
peaceful May the right leg be
happy May the right leg be
peaceful May the hips be
happy May the hips be
peaceful
May the belly be
happy May the belly be
peaceful May the chest be
happy May the chest be
peaceful May the lower back be
happy
May the lower back be
peaceful May the upper back be
happy
May the upper back be
peaceful May the hands be
happy May the hands be peaceful
May the arms be
happy May the arms be
peaceful May the neck be
happy May the neck be
peaceful May the eyes be
happy May the eyes be peaceful
May the head be
happy May the hand be
peaceful maybe there's some area of the body that could use some
kindness some warmth and some
care sending some well wishes some good wishes some good
will to those
areas
and then to continue with a body scan
at whatever Pace You'
like maybe changing the words to words that more
resonate keeping it very simple very
simple and imbued with openness spaciousness and care
e
e [Music]
[Music]
so good morning good morning everybody or good afternoon good day whatever time
it is uh where you are so I'm continuing on this theme of
uh this inner critic this uh Inner Voice or constellation of experiences or
structure or dynamic I don't really know exactly which word to use but this thing
that's kind of like nagging or belittling us or making us feel like we're inadequate in so many different
ways and in so many different situations this voice of negativity of
how like blaming ourselves and some kind of way and it
might be in an obvious way you like very particular thoughts that we hear like oh
you're no good or something terrible like that or maybe it's just a sense
that things aren't quite right but it comes with a sense of Shame and shame
for how we are or who we are and this
harshness and there's this feeling of inadequacy that comes with this that some how who I am or how I am is not
enough and so there's wow so much pain can be like caught up in
this have to cough
here excuse me sorry about this I mean to cough there so I want to spend just a
little bit this morning talking about how the inner critic works not not the
you know complete everything like unpacked but to just point to something
that might not be noticed and that can be enormously helpful when it is noticed
and that is this the inner critic it finds let's say a fault with a
particular thing like one specific thing and then opens that up and
globalizes it into an entire assess of how we are as a person like the
entirety of how we are a person it goes from one specific little incident and
says therefore it means that you're no good like for
example there might be a way in which for example you might meditate before
hearing this talk and there might be uh instance where you find your mind
wandering off and you know not with the meditation any longer this is what Minds
do right this is why meditation is a practice where we kind of have to train the mind to keep on coming back to the
anchor and that meditation that I guided us and it was the anchor was of saying
phrases directed towards different parts of the body and maybe you found the Mind
chattering away things you need to do or thinking like oh this is silly why am I
doing this then realize like oh yeah oh yeah I'm supposed to be meditating and coming back to Anor I don't know maybe
there's a that might have happened once or twice while you were meditating maybe for just a few of you maybe
not but there's this way in which uh
this uh having noticed that the mind of wandered turns into she you should be a better
meditator by now you're hopeless you're never going to get it or
you know something that just has like this Global assessment of how you are as a person just because the mind wandered
when you were meditating can turn into just this whole
sense of like inadequacy and this sense of being inadequate it might be really slight and
subtle or it might be harsh and obvious so there's a way in which we can feel
just a little like out of sorts or off-kilter or maybe there's a way we
feel a little deflated or unenthusiastic it kind of like you know takes the wind
out of our sails kind of a feeling just in general or it can be this uh really
harsh and really maybe obvious it might not be obvious either just because it's
so familiar we just feel like oh yeah okay this is the way it should be there's this way we can feel like uh
annihilated or like deeply flawed or deeply disappointed in ourselves not
only in ourselves but uh in the world in this way in which there's this uh yeah
sense of hopelessness or like kind of like this lack of energy now or this
want to like just disengage and you know move away from whatever
we're doing this way we want to like go distract ourselves to try to make ourselves feel
better so this feeling of inadequacy it can be just really slight or it can be
really harsh and devastating and it might be obvious or
it might be really subtle and it might show up in specific words I'm using words like uh I'm
hopeless or this just uh you're no good or you're
not good enough or something like that or it might not be in distinct words it
might just be this General sense of I don't know deflation and uh this
you know losing um some well maybe losing energy of wanting to go forward
or if there is energy the energy is all about okay I have to fix it I have to be better here I'm going to do something
about it instead of this sense of kind of some uprightness an ability to just
meet whatever is to be showing up next so just this general feeling of
inadequacy or not being enough and part of this inadequacy shows up also as a
sense of should like okay something should happen maybe it's not even clear
what it is but there's a sense of okay whatever is happening whatever I'm experiencing it's not good enough
there's got to be something better like I have to be better I have to be having
a better experience or I have to be a better meditator I have to show up in
some kind of way so the impact the consequence of
this feeling of inadequacy that this feeling like things need to be better or it's not good
enough is that it is uh squashes our ability to see clearly like see clearly
what's actually happening there's this way when the inner critic is up again whether it's subtle or it's
obvious there can be a wish to either like distract ourselves because it's so uncomfortable or there's this real sense
of whatever is happening is not good enough and we have to go seek or create or manufactur manipulate engineer do
something to make it better so when this feeling of
inadequacy is there we're not able to get a clear sense of what's actually
happening we're not we're kind of like disengaged
from what's actually here what's the felt experience of this
moment we're no longer to be present with that we're no longer able to be present with that like this feeling of
inadequacy kind of like hijacks our attention and it feels so uncomfortable
that we're distracting or going elsewhere or trying to make this uncomfortable feeling going away so
we're not able to see or get a clear sense of what's actually happening in the moment this is often why the inner
critic kind of like just feels pervasive and isn't able to be seen but also what
we can't see is what's needed to learn from the
situation maybe this um for example that I gave like during the meditation maybe
you found the mind was wandering a lot and maybe we can learn that oh maybe it
it's for example maybe it's helpful to have my morning coffee before I meditate
I'm one of those people I have coffee in the morning before I meditate it's just what I do I I I don't know I enjoy it I
like it and maybe but maybe that's something that I have learned like okay yeah meditation is a little bit
different if I have my coffee or maybe when the inner critic is up and running
and we can't see clearly we can't see clearly what is true the mind
wanders and then what is extra this feeling of like Oh I'm a terrible
meditator or it has to be better or I need to be better or it should be different these are two different things
what's true what actually happened and then what gets added on Top This you
this inner critic is adding some assessment that um somehow we're
inadequate in some kind of way so what are some ways that we can
practice with this and this uh is will be kind of what we'll be exploring with this week is
first of all we want to relate to this inner critic if we're able to see how
it's showing up and belittling us and with a a sense of harshness or
inadequacy or shame or whatever way it shows up we want to relate to it with
spaciousness and kindness and right it would just be the
critic on the critic and then there'd be the critic of the critic of the critic and off we go just this cycle of being
critical so the inner critic would love to co-opt our looking at the inner
critic it would love to do that that's partly why I'm doing a different guided
meditation because that guided meditation kind of gives the Mind something to do so it's not so readily
coopting uh our experience so we want to relate to the inner critic with
curiosity spaciousness and warmth like oh okay here it is and to be honest it's
not surprising if it's there it's so prevalent and kind of like modern
society or the way things are these days and so when we discover that
there's this strong feeling of inadequacy part of the way that we can
undermine like usurp of the power or the authority that the inner critic likes to
give is to just simply and with some warmth and some spaciousness ask
ourselves how am I right now how am I right now what's the
experience at this moment and so tune into the mediate felt
experience the inner critic is always trying us to feel like something is better and we have to do something else
but to kind of just tune in okay no actually what's happening is a way that really can
undermine this thinking mind that's trying to convince us that something else has to be better so just ask
ourselves how am I right now in the way that we might see uh a child that is a
bit out of sorts but uh we're not sure what's happening and we just ask oh what's going on how are
you with care and warmth not because we have to fix it not because it's wrong to
feel that way but because this is how we Express Care this is how we express warmth and
uh engagement and connection how am I right
now and then just be open to what's happening we don't have to find the answer don't have to dig for the answer
because the inner critic is telling us that the experience should be different and we should be
different and so we can add this how am I right now just with some warmth and
some care and allow whatever is to be found to be found and maybe we discover
that actually we feel terrible and can we bring some care to
that maybe we might find that oh no things are fine and can we bring some care to
that and so we can add this to yesterday's instructions of I'm doing
the best I can right now I'm doing the best I can right now
maybe is a way to uh respond to the inner critic or maybe the sense
of how am I right now how am I like what's what's going on these are two
different ways in which can we can respond to when we feel the inner critic
and maybe sometimes one way is more accessible than another way maybe sometimes you can't really like respond
or feel into how you are right now and maybe all you can have this idea is I'm
doing the best I can right now so whichever is available these are two different ways in which we can respond
when we discover that this inner critic is up and running and not only is it up
and running but it seems as believable and authorita which is what the inner critic likes to
do right to convince us that it's correct so meeting the inner critic with
some curiosity and care we don't have to be critical of the
critic so with that I'm wishing you a wonderful rest of the day however
whether it's the end of the day for you or the beginning of the day meeting the critic with curiosity and Care thank you
thank
you