good evening welcome welcome it's nice to see you all I st
practice together
so today I want to talk a little bit about balancing the amount of effort we
put into this practice of course it takes effort to go
against our usual patterns to go against entropy you know just kind of this less
and less energy and more and more chaos right of course it does anything we want
to do in our life takes a certain amount of energy and effort for the purpose of
this talk I'll just kind of use energy and effort
together so if we want to kind of like bridge this idea between the theoretical
between this ideas that we have about practice and Buddhism and meditation and
what's possible bridge the gap between the ideas to the actually having that in our
life what's possible of course of course requires a certain amount of effort and
energy and part of the question is or well how do we do that is it it just
like do you just push non-stop because it feels like such a big thing that's being asked of us such a big
uh shift to have more and more freedom in one's life it often can feel like wow
I'm so far from that it the amount of energy must be an amazing amount of
energy certainly more than I have I might have that kind of a
feeling maybe I'll start by saying the only energy that's
needed is just the energy to do one small tiny next step that's it that's
all sometimes we can feel overwhelmed we have to think like wow I have this seemingly large distance to
travel but right always starts just with the first
step so I'd like to talk a little bit uh i' like to share this simile that's uh
in the suit does that talks about this a little bit and like to come at this idea
of energy and effort from a different angle so here's this simile it goes like
this suppose a gold smith would prepare a hot
furnace heat up a receptacle take some gold using tongs
and put it into the receptacle then from time to time the Goldsmith would blow on
it they'd sprinkle water on it and from time to time just look on as
the gold was heating as you can imagine right this is somebody who has gold and they want to
make some bracelets or jewelry out of it and so get it from a nugget they have to
purify it and make it so that they can work with it so the assimil continues if the
Goldsmith were to only blow on it then it is possible that the gold would just
burn up it would get too hot if the Goldsmith were to only
sprinkle water on it it is possible the gold would cool down and couldn't work
with it and if the Goldsmith were to just look on it is possible that the gold
would not reach the right consistency they wouldn't be paying attention whether it's too hot or to cold or what
was needed but if the Goldsmith would from time to time blow on it sprinkle water
on it or just look on then the good would be the gold would become purified
bright unblemished rid of imperfection so purified malleable and wieldy can work
with it and steady attained to imperturbability wasn't gonna I don't
actually know how to interpret that honestly I was going to say something steady and attain to imper Ability but the reason why that kind of
expression is in there because this is the exact same language that The Bu
Buddha uses to describe his mind before
Awakening purified bright unblemished rid of
imperfection malleable wieldy steady attained to
imperturbability this whole idea of being malleable and wieldy sometimes we think like oh okay
meditation or practice is about you just got to stick your mind on something and
staple it there and you'll be apply more energy and keep it there and you'll be good to go but it's not like that it's
you having to be malleable and wieldy that is to be able to work with whatever
life is bringing you whatever that moment is bringing you whatever is being
experienced and then I'll continue this last part of the um simile says but if
the Goldsmith were to blow on it sprinkle on it or just look on it becomes malleable and wieldy and
purified and then it continues and says then whatever ornament the Goldsmith
wishes to make from it whether a bracelet earrings a necklace or a garland that
can be achieved so this idea of what if it's
malleable then we can do what we want to
do we can make something beautiful that maybe we share with
others maybe it's jewelry for ornamentation for ourselves maybe it's for others but something that's uh has
some beauty to it and some value to it so I'd like to unpack this simile a
little bit because there's this the in this description there's three ways to work
with the gold you can blow on it make it hotter sprinkle water on it make it
cooler or three just look on and the first two with a making it
hotter or colder I feel like we can do this there's a way like okay just give me the instructions
I can do it you know water okay should it be distilled water sparkling water should I get it purified mineralized you
know I get what temperature should it be this like something we can do our blow on it okay should I get a Bellow can I
just use my breath it's like you know this activity we feel like oh okay I I can do that I can do
that the hard part is just looking
on this is really the hard part often right so much of like our lives
I'll speak for myself my life I feel like I can fill it up with all these to-do list thing after thing after thing
that needs to be done this NeverEnding to-do list you like a life could just be one long to-do list right if we let
it and then this whole idea of but from time to time just to look on it's not
saying to just exclusively do that it's not saying to just exclusively make it heater hotter put heat on it I made a
new word make it heater but this idea that to have some
of the wisdom or to learn really it's not like we know
automatically for the example with gold like when to put water on it or put uh
heat on it or when to look on chances are that I know in Ancient India that
somebody was would be an apprentice before they were going to be a Goldsmith they would learn from somebody and
through trial and eror so this idea of just looking
on I'd like to say another word we could use and this word is part of the parames
these are a collection of practices and characteristics that we often do not
when we're meditating or I should say in addition to meditating in our daily life
and that is this word kti and poly in
English patience patience we all know we should have
patience right this is not a news for anybody but this is kind of like a
reminder that practice isn't only about like just putting more and more energy
into it and it's you know in certainly in times
that we need to just be patient be simply looking on because if we only
apply energy then we will exhaust ourselves and get burnt out or there's a
way that we can be this really striving that can make our practice feel brittle
and very enjoyful very dry and burden some and you know humans can only do
that for so long and we will only get so far and I remember I think I've told
this story a few times but uh being on a Meditation Retreat I don't this had such
a big impact on me that uh this was a long Meditation Retreat and a having a
practice discussion with one of the teachers and uh she was saying to me
something like well you know people like you Diana that like to strive I was like
I don't strive what are you talking about I was like so offended and then I
left I thought okay I'm going to strive to make sure that she knows that I'm not a striver you know I just had this whole
idea of like I have to work harder in order to show that I'm not a striver I just couldn't see how hard I was just
working working working I couldn't even I just felt like I had to do more just
that was the only message I had gotten I had to do more and didn't appreciate that no it's not about just more more
more it's about being sensitive to what's needed and sometimes it's stepping back
and looking on and allowing things to unfold the way they're going to
unfold because there's this way if we feel like we always have to be putting heat on or cooling down there's a way
that maybe we like to do that because makes us feel like we can control
things but have you noticed we don't get to control as much as we think we
can and so there's this way in which sometimes maybe we want to do this because it helps us to feel anything but
helpless we're just trying to do anything we're not even sure what we're supposed to do sometimes or maybe we
have this inner critic that raises up and is telling us
us yeah whatever you're doing it's not good enough or whatever you're doing it's inadequate in fact you're
inadequate right this inner critic can show up in our thoughts and then kind of
as a in response we can just apply more and more effort and to be
patient is a way that's kind of admitting like okay I'm not really needed right here
right now I don't have to jump in and try to fix everything instead to be
patient is to recognize okay this maybe isn't what I want maybe
it's uncomfortable maybe it's uh not what I'm looking
for but maybe uh it doesn't have to be fixed
right this moment maybe I can look
on maybe it's too hot and it can cool by itself without my sprinkling water on
it so there's this way in which if we just overexert
ourselves we maybe it makes us feel better that we feel like we're doing something covering up a sense of any
sense of inadequacy or
helplessness but there's this maybe the opposite side too she was like oh okay well sometimes we can collapse and feel
like okay well there's nothing I can do and uh maybe there's this way in
which we just kind of like disengage and you know maybe with it like well the
hell with that I'm not going to do it and just go somewhere else instead of looking just simply
looking on there a way of disconnecting or being disparaging or
dismissive of whatever it is and then going off and doing something
else or maybe there's this way that also if we are don't take the time to maybe
simply look on we may be ex uh not using energy or
effort in a wise way maybe we're making mistakes or doing things that aren't
helpful just because we're just busily doing and the Buddha has a simile for
this also which um I really appreciate here's
a he spokes about this and as the Wagoner so the person who's you know has
a cart with horses and cart and is directing them as the Wagoner who left
the highway a road with an even surface and entered upon the rugged
path Broods mournfully with a broken axle so the wagoners is upset that they
have a broken axle because they thought oh let me take a shortcut I'm going to
go off of the highway here and I'm going to go you know Overland and and then their exle breaks and then you're like
filled with regret or feel like oh why did I do that part of the reason why I
like this uh simly I think it's very illustrative but I mean this like
literally happens well I don't go off the highway but there's sometimes like you see like the traffic oh I better
take this exit first and then right it ends up being much slower
right because the roads are just as busy or even busier or something like this
this way like oh no I I'm I'm I'm don't want to be patient and get through this traffic
so how many of you have done that right many of us
right but for us usually we don't end up with a broken axle or something like that it just takes longer but in the
simile here the Buddha is pointing to you know maybe there are things that's
taking the shortcut leaving the this what what is the expression
here the even surface of course concrete or pavement
that just didn't exist back in Ancient India just like didn't exist so in order
for it to be an even surface meant that there was lots of of people that had been down that path
before and so that can be helpful to note in the same way that The Apprentice
is learns from the Goldsmith often we learn from what other people have done
before I'm not saying that we have to do Lemmings and just without thinking follow other people but neither should
we all also think that there has to be a shortcut or sometimes these days we use
this word hack there has to be a hack you know like oh okay I don't need to put that much effort or take that much
time and there's got to be a shortcut sometimes these shortcuts don't work but because we have this
impatience we want to take
them so if we don't maybe I'll just say this
so what is needed is this balance between effort energy plain energy and
some patience and this is part of practice it's like
learning when to do what when is it best
to apply more heat when is it best to cool down how do you know when things
are too hot and when is it time to just look
on I want to talk a little bit about patience here we can think about it as
as uh nonreactivity as this uh not raging or blaming blaming
ourselves blaming others or not despairing or making wild stories when
we encounter something that's uncomfortable or
difficult so often the Mind wants to just start blaming oursel or others or
wants to it shouldn't be this way as soon as I get home I'm going to write a letter to
the highway calr and this road should be
shorter wherever I want to go or there should be less traffic or whatever it is right these things that we want to do we
start blaming or you know something thinking that it's something has to be
done but patience is this way in which we like hold these difficulties in a
spacious way yep this is what's happening right
now and it's difficult but it doesn't have to be fixed
precisely this moment doesn't mean it needs to be there
forever it doesn't mean this is the best thing but all it means is kind of acknowledging it's what's here it's
actually what's happening and can we be okay for that
moment there's this way if we can like hold it with this little bit more spaciousness
then the mind can feel a little bit more peaceful some of the agitation or the restlessness has the time to maybe
settle down a little bit and with that settling down can become more and more
wisdom like the wisdom can bubble up and we can see things in a clearer way or
maybe even see like a bigger picture which can help point the way of maybe
what's to be done next as opposed to just reacting immediately when the thing is difficulty
so patience when we encounter things that are
uncomfortable patience uh in our relationships with others can we be in a difficult
situation with someone instead of lashing out with anger saying things that we might regret is there a way that
we can maintain our composure doesn't mean that we're happy
it doesn't mean that we approve of what's been happening what's happening it just means that we're not lashing out
we're not collapsing we're not bolting but to maintain some composure
composure and and be there for what's going to
unfold next take a deep breath and be present as best you
can just think how your life would unfold if those times when which you had
conversations and they were difficult but you were able to kind of like stay grounded and
spacious even though it was not what you wanted to hear how many times have we said things
that we have regret I know I do say things like oh yeah I've regret about
that and ouch regret is one of those painful painful
things patience and meditation right so much where we were sitting and then you
just bring the Mind back you get lost in thought planning the grocery list as soon as I get home I got to remember to
do this or that or you know whatever it is and then oh yeah that's right I'm supposed to be meditating just again and
again and again maybe there's this feeling like when is that Bell going to
ring here's a here's a little hint that I learned never look at your watch it
doesn't matter what it says it will never be good news because if it's 30 seconds before
you're like oh I shouldn't have looked I could have waited and if it's uh 45
minutes before the bell's going to ring you're like oh my gosh when is it gonna ring I can't believe it so this is
Diana's little hint I I stopped ever looking at the watch or the clock and that made me feel
better so patience as maybe this non-reactivity whatever it finds us we
what kind of this difficulties find our way and maybe
maybe a different way to say non-reactivity is just holding things in a spacious way that is not getting tight and
insisting things being different but instead like okay this is how it is and
being able to maintain composure or you know not lose it not lose composure but
also patience is also perseverance it's kind of like maybe this little bit of
maybe forbearance or something like this like sticking with things even when they
take time to show results not
uh leaving right away or maybe I heard this expression like patience is like
giving up a deadline that something has to happen but it's not giving up it's
just giving up the deadline that has to happen right then so still hanging in there and the
same way that we plant seeds and it takes time to Blossom or flower or seed or grow
whatever they're going to do so many things are like that and while they're underground of course we
don't see what the seeds are doing so often we don't really know how
things are I I keep on using this expression unfolding unfolding within ourselves
unfolding within others and folding just in our environment so this idea of patience is
more like focusing on maybe consistency or perseverance or hanging in
there so what I think it's also important when we're talking about patience to talk about well what
patience isn't because it's not this numbing
resignation like H okay you know kind of like
disconnecting and being um annoyed like you know tapping the foot
type of you know thing whether you're literally or figuratively doing that so it's not like disconnecting from
what's Happening and patience is not like gritting your teeth or clenching your hands holding on for dear life or
when is this going to be over that's more like waiting with
aversion that's not patience either or maybe patience also isn't like
being impervious to the pressure to change or do something
different it's not like being completely uh um not imp I use this word impervious
it's being impenetrable or uh just not paying attention to what's happening and
said nope I'm going to just do this no we could say that's more like
stubbornness that's not really patience or maybe that's uh just resistance to
change this kind of nope I'm just going to sit here and
wait and PTI patience is also it's not a paralysis or it's not a weakness wow
right patience is a strength of course it
is and so often we have this kind of our society or kind of like promotes this
sense of go go go do do do and the busier you are the more important you must
be so it's easier to be busier in doing but it's not so easy to be patient I
think we all know this so also patience doesn't mean that
we become a dant that others can just tread upon however they
wish but instead by this holding things spaciously and still being connected to
them not losing our composure but staying there we can start to see
oh this is what's really happening here this is taking longer because of
that and maybe it's helpful for me to just push a little bit over here or
maybe it's just helpful for me to get out of the way but whatever it
is patience kind of helps creates the conditions in which the best wisdom that we have can arise and then we can do
what's best to be done that's so different than just passively being a doormat or that's so different
than just uh being stuck and staying there or something like this instead of
being a doormat maybe the part of the wisdom would say like nope actually I need to Clearly say no to this person to
this whatever it is that might be so maybe the next step is after a little
bit of patience is to see okay it's time to do something here andless something is to say
no maybe I'll say something a few words about okay well how can we cultivate
patience because we can't always make things go faster we can't necessarily
make things be pleasant all the time right if we could have done it we would
have done that already certainly
but there's this way that we can we can adjust how we respond or
react to whatever life is bringing us and Sylvia borain she calls patience
this unglamorous courage I kind of like this unglamorous
courage courage sounds I don't know LOF
we all want to be courageous but unglamorous courage maybe
patience is this way to stay connected not
disengage and not feel like we have to fix it at that
moment and this way we can think about um patience
requires maybe two things some un Pleasant circumstance
right you don't need patience if everything is perfect and lovely and a little bit of effort this is the effort
to hang in there not run away not disconnect not just jump into busyness
if unless we have a sense of what some wisdom about what needs to be
done so we don't need to cultivate uh opportunities to
cultivate patience life will bring those to us that they just naturally will but in the
way that Sylvia Borstein is saying that patience is unglamorous courage
something that patience and courage share is that you become more courageous
by being courageous you become more
patient by being patient when there 's this uh one
line from uh this poet Katie
Lang she's also a singer some of you know might know her and this uh one line
that I just love it says I've worried is it so that lessons of patience are
learned slow is it so that lessons of patience
are learned slow yes it is
so so I'll just say a few words here so this won't be a surprise to
anybody well what can we support this uh how can we hurry up this patience
learning for patience one is just bringing some mindfulness to our
experience one is to notice when we're impatient sometimes we don't even notice
notice when we're standing there with our hands on our foot or you know our foot is doing this or we're kind of like
I don't know doing something fidgeting often like oh okay this could be an
opportunity to practice patience let take a deep breath and like
it's like this right now that could be an opportunity to
practice patience but takes some mindfulness to recognize so often where there's these little bursts of
impatience that we don't even notice and often we'll notice by how it feels in the body like this restlessness
like we want to get up and run or we want to honk the horn if we're in the
car or something like this the second thing
is love and kindness practice this way in
which having some warm-heartedness some spaciousness
in our hearts and Minds supports a sense of well-being of course it does and we all
know if we have more of a sense of well-being then we can be more patient if we are feeling really
agitated of course we're more impatient so part of this practice is to
cultivate it does cultivate a sense of happiness and well-being and ease
mindfulness can do this loveing kindness practice can do this and also if you
have a concentration practice that also can kind of like be a way in which that
uh enriches one's life or nourishes one's inner life in a way which it feels
like a little more space a little more steady a little bit more warmth so that impatience
doesn't arise as readily in so many
situations it's a mindful practice and love and kindness practi is a way to support
patience and then we need patience as a balance to the effort that we're
doing patients both in times of um just being willing to
wait takes time for changes to be made for us to undo patterns of a
lifetime patterns of whatever patterns it might be patterns of impatience or
patterns of trying to fix everything immediately or flying off the handle or whatever it might
be and also patience as a way of just kind of like holding difficulties
spaciously not insisting that that moment they be different but instead to be recognized
it's like this and then babies in aside I'll say we might say well how is patience
related to equinity which also kind of like holds things spaciously I would say patience is more
when you are really really wishing that it were different but you're not you're kind of like holding yourself in
check kindly whereas equinity is you're not necessarily wishing things were
different you recognize that oh yeah this is uncomfortable but it's uh not as much of
a problem whereas patience maybe the uncomfortableness is more of a problem
but but um you're holding the problem this more spaciously but it's maybe
patient there's more discomfort than with equinity I would say if you wanted
to think about those so patience is the counterbalance
to energy and effort so thank you for your attention
and if you like I'll I'll open it up for some questions and comments if you have
something you'd like to add so thank
you yes the question was did Katie Lang sing
that song constant craving yes and she was actually a Buddhist practitioner so yeah yeah yeah so it's not a not a
uh what's the word I'm looking there's a reason why she uses these lines right in her some of her songs thank you yes I
was struck by your comment about not wanting to fix things
immediately or can it wait do you have any comments about how you find that
balance between being patient and that point at which you do take action
or jump into the phay so to speak yeah this is such a um great question part of
the way that we can find it is maybe the uh I'm going I'm pointing to my body because the way it feels in the body
there's a difference between agitation and that fuels uh activity and like some
like oh this is what needs to be done in an activity so it's to maybe like feel
in is it is it being fueled by agitation or restlessness like oh something has to
be different here or is it like some clarity nope this is what needs to be done is that helpful yes thank
you so there are times when I need to be patient and I realize that the problem
isn't the situation I have to be patient about the problem is an abundance of
energy because I got triggered and so how do I deal with this
abundance of energy can you say a little bit more when when you mean triggered you mean
like that your that's your emotions are up or what does that mean yeah emotions are up um I don't like what's going on
and I'm going to do something about it and the energy do something about it is
right there for me and I can't put it to one side and so your question is what how do
how do I put that energy aside I see do you need to maybe there's maybe
there's a time like you have a sense of okay I know I none of this could be done now but maybe um take some notes or here
was like here's some ideas or maybe to look into this or maybe talk to that person or do that or maybe there's the
energy could be used in a way that can create the conditions in which something could be done at a time when it is
appropriate no I'm impatient with that because I want to put it aside because I
want to put the energy aside but I get what you're saying so you there's this agitation and
it's uncomfortable yeah yeah oh
busted yeah so maybe here's something else that I'll say this is not some it's
like so uh I don't know it's simple right and some people feel like no
that's too simple but I'll just offer this feel your feet on the ground and just keep on coming back to your feeling
your feet on the ground that does two things one it kind of brings the Mind back to the body which even if you're
walking is moving slower than the what the mind is doing and two being
connected like being kind of grounded and connected is just something that's
really helpful so that we don't fly off the handle so to speak so this is some
and sometimes like when we're really agitated we don't have access to our greatest wisdom we don't have access
to much really so feeling one's feet on the ground just that pressure on the
bottom of the foot can be enormously helpful it's surprisingly helpful thank
you thank you for your talk um brought up many things for me um
the one I'm thinking of um was prominently is the story about the uh can you can you hold this just a little
bit closer thank you the student that was asking the master if I work really hard how long will it take me to be
enlightened and he said 10 years and he the student said well what if I work do
double time and work really extra hard Master said 20 years yes exactly it's a
great story that's that's what uh eroses me with that and also the Serenity
Prayer um about you know having that wisdom to know recognize the things you can change
and the things you can't and finding that that space yeah yeah thank you
thank you that's great if you work extra extra hard it
takes longer I think that's such a great story
because uh right kind of sums up so many
things just calls to mind as saying that you're trying to dance faster than the music oh I haven't heard this very nice
yeah
okay okay well thank you all and I wish you all a lovely rest of the
evening if you have some questions or comments you're welcome to come up and talk to me if you like