okay so let's get started uh this week I want to talk
about a set of pithy instructions that the Buddha gave to a
follower and which I found very meaningful to unfold over some years of
practice I'll just tell you a little bit about it before we start
meditating so the Buddha teaches about four foundations on which a liberated
person stands and then he gives four instructions or verbs that go with those
that we can follow in order to strengthen each foundation and even though the context
is this liberated person they're remarkably simple instructions and my
impression is that they're meant for everyone and are simply ones that are
powerful enough to take us very far so we can start with them right
now and then these same four appear in a teaching from a later Buddhist tradition
from the Tibetan tradition but in a a different guise there they're called the
four inspirational blessings so we'll call this series the
four inspirational blessings but that's not from the suta um we'll talk about
the blessing aspect on Friday after we go through the list as it appears in the
original suta for those who track the sutas this is Maji Manaya 140 and the four
foundational practices are to not neglect wisdom to preserve truth to
cultivate relinquishment and to train for peace so we'll talk about each of those
and then step back to the bigger picture at least that's the that's the plan and
we'll see how it unfolds so let's go ahead and meditate
together so settling into your meditation
posture finding your place and if you're comfortable doing so
please close your eyes bringing attention
Inward and just sense the places where you're making
contact your seat against the chair or the
cushion or whatever you're lying down
on feeling the settledness the balance of that
posture and allowing yourself to be
supported letting go into that
stability and sensing how the body Rises up from the stable
Foundation if you're sitting up it could feel as if there's almost a force lifting the body
gently booing it up like water supports
something feeling the straightness of the spine in a relaxed way
and then beginning to soften the
body softening the muscles of the
face and the eyes in the eye sockets
softening the [Music]
jaw down through the
shoulders relaxing the rib cage in the
diaphragm down into the belly
area releasing the arms and the
hands and down through the hips
legs all the way down into the ankle joints and feet just inviting ease and
connecting with the body as it
is it's fine as it
is connecting with the quality of mindfulness
of being present feeling the presence of your
awareness right here not thinking about the past or the
future but being willing for now to just follow along with the
present
connecting in then with the simple sensations of the breath an easy way to
connect to the present
moment
really feeling the direct sensations of the breath so not an idea or picture in your
head about lungs what the actual
Sensations felt by the
body you may notice that the in breath is different
from the out breath on the in breath there's the
touch of air on the nostrils or the upper
lip perhaps coolness as the air enters the nasal
passages some feeling of flow and expansion
maybe you feel it in the throat or the chest of the
belly shifting clothing against the
skin and then at some point that comes to an end and there's an out breath that
has a different set of Sensations more a feeling of softening
or relaxation or falling of the diaphragm maybe the air is a little
warmer and the flow is
outward not just simple distinctions that help us know whether it's an INB
breath or an out breath how do you
know
we may begin to sense the breath as a whole body
phenomen May really it isn't just the literal air that we can
feel maybe as the chest expands and the shoulders
shift position there's a slight shift in how our hips
are maybe we can feel the breath is energy that flows throughout the
body so as we connect with the body in a gentle
way okay again notice certain distinctions the body
isn't all one
way we can feel places that have a sense of more solidity in other areas that
feel light or open or
soft warm or cool actually quite
varied throughout the body and just letting that be as it
is in particular we may notice areas of
relative tension and relative
softness it's not that one is right and one is wrong but it is okay to Incline toward a
general [Music]
softening maybe allowing the breath energy to pass through or around places
of
tension perhaps letting the body feel like it's being lowered into a warm pool
water
e
and as we continue to sit it's possible to notice when the mind gets
distracted and when it is mindful
and again we don't need an assessment of right or wrong good or
bad but a simple noticing of how it
is when there's mindfulness and when there are BS of
thought what is different between those different states
of the Mind
youing off thinking for a while and we come back does that thinking have an
impact on the body something different
there
it's very natural that things change the body
changes the ability to be mindful
changes the thoughts and maybe emotions change
come go
shift
e
another layer of noticing is how we are
meeting all of this changing experience in the breath in the
body in the emotions and thoughts
and awareness how do we meet all of that we may meet it with
kindness interest
care or perhaps there's striving
or aversion or
judging and what is the distinction between kind
interest and judging or [Music]
striving can we feel the distinction between those is there anything noticeable in the
body
perhaps
so it's very helpful in meditation to be able to make beneficial
distinctions spiritually meaningful distinct distinctions or
distinguishment
so allowing the mind to rest with just simple interest in all the
differences and changes that are going
on with an eye toward not suffering not
clinging and that includes both what we're aware of and how we need
it
e
so it may be that even from
this relatively short exploration
of beneficial distinctions you've already
seen how it's possible to be with tension in
the body and softness how it's possible to be with
different emotions or thoughts or the way the mind gets
distracted and then just coming
back checking the attitude in the way that we're
aware there's so many different I want to say handles or knobs
to turn in a sense it's not complex but um we have so many ways that we can make
simple adjustments toward being more easeful suffering Less in any given
moment and this is much of the art of just living a mindful
life how are things now how am I with it could I be
Freer oh my mind isn't free right now okay I'll be with
that so the encouragement is to bring this same kind of
simple awareness into daily life it's definitely a more
complex um set of inputs that's why we practice on the
cushion but during the day could we have a simple attitude of kindness
interest awareness paying attention to whether
our body is getting tense paying attention
to other
people having a sense that if we're present and aware with an attitude of non
clinging that's a spiritually meaningful way of being and it's very
simple and it rests on the mind's basic ability to notice this and that to be
aware of spiritually meaningful distinctions between
[Music] things we can help ourselves this way
and by natural extension we have to help everyone else in doing
that
so this week we'll be exploring a suta that has four compact
instructions for walking the path and in the suta the Buddha meets a
very dedicated practitioner a monk who has gone forth as a Buddhist monk
without even meeting the Buddha so he must have ordained with one of the Buddha's senior
disciples and the Buddha is impressed with his practice and
dedication so he offers this teaching on four fundamental practices that are simple but can take a
person very far along the path maybe all the way to
Liberation and so the Buddha says in this teaching that a person can stand
upon these four foundations as reliable activity that
will move us toward Liberation so we'll explore them as
practical activities that we can engage with both on and off the cushion and
they can go very deep they keep unfolding over time they you maybe even
when we first hear them we think I don't really know what that is or it sounds kind of abstract but as we start looking
at little specific examples it's like oh I get it oh and there's more and there's
more here we see new and different ways of seeing
them so the first one is to not neglect
wisdom to not neglect wisdom so today is April 8th
2024 there will be a total solar eclipse visible in the northern hemisphere which
is amazingly happened twice in the last seven years and where I am it's going to start
in just a few hours it won't be complete where I am um
in the past solar eclipses were associated with
various stories about Gods eating the Sun or Gods fighting in the sky uh
nearly every culture has come up with its own stories to explain
why the sky gets dark in the middle of the day and typically in history these have
been somewhat negative stories because it's disturbing when the Sun goes away
briefly during the day that's not our usual intuitive understanding of
it but but now in our present time right people treat it like a spectacle and
they they flock to see eclipses out of Amazement or for fun or for scientific
interest and it is amazing and it's interesting we have a whole different story about what's going on we have
stories about the Moon and the Sun and the
Earth so what does it mean to not neglect wisdom it has something to do with not
getting caught up in the particular story but to remember to pay attention
to what is spiritually relevant about any given experience and as experience
unfolds so whether experience is totally mundane and ordinary or whether the sun is
disappearing from the sky can we direct our attention in some beneficial
way so wisdom is about making beneficial distinctions like I said spiritually
meaningful or in in the medit ation or maybe valuable valuable distinguishing
of experience so the ability this ability to make distinctions is inherent
in the human mind that's the faculty of wisdom of making
distinctions but if we look at our mind and our experience we have to admit that
sometimes we don't use this capacity as well as it could be used yes so you know we're not talking about
the distinction of whether to watch the eclipse from Houston or Buffalo that's
not so important spiritually uh even if we might have to make such a choice um
but non- neglecting wisdom is means remembering to make the distinctions
that are important that are going to be valuable or beneficial for us and usually that means starting at least
with what is actually known what is actually present in this moment um not
an imagination about the future not a getting lost in a memory about the past
not coming up with a fantasy or complicated story and living in that or some kind of
an ideal that's not actually present what is actually present are
various experiences in the body and the mind and also various perspectives that
were're bringing to those experiences which maybe are wise like the fact that
things change that's a wise perspective yesterday I was driving in a
parking lot looking for a space and I saw someone backing out just
ahead it's nice timing so I stopped to wait and take that
place and the car um backed up and then it kept backing up and backing up
getting very close to my car I think it didn't see me the driver didn't see me so I uh the first thing I could remember
to do was I honked um and I couldn't easily back up so quickly I wasn't in
the right gear um and the other car was going pretty fast but it managed to to just
miss my car it was just it just swung out a little bit to the side it almost then overlapped um but to the side it
must have been just inches um I don't think that person ever saw or heard my honk but they stopped
and and then went on forward on their way it was really close and I was rather
amazed that we didn't Collide um but once the car was gone and nothing was
aiss I found that my mind just went went back to calmness and I I even checked in
my body I actually hadn't there hadn't really been time for me to have an adrenaline rush and get agitated there
was but but there was a little part in the back of my mind that wanted to get
agitated or irritated or scared you know it it kept saying but shouldn't we be
rattled by that shouldn't we be afraid shouldn't our heart be pounding um and for the most part I wasn't really it had
all been quite quick actually it was over and nothing had happened um so I
thought yeah my mind didn't neglect wisdom at that moment it didn't fall prey to spinning out or getting off into
discursive thought or getting angry at the other person how could they have been so distracted to not even see or hear me as
far as I know um it kind of just stayed with reality it was like yeah that was
really close but our day gets to go on we're not standing here right now exchanging information with someone so I
even felt grateful at that moment and I don't quite know how it was so fortunate
um but we can notice you know in our practice that we have gained some modum
of wisdom um even if you've just started mindfulness practice usually we can feel
right away intuitively that there's some wisdom uh about meditating or you know
this seems useful something like that so uh the question question then is can we
honor that wow even whatever small amount of wisdom there is in my mind in
my life in my heart um can I honor that and we have to
admit that we don't always you know because because we don't but it is um it is possible to
consider then what does cause me to neglect my my
wisdom I have it sometimes and why is it that sometimes we don't honor that or
why is it that sometimes we neglect that so I thought about a few things in my own life that I know get in the way of
remembering wisdom one of the main things is surely desire wanting something you know when I
want something my mind Narrows in and focuses on that I'm going for that and
it's easy at that moment to forget all kinds of things to forget that things
change to forget that things aren't mine to forget that to forget to pay enough attention to other people um you know
it's not always in a dramatic way but I see uh that the desire Narrows the mind
in a certain way so it's not that we don't um operate by means of wanting to get
the next thing like a drink of water or the next or going to the bathroom or getting somewhere in our car uh we do
have those simple daily life movements toward things but can we keep our mind
open and spacious so it's still in touch with wisdom while we do those things um another thing that can get in
the way of um honoring our wisdom can be a lack of trust a lack of confidence in
um allowing things to unfold trusting the practice we get in the way of
ourselves and we try to make things happen or we um don't think that it will
be enough to be present with kindness with someone we have to engineer it or
manipulate it or control in some way and ironically the very Act of trying to get
in there and make it all happen uh doesn't allow wisdom to happen
doesn't allow things to unfold in the best way so that's all Al something that
we learn over the course of practice is how to stay present and use the wisdom that's coming but not get in the way of
it through our control and manipulation of
things and then also um I think conventionality gets in the way of
wisdom our mind is conditioned by so many things from our culture our family
our education our religion these help us make distinctions between things me and you Us and Them
the way it is and the way it should be all these things um but are they always
wise distinctions between things so these conventional things lead us to
make distinctions usually that benefit our self and are based on things like seeking Comfort eliminating things we
don't like uh deciding what's right and wrong in an abstract way but the path is
asking us to make make different choices choices that are about wisdom choices that are about um suffering and
not suffering which might not always be the same as that first set of distinctions I
named so we have to go against the stream sometimes in this practice
against the conventional distinctions we've been trained to make and I think at some point we have
to admit that in order to go farther on the path and be willing to distinguish
in the way that we're invited to so specific practices that we can do
to not neglect wisdom um a wonderful one I've heard from Gil that I've used for many years
what will I sacrifice my peace for like a simple question so for example after
meditation when you get up what's the first thing that you sacrifice your
peace for and then look at what that is was it
worth it how did that end up and there's always something because we're not you know we're not fully awakened we're
going to fall out of it at some point but notice over time what are what sorts of things are we willing to sacrifice
our peace for it says a lot about our mind another useful practice to not
neglect wisdom is to bring in feeling tone more often so that's whether noticing whether things are Pleasant un
Pleasant or neither just as a noticing so so often we're in reactive mode this
is something that's unpleasant and I don't like it and I'm going to get rid of it and we're already in the mode of
how do I get rid of it how do I solve the problem how do I control it how do I fix that other person so they don't do
that that's all that's already happened uh long ago we had an unpleasant
experience and this all of this activity is about that so if we can just step back and say you know what what's
happening is that this is unpleasant at this moment really cuts out a lot of that
Bona and that wandering off that's a technical term for the discursive mind wandering off into stories and plans and
fixing things so using feeling tone is this
Pleasant is this unpleasant and then we have choices about how to react how to respond much more often out of
wisdom and then having the wise perspective of noticing change without adding a judgment of good or bad things
are changing it might even get dark in the middle of the day but just keep on
with knowing how things are um without this added reactivity of is this good
bad right wrong so when wise distinctions open up other Poss wise
distinctions are brought in other possibilities open up for us so we can become more attuned to the actual
situation and we can have actual responses that are more precise to
what's going on on the cushion um we can help the mind to settle into a more
balanced place if we're aware of wise distinctions between things so not
neglecting wisdom remembering to make distin distinctions that are helpful and
not the distinctions that are just conventional so distinction that lead
toward or away from suffering those are useful to know what's beneficial and
what's entangling what's helpful and kind and what's harmful these are the distinctions that
matter for the path so see how that goes
today to not what if I were not neglecting wisdom as often as I do and
remember that judging yourself for not negle for neglecting wisdom is not so
beneficial so we be aware of that and tomorrow we'll start exploring
what becomes possible when the mind has remembered to stay present and
balanced what opens up at that point what other things start to unfold so even if we can only for a few
minutes at a time throughout the day remember to be with wisdom that's good
enough it's significant so have a wonderful day and if you're in the path of the eclipse
please enjoy it take
care