so uh so welcome folks I hope you can hear me
um yeah great to see uh great to see the names
um I uh I'm sick and I have a pimple on my nose
nevertheless tonight we begin Wednesdays so um
perfect ah very sweet with these uh
names okay
um so uh so welcome so
I uh we'll just uh Jump Right In with a
few uh comments and then we'll uh will sit and
uh yeah so so I was was reading a uh uh
an evolutionary uh Anthropologist um I'm reading about the
the sort of Origins of of War of cooperation the possibility of
peace and uh the article the article doesn't exactly say that there are like
good forces in US cooperation and then bad forces violence it's not exactly like there're
sort of like the the two wolves in inside of us love and hate it's more like one wolf and it can
become War or peace and so the uh the the author GL
glowaki I think the name is says um the traits and the technologies that allow
people to mobilize achieve Collective action cooperate across groups and
sanction spoilers to enable peace are the same traits that are used to wage
War the better our species became at creating peace the better we also
became at Waging War goes on to say while Intergroup
coalitionary aggression and interr group
cooperation maybe evolved traits peace is an invention
yeah so um the kind of same tremendous
human intelligence and effort and Ingenuity all of that can be leveraged
For Love or hate for war or
peace and of course I'm reading this because I'm uh concerned you
know and um what what will become of us as a society species what will become of
me of each of us peace is an invention that kind
of there's cooperation and there's war you know
violence but peace that is an invention and so can we invent it can we
invent it aenta said um that we find our
freedom in the same place we find our suffering so beautiful we find our
freedom in the same place we find our suffering so it's all
right here and
uh let um that's it that's
it so finding a posture that feels uh
sustainable
e
so what's already what's already
here
we uh go [Music]
looking but uh the grace is in being
found some uh alienation when we go uh go
looking try to make something happen make something of
ourselves Grace is in being
found let your self be
found
e
don't uh go looking for the breath let the breath find
you
let the breath uh suffuse you drench
e
you don't need to go anywhere to be
found
e
in the the looking there's a maybe a sense of duality
alienation me looking for something me looking for my
breath me looking for
peace but in being
found much of that melts away
there's no ground anymore for
self-doubt
refound
e
all freedom is uh found in the same place as
our
suffering
we don't have to go looking somewhere for a
freedom we rehearse our freedom In This
Moment
embody
Freedom so we let go of looking for something
thing
e
so much forgiveness for the ways our mind
forages where is we uh
look rep peace
seek so we just come back
resting in uh it's already
here
being found by Stillness being found by
silence
letting that heal the kind of fundamental alienation always
looking
e
okay uh so um so welcome welcome
um I uh honored to uh to be with you and
um um yeah from
2017 20077 until
18 I had a you know did a group weekly or bi-weekly in LA or San
Francisco and um it's been six years but some intuitive sense of uh it's time to
uh to start start something up and so uh so here we are and um yeah very happy to
um to be with you
so teaching teaching is it's a weird it's a weird thing you know I
still I still do find it kind of strange that anyone wants to listen to me if no
one wanted to listen that would be very understandable and I know you're going
to say like no Matthew that's just the self-hate talking I get it but I don't think it's
that I actually don't think it's that um it's
because most of the time in my life I feel like a kind of big dumb happy
golden retriever not a Dharma teacher it's my
spirit animal the retriever really is that's like kind of
the Baseline self viw you know and experience of
myself but the thing is you know our mind is not not our own it uh it
constellates in you know in very particular way is based on the totality
of the conditions your mind your mind is not your own there's
continuity but then what gets drawn forth from conditions a lot a lot right
and so who we are is partially reflected by who we are when we're with
others what others pull to the surface it's not like the real self is the kind
of Retriever and this is like some performance no the Buddha emphasized friendship
spiritual friendship associating with goodness because our mind is not our
own and something happens to my mind when I'm with
Sanaa something happens to it it's not a performance something happens to
it and it it becomes very easy
to uh to know love it
becomes very easy to to sense the Dharma you know like
some uh living presence between you and I and
it's there even you know in chat I can't see a face but I I am you know just the
names that's enough that's enough and so on the one hand I don't
feel very identified um with the role of of
teacher but a big part of how I actually know myself know my heart is from taking
the seat and so um
all of that maybe is a long winded way of saying that I'm here for me you
know but while I'm here I kind of want to be useful
yeah and so uh and how we
begin as we begin I've been uh thinking about
um about pedagogy how how Learning Happens how do we
actually absorb the Dharma how does it become sort of woven into our
biology and it's something maybe pedagogy is something we Dharma teachers
have been a bit in curious about you know I sort of like inherited certain
ways certain pedagogical assumptions about how to how to transmit the Dharma
and I think there's incredible wisdom in that but it you know I wonder okay how
do we how do we actually learn how does this thing go so was reading something about um
lessons from uh lessons from cognitive science
for learning sort of what gleaning some kind of core lessons for for Learning and
um excuse me the author said uh people learn new M material better when it
creates impasses in their current mental models contradictions conflicts
anomalies uncertainties and ambiguities which stimulate
curiosity inquiry questioning problem solving and deep reasoning to restore
cognitive equilibrium impasses in the current
models we're all trying to kind of stay balanced to
keep our equilibrium and we
prefer knowing to not knowing we prefer familiarity to uncertainty or shock we
we really have routinized our mental life to a to a large degree
and um for good reason right if I'm walking and I
Stumble very very quick impulse to get back you know into balance to
reestablish balance you know before I even think you
know there's just aware whatever body propri reception it's like off balance
okay do my best to write myself and that's a very um it's a
wholesome impulse but our Dharma paath is a kind of dialectic
between equilibrium and disequilibrium a little bit like you
know what I was saying about learning learning creating impasses in the
models so if it's all upheaval if it's all disequilibrium nothing gets
integrated it's kind of chaos right just trying to get a kind of some kind of
footing right and on the other side if it's all
kind of like cruising altitude equilibrium we do we sort of get
too the models become too comfortable too familiar our Dharma understandings
become stale in a way and so the path is this kind of
dialectic between uh equilibrium and de
disequilibrium between uh kind of coziness and being thrown out of the
nest pamet troan said like to be to be truly alive is to be thrown out of the nest Moment by moment
right and so the path the Dharma path it
um it feels like home and it feels like
Exile it's so um it's so wonderful to
come home you know hopefully it feels like
that to to come home and to feel the kind of coziness
of of home you know and the Dharma is a lot like that it's this kind of sense of
like I knew this but I forgotten I'm returning I'm remembering um I'm like uh the heart is
returning to its native ground okay yeah and that is such
um that's a beautiful way and so the lots of people have talked about the path certain kind of
homecoming but we all know that spending all time maybe at home is not good we
venture out into the world to be
startled you know the startling quality when
we feel uh kind of estranged from our
prior models our prior understandings the stess of what we took to be
so and that kind of sense of of possibility and deep liveness when the
you can kind of sense it like the current model the current mental model the current frame the current Dharma
understanding starts to develop a little crack right as like part of us wants to
like patch it up right and there's some fear there you know it's like wait a
second the kind of ordinary reference points losing
them and then there's this incredible kind of openness too in that
disequilibrium and this can happen in a lot of ways when we look at the the
world when we look at the enormity just how deep the first Noble
Truth the Buddha's first Noble Truth of dukka just how deep that runs when we
look at the immensity of of goodness and Beauty the the Buddhist Grace you
know that disequilibrium can happen when we look into the eyes of another
person but don't look in that familiar
way where they lie you know a foot
behind kind of the plexiglass of all the accumulated
Concepts we have we just look at somebody maybe into the eyes maybe we
just gaze at them that kind of deep mystery of their being
onsets this disequilibrium happens when the kind of song of
self that we've been humming incessantly
stops scientist Jude Pearl said um you cannot answer a question that you cannot
ask and you cannot ask a question that you have no words
for so maybe part of what the Dharma is about
is finding finding words actually words for
new questions new questions of about
ourself our life our deaths to others new questions about um Love and
Death and what consolation is possible given the UN graspability of
all things the unpossess ability of all things what is possible what consolation
is possible what kind of piece might be
invented so I
uh I look forward to uh to our questions together and
um and uh to be uh Changed by their
articulation so a deep uh bow to you all welcome and
uh see you uh see you next week
okay