Welcome to our morning sitting and I want to begin today by
emphasizing that one of
the strong associations people have with Buddhism with the Buddhist
teaching is especially in relationship to nonattachment is the idea of letting go
let go let go let go some teachers will emphasize and what's remarkable in the
Buddhist teachings uh he never talks about letting go of anything any person any in the
world the emphasis over and over again is to let go of the grasping in the mind
the clinging in the mind grasping can be done towards things
which are healthy and beneficial for the world and grasping can be done with things that
are unhealthy and harmful to the world but grasping itself is always
harmful to the person who grasps clings attached so when the Buddha emphasized
Letting Go Letting Go letting go uh it was uh really Letting Go the
clinging and so in this week that we've been looking at grasping
clinging certainly it helps to see what we're clinging to what we're holding on
to but those are a mirror for doing the Deep inner work work of letting
go so for this meditation I'd like to encourage that it be an ongoing
meditation On Letting Go not of
anything but of the grasping to anything that arises here for this next you know almost 30
minutes that stay very relaxed in the present moment I'll guide
you and then at some point whatever it is that you
know that's happening in the present whatever you are aware of gently
lovingly release any holding to it release any preoccupation with it any
fixation any concern any lingering with it any even
interest and curiosity to it just let go let go let go and when you let
go something else will come into awareness let it come into awareness and
let go when you let go become aware of whatever is obvious that's Happening
Here and Now and know it and let go know it and let
go so to assume a meditation
posture and gently closing your
eyes the closing the eyes is a beginning process of letting go of concerns with
what is seen some people have a lot of attachment
to looking and seeing searching with her
eyes the eyes closed feeling the body and taking some long slow deep
breaths and as you exhale to relax the
body relaxing is a form of Letting Go
releasing we might be releasing muscular tension but
generally much of the tension we hold in our our
body arises from some holding in the
mind letting the breathing return to
normal
and as you exhale as you inhale feel the muscles of
your
face and as you exhale relax the muscles of your
face as you
exhale relax any concerns preoccupations about your
face except for it to
relax as you inhale feeling the
shoulders on the exhale allowing the shoulders to relax
soften
settle
e
as you inhale feeling the belly relaxing the belly on the
exhale
on the inhale feeling the whole body the global body
in whatever way that's easy
on the exhale relax release the
body and letting go of any thoughts or feelings
emotions judgments you have about your
body let go
of thinking about your body except to have it
relax and then to Center yourself on the body
breathing
as you feel the body
exhale relax and release any tension in the thinking
muscle the thinking
mind
relax let [Music] go of your
thoughts as if letting go of your thoughts the thoughts can drift away
into the space around
you
for
e
with every exhale releasing the hold of anything
you think about like let go of the need to think
about whatever you're thinking
about
as you exhale let go of any attachment for
against any emotion that you're feeling let the emotion just be there
but let go of your preoccupation with it or judgments of it
or just relax the mind the
heart
e
whatever comes into awareness whatever you know
or let go let go of
everything when it's known even let go of the
knowing so so that the next moment of knowing can arise fresh and
new and that too let go of regardless of what you're aware
of release it from the hold of the mind let
go let go let
go
for
e
can you let go of what's in the
mind can you begin to release what's in the
heart here every moment of knowing can be a
moment of non-grasping or of letting
go
e
every exhale an occasion to let go of what is
arisen let nothing stay in the
mind
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to consider how like letting go
of desires diversions in relationship to
people letting go of our judgments and fears and agendas with
people allows us to see them clearly is an act of respect where
they're allowed to [Music] be how they
are in our kind
gaze letting
go is the windshield wiper for the
heart so the heart is UN
covered and we can see people with our hearts's Good
Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
free and may they be free of all the projections and agendas
and desires that I have no judgments just
see with an open
[Music] heart
thank
you
e
so hello and welcome to this Fifth and last talk on the five bundles of
grasping the five bundles of clinging
the word for clinging in P is upana and it has an interesting meaning
double meaning it means both clinging and
fuel the food like the fuel that keeps a fire burning and
so clinging is the very fuel for more
clinging so as long as we cling it's very hard to get the the uh the
fire to stop fire of clinging but we have to somehow
stop sooner or later and appreciate the stopping appreciate the moments the
minutes the hours where the heart is not caught in the grip of
anything the mind can just move freely lightly
fluidly without stopping for anything by getting hung up by it or blocked by it
or preoccupied by anything it's a remarkable State of Mind of
heart so the last of the five bundles is usually translated into
English as Consciousness and uh the poly word is probably more
like cognition the problem with translating is
consciousness is that uh for one thing we English speakers
have very deep-seated kind of assumption about what Consciousness is and philosophers
psychologists have been trying for years to figure out what it is as if it is
something in P the word vigana um is not a continuous
state of awareness but rather is the individual moments of cognition of just as simplest
knowing more simple than recognition so the word
recognition and cognition have similar root word cognition in them just like
the word SAA in P the third bundle SAA
has the same root as Viana so they both have this word
knowing in it but the vigana the is the individual moments of
cognition so a moment of hearing a moment of seeing a moment of smelling of
tasting of touching a moment of knowing a thought an idea whatever it is there's
idea that that that the mind is in a sense con conly taking in all this
different sense data that coming in from within from without and they're made up of a lot of kind of small moments of
cognition maybe some of them are simultaneous maybe there's a lot coming in at once but each of them like you can
hear and see and smell maybe at the same time but each is unique
discreet and so um but what we tend to do is to uh lump it all together into a
gastal into a hole and the analogy of my teacher in Burma like to give was that
of um a row a row of ants from a distance seemed like a continuous stream
of black line if you get close you see they're very all these discreet
ants or they would take a fire wand and uh talk about it and if you take it in
the dark and and swirl it around fast the eyes will see a continuous circle of
flame however that's not really there it's partly a construct of the Mind in the same way as we the old movies that
were made up of you know um um you know individual still shots at 16 frames um a
second or something eight frames a second would um uh would be
reconstructed in the mind as continuous movement of the people in the movie
where there's no movement it's just individual shots still shots so um so the mind has this ability
to kind of gather things together and hold them all as a whole and thereby Miss some of the
individual things so there can be a lot of cons a lot of attachment
to the the the whole of cognition the process of cognition and there's a
tendency to take that whole to be um Consciousness a state of being aware and
it feels so real so second nature so like that of course it's there but it's
not there in any kind of way that you can take your hand and grab it it's like grabbing air you can't end up with you
know not holding any of it it just all disappears with the fist closing up and
um the uh it has no weight it has no color no shape um and um and it we might
understand it to be a a gathering together of all the different ways of perception Works into a kind of a
hole that is not really continuous but looks like that just like the
movie and um and so cognition it seems so primary to what it means to
exist even the momentto moment Co flow of cognition can seem so primary to what
it means to be alive that this last bundle is almost
the same as being attached to life itself to
existing uh there's a clinging a grasping to just exist there's also uh for some people
the idea of Consciousness or even just simple cognition would seem to be the
very Foundation of who they are nothing is more foundational more core to our
identity to Who We Are that of course we're going to cling to it this is we're going to take this as me this is
mine and um and uh and so for the Buddha
nothing is worth clinging to not any single moment of cognition not the whole
process of cognition over time the sense of continuity of a of awareness or Consciousness that can
exist nothing is worth clinging to and um but we cling to it we cling to
our ideas of what it means to be conscious we cling to the how Consciousness is the core feeling of
being alive and being a person we cling to The Refuge of Consciousness some
people can get a very beautiful feeling of kind of a wide spatial spacious
spacious Consciousness or all abiding Consciousness that um can feel so
distinct from the vagaries of Life the particularities of what's challenging our life it seems also
transcend the preoccupations of our thinking mind and our emotional heart
it's a place of peace and space and freedom and in a sense it is and it's uh
quite meaningful for people to have this wonderful sense of unpre accupedo
Consciousness that just seems to exist independent of me even for the Buddha that also could be
an object of attachment and any assumption any belief that even the
Consciousness is who I am with for the Buddha would be a form of clinging any
kind of engaging in it or involvement with it is a kind of preoccupation kind
of attachment can be very very subtle in the teachings of the Buddha
everything is a everything is an occasion to let go we also let go of
Consciousness we don't let go of being aware but we let go of any clinging to
being aware and at the deepest stages of meditation it's almost as if
Consciousness lets go of itself awareness lets go of itself there's no one doing the letting go it's just let
Letting Go Letting Go letting go and to have letting go be so thorough so
complete that uh that we find oursel without any grasping to any of the
bundles we don't grasp to appearances we don't grasp to Pleasure and Pain we
don't grasp at um our recognitions or ideas of things we don't grasp at our
stories we don't grasp even at the very sense of being of cognition itself that
which knows all these things it doesn't mean that these have to
disappear but they exist without grasping without clinging they exist
freely the ongoing flow
of knowing seeing tasting thinking and it's a it's a it's a
requires a some people would say it's a deep sense of trust the trust that we
don't have to hold on we don't have to assert we don't have to get preoccupied
and hold things and be attached we can learn to take care of
ourselves without being attached we can learn to get through this life successfully without
clinging it doesn't make us a victim it doesn't make us helpless it doesn't mean
that we can't plan and set things up for ourselves that means that whatever
planning and care and preparations we do for this life that we live we do it with
no clinging we do it we hold it lightly we hold it freely we fold it without
assertion and therefore without any exhaustion without the Deep weariness
that comes from living a life that goes from one clinging to another one attachment to the
next so these are the five bundles and at least in the teachings of the Buddha
these are emphasized over and over and over again as the
primary things that we get attached to and the primary things we create a self
out of and the Buddha's idea is you just let go let go let go and let them let these
things operate freely without getting caught by any of
it and and um and so in the Buddha's own classic tra teachings on
mindfulness the the in the satian the discourse in the four foundations of
mindfulness um this is actually one of the
um instructions to be able to see clearly
the five bundles of clinging and the way to see them the
Buddha said Is You see them arising and passing arising and passing you see them
as part of the ongoing flow the River of Life that we're
in and with that I'll leave you to the river of your life may you flow freely
in that River without icing up without grabbing onto the
embankment without drowning May you float without any clinging whatsoever
and in the Stream of your life so thank you and um very much for
this chance to teach about the five bundles and um I look forward to being
back on Monday to continue with this introduction to mindfulness uh series
thank you