good morning everyone welcome one of
the little bit continuing themes I've done the last couple of Sundays here am
I loud enough for you all yeah so uh little bit continuing the
themes from the last Sunday I want to talk more about the body our bodies mindfulness of the
bodies uh it's surprising to me how much uh in these 2500 years ago the Buddha
emphasized the tremendous value of being present being attentive to your own
body and there's a lot of uh uh a lot we can discover in our body uh there's a a
tremendous support that the our bodies give to being present and attentive to our lives and to
ourselves and um and one of the things that's interesting is that for in these
ancient teachings the word that's most commonly used for body is Kaa Ka a y a
and it kind of has some of the same range of meanings as the English word body in that it doesn't just refer to a
physical body but also refers to an assembly of things uh we might talk about a body of
work of an author who's written a lot we might talk about a student body
students of a school and a body of water which you know so there's a it's a range
of things that have collected together and held together and with implying that
this body of ours is an assemblage of assembly or assemblage of all kinds of
different things that come together and what's get more interesting
in this ancient teaching is that there's an understanding that the way we experience the body is
variable and it's almost as if we have different bodies at different times so
there are some people who uh can talk about the pain
body whole relationship to our body and how the body can feel can be very dramatic when there's a lot of pain
there's the the fear body and when there's fear and anxiety the physiology
of fear and this not just psychology of it but physiology of It kind of shifts
and changes how our body feels and the experience of body is very different
maybe that's what part of the purpose of fear is to get our get us connected to the body in a way that we can fight uh
you know we can it activates us to do something about it protect ourselves or fight or hide or do something so the
body get you know wants to be engaged and um there's the angry body I
don't know if ever any of you have been super duper anger angry at something and you know the whole body is kind of on
fire and tense or something and um there's also things
called like the Bliss body that uh sometimes in meditation is
felt kind of very clearly that the whole experience of being in a body is just
saturated with a feeling of Happiness of Joy or Bliss just like
pervasive some of these bodies we can experience assemblage of the psychological and physiological
processes and as they interact um makes the body feel really tight and there's a lot of focus on particular areas of the
body and and kind of a narrowing and a tightening of the focus perhaps and
others uh the the focus on the body gets much more suus of and Broad and and uh
there's a feeling of almost um no particular sharp boundaries even of the body the body feels very kind of a
porous in a certain way and in some schools of Buddhism they
talk about the Dharma body uh that uh people experience in meditation that something about
meditation starts shifting and changing our relationship to our body and even beginning meditators can feel that
usually a little bit um if the if they're chronically tense and they sit down to meditate and the shoulders drop
drop a millimeter or two oh look the experience of the body has changed and
um it maybe some kind of tension that we car for a long time the for a while and meditation disappears
entirely it certainly did for me uh when I after some years of meditation I held
my belly chronically tight I held it in and when I sat down to meditate that's
when I discovered that and so I would relax it and that was very successful for about a second
and then uh it would tighten up and so I didn't worry about it too much I just would relax it a few times in the
sitting and then I didn't make it a project and so in that and but then after I don't know how many years three
four years of regular meditation I noticed one day oh it is not tightening up anymore now it's just staying relaxed
the whole time and and that affected my experience of breathing and the breathing body how breathing felt
through my body shifted and changed because it wasn't being restricted anymore by the tight tight
belly um the um for many years I teach a a chaplaincy
training program and for many years uh we would take the students to an anatomy
lab at at a community college and we had this wonderful uh
Professor there who was she was like so in we were all inspired the part of the
reason to go there was just to meet her and um and she would do this very
respectful uh introduction to us to the various peoples whose bodies were there
that uh we would then study and uh various stages of dis
dissection and uh for chaplains it was partly the reason to do it was that
chaplains uh will often go into situations where there's a you know
dramatic things have happened to people's bodies they've been injured or hurt or their die or dying and in the
hospitals and so chaplain need to have some familiarity with that world uh chaplain me to need to have familiarity
with death and dying they need to have some degree of familiarity that gives them a degree of comfort with it not
Comfort but ease or certainly not tense and reactive and
um and this surprising you know and also part of chapy training is to discover
where people are going to be reactive before they go to offer spiritual care
to someone so it doesn't work if you're there giving spiritual care for someone and you
faint or if you you know start crying yourself and you're more more grieving
more than the the griever that you're supposed to help so you have to kind of really see yourself know yourself well
and have been able to process and gotten wise about your own way of your own you
know inner life I remember one of the toughest people made all the
presentations of being a really tough guy meet sweetheart of a man but just
tough kind of like he had this he grew up as an in inner city guy
and with violence and kind of a little bit of gangs and just like carried himself with a dialect that was tough
and you know got your attention kind of when he spoke doing chaplain SC and um
so he was the one who fainted in the an an anatomy
lab so uh so we will go to thead lab and and uh and uh we would see these this
for these are for the students there who are going to become nurses or doctors and they they learn how to dissect the
body and so there was all these bodies usually there were two or three of them there at any one time and they would
open them up and some of them were quite open you you just and um and every time
I went there and we open we looked into an a a torso that had been opened up so
you can see all the organs inside uh I was always surprised there's
no space in there it's like packed in there with kidneys and intestines and hearts and
all this stuff like wow like it's and um and the reason I'm surprised is that
when I sit and meditate I have a lot of space inside I mean it's like really spacious
in there and what's going on you know do I just have physiologically different am
I kind of like strange you know maybe I have teeny teeny little intestines
and you know so there's lot of space you know probably has something to
do with how many nerves you have and maybe you know the nerves that are there
for you know the intestines and kidneys and all that are very different than the
nerves elsewhere so I don't have a strong inner proprioception of the body inside and so
when I didn't close my eyes I I'm not really aware of the all that stuff
that's packed in there so it's but what happens as I sit and meditate uh it
becomes more and more spacious in there and more and more relaxed and open and
um and so uh sometimes it feels like like my the inside of my body feels you know
bigger than this room just like wow just like so much
space why that is I don't you know it's it's I know it's not literally true I
mean it's kind of to take that as literal truth is kind of silly but it does speak maybe to uh a very powerful
sense that we have very significant uh sense St we have which not part of the
usual five senses but that is our spatial awareness spatial awareness is
partly constructed and we close our eyes and you can imagine a size of a room you can
imag some people can imagine uh even the route through a city they can kind of get a sense of the space and the
distance and all those things and so uh when when there's in meditation when
there's the sense of um Concepts and ideas and preoccupations that the Mind
focuses on are no no longer focusing on things that way and the mind doesn't
have this kind of these all these object of concern that they're preoccupied with
then awareness kind of begins maybe sometimes takes kind of as an object
some kind of spatial awareness and since there's no objects in that spatial
awareness space becomes bigger and bigger and it can feel really really
peaceful and Broad to have the spatial awareness and um and it's kind of
wondrous sometimes and it provides a very different reference point for what
goes on in us in our mind psychologically it's because it becomes it's you can only start feeling that
really in acute way if we're not totally preoccupied with whatever we're PR
preoccupied with um uh maybe all of you have finished
your taxes that's why so so people who are not here today you know they're
still preoccupied at home and but you guys have maybe or maybe I shouldn't
have said anything now you will be preoccupied and won't listen
anymore and uh the um and so we have these preoccupations again very
intense and you know we some we discover that when we sit down to meditate it's one of the values of meditation to
discover what we're preoccupied with and what the mind is concerned with and sometimes if you relax a little bit the
surface kind of agitation of the mind then you discover these deeper preoccupations concerns the mind is all
about that needs to be resolved it needs to we think it needs to be resolved and so we're kind of we start discovering so
much more about ourselves when we start getting quieter and to have this kind of spacious feeling of being present here
um that's it's kind of like having a very quiet still body of water and then
you have a little uh fish or turtle or something that that comes and it's fin
or something kind of at kind of comes up out of the surface and mix a Rings he oh
there's life in there otherwise you didn't see it oh there's something in there so the mind gets quiet and then
something comes up oh look look at that that um you wouldn't have seen if the
mind was completely full of waves and uh but but so you see something different as you kind of see what's under the
surface sometimes so this is a long introduction to read to read you a
poem the the um it's the English translator trans gave it the title of a
ballad I'm not going to try to sing it but it's uh it's written by um or
composed by aanm and this aan means teacher in Thai and it's um moon is uh was an extremely
important teacher in the in the 20 Century I think he died in the late
1940s and uh some people attributed him to the as the Rev reev re not reviler
revor of um of a certain kind of uh strong powerful meditation tradition in
Thailand and revivor of understanding experientially how far this path of
Awakening can go that he was somehow fully awakened as a as a individual and he was a forest Monk
and so he at some point in in his adult life he disappeared into the forest and spent decades living in the forest very
poor in very poor circumstance but living as a monastic doing lots of practice I think he felt that uh the
existence existing scholarly focus of Thai Buddhism variety of things uh there
wasn't anybody who could teach him how to meditate in some deep way and um so he went off and spent years decades
meditating and then um he started attracting students and uh and they he
transformed their students kind of opened the door for them to go deep into practice and and um and one of his
students was aan Sha aan Sha is the teacher for Jack cornfield for aano aan
soito very the whole school of um of uh monks and late people studied with him
and came back to the west and and in some ways IMC is partly a continuation
of of that momentum created by this this man aanm the story of aan CHA was that
uh he had been a monk for many years and he and he heard about this man and uh so
he went looking for him and it took he had
to walk for a few months uh I think up into Northern Thailand
into the forest looking for him and it wasn't just got Uber and just took took you take me to aan Moon back then it was
like you had to be pretty determined that you know there was no you know to
find someone like that you had to be pretty determined and ask around and keep walking and and then when he
finally found him he spent three days with him and those three days trans transformed him and gave him a clear
sense of how to continue his practice and and uh then then uh so a there was no
you know living in the forest there was almost no records of him and he didn't write apparently much or all or very
little and so so mostly we have stories about him but he there was this one thing called The Ballad of Liberation
from the kandas from the and um B Ballad of
Liberation and um maybe you'll understand when I get to this one part of it in the middle why I gave the
introduction I gave and also the the uh I think there's
some idiosyncratic maybe tie ways in which it was written so the pronouns are
not so clear to who's being talked about I've tried to inter I interpret it one
way that um and it's uh the first half of it is either about himself or it's
about the Buddha and the second half is um it's not so clear who's being
addressed and who's doing the speaking but so i' so I just adjusted a little bit to make one interpretation and for
this purposes here that part of it is not that important once there was a
Man Who Loved himself and feared
distress he wanted happiness beyond the reach of danger so he wandered
endlessly wherever people said that happiness was found he longed to
go but wandering took a long long time he was the sort of Man Who Loved
himself and really dreaded death he truly wanted release from aging
and mortality then one day he came to know
the truth abandoning the cause of
suffering he found a Cave of Wonders of endless
happiness the body as he gazed throughout the Cave of
Wonders his suffering was destroyed his fears appeased he gazed and gazed around
the mountain side experiencing unbounded peace but then there were others afraid
of death their hearts all withered and discouraged they came to me and spoke
frankly in a pitiful way they said you've made an effort at your meditation
for a long time now have you seen it yet the true Dharma Dharma of your
dreams they asked to stay with me so I agreed and I said to them I'll take you
to to a massive mountain with a Cave of Wonders free from suffering and stress
mindfulness immersed in the body you can view it at your leisure to
cool your heart and end your troubles this is the path of the noble
lineage it's up to you to go or not so the Cave of Wonders isn't that I
thought that was a delightful expression of your body is your body a Cave of
Wonders or is just a cave it's not even a cave it's just like a you know it just
packed full of intestines and spleens and pancreas
and the um Cave of Wonders the
um some people have such complicated relationships with their body some people hate their bodies are ashamed of
bodies and these are all ways of kind of relating to the body as an object which
in a certain kind of way is from the outside in even though it's you know in inside your mind but it's kind of as
objectifying the body and what's being talked about here is uh a very deep
subjective experience of the body which is freed from the
objectifications from the judgments from the comparisons we have compar comping
our our body with others or with ideals how it should be and so that's one of the things that happens in meditation
that can happen not only do we see clearly what we're doing in our mind but the Mind quiets down becomes quieter and
quieter and after a while uh the way we get tricked into believing our thoughts
or tricked into being hijacked by our thoughts and our ideas and our judgments
and like have to keep thinking this lessons and it's not an easy switch to
make be uh in daily life because I mean still I've been doing this for so long
meditation uh I still am tricked by my mind I'm just going along and thinking
my thoughts and you know thinking mostly he's innocent enough but thinking about all the activities of the day and what I
have to do and um and uh I take it for granted I think I take this idea that's
business as usual that's how it is I mean it's like like you know it's
like this you know I don't question it I just kind of oh this is this is how things are and just I have to kind of go
along with how it is and then I sit down to meditate and I realize no I don't
have to do that uh it's not business as usual that was a particular way of being caught up in thoughts and activities and
that there's a whole other way of being that those get quiet and that not so caught in them some people have never learned that
and so they think think that chasing their thoughts being chased by their thoughts spinning around thinking over
and over again and concerned and worrying um is the way to be and that's
has to be that way it's kind of the truth of how things are and um and some
of those ways self-perpetuating you have a thought and that's uncomfortable and
that triggers another thought and another thought the same thought over again and over again and it just kind of
you know just seems we and we're blind Ed by the blinded by our thoughts by the thoughts blinded from our thoughts by
the fact that we're thinking so much so then to quiet to allow to
not you know live in the hegemony of thinking to let the quiet become
peaceful and then the Cave of Wonders I read this poem last week
and I sat down one day and I yeah that's Cave of Wonders in there it's pretty
cool the next day I sat down
nope and the next day it felt like oh the door's
closed and okay so I just have to sit at sit at the door and what the door was I I think I was I was caught in certain
things and somehow i' been living a day was kind of full of activities and so I
was kind of uh a little bit kind of tense little bit caught up a little bit
not quite in my you know settled and and so that the door wasn't
the cave wasn't opening and so I sat and just breathed and was present at the
door meaning meaning I stood where the tension was where the resistance was where I was kind of held tight and okay
that's the name of the game today so I was quite content to just do that way I don't have problem with that and so I
just sat there and sat there and by the door and and then after a while the door
opened and then then I was invited in invited into the Cave of Wonders and
this Spa this this spacious open place
where the eyes that see see
differently the eyes of the mind that can see you know that sees what's happening within us
and even our physical eyes how we see the world uh depends a lot on the filters
through which we see and if we're seeing through aversion then a lot of things in the
world are wrong if we see through the uh through the lens of Desire of our desires then
we a lot of things in our world are desirable and we have a clear sense of and disinterest in what is undesirable
kind of like we're dividing the world up what satisfies my desires and what doesn't and um if we see the world
through fear we might see a lot of danger if we see the world through
confidence maybe we don't see as much danger in the world and so same thing if
you look within if we live in the world of fear what we feel inside can be a source of
danger and um and uh you know can we can see Danger
things in there if we see with aversion the same thing if we see with desire if we see
with conceit uh this conceit is such a complicated world that that uh when we
see through the world of conceit we might get depressed we might see oh this is everything's bad about me or it could
be that we get kind of hyped up and like everything's good about me and people better start praising me because you
know I'm like the hottest Cave of wonder in town
and so the U and so we see through these filters
and um what happens when you don't have the filters what happens if we kind of see
without conceit without fear without aversion without desires things get
simpler and that's when uh I think we start seeing um some of the Wonder
Wonders that exist within us we do have the capacity for love we do have the
capacity for peace we do have the capacity for calm and equinity we do
have the capacity for kindness we do have the capacity for wisdom we have
these amazing capacities that seem to thrive when the rest of us is not
preoccupied where rest of us is not limiting ourselves through a particular
um unfortunate lenses perspectives that we live in all the time and how do you
know what is an unfortunate lens and some of you say well fear is a necessary and important
thing how do we know one way we know is not by having an opinion about it or a
policy about what's right and wrong to way to be but we start getting quiet
enough to see for ourselves to experience for ourselves um this activity that's going on is
extra this activity is not really useful to be doing let's quiet down so to use
fear for example um I've had anxiety in my life
that as as I got clearer the mindfulness you can see I could see this is not the
anxiety which has any real reality it's it's kind of built on all kinds of kind
of quick sand of strange ideas and this one I can just settle settle out it's
okay to quiet down and I've had other fears where I thought oh this is reasonable to be afraid here and uh and
so then uh it becomes my friend and I have a friendly relationship to that to
that fear I think it's keeping me safe in certain situations sometimes I have a
little bit of fear when I'm driving sometimes a lot when there's you know depending on other
drivers but uh a little bit of fear when driving and um and um and I just take it
as my friend it's trying to keep me safe and I think that as I'm getting older now I think I'm having a little bit more
fear as I drive and I I come to the it's kind of like why is that I'm a little more attentive and
hped up and I why am I more afraid and I suspect maybe this is pop psychology but
I suspect that it's because as I get older my reaction time is slower and so it's actually a while
thing to have a little bit more fear as I get older my system knows something here knows what's going on more than I
do and so always makes sense to have a little bit of fear so it's my friend that's taking care of
me so there's a way in which we become wiser about all these things maybe it's
it's wise sometimes to have aversion but it's never wise to have hostility and so you can feel sometimes
the difference of uh turning away and saying no not to something versus being hostile
and so as we we as we live in this Cave of Wonder as a degree of Peace of calm
of openness of spaciousness um it provides a very different reference point a very powerful reference point
where we can see these details of what's driving us in the operating systems to see it in a fresh way in a new way but
the cost of doing that is to temporarily stop
investing so much value and importance and and
urgency around the thoughts you the thinking that's objectifying you objectifying the
world just spinning and world creating worlds cathedrals of edifices of
constructed thought we have to somehow be able to calm that down enough and one
and to calm it down enough we have to know that we're part of us is no longer addicted
to the thought part of us knows this is not as important as it thinks it
is that doesn't mean it's going to stop or slow down but as long as you are believe in thinking and you're investing
in your thoughts and going along with them and think they're really telling you the important stories and important
things um they are sometimes I don't want to dismiss the value but this o overinvestment in thinking has to stop
if we want to kind of see what's going on more
clearly and um so
um I this the one story occurs to me
was um many years ago now 30 years ago or
something I thought it'd be nice to watch football on TV and
you know I had friends who watched football and loved it and the 49ers were doing better
then I guess they're doing okay now but uh but so I was um um and I
found myself pulled into the world of the football game and I thought I enjoyed it but when it was over I just
felt miserable I felt I felt uh agitated I felt tight I had a little bit of a
headache I gotten too invested too in involved in the game somehow other
people can watch it and not have that investment and maybe enjoy it more than I did but uh but what struck me was that
um I didn't know I wasn't attentive to myself to to see the cost of how I was
watching while I was watching it was only when it was over that I saw the cost I saw that I think I did it a
little bit wrong here it must be another way to do this and um so that's so this this uh we
often don't understand the cost of how we're living Our Lives running our lives thinking at all
this and now so this disinvestment enough so that we can
start calming down and relaxing and centering ourselves in our body centering ourselves in the body's
experience of our life centering ourselves so the body has a chance to have space to relax one of
the ways I think of meditation is we're giving um space mindfulness is what
gives space to our experience so whatever we're mindful of it's almost like we're making a room for it to be
there freely so if we feel pain we're making room for the pain to be there if we have tension we're making room for
the tension to be there if we have calm we make room for the calm to be there
we're making room for things and the things which are there because of of
clinging and attachment and and kind of being wrapped up around things when there's more room for them they
tend to unwind the things that are are there because it's
the emergence of wisdom emergence of some of the deeper Wellsprings of goodness that
we have when they have space they spread and so there's a spreading of
goodness spreading of the wholesome qualities and the suffusion and one of the values of
making space and room for things is that uh is to say it in
shth hand it tends to unwind the tensions and spread the
joys kind of suffusing us through through the body
so the Cave of Wonders so this man a janmon went traveling all over Thailand
to visit other teachers and to practice and to find an answer of how to be happy
and in the end he found it at himself he found it in his own Cave of Wonders and
that's what he taught to find you each have a Cave of Wonders within and uh
wouldn't it be nice to be able to visit that a place
where there he as he writes there's Un unbounded Peace and I love it that he
talks about that that he looked around he he gazed and gazed around the
mountain side experiencing unbounded peace all the Time in the World to gaze
around this Cave of Wonders and see the peace that's there so those are my thoughts today and
um we have a few minutes before we usually end so if anyone has any
questions or comments or testimonials about the their Cave of
Wonder thanks hi my name is jeie and uh I would
just like to I don't know argue might not be the right word but to um say that
I don't think it's fear that's making you drive differently
I I think it's caution perhaps but and wisdom because I mean I too know that I
don't have the capacities that I had 30 years ago or 20 years ago and so I'm more cautious but I don't
feel fear great great well I I appreciate that a lot what you said and uh it depends these what's so
fascinating is how we different people have different reference points for these words and you know the words the
words don't have the kind of clearly defined meaning that we think they do
right and they're just sounds we make and so so for you that that's an
important distinction for me I think of caution as a subcategory of fear so but
you know I'm not going to say I'm right and or you're right it just but I I very much appreciate the distinction because
I think your distinction might help some people to um to see clear more clearly what's happening inside of them
William
yeah hi Gil um could you speak more about vamba Kaya can you hold it like us
yeah could you speak more about vamb Gaya but bliss body this the uh Sakaya
yeah so in it's not in our tradition but in the Mahayana tradition they have this idea of usually
it's the three bodies of Buddha the three kayas of the Buddha and the nman Kaya
Buddha sodar Kaya Buddha and the Dharma Kaya Buddha and um and if we apply it
kind of to to how it is in our tradition these three
categories the first it kind of uh by calling it a Buddha it kind of
makes it sacred kind of special and wonderful that we can be have a Buddha
body and um n monakaya is uh just kind of the body that we ordinarily have and
for many of us we sometimes call it a karmic body a karmic body is that body
we experience that's the product of a lifetime of karmic activities choices
we've made attachments we've had reaction re activities we've had uh
policies we've had um I I don't know I was I remember there was I was told that
it was read somewhere it was Abraham Lincoln who wrote that by the time a person's 50 or 60 they're responsible
for their face because of uh how they lived their
lives you know with their attitudes and their smiles and frowns and you know how
they consistently are attitudes they have it affects you know we all these little micr muscles that we have and and
um you know affects us and but that's true think with languages we speak different people speak different
languages consistently have slightly different physiology in the face because of what microm muscles are used for
those speaking those languages and um the um so uh so the the ordinary
first is the ordinary experience and then uh uh in meditation then at some
point as meditations deepens uh there's experience of of a bliss body Joy bodies
which is the the body of of uh enjoyment that we really en enjoy being in the
body just filled with enjoyment and and it's quite sometimes qu especially if
you get concentrated quite remarkable to feel that it's like every cell is
dripping with happiness or Joy or fusing spreading through the
body and um and uh but that's not the end point that's just a part of the
process of the path of letting go to experience that and then the dharmakaya
the Dharma body is the body of Freedom so when we've really let go of any
clinging and attachment and so that there's no more any um being closed being resistant being
preoccupied being um caught up in things there's a very different experience
that's not Blissful exactly not the conventional kind of Joy but there's this wonderful F thing of just feeling
this tremendous ease or peace of being free and um and that would be the
dharmakaya thank you you can my the mic down
there thanks for the talk you um I wonder if you can share a little bit
wisdom on how to distinguish uh useful aversion from
hostility and uh um like what kind of aversion still can be accompanied by
peace feeling of peace and ease yeah the reason I ask is it kind of remind
me um one of those difficult dis
distinguishing I have been um try to to feel more is sometimes when I make
certain effort whether that's wholen like helpful prevention or
maintainance of wholen condition or I'm just running away or attacking the
circumstance that I'm involved yeah thank you your asking is a very important question and I think each
person some ways has to discover that for themselves but you know I can give some broad broad
category broad ideas for for you to explore um the English word
aversion uh mean it kind of means uh to avert avert means in Latin to turn away
so there are times when it's really appropriate to turn away from something if you put your hand on the hot stove
it's appropriate to have a ver you know don't to have a version don't sit there and ask a question is that hostility or
ver verion you know only move your hand when you've decided um but the the um you know the
avert from danger for example is a healthy thing to do to invert from
something which is uh unhealthy for us or that's not you know not appropriate for us to do is healthy thing to do to
to have aversion for a certain kind of aversion where we want to avert we say no and we pull back I don't want to do
that uh doing uh une ethical things that harm people this is a health it's actually a healthy movement to
have the um but we use the uh we use
Buddhist English we tend to use the word aversion to involve uh not just simply a
healthy averting but we tend to use it to to be a mixture of hostility and
averting there's a kind of judgment and like this is wrong that's bad that's terrible or it's a kind of a it tends to
have a kind of a very negative uh uh kind of painful
like having having uh darts in her eyes like you're terrible and so we are kind
of hurting people we we uh where there's a hostility a little bit built into it
and hostility means that we're trying to we want to hurt someone uh we want we want to destroy
them or throw them away or get them away or you know you know jab them and with
verbal daggers you know be say mean things just to kind of get them and so the one way to look
at is and and so a similar question the question you asked is the distinction between anger and
hostility does is all anger have hostility in it or is there anger which is there's no hostility you don't want
anybody you don't want anybody to be hurt um but you want to some things have to stop and so with certain ferocity we
say no but we do it with we might even have love for the person or we care for the
person and and but we we're not trying to you know get at them and but too
often anger is a kind of hostility and so again it's it's where we want to cause harm for someone else in some way
or other that does that help you think to your investigation
yes I love uh the analogy is like you said uh thoughts in your eyes and uh
Theo like verbal thank you so much thank
you okay well thank you for being here and uh it is the usual time for stopping
and you know is really nice when people you say hello to each other at least for for me they hear you talking and saying
hello so if you're at all inclined to say hello to a couple of people next to you and say hello little bit and and uh
say tell say something about this Cave of Wonders was that an interesting idea for you or was this like you know you'd
rather go to Disneyland