good morning from Redwood City and welcome to this meditation
session meditation is often associated with calm
tranquility and in the ancient instructions the Buddha gave for meditation he emphasized this and he EMP
ized it by uh saying that it's uh okay or encourage people to instructed people
to calm uh the body whatever ways the body
is agitated let it be calm
it bring a gentling force to the body so that it
can settle he emphasized calming the mind the agitated
mind again bringing to the mind the kind of reassurance that kind of
settling that calms the mind we can apply his teachings
instructions to one more area of calming and that is to calm how we
know mindfulness is a lot to do with knowing recog recognizing what's
happening as it's happening so in the present moment and
it also has to do with feeling or sensing what is happening as it's
happening and the Art of mindfulness is to somehow move
between knowing and sensing and
um and some people would prefer one over the other as a calming
force and sometimes it's invaluable to go back and forth and to have for a
while one for a while the other and um but either way we can what
we can try to practice is to know
calmly to sense our experience calmly and that helps when we're body is
agitated the mind is agitated I and there doesn't seem to be much room to change
that but we can step back metaphorically to observe to
know in a calm way and for people who use Mental noting uh this can really
help us find the calm way of knowing so if you breathing in to say
in but to find a way in the mind as
you have the thought in to do it in a calm way maybe even a calming
way and now when you are breathing out say the word
out or some people count the breath and to count in a calm way and a calming
way and um if we are agitated no we're
agitated but to know it in a calm way and if it's a more useful and more subtl
to sense and feel the agitation in the body or in the mind to sense it
calmly and um in the way that maybe you would um
calmly p a cat or calmly if you're a woodworker feel the
surface of wood to feel smooth it is or how rough it Still
Remains so to know calmly to sense
calmly and if you can to allow yourself to calm relax the
body so to assume a meditation posture and
to adjust the posture sure in a way that you think will allow the greatest
settling and for some of us it might seem paradoxical that the greatest settling
happens when the body is placed upright and um of course that's not
possible always but um there's a way in which the shoulders
can soften and relax if they're
hanging from the from you know from the
Torso and the pull of gravity supports their
relaxing gently closing the eyes and gently maybe in a gentling way
calming way take some deeper
longer inhales and
exhales on the inhale feeling the
body on the exhale relaxing the
body maybe a exhaling an extra second or two so there's a little bit more
opportunity to let go in the
body and then letting the breathing return to
normal and with a whatever seems like an ordinary breath
close
enough on the exhales continue to relax the
body or
soften sometimes it's nice to take the inhale as a time to feel some part of
the body and the exhale to relax
it so breathing in and feeling the
face breathing out softening the face
breathing in and feeling the shoulders breathing out relaxing the
shoulders noticing if a small shift in how the arms
are positioned can let the shoulders relax a little bit more
on the inhale to feel the area of your chest the heart
area and then to relax on the exhale
on the inhale feeling the belly and softening the belly as you
exhale
on the inhale feeling a broad awareness of your
body and on the exhale calming the whole body
and on the inhale feeling your mind your thinking
mind feeling whatever way it's activated
energized whatever way it
is agitated or not
and on the exhale calming the
mind maybe with the image of letting the
Mind spread out and settle down like the surface of a
lake that has waves Wes that
settle and then calmly settling yourself on the
experience of breathing in your body
body centering yourself on the rhythm of breathing in
and breathing
out and as you breathe in clearly know you're breathing
in and clearly know as you're breathing
out or allow yourself to
ride the inhales and exhales as you feel or
sense the rhythm of breathing in and
out and experiment with knowing breathing
calmly sensing and feeling breathing calmly
even if the body is agitated even if the breathing is
agitated or
no that calmly know calmly know
agitation calmly know anything that excites the mind
know it as it is but calmly as if you have all the time in the
world
for
e
e for
whatever is happening for you in the Mind Body your
heart know it calmly recognize be present in a tranquil way
even if everything else is not tranquil experiment with tranquil
knowing tranquil
sensing as if you're your own good friend who's with you in a calm
way when you most need a calm friend
for
e
e e
[Music]
for
e
e for
as we come to the end of this
sitting to feel recognize any way that you're calmer
now than you were at the
beginning where in your body might you be feeling
sensations of calm or
Tranquility open to those feelings soften with those
feelings in what way is your mind calmer
if it's easy allow the calmness of mind to spread through the
mind and on the foundation of some
calmness can your mindfulness become cm
even if your mindfulness of that which is not calm can you know what is not
calm
calmly so knowing is not pulled into agitation or excitement
tension as if you're looking across a landscape in a calm
way spend the last moments here gazing upon your your body your
mind as if it's the landscape that you calmly you're calmly
surveying and then to turn that calm awareness calm
gaze out into the world
maybe considering the people and activities
you'll be doing
today and gazing upon it
calmly without a hurry without
preoccupation a simple knowing
and gazing upon the people of your life with calm
awareness wish them well gaze upon them
calmly and
kindly may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of our contribution to this
possibility begin in being calmly present for
others especially when they're
troubled may all beings find peace
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello everyone and welcome to this second talk on the hindrances where the focus is uh
to understand understand how the hindrances are UNH wholesome and how to bring in the
wholesome that the hindrances hinder our wisdom for how to act in this world how
to be in this world and but when we understand the difference between UNH wholesome ways of
being and wholesome then it's easier to choose the Wholesome Way the healthy way
the wise way and in the modern world it might be
shorthand to say this that's more accessible for many people is to see the difference between a stressful way of
responding to a calm way of responding and uh no matter how
difficult the situation is uh it can make it more difficult if we get agitated if we get more and more
stressed in the situation and um and we might have more wisdom
more wiser wiser ways of responding uh better able to understand
the situation if we can stay calm if we can somehow not allow the stress to take
over um and so um one of the so today
the hindrance to look at this uh going backwards through the list is uh uh
agitation and regrets agitation and uh
remorse I like the word remorse because uh in Latin it uh literally means um
kind of to chew again to you're chewing something over and over again in an agitated stressful
way it's possible that uh it's helpful to understand this agitation as a
stressful stressful excitation and uh it can come from
anything that's UNH wholesome um there's a way in which greed uh can be um especially frustrated
greed or certain kind of excitement or ground greed can really agitate the system and in that agitation that
excitement uh we kind of lose ourselves and um anger hostility can be
um also excited and and uh if it's frustrated if ation if aversion comes
from a lot of frustration frustration makes kind of build can build up the tension in the body the agitation in the
body or pursuing uh uh or kind of engaging and fueling uh feeding anger
and hostility can come with a lot of agitation in the body and this agitation we're looking at
here uh it's possible to feel to recognize that it doesn't feel healthy
to have it that uh it uh puts on a lot of stress it
we kind of lose ourselves in it it's kind of like takes over and there's a kind of a maybe I don't know if it's a
surrender to it but it has such a kind of a uh convincing force that we almost
believe that whatever we're agitated about that you know we get involved in
agitation and um and we can so we can be agitated by
many things things that bother us many things that we want different we can
also be agitated by uh uh our regrets
our remorse for what we have done in the past and uh ideally uh the regrets are
genu involve things we genuinely we deserve to have some kind of um regret
for but to spend our time chewing over it oh ruminating over and over and over again uh about the things we done in the
past um is debilitating and keep the mind kind of on a Surface
agitation uh in the Buddhist approach to uh having done something
which causes harm or something which has some kind of fault to it um is uh not to
be stuck in a backward-looking mind reviewing the past over and over again
but to uh look at the past just enough to learn how to do better and then to be
forward-looking even inspired to try to to live now uh Having learned from that
and let's do better in the future so we don't want to ignore what we've done that we need to learn from but we also
don't want to be weighed down by it uh the idea in Buddhism is to always look
how can I respond uh how can I live in an onward
leading way to A Life That's calm that's peaceful ful that's liberating that's um
loving even and um and so to be inspired by that possibility of an onward looking
way to go and agitation doesn't do that agitation is stuck in an UNH wholesome
um the kind of agitation we're talking about here as a hindrance covers over
wisdom covers over our ability to see what is actually a healthy Wholesome Way
of engaging in an issue a problem uh taking care of something and um and so
it's very important to uh see and feel the limitations that come with being
agitated limitations that um come with ruminating over and over over again with
regrets and remorse that we might have and part of a wise life in Buddhism
is actually to recognize how C the the what the Buddhism calls the dangers but the limitations the
downside of uh of things which are unhealthy for us and the reference point
for that unhealthy is somatic is really to feel in our body that something is
off something is grading something feels um uh deflating something feels uh makes
us feel tense and or empty or AF afraid
or uh kind of uneasy in some way and uh
and knowing that that is not really how we want to live what can we do to bring
in what's wholesome healthy that has a sense of ease to it and can we
understand the value of doing that can we understand the the downside of the
UNH wholesome and the upside of the wholesome and then choose the wholesome
and the simplest wholesome thing for a mindfulness practitioner is to be mindful uh to be mindful calmly and
clearly so that the mindfulness is not uh entangled caught up in aversion greed
and conceit uh another thing that's wholesome to do when there's a lot of
agitation uh the body stressed out in some way the Mind stressed is to
calm um uh the the Buddha put a lot of emphasis
when he taught mindfulness to begin mindfulness by calming the body in mind
um the uh to um relax and it's interesting the Buddha
called um the food for calm the what feeds calm is calm itself so whatever
degree of calm that we experience uh let that register don't uh
because maybe it's not so exciting calm uh the mind orients us to what's exciting or Orient towards what's big
and kind of doesn't understand the value of calm that that's really a good place to be and so to recognize when we're
settled Rec recognize when there's a Tranquility or a peace and that recognition supports it to continue so
we don't lose track with it track of it don't forget wholesomeness don't forget
uh don't lose track of it maintain it don't sacrifice it too easily because we
see something that excites us and in the excitement we become agitated we become
caught and we're no longer really present for ourselves so um
so if we live our life and that's the theme for this week uh attentive and and
uh knowledgeable and and uh uh to be able to feel and
sense when what's going on feels unhealthy when what goes on feels
healthy physically mentally spiritually that's the guide for
ourselves and um and this is the way that I've been talking about lately that
you become a self whisper that you want to really um be ATT tuned have a report
with yourself have a sensitivity to yourself that you can read yourself well you know yourself well you you can
approach yourself uh in a way that uh the inner life feels safe feels calm
feel held feels respected if we're caught in agitation
caught with regrets from all kinds caught with resentments of any kind that
um and the way that we are aware of ourselves the way that we know ourselves
is through the filter of the agitated stress the agitated excitement if it's
through the filter of regrets and maybe even criticisms of ourselves that then
the inner life just feels more of the same it feeds the wholesome feeds the
wholesome the UNH wholesome feeds the UNH wholesome and so we don't want to keep
doing it that way and it can be a phenomenal exercise phenomenally
freeing to at least kind of take a deep breath and
know how you are in a calm way almost as if you're saying to yourself
oh I'm quite agitated right now to take that long to say it you know two seconds
or whatever um can change the whole dynamic it's like stepping out of the
feeding mechanism that keeps feeding and fueling
agitation and then to feel to recognize that that calm way of knowing is
wholesome and to begin finding ways to support the growth of a healthy
positive uh supportive way of being in this world by being able to read and
feel and sense um deeply uh what's happening in here in
for ourselves what the need is um how to approach in a way that's supportive and
helps create safety and kindness and to learn for mindfulness to be that approach to mindfulness be the
sensitivity the care the Rapport that helps the inner life settle helps the
inner life feel safe and cared for and respected and generally when there's a lot of
agitation and regrets remorse uh the inner life um uh feels uh you know
doesn't feel supported it feels like it's being somehow
um made more and more uneasy so don't please don't
underestimate the tremendous value of being calm it can certainly be over done
certainly be attached to cob and try to hold on to it there's a time for healthy
excitement and hopefully uh by being cognizant of the impact our Behavior has
on ourselves we'll recognize when healthy excitement is um is healthy and
when excitement is not so um may you have a calm day and
may you bring quality of Tranquility uh to help everyone feel safer and more
at ease thank you