so hello and to everyone
and so for this final meditation on the topic of the
week [Music] the the symptoms or the consequence of
letting go well consequence of non-
clinging that when we uh when we are able to let go of clinging to
something take the time to appreciate the after effect the results
of that and one of excuse me for a
minute and uh one of the consequences that is that we're able to
think better that when there's a lot of clinging a lot of attachments it isn't
just we're attach to one thing we're being propelled by um momentum of
wanting not wanting grasping resisting it's an accumulation it's a gathering
together it's a it becomes almost a way by which we are thinking we're
thinking motivated or driven by the very uh force of attachment force of
clinging force of preoccupation force of worry that we
have and thinking that comes from that kind of pressure
is not usually the best kind of thinking we can have uh it limits the the the fullness
or the full um um the full or the Deep capacity we have
to think to reflect we think much better wiser
Kinder more loving more wiser is probably the word I like to use the most
when we've let go when we've when we're not thinking is not being driven by
clinging and so one of the symptoms of non- clinging is feeling and sensing
experiencing a wiser more useful more connected way of
thinking and in meditation that plays out in that we're not so preoccupied
we're not preoccupied at all to think about things having not that have nothing to do with meditation or say it
more precisely that have nothing to do with connecting to what's happening as
present moment experience the Mind might be thinking about the the
future planning or worrying but the deep
thinking is uh is thinking that helps us to have an overview of that what's going
on for us to see clearly oh this is thinking about the future there's a deeper place from which
we observe we reflect we consider what's happening including considering the
surface thinking we have that is the thinking that comes from when there's
still some of this momentum of of grasping that might be
operating so it's not a matter of in meditation thinking or not
thinking it's a matter of thinking superficially or with blinders on or
with with thinking with agendas and thinking in a deeper
way holistic way a way that feels the thinking connects us to the present
moment as opposed to thinking that takes us away away from it and that thinking tends to be
quieter slower more peaceful and it's a thinking that
doesn't need to think it's a thinking that points
almost to that which is beyond
thinking it's almost as if you can sense in that deep thinking
the quiet or the peace or the Stillness or the
well-being the expansiveness within which this deep
thinking is occurring and so as we let
go in this meditation you might want to see if there's that gives you an
opportunity to have this deep form of thinking
this more holistic quieter peaceful thinking that points you or keeps
you in this very rich and valuable connection to yourself to reality that's
all about what's Happening Here and Now and as I said you might your surface
mind might still be thinking about other things but the Deep Mind
sees it all clearly is not tricked to be pulled away from
here so assuming a meditation
posture and thinking of the posture a little bit like a temple or a sacred grove or
a peaceful spot that you've known nature or at home
that the the posture you take let it be somewhat
intentional so it can be the it can
house a deeper connection a deeper
source for thinking and gently close your eyes
gently intentionally intentionally in a slow
way take a few long slow deep
breaths
relaxing as you
exhale and then letting your breathing return
to
normal and as you exhale to relax the muscles of your
face the tensions We Carry in our body are part of this accumulated
tension accumul that perpetuates the shallow thinking the
surface thinking the thinking which has a comp
compulsion behind it relaxing the body is a beginning of
softening that compulsive
thinking as you exhale relaxing the
shoulders
softening
then softening the
belly and then taking some time to feel and sense
the momentum or energy or pressure in the thinking
mind and as you exhale to soften relax quiet the
thinking mind
for
and then settling into your
breathing
and with every exhale let go of whatever you're
thinking about let go of preoccupation with what
you're thinking about
let go and while you exhale so you're able to receive the
inhale with a freshness or an openness
for
for a little bit longer with every exhale let go of your
thoughts any thoughts so so
that when you inhale you can be more connected to your
immediate experience here and now maybe through the sensations of
inhaling maybe through your body's
experience or maybe through a PR present moment
recognition of what is happening to you otherwise let go with the
exhale and then remember to be present Here and Now on the
inhale
for
e
continuing on the exhale to let go let go of any momentum any
preoccupation let go of even what you're not attached
to for these few moments as you exhale so it's clear here nothing you're
holding on
to if you can't let go relax
soften lessen the attachment to whatever degree you
can
for
and then as you inhale from the profoundest place you
know within or the most holistic way you
know use the simplest possible thought to connect you to What's
Happening Here and Now maybe the simple
thought this or
here or
now an upwelling of a more deeper way of
thinking that put you in a part partnership with the
deepest fullest place within a place of non- clinging
nonattachment
for
and then gently softly
take just a little bit deeper inhales than usual in
meditation so you can have a longer exhale in which to let
go relax settle in more deeply into
yourself
letting go of the tension or pressure agitation that might be
associated with thinking thinking
mind a softening of the thinking mind
for
and from whatever degree of Letting Go relaxing being present you
have see if there can well up from
within some wisdom that you have some way of thinking about the
present moment about practicing in the present moment
that you have what Wise
Way can you think about being here and
now thinking about how it's valuable so that it connects you to that
very way of being
her
and then from this deeper source of thinking a quieter place a wiser place
within from that place turn your gaze outward into the
world to the people you'll meet today both people you know and strangers
on the
streets and from a deeper place of wisdom deeper place of non-
clinging what for you would be a
friendly respectful kind way of gazing upon the people in your
life
and maybe perh from this deep
place these following words will resonate for you May
others be happy May others be
safe may others be
peaceful May others be
free and may I look upon the world without those
wishes may my thinking my way of being
support this way of seeing everyone may all
beings be
[Music]
happy thank
you
e
hello and welcome to this last talk
on the results or
the symptoms of of non- clinging now non- clinging letting go of
clinging dissolving clinging having clinging
somehow lesson and lesson until maybe it disappears The these are not easy to do
and it can't be done necessarily just sit down and just let go let go let go like we did in the last
meditation but but as we keep practicing every time we come back to
breathing every time we come back to mindfulness a Moment of clarity of knowing and seeing it is a kind of that's letting go
or maybe a different way of saying it is is a kind of kind of way of no
longer uh feeding the clinging we have the attachments we
have and it might not seem very significant one moment like that but the
accumulation of moments of not feeding or clinging not being involved in our clinging is has a dramatic results that
you can see and highlight if you remember or consider that for many of us
we have spent decades with a kind of thinking that's being propelled by some forms of
compulsion attachment clinging wanting not wanting and U and given that we've done
decades of that the amount of time it takes to begin softening and relaxing is
relatively short even though the process might be imperceptible in the moment
still uh can happen much faster than the opposite
happen so as we begin to lessen our attachments lessen that drive to be
attached to be clinging to be to be repressing to be resisting to be
the whatever that whatever form the attachment takes at some point something begins
shifting within us and it's not just a matter of clinging or not clinging but
it's beginning to appreciate something that's growing within us something a different way of being a different
sensibility and that's been the theme for this week so um there can grow a
sense of well-being a sense of spaciousness
expansiveness a sense of um Peace and ease there can grow a sense of feeling
more connected to our life and what's happening now there can also uh arise a deeper
deeper sense of creative thinking or deeper Wellspring of thinking in a new
way a different way A Better Way um um if um there have been times
when I felt kind of overwhelmed by things in my life what was going on too
much happening and my mind is kind of spinning and actively you know running
and jumping around from one thing to the other and so I've learned when that
happens I'll go sit down meditate for a while but sometimes it doesn't take that
long for things to settle and relax enough that it changes the quality
character istics of my thinking and now my thinking is not jumping so much it's more relaxed and settle and able to
address uh in a kind of clear way one thing at a time whatever the issue is
rather than jumping around and hopping as we let
go uh the uh letting go is not just a
you know a surface thing we do it begins opening up and releasing the
the Wellspring of intelligence that's in the the whole of who we are whenever
there's attachment whenever there's clinging whenever we there's repression going on it's um we're limiting
ourselves we're restricting ourselves and the movement in this practice towards freedom is to uh have
an unrestricted feeling uh within doesn't mean we're unrestricted do whatever we feel like we
want to do but there's no sense of anything here being restricted at the
movements within us and so then there can be a very different way of
thinking and deep meditation sometimes has a certain kind of rudimentary simple very light very calm
almost silent way of thinking that um is about the present moment
experience this is the this deeper source of where wisdom can
arise and um and so one of when you have non-
clinging not easy to do but certainly possible for every single one of
you uh as you begin sensing that you're letting go or relaxing even
temporarily one of the things to appreciate is the different way that you
think maybe you know I I talk about it being more deeper or more profound way
of thinking some of you might have a different vocabulary for it it might be
that it feels the thinking is more holistic or simply that the thinking is more calm it's more settled settled
thinking but one way or the other uh it doesn't have to be any of these words it
can be your own your own discovery of for yourself of what the difference is
is between uh clinging U thinking that's driven by
clinging thinking that's compulsive thinking jumping
thinking agitated thinking scared thinking versus thinking when we're
settled at ease feeling safe feeling contented feeling here we're really here
in the moment in its fullness and then can you see how for you there are two different ways of
thinking and uh and maybe you'll have your own way of describing that
distinction I I'm particularly fond of these days about the idea of profound
contemplation a deep way of thinking from deep within from the belly almost
that um settled and connected a feeling of being really in the body holistic and
here and that what wells up uh from within and then thinking can be there's
a different kind of intelligence there's a different form of creativity different form of of
um of um wisdom that can
come and um one manifestation of that when I first was living at a Buddhist
Monastery was um the creativity that started flowing through me that didn't
hadn't existed in my life before and I started writing poetry I started
doing art in a way and as a way of kind of giving voice in a sense to this
deeper Wellspring of um of uh emot emotions
even creativity that uh I had and certainly the art certainly the Poetry required
some kind of thinking but it was a very different kind of thinking sometimes there was a kind of spontaneity to it
and a con connectivity to it a a um freedom to it
where sometimes it feels like it's not me thinking uh I can't take ownership of
those thoughts I can't because they seem to be just coming from some place deep inside that um knows better knows
best and um not that I we should automatically believe everything that
comes from this deeper place place there's always a place for check and balances
to take a second look at whatever we're thinking and uh question everything but
it can feel be so satisfying to have have to think in some deeper deeper
Source within where kind of thinking flows in a very satisfying way um this
maybe even a sense of flow and and um with uh what emerges from us some people
find that that happens with uh when they think from that way um as they write
that they're writing it out and there can be a sense of flow and spontaneity and even Surprise by what might
come so um
so I'd like to repeat what I said that um the way I describe this doesn't have
to be how it actually is for you the important principle is that you might uh
as you begin to relax subtle get calmer less driven by attachments that you
might notice that your nature of your thinking changes and it's valuable to see that
change and it may be appreciated if it feels right then feels good um and um
because the appreciation of the consequences of non- clinging strengthens
our the value strengthens our connection to non- clinging if it's just a matter
of non- clinging and like that's all it feels like I'm doing then why would we do it but we start feeling the benefits
from it and feel the feel a choice word here that to really
feel it to sense it to experience it then uh non- clinging is not the duty
then and it's not just simply to let go of something that's some suffering we
have we let go also to receive the benefits of this uh uh of a life of
Freedom a life of mindfulness and we coming home to these
benefits so um so thank you very much and I hope
that this week has uh given you a filled out and expanded the domain the realm of
mindfulness so this has been a long series now since the beginning of the year on the introduction to mindfulness
and in some ways this is the kind of a culmination of the basic mindfulness instruction that also includes being
mindful of the consequences of the practice The Good the benefits that come
from it so thank you all very much and uh I
will be uh away uh for the next three weeks and uh
and I will miss being here with all of you and but you'll be in very good hands with uh
the other teachers who come and uh right in the moment I don't remember who they
are but uh the wonderful let's see I can tell
you uh next week it's Diana Clark one of the wonderful teachers here
here at IMC and Kim Allen the following week and the following week is uh don
Neil So are three really good teachers they've been here before and and I feel
very fortunate to have them substituting and I'll be back on the 21st of April
and um and uh I hope you all stay well and
connected and find your deeper source of creativity and intelligence and wisdom
through this practice thank you very
much