so again warm greetings as I said the electricity was out at home today
and and uh so it was a slow start and a lot of things
to different things to take care of and figure out to get come down here to
IMC
so so this is a also continuing this series
of introduction to mindfulness meditation and U now we come to
the week on emotions
and partly the idea in the sequence is that it's easier to be aware of
emotions if we are aware of the body the more we can can be embodied in
a direct and simple relaxed way the easier it is to get a some wisdom and
clarity about how to be present for emotions without being
excessively caught in them or involved in them or troubled by them
or and to be aware of the body it can help to be aware of
breathing of course breathing doesn't work for everyone as a foundation but the
simple uh rhythm of breathing in and out the Simplicity of just breathing
with maybe relaxing on the exhale and relaxing on the top of the inhale
just so that the breathing is a little bit longer just slightly longer not
forcefully almost naturally the breathing can be relaxing
and kind of settles the nervous system it it uh can be even reassuring at
times and it's a place to go where we can be present for our life without
being caught in our thoughts so for today I want to say that
uh what makes mindfulness sacred at least for the way my
understand understanding of my approach to this word sacred is when there's no outside
nothing is excluded from awareness there's a way in which awareness has space has room has the ability has the
wisdom to include everything within it and of course some emotions are quite
difficult but to discover how to include them in a caring way and an open way
so that wisdom can arise so that we can
see that every emotion is in somehow way connected to
something profound within sometimes the emotion might be
maladaptive adapted poorly or to something that's really profound
about ourselves and so the simp simple art of just recognizing we're
thinking and not being pulled into thoughts is the art of
mindfulness and we'll go through this in the course of the week but for today let's keep it
simple recognizing and leaving at that just
recognizing when we're thinking and keeping it super simple just
recognizing and then returning to the breathing returning to the
body so
gently assume meditation
posture and to close your
eyes and whatever way is grounding for you here and now in the
body let yourself be grounded if that's the breathing take a
few long slow deep breaths if there's a more direct way to the body
than through breathing you might use
that and for breathing in deeply relaxing long relaxation as you
exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and continue on the
exhale relaxing your body
maybe different parts of the
body
relaxing the thinking mind whatever tension or pressure is associated with
thinking physical sensations of pressure tension contra
raction tightness on the
exhale imagine your mind is like
a waves like a like a surface of a
lake and as you ex exhale and relax the waves on the lake flatten
out and the way and the lake surface becomes
calm and now in the simplest possible way
way the easiest possible way if you're
thinking recognizing recognize it as such maybe with a simple word
thinking where how the word is said or imagined in the
mind is easeful matter of
fact their recognition is maybe
free of any attitude about thinking or preferences around
thinking opinions about it being there
just almost like you're hear a bird singing in the trees
nearby you hear or know there are thoughts
happening and then Begin Again with your
breathing and the exercise this
morning is to discover how simple you can recognize think when you're
thinking and then to begin again with your
breathing maybe every exhale you recognize your
thinking and then begin again with the
inhale if thinking is in the background and it's easy to stay with your
breathing no need to recognize that you're
thinking only if you lose touch with
breathing or if the thinking
predominates
e
for
[Music]
e
for
recognize if you're
thinking the exercise is to recognize that as simply as you
can and then to begin again with your
breathing
for
e
and then to bring this meditation session to an
end to First for a few
moments continue the exercise of recognizing your
thoughts is simply thinking the content of the
thoughts for this this exercise doesn't matter just know that you're
thinking whether it's in words or
images
and then bring to mind people in your
life maybe people for whom for these few moments
you can remember or think about recall with the same
Simplicity just simply to know them without any
extra ideas
preferences desires
aversions simply know
them and maybe with the idea that this Simplicity of knowing remembering thinking
about is a means by which Good Will can
flow in an uncomplicated
way simple good
willll well wishing care and love and
kindness May these people that you think about may they be
well may they be
happy may they be
safe may they be
peaceful may they be
free
and may your Good Will in it simplest
form so simple there's no need for now to act on
it spread out across the world in all all
directions may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free [Music]
thank
you
e
so hello and welcome to this Monday
morning's introduction to mindfulness meditation we're now on the fourth week
to do a to do thinking and um we just had a meditation
before this that I was happy to do I think I arrived
a little bit unsettled and uh maybe I spoke a little
bit in a confused way at the introduction about what we're doing this
week There's was no electricity at home and other issues going on at home so to
get down here this morning there were a lot of steps involved and in the
dark so um so
thinking there's
a excuse me so thinking there's not a few meditators
who feel challenged by their thinking and uh there's not a few people
who are challenged because of their thinking Some people are troubled at the
by the fact that they're thinking in meditation and feel like that's wrong and uh kind of trying to bat them
away or and some people are not troubled by
the fact that they're thinking but they're troubled by the what they're thinking and I think thoughts can
sometimes have a huge impact on our mood or state of mind and
um so in mindfulness meditation we're looking to become wise about thinking
we're not trying to get rid of thinking and we're not trying
to um uh judge our thoughts we don't have to be critical of
them in a certain way we're trying to understand how to be with thinking that serves us the best
that uh is respectful for ourselves and our thoughts and that uh allows us to Source our
thinking in some of the deepest place within and uh this language of sourcing
I think it's maybe um an a uh industrial term when you
Source material uh you're looking for the material in which to build something
or to make something uh the place to make it and um but we can do that with
ourselves we thinking we Source our thinking where is the source from which we're
thinking and sometimes the source the origin the place of thinking is not
really so deeply connected within even though the content of the thoughts
affects all of who we are and it's possible to find a source
within to Source our thinking in some profound place within that if if we
think from that place that um this will have a very different effect on our mood
our state of mind and our relationships to this world of ours and so the way to become wise about
thinking and included in mindfulness Begins by uh understanding
that we're not going to be the enemy of thinking that thinking is part of the
what we can be mindful of it isn't that we stay and this is the advantage of the
kind of mindfulness practice we're teaching here we're not limiting attention to only breathing some
meditation techniques which are quite effective in some their own way can uh
focus is only on a narrow subset of our human experience and sometimes that people use
that they get concentrated absorbed in that subset like just the breathing itself but in doing so we're not being
inclusive of the full range of what it means to be a human being the full range
of human experience and the brance of Buddhist
mindfulness practice is that it can be inclusive of everything nothing is
outside of its range and as long as we're being mindful
of then um there's a place of Freedom we can find Freedom we can find balance
equinity wisdom if we're mindful by our anything if the
mindfulness is shaped by our emotions shaped by our thinking then we don't
find the same degree of freedom and wisdom so it isn't uh so the thinking is
not sourced in our emotions our life is not sourced
in our thinking but rather we discover a a different way of of
holding our thinking holding our emotions holding our bodily
experience and over time as we begin learning about how to be mindful uh there's a it comes a point
where we feel and recognize everything that we experience can
be held by mindfulness held in Awareness everything is something we can be
mindful of and because we we understand that the Act of mindfulness of awareness
is kind a certain kind of freedom in and of itself the act of mindfulness is not
being entangled or caught or reactive it's just a clear recognition simple
recognition this is what happening and uh I remember when I came
to this understanding um that it first it was theoretical the understanding was
wow um in theory I could be have this mindfulness that I was learning uh
directed or inclusive of everything in my Human Experience and if that's the case then I
can be free in all experiences and I became so happy and uh
it was kind of like a revelation for me and say wow to be able to have to live
without that freedom wow that is that's possible now now I understand what it
takes and that gave me a lot of enthusiasm then for really relying on
mindfulness having faith in it as opposed to having faith uh in my
thoughts in my beliefs I I stopped having faith in in thinking worrisome thoughts about the
future I spent a lot of time thinking about how challenging things were going to be in the future for me I I no longer
had so much faith in reviewing the past and the resentments I had and that reviewing
them and living them was something that had tremendous value which of course I
didn't actively think that way but I was behaving that way the mind was that's what it was doing and when I really
started to have faith in mindfulness then I began to understand that in
contrast to that how I placed my how I invested myself in all these areas of
life how how to be how to think what to think about as if those were the important place to
live and and learn to shift it to something else just mindfulness of so
so we want to learn how to be mindful of thinking not just to let go of it and
part of that is so we can have a different relationship to thoughts uh to hold thoughts lightly and
openly without being caught in them and also because our thinking is just a
tip of an iceberg thinking is is a is often very deeply connected to other
parts of ourselves and if we're lost in our thoughts caught up in our thoughts or think that navigating and negotiating
the world is only through our thinking then we're riding on the tip of that
Iceberg and uh and there's a whole big thing uh to explore and to discover um
below that tip um and that's when we kind of enter into the kind of a big fullness of who we
are and so um one example of this that was I was trying to say earlier but I
didn't quite manage is um it's easier to be aware of
thinking when you aware when you know how to be present for
emotions it's also easier to be aware of emotions if you know how to be aware of things
thinking because the two are so deeply intertwined it's so easy it's
fascinating to watch how we think certain thoughts and the emotion follows
other times we have certain emotions and the thinking gets changed accordingly and so to learn to to how to
see these more clearly see that influence back and forth is a way of stepping back and not being in that
exchange it's easier to be aware of emotions and also thinking if we're know
how to be mindful of the body and the body is a rich area of attention body is
not just a Corporal physical event it's deeply connected to our deep
life and then it's easier to do all of it in the Simplicity of breathing
breathing is a way of protecting ourselves from being swept away in
Endless thoughts that spin and spin and spin
so for today the the exercise the suggestion was to
experiment with how simple you could know that you're
thinking and simple doesn't mean that you're
condoning participating condemning your thoughts it just means you step
back almost like you step back two feet two steps and you recogniz oh that is
thinking with the recognition not caught up in the
thoughts so we're using kind of a thought to recognize that we're
thinking so might seem like a paradox or confusing but the thought of
recognition is um is really simple and
not sticky not caught in stuck with whatever we're thinking this is a
powerful exercise if you can get a hang of it one thing that might help you with
this is if uh you can also begin noticing if you think if you're thinking
in words or thinking in images some people do predominantly one or the other
some people do a comb ation of them maybe at different times and
um but uh some people have never considered this for themselves and um so
but if you can clearly recognize I think more in words and where's the source of those
words in the mind where do you have a sense those words are being spoken in the mind and if you have a location then
you can step back and oh I'm thinking I'm thinking words if you're mostly
thinking through images where are those being projected maybe a little bit in front of
you um but uh and then oh thinking I'm
thinking images that's what's happening so as you go
along today through your life look for opportunities to in a regular way to
recognize thinking and recognize whether you're thinking in words or images and
see if you can how simple you can recognize that you're thinking without
being caught in the thinking almost like you've stepped away and looking back
without being in in the midst of the fry so thank you very much and
um look forward to seeing you being part of this again
tomorrow