so hello everyone hello and welcome to this edition of happy
hour so so for today's practice I want to invite us to
um yeah to embrace Embrace
um where meta where compassion is easiest where it's
easiest and and um for some it's easiest to start with someone
we care about that's where it's easiest that's where U it's simpler and then we
can turn it to ourselves and one reason for um turning
to where it's easiest is you know with meta you don't want to fight against it you want to find a way that's really
easy and wholesome and nourishing and and your whole heart and body and mind
can be suffused with it and sometimes when we start practicing with ourselves
there might be some edges there might be some nooks and crannies that are like nope not quite I'm not ready to love all
those parts yet so it's okay it's all right it's okay we take it gently we
turn we warm up the The Meta um through someone else who's
really really really easy to to have metaphor um and then we as after it's
been warmed up then we we turn it towards ourselves and and one reason why
I'm bringing this in right now especially with everything that's going on in our world in our um politically
Etc is is taking Refuge where it's easy
where it's nourishing really where it's easy and nourishing for for your own
heart no matter which side you're on what you're thinking it's just we're all tired and oh there's just so much going
on so so going back back to the basics nourishing the heart um through care
through love um and common humanity is is um feels feels right so so that's the
invitation for today's practice you're welcome to sit if you want to lie down
you can do that too um as long as you're not going to fall asleep if you know
you're going to fall asleep don't lie down and I think that's all I need to
say right now yeah so um yeah so let's begin let's begin let's
begin arriving arriving in our bodies
arriving arriving this moment this moment embracing this moment
fully however it's showing up this body however it's showing up in this
moment inviting the body to relax
settle to feel our feet on the Earth
to feel our sit bones to sense our sit Bones on the chair on the
cushion and our hands touching one
another inviting ourselves to spend some
time with the length the entirety of the in breath
the entirety of the out
breath Letting Go softening
arriving with each
breath e
and if the mind is wondering here and there still engaged with what was
happening before this sit noticing with a smile the stories
the thoughts and inviting your dear heart your dear mind to put it down thank you
not now we'll come back to this you'll still be here dear mind let's put it all
down and give our heart to this practice
settling more deeply Letting Go relaxing more of the
body with each breath with each out breath
now I like to invite each of us to bring into our heart space invite
someone for whom our care our meta flows with ease there's
no complication in the
relationship babies are really good for this category babies
children grandchildren pets
and if your children are now adults when they were babies
young friends and loved ones are good as long as there is no complication in the
relationship
you can borrow nieces nephews when they were
[Music] young bring this being bring this
being to your heart's mind your heart's space
and if you're going through the Rolodex of your mind to find the perfect being it's okay to settle on
one and also might be some baby child or pet you don't know
very personally that's okay too but the being that conjures up just
brings joy happiness meta warmth
Goodwill bring this being to your heart's
mind either if you're visual seeing them
your auditory hearing them
feeling them as many senses as you can use to bring a felt sense of this
being it's a baby perhaps how soft and cuddly they are how they
smell it's a pet maybe how it feels or it felt at some
point to stroke them hold
them play with them spend some
time connecting really connecting with the felt sense
as you connect with the felt sense as many sense do as available you can
conjure up then bring attention to what comes
up in your heart space in your mind in your
body as you feel into this being this
beingness for me I notice a smile comes up sense a warmth in my heart center
connecting with how sweet and cute my friend's baby is wishing them well
wishing her happiness just naturally blows out I want this baby to be
happy to keep giggling being a source of
Joy it's being happy in her being a
baby and see for you it naturally comes up this is meta it's not so
complicated it might be very [Music] gentle that's okay might be big that's
fine there may not be so much sensed but the feeling that you're planting
seeds and that's great too hang in there doesn't have to feel a particular
way keep connecting with the beingness as
multi-dimensionally as possible your body and your memory your felt sense as if they're right here
Conjuring them up
that's the first aspect the second which naturally arises from connecting with
them is this Sensations in the Heart
Center perhaps Goodwill meta that naturally arises in
the heart and if you like you can add
phrases as the third support as the third wheel
may you be safe de
one may you be happy dear
one may you be healthy dear one
and may your life flow with ease dear one using your own
words maybe simplifying if that feels
better something that connects with your wish I wish you happiness and heal I
wish you Joy wish you
ease whatever might be can add their
name dear so and so sweet so and so whatever feels right for
you keep connecting and keep resting and biting
this nourishment this cultivation of the
heart if at any point it gets weak then reconnect keep reconnecting with their
beingness as multi-dimension Al as
possible
e e
and remember that this practice is not about attachment to outcome so
that this being is definitely happy and safe and all that but it's about
cultivation of our heart hard in Wishing Well in Sharing
kindness in caring and loving well it's all it
is keep planting seeds sharing goodness that's
all without attachment to
outcome e
keep connecting to their beingness
e
e e
keep connecting with their
beingness
e
e e
and as we turn to end this practice period
together in your heart thanking this
being who has supported your practice today this child this P this individual
this being with their beingness just being in the world and also appreciating yourself for
having practiced without judgment not reading
it whatever it was you planted seeds you've showed
up yay it's all that matters you've showed up even if there was one mind
moment of kindness Goodwill that's infinitely more than none more than zero
so appreciation for your yourself the community let us
dedicate the goodness the co-created goodness of this practice to all beings
may my practice May our practice be a cause and condition for more goodness in
the world more kindness more care more love more
stability more happiness may all may all beings be happy may all be be free
including
myself thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so tonight was simple and sweet
Back to Basics where it's easy where it's simple could be quite nourishing
and connecting and happy
making so basically with this practice I review it one more time Conjuring up a
being for whom our care or Goodwill flows with ease there's no
complication and um and really trying to connect with
their the way they are their beingness is their suchness their beingness how they sound how they feel
how they look just maybe how cuddly they are whatever
this this felted sense of this this being and uh as you connect with it then
notice what comes up in your heart in your mind and so that number one is the
being their beingness the being is the first leg of the stool the second
leg is is what arises from connecting with them is the feeling in our hearts which is a tenderness kindness warmth a
smile whatever comes up that's number two and from number two we allow phrases
to flow phrases to flow of Goodwill of kindness to keep the the uh all three
going so so for today's um and I'll open it up later to questions
and Reflections but R now like to um invite us now to engage in small groups
in breakout groups um to practice together practice
me meta as the rubber meets the road um and
MTA I have it in chat it's um
am standing for mindfully listening and speaking considering the practice and in
small groups as a continuation of our practice in in
Silence with ourselves how do we show up can we show up with awareness with
kindness for ourselves for others staying embodied embracing compassion and
kindness if there's any internal resistance reaction discomfort can we hold it with kindness both internally
externally staying on topic and the topic I wanted to give you tonight is
um as you practiced today with with
someone wh for whom um you met to flows with ease what did you find supportive
was there something that you found supportive and by offering in the community what you found suppor if you
can support other people again you're not so much saying to instruct them and teach them but just a stone soup you're
offering oh yeah this was supportive to me and again um please only share about your own practice don't comment on other
pra on other people give them advice no cross talk um and take turns
briefly offer one short nugget let let the next person speak and then the next
person next and then comes back to you and you go around round and round a few
rounds and let's go in reverse alphabetical order tonight um reverse
alphabetical order so I'm going to create the breakout rooms
now and if you allow me a moment or two to to uh let's
[Music] see let me recreate that um it's always
an interesting thing to do this recreate
let's try this again okay and I might need to move some folks around we'll see how this goes but okay I'm going to open
them for now here we go take care of yourselves take care of one another and
connecting with with meta and joy and care for for these other beings in our
lives and also care and joy for everybody having someone or some being
that they can conjure up to uh uh to wish well for so here we go opening all
rooms okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back so we have some
time for Reflections for questions everything is
welcome I'm going to change chat you can type uh
your questions Reflections either to everyone in which case I'll read your name too if it's just to me privately I
will only uh read your reflection then you could also raise your Zoom hand if you like to share what did you notice
tonight what what happened what came up
[Music]
Isabel ah um one thing that really is starting to um come into my life with
doing happy hour regularly and tonight especially is the the coming back I to
to be reminded to come back to the pet that I was thinking of and that would like became kind of like um a mantra and
uh like a coming back to the breath it was coming back to that space of Love of
something that was not difficult to love and care and and um so I'm really um
committed and grateful to be having this uh new new chapter in my life with this
group and I find myself attending pretty regularly now so there's something
happening for me thank you Nikki yay thank you Isabelle that's lovely thank
you for sharing this um I'm hearing that you're noticing something is happening a
shift is happening which which is why you're showing up there's a shift happening and and um all U and also what
you noted with coming back the same way that in um some practices for example in
vasana you know we keep going back to the breath as the anchor here going back to the being that being is the anchor we
keep going back and in that that being brings up the meta and and the phrases
flow out of that so having that anchor that's oh yeah it's clicking things are clicking for you which is which is just
lovely and you're seeing changes in your life yay lovely thanks Isabelle it's
awesome uh
Amy uh so tonight I was having actually I was having difficulty I was noticing
like an inner critic thoughts saying like well do you actually feel
compassionate to them or you actually you're not that actually that loving like you you're going to find a problem
with everybody everything no matter what and and every time I cut I was like well
let me try something a little more simple let me try this and it was everything felt sticky um and so I kind of just gave
myself like I even though I didn't feel it in Heart Like body way I was like
trying to you know give myself some compassion like okay right now the brain is doing this it's like this yeah and
then I moved to the breath a little bit just to just to have something else that was a focus nice nice nice beautiful
thanks for sharing Amy I really appreciate the wisdom of okay
I'm I'm the one who's hurting right now and the mind and also I appreciate how how you yeah the mind is doing this
right now okay the mind is feeling a little critical right now
okay dear mind all right sweetheart okay it's okay it's all right turning instead of really trying to to beat beat oneself
up like okay this is what's happening right now the realization of that accepting it and then the appropriate
response which is compassion for yourself great perfect and and another
um option I also want to suggest to you sometimes is sometimes it might actually be very helpful maybe tonight this
wouldn't have worked either but I'll just say it is um sometimes when the mind is very
critical people whom we know and near and dear than the mind can be critical
but you can go to maybe you've seen a a I don't know a video of a of a kid of a
kitty on the web like right it's it's almost like the neutral person because it's so removed it's like it's a kitty
it's like how can you find fault with a kitty like just a cute kitty you can wish well for that unknown Kitty in that
cat video so that sometimes could be helpful as well well I don't again night might not
happen but just so so you know that it's in yeah that feels like just picturing it now is you know brings a smile to my
face so I feel like there's a flow of something different just even yeah picturing you know an animal bunch of
little baby animals exactly bunch of little chicks oh my goodness when I was growing up I used to have chicks and it
was just like oh just seeing an image of a chick just my heart is happy they're
so cute and cuddly so yeah have at it yeah great thanks
Amy and Jerry first of all thanks for the
direction of the beginning Nick and I'm sorry I was a bit delayed com from work but um oh good so I was thinking about
this that it does help to in terms of the practice in terms of what makes it
easier or more focus it does help the pick an easy person that's for sure like
uh that's doesn't uh that you don't have a sense of uh some St uh strain with but
the effect of it though is um quite powerful because it gives the me a sense
of enhances not all not all of it but is where I get it but it enhances a sense
of purpose a sense of belong longing and a sense of security so fundamental
issues in terms of psychological Wellness uh to be able to sort of and so
you feel this shift in your body and you think this is this is this is where I want to be and now listen I get tired I
get lonely I get angry I could not but in the state that I was thinking when you asked the question uh how do you
enhance the practice or how do it help the practice but also the downstream effect it's quite anchoring so thank
you thank you Jerry well well put well put um and and knowing
that you you have expertise and and um a
lot of knowledge in this area as you're talking about you know the the really the psychological resourcing that this
kind of practice can allow in ways that really expand to bring more um more
physical stability and and and uh regulation and and the heart and mind
and yeah so many benefits and so easy right so it seems straightforward like
yeah we all can conjure up some being that's cute and cuddly and lovable and just give him love in our hearts and oh
guess what I feel better I don't feel as anxious or angry or upset or exhausted
that I did 30 minutes ago wow I feel better and gosh my heart feels more open
to myself to others oh that's the the
wild amazing thing that happens with these um precious practices yeah thanks
Jerry you
Claire thank you having a lot of video problems tonight I just wanted to add
because I don't think anybody mentioned it that several people in our group talked along exactly the same lines you
were just speaking about of animals and pets and the nurturing that they provide
us yeah yeah indeed which is exactly what you were saying right absolutely
yeah yeah thank you Claire yeah very important it's unconditional love and
it's yeah very nourishing thanks for highlighting that
Peggy hi um in initially I had some a
little bit of lamenting that I I had trouble finding someone that I had unconditional love for um but
I did manage and but what's interesting is I was a little sad about that starting off and now it's like that love
is in my heart without needing an object like just that
feeling so it's it's really nice and um thank you just kind of for everyone a that's lovely thank you piggy
thanks for sharing that's um yeah I so appreciate the
progression that you shared and that most importantly that you stuck with it
you know maybe that feeling comes up like oh I can't find anyone H going through the Rolodex which is very old
school but any going through my contact list ah um and and then hanging in there
and keep practicing as best as you're able to and then realizing actually wait there's a lot of love in my heart wow
it's our it's it's here it's already here it's here in in ways that so so hanging in there with the practice
allowed this this burgeoning this this shift instead of staying in there so I
really want to reflect that back thank you thank you thanks Peggy this is so
lovely this is so heartwarming your practice report um and I'll share my my
practice report too so um as I mentioned earlier in the guided meditation the
person who came up was a a baby of a of a friend of mine who was so cute so
adorable and I was just finding myself so happy and uh she just turned one so
I'm just happily um Conjuring her up her photos her recent photo just cuddly and
cute like may be happy may be well you just and I noticed big big smile showing
up on my face and and feeling really uh really happy of of offering Good Will to
this kid um so that's my practice report I'm much happier than I was before this
this session so I thank you all for your practice and joining me and I want to
keep um maybe uh give a pause for any last minute Reflections questions
anything before we close the meeting
together okay going once going twice okay feels
complete so thank you all thank you for your practice for
cultivating goodness care meta love kindness yeah may all beings be happy
may all beings be free including ourselves