so let's do uh some
meditation maybe there's a way that there's a little wiggling of the body as
we like settle into our meditation
posture some bigger breaths as we connect to the sensations of breathing
connect to the
body and tuning into the connections with our Cain
surface whatever that surface might be
the couch floor the
bed maybe even some of you are walking probably not driving but
walking I find it can make a big difference to really feel the foundation
upon which I'm sitting and to feel grounded and I'm
here which also means
now feeling the feet on the ground
feel in the back of the legs the contact with the sitting
surface the Bic the pressure
of the cushion chair seat whatever it might be
L that against the
body and if you're using a back rest pressure against the back
opening to Sensations in the
face we often hold tension around the eyes or the jaw
it might be that bringing awareness to areas that have
tension help soften or loosen the tension
it might not be
also can we not be tense about having
tension cheen in with the neck
for me I like to move my chin like directly back not up or down
but back just a tiny
bit opens up the neck and it's a little bit more speed
the shoulders letting them relax and move
away from the ears shoulder blades sliding down the
back
justest can it be just a tiny bit more
open moving the should shoulders back maybe it's not even perceptible by
another person if they were to be looking at you this really small movement
something
resting attention on the sensations of
breathing noticing how the body breathes noticing the
experience the sensations no words are needed
e
feeling into the experience breathing
noticing the stretch and the release of the stretch
as we inhale and
exhale
e e
when you find yourself lost in
thought no need to make a story about what it means about you as a
meditator or this meditation
session we just Begin Again
with the sensations of
breathing the experience of
breathing
e e
Bing pretty particular needs to be
happening or just noticing the experience of
breathing
e
e e
part of this tradition
the story of the Buddha
meditating under a
tree is there a way that you can feel
supported encouraged knowing that countless
individual have been doing this practice
sitting literally or figuratively under a
tree what would it be
like for you imagine you're sitting under a
tree in a relaxed easy
way but with dedication
commitment
e
e e
[Music]
morning welcome welcome
again so I'm continuing on this series about
stories and in the preceding days I earlier in the week I spoke about you
know I gave few stories and sort of to talk about the role of stories have in
our lives and our relationship to them and I'll do the same today with a
different story and that is the story of the
Buddha's path to Awakening and uh as you may know
different uh Buddhist Traditions have different versions of this story and um I'll talk a little bit more
about that in a moment but um I'm going to give one version of this
story as you know there's different versions of different ways I could do
this so this version of the story is in one that if um it's not uncommon uh in
this lineage this tradition is that the the Buddha was a historical figure like
somebody who existed who Scholars will say died in
483 in the before the Comm era so you know about 2600 years
ago and his name was sidartha ktima and he was a human he lived and died just
like humans do so he wasn't a God in particular or he wasn't born from a God
or something like this but was a human just like we are and but he uh during
the course of his life made some discoveries about Freedom peace Nana
Nirvana and these discoveries were very practical and profound and
groundbreaking so over the ages people have felt compelled to have shared of
his teachings including the story of his
Awakening and in some ways uh we might say that this story has become
um maybe little bit more myth than fact or I don't know but it doesn't mean that
we uh can't be inspired by or moved by his life and his uh Discovery so the
Story begins with this person Sara Goa who uh was a prince that was in Northern
India probably what is [Music] in in modern times at Nepal and he lived
a very sheltered life he lived in his Palace and he was was very pampered and
had a life that um made him not really experience some of the difficulties of
his life and so it wasn't until he was a young adult that uh he really
encountered what we sometimes call like the Heavenly Messengers that he encountered old age sickness and
death and in some versions of the story The put in a fourth Heavenly messenger
uh so a monastic somebody who was uh had some great peace but having encountered old age
sickness and death while he was out on a ride in a chariot being driven by a
chariot driver of course he was a prince so uh he didn't drive himself he was
driven around but he was deeply troubled by seeing this old age sickness and
death and realized my goodness you know this is going to happen to me as well
and everybody that I care about and everybody that's important to me and there's got to be a way out of this this
suffering of knowing this impending old AG sickness and death and or if there
people who are already experiencing old age and sickness maybe see a death on
the horizon there's got to be a way out of this suffering out of the difficulties of
this so he left his this Palace this beautiful palace where everything he had
was a catered to apparently in this quest to go find the end of this
suffering of this part of the suffering that's uh The Human Condition and it's noteworthy that he
left behind a wife and a baby the wife was uh named yasodara and the baby was
named rahula so after he uh left he discovered some
meditation Masters and he studied uh meditation with them and becoming
incredibly proficient and the first meditation Master said well you know you're as good as I am now maybe you can
teach with me but uh the person who is to become the Buddha the bodh
S said like yeah you know but I haven't found the end of this suffering so he went to the next meditation Master uh
who taught a little bit further a little bit more depth than what the first one had and uh acquired the same skills and
the second meditation Master meditation Master said okay well you're so good maybe you can teach with me or another
teacher and person who was to become the Buddha said nope I haven't found an end of
suffering so he continued on his quest and then uh said that maybe he
would try some extreme asceticism and which included uh not
eating and he nearly starved himself to death and you can find statues of him
being incredibly emaciated with with his ribs and all his bones are really being
uh predominant and but he still couldn't he was near
death and still hadn't found an end to suffering and he just found more suffering
really but then uh had this memory of when he was a young person having uh
was often I said the first jna this meditative experience where there wasn't
suffering there's this incredible ease and some joy and some happiness and he had the sense of maybe
that's the direction that's the direction to go but he was so uh emaciated he didn't
really have this strength so uh young woman as it happened encounters him in
this near starvation near death and offers him some rice milk he takes the
rice milk and starts uh regaining some of his health eating a little bit more
and then he when he had enough strength he sat with this incredible
determination under a bod tree like a ficus religiosa I think is
the name this is a type of a Fus that I'm sitting next to here too and he set up with this incredible
determination okay I'm not going to move until I become awakened and while he is sitting there
he becomes attacked by Mara can say is this a personification of difficulties
or things that get in the way of a hindrances some traditions hold that
Mara is a demonic uh figure but uh I personally don't have that view I just
that representing what uh gets in the way and Mara is throwing all these uh
terrible things towards him there's different versions of the story but some of them you like a mud
and fire and all these things are getting thrown at the Buddha and somehow
he's able to meet them in such a way that uh they get transformed into flowers and instead the Just Flowers
fall near to his uh seat and at one point he like touches the ground and
some as the Earth is my witness I'm going to become awakened and
he becomes awakened so that's the version of the
story that bana is telling on this uh Wednesday morning there's so many
different versions of the story and that uh maybe on another day I might uh
include other details and not include other details but one thing that's interesting
about this I think that um some of you know that like in this tradition and and
I would say in particular Gil Fran's lineage there's an emphasis on the sutas
there's emphasis on the poly Canon some of you know that Gil and I just we spent a number of years talking about the
majima Naya we offered a course on the majaya and um we've in other settings
have done of course on the samut Naya and the de Naya and a lot of stuff uh
with the suit do you might be surprised to learn that so much of what that story
that I just told about the Buddha and his quest for awakening is not in the
poly Canon some of those elements are there but uh they're attributed to other
people it's their part of other people's stories and some of it is just simply isn't there including this named sedara
Goa the name sadara is not in the poly Canon we just have um Goa some people
pronounce it gotama but in poly we would say
go so this for me is all fascinating well our tradition has the story We
value the PO Canon and yet the story is not from the PO Canon the story of the
Buddha's Awakening in the poly Canon has a different emphasis about some of his medit ative practices and how he worked
with fear and some of these types things so you know as maybe the story of
the Buddha's Awakening as is true of all Stories the person who is telling it tends to
emphasize those aspects that speak to them those aspects that uh tend to think
are important and maybe like disregard those other aspects so I didn't talk about any Supernatural elements for me
that's uh not what's inspiring for me what's inspiring is the fact that the Buddha was a
human I'm a human you guys are humans right and there's for me like
this the potential for awakening the potential to find greater peace and ease
and freedom is really meaningful and inspiring for me and the fact that uh
this the Buddha story is a I feel uh inspired by so one thing
I want to talk about is how stories create connections they serve as a bridge but
connect individuals a bridge like through time or through geography through cultures a way in which we can
find some of these common elements some of you might recognize that this version of the Buddha's Awakening is a Heroes
Journey that is where this which is an archetypal you know story like Through the Ages that individuals have a person
embarks on a journey overcomes various challenges and then undergoes uh
personal growth and transformation these types of stories really resonate with us there's a reason
why Star Wars was so popular right this typical uh Heroes
Journey so that's one way in which they create connection is there these archetypes but there's also other ways
in which stories really create connections and some is that they um
represent or evoke emotions like maybe there's a way that
uh we could uh relate to I know I certainly can relate to the story of the Buddha's Awakening where he had some
confusion he wasn't clear to him okay well how do I find greater Peace and Freedom he went to some meditation
Masters that didn't work you went to work with some Aesthetics that didn't work and it was until he had a memory
from something from childhood which for me kind of like represents some innocence some ease you know when we're
children we don't have as uh as much idea of who we're supposed to be instead
we're just with the moment maybe there's this way in which
stories um kind of connect us with some emotion in this case maybe there's
frustration or perseverance and but maybe also some peace but there's also a way in which uh
stories pass down Traditions sitting sitting in a meditation posture
for us we sit cross-legged I can imagine that there's other Traditions right that don't necessarily sit in this particular
way but there's a way that um we also are passing down some of these uh
beliefs and values get shared uh with this with the stories in this particular
story of the Buddha's Awakening this idea of that okay there are difficulties in life daa there are struggles and for
me this is also really meaningful just to recognize okay I'm not the only one who has had struggles and a certain
amount of relief to like oh yeah even thousands of years ago they were
struggling too they had difficulties the particulars were different but there's
something the same that all of us humans have and there's also this way in which
through this storytelling is this uh in the Buddhist tradition in particular this um this uh
emphasis on Behavior ethical behavior in this version of this of the
story that I told the budha is not doing anything unethical right he's following the precepts he's uh has a standard uh
for his behavior that he's not going around you know trying to harm other
people and convince them or he's not uh gossiping about people like oh I had to
leave those the meditation Masters they were so terrible you know there's nothing like that no he's just finding
his way there another way in which like stories help uh connect us through what
we hold valuable and shared and some of our shared
struggles even though it's not in the poly Canon which we hold up to be really high this exact version of the story
it's a version of the story that get Carries On from Drama teacher to D teacher and Dr practitioner to Dr
practitioner books and so many different ways movies because it's meaningful and
it connects us so the stories that connect us
connect us as humans maybe today you'll notice some of
the stories that connect you to this tradition to this practice and to other
people are some of the stories that you share and are they helpful or not
helpful thank you thank you for your practice and I'll see you
tomorrow e
thank you thank
you it's lovely to practice
together and I'm looking at the chats but I recognize that there's many people that are also watching who are not uh
engaging with the chats maybe you're looking at at them but not uh posting or connected and you know that
we're um maybe paying attention to the same things here whether you're on the
chat or not
what a pleasure it is to be with you all
best wishes best wishes everybody