hello everyone and welcome and today the plan is to
mostly have a silent meditation after evoking a
very uh very simply evoking a particular quality to include in your meditation
which I'll mostly just name so but be since people are still
arriving I'll take one minute to say that
um uh for the after I'll be here tomorrow
and then for the next four weeks I won't be here on YouTube I'll be away and we have wonderful teachers
coming to fill in uh while I'm gone and um and I'll will be uh for three weeks
uh teaching uh this whole Insight approach to practice
in the wilderness uh camping and backpacking with people and then uh and then the
fourth week I'll be backpacking with my wife so um so I'll be uh uh that's where
I'll be and you'll be really well attended by some of the teachers you've
we've had before and I'm very happy that they're they're filling in
so so for this sitting I want to
evoke particular quality that I'm not going to say much about or guide you into the
meditation but rather let each of you if you're interested to find your own way
because each of you will have a different understanding of this concept Well a different approach to it
different way of living living with it and um but may it be that you keep this
close this concept this quality this uh capacity human potential that we all
have that you keep it close in this meditation it's a guide for The Meditation it's a reference point it's a
a um orientation uh uh uh with which to
through which to know and see and be mindful
so so with that the quality is
kindness friendliness good
will or perhaps positive
regard to gaze upon to have one's gaze be a gaze of
positive regard kindness for ones
self kindness for one's experience
friendliness as a almost a synonym of
mindfulness Good Will to be
mindful through the lens of a positive regard
so that is the orientation for this sitting and I
will I'll leave it at that and leave you to settle in and find your way with
these I consider them extremely profound
qualities qualities that
mature on this path of Liberation these are not kindergarten Buddhist
qualities these actually are the fruition of this
practice
e
for
for for
e
for
for for
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this sitting to once
again tap into your
capacity for kindness for
friendliness for Good Will and positive
regard perhaps thinking of anyone in the the world that you have
these feelings for even if it's a a
pet or someone you don't know personally I know some people think of the some
great spiritual
leader and to remind yourself that you do have the capacity for kindness or
friendliness at
times in certain contexts maybe when you're with a small
child maybe when you're at the bedside of someone who's
dying maybe you stop on the side of the road for someone who's been in an accident
and we all have some capacity for Good Will positive regard care
kindness each person in their own way doesn't have to look the way other
people have it and to have the occasion of
meditation to be a time in the safety of meditation
and the quiet meditation at the very end of meditation to spend a few
moments reflecting gazing bringing to
mind all beings everywhere or say differently bring up
that kindness and see if for a few
moments it can be there directed to all beings all
people a regular tapping in to a universal Good
Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
is
so hello and welcome to this fourth talk having to do with the upay
suta and um I'll read it again to you every day beginning of each of these
talks and the Buddha talking to his disciple Ananda his attendant attendant
monk it is not easy Ananda to teach the
dhma to others the dhama should be taught to others when five qualities are
established within oneself which five the dhama should be taught to
others thinking I will speak speak step by step the dhama should be taught to
others thinking I will speak for practical reasons I will speak with
reasons the dumb much should be taught to others thinking I will speak for I
will speak grounded in kindness that dhama should be taught
with others thinking I will not speak for material
reward the dhama should be taught to others thinking I will speak without wounding myself or others
so and as I've been saying I believe that this teaching that supplies to
teaching the dhama that uh when we're not teaching the dhama that um we can apply this to
any way that we speak or any way if you're a teacher of any kind it can be
applied to teaching in any way and um and so here today I want to uh talk
about uh in on this list the third piece which is
kindness and the word here is some probably a poly word many of you don't know it's anuda a n u d a y a and um and
Dia also means kindness or so Anu means with or following or directed directing
um kindness and um and uh some people will
have called uh have tried different ways because kindness is often associated
with meta one of the challenges when there's all these different words in poly that are related having to do with
our they kind of the posit positive social emotions and um and so some people have
translated anodia as compassion some people as tender
kindness um sympathy um um so all kinds of it was one of the problems of one of
the wonderful delightful challenges of translating poly into English is finding
English words for these positive emotions so uh for here it's a kindness
today anuda and um and so this positive regard of
others and the reference point for me for very important reference point for
all the positive social uh care emotions loving kindness
compassion um sympathetic Joy equinity kindness friendliness all these
is the way when I started practicing Buddhism in my early 20s I think I was
20 when I started that um these these uh these motions of
positive regard kind of found me they arose as part of the meditation
practice they were not something that I Tred
to make happen it wasn't something I was told you should be do do the things uh
they seem to arise in the course of the practice and since I was practicing Zen
at the beginning there was a big emphasis on emptiness and certainly we were in Zen not supposed to be we were
not supposed to be really in Zen in Zen meditation you're not supposed to be trying to cult at or develop anything uh
it was really kind of just sitting completely uh with the truth with no gaining idea just with the present
moment in a full accepting um uh a
um a a kind of a thoroughgoing acceptance of the
present moment and um and in that there arose in
me compassion and uh first I think it was because I suffered so much that um this this uh
thorough acceptance of the present moment accepting suffering um not fighting it not struggling against it
not trying to fix it it made room for something to soften in me made room for something new to appear that I never had
before or not had in any kind of significant way and there was the rising of compassion and because it didn't seem
to have a source in me it just seemed to arise um uh it seemed to arise in the
emptiness of this that was there with this thorough thoroughgoing acceptance of the present moment I I came to the
conclusion that that emptiness in a certain way is um is uh not exactly
synonymous with compassion but emptiness contains compassion something like that there's a natural function that
arises that doesn't have to have a reason exactly or it's not engineered or
made happen and and um and then as the practice continued to develop over the
years and with you past the same thing happened with loving kindness with meta then then it's evolved more with this
more profound thing I think or related thing called anukampa I translate as
care friendliness has became a more more more and more something that I was
oriented towards and so I say all this to talk
about uh uh that the the the um the um social care the social
positive emotions we have for others that um they are part of the fruition of
practice part of the the fruit of doing this practice itself because a lot of
what the practice is about is getting out of the N the way of what wants to arise in US
naturally now it can feel very natural to be angry and hostile can be very natural natur to be greedy and want
things and be afraid and of course in some ways it is natural it's a part of our being but it's this uh as I said
last last few weeks it's a very different operating system that uh is oping within us and um
and it's the operating system which in a sense is more um synthetic it's more
something that the engineering mind the constructing mind the the survival mind
uh kind of operates under and uh tends to have a a strong orientation towards
the contraction of tension of stress which uh in all kinds of ways becomes
the focal point or the organizing principle for our more attached ideas of
self of Me Myself and mind and sometimes the very feeling we have of amness I am
in a certain way uh is uh really the place where the subtlest little uh
tension pressure Gathering Together coagulation of um of of these kind of
muscles and tensions in the mind um are come together and it feels like it just
what is is just an amness I am but it's actually a manifestation of very subtle
or maybe not so subtle tension and that tension then gives rise
to emot that arises out of this kind of constructed part of the self the
survival part as that survival part is not needing to operate so much as we relax
all the tension we have it'll gives room for something else to arise that's
something that doesn't seem to be connected to self is not synthetic it's not uh an artifact of the mind's making
things up making ideas up of self others and Futures and pasts and all kinds of
things and so that I call the more naturalistic and part of this naturalistic movement within us is these
uh social care emotions these positive regard emotions and one of the really
wonderful pieces of modern Psychology was the lessons we many of us
learned from Carl Rogers who was an American psychologist who was uh taught
us the tremendous value of positive looking at people being with people with unconditional positive regard and uh he
did that in Psychotherapy while really listening careful to people people really felt listen to him because when
they spoke he would repeat back to them what they said maybe in slightly different words and the combination of
being listened to being heard hearing them their own ideas being spoken in a
little different way um and this positive regard who car people caring for them allowed something
to shift and change and it's if you can watch some of the probably on YouTube videos of Carl Rogers with his sessions
and watch how people transform I call it this natur again this naturalistic
transformation that can happen to people when we're listen to carefully when there's a kind regard for each for
ourselves when there's a kind of a presence that uh we get out of the way and allow people to be who they are to
be heard to be seen to be understood um uh uh without allowing
them to harm us or harm anyone just but but we step forward and hold what's
there in positive regard this is a remarkable thing and um
so here in the teachings from the um the uh UD suta the Buddha says to speak
grounded in kindness it's possible to do this to speak with
care to speak with positive regard and it doesn't have to be so certainly
shouldn't be saccharine it shouldn't be forced and but a lot of it comes from making
space um making room uh a wonderful American Theologian
talked about uh named Henry Nan talked about making um um uh empty friendly
space to receive the stranger so an empty space makes room
for people to be who they are but that space is friendly and and for him it's
the receive the stranger not just our friends and um so to speak grounded in
kindness um this is at least the Buddha's instruction for Buddhist teachers and um so so
uh may you on this day that
um it's it's good for every day to ground ourselves in kind kindness in
positive regard but there are times when it's really difficult and uh in some of those
difficult times it doesn't have to be difficult some of the
times um those those are the times when this practice of ours it comes really
alive don't succumb to despair don't disc succumb to
helplessness don't succumb to hostility and
anger rather see if you can find a positive
regard through which by which you can address the problems of
this world kindness is not a avoidance but it's a
means that carries with it a profound
message of respect and positive regard for everyone
even those people who are considered our enemies so um thank you very much and um
tomorrow will be the last uh in this series and and um I look forward to being back here