so uh so welcome folks nice to uh see the names streaming on the side
there um so one one announcement we I'll be
away and Retreat next week so we won't won't have class uh reather
22nd and um yeah I think there's enough Terra
flops or whatever it is of Dharma out there so uh we can make it a week and um yeah I was going to call the
class certain Wednesdays kind of like that it's a little too cute or something
but uh given that I'm very uncertain and that we'd be meeting on
certain Wednesdays but um it's just Wednesdays with Matthew that's what we ran with over at the uh shop and uh so
here we are and ready to uh to practice
together so um let's uh let's settle in
so part of why our breathing is
emphasized is that our breath doesn't depend on whatever we call me doesn't
depend on that
whatever feels like the headquarters of I
amness the locus of our willfulness the place where we must strive
from the house of uh our energetic
Vigor are glory and our shame all of
that the breathing doesn't depend on any of
it and so just to to
breathe e
and it can feel like well yeah the breath does itself but my
jobs to attend to it my jobs to point my attention at
it to not get distracted to be a good Yogi
but in the end the awareness doesn't depend on you
either you can't start it or stop it
so the eess breath being
received in the egoless awareness
emptiness knowing
emptiness
e
e e
trunk fore said we're stepping out of the bureaucracy of
ego the micromanagement of self
and we set aside a kind of special C category for self-rated
phenomena but
uh it's all made of the same stuff rising and
passing the openness of awareness the
effortlessness of
breathing
e
e e
when we're especially moving our body keeps its uh balance
with sense of
proprioception the ego almost has its
own system of apprpriate reception egoic proprioception keeping
tabs on
self keeping tabs on the egoic
balance so we just keep reiterating the sense of self keep
humming kind of song
myself image of our body arises and
Rises the thinking and subtle thinking
that create a sense of place within experience
when this flies beneath the radar of
awareness the existence of me it's
unquestioned but as we become sensitive to more and more of
these
phenomena the self no longer feels like a home
refuge and modes of awareness that taste less and less like me
come
online
e
e e
okay so uh that's good to good to say with
you um
so Dara practice is well maybe we
say it's about coming home and leaving
home it's about uh loving what we have
always loved and also learning to to love new
things uh the practice is a kind of um
sort of dialectic between incredible
coziness and uh venturing out into the world in order to be
startled so we come home to what we've
um what we've sort of long known long loved we come come home to what is
familiar maybe we've been uh neglecting what we know or what we
love but the Dharma when our heart is ripe and we
hear it it reawakens something and it has the flavor of of recollection Plato
said all knowledge is recollection it has that that feeling of like very familiar kind of
a home and uh even though I had a fortunate
childhood maybe maybe because I had that uh I was I was on to the first
Noble Truth you know early and
um and so when I actually heard it when I heard it spoken those words spoken my
heart just kind of lit up you know sense of recognition uh
recollection and as a teacher I I often have the sense that um I'm pointing to
some love in you that perhaps you've forgotten something that's dormant
something where I don't know it's like um I'm connecting some dots
or Reawakening something you you once had an intuitive sense
of and it feels like a kind of homecoming a lot of the Dharma feels
like the heart remembering itself returning to some ancestral ground Su say kind
of uh the kind of yeah I've always loved this
and that sense of homecoming of um of Refuge is so important because
we're also doing something new and so the path is is both about
loving what we've always loved and it's about learning to love new
things learning to love uh peace more than
pleasure space more more than stuff awareness more than
unconsciousness some of us have to learn dependency others have to learn
Independence but the Dharma kind of curriculum is perfectly tailored to the
way you suffer and it requires you to do
something new and today I read a um a story about
one of Freud's kind of most famous disciples um Alfred
Adler and uh at at at the first meeting Adler would often you know ask the
patient like what would you do if you were cured you know having the
assessment the kind of first consultation okay what would you do if you were
cured and the patient would answer and then he says
okay now go do that right that's kind
of uh compelling right compelling story but um the patient usually can't
do that it's more complex than just a decision and so when someone says you
know I want to practice more I want to meditate each day but
can't what they're really asking is like how do I love something
new and when someone asks how do I stop
um stop hating myself they're asking how do I love something new when we make New
Year's resolutions we're trying to Value
something new
uh but how does that happen you know if you've have you you know ever tried to
force yourself to fall in love
right I can't make you fall in love the path neither can you it's not a
kind of decision that you make what we value what we come to love
maybe we could say it grows through small gestures and we take small actions that
maybe seem insignificant small actions many times
small moments many times and maybe through that our uh our
love grows this is um
Agnes callard the philosopher she says
um uh we can all think back to a time when we were substantially different
people value Wise from the people we are now we care
about things we once did not care about how did this change come
about the transition from indifference to love cannot typically be affected by
way of doing any one thing no matter the strength of my will it
does not seem that I can muscle myself into suddenly carrying to be sure the path to valuing
something valuing something sometimes includes momentary expressions of
commitment the moment when you say I do sign the adoption papers or buy the
oneway plane ticket to a foreign country but these moments are themselves
only part of the story punctuating a longer process coming to Value something tends
to represent a deep change in how one sees and feels and thinks acquiring a
new value often Alters the structure of one's priorities by demoting or even dep
displacing something one valued before such changes take time over the
course of which one has done many things in service of value
appreciation the latter actions are shaped by the small changes that the earlier ones have engendered in such a
way as to allow someone to slowly develop new priorities concerns and
attachments the process as a whole is not structured by a single moment of
intention or decision at its
Inception um how do we come to love new
things we we make these small
gestures as we learn to love new things we sit
quietly or maybe we go to a group and practice with a SAA or we reflect
on goodness or we have just a a moment a conscious moment of
suffering we're awake to it and we plant seeds you know we want
to do so much more but but in coming to love new things we just plant seeds and
it doesn't seem like a big deal at all
but what does the Acorn know of the
Oak and so we in coming to love things
that are new we tolerate the the
disorientation you know we tolerate sense of not knowing we
tolerate the loss of one's old home this venturing out into the world to be
startled by newness
and in this way we begin to to live into
a Dharma life we begin to live into a Dharma life not something that happens
at once not something we chose at one moment and then just begin to
fulfill and then maybe at some point uh
there's a kind of moment and we look around we look
around and somehow we don't know even exactly when
but I've come to to uh to love this this is a new home
a new home somehow we don't know we it's very hard to track how the Dharma has
transfigured our life but it has at some point we wake up
to this and of course we we uh we keep
going we keep going we've
uh we're never done in coming to love new things we appreciate our home we venture
out so we uh rejoice in our home in order to uh to leave it
so uh offer this for your
consideration and uh yeah I wish you all a good couple
weeks and we'll um see you uh see you on the
22nd okay folks you uh you be well