so good morning everyone and or good day hello and
welcome to the Insight Meditation Center
virtually so I like to offer the theme for today's meditation to
be something fundamental to Buddhism and that is freedom or
Liberation and what we can learn about freedom in the mind or in the
heart maybe through meditation or through Buddhist practice uh has uh invaluable lessons to
offer us for how to live in our regular life and the world with the degree of
freedom and Liberation as well but we learn it here we learn it in our own
minds and to have a mind which is not free is to have a mind which is caught
in its preoccupations a mind which is caught up in fantasy and lost in its
thought and we bring the Mind back to the breath or to the moment and then
immediately the mind has a mind of its own and takes us away and we feel like we have no control no role no agency
with our own mind and there's two things that uh stand out to me when I think about the
freedom in the mind one is certainly to have mastered a degree of agency with
the mind where we can choose what we think about where we can direct our
attention and the mind will stay there we know have the skills we have the capacity we have the freedom to be able
to direct the Mind where we'd like it to be and so in meditation that's invaluable to direct the mind to the
present moment to the breathing to being focused Here and Now is profound L
meaningful and valuable and now but the other understanding of freedom because we
can't always have that level of agency and freedom in the mind is the freedom to be
aware of what's happening in the mind the freedom to know so it's kind of like there's an
over uh you know there's a kind of sense of of a indep dependent Observer
Observer or observation that goes on where yes what the Mind thinks about
what it's involved in maybe is not so much under our control but we feel free because we can
observe it we can know it as it's happening and because of that we're not
so caught in it we're not so invested in it uh as we are when all our mental
energy goes into it there's a really important part of ourselves which is um um not
fueling the the patterns of the mind but rather is fueling her capacity to
observe to know to see to kind of stand independent of what the mind's Oddities
are so two forms of freedom and both of those uh can give us a sense of agency a
s sense of um not being lost not being the victims
of whatever the mind brings up to us so Freedom so this that'll be the
reference point for this meditation two kinds of Freedom if you can do the first great if you can't then
the second is the is the place to discover
Freedom so to assume a meditation posture
and to give some care and time to
establishing adjusting the subtleties of the posture is an expression of freedom and
agency that we are engaged in the process of finding a way to meditate
with our posture that feels the best we have
given circumstances straightening maybe the
spine letting the chest be open adjusting where the hands are so
the elbows have can be relaxed and it
ease adjusting where the weight falls on your sitting bones
maybe so the belly can
relax and then to close your
eyes and with a sense of Freedom Choice
agency in your own way in a gentle supportive way take a few long slow deep breaths
where your choice your engagement in those breaths it's something you appreciate
you can do
enjoyable deep and full to the point just so it's
enjoyable and relaxing on the exhale
letting the breathing return to normal and maybe with the same appre
appreciation of your choice to do this more than your how well you can do
it as you exhale soften in your
face around the
eyes as you exhale soften in the
shoulders as you exhale soften the
belly breathing in a normal way
on the inhale feel whatever tension or contractions pressure there might be in
the thinking mind and as you
exhale soften the thinking
mind being less concerned about doing it successfully then with the pleasure or
Delight appreciation of being able to direct
your mind in in this into this effort to
soften and then on the inhale to feel what's happening in your heart
allow it to be as it is just feel it maybe appreciating the choice the
ability to feel more than what you
feel and then as you exhale to soften in the heart
again less interested in being successful as appreciating the
freedom to make the choice to attempt softening
and then with whatever ability you have even if it's for a
moment appreciate the freedom you have to now direct your
attention to the body's experience of breathing
feeling the inhale the
exhale and feeling how they're different from each other
appreciating whatever freedom and abil ability you have to stay with your breathing forever
long it might be and appreciate that as it
is and if you can't stay with the breathing appreciate your ability to
know and observe what it is that's happening
otherwise an observation that's not entangled or
reactive or if it is step back further and observe
that find the freedom in observing what's happening
rather than being entangled with what's
happening
for
for for
perhaps you can find some degree of fre Freedom or peace in the simplest ability to observe
what's happening or to know be aware of what's
Happening even if the ability to do so is ever so
short appreciate the ability to do so so you're not so caught up in what
you're aware of
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting is there any way that you can appreciate your own inner capacity for
freedom freedom from afflictions mental afflictions by being calm and
peaceful a freedom to be able to direct the mind
and the mind is directable direct the mind to back to
the present moment and the mind goes along however
brief or the freedom to Simply observe know be aware of what's
happening and to sense that awareness that knowing is not
entangled not caught in for
against and however the mild that senses of the mind's
Freedom appreciate it be nourished by
it and imagine how that freedom can have a beneficial
role for when you interact with other people conversations and seeing them
thinking about
them and perhaps your own mental
Freedom can create the space in the mind and the Heart
for Good Will to
arise basic Good Will towards others because the absence of Good
Will is a kind of closing down kind of losing of the freedom
and with whatever good will that you have kindness
friendliness to wish others well and perhaps you can choose
particular people that you have you know or more generally for groups of people
or all people as I say these words
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we with our freedom choice
contribute to this possibility however small our
contribution is May all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for [Music]
so welcome to this third talk on 10 Reflections for a Dharma life to live in
the Dharma in fact these uh 10 Reflections
can be called uh for living a spiritual life because there are reflections and
orientations for understanding people that are used by people who offer spiritual
counseling chaplaincy to others and um and I find them very
useful because they're really basic kind of to our Humanity so they don't know
out a purview of just Buddhism but in this context of teaching here I offer
them a little bit in the Buddhist context so uh for today and tomorrow the topic
is agency and autonomy and what I associate that with
the Positive coraly is a sense of freedom and
um and so uh when we are free to Enga to
have agency to engage and to act and to do and when we have sense of autonomy in
that activity that those actions um that comes with a sense of freedom
and capacity that uh if that's curtailed uh people suffer a lot people
are frustrated they feel oppressed they feel held in check they feel boxed in
they feel a sense of hopelessness and even helplessness but to uh give people to
allow people people discover a sense of agency that they can do they can make a
difference they can act and uh they're not held in check and this relates to
the to spiritual uh kind of needs that people
have human needs people have that we talked about Monday and Tuesday uh meaning and purpose that once
you have the real sense of what's important for you and uh the most important things most important values
most important intentions and important purpose the what you want to do how you
want to live your life then to have the ability to actually live that way and uh
and not be held in check by Inner forces in ourselves by our own uh fears our
resistance our hesitations our procrastination and not being held in
check by the world around us uh by the oppression that some people live in um
the oppression of war the oppression of racism M of poverty and um lack of
opportunities educational opportunities lack of work opportunities there all kinds of ways in which people feel like
they can't engage and um and so to discover a sense
of agency to be empowered to act and then in uh some schools of
Buddhism they actually do empowerment Ceremonies for people
and uh and we don't we don't do that in our tradition particularly but maybe
sometimes we should because people don't sometimes feel like they have the
ability the permission the capacity to engage in certain kinds of practices
certain kinds of ways of living this their life living from certain values and um and on their own they can't do it
but if you're given permission if someone believes in you if someone Champions you and there kind of support
you has your back as you do it um some people then feel oh now I can do it I can step into what's challenging and
Afraid for me and so to empower people to affirm people to encourage
people uh is for some people is in phenomenally useful and important and so for you uh as you
consider your own agency is that something that you feel like you're an a
agent of your own destiny that you have some choice and ability to act and um in
ways that are important for you that're invaluable for you uh that uh you feel
like it really would be an expression of being free to live the deepest values
that you have the deepest possibilities you have and um and so to understand where
do we have agency and where we don't where is realistic agency healthy a agency and where is uh kind of unhealthy
ideas of agency and ideas of agency that are caught up in greed and hatred and
wanting to act and and uh uh uh from these kind of very negative UNH
wholesome impulses and to feel like I want to be free just to be angry I want to be free just to um you know to get
whatever it is that I want um that is a certain kind of freedom
but at the cost of hurting other people that is a certain kind of freedom but it's only an external Freedom it's not
an internal freedom in fact if we're caught up in greed and hatred um
something inside of us has been frozen something inide of us has stopped is
covered over is lost the deepest kind of agency from the deepest place of
well-being the deepest places in our hearts and minds and to discover that
uh like through meditation to discover a place of deep abiding value a deep
abiding sense of reflection and intimacy and peace and wisdom and creativity that
just feels so good to have and then feel like that can flow out of us into what
we do that we don't we have no we we don't have inhibitions for what is
healthy within us to come forth we don't have inhibitions to speak what feels
true speak the truth if necessary but to do so without being caught in fear or
caught in hatred or in greed to to do it from a deep sense of inner
freedom and so agency in Buddhism has a lot to do with the inner Freedom that we
can have even when the world around us oppresses us uh which is unfortunate and
terrible and something that we should work to overcome um we can't always do it completely but
we can even in mid midst of the life's challenges and limitations it puts on us
because of illness and sickness and loss and all kinds of things it is still
possible to find agency with ourselves how to find our own Freedom our own
relationship with our experience our own freedom from the ways in which we dampen
ourselves down or limit ourselves or um Clos close up or get
contracted which we do when we're operating from greed hatred and excessive
anxiety and so to discover these deeper Wellsprings within and feel the freedom
for those to flow out of us in spite of the external limitations that somehow we
have to live in maybe we have no choice sometimes uh to live certain ways um I
don't know if this is a appropriate example of this but uh certainly um I
became a parent a little bit late in life and um and I was surprised that
after being living for years and monasteries where there was a lot of limitations um that parenting with for
young children was phenomenally Li phenomenally limiting and um on sleep
and selfcare and all kinds of things just taking care of the babies and all this and um and so I mean I was a
limitation I had to live with I had to take care of these children and um at the expense of being free to do all
kinds of other things I was used to doing in my life but even there this was invaluable for me to Grapple with this
because there I could find work through these layers inside to find that deeper
place of Freedom where agency had returned turned agency to be free in the
midst of limitations agency to engage choiceful and wisely with life as it's
given to me as opposed to how I wanted it to be and to be different so to um so to really look
deeply into this question of maybe in the wake of reflecting on meaning and
purpose um what is your sense of agency do you feel like you have agency in your life where do you feel like you don't
have it where are you held in check and where you're limited and where where can you find it
where can you find um an an empowerment maybe a
self-empowerment so you're not held in check you're not held in resistance you're not held in
procrastinations that you can step forward and uh let Set something
free but not something free that is crazy that's going to harm other people
or even harm yourself because we do have Oddities in our minds and hearts about
our desires and our wishes and our fantasies and delusions about what goes on what is it that's reliable what's the
reliable source of agency within that uh allows us to feel free creative
intelligent wise um and one of the characteristics of that is it has a profound sense of
peace peace as part of it and a pro profound sense of Good Will and respect
that comes from this deep Wellspring where the spiritual Freedom lives within
us so um um so agency and that's the if you're
inclined at all that's the theme for reflection for these next 25 4 hours um
how does that work for you uh is another word that you would rather use an agency
that maybe speaks to this what I'm talking about today better than
agency um maybe simply the phrase freedom to act freedom to live from our
deepest values but maybe you have a different phrase that is useful for you to reflect on this and where do you not
have a sense of agency where do you feel in check where do where would it be useful for you to discover um greater
freedom and agency to be empowered to be self-empowered or to have someone who
believes in you um reflect back to you yes you can do this it's
okay and um and uh so agency so thank you and tomorrow
I'll talk about autonomy which uh also then ra raises this interesting uh question of um
doesn't some of these teachings of meaning purpose and an a an agency uh rub a little bit
wrong against the Buddhist teachings of um not self the idea of autonomy isn't
that little bit opposed to those teachings and I would like to say not but that will sa for
tomorrow so thank you very much and um May you have
a day of uh discovering greater freedom for how you can live your life