right so this week we are touching into
various wholesome qualities during the meditations just as a way of flavoring
the sit and allowing these things to register in our system and then we go on
and do our usual meditation but maybe noticing the way evoking that quality
has some effect on the way to it goes at least that's the hope as we
explore this this week and today's quality that we'll be evoking is uh
Clarity so with that let's settle in for sitting finding a comfortable and
upright or at least straight posture and it's okay if you're sitting
or lying down you could also try standing or walking softly back and
forth those are all fine postures for meditation and just allowing the
attention to come inward closing the
eyes finding some sense of
centeredness in the body in the mind I find it helpful to bring bring
attention briefly to the contact points where I'm sitting so my seat against the
cushion you may be on something else legs or feet against the
floor usually there's at least three contact points and those are that's a very
stable setting so to feel that the tripod of stability wherever you're
sitting or lying and just having that feeling of
groundedness or support and allowing yourself to be
supported and as we have this connection to the body through feeling
resting points perhaps also bringing in a sense
of bodily presence so your body is in a particular
place you're sitting here in this room or maybe you're
outside but you're in this particular spot you're surrounded by some space
perhaps perhaps you're in a room or some
location and it's fine to sense that as the specific
conditions of today you're
here feeling that presence
and then in the mind bringing up bringing to the four as they say in the
sutas the quality of mindfulness so that's not any meant to
be anything big that you have to generate effort for it's as simple
as if I tell you to direct your attention to your right hand see how easy it is for it to go
there so evoke mindfulness know that you're here very simple very
light and then allow that quality to remain in your awareness for for a
bit a this is what it's like to have mindfulness at this moment
mindfulness is not just one thing it's not always the
same so a further question is how is your mindfulness right
now sometimes mindfulness feels
precise sometimes it feels large and spacious
sometimes it feels soft and [Music] warm can have different character at
different times so how is it for you right
now and now further refining our
sense we can notice specifically the quality of clarity that naturally
accompanies mindfulness if we become mindful after
some period of not being so mindful it can feel like we're looking
outside through an open window pane compared to having a window there it's
it's like the window is opened and we see directly through the window
space there's a awareness will have that extra vibrancy or sharpness to it when
mindfulness is present compared to just ordinary Consciousness and
attention so seeing if you can notice that extra Clarity that comes when we know
that we know when we have have this additional quality of mindfulness compared to just the going through the
day we are paying attention to something because we're awake and conscious but
mindfulness is a little different isn't
it so that isn't meant to Tire a tie us up in anything complex it was just a
pointing now turning to the the breath or the body
sensing normal meditation object and allowing yourself to
rest the flow of the say the breath
Sensations having the sense that you know that you're meditating
time to time register the clarity of the
mind at a given
moment just allowing yourself to appreciate
that direct knowing of things as if we were seeing them with no medium
not even glass between us and them and continuing on like
this
e
e e
sensing in to the quality of clarity that is possible in the
mind maybe the act of checking helps bring up a bit more of
it without appreciating this potential of the mind to just have a
clear recognition in the moment
and it might be that experience feels unclear when you
check and we might immediately assume that the mind was dull and that
may be the case there is that certainly happens during meditation
um but there's another possibility which is that sometimes we
have a clear knowing in the mind of an object that is somewhat
vague and do you know how to distinguish those in your
practice so a mirror can have can be clear and
direct or it can have fog on it if it's in the shower bathroom and you've had a
shower now that foggy mirror does not reflect an object very well looks
blurry that's what we think but it's actually perfectly reflecting the
multitude of water droplets that are stuck on it that's what they look like
so it's worth checking if we have a dull mind or if we can have a clear knowing
of a vague object because that does happen in
sitting that can be something interesting to check out around this quality of
clarity
e
e e
so you're invited to let it register and
appreciate that our mind can have this quality of
clarity even if it's just from time to time the
special heightened noticing that the human mind is capable
of is a true
gift something that can be directed in ways that are so beneficial far beyond
what we can
know so resting in this quality of
clarity of clear seeing that we already have and can
continue to
develop
e
e e
and as we will soon be going forward from the time of
[Music] meditation we can consider that this
quality of clarity brings multiple benefits into
our life our daily life and also to others one of the biggest ones is that
it's a protection so by having a clear sense of
what's happening and how we're entering into situations we're much less likely
to to say something or do something mindless that we regret
later you know there's not a 100% protection from that in the in our mind
but this Clarity really helps and I'm sure some of you have already seen that
so we can have confidence in just bringing up mindfulness this clear
seeing you know that will we remember to be kind and
to stay in line with our values for example and that protects others also
from our any any slips we might be making and then a little bit more
proactively clarity can bring us understandings that are so useful like
we could suddenly realize oh I hadn't noticed that this person uh
is nervous this person talking to me you know I had thought they were just being kind of irritating but now I can see
through that to the fact that they're actually really scared in this moment oh and so that can change how we interact
with them for example that we might not have allowed ourselves to see if we hadn't been willing to bring in that
extra Clarity so there's a way in which we're protected and also a way in which we can
proactive notice things and then act from that new knowledge and it's a refinement we may
not have seen everything yet but if we're willing to keep seeing with Clarity more and more will be
revealed so having confidence in this mindfulness that we're cultivating as we
go forward and wishing that all beings can benefit
in some way from our on ongoing awareness and Clarity of
Mind may all beings be happy
peaceful and may they come to see more and more in their lives and may we in
some way help that through our practice
so we'll continue on this week with our exploration of the attributes or
epithets of the Buddha and I've decided to be more precise and say that there are 10 of
them to imprint that into your memory there are 10 budha gunas um only nine technically in the
formal recollection that's done not to leave you hanging by the way uh the extra one is tagata which um some I'm
sure many of you have heard as a name for the Buddha it's actually traditionally the first one and then
there are these other nine for some reason the tataga is not part is not included in the reflection maybe we'll
touch on it on Friday seems to fit in there but don't worry about it if you
contemplate nine or 10 qualities it's equally good so the 10 the 10 Buddha
gunas and today is the day when we'll uh talk about just one of them
uh the fifth we've already done the first four and the fifth quality of the
Buddha's awakened mind is said to be loca vdu loca vdu uh Loca is the world
and Vu is has to do with seeing so it's usually called nowh of the world
translated as nowhere of the world or we could even say nowh of the Worlds the
word is not plural but um there's a lot of different worlds that we'll talk
through that the the Buddha has clear knowledge of clear seeing and this quality I remember I
said at the beginning the order of these um traits or epithets is not arbitrary
they do have kind of a sequence so we've talked about how the Buddha's mind is
completely wholesome free of grief hatred and delusion and that he's able to manifest that understanding through
Clarity and um accomplishment is what it says in knowledge and conduct in how he
is in world so he manifests that in his way of being and then also that that the
result of that is that he is always happy uh he's never separated from the
peace and happiness is almost to light of a
word of nibana and but nonetheless nothing can shake his mind things that
happen he's able to just flow with those be with them in a Wholesome Way all the
craziness of the world that the Buddha emerged back into after his Awakening uh
it couldn't throw his mind off so that was sugat the happiness of the
Buddha and then what emerges from that is that he can see very clear l so his
mind is not thrown off by things it's not colored by carrying a lot of fixed views and it's not reactive about what's
going on whenever he turns his mind toward what he's seeing he can know
clearly what that's about and this is a beautiful quality so
uh his own pure mind excellent conduct and inner peace allow him to look with
clear eyes at the world and he decided to do that he decided to under really
understand um what's going on here we can consider this for ourselves too is
that you know many of us have some interest in understanding the mind the body how psychology works how
relationships work how is this world you what's going on in this world that we got born into somehow so the um maybe by
understanding this list we can understand that it's a good idea to practice and find
some measure of happiness and uh Good Conduct in ourselves and inner peace in
order to really know what's going on in the world not to trust our assumptions
based on a reactive mind and similarly if we have some idea that we want to help the world we we might want to do
some practice first and really get ourselves grounded so that we can see clearly and know how to help so this
quality is where the Buddha looks out and gets it so that he knows what to do
that'll come later so what are the worlds quote unquote that the Buddha could see could
know in the broadest sense what he looked at was natural laws in nature he
saw that the universe is not random in how it is unfolding
um there's a a wonderful idea actually from Western philosophy of um Cosmos and
Chaos I don't know if you've heard that pair there was a wonderful TV show in the 70s called Cosmos with Carl Sean and
um uh essentially chaos we know what that is right Randomness disorder of
various kinds and it can feel like that in the mind when things are not organized or clear
but Cosmos is kind of the the idea that the Universe has organizing principles
behind it there is a wholeness going on here and if we if we're not clear then
we see chaos but there is behind it a cosmos A sense of unity of wholeness so
the Buddha could see that he could know the dhma the word dhama the biggest sense of
it is the lawfulness of what's going on most comprehensively is teaching that
lawfulness who was the law of dependent arising so understanding the causes and
conditions are what bring about basically everything um sometimes they're going in a wholesome Direction
and we're building a path sometimes the causes and conditions are creating samsara the wandering on of more and
more suffering because we're not seeing clearly but um you know for us we get
little glimpses of how conditions come together and we suddenly have insights into how things work but imagine that a
mind that could comprehend all of that to be clear the Buddha wasn't omnicient he didn't see all of that all the time U
he still had a human mind but anytime he directed his mind toward understanding a
certain aspect of life he could I think it's important to say that he's not
considered omniscient in the early teachings um there's a suta that says um
whether or not there is an arising of tagas of Buddhas there is this
regularity of the dhama he goes on to say more about that but essentially says that the lawfulness
of the universe is independent of whether or not there's a Buddha to know it so that's a pretty profound statement
you know there is there is a lawfulness here and luckily for us there are people
who arise from time to time who are able to see it and that's the case for a Buddha for
example so this is I I find this tremendously um comforting in some way
supportive to know that in the background and the degree to which I can just barely Glimpse pieces of it in my
practice I find very nourishing and uh is a form of Refuge for me and I hope
maybe you can touch into that also it's kind of an idea that's evoked from this local of you do knower of the
world so other things to say about this knowing is that um the Buddha didn't
know only you know when we talk about lawfulness in our Western some of you
are Western uh understanding there's a kind of a sense of going to physics or
biology you know the physical the understanding of the physical world the law of gravity the law of Electro
magnetism the laws of chemistry that are flowing in our bodies and those are all true those are all they're even named in
the commentaries as things that the Buddha knows um but in addition the the Buddha knew the how the mind works of
course that's really the key for understanding suffering um I started out my own
training in physics due to a love of Nature and at some point I realized that
as beautiful and wonderful as was and inspiring really uh it didn't address my
deepest questions about Dua and uh that was something I had to sort of
articulate later and then I could expand into deeper understandings so we have
also understandings of the psychological world how the mind functions you the mental world and maybe most importantly
the Buddha understands how Karma functions so how intentional actions that are done by beings who can inform
form intentions how that unfolds into uh greater suffering or a path toward peace
and um this is the understanding again of the lawfulness of the dhamma um in the sutas the world Loca
literally says is defined as the six sense spheres and their objects so it
says you know the the eye and seeing the eye and forms the ear and sounds no and
sense the tongue and tastes the body and tangible things and the mind and mental
objects that is the world that is it for us that's what we can
experience and to understand how all of that works how it's interrelated how the
mind arises together with an object all of this is um and of what the you know
the realm of what the Buddha could understand and you can imagine oh yeah that you would need to know all of that
in order to not have any suffering in mind so none of that was outside of what
of what you could know and therefore you couldn't be fooled by any of
that so then we can say more specifically what the Buddha knew is how suffering works and that was what you
know he maybe he knew the whole six sense speres but what he taught was then this handful of leaves here's how this
leads to your entanglement and here's how it it cannot this is is where it starts getting practical into what how
we can apply this particular quality of the Buddha
so um one thing that we do in our minds you may have noticed is create worlds we
create views of things we create our understanding of oh this is what's going
on or this is how I am or this is how the world is or should be and then we
act from that view from that picture that orientation and one very important thing
to start understanding in practice is how those views come together they're
not actually absolute truths and they're not um random they're created out of
conditions partial understandings that we have conditions of the moment physical and mental feelings that we
have are are very important in forming our views so we can observe this
one thing that we can do in meditation um is we can sit and watch the mind
let's say we're being mindful the flow of experience Sensations in the body and
mind are arising we're noticing them I have seen at times the Mind start to
move toward having a thought or having a view you know like for example a a pain
arises in my back and the thought comes oh maybe maybe that's because of all
that hiking I did yesterday and I can feel my mind starting to form a picture
like oh maybe the amount of hiking I did should be set in my mind as the limit I
shouldn't hike more than that many miles because otherwise my back is going to hurt you know we we're creating suddenly
an understanding a world out of what a pain a feeling but just one sensation in
the back starts forming this world view and we can see it like a little bubble
uh kind of getting coming into creation and usually what we do is we say great I'm going into that and we we jump in
and we become the person in that world the person who's going to decide I can't hike more than x miles or kilometers
because my back's going to hurt and I don't want to hurt my back and we become that and it's great it feels comfortable
we get to be that person but what if we hadn't gone into that bubble we just saw
it as oh there's a thought arising tempting to go in and do that but I'm not going to go do that wait for the
next moment to arise stay with mindfulness stay with the present moment so the knower of the worlds is someone
who knows when a world is coming into being and decides no thank you I'm not
going to jump into that world or um you know I'm just going to see it as one
more formation and let that bubble go on in daily life we can observe the same
thing it's not as clear as it is during the flow in our meditation or we have a lot of
mindfulness but uh we can also observe that we're living in certain stories or
we can sometimes observe other people have views about things like our friend
comes and talks to us about I have this problem this and that is happening and we can see very clearly oh it's all
because they believe such and such and if they didn't believe that they wouldn't be making this into something
that they're so anxious about and you know then there's a question about how we say that or don't depending on our
relationship with the person and we may not be right in our perception but
nonetheless um I want to suggest that this idea of observing the views the
worlds that we create with our stories is one very important way to avoid
falling into suffering and avoid falling falling into the enactment of so many of the selves that we think ourselves to be
so um this is really worth seeing maybe
I'll just give one more little example um which is that I one time went to both
a western doctor and an acupuncturist for the same physical issue that I was
having the same problem with my body and it was a totally different World in each
case right the tests that they do the questions that they ask the views that
they bring in to decide how you might be helped with this particular problem it
was like it was two different worlds and they could not they almost didn't overlap and it was great I actually
benefited from both of them but I could see so clearly that each person that I
spoke with was acting within a realm of understanding understanding it was limiting and describing defining what
they would see and what they would put their attention in and it's so interesting to see that in others and
have kind of a sense about it much harder to see it in ourselves but it's operating in the same way so this seeing
of the worlds is so important for understanding our suffering and then
bringing it back to the Buddha here at the end it's also a big part of the Buddha's ability to teach the ability to
guide people out of their suffering so this is a transitional quality the Loca
Vu is a transition from qualities of the Buddha's own awakened mind that he experienced internally then he sees the
worlds and how they work and then there's a way in which he can act from
that uh to help the rest of us and that's what we'll talk about tomorrow so
thank you all