welcome welcome everybody can we turn down the volume just a tiny bit so I
don't have to feel like I'm whispering let's see is this better if I
if I'm speaking in my regular voice oh maybe that's a little bit too low I'm sorry Jim this is hard to here we go
okay great thank
you so tonight I'd like to continue on the topic of question
that I introduced last week this idea of questioning as a part of
practice I want to expand on that a little bit and talk about how questioning is actually you know in some
ways we can consider it an expression of Freedom right to
ask is you know a a sign that we're not
locked in or stuck or um somehow not
even realizing that there could be an alternative or if maybe we are in a
situation where we're just not allowed to ask questions whatever kind of situation that might be people in power
sometimes like this nope don't ask any questions this is the way it
is maybe our parents say something like because I said said
so just as the you know rationality you don't get to really ask but
why because I said so and that's enough yeah so this even this whole
notion of be able to ask questions about anything or
everything is this uh maybe it's an assertion of a certain amount of Freedom
certainly we don't think about that often we think that we're asking questions just because we want to know
the answer but what if we start to think
about it as an expression of freedom and that this path of course is
leading to greater and greater Freedom greater and greater peace and
ease and well-being and it's not like there's no Freedom no Freedom no Freedom then bam
there's Freedom right it's just there's the All Along The Path all along the path is what's near is at the end
there's more and more well-being there's more and more peace there's more and more
freedom as we walk on this path or practice in this
way so naturally there's more and more questions
too and so we can ask big questions sometimes even the fact that
there's big questions is a a sign of Freedom too instead of just the minor ones
uh do the knives go into this drawer or the other drawer you know that's just a
minor one but what if we ask questions like what is it that opens the heart and
mind what opens my heart what opens my
mind recognizing that greater Freedom comes from like letting go kind of like this opening is this letting out
whatever's in there no longer really holding on to and for us to find for ourselves part
of this path is every single one of us will have our own flavor our own take is
not exactly the same for every person that's part of what Freedom
means each of us will show up wherever we are in our lives bringing whatever we
have with us and so we can ask what is it that opens
the heart and mind this is a worthwhile
question for each of us maybe it's obvious maybe it's not
obvious maybe we could ask the opposite what closes the heart what closes the
mind what is it that creates the conditions in which we kind of like close our heart Hearts maybe we feel
hurt maybe we feel threatened feel unsafe in some kind of
way or maybe we feel just have a feeling of uh we want
to make ourselves feel better so we're going to put somebody else down kind of make that we have the
superiority that's a way that kind of closes our hearts and mind
another question we might ask is can we live from Love and
wisdom can we have love and wisdom be foundations be a support for our
life however we understand love and wisdom for each of us be a little bit
different and I'm sure if I were to ask you a few decades ago what does love
mean what does wisdom mean you probably would have a different answer than you have today so this is something that uh
like you know shifts as we mature as we have more life experiences and it's
really as we practice more too this whole idea of what is love and
wisdom but this question is can we live from Love and
wisdom can we have that animate our life can we have love and wisdom be ways
that are like a North star that helps Orient us and the way we respond to what
life is bringing us because so often we see around us all
the roots of fear or confusion or greed or hostility we see all
that and we also see the suffering that that brings the suffering for ourselves
the suffering for others it's that's just everywhere you just open up a
newspaper just look at your phone it's filled with that kind of stuff that's
what the media companies want you to really get anxious about so that you'll
do more clicking but maybe what about the roots
of love how deep are they how do we
understand that can we tap into them can we trust
them how do we know if we can trust them this roots of
Love whatever they are like for different as I keep on saying this but I
think all of us will have like a little bit different idea what are the roots of love and maybe it's not so clear
again maybe we can find it by thinking about the opposite well what's the roots of hatred the opposite of love and we
can think about okay hatred often comes from
Fear comes from feeling threatened so roots of Love is this
sense of settledness this and sense of um
softness maybe and then I'm up here talking about
you know questioning as part of freedom but you could even ask for yourself well what does freedom mean what does it mean
for you what is freedom mean for you I'll just say earlier in my life
Freedom certainly meant the the capacity to do is I damn well pleased that was
what Freedom was you know kind of like an Inc Ed like just do whatever I want
whenever I want and I kind of like organized my life around that you know trying to be able to do whatever I
want but now I would say you know Freedom means something a little bit different not a little bit different
very different now freedom is more this sense of not being pushed around by what life
brings me not feeling like like oh I have to avoid that and I have to avoid this person cuz I don't want to tell
them or I don't want them to tell me about this uh or I don't want to you
know look at that thing because it'll make me upset instead freedom is having
the capacity to okay if it hurts my feelings it hurts my feelings it's not
the end of the world if it's sad what I hear it's
sad it doesn't have to be a huge problem it doesn't have to be something that I
or other people have to go way out of their way to
avoid so freedom is this you know being able to stand up for what we believe in
or what we think is helpful for ourselves and for others taking everybody into
account and being willing to do that without having to always be
[Music] guarding what's coming guarding ourselves or protecting ourselves from
what may come as a response I'm not going to say that I'm completely immune
from you know what other people say and do I'm not but I am much more than I
used to be let's say that just this much more sense of steadiness and this sense of being able to feel grounded and
connected and standing upright like okay yeah I'm here and I'm not going to get
pushed around as much and I like this capacity to open my
heart to so many things that before would have made me feel uncomfortable and felt like oh I have to
avoid situations I've never been in there before uh it makes me uncomfortable oh that person's really
different than me no instead now like okay I think let's see what let's see
what it's like I can hold this and if it's painful I I can hold that too
so we might sometimes in this uh practice we have these questions um less
so in this particular lineage but uh it's um it's definitely in there and I
have had uh dma teachers give me this kind of like instruction like pointing
me this particular direction at a certain place in practice so there can be this question
of uh who am I and then when you first ask that there's
all the obvious stuff that happens well then you just ask again and again and again and again and again and
again and then it starts to be a little bit
slippery who am I or sometimes something like this or what is
this and again the I I'm saying again because I talked about this last week
the purpose of questioning is not so much that we absolutely find the
answers isn't like a quiz or an exam or something like that it's more for us to
just adopt a stance an attitude of openness and
listening as opposed to you know when you feel like you have all the answers it doesn't matter what anybody else says
you feel like you have the answers you're not going to listen to what anybody else says when you know the
truth but this idea of questioning so what is
this as a question is can be a part of a practice can be like dropped in usually
during uh when after the mind has uh settled some bit some people do it as
part of their daily life just throughout their day just dropping in this question what is
this and kind of like feeling their way into the answer
like leading with the heart what is this and then the having the heart answer instead of the mind if that make sense
it's a different way than if you were taking an exam nobody's going to be grading you
this it's just an
exploration so we kind when we find ourselves lost in this story that we're
telling about somebody else or about ourselves I'm a great person because XYZ
I'm a terrible person because of ABC that person's great or terrible because of lement
op we can if we remember we could ask who is it that's telling these stories
and there's a way kind of like who is it you kind of like looking behind like who's telling these
stories and see if it's you can find the Storyteller
so these questions can be a way this um in our practice as a this
inquiry into is there a this Gore self
this Essence that's at the center of everything making it happen and telling
the stories asking the questions is there and you can just
investigate it can be a really fruit
practice and as I mentioned last week this idea of
Investigation is the second factor of the seven factors of Awakening so it's
definitely part of this path it's not just some that you do on the
side it's definitely a part of this movement towards greater
Awakening it's also an antidote to doubt if you feel like yourself hesitating or
vacillating like I'm not sure I don't know I don't know about this practice I don't know about this
teacher I don't know about these teachings what what who is this Buddha
person investigate ask
questions read dramaa books listen to Dharma talks ask teachers ask other
people who have a practice or ask people who don't have a
practice but also there's a way that this this the
activity of asking is maybe it's such an integral part of practice even if we
don't say it explicitly because this practice is asking us to adopt an
attitude of listening adopt an attitude or a stance
maybe of openness and receptivity and that's a big part of
what questioning is about is just being open to hearing something
new being open to being surprised open to learning something open to realize
Oh I thought it was that way but maybe it's not
I thought I was I was always sad I've been feeling
sad for months now I'm trying to meditate so that I'll feel better
perfectly legitimate way to or a reason to meditate but you might discover with
meditation maybe there's lots of moments that are perfectly neutral there's no
sadness it's just neutral or maybe you even find that
there's little moments of happiness or Joy or senses of well-being or
contentment and then you start to realize oh yeah I'm sad a lot but
there's also these moments of happiness or Clarity or ease or whatever it might
be and then we slowly start to rewrite kind of like our narratives oh yeah
instead of I'm always sad can be like oh yeah sadness arises a lot maybe that's
very different than saying I'm always sad it's such a different feeling instead of like identifying and
saying this is sadness is something that's always uh present for me we can
say yep sadness is present sometimes sometimes it's perfectly
neutral and maybe even boring
and so when we sit to meditate it isn't so much that we're trying to make
something happen we're not trying to have some particular
experience we can't make those happen all of us I think have tried I certainly
tried I didn't quite understand meditation in the beginning and I thought like okay something you know
fantastic is supposed to happen and then I just was kind of like huffing and puffing and straining and I just made
myself really tight and tense and didn't like meditating
anymore so it's not so much that we're trying to make anything happen instead that we're trying to listen or to what's
happening here in this body and mind what's this
experience being open to it being receptive to it noticing it in the same
way that's like uh asking a question and so when we're meditating
we're have this maybe this receptivity as opposed to this idea that we're just
trying to confirm something that we already know and there can be a way when we meditate we just feel like we just
have to check the box okay I meditated today and there can be a subtle way in
which we are like okay I know it's like this at the beginning of the sit and
then maybe after 10 minutes the Mind settles down it's like this okay
done but instead we maybe this kind of like this attitude like well what is
this what is going on is this is a way forward with
practice a meditation practice and there is this way that
um you know all these practices and this teachings are offered with this uh
invitation to like see if this matches your own experience as opposed to saying
like Okay this is how it is and you have to believe it and and go off and believe it instead
there's a real invitation okay is this is this true for you does this make sense for
you and uh some of you may be familiar with this expression easo which uh translates as come and
see so it's not like a go and believe it's more like a come and see is it is
it this for you does this make sense for
you and so there was a it is a number of years ago when I had to
um log into an account for something had to do with a IMC and this account was
shared by a few people and uh when they we were all sharing
this account and when they uh gave me the password the password was eh Paso
and I thought oh yes this is like such a great uh way like not only this come and
see but it also showed how important this was for the person who set up this
account you like this this basic tenant of an invitation
to welcome what's uh what's arising and maybe bringing some curiosity to it
rather than this idea that we know it already and so in this way we might even
understand that to see for ourselves that is to come and
seeo is the Dara is the
Dharma there's this way we kind of think like okay the Dharma is out there there are some of these teachings they're
written down in this poly Canon and you know all this stuff that we can have
about it but the Dharma and maybe there's one way we could understand the Dharma that way is
the teachings of the Buddha but really the Dharma is only exists when human
beings are interacting with it or expressing
it if it's not some abstract thing that just uh exists independent out there as
much as it's something that when we are walking the
path that's the Dharma and this gets pointed to in the
suit does in fact when the um Dharma is described as visible Here and
Now immediate inviting to be seen for
oneself onward leading and to be personally
realized by the wise it's a definition of the Dharma
that we find Visible Here and Now immediate so immediate like something
that we can experience tangible I mean maybe it's tangible like
this or maybe it's an experience we have in our mind or heart but an inviting to
be seen for oneself and onward leading I love this this is
kind of like you know invites all of us will have a little bit different or maybe really different expression of it
or experience of it something that uh we each discover as
we kind like move along this path towards greater and greater Freedom so then we might ask okay Diana
if this uh questioning is an expression of Freedom you might say but I don't
feel very free or you might say I don't ask questions so we could ask what blocks
questions like what gets in the way of questioning and one is this inner critic
that can arise that it can really like show up and then when the inner critic is um
active and being believed it's asking questions but it's not questions that
are helpful instead there's this uh question is like am I getting this right there's
this real concern like this feeling like oh whatever I'm doing is wrong and am I
getting this right it's there's one way we could ask that question like I'm not sure if this
is um the way forward but there when it's kind of like being asked again and again underneath that is the sense of if
I'm doing it it must be wrong so this question am I doing this right or there might be this inner
critic might be saying something like well who am I to question like surely you know everybody
knows better than I do like I'm who am I to question I don't know enough or I
haven't practiced enough who am I to question and then that kind of like
implicit in that is the sense of comparing ourselves to others and have the sense like well maybe somebody else
has the right to question but I don't and that's just the inner
critic that's just to Inner critic this uh aspect of our experience that shows
up on occasion and likes to kind of like squash us or make us feel inadequate in
some kind of way we don't have to believe it we do give it Authority but
we don't have to believe it and that is a whole practice in it self how to work with the inner critic but it does Black
Block our questioning it does kind of like get in
the way and make us feel like no I can't question can't question the teachings
can't question my experience I even can't question the questioner who is
this what is this there's another reason why like
there what kind what can get in the way of questioning what can block questioning is that in some ways our
culture or Society doesn't really support it in some ways in America we
like to think that okay we're fiercely independent and we are all about
freedom and we have this sense we have a real pioneering Spirit we're going to like go and discover new things that's
all true and there's a way in which there's
also we clearly get the message don't question the media often wants to have
this like okay let us tell you how it is it's like this this and
this I don't want to demonize the media but some of it is you know has that has
that sense of like okay you know we're just going to tell you what you need to know and you if you don't know what it
is if you if you have questions you don't need to know the answers to those questions just listen to us we'll tell
you and please pay more or there's leaders who don't want
us to question leaders of Institutions you know whatever institution you want
to think of especially you know the really large institutions there's often the leaders don't want us to question so
there's this way in which our society kind of like really promotes the sense
of passivity promotes this sense of kind of like let's just consume
information and not question it let's consume the stuff let it affect us let
it impact us and not question it which isn't
healthy all of us needs to you know bring some of our own
um sense of what's appropriate and our own sense of what
is right and wrong and these types of things I'm not saying that we can't
believe anything of course not some things we have to take on faith we have
if people that we trust or say this or something like that but there are some things that we
should question if something's like wait that doesn't make sense then maybe there's this uh piece
of the story that we don't have or if there's a sense of like well if somebody
says oh um the reason why you don't understand it is because this institution over there they don't want
you to understand well these people here I don't want you to understand they're
just blaming it on somebody else or something like
this and so another reason why maybe we don't um block our like what blocks our
questioning or what blocks our questions is we like to have
answers it feels comforting like okay I know the answer I understand
this this makes sense to me I don't have to worry about it I got
it there's a certain amount of comfort in that and it's 100% appropriate to do that with some things and for other
things to question and that's part of the art of practice and I would say that's the art of you know having a rich
Life Is Knowing okay which things to question and which things not to question
because the truth is I mean we don't know the future we don't I mean we know
the likelihood that certain things will happen but we don't know exactly the future that's going to
happen and so there's this story that uh in the suas about this person
Malia and uh he goes up to the Buddha and he says I'm I'm going to disrobe unless you answer my
questions and he um he said and and you unless you
answer my metaphysical questions including the questions of what happens after a person
dies and the budha said I never promised that I was going to answer all your
questions why are you threatening me that you're going to disrobe I didn't promise you that all your questions would be
answered and so the he the Buddha kind of says okay disrobe if you want you know I I'm not going to answer all your
questions and specifically he didn't answer some of Malia's metaphysical
questions including like what happens after a person dies and the budha said that uh he
didn't want to answer them because it wouldn't be beneficial it wouldn't uh
lead to peace or Insight or Awakening just to know what happens after a person dies
it's so way that like then that person would just kind of like be passively accepting information and there's no way
to know whether what the Buddha said would be true or not like what there's no way
to put an end to questioning because then what was happen if somebody's if the Buddha were to say
well this is precisely what happens after you die like well how does the Buddha
no well cuz that's different than what somebody else said over here so it doesn't put an end to the
questioning and so then uh the Buddha gave a simil to malapa
saying a person is uh injured by an arrow they get shot by an arrow and then
the uh other people see this and they go and call a doctor and the doctor comes and they're going to remove the arrow
from this person and then the person who is I imagine in
tremendous pain says no no no wait before you remove the arrow I'd like to know who
shot the arrow where do they live what is their
name and then and about the arrow what type of Arrow Head does it have is it
made out of rock or is it made out of stone or to ask what kind of feather is
on the Arrow is it from this this type of bird or that type of bird and the shaft of their arrow is it you know it
goes on and on all these ridiculous questions meanwhile he has an arrow sticking in him and he's bleeding and
he's in terrible pain and so the Buddha is pointing to
saying they we that if we are busy like asking these types of questions there's
no end to some of these metaphysical things and instead we're still suffer
suffering while we're kind of asking these questions that aren't going to lead to the ending of
suffering so can we put our questions to a way that's going to lead to mors freedom I mean to ask a question is
freedom but can the type of questions we ask lead to even greater and greater
Freedom so what are some questions that we can ask
what is it that's being clung to if we're experiencing discomfort
dissatisfaction suffering Duca whether it's really mild or
really is terrible we can ask what is it that's
being clung to what am I clinging to what's being held on
to and so this requires there's a distinction between like there's the pain of what life brings you then arrow
for example but then there's often what the Mind adds on top of it oh I have to
figure all these things out about the arrow or just wait until um I'm Healed again I
got to go and get revenge on this person or whatever it might
be all the story making that we do that perpetuates or and amplifies the
discomfort those stories are revolved around a certain amount of clinging clinging to ideas clinging to
views going into like what uh ourselves like how we should be treated or how we
should not be treated I'm not saying that these things are not important they
are but is there a way that we can notice how we're clinging to some things
that just bring more suffering that's a question we can ask ask ourselves what is it that's being
clung to and then we could ask where does this clinging come
from is there a belief that's underneath it this belief that in order to be safe
I have to cling on to an idea of myself or in order to feel more comfortable I
have to kind of it dogmatically hold on to certain beliefs and not be open to
maybe learning something new having new
ideas the questions we can ask ourselves are what are the conditions that support
the arising of more freedom what is it when do I feel more
or less ease and peace and E and freedom and what are the conditions and where I
feel the most well-being and peace and ease and what are the conditions in which I feel the least
can I organize my life can I create conditions in my life so that I feel more and more peace and
ease this idea that conditions are so important we know that um of course it
only rains when there's rain clouds of course it doesn't rain when
there aren't rain clouds if we rain only arises when
there's the conditions for it suffering only arises when there's the conditions for
it so questions to ask ourselves are what are the conditions that support the arising of more
freedom that's kind of a clunky way of saying what just to be sensitive to
where is there more suffering less suffering more freedom less freedom and some of you might recognize
that part of this is the for Noble Truth this recog that what's being clung to is what leads to suffering the
opposite of Freedom so this idea of questioning as
an expression of freedom and questioning as a way to lead
to more freedom and as an integral part of our
path both as a stance as a attitude of being receptive and
open and also of a way to kind of like um highlight when we're really tight and
constricted and not being receptive so questioning as as an also
as an alternative of just believing but instead for all of us to find for
ourselves find discover for ourselves where there's more suffering and where there's more
freedom and I'll end there and open it up to see if there are any
questions Diana so I'll I'll ask say something when you were towards the
beginning of your talk I was thinking about a phrase that I've heard people use from time to time about don't go
there and I realize that that's in some ways could be very skillful or very
unskillful so I just wanted to yes like this idea of like don't go don't go
there is like don't ask questions don't go there is that what you mean like yeah yeah yeah and in what ways would that be
really skillful to say don't go there well all of the questions that you're talking about that there are some
things that are just you know you're not going to get it's not going to get away from
suffering or it's just gonna wind you around the
axle I like that expression thank you Jim so like the questions of like well what kind of bird did the feather on
this Arrow come from like don't go there don't waste your time without those types of things yeah yeah thank you yeah
one of the things I was think I just got a text from one of my um College friends
yesterday and I was thinking about when we he and I were roommates one of the big arguments was like who is the best
rock [Applause] band who's better Superman or Batman or
you know these types of things yeah great great thank you
Jim thanks Diana I've been listening a lot repeatedly to a talk on courage and
you talked about how safety can lead to investigation or
fear can prevent investigation and those always seem external to me
like I have to wait for fear to go away or safety to come so I really like focusing on Courage is it's empowering
and it's like I can investigate even in the presence of fear or without feeling safety yeah very nice very
nice yeah we could even like investigate well what is courage what does courage feel like what does Fear feel like and
that's a way that can that's a way of kind of like turning towards what's uh
we don't want to turn towards often fear yeah thank you thank you for kind of making that connection
there okay so thank you all and I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening
thank you