yeah good morning everyone welcome to IMC and to our time
together and I'd like to begin with an ancient analogy that
um Buddhist analogy and that is that of using um
picking up a quail little bird and bringing it to
safety and the idea is that the analogy is that you don't want to hold the quail
too tightly and you don't want to hold the quail too Loosely so neither forcefully nor laxly
neither with stress or strain and not with u hesitation or or kind of
complacency or something it has to be just right just
between those two so in the same way uh the Buddha says that when we make effort
in doing Buddhist practice it should be kind of like holding that Quail so
neither too much effort or too little neither straining nor being LAX or
laxidasical neither uh stressful or complacent
they're just finding a just the right way and um and so in this
analogy uh what you're doing is less is isn't really
highlighted it's how we do it that's being highlighted and this is one of the principles of Buddhist practice that uh
more important than what you do it's how you do it and the how you do it then guides
actually what you do it's uh so that you do the thing which is ethical or
appropriate or healthful healthy and um so uh so the how do it is
is so important that uh one of the principles in some Buddhist teachings is
that uh the the goal of the practice should be found in the means so the way
your practice should contain qualities characteristics of what the purpose of
the practice is the goal of the practice so for example if the goal of the
practice is to be peaceful then you should find uh some PE some sense of Peace in how
you do the practice and uh you don't get to Peace by straining or struggling or
being in conflict with something you find some way to be peaceful in the
practice if you want if you want to become a generous person practice
generosity there should be generosity in the very thing that you're doing uh if what you want is to become
is to not to cling then uh you should practice in a non- clinging way or it
should contain some quality it's hard not to cling but uh at least that should be an orientation that we don't cling as
you do it uh one of the ideas here is that the
most healthy thing you can do for yourself in a spiritual life is to
liberate the heart to liberate the Mind from all that uh cause of suffering to
yourself all the ways in which you cling or resist or shut down or push away that
um that are actually ways of causing self harm just because partly the very nature of clinging the nature of intense
resistance to ourselves some part of ourselves is um that in itself that is
suffering in and of itself and if we do some if we practice in an unhealthy way if we live in an
unhealthy way then uh that's the that's what we're setting up to be the goal or the
consequence so if we live with hate uh chances are that it just kind of
reinforces the hate if we live with love chances are that reinforces love and so
we want to be really careful so there we could say that's what love or hate but how we do anything uh we want to uh so
so um and one of the very important principles in Buddhism is the idea of
wholesomeness the idea of doing things in a Wholesome Way no matter what you do
do it wholesomely and what wholesome means it feels for our psychophysical system it
feels nourishing it feels healthy to do it and uh and that reference point for
health is something that is um somatic you can you can feel it you know it for
yourself in a very clear way and the the analogy I used like to I don't if it
works for all of you but um I've been maybe doing some heavy work in the
backyard gardening or something gotten sweaty and hot and tired and and dirty
and um and then I'll go Tak in a shower and I feel so clean like it's my my skin
kind of vibrates with a feeling of being clean and good and settled and I feel all warm or
or um or when I was a little when I was a small kid um I would take a bath and
at the evening before going to bed and then I would just put in my pajamas and slip into bed but my mother had um just
washed and the the sheets and so they were still warm from the dryer and that
was just so it just felt so somatically comforting meaningful healthy to kind of
be clean and into these warm sheets so I don't know if that analogy works for any
of you but the idea that's a sematic you can feel that what you're doing feels good for the heart good for the mind
good for the body and um and that's what makes it wholesome and uh that also then becomes
a guide for what we do because some things we do will never feel that way if
you lie it's just not going to feel that way if you are form if you are hating
someone or hating something it's just if you really pay attention to the sematic experience of it um it it deep down
inside or it's not going to feel comforting or meaningful or or healthy
even the only thing that might feel attractive is sometimes something like hate comes with a lot of energy and
comes with a lot of righteousness and that can feel good but if you feel those
they don't feel good in any deep way either even though there might be energy good some kind of being energized or
feel powerful or something that might have a good feeling but to have power from that if you really pay attention
will not feel wholesome so uh so this idea that uh and
uh the we want to pay attention to how we're doing things and um and the most healthy thing
you could do is become um liberated from clinging this is a core definition of in
Awakening or Liberation is that we no longer have the forces in inside of ourselves that are going to add this
kind of suffering stress UNH wholesome feeling for what's going on for us and
you can't find the wholesome results by doing UNH wholesome things so so the
idea is to use ourselves as the book use ourselves as
the guide for how we find our way by noticing how we're doing things how
we're doing it how doing it and um so one of
the uh kind of consequences of Bud of doing Buddhist practice is that
increasingly as we mature in the practice we have an increasing focus on how we're doing
things and one of the benefits of that is that you can then it's easier to bring the practice into our daily life
maybe at first you don't see what the connection is but as you continue practicing why if you if if meditation
makes you feel at home makes you feel calm peaceful gives you a healthy Good
Feeling then at some point it might occur to you why should I only have that kind of Good Feeling while I'm
meditating I mean you know the line between meditation and life is not that
sharp why not have that kind of healthy feeling everywhere I go and so then uh
for some meditators that's a turning point in their whole practice because then they have a reference point for how
to live their ordinary life so they're not sacrificing or giving up or
compromising that sense of well-being uh in their daily life as well and so then
the one of the tasks in daily life is how we want to do things how do we do it
that it's healthy how we do it that it's stress free or or diminishes the stress
how do we do it so that it creates a wonderful sense of Health wonderful sense of Vitality even that as we go
about doing it and uh oddly enough maybe that when I
had came to that point in my practice uh that's one of the reasons I went to live at a Buddhist Meditation Center because
I wanted to find ways to uh take what was happening in meditation and discover
how to live that my daily life and I thought by if I lived in a Buddhist center where that was the whole point or
the community was all doing the same practice that then somehow I'd find myself more able to bring the practice
into daily life and um but then I was in a Buddha Center so we meditated
more and so that wasn't exactly what I came there for but it was it was a nice
kind of consequence because then it became even more clear the difference or how to do this you know the meditation
deepened and then they had diff different reference point for done doing in daily life and and then uh and then
so then I wanted to do it even more and then I went from living at a Buddhist center to I moved to a Buddhist
Monastery and uh again not to meditate more but it turned out that if you go to
a Buddhist Monastery you meditate a lot more and um and so then there was this
wonderful kind of circular movement of meditation and finding out how to live
this in my daily life and apply it and um and so this idea then of of
finding you know the maturing of Buddhism has to do with the uh being
interested in how to find this healthy way of being Wholesome Way of being um
throughout our life you know why not and the why not is not answered by some kind
of moral dictum di rule or something but rather it's uh because the the reason
the whole you know is that to not do that hurts to not not do that is a drag
you feel how not to do that you you yourself are diminishing the quality of
your inner being your inner well-being that uh if you uh are doing
UNH wholesome things then you're you're you're kind of harming yourself in a certain way and if
you and if you can feel that self harm then why would you continue you know I mean of course some
people will come up good reasons but uh but uh but generally it's you
know why would you continue doing that and um and so that's the motivation even
for then stop doing the unhealthy things and what should you do instead well if
you're interested in a Buddhist practice you would search for the healthy alternatives of how to do it and um so
generosity instead of being miserly being uh loving instead of being hateful
being um being generous instead of greedy
being wise instead of foolish being equanimous or patient rather than
impatient or reactive so they're go the list can go on and on to kind of how we
what we're looking for and um and then at some point uh
with this whole process because Buddhism has this path to maturation maturing to become healthier and healthier in this
psychological spiritual way at some point uh the reference point for how we
practice is also affected by what we're discovering through the practice and at
some point there are three things that become the basis or the foundation for
how we want to do this practice itself and these three things are ways that the
goal is really found in the means and uh more and more as you practice the you
know you have the sense of this is possible to have this Awakening experience or something but then the
qualities of that what that is uh you turn back into how you practice so it
becomes the reference point for how to practice and that's immensely supportive me immensely
helpful and um so I'd like to offer you three of these qualities one is that uh you base your
practice on not depending on anything most of us so are constantly as
to go through life we're depending on something that we're kind of the mind is preoccupied with concerned with wanting
there's us some some condition that we want to get or avoid and which are very
n very nature of Consciousness very nature of the way we attend to the world attend to ourselves is is not depend not
independent not non-dependent but it's really dependent on wanting something not wanting something some condition and
the remarkable thing can discover through this practice is a way that our awareness our attention the way that we
attend the way that we are present for ourselves here that um uh it's free from
any kind of dependence on anything else of course we live in dependence on the
world and breathing and eating and people and Society in all kinds of profound ways important ways I don't
want to dismiss that but it's also possible to sit in meditation for for example or go to the local park and just
sit on the bench and kind of just just gaze upon the world there or
something and uh and um and feel like there's a way a sense of presence or way
of attending or paying attention that is not dependent on anything it's not
relying on anything not attached to anything not requiring anything to be any particular
way and uh and and have the opportunity and have the situation where you to let
go of all the things upon which we our Consciousness our mind is operating that at that moment is dependent on other
things and just be there is really remarkable
thing I traveled through from a different time zone yesterday so my my
whole six my little inner clock was kind of a little bit off I suppose and uh so
I woke up in the middle of the night and um and at first first my mind was
dependent on a lot of things it was a dependent on the idea that this is not
good it was you know if I don't get enough sleep then I have to give this Dharma talk tomorrow and you know I'll
just fall asleep during my Dharma talk and this will be bad my reputation's at stake and so you know so all these
things were kind of you know kind of operating maybe and uh and
um and then I you know was my my whole up operating system was operating under this assumption that I need to sleep I
should sleep I have to do what I need to sleep here and um and I've done this
enough times now to know that it's that it's not a helpful St position to be in it's not just like self-defeating almost
to have those those ideas and and so um I've learned to just lay there and um
and and try to be content with the moment and just I take it as a time for practicing and I'll lay there and I I'll
often first uh just relax my body usually if I really want to go to sleep
or think it's not right to be awake um if I pay careful attention I find that there's tension in my body um and
sometimes it's in my forearms it's very subtle uh sometimes around my chest sometimes in my face and so I'll lay
there and just kind of relax those things relax those things soften and relax and then I'll uh tune into my
breathing which has been a lifetime kind of practice of mine just just be there but as I do that I'm just seeing can my
mind uh operate without dependence on anything without needing to be any
particular way or have any values or purposes or fears that it's kind of the
foundation for the whole mental activity that I'm doing and eventually I this you
know it was easy matter eventually I could sit there lay there and just be
kind of oh I'm content nothing had to happen nothing had to be any different I was just awake and I wasn't tired so
that wasn't a problem um the only problem was the idea that I should be awake I should be sleeping but that was
just an idea so do I want to base my inner sense of well-being on an idea and
um so anyway so so then eventually I fell asleep and then I slept more than I
usually do and um so um so to to find a way to
practice where the practice is not depending on something not requiring anything to be any particular way is one
of the one of the characteristics of the practice becoming mature and that's the same as so so in terms of that being a a
um a quality of the goal The Awakening experience is the same way the the mind
that becomes free liberated in Buddhism is radically and fully now present some
people would say radiant um without any any depending on anything
whatsoever um and um so that's nice so so so those those
qualities then you know that's that's the orientation so I'm practicing now am I depending on something some people are
depending on getting concentrated life only if I get concentrated will it really work it count I have to get
concentrated well that's a depend end and state to be in um and other would be
wow my mind is really distracted I'm caught up in my thoughts so a dependent way of thinking would be I have to stop
doing this I have to be undistracted I have to be you know not so lost in my
thoughts well that's to be dependent if you ask yourself what is it to be nondependent here for a
non-dependent attention and you kind of feel your way into the answer the the
the consequence of that is you're kind of in the present moment rather than
trying to be in the present you find yourself way in the present so we'll get back to this point so I said there's
three three characteristics of the goal that are that we then find in the means uh the other one is
freedom and that is it's these are all related but for some people these
different words work better for others but now now what's we're we're we find it we recognize that part of ourselves
is free of greed hate and delusion part of part of who we are part of what
awareness is part of our heart part of our very being has some characteristic
of non- clinging non grasping non-closing down non um you
know non-grasping nonattachment and uh and ultimate
freedom in Buddhism is a radical total complete letting go of every attachment we possibly have uh even at first it's
just temporary but it's really you know it's really kind of maybe it's a pun but it's
mind-blowing that that you know the degree of of uh the all attachments are
blown away and um the um and so now we're
finding that how you know finding some quality of non-attachment that's in the
nature of how the mind operates and we're building on that growing on that letting that non- clinging begin to
spread into more and more areas of our life it's one thing to have some sense of what it's like to not cling it's
another thing to be able to apply that to in all the circumstances and place that we live so part of the maturation
of Buddhism is the is the expansion of that into more and more areas of our life so then now practi is based on this
notion of freedom freedom from clinging and the third is peace
that uh that one of the primary kind of um emotional I guess kind of
characteristics of Buddhist Liberation is a very deep state of peace and so so
now there's a reference point to that peace and so is it peaceful is there
peace as I do this do I sit down and am I immediately kind of content in content
in a contentious mode of being with the world with myself my immediate L uh
focusing on what's wrong right here and I had to fix it uh instead when my those
things might exist but but the orientation is how do I do this peacefully where's the peace as I find a
way to change what I have to change how do I find peace with sitting Brea
breathing here and being practicing how do I find peace in a situation that's uh
may be very conventionally very challenging all around
me the um um I recently I I remember I was in a
situation where the people around me were having some major conflict but nothing was required of me I didn't know
them that was they were strangers it was a public place and so it wasn't really my place to get involved to you know the
anger and what was going on but it was kind of uncomfortable to sit there and so I just sat and I didn't close my eyes
I thought that would might be kind of weird for the people I was kind of sitting close to them uh but I didn't want to make any problems for them like
looked like I was closing the tune them out or something so I just kind of lowered my gaze and then I looked inside
and could I be peaceful as opposed to reactive or preoccupied or caught in by what they're
doing and and judging them or whatever it might be could I at least be peaceful in this
situation and uh and I thought that was a nice Sol for me that was a better alternative than the things were already
going on my mind because I wasn't you know I was kind of having my reaction to
them which was not healthy so I thought Let's do let's do the better alternative
here so I could find my peace and I don't know what happened in the end
but but um you know I was as I said I wasn't involved with the
situation and um so those three things uh nondependent
freedom and peace these are the three as we mature in practice at some point that
becomes the reference point that becomes in the ancient Buddhist language um they say it's the basis of the practice we do
the practi is might be the same practice we did as a beginner it might be something like beginner some people do breath
meditation just tune into to the breath and um and uh so it might be the same
practice as always but now the practice is in for informed by these qualities or
supported by these qualities and that makes all the difference in the world because that's where we're trying to
grow we're not necessarily trying to grow become better and better uh people
better and better at mindfulness of breathing we're trying to become um um more and more free as we do mindfulness
of breathing and mind and whatever practice we're doing then becomes the way that we're cultivating the how okay
how I'm going to do how how am I going to do mindfulness of breathing how do I meet it and not a few few people uh who are
beginners and uh maybe sometimes longtime practitioners find the breathing
boring why would I do it it's so boring and um and the the mistake
they're making is that they expect the breathing itself to be the solution
there's something is there's something in breathing that's the key in the Magic The Magic doesn't come from the
breathing per se but the magic comes from how we're with the breath and the how is where something
begins shifting and changing and at some point the breath can be experienced as
being a tremendous pleasure a tremendous beautiful thing to experience and can be
very captivating and fascinating to be with a breath but so you might say oh
the breath is fascinating and then your friends you know your neighbors say what my this is so
boring but it's not because the breath is inherently wonderful it's the how
with the breath and the how then uh uh
changes um how the breathing is experienced so it's the how that shifts
something and how we see the breathing or how we feel the breathing so that it starts feeling it very different it can
be quite beautiful and peaceful and inspiring to be with a breath but it isn't so but you have to
understand it's a lot of it has to do with the how another thing about this thing that
these three qualities of the goal that's uh it's in mature practice is is found
in the mature practice non-dependence freedom and peace is that
as you go about your life if you focus on that even if just one of those maybe
a piece is the EAS easiest one maybe rather rather than focusing on mindfulness um uh it might actually be
better we're like this mindfulness movement part of right so we think that mindfulness is all about what we do
we're supposed to be mindful I have to be mindful should be mindful and I'm going to be mindful I wasn't mindful I
can't be mindful mindful mind are you being Mindful and people ask you what's
your practice I'm being I practice
mindfulness what if people instead of what what asks ask you how are you
practicing I think it would be more useful but maybe it's too personal to do it in you know polite
company but um but uh you know rather than asking what are you practicing uh
how are you practicing that would be kind of like uh to be asked that question is is kind of
personal ask that question and and you're accountable now for something personal but how you bring yourself to
it if you say well I pract what do you practice I practice mindfulness of breathing
great what are people going to say you know that's nice you I do that too or I've heard that's a good thing or you
know it's just kind of something abstract it uh but if they ask how are you practicing now we're talking about
something very personal oh I'm pack practicing with a lot of aggression
thank you I'm you know I'm going to get in lighten their bust I know how to do this and I'm going to push and assert
myself and I'm I'm I'm I'm doing it to be the best enlightened person on my block wow okay well that was
clear um but if you but if you say rather well how well I'm trying not to
be contentious I'm trying not to be uh in argument with reality I'm trying to
find my peace with how I am in this world um you know that's a very very
diff then then we're focusing on what is actually important what is to be developed what we're
developing and but how this folds back into the practice of
mindfulness is that if you focus on how to be peaceful in the present
moment lo and behold you have to be mindful but if mindfulness becomes a
byproduct not the thing you're trying to to do so if you focus on how you should
be you can't help but to be mindful because the how always puts you in the
present moment how are you doing right now what's happening for you right now as you do this and so if you looking for
freedom from clinging in how do I go through this day so that I'm free of
clinging well this is now that I have a flat now that I have two flat tires my
car I think this is a good time to experiment explore this because now I'm
have so much reactions I I have a lot of things I cling to being on time to the next thing I was supposed to going to
and clinging to how wrong the people at the tire company were to give me those old tires clinging to you know just like
it goes through you know there's a long list of things that now suddenly woke up that I'm now clinging to or reacting to
or resisting okay how do I want to be with this
should I I'll yeah I'll write an angry letter to that tire company or how do I want to be with this
well how do I want to be with this is of course I'm angry of course I'm afraid of course this is difficult can I hold this
peacefully can I hold my clinging with non- clinging how do I do
that well it turns out you have to be kind of mindful to do that mindfulness
has to mindfulness and follows by the very motivation to what you want to do
so it might be a a valuable reframing of mindfulness
practice uh because sometimes the the simple idea that I'm practicing
mindfulness supposed to be mindful um is a little bit too abstract and have a little bit more sense of Duty little bit
more sense of a rule you're supposed to follow and it can be hard because maybe it's not being
Guided by the how Guided by a so maybe somatic
heartfelt body felt mindf sense of what is healthy and what is not healthy what
is wholesome and not wholesome but if you say but if you say okay I'm going to I'm going to figure out how to be
peaceful here that's going to be my practice and how am I not peaceful and
what would peaceful look like and how would I feel that how do I feel the lack of peace and how do I hold it peacefully
um then after doing that for a while you find out wow the last five minutes I've been really mindful you had to be
present and attentive in order to answer those questions and uh and then at some point
you might occur to you how do I continue being mindful oh
now there I am I've been mindful for five whole minutes I I think if I just continue the
mindfulness continue the state of present moment awareness that's going to maintain
uh my peace so the goal it to have the goal
expressed in the means to be very careful not to try to get somewhere in your
practice without considering how you include the destination in how you're
practicing and it's a very very effective form of self- protection you
do that and you're protected from straining striving wanting being
conceited being somehow there's all these ways in which practice gets
hijacked by our attachments and our fears and our resistances and our
dislikes and likes and um but if you're constantly asking you this question about the how
am I practicing how is this supposed to uh in it of itself Express part of the
goal then you it's kind of a prote ction because you'll notice when you're straining you notice when you're
clinging as part of your practice and so it helps helps to support a healthy how
your practice and if your if your how your practice is healthy then um you'll
become more healthy at least spiritually or psychologically so the simple principle
of today that I'm hoping that if you me if you want to memorize one few words about
that carry with you as a reminder is um that uh to have the goal in the means
have the means Express what the goal is include the
gold so the two aren't so far
apart and if the goal seems so far away though the
enlightenment boy that's like seems like a good idea but I'll never get enlightened in this life it's just like
too impossible well if you're caught up in that kind of
idea then the goal is not in the means but you instead of you go wow yeah
it's probably really far away you know the total full absolute
complete Enlightenment of the Buddha that's maybe a little bit far away but um but look at that I can be a little
more less clinging right now look at that I can do that I could not be so
caught and trapped by this idea of ultimate Enlightenment and right there
you you contain part of the goal and then you build that and expand that how you
are so we have uh nine minutes left before the tea time everyone's welcome
to stay for the tea and uh wholeheartedly welcome nice to have you here and um and if you'd uh be willing
to uh you don't have to stay now we can end but uh it's very nice when we have tea to for uh uh to stay for a few
minutes and to meet some people in the community and say hello and and I'd like to emphasize how valuable it is for each
of you to welcome the other here that even if it's your first time you're already here you're part of the
community so you can welcome the person you're with even if they've been here many times just say hello and welcome
and say your name and and that's and then if there was something that was important meaningful for you or
something that was evocative for you or provocative for you about this talk maybe you can share some simple thing
about that uh with your partner and um so also it' be nice if you kind of look
around maybe it be groups of two or three but look around because sometimes people turn opposite directions with
person in the middle left alone so I just look around so everyone gets to kind of be included and and if
you prefer just sit in silence then you close your eyes and it's kind of nice to listen to all the talking and then you
can stay for the tea or whatever you'd like to do is fine and I'll ring a bell in a few minutes when it's time to stop
for the tea and so thank you