good morning or good day hello
welcome and um as we're coming to the end of this
two week series for this meditation I'd like to uh introduce something which in my mind
my heart is a kind of a uh the Gathering Together of all that that we've done
these good morning oh all of these
days and
um sometimes the word Dharma is used to refer
to uh something profound in our own nature that we have the
nature of being Dharma
vesicles for the Dharma we are uh we are there's a wonderful
capacity force uh wonderful processing that is
within our psychophysical being which we can't exactly appropriate as being
mine in a sense from a certain kind of way it's a greater
power within us that is not what we normally identify as me or the me the
one who's going to do something and um we have agency but one
of the really powerful ways to use that agency in Dharma practice is to use it
to create the conditions for our own inner nature d
nature to move through us and a lot of uh the Dharma Dharma
practice sooner or later has to is about getting out of the
way not interfering not blocking not
messing with the natural movement Dharma movement within
us and sometimes that movement is a movement towards healing
and our heart's nature is to heal if we allow it if we create the
conditions and the time and the and the non-interference and a radical non-
interference radical way of not being a victim not being a fixer not being a a
um avoider not being a Builder and maker of making things
happen the natural movement towards homeostasis or towards health or towards a certain kind
of healing sometimes it's a process of maturation maybe we are healed in
conventional way and psychological way and something begins moving through us to mature us to we grow and develop and
Blossom come into fruition is the Buddhist language for
it and so to have a profound
respect for our own capacity and everyone's
capacity for this natural natural process of healing
maturation of moving into a kind of wholeness or moving into a kind of
healing moving into a kind of [Music] maturity that is
wholesome that is in some ways
ethical so as we sit with this
meditation the task is to sit with mindfully present for our experience
centered and maybe in the breathing and being very simple being here and
now but notice whatever takes you away notice whatever takes you away from
this this inner process that needs awareness for it to make have space for
to allow it to come and grow and uh whatever takes you
away notice whatever ways you interfere with it judge it try to fix it try to
avoid it react to it to see if there can be a radical way
of getting out of the way of your deeper nature of your
psychophysical system and sometimes certain things will
have to get more intense before they heal before they
resolve but to have the profound trust to the trust in getting radically out of
the way and staying present so I hope this makes
sense so to assume a meditation
posture and one of the ways of understanding this meditation posture it's a posture that is that
doesn't interfere with the
full Dynamic
freedom of this inner process while we sit
still not to hold ourselves still but to softly allow ourselves to
be still so
there's a kind of soft space for each unique thing that's happening
within us to appear persist pass
away and perhaps you gently close your eyes and with the eyes
closed a kind of soft homecoming to the body
a soft willingness to turn the
attention here in this body at this
time and as you breathe in to feel the
body feel the tensions of the body without
reactivity judgments to feel on the inhale and
relax on the exhale and if relaxing is too active
allow for a release allow for letting go in the body
as you
exhale for
and finding where in your body the body's experience of
breathing has some sense of freedom
where the inhale begins freely on its
own maybe in a different place where you might be controlling the
breath where the exhale happens on its
own and as you stay with your breathing in and breathe
out maybe you can have an appreciation whatever piece little piece
of breathing is a natural
process that happens without you're interfering and
doing consciously and intentionally and it could be as simple
as the contact of your skin against your clothes how it shifts as you
breathe or the expanding and Contracting movements however
subtle in your back rib
cage for
and then noticing any way in which you interfere or avoid
or judge or try to
fix instead leave things alone radically
alone maybe with the
support of the way in which breathing happens
naturally breathing is the
centerpiece of a natural process that everything is part of
if we can get out of the way
while clearly aware of what is here
for
for for
trusting trusting the natural processes within
us works best
when we're radically thorough in non
interference noninterfering
awareness really present here in a clear Living Way
not participating actively in anything leaving all things alone each
individual thing that arises within us around us let it
be content to just be
aware
for
e
for for
whatever is happening make room for
it don't do anything about it just know
it in this simplest way you can be
aware be mindful know that it's
happening like you would know clearly a
cloud floating in the sky
or water flowing down a
river let it be let life flow Here and
Now
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to imagine how how it can be deeply
respectful of others to from a place of our confidence our
safety our self-respect that we can just know
others as they are take the time to listen to others to
see them to hear know them without our agendas without
our interference not giving in to
others but not asserting ourselves on others not avoiding
but present
interested knowing each person in their own right for who they
are not for what they are to
us free of our fears free of our
desires just allow and know others and maybe there too there's a
natural process that unfolds and one of
those is our our love our good
will our sense of being in communion
together May our good will spread out into the
world may it be a bomb may it be medicine for this suffering
world that we offer it our good will our kindness our
friendship compassion
love that respects each thing in a profound way free of our
interference may all beings be
happy may all be
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so today the I I will I will reflect on that
final and 10th of the 10 Reflections and in some ways I very much
think of them it is following all the others all the others are a foundation for this last
one and um I think of it as healing so yesterday was reconciliation
today's healing and the difference between reconciliation and healing in the way
that I'm using it here is reconciliation is the healing we do
socially the coming into wholeness into communion and coming together and with
kindness with Good Will with others healing I use here as how we
reconcile ourselves with ourselves how we come into communion to wholeness
with ourselves and uh I like to believe is
not a coincidence or not a or that it's very
significant that the English word
wholeness and healing and health all kind of come from the same uh uh
indoan Roots through the Germanic
and Scandinavian and northern European languages that
um that there's something about uh healing and health which means to be
whole to be undamaged to be un uninjured and um to be complete in a
certain kind of way and uh and so uh to not be divided in ourselves and
there are times when we are at war with ourselves we have uh we have values we
believe in and but we don't live that way we we have ways of being and
thinking and feeling which somehow or other not we think is not acceptable and we have to get rid of it push it away
and uh I've seen in some people quite an intense standoff kind of a impassible
kind of Checkmate around the war between different parts of themselves and
um and so to uh heal the divisions we have to heal the ways in which we are
critical of ourselves angry at ourselves hostile towards ourselves heal the ways in which we shut off from
ourselves uh divided in ourselves and uh and one way or the other most
people are to be attached is to be divided to have hostility towards others
is to be divided in oneself to live caught in fear is a way of not being
whole and of course there's good reasons to be afraid and fears are necessary
important part of life in certain kind of healthy ways but there are ways in which people get stuck in ways that
they're not full not whole not complete of these 10
Reflections I think over the last one is being the one that uh is uh is closest
to being religious um the these 10 Reflections as I've introduced them come from the world
of chaplaincy where hospital and prison and and hospice
chaplains um especially in some parts of this country like California are available to do Interfaith chapy
Interfaith spiritual care where they meet people of other religions in their own and not to prze but rather to
support them in their own way and um and so the orientation has to
be kind of more spiritual than religious more and and it's so broad these 10
Reflections that um these themes that they also work for people who are
non-religious or humanists or atheists they're such fundamental human things
but as we get to this sense of healing the possibility of healing the trusting of healing of
wholeness that there's something here within us that is a kind of a greater
power than what we have uh full agency over that's different than what we have
control over or can make happen or do or um something that we no longer need to
resist and hold hold back from something quite significant that in a sense in my
language is a greater power within us that um that uh is not appropriated to
our identity to that part of it that we create a self and build up a sense of self and um it's not so strange what I'm
saying uh and as as often will point out it's kind of like the natural great
power of physical healing from a cut we can cut ourselves and uh it's a Rel
physiologically a fairly complicated uh multifaceted event for the body to heal
itself but if we can let it get out of the way of the healing keep the wound
clean keep it from getting dirty not not pick the scab that uh the body has a way
of healing up to a certain point and the certain point is I still have on my back of my hand um the
remnants the leftover of uh that's I think fully healed and as far as healing
is concerned but I I um I still have the scar of being deeply cut on my hand and
um the U and uh and I appreciate the scar
that's left it reminds me of my fragility my morality my by uh all kinds
of things um that's part of the wholeness is to include that what's the remnant of
what's there it's not necessarily we have nothing left over psychologically
emotionally physically from how we get healed but um but there is this power
within that this Force this ability this capacity within that I can't say it's
it's mine in the sense where I I usually usual place where I identify or me as
the agent me as the experiencer me as the doer me as something and it's a so
lovely to relax and trust this deeper process I still have a role uh to
support that but it's a role mostly of non-interference don't interfere with
the healing that goes on and this is also true in the heart emotionally it's
true in the mind we have a phenomenal our whole psychophysical system is kind of maybe built to move towards balance
to homeostasis to wholeness um and we very sophisticated
system within us that none of us can fully understand how it works and so at some point in Dharma
practice to uh the movement towards wholeness or to Freedom or to peace or
to non Divi not being non-divided um um requires a radical
kind of non-interference a radical trust and allowing for this natural maturity the
natural healing that uh our system is capable of but if we're always writing
close like a kid in the backseat saying are we there yet are we there yet we're always there kind of you know pushing
and trying to make it happen or scratching the scab uh uh this natural
process cannot happen and so to to come into some deeper trust
that allows some deeper uh movements within us to begin unfolding and opening and and um and
coming into a kind of wholeness and part of that process is
healing a personal healing healing within ourselves and of course the the
reconciliation with others is not going to be independent from our healing and our eles in the way I'm using these
words um they're not separate but they uh there is a whole process of
selfhealing that goes on and for many people when they come to Dharma practice
uh in the beginning uh I think a lot of what's happening is healing uh or if you don't like the word
healing or it's not quite right for what your process is coming into a wholeness and to some degree it's it's
it's aided by a certain humility uh not the humility of beling belittling
oneself or being submissive or anything but the humility of not feeling that uh
uh we know everything we're in charge of everything we can do everything ourselves and and kind of just Barrel
ahead and make everything right there is a humility that trusts and allows for um
the that we don't know it all we're not the one who's the doer and the maker of it all we have to allow some other
process to unfold make room for it and that allowing then just that
itself heals some of the divisions that are formed by excessive um self
assertion self de deprecation humility is not
self-criticism or diminishing yourselves it actually heals that as well it's we
come into a Simplicity of being and um and from that Simplicity of being
from that kind of simple maybe humble um wholeness or healing then when
we we can still be agents in our life we can still do things we can still live
with dignity and value and purpose and meaning but it comes from a very different place it's it rises within us
with uh uh without stress stress without strain without creating further division
either socially or personally so this personal
healing and uh remember Steven Levine a wonderful teacher from many years
ago made the distinction for Me Maybe other people maybe have done it between
um um curing and healing and he worked a lot with people who were dying
and he was kind of the one of the pioneers of the hospice movement in working with death and dying and uh and
he was a uh aided and supported people in their last days of their life to be
healed in a psychological emotional spiritual way uh that didn't cure them
of their illness um so didn't bring them back into physical health but uh
still helped them with profound movement towards healing and it was one of the
greatest things I that uh we can do for someone as they're dying or we can do
for ourselves if we're dying is to come into that wholeness that personal healing it is
possible and uh and uh and it's not the same thing as having a
cure so um so what is your experience of personal healing or if you prefer com
coming into wholeness and U or if you prefer rather
than these positive formulations uh uh becoming
undivided um and how does that work for you and
how do you move into it and is there space in your life to trust it more to allow for it more to happen it takes
time and we have to give ourselves time I like to call it sacred time
for this process to unfold within us so those are the 10
um Reflections and I'm delighted to have shared it with
you and uh and uh if you want more of
this then uh in the fall I'm going to do a program through the Sati center that
is kind of uh adop adapting some of the things that we do in the uh uh
chaplaincy programs I teach that uh that presents it kind of to a lay audience or
to people who are not being trained to be chaplain but uh some of the fundamentals of spiritual care and uh
one of the things we'll go through over the year is these um 10 themes we did
this last two weeks so that's on the Sati Center website if you're interested and then for the next three
weeks I won't be here and um teaching a teaching a retreat for the next two
weeks and going on a pilgrimage Buddhist pilgrimage uh the following
week and um and so next week Shelley G will come a wonderful teacher from Santa
Barbara and then may uh Elliot will come and and I don't think we have a teacher
yet for the third week but um that's um you you'll be in good
hands so thank you very very very much and um I appreciate very much that uh I
had this opportunity to reflect on these themes with you