hello hello voice is coming it's coming it's coming there we
go I'm happy to see you this
evening so my name is Maria stropman and I am here for Diana tonight she'll be
back I think next week so last week we talked about
intention if you were here we talked about intention mindfulness and the
journey and we talked about it in terms of intention being a motivator an
instigator the thing that gets us started on the path and guides us tell
us tells us we're going the direction we want to be going sort of sets sets the
tone for what what it is that we're doing on our journey and it takes effort
then to sustain that to get it going to persist in the in the journey and
that it is mindfulness mindfulness that marks the journey that
keeps us on the way that brings us into the now of being here being with what is
happening and that all of this has to do with what we like to call the uh first
three factors of Enlightenment Faith or confidence that is the intention leads
to Faith of I'm I know I'm going the right direction and every step that we
take reinforces that and increases the confidence in the path and the effort
number two the that keeps us persisting in the path that is the second item and
the third one is mindfulness without mindfulness we're not going anywhere we don't know where we're going so those
are the first three this evening what we're going to talk about are the last two which are
con uh concentration and wisdom or
discernment now when I list it that way it all sounds a little bit like um a
catechism you know you got to do this this this this and this and we have definitions for what those
are and it's just one more part of our practice and if you recall one of the things that
I said is that I always feel like I'm starting in the middle of the story because everything affects
everything else it's not as if we do this then this happens and we do this
then that happens in fact everything influences everything
else so what I really want to talk about is what the effect of concentration is
on whether we have faith in the journey Journey how does concentration affect
mindfulness what does mindfulness have to do with concentration why when we sit down to
meditate do we become so obsessed with I'm not concentrated and does it make any
difference why do we do that what's it about what's the
usefulness of that and by the way what we practice
here is vasana which is Insight Meditation and where are those insights
anyway how do I get them what do I have to
do it's not as mysterious as all that it's really not as mysterious as all
that and when I point to these factors I really want you to understand
that you already have them all and all we want to do is cultivate
them all we want to do is learn learn how to use them skillfully all we want to do is have them as supports for the
practice that we do they're not goals or endpoints they're not things that we
have to have they're not things we pack in our
suitcases they're Maps they're AIDS they're the
GPS but they're not the journey so uh a few days ago I was in
this the Sleep Clinic at Stanford and one of the technicians was very attentive uh on the
subject of being grounded he said the only way you can get good sleep is you've got to be grounded you've got to
be grounded and so I was trying to figure out what he meant when he talked about being grounded because you know
people mean different things with these words and as he talked about the
importance of being grounded it occurred to me that it's not
unlike what we think of as the Stillness that arises when we're doing
mindfulness the continuity of mindfulness when we're just we're in the flow and we're we're we're centered
sometimes we say we're centered sometimes we say I've got my feet on the ground sometimes we say I'm right here
with my breath but it's that Gathering Together of the
forces it's the sort of centering pulling in settling in part that I really want
to talk about in concentration they're kind of two different forms one of them has to do with uh what we usually think
of when we do concentration which is one pointedness you know I'm going to I'm
going to concentrate on my breath and I'm going to be stuck on that breath and I'm going to be with that breath and all I'm going to think about as a breath and
the mind is going to go away which you know most people have a hard time with some people by the way are very very
good at that I'm not and for years I tried to do
that and what a waste that was what a waste that
was the one pointedness is a kind of absorptive kind
of concentration and it can be very important it's a very good place to
notice the the basic tenants of uh characteristics of existence a very good
place to directly experience impermanence because the mind slows so
down and we are free of all the the distractions that are normally part of our
experience and we can see things arising persisting and passing away and
impermanence begins to make sense it's something that we can actually see can
see something arising and we realize that impermanence is not only about things ending but also arising because
we see them arising persisting and passing
away and I can sit here all day and tell you that but the direct experience of it
is so much more profound and you'll never truly have faith in it until you have the direct
experience of oh oh I just watched that
oh oh it was here and now it's not and I
saw it come and now it's not and the thoughts come and they go and it's not like well I was thinking
about going to Hawaii and now I'm not I remember one time on Retreat I was
having a really difficult time because I couldn't seem to get concentrated and I talked to Gil and
said well you know what really restless but fortunately I believe in impermanence I know it's not going to
last and he said come and talk to me when you've got a little more fine structure on that
would you know he didn't want to hear something was going to change in an hour
he wanted to hear I can see it arising and passing away the instantaneous
arising and passing away with one pointed absorptive con concentration you
can see that so yes it's important but it's not the only kind of concentration
there's another kind of concentration and is the kind that we call moment to moment awareness and
that's more common when we sit in meditation and when we are have continu
continuity of mindfulness in our everyday life as well where we can see the breath comes the breath comes and
the breath comes and and the breath comes and the breath comes and we know it's leaving but we're watching it it
comes and we're continually following it and we're continually following it but
we're not absorbed in it what we see in that kind of state is
a little different we develop a steadiness of
Mind where the mind is not running off to Hawaii or running off to the argument
we had with somebody this afternoon noon or trying to understand what how to solve a particular
problem we're staying in the room there's a certain steadiness of effort
and the being mindfulness the being in a meditative state becomes easier it
doesn't it's not so much of a struggle and we're just there we're just
there not that the mind doesn't wander away but it more readily comes
back and we can pull it back and we say I'm here and then we start noticing
something about the quality of the thoughts or the quality of our feelings or the quality of the
itch and we can see things happening when the mind is steady when
the mind is running around all over the place it's very difficult it's very
difficult to see anything if you're constantly chasing crisis with your mind if you're still trying to solve the
problem that you left at work if you're still trying to figure out what to do about next week's party
or next week's crisis or anything else that absorbs your mind to rattling
around until you can step back and say ah the mind is
worrying and develop a little distance so that the mind can be steady
in the midst of that chaos that's a form of concentration as
well and it's a very important kind of concentration it's the kind of
concentration that allows us to notice I'm wanting I'm wanting or I really
don't want that I really don't want that or I I'm Restless or you know I'm
just sleepy we become aware of the hindrances
you do not become aware of the hindrances if you have no concentration at
all because the mind is off most people don't give themselves
credit for the settling that they have for the easing that they
have and when you begin to notice that's what's well that's what's really happening here it becomes easier to see
it and to watch and say okay now it seems very peaceful now oh it seems
jittery now it seems anxious now and you can begin to see what's happening
without having so many opinions about it and it be you become an observer of
your
experience you can see th things happening and experience what's going on
in your in front of you without grabbing onto it and being caught by it and
having to tear it apart because you have just a little
distance I'm sorry I'm having a little trouble here with this attachment I'm I
think I'm going to just let it go I'm feeling
confined by the microphone so
so the first thing we want to think about when we're thinking about concentration is what we're trying to do
is develop a steadiness of Mind a kind of resilience if you think
of it as flexibility where I'm here I am here I'm
right here and I'm following this I remember uh another time on Retreat when
I simply could not settle it was about a day and a half I was on Retreat sitting
walking sitting walking sitting walking and it was
torture so I decided something had to happen and that the problem was that I
was trying too hard to settle so I decided to give the Mind
something particular to do and I decided I wanted it to notice
when this muscle in my thigh twitched when I took a step and I went out and
did walking meditation and tried to notice when that twitch occurred as I was walking the
first twitch of that muscle in my thigh and so much attention to something
in particular took so much one-pointed
effort that it all went away it's sort of like if you put your hands together and you hold them so that the fingers
just barely touch not not where you clamp them
together but where they just barely touch it takes a great deal of effort to hold them where they just barely
touch and what it does is gather your attention there you are gathered right
there in order to just barely touch you do do that long enough and all
of that scattered mind dissipates because you've pulled it
together it's that gathering in that you do and everything
slows it just slows it's not that the thinking stops the thinking doesn't stop
at all but we steady it's like we're no longer rocking
now we're just walking upright and it keep keeps us from getting too caught up in the thoughts
and the feelings and all of the other energy that we've brought into the
exercise as it turns out this happens yeah even when you're not
meditating so have you ever noticed there's some people that always seem to be sort of chill right they just seem
they're always cool and every everybody's going crazy and there's this person who seems to be
just totally unaffected by it you ever wonder what's going on with
them how can they be that way so I started watching some people
and you know it was very similar to what that sleep center person was trying to
tell me about being grounded they simply did not engage in
the frenzy it just stopped
just stopping is is a form of momentto moment awareness where you
just say wait I don't have to do
that and in the moment of stopping you give yourself a moment of
rest a moment of gathering a moment of pulling yourself
together so that you can say ah things are crazy right now but I'm not
crazy and then you go back to attending to craziness but it gets you out of that
mode of being totally tied up in it it's a settling of the
mind that's what we're looking for a settling of the
mind that's the place from which we have a position for insights
now since what we do is Insight Meditation everybody wants to have
insights when was the last Insight you had you know I had one this
afternoon where I realized look what you're doing look what you're doing you're
running around you don't have to do that why don't you go for a
walk you're worrying about you can't can't find this reference why don't you go for a
walk the energy of being caught takes energy away from everything
that's going on and if you can just see oh this is what's happening and realize
you don't have to get in caught by it that's an Insight just the
realization I don't have to or when you
see um I my husband was trying a new recipe
this afternoon and one of the things he needed was black bean paste and he went to three grocery stores and could not
find black bean paste and so uh he came home and found out that he could substitute miso he was very excited
about that and I thought about a time where I was with I was helping somebody
in a kitchen we were making guacamole for 40 people and we had it all made up
and it had way way too much garlic in it I mean way too much
garlic and so the cook said do something with it so I started adding things and
he's and uh I I I don't remember it was 20 years ago so I don't remember what we
did I know it involved almonds but we kept adding things to
this trying to cut down on that garlic taste and keep you know something to it
and as it got more and more voluminous of course the garlic kind of dissipated
because there was more volume there to begin with and then finally we realized that the real problem was calling it
guacamole as soon as we gave it another name it tasted
wonderful it was great all we had to do was stop calling it guacamole
very often when we're looking for insights it's because we're looking for something in particular we want to
explain this thing and it's not only that we want it we want it to be
blue well what if we give that up what if we give up looking for what we think
is true and just say what's going on
here and get back to get closer to what the intention was in this case it was to
have a sauce to go with with the Mexican meal that involved
avocados but it did not have to be guacamole and it certainly didn't have
to be named that and everybody raved about that
sauce and they wanted the recipe and we just smiled like the Buddhas we were we had
no idea what was in it anymore
and we were free of it having to be a certain way free of it having to be a
certain way so much of our suffering is about having it to be a certain
way if you loved me you would bring me
flowers fill in the blanks we set up tests for
ourselves we set up tests for those around us we set up tests for how what
proves that we're doing the things right so part of what we need to do in this
practice is notice when we're setting up a false
test notice oh I'm unhappy here because
I want something to happen but what do I really want to have happen
it isn't that you do this thing it's that I want you to love me oh well maybe
I should change what I'm looking for I can see that only if my mind isn't
build busy Building stories around what I expect I can see that because my mind
has slowed down enough that I can see what's happening I gathered it together enough
that I can see oh this is what's happening this is the value of
concentration and the importance of concentration in the form of
Stillness steadiness of mind to develop the steadiness of
mind this is how we learn to be nonreactive by coming to a place of
saying ah I can take a breath here
it doesn't have to look this way it doesn't have to be this
way we can we can come to a Still Point you know if when the pendulum
swings it goes back and forth back and forth and a certain place it changes
Direction but it doesn't really stop it just there's kind of a null point the
same thing is true in your breath when you're breathing in and breathing out at a certain point nothing's
happening catch that point where nothing's happening familiarize yourself with
nothing's happening because we're very often in a race for something to be
happening concentration is going to look like this so if it doesn't look like this I'm not concentrated
the mind is still working so I must be the Mind must be too busy so there's something wrong with my thinking there's
something wrong with my meditating there's something wrong with instead of looking there's something wrong with if
we can just say ah this is what's happening doubt is
here but I'm not doubtful doubt is
here I can come to a zero point point where I don't have to call it good or
bad me or not me I can just be here in this null's
place so tan is a a famous fasan teacher and he said the work of awareness is
just to know the work of wisdom is to differentiate between skillful and
unskillful it's when we see when things are happening and how we're contributing
to what is making them skillful or unskillful that we can discern the
difference this is what we call wisdom it's not that we suddenly know something
that we didn't know before what we know is ah it's what I'm naming this that is
at fault here it is trying to see things a certain way instead of how they are
that is at fault here the skillful thing is to see see this is what's really
happening where we learn to discern between skillful and unskillful
skillful this is what's happening with each Insight we see where
we get caught and when we're free of that being
caught when am I tied up with something and when am I free of that being tied up
we see wanting it to this be this way is what's making me
unhappy you know it used to be at every holiday I would make four or five
different Entre because everybody in my family was on a different diet and I would drive myself crazy
trying to make everything perfect for everyone and I was miserable and I
couldn't figure out why I was trying so hard why I was so miserable and it's
because I wasn't actually getting to spend any time with my family how did I know whether they were
happy or not happy I was totally blowing it because I
was saying if I do this then they'll be happy and I'll be happy but doing this was exactly
wrong making five different Entre was crazy it was only when I told everybody
bring your own entree that I started at having a good
time so simple so
simple and the first time someone told me you know you're being unhappy is your
own fault I just about threw her out of the room but it was true it was my own fault
it was not what I wanted it's had to look like what I
wanted that's what was causing the the suffering being able to still the Mind
draw it together is what allows us to see
clearly the pause oh that's
happening no blame just oh that's what's happening because then we know what to
do then we know what's skillful or if we don't know we can try
the next thing and we'll say well that worked or that didn't work I can try something
else but we're not repeatedly trying to do the same thing we can discern the
difference we stop trying to make the guacamole better and we read
name it and we realize what we really want is the sauce that just happens to
use avocados and a little
garlic so I'm going to read you a poem this is called this Shining Moment In
the now it's by David budbill this is the wrong time of year
for this poem but I like the ending so I'm going to read it anyway when I work Outdoors all day
every day as I do now in the fall getting ready for winter tearing up the garden digging potatoes Gathering the
squash cutting firewood making kindling repairing bridges over the brook clearing trails in the woods doing the
last of the Fall mowing pruning apple trees taking down the screens putting up the storm windows banking the house all
these things as preparations for the coming cold when I'm every day all day
all body and no mind when I'm all physically wholly and completely in this
world with the birds the deer the sky the wind the trees when day after day I
think of nothing but what the next chore is when I go from clearing Woods roads to sharpening a chainsaw to changing the
oil in a mower to stacking wood when I'm all body and no mind when I am only here
and now and nowhere else then and only then do I see the crippling power of
mind the curse of thought and I pause and wonder why I so seldom find this
Shining Moment In the now when I am only here and now and
nowhere else then and only then do I see the crippling power of mind the curse of
thought and I pause and wonder why am I so seldom why I so seldom find this
Shining Moment In the now
in the midst of all the work all the activities all
of the cares that you normally do can truly be found The Shining Moment
In the now you simply have to notice
it The Shining Moment In the now this is what I wish for you thank
you so we have time for questions
comments
objections yes
um I'm really relating to what you were talking about
how um how uncon
concentrated we can get and the mindfulness goes away sometimes
um and uh just last week I had an incident that I couldn't I was very
upset from something that someone said which wasn't true and and um
I I was upset I didn't want to react but by doing that it was uh kind
of was bothering me and I was trying to look at it to
meditate and observe it and embrace it and you know go through the process to
to be able to let it go and get a good sleep I lost the sleep over
it um that's one thing that I keep asking that there are moments and I
actually like last last Monday you you explained it to me that
um I I just at at some moments you you
you lose the concentration you lose the awareness of what's going on so when
that happens and it happens what I
notice so so when Ang arises in
me because I've watched it a lot I used to have a lot of trouble with anger I
can feel it in my belly before it comes to my head that I'm angry so I have an
early clue and I realize uhoh I need to pay attention to what's happening here
because I'm aware of that I'm getting angry the thing about
anger or hurt any kind of reactivity is there are chemical things that happen
in your body right so when you're angry you have adrenaline and it's shooting
through your body and no matter what you're doing in your mind you've got to deal with the adrenaline in the body so
know that know okay there's energy here there's a
lot of energy here and when you stop for just a
moment I have just a moment to remember remember that I have an intention toward
kindness okay so is it more important to be right or kind we're in the quality of discernment
here but the energy is up I need to do something with that
energy because I I can't consider because I've stopped and I'm an
intention to be kind I haven't burst out okay but the person can see it in my
face I'm sure Telegraph everything my arms are waving I've learned about my arms waving
when I'm angry so I will go and wash my hands I will do something physical with
my hands that is not directed toward the other person I pay attention to the fact that there's adrenaline in my body that
I have to deal with it's a matter of where do you place
your awareness are you going to leave your awareness are you going to fight the
guacamole or you just going to Fig okay I got to deal with the fact that this is this is
happening when you stay with something like well I'm hurt by this person you
don't step out of the story when you move into the body of oh this body is
aching now you have something you can work with and you're not tied up in the
story when you're in the story explaining it justifying it
understanding it it just repeats it and restarts the emotional cycle over and over and over again somehow you have to
step out of the story one of my favorite stories was
when um uh I have just begun a diet and it
was a very very strict diet and I had to eat every four or five hours because I
got hypoglycemic and uh my husband was going to fix dinner and he had this elaborate
plan for dinner and I said you know I'm really I'm hungry and he kept saying it and I said I'm hungry and pretty soon I
was yelling at him and I left the room and I came back seconds later I was
yelling again I left the room I left the room three times the third time I came back he handed me a carrot which was
just the right thing I couldn't do anything about the fact I was hypoglycemic leaving the room wasn't
good enough but we somehow managed to communicate I'm hungry forget anything
fancy this woman needs to put food in her body because she's falling apart it was nobody's fault you step
away from it's somebody's fault and you deal with this is what's happening I hope that helps yeah helps a
lot because um I definitely when I um I
get you know excited or I get angry I feel it right here and what what you're
saying is that pay attention to that pay attention to that that's really do
something about that yes yes locate it go for a walk yeah tell somebody you
know I got a break now that's true thank you consider it when that is not driving
it thank you so anybody else
yeah you um so I'm like pretty new to like
meditation um and I feel like when I am uh meditating I struggle to find
direction and I think that uh can lead to a lack of concentration so what are
some like basic like productive things to focus on would you say um in meditation well the first thing is focus
on your breath right I mean I what kind of medic do do that kind of meditation
yeah that's what I've started with um and uh I just uh don't know if there are
other like things prodive so one thing that do you are you familiar with
meta okay so there's a form of meditation called meta in which one has
a series of phrases that are wishing oneself well others well and
there's a series that you can step through but you you begin with yourself and so uh I might
say uh silently to myself may I be filled with loving
kindness may I be well may I be peaceful and at ease may I be happy so those are
phrases that are very familiar to me and I would mentally repeat those to myself over and over and over and over it forms
a kind of Mantra gives the Mind something to do it is in fact a con concentration practice and so when I'm
really having a difficult time I'll spend maybe the first five or 10 minutes of my sit doing that and that will tend
to to slow me down and settle and it's rhythmic the way that I've arranged my
phrases so it kind of lulls me into to that settling and then I go back to to
my breath and I follow my breath and I set that aside So Meta practice has a particular
purpose for softening the heart which often is the problem when we
can't concentrate we we have things on our mind we have irritations that are
bothering us and there's a kind of rigidity in place and we have to be able
to relax a little bit in order to get that concentration and sometimes that relaxation involves softening our
attitude of mind which also is a benefit of meta practice it's the primary reason
I do meta practice is to soften my heart so that's one suggestion I have
it's sort of oh okay and then then it's
okay I'm here and this is what I'm doing now and I'm doing this because I wish
myself well and that that's often a big big help thank you so much
anyone else okay it's been a pleasure being with you
I wish you all well good night