so welcome folks um happy to uh to be with you yeah it's sweet to see familiar
names um so what are we going to do we're going to
meditate as I was sitting just before this uh for a few
minutes what came to mind I don't know where from why maybe because I'm tired
but as a kid good night Moon that was like a bedtime ritual
situation and um uh yeah and I have not thought about
that book in a long time good night Moon and uh but it came up as I was
sitting and it was like okay good night
memories good night pain good night thoughts it's good night
feelings good night
Matthew and uh maybe that's our uh those are our
meditation instructions it's just like okay blessing all these pieces of
experience with uh um that kind of Gentle Spirit I love
the rhythm of obviously the book is so famous because kids love it you know
it's like oh yeah there's something about rhythmically moving through
everything that needs to be put down everything we say good night to and
um and so maybe we just take our cues from that tonight and
uh look to all the things we might just bid good night
too so that unusual instructional note let us uh
yeah good night Dua let us uh let us sit
okay
so maybe we uh begin with a few deep breaths
the in breath enlivening awakening
us the out breath
soothing the energy of our body as if like running our hand over sand on the
beach just smoothing it now
and to say uh good night Moon not to brace
against or avoid or
it's just this um very gentle gesture of putting something
down and so we sort of like palpate our psychospiritual
body what uh needs to be put
down but lingered from the day or the week or this
life e
it's almost like when we've bid a good night to something when we fully actually blessed its presence
there's no more stickiness to it
and so becomes possible
to let it be in the
background for the kind of gravitational force
field of that Loop of thought or that memory that plan that sensation
to take its place Miss uh
much more open vast
field
e
e e
it can be painful to thoughts can be painful painful to
think but also can be painful not to
think somehow to renounce some of our preoccupations but
maybe maybe it feels okay to do this very
gently good night Moon
and one of the things we're left
with is the
uh effortlessness of our
breathing
e e
the awareness is uh very gentle with our
breathing e
sometimes it feels like the attention is inside the
breath and sometimes it's like the breath
arises amidst the vast
openness
e e
just gently bidding good night so
whatever can be put down
when we put something down we're not saying I'll never pay attention to you
just that uh phenomena need to be more patient
just placing all of your hope
into this
moment
e
e e
letting any uh fatigue the sweetness of uh
fatigue soothe uh everything
just leaving brightness awareness in its
wake
e
e e
okay um
so there are probably uh a lot of different different rhythms that run
through a practice life different phases and and some of those phases are
really maybe not discernable we because we can only
perceive some small segment of our um existence we sort of go to what
naturally we can perceive what's conscious what awareness can
penetrate and so we we maybe uh
over read some of that some some aspects some fa kind of
phases of practice are Maybe not discernable but we kind of know
something is happening something's changing something the tectonic plates of my being are rumbling but I don't
know what is going on some phases are maybe discernable but
we can make sense of them but only after a long period of
retrospection looking back you know and I I had a long
phase that I was not conscious of being in but it was like years years and it
was only when I kind of like woke up from it that there was like oh that was
there was some some kind of the Mind was tinged
with some measure of disillusionment maybe on the slightly nihilistic side
somehow and and uh and it wasn't it wasn't uh kind of you know an obvious
thing and so it only actually registered after the fact it's almost like you
can't see it until you have something new to contrast it
to and um a friend last last week um said um
she Dharma Dharma teacher you know close close
friend actually just before I went into to teach and she said she felt like I've
been been holding grief as a kind of fundamental Bedrock of the
universe and she said that in the the kind of attempts to Def kind of defend
grief from spiritual bypassing I had reified it my attempt to
defend it against you know the charge of being just another afflictive emotion I
had somehow reified grief as this kind of like non-negotiable Bedrock of the
universe which we could make the case for it that to actually look deeply is
to to appreciate uh the necessity of
grief but she went on to say that um that
um suggests not that I use my kind of like vasana laser to dissolve it into
anich to dissolve the grief into just empty
phenomena but her suggestion was instead to appreciate what what is even bigger
than the grief and she didn't say what what but I
think she meant love awareness no okay it's a phase I've been
in it's hard to tell what phase we're in you know but um the Dharma does go in
phases and I think the last time I spoke two weeks ago I talked about um coming
home and leaving home the ways that Dharma is is a way of Reawakening old
loves you know dormant loves things we've loved before coming home and a way of learning
to love new things leaving home and there's
another kind of uh discernable rhythm in
practice that maybe we characterize as something like cruising altitude and
upheaval so
um we uh we come to to practice
um with pains with questions with problems with some need and sometimes
somehow those things get resolved they actually do it's like practice fulfilled
its promise it it it met the need and maybe we have an Insight or a
problem just kind of it dissolves or
it's still there but it doesn't have the same weight on the heart and there's some burden that gets
shed and um that's beautiful and then we kind of get comfortable in that
understanding and it feels so good and we kind of
maybe cruise at that altitude for a while and that's that's genuinely good
practice it's comfortable it feels good I'm not trying
to uh suggest there's something UNH wholesome about that right because it's
like that sense of like oh yeah we constantly have to be growing the urge to always be growing is
often just another case example of greed okay that my cruising altitude the
Dharma feels uh like home this understanding feels like
home and I thought of there there some there a little bit of a strange parallel but some parallel with um if you're
familiar with the the philosophy of science and uh Coon's normal science
science the the kind of nature of scientific uh
Discovery um science is often at a kind of cruising altitude science is working
contentedly within a paradigm tinkering and making advant you know
advances and generally quite orderly but then in Coon's view
something happens in science there's enough anomalous data enough
inconsistency enough uh um enough data that doesn't fit well into the old
Paradigm and then there's a kind of Scientific Revolution and the criteria by which one
might judge the old Paradigm doesn't really work for judging the new paradigm
there's no common standard of comparison and it's hard to know what's
true or how to compare the past with the present and that sense of being in a new
land a new land this is how practice is sometimes sometimes we're tinkering and
sometimes there's some kind of Revolution and it might be something
that's great and beautiful it might be painful and bewildering but there's
anomalous data and you have this sense of like the old Paradigm my old way of
framing the Dharma my old way of understanding my path it can't contain
this data anymore there's enough anomalous data
that there's some kind of break and you realize that the story
you've been living in feel obsolete the vision you had the Dharma
has to give way the rug the rug the Dharma rug gets pulled out from under
us and that happens with Insight that happens with grief or pain or some Shock
to the system and it's like ah the old Paradigm will not be able to accommodate
this and there's often a sense of um of
disorientation disorientation you kind of don't know well how to judge or assess this
new land I don't know who I am in this new realm I don't know what is left of
me after that Insight that love that loss that grief that
whatever the old standards don't really
work right and that sense of disorientation that can be really
dramatic or it can be more subtle it happens you know at a kind
of micro level anytime our model of who
we are gets challenged right we sort of
like have to tolerate a measure of disorient orentation so when somebody says
that question you know that horrible question can I offer you some
feedback like oh no it's almost like the the cage of self
like starts rattling immediately you know and then okay you get some feedback
and this might literally be feedback from somebody but this may be just the
feedback of the world right and sometimes the attachment to self-
view is only apparent when that cage gets
shaken and so uh this can happen at the level of
practice more generally not just something being rattled but like the
whole of one being gets rattled the familiarity of the
view all of the familiar kind of reference points and the frames and the
language the connotations the stories we have used to um stabilize a sense of
identity a sense of what practice is sense of our life project that gets disrupted
and you can appreciate like how your
your yeah your prior understanding the prior story you would tell about the darma
about yourself somehow and I don't say it pejoratively
it's very tender but it's like somehow all of that the story was just a
little naive to wake up is to wake up to
more and so our previous understanding of myself of what I was doing here of
what the Buddha's offering is it somehow failed to fully appreciate the
complexity of Being Human you know maybe
we failed to fully appreciate just how deep suffering can
run or maybe we fail fail you know failed to appreciate just
how wide love can be and maybe it's interesting to
consider to use the C parallel with
just how much anomalous data is required in your life
to usher in the next
Revolution when can you feel like the Paradigm the story I tell of me my life
is just like can no longer quite contain that anomalous
data and then something breaks
open and this is not a way of saying we should
always be in periods of upheaval but to appreciate this
cycle normal normal science
Revolution normal life normal Dharma practice
disruption that cycle just keeps going as far as I can tell just keeps
deepening each time we shed some measure of naive each time our heart
grows in uh subtlety and
sensitivity and then we rest we hit our cruising
altitude and know that um there will be
uh turbulence some other time and that will be an
opportunity so I offer this for your uh consideration and U wish you all a
lovely uh lovely week and we'll see you see you next time be back next week same
place okay