so normally when I come here on Sunday morning I give a Dharma talk and part of
the purpose of giving a Dharma talk is somehow to convey the
Dharma and if I don't have a Dharma talk on my heart if I give a Dharma talk
anyway then I'm probably not going to convey the Dharma Dharma talk shouldn't be forced
or be contrived or be and um and
so uh I think that the better way of conveying the Dharma today is uh just
tell you I don't have a Dharma talk and to um use this time for your
questions and I'm happy to try to respond the best I can and maybe in those wonderful exchanges that the
Dharma will be born here at IMC so um do any any of you have anything
you'd like to ask or topic or something then we can take some time to
you think about it you weren't prepared for this
what do you personally think happens when we
die yes so so I personally believe that um if the dying goes
well to you know it's not too sudden or not too much too much pain or mental
kind of chemistry changes that if it goes well that that
process is very much like the process of Letting Go in very deep meditation and
in very deep meditation that process of letting go is so good it's like some of the very best things that can happen to
a person the greatest happiness the greatest peace the greatest meaning it just gets better and better the deeper
the letting go is and so I look forward to dying I look forward to that process
of dying if I'm lucky enough for it to be you know a good death because I have a strong very strong Association that
it'll just be this process that I already know and it just gets better the more you let go so so it's just I look
forward to that process and I don't know what that I don't know what happens at the you know the final letting go but
the F it has to be good does that answer your question well
enough yes yes so I have been reading the Tibetan Book of the Dead and as you know
they're they they believe in reincarnation and the BAU is the time
between when you die and when you get your new life if you do get a new life um I'm sure you're aware of this
book and uh I mean what are your thoughts on that because it's it's the book itself is kind of complicated to
read it's kind of what complic ated oh I see they talk about all these deities
and all these you know demons and and the light is really bright and shining in your eyes so
it's yes so uh uh well the title of the book says a lot for me because it's it's
a Tibetan book of of dying living and dying and um the um we're not in the
Tibetan tradition here and uh we're in the terad Buddhist tradition and and in
in the inside the terad tradition we're much more rooted in the earliest part of that tradition uh in you know the
earliest teachings of the recorded recorded teachings of the Buddha and so uh we don't share the same
world viiew as the Tibetans and so we don't share the idea there's a BAU period we don't share the
same cosmology of the that they have and the same relationship to it so um you
know I I wish them well and with their worldview we have a different worldview
but I I do have a uh several uh colleagues from Burma who are very
devout Buddhists and they very firmly believe in reincarnation I don't know about yeah yeah the other Realms or what
have you but they do firmly believe in reincarnation generally generally this is a minor maybe semantic issue uh
generally in Buddhism we don't use the word reincarnation is sometimes used in tibetan Buddhist circles in English but
uh we tend to in our T Traditions usually rebirth has a little different
connotation and um and it's true most Buddhists believe in
rebirth but they don't believe but terad don't believe in the Bardo it the people who believe in
rebirth in terad and Buddhism see it as kind of an instant process you die and
then move on to the next round
oh thank you okay thank you hello
um I turn it off
okay what's your name my name is Pearson hi yeah good to meet you um I had a
question about um kind of like the origins of fear and anxiety um specifically when it comes to
like things that that you logically understand are not a real threat to you but like right now my my blood is
pumping faster I feel like a pressure social pressure where does that come
from how do you kind of start to feel comfortable dealing with it yeah
wonderful I love the question thank you and uh yeah so uh fear anxiety distress
anger all kinds of emotions like that I I kind of like to understand them as to
the perceivable response to the world we live in or the imagination which we live
in and um and what we want to do in this practice is not stop at the
perceivable and we want to be careful not to give a lot of authority to the perceivable emotions we have and or to
be invested in them or to identify with them and at the same time we don't want to disrespect them and so to not
identify with them not assign a lot of meaning meaning and
value to them and and to repeat the importance of it to respect them um and
then to doing so to begin discovering uh the less perceivable Source within of
where they come from and and it's in particular that they come from they have
the the where they come from uh as often there is a place inside where it uh we
have a a Caring Heart we have a place of care of of uh caring for ourselves
caring for the world a capacity for love and compassion capacity for goodness
that often is not so perceivable especially if we have these strong emotions on the
surface and so uh so for
you what sense what experience do you have of that less perceivable Source in
you what's my experience of the less perceivable yeah that's underneath all those emotions you're asking about I
mean um I mean it's like a desire to connect and feel comfortable I think at
the end of the day I think that's fantastic and then if you take one step further that desire to be connected and
feel comfortable what has to be there before that
yeah I mean I think I'm still rooted too fast in know and like trying to escape
the pain that I don't know where the origin of it it comes from oh so but
then that was a great answer so underneath this desire to be comfortable and connected there is some pain
so we would hold that pain like this so we would go through from the perceivable
and we would that that's a that's a profound from in our point of view it's a very profound answer you provided so
then that that pain uh probably needs your care your
attention and what part of you can offer that care to to your pain
and it's maybe not a what question but I like I like very much how you've been work wording this so maybe I say where
in you from where within you can you offer care to your own
pain not to be corny but from my heart I mean I guess from the center I don't know from the origin right where it came
from uhhuh before I was in pain I guess I don't know wonderful so so from my
point of view these are profound answers you provided for your own question and so that's that's you you know that's the
wear that you're asking about what's underneath it all and that's where we in this practice that's where we're going
to rest there and to trust there and allow something to new to
emerge uh in that care to the depths within us that cannot emerge if we're
giving a lot of authority identification to these perceivable
emotions thank you thank you I hope it was okay to do this with you ask these questions yeah absolutely I appreciate
it thank you thank
you I guess yeah so I have a question about
um working with pleasures of the flesh and developing a relationship to
Pleasures that aren't of the flesh so I'm wondering if you could address that a little bit and maybe refer it to some
pudas Etc so he's asking a question that comes from the ancient language um so
little contextualize that the Buddha distinguished um the honic experiences
we can have a Pleasure and Pain into two categories and uh the most common way
that this is translated into English is um is uh spiritual and worldly but it
turns out that the literal uh wording that the Buddha used was of the Flesh and not of the flesh but that kind of
doesn't quite speak to something profound for many people in the west so
there are uh surface Pleasures that we can have that are worldly in the sense
that they have to do with um something in the world World pleasing our senses
so it could be as simple as going out and feeling the sunlight in a cold day and feeling the warmth and feeling the
pleasure it could be eating nice food and not only feeling the pleasure of the
tasty sweet food or something but uh if uh you're with
someone who says you know is caring for you you're distressed and Afraid or
something and you're cold and they said come with me my friend let's go stand and the sun together now there's another
pleasure that's there that's not just the pleasure of the sun warming you up but it's the some deeper pleasure that's
not exactly of the Flesh of the being accompanied by your friend and so wow I
mean and that might actually be more nourishing than the sun or uh someone provides you with a
wonderful meal but the person who does it like my grandmother when I was maybe
eight or seven I would I would lay in bed in Norwegian bed this wooden kind of
all wood Norwegian little room when I grew up in Norway and sunlight coming through in the early morning and as they
comforter and I'd be reading Donald Duck magazines and she would come with a
tray with uh milk and toast with Norwegian goat cheese on it and I just
took it for granted when I was seven or eight but that has stayed with me my whole life since then as a as an
expression of of a profound pleasure not of the Flesh of not of the you know you
know spiritual almost the love that she conveyed the care and which she offered so uh so there's all this whole
these two different dimensions and that to go deep into the Dharma we need to appreciate this second dimension not to
dismiss pleasures of the of the flesh this worldly pleasures some of them can
be very helpful wonderful inspiring and some of them can be deadly
some of them can ruin lives can ruin societies can ruin
families uh and uh so that's a world that needs a lot of care and uh and a
lot of love and needs a lot of friends to take you out into the sun uh to make
sure that you know something deeper in you is nourished and supported and um but the Dharma practice
really wants to support this you know this uh spiritual side or
this not of the flesh side or this I like to I like to call it profound you
know I don't really like the word spiritual too often and I don't really like the word of the flesh for this but
I like to say more surface pleasures and profound pleasures and the Dharma Dharma
um movement is to start becoming sensitive and aware of these deeper
profound possibilities of well-being that's in here and to nourish that to
and to and just recognizing it is part of the nourishment because many people
uh haven't even ever learned to tune into that part of themselves uh they're so busy being busy they're so busy being
busy that uh that they don't have time for it and so the easy thing is to get be busy than just picking up the sensual
Pleasures here and there and get somehow get distracted even more from really feeling what's here in a deep way
and um and there's a profound pleasure I don't know pleasure is the right word but profound
rightness in feeling our life from this deep inner place that even if it's pain
it just feels so right now I'm with the truth and then as we begin sensitive to
this deeper place of feeling and sensing the profundity then uh to start when
it's there start recognizing the goodness that's there the well being that's there so that can grow and that
can grow and fill us and create a very different context for how we live our life than the life that's dependent on
being comfortable in the world externally is that
adequate thank you so up here
Scott and take a stab at circling kind of combining two questions that have been asked I want to Circle back
to well I think most of us I do certainly sort of suffer from a little bit from our psychosocial stress like
right now I'm talking to you I have to answer in [Laughter]
publicly uh so uh we could sort of dial into the
sematic experience of that and then you want to go a little deeper and I'm
looking sort of okay what maybe what am I clinging to and I see these like the
ill Winds of like sort of a thirst for recognition and then insignificance kind
of at the other end of that and
um on the other hand those aren't entirely unhealthy I mean we've probably
evolved from small bands of humans and it was very important to get along with our
bandmates um so are you sort of suggesting for the last answer with Richard that we sort of befriend a
little bit even even that discomfort in the sense
absolutely we should be befriending everything everything needs our
friendship everyone knew okay so in a way maybe just like our reaction to this
discomfort is really just piling it's it's not helpful yeah it's making a much
worse or not useful I I don't so uh yes I could say yes to your what you just
said but I would be reluctant to live in a world where that's the response um I
would uh just be ready to just resp to meet everything with care with love with
friendship whatever it might be and you said earlier that you know we I think you said you know we have an
evolutionary conditioning to respond with fear maybe with anger with all
kinds of is ways and um and yes that's true the problem becomes and again you
said at the beginning the clinging to it or I said earlier the identification with it or the give granting it
Authority we do all kinds of extra things we lay on top of it and um I
don't know if some of you have seen this I had a wonderful movie called uh I think it's called the perfect day or
perfect day I think it's perfect days right plural right perfect days and
uh it's a movie about cleaning toilets in Japan and uh about a toilet cleaner and
it's a people who have done uh Zen training in monasteries that I know who seen the movie recognize oh this is Zen
training this is like they they just love it and um and that's a whole movie
and um but the in my mind well maybe I should I shouldn't give away the end should I
[Laughter] well if you see the
end then you'll get part of my response to [Laughter]
you that movie had been recommended to me I haven't seen it yes so see it to
the end it all it all comes it all come all be it becomes the the movie perfect days
becomes perfect in the last scene so
here so you can mik here
yeah thank you um maybe this is just another variation of the other questions
that I've been asked but I'm thinking more and more about how to respond to violence political violence um I was
just somewhere recently where someone had a different political
perspective and they were forcing it on me and I felt fear of course I felt fear for my family of
course of course how do I both respond with
love and with safety of
course you know you know who John Lewis is
was John Lewis had a lot of reasons to be afraid growing up as he did in the
South the time he did I think that he got beat up three
times maybe more in his efforts to uh to
change the violent segregated
South there's a beautiful story I think of um he was in a bus stop
and the member of the Klux Clan came and of course he had reasons to be
afraid when they showed up he was doing a demonstr you know nonviolent Civil
Disobedience and uh one of them beat him up in
1961 in 2009 the man uh elwin
Wilson came to the office his office off he was a congressman so he came to his office in Washington DC with his own son
and came to ask for forgiveness it took 48
years for uh John Lewis's willingness to stand
there and love rather than succumb to his fear to change this man's
heart it's quite phenomenal and uh and John Lewis then went on
1963 I think to do the march from Montgomery to
Selma and he was in the front of that line the police gave him two the group
two minutes to disperse after 1 minute and 5 Seconds they started beating him
and the were others he was the first one to be beaten they they fractured his
skull six months later the president of United States Lyndon Johnson signed the
Civil Rights Act that U his willingness to stand
there and not be afraid but to love instead change the
country so I respect a lot your fear fear of
your family and there's a lot of hatred in our society but I think our society won't
change if we get caught in our own fear that the the task of especially
this practice that we have here to really help us find a way to uh to um be
the change we want to see in our society so that's one of the reasons why
this this you know this deep profound place that we talked the Richard's question about this this spiritual or I
call profound or there's reason to go in under the layers and find out what's there is so that we can tap into a very
different way to respond to the world and to ourselves with love with care
with respect so we can be the change we want to see in the world and respond
accordingly but it comes with risks and I don't think we can avoid
that but what world do you want your children I don't if you have children but to grow up into what do you want to
what do you want to pass on to them and I'll tell you this story I've told the story a few times about what we pass on
to our kids uh there was a many years ago there was when I was teaching Retreats there
was a woman who kept coming in my Retreats practicing sincerely and then she came to me one
day and said I have cancer but I have this young child I don't know 10 years old or
so and I really don't want to die so she did everything she could just to live
and then she came to retreat sometime later and said um done everything I could
do but I'm I'm going to die that's the diagnosis now and she was really
angry and I said to her if you die angry
that's going to create uh that's going to condition probably your child's whole
future life the child's going to see that the response of anger is response
which uh around this fear anger is really going to be you know a message
about what it's like to to live as a human being in this world but if you could somehow and a in a in a healthy
way resolve your anger and be able to die peacefully that will uh change your
your daughter son your little child's uh life the rest of their life
and then at some point after the woman died the husband called me and said that
she had died and when she died both her and the CH him he and the child were there and uh they both went out into the
garden and got a flower and came back in and put it on her chest and when I heard
that little vignette I thought okay she she died peacefully so how you live with this
world that's so difficult and so much risk and fear um uh
there's a there's a I hope a loving challenge to you that not from me but
from your own heart to meet it in a different way and and find a way to do
that courageously is that an okay answer you want to answer I want to respect the
question do you want to ask anything more or thank you thank you
um when should one seek a teacher and how does one seek a
teacher because there is um how should I
know I guess this in in this journey there's always the feeling of being lost and uh at times it feels like
there's someone needs a teacher but then it never yes the journey is difficult at
times but how does one seek a teacher is my question I think having a teacher to to
support one in practice is invaluable and I've had a number of teachers I I probably I'm very confident if I didn't
have my teachers didn't have a fellow practitioners to practice with that I
probably wouldn't have practiced as much as I have so I really depended on that
support all around and uh and how one finds a teacher that really is works for you as
a person is kind of like um magic or or the chemistry of it and you know it's
it's unknown so one possibility is to go spend time with different teachers until
you feel a resonance with someone or you feel really trust in someone or feel inspired by what they they have and even
then you want to be careful the Buddha himself said that you used to hang out with a teacher for some time before you
decide to be their student uh to really feel confident that you know them and
know their different know their quirks he didn't say that but but um but uh know their ethics know
who they are and um and so don't don't be quick in choosing someone but so you
kind of look around and search around there is a kind of common maybe folklore and spiritual circles that um that the
teacher will find you not because they're looking for you but somehow it'll happen kind of when you're
not looking exactly um but you have to do your part which is to so you can nowadays you can
listen to people's Dharma talks online and see if you know to check out many
people really quickly and um but that's the work you have to do and then when you find
someone that you feel some resonance with um uh in some spiritual circles
some Buddha circles uh you have to have a certain amount of um healthy
assertiveness to go ask the teacher what you know how they're
available or are they available and or what does it mean to be a student for you if I want to I want to study with
you what does it mean to study with you how does that work and and um and different teachers will have different
answers and you can hear the answers I'm I'm causing trouble for myself
now uh they uh when they hear the answer then that helps you understand also if this
is the right person for you is this an okay qu answer thank
you so now
here uh so how would you explain or describe the benefits or the purpose of
meditation to somebody who has an experience that who doesn't know anything about
meditation I think it it's so contextual so it's you know without having the context it's a little hard to how to
answer I but the how would be I would try to do it very briefly I would try to
say something that's memorable to them and uh so not to go into a whole
Treatise and bring out the clinical studies and uh so so um so for example I might
say something like so you can really be your yourself you know that that's pretty
vague but it's but it's memorable and it's meaningful for some people and oh
what does that mean or yes that that sounds like a healthy good thing and so what we I wouldn't say is yes when you
can really be yourself uh you go beyond yourself you know but but I might say
that at your in context so rather than saying so you could really be yourself I might say to someone else I might say um
maybe they it might maybe they already have a meditation practice and be doing it for a while and so they know it all
and so or they have a spiritual practice or some kind so they kind of have already have some sensibility I might say uh uh just that
that oh uh so you can really be yourself so you can go beyond
yourself so is but uh I mean there's I can give many more answers but are you
asking for yourself uh no uh more just trying to understand like uh from the
perspective of like say an average person who doesn't know anything about Buddhism or kind of the benefits of meditation like what's a good kind of
short answer to give to explain to them why they might be interested in yeah so it's again so so contextual someone else
I might say um it's really a good way to distress you know we have so much stress
in our society this is a really good way to kind of settle and and it's probably you know it's it's a healthy way of
finding it to just d-stress you know all someone else I might say uh
this is how you get to see the truth the truth of yourself so there's all these answers so um you know if uh I
don't I I don't want to again I'm causing trouble for myself but what would be really
interesting fascinating is to have a teacher maybe like me some other teacher uh go around and answer that question
for each of you because I bet the question the answer will be different for each one of
you yes
Morgan so um I have a question that relates to somewhat uh the earlier
questions and that in meditation has become very popularized so to speak so
if and I run into people that are that have a meditation practice without the
other part and so I feel sometimes I'm walking a line that you I'm not trying
to proze or you know to tell them how joyful it can be to add Buddhism to it
and so I don't know how to navigate that somehow because sometimes I feel that uh
maybe I am pushing the Buddhism part because it's so rich with yeah you know
it can enhance the other part yeah so I'm not sure how to navigate that um
well F we'll answer your question but uh I just want to First say that I love that you're asking the question because
I think it comes from someplace deep in you and would you ever mind saying
something about that depth
um why I'm asking the question yeah well because you know when we talk about the
the sanha in the the Buddhist circles and so I find that um
I enjoy it the friendships more when I can learn from them too so some of my
friends become my teachers uh when they're rooted in the same practice that I have great but I like to be open and
uh when when I'm talking to people about you know recently I've had a a new
friend that started to to meditate and she likes it she's in France and she she
she has been following on YouTube so I'm I'm not sure when or if I should even
talk about the other side yes yes CU I don't want to turn her off from the meditation uhhuh so um well thank you it
was great to have that context for you from you personally for that question and um so what you said in response to
mine was my question was that a lot of do with had to do with the friendship and the support of the SAA friends and
all that so I think my first answer to you is without telling you you're being being her sa friend uh just be her
friend with her meditation practice be the supporter of it be just kind of you
know be there to you know maybe talk about it a little bit
with her or share your experience in meditation or just kind of say you know there's you know find find ways to
without making without telling her anything about Buddhism and just say you know just kind of accompany her a little
bit on her meditation path so be be that friend for her without touching the other parts of it
well I think that what I just said now is would be the first first line the first thing to approach and but then
it's okay within a certain with with a certain uh certain
um Simplicity to say something like you
know uh this uh I see you're meditating some and listening to the talk some and
um you know there's uh I found so much value to be in the S to have other Dharma friends who share this practice
with um you know if you'd like to come with me to IMC one day or uh you know
let's go together so you you're giving her the message but you're doing it in such a way that um you're
not poking her at it with it you're not like s telling her that she should but
you're you're say this is what I found useful and here you know it's available to you and if you like to come with me
I'll you happy to go with you um so keep it really simple and uh and that's
enough I I think Kirk was had his hand up be first in the
back so first of all thank you Gil and thank you everybody this this is really
helpful for me and my question has to do with courage because when you were
talking with this gentleman's question about John Lewis and standing up there and um it it took a lot of Courage I'm
sure and so if you could share some thoughts about that and how one can actess courage in their own life and
then I also want to just add that uh courage um comes in French the word
kurur is your heart so that just occurred to me that there's some heart going on with courage but if you could
say something about that uh and you know I I don't know your context in your life well enough but uh
as a so I want to be careful what I say and just talk a little bit in generalities maybe and hope it maybe
fits is that um uh you let begin your
courage with having courage to face yourself to be with yourself sit and
meditate in a courageous posture which maybe means sitting up a
little bit straighter and taking a stance internal psychological stance to really like your
be courageous and then be really honest about what's happening with you
uh I like I I I a wonderful for me a wonderful synonym for mindfulness or for
meditation is honesty so you know it's um you know you
asked about what's you know what's the benefits from meditation um to me that's I would for
some people I would say um that oh meditation is just a way of being
honest and uh and it's being honest with yourself a radical truthtellah
so maybe start with yourself and and do it in a more in a deeper more more
thorough way maybe you've ever had been before I don't I don't associate you with being a dishonest
person but uh but to really know yourself and there might be some context in
life where uh that process is supported maybe put yourself in situations where
you normally shut down or reactive or afid and really take that courageous
stance maybe in your meditation or mindfulness and really start being with the fullness of yourself in that uh if
you have a really good friend uh you might ask the friend say to the friend
what I just instructing you to do or suggesting to you and uh and ask them if
there's any any direction that they understand about your life or you think it would be useful for you to be more
honest about for yourself or see the truth of they don't have to have the answer answer they just oh it just you
know I think it might have to do with some quality of the heart that needs needs your attention
they might be that vague but uh but that's so that's my response I hope that's
okay question yes this will can be the last one
thanks so this uh conversation reminds me of a teacher I had in grad school a
guy named Charles hamton Turner who um believed in connecting
opposite values sorry he believed in connecting opposite values and he would
say and I hope I get this right courage without caution is
recklessness caution without courage is cowardice very
nice so so so being a human being is
difficult being a human being is [Music] profound and each of you is a profound
human being and may your profundity support this world that we're
living in the world needs our support from that deep place inside and may all
of us know it and let all of us be courageous so
that we have more love in this world and more Care and More
Justice thank you