greetings dear ones this week we've been exploring what
it means to have trust in the practice and for this we also need to
trust the present moment when awareness is well
established it becomes possible to just remain receptively aware of the present
moment in whatever way it
arises when we trust our practice we express that by saying yes to the
present moment whatever arises we trust that it's
okay and also that we have the capacity to deal with
it no need for tuning out being here and
now resting the present moment is
also to trust the Dharma in our tradition the Dharma
refers not only to the teachings of the Buddha but also to trusting whatever is
on offer to us in each moment
if it feels right for you you could begin your meditations
with I surrender to the Dharma as a reminder to deeply
trust how things
unfold it's the tremendous relief when we can know and rest in the present
moment without being triggered with judg ments
opinions selfing and the body breathing is the
place where we train ourselves to calm down enough to settle
the mind so that we can begin resting
peacefully in the present
moment in our meditation yesterday we practiced calming the whole body
while staying present with the [Music]
breathing in the scheme of anapanasati deeply calming the body gives rise to
experiencing joy and the Buddha's next
instructions after calming the body are
one trains I will breathe in experiencing
Joy one trains I will breathe out experiencing
Joy you may wonder why does the Buddha encourage us
to train by experiencing [Music] Joy with the momentum of the meditation
practices we done this week culminating in deep relaxation of the
body Joy can often arise quite spontaneously at least in a subtle
form also since we're reward-based
creatures our ability to remain anchored in the present moment is
strengthened when we perceive our experience as
pleasant noticing these subtle Pleasant feeling tones in
meditation can then serve as a foundation for the arising of
joy and this creates another virtuous cycle where joy and turn boosts our
ability to stay in our lived experience
so to begin our [Music] meditation calmly closing the
eyes and ex assuming a posture that expresses your highest
aspiration
gently straightening the spine perhaps imagining that you're held
up by An Invisible Thread suspending your
head from the crown from the sky all the way down to the
toes so take a moment now to do a slow gentle body
scan from the crown of the head all the way down to the
feet e
establishing your priority to leave all your concerns
outside the door and to stay grounded in embodied
awareness asking yourself if you can trust abiding in the present
moment letting go of past and future
just staying with this body
breathing e
when you're settled enough and comfortable trusting the present
moment you can try the fifth step in the Buddhist instructions on mindfulness of
breathing in which he says one trains I will
experience I will breathe in experiencing Joy one trains I will breathe out
experiencing Joy
if you've never trained by experiencing Joy you might
formulate this simple aspiration May Joy
arise and then remain receptively open to whatever
happens allowing space in the mind for joy to man EST in whatever form it may
take tension or becoming distracted will prevent Joy from
arising but just knowing our distractions or tensions and relaxing them may suffice
for joy to our
rides e
I found that in times when grief is front and center in in the
mind experiencing Joy during meditation May well be
unavailable in this case we may still be able to find peace in the Present
Moment by cultivating our inner contentment which is
softer and quieter than Joy e
so staying in the body and staying with the
breathing letting the mind be open to the arising of
joy
e e
giving yourself permission to Simply
Be and most of all enjoy your [Music]
meditation
e
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting we return to our circle of
caring for ourselves for everyone here
meditating and for all
beings may all beings be safe and
protected being safe may all beings including
ourselves be happily at ease may we all abide in
peace and may all beings everywhere be
free so to end our meditation let's all join our hands
together and bow to one another to honor everyone in this
beautiful
SAA e
greetings everyone quite a few of you expressed
interest in the chat yesterday in having the text of the peach blossoms poem by
dogen that I read so at the end of The Talk
the audio visual team will kindly put it up in the chat for
you we started last week with training in
emptiness well trusting the present moment as we meditate has a lot to do with trusting
emptiness we constantly project our ideas Concepts
memories and associations onto
reality so we need to first of all see that our discursive thinking is not
reality and then Savor those moments when we're no longer projecting self and
permanence onto our experience because that's
when there's a possibility for the mind to really
relax and let go in a deep
way relaxing with insight into Emptiness is one of the conditions for
[Music] awakening venerable analio says that
compassion and emptiness are like two sides of the same coin as we
practice they start to
interpenetrate so being okay with not okay is the beginning of Learning
self-compassion and when the mind is compassionate it's boundless
y says that all the wisdom all the Insight we need for
enlightenment will only be found when we're able to stay in the
present it's a profound thing for the body and mind to come to
rest when momentarily we're not caught in wanting this and that a
sense of well-being and contentment with what
naturally arises can
arise the contentment of knowing that just being alive is
enough with nothing to improve to apologize for or to
defend this then inspires confidence which then circles
back and further inspires us to be present for this lived
life as we're living it right
now a Monday I shared with you the quote from the Buddha in which he assures us
speak or act with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never
departing Shadow but our ancestors have given us
powerful DNA which tells us that we need to stay stressed in fight ORF flight
mode rather than allowing the mind to rest peacefully in
spaciousness but when everything becomes our friend we can then dare to
trust letting go into the present moment and we have the
support for developing lasting happiness our
practice is to untie The Big Knot of
selfing and we need Serenity as the foundation and preparation for insight
if the Mind remains contracted it's easily
Disturbed but if we have a big skylike mind many things can
arise and the mind is able to hold them all without being
disturbed however if we don't tame the elephant of the mind to be
confident calm imperturbable and [Music]
peaceful we'll never dare to trust ourselves or to trust the Dharma of the
present moment Yong
Ming tells us if you're determined to think of
yourself as limited fearful vulnerable or scarred by past
experience know only that you have chosen to do
so and that the opportunity to experience yourself differently is
always available when you enter the path of
Buddhist practice you're ending and abuse Ive relationship with
yourself so this is a strong statement but I think what Ming rache is trying to
convey is that we can choose
Freedom Gil teaches that the foundation for a practice is knowing sensing or
feeling and relaxing
this can provide a radical change from how we usually live our lives because the process of knowing sensing and
relaxing can be free of any pressure or
projections and in and of itself just knowing and sensing can be
peaceful thanful spacious opening us up to a wider world
so be patient with your clinging when we dare to trust ourselves
in our practice then we become a beautiful
witness and we can see the beauty inside ourselves and in the
world we can trust relaxing into this marvelous body of
ours we dare opening up to the vastness
of a spacious mind and to the joy of inner
goodness when the mind is at least temporarily free of greed hate and
delusion in this practice of embodied awareness we're letting go of the
holding and identification that freeze the mind and the
Heart everyone is looking for a safe
place and we can know the real safe place is within us all the
time the well-being of our Pure innate
awareness is our safety
and we begin to be less driven wanting to be someone to
accomplish results there's a big difference between
setting a powerful aspiration and trying to get
somewhere as mammals our biological instructions for
survival are to be goal oriented and to lean into the future
and our culture teaches us to keep on focusing on getting the next task
[Music] done as a
consequence many of us have internalized endless striving
consciously or
unconsciously The Reptilian part of the brain tells us to remain stressed and
fearful the neuros psychologist Rick Hansen author of Buddhist
brain says the Mind tends to transfer unfulfilled needs from
childhood into the present needs such as to be safe worthy
successful or loved and what's surprising is that
these ancient longings often continue even we've after we've already
resolved the original
issues it's important how we live in this troubled world we know that everything we think
say say and do is influencing the world around
us and I'm convinced that the practice we're all engaged in is teaching
us how we can live for the benefit of all beings
I'll close with the beautiful atmology of the English word
arrive it comes from the old French AR which means to come to
land and this in turn comes from the Latin to touch the
shore after a long Voyage at sea
in our meditation today we practice trusting the present moment and
cultivating joy and if you'd like some more
homework after this week you're invited to adopt the
Mantra relax you've arrived
whenever you see that the body is moving a bit too fast or you feel uh a little
stressed so the homework going forward is simply to
relax and Trust
knowing that you've already arrived on the other shore of supreme
safety thank you for your P participation this week thank you for your practice