good morning everyone it's very nice to be here it's been a long time I used to
be here a lot for many many years from the beginning and with
Co I stopped coming in person and I got very used
to since it continues on YouTube I just tune every Sunday morning on
YouTube um so it's it's both exciting
and a little bit different to be here I'm just not a customed to it and
there's so many new faces so many new people it's wonderful it's really
wonderful that um everybody together has been able to keep IMC so active and so
meaningful uh for all this time
so a sentence that I read this morning that touched
me wisdom Springs from meditation without
meditation wisdom
wains so Joe asked me what was the title of my talk
today and I said the fallacy of
perfect so that gives you a clue where I'm going doesn't
it what is this idea of
perfect what do we mean when we say that as I say it what does it bring up
for you what do you think of perfect or might say
perfection it is used I think pretty commonly in our culture these days since
I've been thinking about this topic I have found myself so frequently in the
mind saying oh perfect oh that's perfect of course it's not perfect by
any in a neat truthful way what is it it's a
personal preference oh that fits with what I'm doing or what I like or what
feels good so we talked about this in Morgan Hill uh week or two ago and I got
an email from somebody a couple days ago in response to something I had suggested
and she wrote and said oh that will work just fine and then in parenthesis notice
I didn't say [Laughter] perfect and what was really nice about
that is it's in her Consciousness now so perfect doesn't just come out she
will think about it and that's that's the point um that's the important part
of Buddha's practice right that we're aware that we're conscious
of what we're doing what we're saying what's happening and then from that awareness
and Consciousness we can make more skillful wise
decisions so when we think about what's
perfect what's appropriate or what's best for
whom for myself for you for a teacher
for who who is it perfect or very good
for think of the last time you used the term
perfect what did you mean and how did it it
fit recently someone asked me to switch teaching
dates and my response was oh that's
that'll work perfectly for me I'm becoming more and more aware how
frequently that thought that idea oh that's perfect oh that'll work perfect
ly comes to mind when of course what I mean is oh that fits very well with my
schedule yes that that works fine for me that's that's good
so I'm trying to be more conscious more aware and use different wording than
perfect because of course perfect has a certain connotation doesn't it
and with that connotation there's the opposite so if something is
perfect that suggests that something else might be
imperfect and what does that mean
imperfect so this topic came up for me
because recently I have heard so many times in
different settings different ways we are imperfect human
beings we are flawed human
beings and that certainly gives a certain bias doesn't
it if we're flawed God if we're
imperfect what does that suggest are we less
that are we
incapable I think it's often said as a way of giving a
slack you know we're human beings we can't be expected to be
perfect but I find hearing that over and over it
also gives the impression that we are less than that we
are somehow not so
great and therefore we don't have to expect certain things from
ourselves well I think it's fine maybe not to have uh high or unrealistic or
whatever expectations but do we really want the notion or
accept about ourselves that we're less than that we're not okay maybe not fully
human so could we see ourselves as
flowers different varieties different colors different sizes shapes fragrances
Etc together a beautiful
bouquet and is one type any
better any more perfect than another type we all have
preferences some might like roses better than whatever daisies some might like
orchids better than
gardinas but those are just preferences aren't they there's no truth
or no reality to a notion that one is better
than another they're just different just like
us we're all different and in some ways not so
different of course but not more perfect or less
perfect than anyone else can
we just
be that's a very important understanding in Buddhist practice to just
be but what does that mean that can be a little intimidating
or a little bit scary or a little bit
concerning I have experienced it what does it mean to just be uh uh how should
I be who should I be just be uh but what is that how do
how do I do that I have
learned I have learned to trust an inner uh I don't know if guidance is the
right an inner unfolding so that sometimes now if if
I'm questioning something or trying to decide you know I'll think about it a
little bit then I let go and smile to myself and say h well we'll see what
happens much easier way to live and for me it feels much more
congruent much more like I am being and not trying to be something or
someone so often that's what we're doing right we're trying hard to be someone to
be something
special rather than just who we are and we don't have
to Define that that doesn't have to be anything in particular but just
being so we still can
practice can learn the teachings the teachings of the
Buddha and many other
teachings we have in Buddhist practice the 10 Perfections we have the
eight-fold path we have the four Brahma viharas we have many
lists and they're wonderful for practice
they're wonderful for developing our awareness expanding our
compassion our loving kindness um
generosity all of the things that we want to
expand we don't have to practice them to be
perfect our practice is not about becoming perfect it's about
becoming more loving more accepting more are
conscious all the attributes that
we want to cultivate and want to expand but not as a way of being
perfect sometimes people want to become the perfect
meditator what's that there's no perfect
meditator there's there's no perfect meditation there's whatever our meditation is right
now and we work with that there's nothing perfect or
imperfect about it
so in our culture judgment is a big thing there's judgment
everywhere and we're taught from a very young age to compare and to
judge this is good this is not good this is beautiful this is
ugly if this is this then that is
that but what we're really expressing is a personal
preference not as I said earlier a
truth some people may think that if you're
this that's wonderful if you're that that's not so good
we take our judgments so
seriously and hold them as truths we don't often we don't see them as
judgments but as truths this is this is how it
is however they're just
thoughts and if we latch on to them
and hold them tightly they expand they
proliferate If instead we can see them as
thoughts thoughts come and go right if we
don't grab onto them latch onto them
they will change they will come and
go so I'm not suggesting
that a form of judgment is never okay we have in this practice
discernment wise discrimination it is important to be
Discerning and and to see things clearly but that's different from
this important judgment Discerning something seeing
something clearly can be very very
important letting go of it as
judgment can be just as important important and a part of being Discerning
using discriminating wisdom is to hold
things Loosely so that when circumstances
change or for some reason our thinking changes something changes we can be
flexible we can change sometimes that's considered we
weakness if you're if you're really serious about something then then you
don't you're not flexible you don't get to change your mind well of course it's
the opposite if we're really serious about something then we have to be open to
change because that's how it is that's how life
is and actually it takes more strength to be be willing to change our minds
change our attitude see something differently when things
change when we get new information or somehow
we see things differently to be able to be flexible with that and change that
takes more strength than holding on to something typically when somebody holds
on really tight to something and won't consider any other alternative um there's fear there's
weakness that can feel like strength to hold on so tightly to something but in
this practice we're encouraged to be more open to be more flexible to
allow a different attitude a different way of seeing something when something
changes or we see something in a new light we
see something different when I was young somehow I had
the whatever ability or something to see both sides of an issue I'm a great Libra
you know I hold both ends of the scale
but I got the impression that I was considered wishy-washy or weak you know and it
wasn't until really I came to Buddhist practice that I recognized that was an
attribute that was helpful to be able to see uh both sides of any issue
I still considered an attribute although in our culture I'm sure again
many would see that as wishy-washy you're supposed to see things clearly
and then stay with it but as we look around
our our very painful
world all all the fighting all the
unhappiness it can be very helpful to be willing to be open to see
both perspectives so this morning when I was
walking my dog I saw I Came Upon my Russian neighbor who's taking care of
his son's dog
and we had a brief very friendly
conversation and as we walked away I was struck
by I know a little bit about he and his wife's feelings
and I have in Southern California a Ukrainian
friend that I met in Ukraine many many years ago and I couldn't help
but you know each of them have very different views of what's going
on different positions from their experience from they're growing up one
grew up in Ukraine one grew up in in Russia and so so they see things quite
differently both very very wonderful
people very um you know on a personal
level and they have different perspectives and it's so easy in our
culture it's so easy I mean I I try to resist it but there's the temptation to
see one side is right and the other side is
wrong that's how we get to war isn't it what if both sides have a
perspective what if we let go of this right wrong good bad but this is one
perspective this is another perspective same with Gaza
right both feel
victims how can
we not be so judgmental hold
both and work together together I have in my notes war is the
problem we we tend to jump to war and we tend to think that you know war or
violence or fighting is the way to answer something what if
we consider things as perspectives
and how can we work together so that both
perspectives can have a
place it can be the same in interpersonal relations right doesn't have to be
countries how can we appreciate and understand
the perspective of someone who's very different from
us without this right wrong that's a challenge isn't it we so
frequently we hear something on the news or from somebody or we understand
something and right away this is right and this is wrong well
when we look a little bit closer it's not always so clear is
it they're different because experiences are
different but that doesn't make one right and one wrong
can we enjoy each
moment each day each week each year without
judgment setting aside the
Judgment we have so many judg ments about so many
things I mentioned flowers earlier flowers and
weeds who determines what's a flower and what's a wheat I don't think it's
nature I think it's human beings so um I have a little reputation
in the community in which I live I appreciate the
weeds so so when the gardeners come around you
know they don't dig up the weeds or they'll say can can we cut these is okay
cut these and I love it you know
um they want so often to have everything
very uh what's the word Prim trimmed
just looking just so well the
weeds add Greenery and some of them have little
flowers and so the tree right next to
me has all this green now I'm sure not everybody likes
it but I love it I love the green and it's a reminder what is a weed and what
is a flower this weed has a lovely little orange
flower I think about the seasons everybody most everybody has a
preference for summer fall winter
spring it's a preference isn't it there's nothing inherently better
about winter than spring we need we need them all of
course and if we're open we can enjoy them
all even what's alive and what's dead
it's all part of life we're taught we've learned of
course that alive is good dead is not
good however we all know don't we we're all
going to be dead one day and just like the seasons where the
leaves die and fall off the tree
um insects rodents um our
pets die at some point and is that
ugly we die at some point is that
ugly can we see it as part of the cycle of
life and that well we may have feelings about
how someone or something
died the suffering that may have gone along with it the actual
death is part of life isn't it everything that comes into being
will disappear that's a basic teaching isn't
it so I want to leave some time for discussion I'm going to end with
um just a little bit about my grandson my
favorite Crooked Tree in the forest
my grandson is 24 he um he has uh he was diagnosed at about a
year 18 months with cerebral paly um he he ha he
cannot uh read or write
um he knows his name but if you ask him how old he is if he's with me he'll turn
to me and he might say 16 just somehow that
sticks in his mind on the other hand he is one of the
nicest human beings you could ever want to meet everybody says that not just his
grandma but everybody he's so friendly you know he's
kind and he loves music so I've taken him to
many symphonies and he can tell you every single instrument in that
Orchestra and I have been known to misname something no grandma that's a
whatever he knows the difference five years ago we were in
Missouri for my daughter's ordination and we were sitting outside having breakfast and we heard this bird
up in the tree and right away Alexander said I didn't understand him but he said
that's a cardinal and I kept saying know what you know finally oh a cardinal we
don't have cardinals in California but his grandpa had given him a book with uh
the sounds of birds and the name and he knew from that it was a cardinal well of
course a couple minutes later out flew this red bird from the tree it was
indeed a cardinal so I say that I I talk about my
grandson because I have learned so much from him and learned you know some
would say he's imperfect well I guess from a certain
point of view he is my daughter and I both
agree we would not want him any other way he's a wonderful human being
imperfect as some might say or as the Crooked Tree in the in the forest
crooked trees can be beautiful can be
wonderful so let's remember that perfect is a human construct it's a human
idea that probably isn't so
helpful because if there's perfect there's
imperfect and what if we dropped both what if we just saw things as
clearly as we can saw things see things as they are
without all our human Notions and
ideas does that make sense yeah so we do have a few minutes are
there comments
questions uh bergette over the last 22 years I've seen and read quite a few
Buddhist teachers and um uh there's one point I think it's safe to say they
don't all agree on um some many teachers or some at least uh do
believe in um the possibility of uh full
Enlightenment which you could describe as a sort of perfection and then other
teachers N I don't think so they would say don't think it's really completely
possible or they have doubts about it um U and for me
it's not something I think of as attainable but something that I can
always get closer to and then closer to closer to whether I get there or not
as you know I have no way of knowing so why why why even think about that just
just keep making the effort to get a little closer but do you have any thoughts on that on on on
enlightenment I think what you're saying is very wise who knows who
knows um when I first came to Buddhist
practice 30 some years ago I didn't know anything about Enlightenment and after a few years oh
all I wanted was Enlightenment I practice and you know
and then it kind of gradually just relaxed and I feel a little bit like you
I I want to make the effort for the qualities I was mentioning earlier I
want to be uh Kinder and more loving and more compassionate and etc
etc uh Enlightenment I guess I sort of feel if it comes great if it
doesn't does that answer totally thank
you hi Berget it's nice to see you and um as I was listening to your talk what
came up to me was discernment right so there is
um the idea of some of the things in um
in this particular philosophy that we're practicing under can be very
idealistic in from my point of view and rightly
so and there are things uh my heart spit up when I
started to hear you talk about war and and the word Discerning discernment
came to mine and um in the way that you know I'm
just thinking about the plan world or the or the um possibilities for choices
for eating right diet not all foods are created equal not
not all of them are wholesome as you know right some plant are really poisonous to
us and so I just um I wanted to drop
discernment into the Consciousness as well today um as a as a possibility that
while all is could be perfect it needs to be
included not all is wholesome there you go right right exactly yes I
did say discernment a little bit ago um I think I see discernment is different
from judgment that's why I mentioned it and yes discernment discriminating
wisdom it is very important um not just for diet all kinds
of things right um
and so I like discernment or discriminating wisdom better than
judgment because of all the uh implications that judgment has
but judgment in the sense of seeing things clearly and making skillful wise
decisions yes can be very helpful and I think discernment discriminating wisdom
uh um might
be more helpful terms than
judgment yeah and I agree with you and
it's one of the things that has kept me with Buddhism it's very
idealistic but you know what it's realistic what we call idealistic is
really realistic is really more
realistic if we followed the teachings and did our very
best that would be so much more realistic in the sense of helping
our communities our planet Etc so
um I love the idealism and I think it's more
realistic did you want to say something thank you so
much speak we invite everyone to stay because it's tea time this afternoon
okay could you say that into the mic please invit an invitation to all of you
to come and have tea with us we got all kinds of goodies and we'll just put a
table up and you just come and help yourself there'll be tea water and um a
chance to you know share ideas with each other just get to know each other a
little bit thank you bergette thank you Diana before we do that any last minute
question comment yes
okay hi thank you for your talk um I just wanted to make a comment about the
notion of perfection and how it struck me that Perfection is something that's
public we share it we use it as compliments with other people but I
don't see it as being a notion that um we might experience or think about
private say a little
more when we use the word Perfection or we think about it we use it as a
compliment about something uhhuh and we talk about it with another person oh
that was perfect oh you did a perfect job so I feel like it's a public concept
more than a private concept more than one that we think about in our our own
private thoughts ah that we might not privately think oh that was perfect oh I
did that just perfectly that's that's what I'm thinking I'm I'm just wondering if
that's if that's something that you if you thought about perfection as being more of a public statement or compliment
or something that's shared with others publicly rather than something that people can appreciate or think about
privately well I haven't thought about that [Laughter] um it seems mostly that people
don't tell themselves very often oh that was perfect oh you did that just
perfectly we tend to be more critical um and more likely to
say well that wasn't so great well you could have done that one
better um we probably wouldn't say that to somebody else necessarily but I think to
ourselves we're probably many of us most of us quite
critical whether it's public or
private it has a judgment and judgments can
be very hard har and
harmful and I would rather that we saw things clearly and saw things as they are
without the need for
judging we judge all the time do we really need to do
that discriminate discern yes
but that's not judging that's not good bad right wrong that's seeing things as
they are
okay Nancy I foret um thank you I uh was
thinking during your talk today about the notion Japanese notion of wabisabi
of there being Perfection and imperfection and I thought um that sort
of encapsulated a lot of what you were talking
about how Nancy how would you define that concept of wabisabi of there
being Perfection and imperfection
um that circumstances people or
um even conversations may go imperfectly but in
that imperfection there's still always something to
learn I mean there is something that can be given even in an imperfect situation
exactly exactly thank you for
that okay I think we've come to the end of our Q&A I want to thank you again and
let folks know that um if you want to hear more um of forgette she is on Audi
Dharma on our website thank you again brette thank you
Mara