so welcome and good evening so I wanted to continue on a
theme that I I started last week so last week I start to talk about this idea I
introduced these um five qualities of
endeavoring of five things that the qualities to bring together if you want to do
something something that that bu talked about is a support for any thing we want
to do of course he's teaching about spiritual practice but it's something that we could do for
whatever I'll just list these five I already gave a whole talk on them but I just want to kind of like add a little
bit on this so these five factors of endeavoring we can
say first one is confidence second one is Vitality third one is integrity
fourth one is energy and the fifth one is wisdom
so this is that's talking about like how to like to gather up certain qualities
so that we can do something or go in a particular direction accomplish
something but now I'd like to maybe add on that but also introduce something
else and that is where are we going what are we doing like which direction or
what are we oriented towards when I talked about it last week was
just you know whatever you want to do and this is true you can apply those five qualities to whatever you want to
do but maybe it's worthwhile considering what is it we want to
do what direction do we want our life to take what direction do we want our
anything about us to take so there's this way that it can be
enormously helpful to just even ask ourselves cuz sometimes we don't ask ourselves and it can be so
powerful what is our deepest
aspiration in my mind an aspiration is a little bit different than a goal goal is maybe more immediate and and uh
tangible want to be able to lift x amount of pounds walk certain amount of distance knit to certain way or you know
something like this whereas an aspiration is in my mind at least is a
little bit more um Grand it's a little bit more
heartfelt what is it what is our deepest aspiration maybe as I'm talking now you
can just ask yourself what are you most inspired
by what what makes your heart sing
the place this direction you'd like to go because there's a way in which when
we're aligning with an aspiration that we have the way that we are being consistent with an aspiration that we
have there's a sense of openness or sense of ease like yeah this may not be comfortable
exactly at this moment but I know that what I'm doing is going in the direction I want to go
just uh recently I I sat a retreat and um after the retreat a number of us were
talking and um I just found myself saying there's
about there's something so powerful about being on Retreat even if it's a horrible Retreat and that you're in
physical pain emotional distress right and these things happen on Retreat too right it's not all Bliss and fun
sometimes it is but sometimes it isn't but I said there's just something about you know being aligned with what's the
most important to you to me that just feels good even if the
retreat is hard and I hadn't really kind of like put that together in such a clear way
that this is there's something beautiful that happens just being on Retreat so this is for me one of my aspirations is
to you know be cultivating my meditation practice
and yeah I'll just say that doesn't mean that you all have to have the same aspiration
either but I just pointing to that there's this sense of openness or ease
or maybe even a little bit of relaxation when you have this sense of
what I'm doing is aligned with my deepest values what I really want from my life from this
life and with this alignment and this ease there's there this way and there can be some power to that power meaning
uh this like a a movement of force or something like this many years ago I had this uh quote
uh in my kitchen so next to the where I would do doing the dishes that so that I
would see it regularly and it I put it there when I was in the midst of having to do
something that was really hard and I didn't want to do it something that was like really hard
and it's and was something that took me many months to do and I didn't just didn't want to do it and um I could and
here's like a different translation I couldn't find the exact translation of the one that I had uh up there on my
next to my kitchen you would think I would have it memorized having seen it however many times but it's by um
G he's a German poet I guess we could say and writer and
he says um in this quote he says the moment one commits oneself Providence
moves too I don't really know what providence
is but just this idea that okay I'm going to go this direction I'm going to
do this there's a way in which not always and it's not always obvious but
there's a way that things can help us along if it's really aligned with our
deepest desires or aspiration and then this quote
continues go writes whatever you dream you can do begin
it this boldness has power magic and Grace in
it begin it
now one way that I think about this idea that um this Providence moves too is
that sometimes we feel like oh my gosh I see all these things that have to happen
in order to have what really is my aspiration what really inspires me my really goal and I don't think I can do
that but here's what we're not considering this beautiful thing called
like impermanence the version of ourselves that's going to get to that step is going to be the one that just
completed the step before which is going to be the one that just completed the step before so we are changing as we're
moving along this path towards something we want to do so maybe when we're way back here like oh my gosh I don't think
I can do that but when we're right here it's the next thing like oh okay I can do
that this this way that we want to project the current version of ourselves
into the future and say well this current version it's going to be hard to do that but the current version isn't
going to be the one that's going to do it it's going to be the one who finished
or completed or found a way through other things and I remind myself of this
whenever I have something big that I have to do like okay well future Diana can take care of that I'm just going to
do this one little step here that the next thing that needs to be
done and so maybe I'll just say the obvious that often just because we're
busy and we are surrounded by a I mean
we kind of built this society that likes to distract us from anything that's uncomfortable right we carry these
gizmos in our pockets that's designed to distract us and just because of that
it's often that we don't touch into what is our aspiration we're just busy taking care
of you know the next thing maybe the next thing that feels urgent and important but really maybe isn't aligned
with what's the deepest wish or the deepest desires that we
have and so it's worthwhile to really spend some time and think about it and
I'll talk about this in a little bit more in the in a moment here
but because there's a way in which we can I don't know we can feel like I know
I get lost in this too just taking care of like the to-do list and that just feels like life is just one big long
to-do list we don't want that kind of a life we can have a bigger life a better life
but it does require us to pay attention pay attention to what's going on inside of us and what's how we're spending our
life energy so some aspirations might be
something like there's this deep in wish in our hearts for
happiness for well-being and ease and maybe that wish for happiness
and well-being is it's not only for ourselves but for others and maybe there's this wish
really wish for the be able to make the world or the our community or family
members or others that we're in contact with to just have a little bit more ease
a little bit more happiness little bit more peace
wellbeing just imagine what the world would be like if everybody had just a
little bit more peace ease and well-being I know I feel inspired by
this so maybe that's one thing that inspires us but maybe it's something more about service more indirectly about
service there's such a beautiful thing to just be supporting others and to help them find what's
important to them or maybe they do know and to help them Reach it and to have you know to show up with
compassion when people have difficulties or or to support others rather than
having it to be about oh it's all about me but instead to feel like let me let me help out and there's a way which
helping and supporting others I don't know feeds us nourishes us too
i s of had that experience when I was um and I I didn't do this for a long time but I was a chaplain up at uh San
Francisco General and there was something that uh it'd be quite something to just meet
these patients some of them really really sick some of them you know to be in the
hospital was a step up in their living conditions and um just to be able to
meet them where they were just kind of it was a beautiful thing to be able to do
but it's not so easy you don't need me to tell you this we have these
aspirations these things we want to do yes I'm going to do this but to consistently Orient our life our
activities the way we spend our resources our energy towards that
towards our aspirations it's not easy if it were easy you would already
be doing it so I appreciate very much that the
Buddha he talked some more about this idea like what are some supports for this some ways to help us go towards our
aspirations and there's this he talked about this uh
quality of steadfastness or I might say
persistence or this stick intuitiveness or or maybe this tenacity
or determination or resolve or resolution something like
this is a quality that's needed because it's not always easy it's not always
easy of course we like things to happen quickly things don't necessarily happen
quickly we like to take the path of least resistance but maybe following our
aspirations is not anop paath of least resistance so it doesn't mean that we're
failing that it because it's hard doesn't mean that we're bad humans or we're failing or anything like that it's
hard because I don't it's just
because it's just the way that it is we could talk about it and philosophize about it but you know it's just not easy
all the time sometimes it is I talked about being like aligned there's this openness when you're aligned sometimes
it's beautiful and sometimes it's difficult that's how it is and you don't
need me to tell you this either everybody knows this if anytime you've ever wanted to uh achieve anything or
gain anything there's been difficulties so this word this uh
persistence or perseverance or tenacity determination po word is
aitana and one person described it and I kind of like this as this gentle but
persistent wind that's like blowing on at your back this just kind of like helping you go a particular
direction this idea of like okay I'm going to go this
direction and for some people I'll just say that actually this kind of like persistence or perseverance is not uh a
difficulty for them for them that's the way that they are they have a goal and they're just kind
of like have a certain doggedness and they just make it happen and if you're one of those people then maybe where the
difficulty is it's different than some other people the stick intuitiveness maybe the difficulty is not to like push
this practice or push whatever it is you're doing to drudgery I have to do this and just
doing it and then your life gets filled like drudgery nobody wants that or if
you're one of those people that stick to itness is easy and that's the way that you move through the world maybe there's
the edge for you is to be able to do that and not alienate others or dismiss
others or there can be a way it's like get out of my way I have to do this I don't care what you're doing right now I
have to do this so right everybody whether this
idea of persistence or perseverance determination comes easily or not there's a way in which we can practice
with it that it can help us with our aspirations and uh Asen goenka some of
you may know is a teacher in the Insight tradition and he says and maybe have all
heard this I know I've heard this before too it's something kind of just uh it's not unique to
him but this idea that well we could say for um in particular
May maybe with a spiritual practice but any other thing that you want to do you can dig 10 Wells one foot
deep but you're not likely to find water but maybe there's one well that's
10 ft deep that you can find water so this recognition of just staying there
staying there and it's this that's kind of like this power of aitana it's like okay I'm
just going to stay here and and I made this resolve this is really
what's important to me and I'm going to hang in there even though right now it's
uncomfortable even though right now I don't want to do it but to find a way to do it but not a
way that is um where we're tied up into knots not without a way than which we're
like uh beating ourselves up like you're going to be a bad person if you don't do it or you are a bad person because you
don't want to do it or something like this but instead this like peaceful
perseverance like okay yes this is what's needs to be done this is what I'm
going to do and we kind of like bow like yes I recognize you don't want to do it we're
going to do it anyway and I'm saying this for myself
too because some you know sometimes I find myself oh I have to do things I found myself you know putting
them off or something like this but recently I had to do something that was rather
uncomfortable and it's so silly but it turned out it worked just like I just said out loud okay I can do hard things
and I'm going to do this and there was just this little tiny pep talk it wasn't a way like Diana you're going to be such
a loser if you don't do it right that doesn't work I've tried that it doesn't work instead like okay I can do hard
things I'm going to do this and it was hard and I did it so it's a way in which
we can stop uh maybe always insisting that we're comfortable all the time I
like to be comfortable I think all of us do but there's this way in which um kind
of like Society really promotes like comfort for the exclusion of everything
else you know never to feel uncomfortable it's okay to feel
discomfort it's just discomfort it doesn't mean anything about the way the universe is made
whether it's a just world or not it doesn't mean about whether we're good people or not it's just
discomfort it arises it passes away and I wish for all of you that it doesn't
stay around for a long time but we don't get to control those
things cuz there's this way in which if we do apply this pers perseverance or
persistence this aitana it adds like this richness to our
life this level of fulfillment or satisfaction like yeah I I I really
tried maybe I didn't get what I wanted maybe I did but I really did
try and there's this way in which so often we can be holding back and feeling
like well I don't even really want to try because the fear of not achieving or
attaining acquiring where the fear of that of of
not doing that often prevents us from even
starting but if we're able to begin again and again and again and again just
begin again and again and again there's this way that it does it brings a certain I don't know
satisfaction to your life when I had to do that difficult thing and I did it there was a little bit of uplift like oh
look at that I did it you know I really didn't want to I wasn't quite sure that I could
but I did it so and there's you know we need to fill
our fill our lives with these types of things there's so much stuff that's kind of like our energy draining
out and this is something that kind of like gives us a little bit of confidence little bit of boost to do something
that's difficult it doesn't have to be wildly difficult it can be just sending
that email that you've been putting off that you need to reply to coworker or something like this or
what whatever it might be so how would we make the a resolution
how would we like set a resolve I like this one way is to think
about is what like for yourself like what well
what is something that I can maybe like practice this Adana with this determination this resolve
persistence and just to ask yourself what qualities would I advise a
friend who is very similar to me what qualities would I advise them to develop
or cultivate or pay attention to somebody that we loved and cared for
what would we do as opposed it's really helpful to think about things that way it's it's a little bit more accessible
otherwise that inner critic is pretty sneaky and it otherwise it'll get right in there well you know you should do x y
z a b c instead just like okay if I had a good friend who was like this what
what maybe something that this friend could work on
to ask ask it that way but maybe this is a reflection maybe
it's not something that comes immediately to mind but maybe it's something that gets dropped in during a meditation or something when there's
some openness or some
ease and when you feel like you have this idea of okay I I really want to set
I want to like Orient towards this aspiration in order to meet this aspir ation I want to cultivate this
particular quality and once you have that sense where you filled in those
words whatever the aspiration is whatever the quality to be developed at next or right then to help with that
aspiration to be a little bit more specific I want [Music]
to have more spaciousness in my life maybe that's the
aspiration and then maybe the quality to cultivate
is taking care of clutter maybe that's just something like okay I'm just going to organize my space like the physical
space I'm going to start there or I'm going to practice saying no
because maybe my life is filled up with things because I can't say no to other people and or or I'm just going to spend
more time taking walks in nature instead of Doom scrolling I'm G to go
outside whatever it might be so after you've kind like have these
ideas then sit with it a little bit and see like how does it feel is there a
little bit of delay like oh yeah yeah or is there a little like yeah okay I guess
I should do this I really don't want to there should be a little bit of something that uh has a little little
bit of kind of excited or this recognition that this is a would
be a great thing for my life and maybe the challenge feels challenging but not too much not like I can't do it or
something like that so feel into it and choose something that feels achievable
and yet you'll have to stretch yourself a little bit not completely be a different person just stretch yourself a
little bit
and there's a way in which we can even like say things out
loud maybe like sit for a little bit and you know I resolve to take care of clitter
maybe I'm going to say this because I am planning to clean my desk tomorrow so I have my desk right I was a
mess I resolved to take care of clutter in my house and then maybe it's
something like and may it be so you know there's like a a bow or a saying or you know something or maybe you ring a bell
or light a candle or do something like this to make it distinguish it from just
one more thought like okay this thought is a little bit
different and then or you can also actually occurs to
me you can also say it to somebody else or maybe you guys can do something together and sometimes be accountable
ability partners and I do this with a a friend that we we
send photos to each other for just making sure we go get outside every day into nature and it's quite it's
fantastic you have to get these little pictures oh okay she's outside look you
know I should go outside it's so nice so how do we keep it it's okay easy
enough to make it but uh how do we do this Adana how do we have this persistence and how do we have this uh
determination this resoluteness well one is when your resolve slips and it will guaranteed
right if it didn't then this then you chose something a little bit too easy maybe
but when the resolve slips just reflect on how that
felt not beating yourself up not analyzing it just feeling maybe the
disappointment cuz dis disappointment like for me it feels like this little tightness in the gut and kind of like
the shoulders kind of like oh you know this collapsing down and allow yourself
to feel that collapse if indeed it is a collapse and the body and the mind don't
like that collapse and so there'll be a way in which oh yeah okay going this
direction leads to this uncomfortable feeling collapse for example going this
other direction gives me some confidence even though it's a little bit uncomfortable not what I want to do but it gives me some confidence so just
recognize both the body and the mind it can be really helpful to bring the body
into it our posture our physical posture or the
internal uh contraction that
happens and then just not maybe there's something
obvious about you know why it's was hard at that
time to follow your resolve like yeah okay I made the
resolve to not eat as much sugar maybe I shouldn't have bought all those
cookies okay don't buy cookies anymore or you know maybe there's something obvious but maybe there's something
that's not obvious too and there can just without a lot of analysis because analysis often the
inner critic gets dis uh disguised as analysis while you did this wrong you did that wrong you did this wrong that
is not where we're going it's like okay just what's what's
can happen next what's what what how did I get here
and what what's next how can I write this or how is there a way that I can
just Begin Again that's all that's needed is just Begin Again in whatever way that's simple I
think um is it James Clear he's this person who wrote This Book Atomic habits if I'm remembering correctly he says
like just do something that's you can do in two minutes okay that's worthwhile like okay
this is how you begin again just do something for two minutes we can do that
all of us can do that but there's this way in which we
can also get in trouble with this resolves I'm saying here's an aspiration and then have a resolve to do it and
like I I don't want to say that it's only upside because there's a way in
which we can kind of like slip into something that it turns into something that's not helpful for example just
beating ourselves up when we have difficulties let's not make this something else that we're going to beat
ourselves up with I'm going to going to just tell you right now there's going to be difficulties and it doesn't mean
anything about you as a person it doesn't mean you can't do it it doesn't mean anything it's just the way things
are it's not a personal failing it's just the way things
are but there's a way also that if we have this resolve or the I'm going to do this in order to meet this aspiration
that we can get really fixed views this is good and anything else that deters me
from it is bad and there's a way that we can have this uh dogmatism or fundamentalism or just this really fixed
view like I don't care about anything else you guys are inferior or something because you don't have the same idea
that I have or it's terrible way right to kind of like move through the world but sometimes we feel like in order to
support this determination and this resolve that we have to like really uh bear down and strain and strive and I'm
even making a fist when I'm doing this because it kind of feels like that but
then this fisted like having this fist um shows up in our minds too kind of
like being closed like no only this don't uh tell me about other ideas
that's silly I don't want to hear it or something there can be a certain harshness so that could be like one of
the downsides of this uh resolve or also there's can just be this
stubbornness or this immovability or obstinacy that kind of like bleeds out into other things
too like okay I'm going to try to control everything because I'm trying to control this one thing but that's not
going so well or I don't know it turns out right we can't really control nearly what we think we can right but when we
try to do something this idea of wanting to control it just bleeds out into other areas of our lives trying to control
other people and once uh I had a friend that was uh
trying to lose weight and this friend discovered that uh they were feeding the
cats less and less because well some you know we all should
be losing weight right but you know the cats didn't need to lose any weight at all but there's this way right that we
could kind of just bleed out into other things so the Buddha also kind gave
somebody some ways to work with this the way that having a resolve can slip into
some contraction or tightness or bleeding into stubbornness or obstinacy
or something like this so the these four
supports I'll just mention these briefly there four supports for this uh
resolve right you know this is Buddhism right so we have all these lists I love these lists but uh I know not everybody
loves them that's perfectly fine if you don't so this for um to support Adana
resolve determination persistence is some wisdom like some wisdom about like okay
how to stretch your capabilities in a way that honors who you are as a person
honors your life experience as well as stretches your capabilities not
something too big and not something too small there a little bit of wisdom required in this
it also takes wisdom to not beat yourself up to not allow this inner critic to get in there it takes some
wisdom to say oh I see you inner critic okay you can be there I'm going to do
this and I'm going to take care of myself but I'm just going to let you be on the side like so we're going to honor
and respect that their inner critic it's a habit that likes to come along but we don't need to give it Authority we don't
have to believe it we can just say okay I see you Mildred come along whatever name we want to give to
this person this is not uncommon for people to name their inner critics kind of names that give them a give a little
little levity to it right wisdom
truth this a second support for Adana this
persistence there's a way a number of different ways we can interpret this one is like maybe just being true
to your resolve staying with it that's I I'll
stick with that I could talk more about that but one way we can interpret truth here is just to be true to the
resolve third one is
relinquishment we're going to have to let go of some things
guaranteed we're going to have to let go go of something views or activities or
habits patterns I I don't know what they is and this willingness to let go of
what needs to be let go of we all know this and there's this a
quote in the dhap if you see a greater happiness that comes by forsaking a lesser
happiness be willing to forsake the less happiness for the greater
happiness tennis he says exchanging candy for gold like okay this candy is sweet but
you know gold is more valuable can help us in ways will make a difference unlike
candy so the third quality that can help us with this uh setting a resolve is
relinquishment just recognizing we will have to let go of things
because often the things that pull us off of the path are those things that look good and promise a quick
gratification and you know and those are well if those worked
you wouldn't be making a resolve for something different so just recognizing you're going to have to get let go of some of
these things and then here's the fourth quality is this sense of peace
like doing this resolve with a as much peace as you can in a way that we're not getting all
worked up with the difficulties that we're not uh as I'm saying again and
again and again that we're not creating this stories that it means that we're bad people or inadequate in some way or
that uh we can't do it or any of that kind of stuff but can we do it with peace like
yeah it's hard but I can do hard
things and maybe I can't do that big hard thing maybe I can do this little
hard thing find something you can do that takes two minutes or
something but to do it with some peace with as much ease and openness as you can find so that we don't kind of like
slip into the downsides of this resolve this stubbornness or
obsy so this idea of making an aspiration what's like really meaningful
for us and then setting a resolve or
determination what is something a quality something that we can do develop cultivate to help support our life going
towards this aspiration and then the Buddha talked about these four qualities to help this
resolve wisdom truth relinquishment and
peace and I'll end there and then I'll open it up for some questions thank
you anybody have some questions or
comments thank you Diana um last week I attended
a one-hour seminar on decluttering oh fantastic and it was for all of NASA
there were like over 400 people on this just you know so decluttering was quite quite
a you know timely for many many people it's a thing and they actually had six
categories of why you hang on things oh okay so I won't go through the whole six
but you don't want to sit up here and just give a whole another talk yeah well yeah yeah I mean it was a one hour talk
that I listened to but you know there were things about um I guess the ones
that stuck in my mind number one was um things that um had no home had no place
to go some things that were just junk you know just needed to be thrown out some things that you had overb bought
like you'd gone to Costco and bought you know like 5 PBS of nutmeg
you 5 PBS of nutmeg a lot of nutmeg yeah
um one of them was sentimental attachment and um I don't remember the
other two but um that sort of helped me at least think about okay well why
rather than just beating myself up like get rid of this more like well what's what's the
attachment here because um you know clinging is
something that we talk about but this was like you you could sort of look at what what might be behind that not
wanting to let go and maybe if I if I may we could even go as further to say
let's go ahead and put them in piles this thing doesn't have a home this thing uh has sentimental value you this
thing has um it's a to-do list and then just or this thing needs to be recycled
or something like that yeah Shuffle the Clutter yeah what and one of the other
categories was the someday Al oh yeah you know the projects like someday I'll
you know so we all have those too I'll get around to that someday yeah just in case yeah yeah thank you Jim thank
you anybody else have a comment or a
question hi um as I was sorry listening to you H I
was thinking that um what what is it that stops us from doing what we want to
do or where we want to give it's very clear in our mind that we we want this
we want this this is my dream or small dream big dream and um then
I I have a feeling that and there are some um training in the back in the
background some memories of you know in the subconscious that um it says why why
would you do that or you can't do that and
then um I I was going through this for a while and then I started
meditation and then um actually for me de decluttering my mind is more
important than getting rid of his stuff you know it's a so then I noticed that this I have to
focus on my conscious mind I have to be aware of what's going on in in my
conscious mind in my right in front of my brain that what is it that um I have
to train this because I it comes from all the background that my
experiences and then then I focus on my
awareness yeah yeah and during the meditation I the I'm practicing for a
while and in the beginning it didn't happen for two years I didn't even know
what what meditation and I sat with no result and I knew something finally it's
going to happen then so uh for for me when this meditation is
helping me to to be aware of what what is it that I
want but why am I not doing it and then
some the clarity comes in the me in the meditation yeah this recognition of
what's like preventing you from EXA what's in the way I'm I'm getting to
know myself yeah yeah yeah I know myself more than before um
that I'm very real when when you know you sit and then you get rid of all the
clutters as I sit my thinking my train of thought is getting less slower and
slower and then I get to the point that it's kind of empty and then I feel like
my creation comes from there and
um this has been really great experience for me I just wanted to share with you
and then you added some more some more knowledge that I can I can bring to my
awareness to um when I meditate and it's just
being aware I um I like to be conscious of what's going on in my mind we can't
just let it go we can't you know it's my baby it can my mind is my baby to take
care of it I'm not going to let everything comes there like before you
know yeah it can make a big difference if we can know what's happening in our minds but we don't always do right so we
can't necessarily wait until we have the perfect Clarity but uh but thank you for
bringing up like okay what what is getting in the way that makes me think that maybe my the next talk next week
I'll talk about okay what are some of these things that we that get in the way of doing the thing that's important to
us right would you be surprised if I said well the Buddha has a list of course of course right but thank
you thank you and what is your name Nicole Nicole thank you Nicole thank you so thank you all and I wish you safe
travels home and uh all the best thank
you