so good evening everyone welcome and uh maybe as we did last week
if you have any questions you want to ask this might be a good time people some people might still be coming and so
do start officially a little bit in do you have any have any questions about
what I taught last week or about medit your meditation up here on the
stage yeah yeah if you can use the mic please
can you hear me um so one of the things that I don't seem the ability to do to
be able to observe my thoughts I guess the thoughts or the emotions maybe are
so strong that I just you know I'm hopped on that train and I don't realize it till I've kind of come off the train
so I was wondering if you had suggestions you hold it closer because my hearing's not so good so I really
have to have get the yeah so I'm not able to observe my thoughts yeah um I
guess maybe they're I'm just so attached to them and I was wondering if you had any
suggestions yeah I don't know what to say I mean uh it then I wouldn't worry
about it but do you notice when you're lost in thought
I I notice afterwards after I've kind of got off the train I can say Okay prob
how how long do you spend on the train it it could be 30 seconds it could be two minutes could be five minutes so so
one part one way to deal with it is uh just be content with that and slowly
what you're doing is trying to develop your mindfulness so when you come to after however long it is just emphasize
exercise the muscle of mindfulness and try to be present for a while to be with what's going on and slowly over time
you'll settle you relax that your ability to be mindful to get stronger and at some point it'll be time for you
to see your thoughts as they occur and you won't get pulled into them so quickly that's one thing you could do
but uh is there any time during the day where you're self-reflective about the
fact that you're thinking like do you ever say I have to think about a shopping list now
or yes so I mean there could be lesser things or it could be you know
more serious stuff you know my mom died a few years ago so a whole bunch of
stuff was happening with the Estates that I understand but it could be a simple because I'm having trouble hearing it it it could be as simple as
yeah did I pay my you know water bill or something like that so so so find something which you can think about that
you can watch also that you can stay you can stay mindful as you're thinking and see what you can learn about yourself so
probably pick a one that's uh weaker so to speak yeah yeah but but maybe not in
meditation but uh but you as you go about your day and and you have one of those weaker ones and you're and you're
you're aware that you're thinking just start start paying attention to some of the different characteristics of your
thinking like we did yesterday last last week okay thank you and then slowly you'll become more familiar and maybe
then you won't be pulled in so
quickly the other thing about uh thinking that uh and the more easily we
get caught in thought the more likely there's tension somewhere in our system
in our body in our mind so when you finally catch yourself uh being lost in
thought oh one of the things to do at that point is check in where am I tense
because people who notice their thinking and they just come back to their breathing without doing anything else um the conditions for thinking are still
there so you have to relax so so see if you can just take a deep breath and just relax and see see what can be relaxed
and that could be the body it could be the the thinking muscle itself the kind of tension around in the mind where
you're thinking because tension it's kind of like this um that um I don't
know if any of you have had the experience that um if you're squeezing a toothpaste tube you could be
wiping it off from the from the opening trying to get it away and it'll keep
coming out you have to stop squeezing so I'm not trying to be
disrespectful of your thinking but um too much but uh but if if there's a lot of
tension in our system it's kind of like the toothpaste tube is being squeezed you know so you have to stop
squeezing and so don't just let go of your thoughts and come back spend some time in seeing where the tension is and
see if you can soften a little bit don't be too too ambitious about relaxing but
it is really helpful to relax someone
else yeah I found that uh the labeling technique that you mentioned I think in
one the which technique the labeling technique that is when I'm racing so every so often it pop up and say okay
that is that and then go again in the train so so that was helping and slowly kind of see fantastic it the labing for
some people is extremely helpful and that also might help you with your thinking that um if you have a if you if
you have a kind of relaxed ongoing rhythm of just labeling your experience
in breath out breath sound
itch breath INB breath out breath belly tight feeling tightness breathing in
breathing out thinking uh if you have that habit regular that that you're using a
thinking to keep you present rather than using your thinking to take your away so
an idle mind sometimes wants to do something and so sometimes you want to give the thinking mind something to do
and the labeling gives it something to do and the regular but it's helping you
out rather than taking you away some people complain about labeling because just makes the mind more busy and they
think however it's actually better than the alternative which is the getting lost in
thought over and over again and then also because if you have a regular kind of gentle rhythm of noting you're less
like more likely to notice if you get lost in thought because you stop labeling so that's a so that glad you
brought it up
to good evening um I remember the first
class you mentioned that there was a reason for your ordering of the breath
body emotion thought yeah I was wondering if you could remind us what that is and then I seem to recall there
was something about it that was maybe culturally based culture culturally
based and I was wondering if you would have a different order if you were
teaching the class in a different part of the world
um well I think one of the cultural things that's uh has developed in
Buddhism in in the United States is putting much more emphasis on
emotions uh if you go to and uh and so very famous uh Westerner who's a very
senior monk in Thailand now he's a monk aano and he's almost retired now but um
uh he says he's fluent and Thai but also teaches lot in English and he says he
teaches differently for the two communities for the ties they don't have the same um e culturation around Freud
and Yung and Western psychology that is kind of part and parcel of some of the
popular or common culture in the United States and so so so so common here in
the United States that people don't even know that it's where it comes from it's just part of life it's just what obvious
isn't it but we use language we use thoughts we use orientations that are very much they're only 100 years old and
kind of crept into our culture in the west they don't have that in Thailand so
here John Sam will talk about psychology emotions acceptance so all these things
that have to do with psychology he would never do that in Thailand ties that wouldn't compute it
wouldn't work so there are cultural differences that we take into account and um and in fact it's hard to
find in some Indian languages a nice clean word for the English word emotion
it's even more so in the in P the ancient language so we we've organized the human
pie we all have the same pie we're all humans but we cut the pie pieces in
different sizes or different ways and we have this we' we've made this cut in the
pie and called it emotions they cut it a little bit differently and called it some could be something else and so so
those are kind of cultural differences and uh so the logic of what I did is that it's a thinking is hard
for many people to be uh one of the biggest obstacles to being present because we get pulled into thought
it's a lot easier and if you if you start with being mindful of thinking what it's going to be is thinking about
thinking it's not really going to be mindfulness so it's a lot easier to be mindful of
thinking uh if you have some mindfulness of your emotions because a lot of them
uh thoughts especially the ones that drive us or catch us have an emotional base the emotions are sometimes the
factory sometimes it's the other way around but as it generically that's kind of it's easier then emotions are always
present moment phenomena thoughts could be about the past and the future and we get pulled out of them present so so
it's easier to be with thinking if we know if we're connected to the emotions it's easier to be with emotions if
you're connected to the body the body creates a container a context a safety
of grounding to be with em emotions that is hard to do for some people if you
just some emotions are just so difficult just be aware of your emotions and some people have panic attacks or
something and so but if you have the body as a foundation it's easier grounding and it's uh easier to ground
yourself in your body some people say in if you start with um breathing and uh
breathing kind of kind of stabilizes some people it gets the other your head enough and so it's easier to be with
your body what I've seen in recent eration of basna teachers like what I'm
teaching here is that we have much more diversity now among the teaching community so my generation were
basically white privileged people and so they had a particular way in which they
organized or had to deal with the world with a newer generation of teachers who
come from very diverse populations some really disadvantaged populations in this culture where there's been a lot of
trauma then uh they they find that it's much better to start with the body than with breathing and so that in a sense
that's a cultural difference as well and so so for them I'm not as
trauma sensitive in my teachings for a certain population uh than they are and that's true you know so we have I have
to kind of navigate all these all these different issues there cultures within our culture
right so how do we manage with it all so is
that hi Gil um i' like everyone else I'm suffering through the all these uh
uncontrolled thoughts coming um
entering uh my mind when I'm uh meditating and it comes and goes Etc
but I wanted to say that uh I've been um since the pandemic I've been uh
attending the morning sessions um pretty much every day that
uh that's on and um I'm finding um over
the past 3 years I feel more
settled I don't know how now I feel my language has
changed I refrain from saying some of the things I used to say or the way I
said them before
um I can't I'm not sure it's wisdom or whatever but I see
it when I digress or move away from what I think I should be doing I see it right
away perhaps before I was Oblivion to
it so it does
work I have no idea how but it does work yes and uh that's all I had to say great
thank you I love hearing that that's a nice testimonial it does work and it's a slow process and uh slowly we begin to
be able to monitor to see what's happening while as it's happening and we
have more choice we have a choice with the words we use and the activities we do because we see it coming we see
ourselves in the middle of it and and there's much more awareness also the meditation provides a different
reference point for what it means to be alive that uh you discover that it's
that you can be alive and feel at ease you can alive and feel um comfortable in
your skin you can be alive and feel a kind of ethical sensitivity the the body
that's one of the reasons so good to be in the body connected to it the body is kind of an ethical
antenna that uh it picks up and understands when something is eth ethically off it'll understand it in
yourself it the attentions the yuckiness or there it's very subtle but if you're
lost in thought all the time or filled with greed and hatred all the time you don't have that subtle tuning in to the
the antenna that's here but if you're slow down quiet down you
sens heighten sensitivity and one of the consequences of that is heightened ethical uh wanting to live an ethical
life so um and uh it's quite inspiring to see it in people as they get into
this practice so you you kind of describe that I feel there's someone next to me watching everything I do yeah
and it's yourself right it's myself but in a way you know in private you may think think do something but not in
presence of others yeah very nice I feel there's somebody right next to me fantastic fantastic so so this
heightened ethical sensitivity is part of what happens through this practice and um and you're not even
asking for it some of you are going to run run away now you and um and one of
the things that the probably one of the more common ethical reports that people come to me about here people who work in
a kind of business environment where work environment where people kind of hang
out to the coffee machine or at snack time talking about things and they say you know the the medium for talking at
work is gossip but I don't want to gossip anymore it doesn't feel good but it now
it's really hard to be social with people it's like now I'm feel like I'm disconnected or I'm not part of the gang
and it's kind of awkward because that's what that's how people connect is by gossiping but it just feels wrong wrong
to do it so um and then there's people who find out that they the work they do
remember one person who said that uh the company he worked with was got a
commission a job to make parts for a fighter jets and he went to his boss and said
you know I can't do that can I be assigned to something else and so he was
and so it wasn't anybody taught them to be ethical it's just this ethical intent
develops inside and what I'd like to say is that that antenna is you already so
it's not like anybody's imposing anything on you it's like you that capacity to feel and sense in a deeper
ethical way is is ever present in you just mostly you're distracted from it
you know busy and too busy to notice so for me that's very inspiring I
don't know what some of you think about that I usually I never said this in intro class
though I have said sometimes that we could just call this a a five-week introduction to
ethics but then no one would
come so um okay so let's uh get ethical let's
meditate and um so what I'll do is uh it'll be a guided kind of mindfulness
exercise is not exactly how you should meditate you could if you want but it's but it's to give you a a um a direct
experience of a way that mindfulness can work so the way that we teach it here is
as I've said the default is to cultivate mindfulness and stability steadiness continuity of
attention on the breathing but if anything happens that
uh is pulling on your attention if it's just a sound in the room and it doesn't pull you away from
the breathing don't worry about it but if a sound is strong enough it starts pulling you
away then follow your attention follow where your awareness is
drawn and uh and and be aware note mental labeling of what that is that's
has your attention know it be mindful of that for a while and then when that's no longer
compelling come back to your breathing and so that could be the body it could
be emotions it could be thinking it could be sounds in the room it's a lot
of different things it could be but it is we're always going back to the center so in this exercise I'm going to we're
to alternate between being with the breathing and then going out to these uh
three other areas that I've taught you about today and then uh I'll add one
more area uh to that so that that's what we'll be doing okay
so so assume a meditation posture if it's the end of the day and
you feel really tired you might feel like relaxing back I would suggest that
for this time you sit up straighter so there's a little bit more energy coming out of your body into your
mind and if you're tense and agitated from a difficult day then you might want
to settle back and rest a little bit more in the back rest
or and then with gently closing your eyes or if you keep them half open
having them pointed down towards the
floor and to transition into the meditation you could take a few long
slow deep breaths deep enough maybe like 3/4 full
not not without a strain but full enough lungs that you
feel your insides your rib cage
expand stretch and then relax on the exhale
with a longer relaxation long exhale than
usual just to allow more settling in the shoulders and the
arms maybe the
belly and then let it then your breathing return to
normal and continue for a few breaths to see if there's more places in
your body that you can relax
soften and this relaxing the body is also a way of becoming more sensitive to
the body attuned to your
body and then you might also see if in the mind the thinking mind is there any
tension pressure contraction associated with
thinking thinking mind and if there is as you
exhale soften the thinking mind as if it's a muscle relaxing the
thinking
muscle
and then Center yourself on your
breathing your body your torso has its own experience of
breathing follow that experience as you breathe in
and breathing
out
for
and now switch your attention from
breathing to some the most compelling sensation in
your body it doesn't have to be that strong but whatever it might
be and the body has its own experience of that place of those
Sensations notice how the body is experiencing this strong bodily
sensation letting your awareness be close in or letting your awareness rest
in this place in your body while you feel it receive the
sensations and for a few moments to allow this bodily sensation to be there
as it as if it has full permission it's okay and for you you accompany it you're
present with
it and then return to the
breathing maybe there's some way that you can Center yourself on the
breathing the body
breathing
and then in a relaxed way notice the predominant emotion or
mood or mind State inner state that you
have doesn't have to be easily identified as an
emotion but some St state that you
have and allow it to be there for these few moments of
mindfulness as if it's never had a chance to be in the sun the sun of
awareness let it be there and just notice it feel it feel how it's experience in the
body
for
see if you can experience your emotional state mood state of mind without any
stories connected to it without adding adding any meaning to
it just let it be what it
is
and then return to your breathing if it helps you you might take a little bit stronger Fuller in
breath to reconnect
for
and then continuing now for a three breath Journey just give yourself over
to three
breaths
and now switch your attention to your
thinking whether it's strong or weak
whether it fades away if you notice it
notice your
thinking and see if you can notice how you're you're thinking without thinking
more very simple matter of
fact if there's an emotion connected connected to
it be aware of
that if there's Body Sensations connected to it include awareness of
that
e
and then return to your breathing reestablishing
yourself on the body breathing
for
and then one more shift of attention now become aware more aware of
how you're mindful as you're aware of breathing or anything
else how would you characterize how you're
aware is there any strain involved
expectation
is there any hesitation or reluctance
or or lack of
commitment and then come back to your
breathing so will continue for just a few more
minutes maybe with the breathing at the center but as you need to become aware
of whatever pulls your attention and then return to the
breathing
for
e
for and then to end this
sitting you can take some long slow deep breaths feeling the contact of your body
against whatever surface that you're connected
to and when you're ready you can open your
eyes
[Music]
so um so this is a particular way of doing mindfulness meditation there are
many different ways it's taught and um and I just want to say
that for some people what works best is to just stay with what I taught the
first evening mindfulness of breathing and don't make it any more complicated
than that and um and if all you did was every time you wondered off you came
back to your breathing stayed with it and developed stability in your breathing it can be
phenomenal the Buddhist teacher that I spent time with in Japan said that everything you need to know about
Buddhism will be discovered through your breathing so it's breathing is
considered really great so if that's you want to keep it really simple that's one
opportunity for you one of the reasons why we expand it outwards to include the
body emotions and thinking and then other things as we go off is that then
more of our life comes under the purview of our attention and
awareness and the more we can hold everything in in Awareness it tends to
move our whole life towards Health it tends to move to freedom to Healing to
all kinds of good things and we learn how to be present in life for our
emotions for our thinking for different parts of our life and it there'll be a time when it's really useful to have
that skill when I was a Zen student um I was pretty good at the
breath meditation thing but I had no idea how to be mindful of my anger in fact I didn't
even know I was angry people would tell me gil you're so angry and I said
really um and uh there was uh no um no
teaching about how to notice your emotions and be mindful of them and so they were just there operating in the
background kind of subconsciously then and having their effect and influence on me same thing with the thinking and so
to be able to have a practice that encompasses everything um in my mind Buddhism
doesn't say this explicitly is that then your awareness becomes
sacred s it's so special to have an awareness that nothing is left out
nothing's outside of it nothing is not acceptable for awareness to
hold then it's a you enter into kind of almost like a different universe if everything can be held in
awareness and um and so so we're learning how to do that in this practice
how everything has a place for an awareness how everything we can include and be present for it and the big big
big Delight Thea moment for me in um when I was practicing in Asia was um I
was learning about how to be mindful and I was learning just just a simple Act of mindfulness there was a
kind of Freedom that could be found there freedom from entanglement freedom from being for and against variety of
kind of freedom and I said wow and I had this moment where I kind of was stopped in my
literally stopped in my tracks and I realized that if I thought you know I
can be mindful of anything that's an experience anything that it's a direct experience that I'm having in the moment
in theory I can be mindful of it and so in theory I could be free in
relationship to everything I was just and I got so happy that wow that kind of
freedom is possible in this world uh and it comes from being mindful being present for
experience so we're trying to teach you here at IMC a way of in bringing in or
encompassing your whole life in the scope of mindfulness of
awareness and um and so one of the things that includes then is uh and not
just meditation but bringing the practice into daily life and one of the great rewards that I get from just do
teaching this is when people come meditating for a little while and they say this is fine and good this
meditation but how do I bring this into my life how do I bring more mindfulness into my daily life and my activities or
what I do and um the line between your
you in meditation and you outside of medit meditation is an arbitrary
line and and this the deeper ethical sensitivity deeper sense of Peace of
calm or deeper intimacy with yourself deeper sense of not being caught seeing
more choice in how you what you're doing and you meditate all these good things that happen with in mindfulness why
should you only do it in while you're meditating why not the rest of your life
that was my big question that brought me to live at a Buddhist Monastery I wasn't
so much interested exactly in the monastery I was interested in how to expand what was happening in meditation
in talking with people working doing the different things that I do and so a very
important part of this practice and or potential in this practice is to start bringing mindfulness in daily life
activities so rather than being distracted and we live in a distracted culture distracting culture I mean
people have written about about this or people who get paid a lot of money to keep you distracted or to to grab your
attention and keep it going you know and get more clicks on the your device and whatever to get people's attention it's
it's you know and so people's minds they are jumping around jumping and jumping and jumping here and here and here and
in doing that they're not being mindful they're not centered settled on their experience here and
now and um and so uh so to bring this
mindfulness into daily life is helped a lot by find things you can
do that you just do that one thing don't multitask if you're at home and
cooking just cook don't have the radio if anybody has radios
anymore podcasts don't have um you know music
don't have don't be on the phone don't have all the on at the same time and read the news on your on your your
tablet you know just to cooking just to be as you're chopping a
carrot just be there like you would be just with your breathing in meditation
just be with a carrot and chopping the carrot put your attention in your hands have your eyes
looking at what you're doing and be and then watch your mind and let if your mind wonders off
talk thinking about something else then you know this is boring come
back no there's more you know I have a lot to do I have to multitask otherwise I can't do all these things come back
it's just you and the carrot and and then slowly you'll learn
something about getting concentrated you'll reclaim your mind that you've
lost to distractions and you'll feel how delicious it it is to be present for
activity washing your dishes just do the dishes with both
hands you don't have to do this of course but if you want to start learning how to bring mindfulness into your daily
life you have to train you have to practice it and develop it that capacity and then um and then start
expanding where you do it um what I learned from Zen a little
trick from Zen was every time I walk through a door
frame you're walking into a new place pay
attention be mindful of the place you're walking into it was it's been a fantastic thing to do I'm certainly
capable of being doing very important things like thinking about how I'm going
to teach mindfulness to you caught up in that and I just walk you know from one room in my house to another room in the
house and like thinking you know I'm capable of that but it's that's not a a good life
either it's good to be present for the life you're living it might seem boring it might
seem you're not getting a lot of excitement in your life then but it's kind of like you have to go a transition
time like kind of like withdrawal time like withdrawing from caffeine to switch over to being present
until being present is delicious it's deeply satisfying it's kind of like you now
feel a sense of Integrity or wholeness or completeness or contentment with
whatever you're doing because you're present for it in a good way and then when you do that that
becomes a vantage point for wisdom and one of the qualities of what
what mindfulness is leading to is wisdom to understand better what we do in our lives and um and so once you have some
subtleness some stability some continuity of
mindfulness uh that becomes a a uh that helps highlight when you start losing
it so an analogy that's given is that if you have a a a
napkin or a towel or something that's full of
stains really dirty you and no one else might notice
one more stain it's just not noticed but if you clean it and bleach
it and there are no stains then you notice the dirt spot that comes and then
you clean it or do something so it turns out the same thing with our mind if our mind is fragmented busy running around
doing too many things distracted from distractions by
distractions then you don't see what you're doing one more mean word I mean
you don't even know to you've been mean to someone because you know you're you're mean all the time you know you
it's just normal or something but when you settle down and become calm you see
the meanness coming oh look there it is you know oh wow that's a big deal I
didn't know how I did it so much and so we start we start seeing how
this works so I wonder do a demonstration to you of what you might
see about how your mind works when you are settled enough and
mindful enough to see and
um and I hope that this is kind of an analogy to you so the idea is you apply
this to yourself in some way so it's a kind of show and
tell so
okay so here we have a
flower there's a famous story in Zen that once upon a time the Buddha had
an assembly of people listening to him ready for him to give a Dharma talk
a sermon and he didn't say anything but he lifted up a single flower like
this maybe most people were perplexed but one of his disciples
smiled and he knew that that disciple understood
it so then we're supposed to figure out what this meaning of the story
is but this idea of holding up a flower so the flower many people think a flower
is beautiful a flower is a flower and with one flower like this we have what in
Buddhism is called the suchness of the flower the flower is just being the
flower just it is itself it doesn't even even use the word flower to describe itself it just
is the isness of the flower it's content being
itself happy but now look what
happens now let's see how I do
this now I'm holding up two flowers and now we can say something
about the first flower we couldn't say before for we can say that this flower in my
left hand is the big flower and this is the small
flower big small okay that's pretty
straightforward this is the big one right so there's I'm going to do a slight of
hand and you're going to see how not going to do it so fast so you don't see the magic you're GNA you're G to be
you're going to see how the magic works and some of the magic is your
mind so this was the big flower
right it's kind of wilted but
now this is the big flower and the big flower has become the
smaller flower you see that small flower big flower wait a
minute big flower small flower what is it it's a
flower the isness of the flower but the human
mind can compare and some things only exist in
the comparison big and small only exists in the mind that compares it's not
inherent in the flower a lot of human
suffering comes from comparisons one way or the other compare ourselves to others to
ourselves in the past or in the future ideals and all kinds of things as we get
quieter and mindfulness gets stronger we start seeing the mind doing
this we see the birth of a comparison and because we see it in
mindfulness we have a choice whether you know do we believe it is this a useful
comparison if I want to ask someone to go get the big flower then that's useful
because I say big flower not the small one there's only two so that's that's
practical but um go get the ugly flower or get the beautiful flower for
me thank you
bring me the beautiful person no no bring me the ugly person I mean isn't
that painful that we live in a world like that and so you know we do a lot of
comparisons and I you know I did a lot of it when I was younger for myself you know I my selfworth was tied
to all kinds of things about my body you know I grew up in the hippie times so I
was a little bit little bit young for it but I used to sit in school pulling my hair to make it grow
faster because that's what it took or it was just it was just a generation I was
in junior high school M Middle School when um they started
um bleaching blue jeans and they would some people would
actually put them on the road for cars to drive over they're brand new right or put through the washing machine 10 12
times to really make them look old and they would tear them and all that and so
I didn't know this this kind of happened over the course of a summer when I was away in Europe and I came back and my
hair was shorter my blue jeans were new and this was a
disaster I was no longer acceptable whereas when I lived in Italy
for that summer I had longer hair than any of the Italians men boys so I was
cool and all I had to do is fly over the Atlantic and come come back to United States and I was no longer
cool right big small fires big flower small flower cool man boy not cool boy
it's ridiculous right when you describe it that way but we do this kind of thing all day
long so part of the wisdom of this practice is have the foundation the
subtleness the clarity that we can see this operating as it's
operating we can see it in oursel we can see it in other people it's tragic what happens in
our society around these kinds of things but to see it in ourselves and
then see it clearly enough we don't buy into it we see it for what it is before
we get hooked before it drives us evokes emotions and tensions and all kinds of
things so this is an example of the wisdom that can AR arise from the practice because we see what goes on in
the mind so this mindfulness of thinking is not just an abstract thing it has
tremendous uh you know consequence and application as we go about our life and
so to cultivate slow they cultivate the greater and greater capacity for
mindfulness so then in terms of daily life and bringing into daily life it's
invaluable to meditate every day or six days a week and um the um and the trick about
that is to uh sit as long as it allows you to sit every day
so if you say I'm going to sit for 45 minutes but your life doesn't allow for that then you get discouraged and you
give it up but if you can only do 10 minutes do 10
minutes and probably should be able to get 10 minutes in if you can't
do it anyway and find out what's going on find
out what emotions what beliefs What feelings what restlessness what
anxiety is operating that you can't take 10 minutes to meditate you'll learn a
lot about yourself that you won't learn if you just give into all those things
and go about you know not paying any attention being driven by your whatever
your your desires or anxieties so sitting every day for 10 minutes what might happen to you is that
you might find that 10 minutes after a while feels too short well don't sit longer because I
said so but if you say so well it's okay if
you get the feeling you die it's nice I like to sit more you might start seeing that it makes a difference in your daily
life you might find that you're kinder you might find that you're more relaxed
you might find that you're more paced in what you do you might some people actually say that um that uh they
meditate regularly and they don't really see the effect after a while they say well does it really do me any good and
then they stop oh boy that was a hard day I you
know I got so much more agitated so much more anxious so much more you know speeded
up so the idea is if you every day for a short period of Time start bringing
mindfulness in daily life um I don't know how it is so much
nowadays but um uh there was a time where uh I could feel that if my
telephone rang there was some inner drive that it
was essential to pick up the phone answer the phone as quickly as possible
no one ever told me that but I I felt like was urgent I have to get there and I learned you don't have to do that most
people don't hang up after two rings and I found that I use that as a
mindfulness spell I would use that just check in with myself breathe relax and
maybe the fourth or the fifth not not so long right four or five rings but just
that little bit of time to be connected with myself change my posture relax I
was so much better shape to answer the phone I had much better conversations
because I took that time to just gave myself that time so there's a lot of
these things you can do through the day and um and the more you do it the wiser
you'll become meaning the more clarity you'll you'll see more clearly what
you're actually doing you'll see the effect that desires
and ill will has and you'll say wait a minute this doesn't make any sense I
knew someone here at IMC who had resentment for an ex
partner for I think seven years and then one day she was being
mindful about her experience of resentment and she said to wait a
minute I'm harming myself more than him
and then she gave up her resentment so to really see the the cost
of these things so here's another teaching story that comes from
Buddhism uh it has to do with uh how you apparently how you uh catch trap monkeys
in India so you take a coconut and you you cut a slit in it and
kind of carve out a little bit the inside and you put some candy inside because apparently monkeys like
sweets but it's the the cut is a slot like you know so in order for the monkey
to get the the hand into the slot it has to have the hand flat and it can get in
but in order to grab the candy it makes a little bit of a fist and once it's a
fist it it can't get it out that slot but it's so greedy it's not not
going to let go and so the hunter just comes and picks it up oh because the coconut is
attached to a rope to a tree right so it so it can't go
anywhere and so um and so the monkey was so consumed by
its greed it doesn't see the the dangerous position it was putting
himself in but if the maybe if the monkey had been
mindful he would have maybe maybe felt the problems of having this fist that
can't get out and then he would let go and pulled his hand out so we can feel
that for ourselves we can feel the effect of greed how it makes us impatient how it leads to anger how it
leads to Compulsive activity that ends up harming us and we can then ask
where's the where's the grasping where are we fisted up where we caught and because we know how to bring mindful to
mindfulness to our experience we can feel it the fist in our body we can feel where the tension is in our
body we might feel the emotions the desire the greed that we might have for
something might be really have Deep Roots inside it might be we feel really
insecure and Afraid and we think if I can have that then I'll be safe but that's fascinating to
understand those deeper roots and then bring mindfulness to that it might be think that because
you're being Mindful and you know how to be mindful as of thinking you start noticing the beliefs
around what you're trying to grasp what you're greedy for if I have this people
will love me if I could have this then I'll be a success and everyone I'll have
high status if I can have this then I'll have the pleasure that will put make
everything right something you know you fill in the blank I'm just trying to make something up but um so to live a
life that two things where you see all these things so you can be
wiser and to live a life where you see them and you know from your direct
experience something better you know you can like you know
it's better not to grasp it's better not to be caught in those comparisons it's better to be settled
than it is to be tense agitated there's a feeling of wholeness feeling
of contentment feeling of Peace feeling of well-being that we can carry with
us it's better than a lot of other things and so we do have a healthy
comparison there's there a place for comparisons oh look at that if I spend my
day you know just pursuing everything that I want
more more and more more that doesn't feel as good as a a
day where I live contented and peaceful and at home here settled the end of the day I fall asleep
in the second way the greedy way I'm still spinning many years ago when I was in my
early 20s um I loved you know this is you know some of
you matter I hope I don't explain to you what this is um but uh there was
something called bookstores and there were lots of them
and um and I loved going into bookstores and uh did a lot of reading
and uh but after a while I realized when I went to bookstores I always was really exhausted and tired when I left why am I
so tired and uh and then I realized some point what it was was I had I had almost
no money so I couldn't buy any of the books that I saw but I wanted a lot of
the books I want that one I want that one I want that one at that one and I was just consumed by greed wanting
wanting wanting wanting and to spend an hour in a bookstore only wanting is
exhausting and that's what tired me out and when I realized that then I went
into booksto I still went into bookstores but then I kind of just chilled I just kind of roamed around and
looked for some sections and you know approach the bookstore in very different ways so I wouldn't get
exhausted so um this is another example of wisdom operating understanding the
consequences understanding the what's better for us and what's worse for us
and having a clearer and clear reference point that that's of for some people it's
unimaginable the degree of peace and happiness we're capable of experiencing the an unimaginable the the
feeling of feeling fulfilled feeling happy with ourselves for no
reason at all just because we're alive in this beautiful way we don't have to
be fulfilled our desires don't have to be fulfilled for us to be subtle and
happy you can just sit and meditate and feel greater degree of Peace than maybe
that you feel any other time and the beautiful thing that happens with this
practice is that then your inner well-being sense of well-being
inside becomes less and less dependent on what's happening in the
world and you're no longer a victim where your well-being is influenced by whoever
comes along and and uh Praises you or blames you then you're kind of like at
their whim but if you car your own confidence and
well-being and happiness that's that doesn't depend on what how people think
about you then you're not so caught in that world let them think what they
do that's not dependent on having the latest and the greatest device that's
out there that happiness only lasts for an
hour after you get the device or something like that but the happiness of this inner device
inner connection that we can get with ourselves that can last for a long
time so um now it's your turn and if we have
time we can do another little meditation but do you have any uh questions now about any of this and what I said today
and what's happened here or um about these weeks we've been
together
yes
please here you go thank you
um this is maybe kind of a trivial thing but uh I think
of some of the practice as it from kind of a science scientific or curious point
of view so like with distractions when you were talking about doing one thing
at a time I uh I have habits of
multitasking and so I will just lately I've been do trying the
habit of just eating and not reading I can talk to you
know I can talk but I just just eat
and seeing what's that's like so I guess this is more of a comment than a
question that I'm just approaching some parts of the practice from that sort of
practical let's just try it see what happens I love it that's that that's the
spirit of this practice that's that's how we become our own teacher in this practice by trial
and error experimenting trying things out seeing what we learn that's definitely the way the go and that's
even true in meditation there's a little bit of we try things out like today I'm just going to stay more with my breath
what's that like or and then noticing how hard it is like when I start I'm
like oh the newspaper's over there I could read no don't read exactly so I think I I that's very very s very
gratifying for me to know that you're approaching it that way with experimentation and learning that's Fant
that's that's the way to become wise thank you
bu um it's more of a comment just appreciating something that you were just talking about
um I found the idea idea really interesting of trying to understand why
we want the things we want um because you know I'm aware that there's this kind of constant engine of
Desire I don't think I'm alone and um and we live in a very
materialistic Society also and um so I I
think the next step after recognizing that you have kind of non-stop
desires is actually looking underneath and asking yourself what the root of it
is and right for some reason that never occurred to me before but I really like the idea a lot yeah that's fantastic so
so there's a number of ways to get to the roots under the surface to see what's going on I mean you a person could go for a
walk and think about it reflect on it and analyze in kind of more intellectual way people go to therapy for that kind
of purpose and find out the the historical roots of these things in the
in the mindfulness practice it's it's one way out one approach out of many approaches and I'm not saying this is
the best approach or the right approach but I was just to give you the full
power in Poss a way that mindfulness Works we're not thinking our way we're
not analyzing we're actually being very simple so we would bring careful
attention to the experience of desire and as we stay centered and
centered on the desire get to know how it feels like in the body what it gets feels emotionally what's happening in the thinking mind what's happening even
in the breathing you start seeing what's going on then at some point things begin kind
of clearing up or breaking open a little bit and then what jumps up at you what
comes to you what gets revealed not through analysis not by figuring anything out oh underneath that desire
there's anxiety or anxiety is the root of it it could be something else I'm
just um so the point being we're not trying to go below the surface in this
practice we're trying to be with what's obvious in such a way that whatever needs to be revealed will show itself to
us we don't have an agenda in in the moment in the bigger
picture we do have the agenda that yeah I really want to get to the root of this and Gil says all I have to do is just
stay really present and then it'll come okay so I'm going to be present without an agenda because
that's a good you know that's guilt says that's how to fills my agenda it's but it's kind of
true just be present for you know so just just be with the obvious the Hallmark of this kind of mindfulness is
is just be present for what's obvious and then what's obvious unfolds and changes as you stay and be present and
over time you get through the layers and the depth
um I've been practicing with is my the volume okay yes for me it's good okay um
I've been practicing with trying to stay present with really kind of strong
unpleasant difficult emotions when they arise and sometimes it's really tricky to do
um especially like with anger it's like there's a heat to it and just it's it's tough to stay with it um I appreciated
some things that you said in the last number of sessions that that have been helpful for this things like I love the
analogy of um it was something about not looking a cat right in the eyes just
kind of coming up alongside it and waiting for it or something like that
and just wanted to take the opportunity to ask if you have any other suggestions or guidance for how to be able to stay
present with really kind of you know big emotions or tough emotions yeah uh there's I mean that's a
lot to be said but uh like with this really strong anger um a nice thing to
do is not meditate with it but maybe go for a long walk and and give freedom to
the anger give freedom to your thinking but be present and so there's something
about walking the rhythm of walking for me at least that keeps me from getting stuck in my thoughts stuck in whatever's
happening and then but I'm paying attention but I'm also giving it Freedom I'm not
trying to stop it I'm just letting it run and then because then so I'm it's
easier to be present for it that way sometimes than it is sitting still the
walking helps it all and that might be a good way to kind of practice mindfulness while walking that's bit by bit you kind
of start kind of breaking it open the other thing to do is sometimes with
strong emotions like anger is um uh again sometimes it's helpful to
just let the thinking just run don't don't try to stop the thinking but uh
because maybe that's even needed who knows but anger you know some powerful processes going on we don't even know
what's going on so in this practice we want to be respectful of all emotions so
even anger um but what I found really helpful is to keep what I call composting it in
the body so every time I noticed that I'm thinking about my Angry thoughts feeling angry I have enough wherewithal
to be present I feel the anger how it's being expressed in the body how it feels in the body and for me that's called
composting it in the body and I keep referring it back to the body the body
and every time I do that I'm kind of disengaging a little bit with the story but I'm not trying to stop the story and
I find that if I do that over and over again something very different begins to happen but I have to be very careful not
to uh want a quick fix I just be patient and just okay just feel it in the body
feel it in the body if there's grief it can be very much the same way
grief grief is more more commonly recognized that the heart knows how to
grieve if we get out of the way if we allow it and so the art of it allowing it is to allow it without sinking into
it without participating in it but radical allowance to grieve you're
allowed to cry all you want in this meditation as long as you sit reasonably straight and but as soon as you go oh
poor me then you're participating and then then the inner
movement the inner processing that can the heart knows how to do gets
interrupted so so I've known people who sat like this look they you know from a distance they look like they're deep in
meditation not moving and they're cheeks are streaming with
yours that that's
fine um yeah just a um experience I had um last session
actually last week that this is making me think of so I came in here and was
feeling some anger about something else and um so I was like okay you know I'm I'm here let me try and be present with
us and something switched and it was grief actually and so I was like okay let me
try and be with the grief and when I was with the grief and not in the story
about the grief it was like it got silent actually and it wasn't grief it
was something else I don't know fantastic yeah that's that's so you're describing very well what can happen
here and um and uh because you weren't in the story the story sometimes feeds
the problem story is kind of participating it and feeding it but if if we cannot be involved in the story
all kinds of other things have a chance to happen that was beautiful for for my point of you is an example of the
potential
here uh I just wanted to say thank you and you spoke on Sunday about um one
aspect of in your talk was about community and I think I'm very new to
this so I I really appreciate the opportunity to meet some people that are also on the path and I think we're all
kind of on our own separate paths but uh towards self-improvement or Discovery
and I just want to say thank you for great for this community thank you very much so that's another thing in terms of
uh learning to bring this practice more into your life and spread it out it's actually helpful from per time to time
to go meditate with other people and uh so we're here so you're welcome to come here but there might be
I don't know where you live there are other groups you can go to but there's something that um about the osmosis of
being around other people who are doing this kind of practice that's something we learn from other people we're
mirrored by other people very differently in this kind of environment than we are you know in a hectic work
environment um we model things for each other we model how we behave when we're
connected to ourselves in a deeper way that sometimes is hard to see and in other other places in this world we can
be inspired um I know that the some teenagers and kids um uh will think that
their parents are really strange because they meditate like weird uh but then they find out that
they come like to a Children's Program here and they find out other parents meditate and suddenly their kids their
parents are not so weird actually now they're kind of cool and um so anyway so as adults you know
it can be help also that you know that you know you're around people who have similar values and as I said there's
this uh ethics antenna that we we tune into in this practice so there tends to
be a little higher ethical values just ethical Norm in this kind of environment
and so when you're not gossiping you come here and um and you don't feel strange here so it's a little bit
reassuring that you're people understand you and um and then uh and then uh some
Sometimes some people find it a lot easier to meditate when they're meditating in a group some people find it harder for the people who it's easier
it's this is available come here and whenever we have a session here you're welcome to
come and um and we have all kinds of programs and a lot of these programs are ways of building a practice or expanding
it and developing it further and further and we have have a whole whole series of progressive programs that you could be
busy here for years because we so we have so much you know in terms of just you know progressively developing
maturing this practice more and more so that's another way of continuing is just hang out in the place like
IMC so well maybe we should we have five minutes and um I want to thank you I
appreciate this chance as I said I think the first their first day I Love Actually teaching the intro class I find
it very lots of fun and interesting and I'm I'm also always seeing what what
else what's new going to come out of my mouth am I going to learn something
today you know and uh so so that's this is kind of uh wonderful for me to be
part of this too so thank you and um I used to teach these three times a year
I'll Pro I'll probably try to do it again in the fall maybe in August um
there's some talk about some other people here teaching one an intro class is that right yeah is that right yeah so
Tom's going to come and teach one maybe in some afternoon like a Tuesday afternoon maybe in the next couple of
months maybe so it'll be in the newsletter hopefully and it'll be in the calendar and then also Diana Clark has
also been talking about wanting to do one uh she's one of our teachers here and so she she does she she might
incorporate it into her Monday she teaches every Monday and she might do an inter class on one of her Monday Series
so we're going to start slowly start doing more here so some people come back
repeatedly to the intro class at first I was worried that that you know am I not
teaching well enough but um but I think it's you know
it's I it's all so I'll end with this uh a piece of
wisdom andbe I don't know I don't think I said it here I say things in all kinds of settings I don't remember so in in
this in meditation there's only two types of people there's beginners and
experienced beginners then you can decide what you
what you are but either way we're all beginners isn't that nice I think that's
great so you then you have to then you don't have to compare yourself to the experienced ones
they're advanced advanced meditators there's no Advanced meditators they're just experienced
beginners and so well thank you for being part of this very much and uh and
if you come back to IMC and look forward to seeing you and and um or some other way and U may this mindfulness practice
support you in your life thank
you oh and then uh you know Tom is available Nancy is available and this
Nancy there's two NES if you want to check in now if you have any questions for them and I'm here for a bit so
you're welcome to talk to me too thank you