we'll uh get our practice period
started so feeling
into the bodily experience bringing an
aliveness to the physical experience bringing in a sense of presence
and into what it's like to be sitting
here
now feeling connect Ed and
grounded I'm often starting with the obvious sensations of pressure
against the
body the feet
if you're sitting cross-legged maybe it's the sides of the feet that are touching the
ground if you're in a chair it's the bottom of the
feet if you're lying down maybe it's the back of the heels whatever it is chances are your
feet are resting on something and feeling the pressure the contact against
the
body back of the legs
the Vex feeling the contact the
pressure from the sitting
surface we can use these three areas feet back of the legs
buttocks as grounding we're
here connected as a foundation
be above this Foundation we feel the
belly can there be some [Music] ease some
relaxation in the
belly softness
and the chest sometimes we can
armor ourselves by having some type of stiffness in the
chest there a way to protect ourselves brace
ourselves just for this small period this morning can we let that soften
tuning into Sensations in the lower backing some care and maybe some
tenderness to this area which often gives
humans difficulties
in the upper
back between the shoulder
blades can we rest our attention there
with some kindness some warmth
shoulder blades slide down the back
we discover there's tension it might be that resting
awareness deviates softens the tension but it might not be
also and you be okay with that
can you be okay with however the body is showing up this
moment as best you can as best you can
and then bringing awareness to the face and the
head not uncommon to have tension around the mouth and jaw the eyes
maybe there's a band around the head that feels
tight is there a way that they can be loosened
and then lastly for this body scan bringing awareness to our hands
the sensations of what they're touching
and the sensations of having hands
do hands feel like on the
inside maybe a little bit a
tingly maybe nothing in particular it's perfectly
fine whatever you find e
and then the attention to tune into become sensitive to the
experiences of
breathing e
just noticing how the body moves as it
breathes
e e
nothing in particular needs to be
happening just tuning into the sensations of breathing
that be
enough
e
e e
[Music]
welcome welcome readings everybody to this is
the fourth day in this uh series that I'm doing on stories
and I'd like to share a short little story that comes uh from the
sutas and many of you might be familiar with this but I like to look at it from
a little bit different way than we often do and maybe there's a way in which uh
it can be a support for our practice in a I mean in a bigger way than uh when we
often think about this story so the story is a simile that's given by
the Buddha and he's talking about teachings so uh so this is the simile
that the Buddha is saying imagine a person in the course of a
journey arrives at a great expanse of water and the Nearshore is dangerous and
the farshore offers safety but there's no fairy booat or bridge to take across
the water so the person thinks well what if I collected grass Twigs branches and
leaves and bound them together as a raft and then supported by the raft and
by paddling with hands and feet I should then be able to reach the far
Shore so the person does this and they succeed and they get across to the far
Shore and then arriving at the far Shore it might occur to them wow
wow that's Diana's little injection there that's not in the suit does wow
this WFT has been very helpful indeed what if I were to hoist it on my head or
load it on my shoulders and then proceed on my journey and then the Buddha is uh
turning to the people that he's speaking to and he says now what do you think by carrying the raft with them
would that person be doing what should be done with a raft and then the people listening to him say
no venerable sir and the Buddha asks so what should a person do with the raft
and then the uh people there in the audience respond having arrived at the far Shore
the person might think yes this raft has been very useful but now I should just
hold it on to Dryland or release it and set it a drift in the water and then
go wherever I want in this way the person would be
doing what should be done with the raft so often when we hear this story
it's h associated with you know this is what we should be doing with the teachings the doctrine uh the Dharma but
what if it's just referring to or we consider it to be referring to just stories in
general like stories have a role they can carry us to a different place but
then there's a time to let go of them they can be a support in some
contexts but not in other contexts and we might recognize that so
much of a some of the maybe even Psychotherapy we might say is to help us
uh determine or acknowledge or discover some of the stories that we have from our youth from our childhood that was
helpful but that then they turn into to patterns of behavior that we carry with us into our adulthood and no longer are
helpful and part of the maybe maturity both in just the
conventional um maturing into an adult as well as spiritual maturity is to recognize oh yeah some of these patterns
some of these stories that I have from uh when I was young are no longer so
appropriate now as an adult and so this question of whether to
carry the raft or to leave it behind I appreciate so much that uh in
this assimile uh the Buddha is saying on arriving at the far Shore so this place
where there's safety it might occur to them this raft has been very helpful
what if I were to waste it on my head or load it onto my
shoulders this is like maybe the definition of something that's burdensome right carry this burden put
something on our head and walk around with it and maybe we don't recognize the
burdensome nature of it or we don't maybe recognize the weight of
it but then the uh Buddha says that um
an alternative is to just maybe we carried it on to dry land or maybe we
let it uh go a DFT in the water and then the person is allowed to go wherever I
want so carrying this raft is burdensome and limits what is available to us if we
bring it onto try land or let it a drift into the water it allows us to go wherever I
want it allows us to no longer be pushed around by the circumstances of Our Lives
no longer to be pushed around by some of the stories that we're carrying instead
we have a certain amount of Freedom so how is it that uh we can even
recognize that we're carrying these stories and that they are burdensome and for this I'll tell a
little story about myself something that happened many years ago this is uh when
I was working in uh Corporate America and I was upset about something and know
funny that now I don't remember the details I have no memory at all what these details were but I remember kind
of like this interaction that I had that um had a big uh impact on me and on my
life so I was complaining about uh somebody in another department this is
uh what I remember and so I remember I was telling this long complicated story
to my friend and like well this person said this and then because so and so was
was upset that they said this and they sent an email to a whole bunch of people including me and then I felt upset about
the email because it was so clear that this person really doesn't care about other people and this person only wants
to look good and you know like this big long complicated story as I said I don't
remember the details I just remember kind of like you know the this gist of it and then after the my long story that
was full of details my friend said I'm sorry that that
happened let's see if there are at least two other stories we can create using
the same facts and I was like what and she said no no no so and so said
something you were there for that and later you received an email these were two
facts what are some other stories that we could do with this and I was like I I
don't understand what you're asking me in fact I even felt offended like what do you mean this is a story no they said
this because of blah blah blah and then they this other person sent this email because of blah blah blah even look
right now when I'm telling the story I'm like feeling a little bit agitated
so uh I did was able to calm down and recognize oh yeah I was making meaning I
was trying to say well they said this because of x y and and
z and then this email that sent reading between the lines was a b and
c and not recognizing that this was fabricated in my mind it's not actually
the truth I don't actually know why that person said what they said I don't
actually know precisely what's between the lines in an
emo so this how can we recognize if if we don't
have a friend that's saying to us okay using the same amount of facts what are some other stories and I for the record
I did end up coming making all kinds of stories just outlandish stories
practical stories it always it became kind of fun to say okay well maybe Mars
came down and embodied this person and then some that were completely ridiculous and then some that started to
be like oh yeah maybe uh has nothing to do with me or maybe
has only to do with maybe they have a child that's sick at home and that's and they're worried
about this child and that's why they were said something with this kind of a tone or something like this so if we
don't have somebody to just remind us okay are there other ways that we could
interpret or and gain meaning from these things what could we what could
highlight to us that we're making stories and this little simile points to
this I would say in the simil the the person who's making the raft says what
if I collected grass Twigs branches and leaves and bound them together as a raft
and supported by the raft and by paddling with my hands and feet I should then be able to reach the far
Shore so this is pointing to like direct experiences like what is here and now
branches twigs and leaves is what the person was experiencing while they were on the
shore and paddling with my hands and feet is what they're actually doing with
the body how the body is moving so it's being present for our
direct experience feeling the hands uh using the hands and
feet is like feeling what is the experience that the body is having what's present right there twigs and
leaves and branches the story is what the mind is
doing what's not the story is what the body is
doing and then the story story what the mind is doing is often very different than what's being experienced by the
body right we often have you know the body is in one place here with leaves and branches and the mind is somewhere
else so there's often a sense of um so that's maybe one distinction we
can make between the story and what's actually happening so the story is not
in the same place as the mind but it also has this sense of this very quiet
uh sense of I don't want or I
should these kind of like two flavors the story has a feeling of like I don't
want or I should so this is often what the mind is
adding on top of our direct experience so then the question arrives
well this the simil of the raft this story is about letting go of stories so
one we have to recognize what is a story and that is to make the
distinction between what's happening in the mind and what's happening in the body and then the question is how do we
let go of the stories and that is about being
embodied it's like being with the fill experience what are the Liv leaves Twigs
branches of this moment what is what is the body feeling
like in this moment feeling grounded feeling our feet on the ground feeling connected to the
whatever surface we're sitting or standing on that's how we let go is is
not that we have to push away the thoughts or we don't have to um negate them or say that they don't matter we're
just bringing attention towards the felt experience of this moment that's how we
come go of the stories when we're embodied from that perspective we can
start to see the sense of I don't want or I should that's uh very often just
quietly like spewing up like um all these thoughts that maybe might be so familiar that we don't recognize like oh
yeah this is part of the story The sometimes it's a story of me
or the story of whatever happened or something like that so I offer this as uh take what's
helpful and leave behind what isn't helpful but as a way for us to feel some
of the stories are burdensome we're trying to carry them on
our heads and shoulders and they weigh us down prevent us from going where we
want to go preventing us from having the freedom and part of it is to recognize well what are stories what are the
narratives that we are carrying around that are extra that we don't need to and
so much about that is just being embodied so thank you thank you and I'll
see you tomorrow for our last installment of this idea of stories thank you
thank you all it's lovely lovely to be part of
this uh
songa Tracy looking forward to seeing a Cloud Mountain in October
fantastic Nisha and I are looking forward to teaching there e
I'm wishing everybody a wonderful rest of the day whether your day is ending or
just beginning Maybe notice the stories that are helpful and
the ones that are not so helpful