warm greetings from Insight Meditation
Center and um this week offering you some reference points
for doing mindfulness meditation and one um remarkable
reference point for it is that if you are at ease if you're
relaxed and and present if you're relaxed and
present if you're relaxed and just here you cannot not be
aware if you're relaxed and at ease here and you know you're
aware you're not able to turn off being aware unless you fall asleep or unless
you ract Yourself by something that absorbs your
attention and this idea that if you are at
ease you cannot not be aware what kind of awareness is
it that you can't turn off what is it that's here the simplest
thing and one answer to that question is that it's an awareness which is
undefined or to say it a little bit more provocatively uh rather than from the
point of view of awareness it's a way of being it's an awareness that does not
define who we are the undefined
self so we're not defined Ed by our
experiences whether we feel pleasure or pain there is a way of being aware of it
there's a way of being present where we do not Define
ourselves and where awareness is not shaped by the pleasure or the
pain if we have gain and loss success and failure praise and
blame Fame and disrepute these are experiences in the
world things are happening around us and experiences in the
mind we don't there can be awareness that is not defined by that or we do not
Define ourselves by those things and to be
undefined is to be deeply at ease as soon soon as we Define ourselves even if
it seems like it's completely accurate and reasonable definition we've added a mental activity
we've added a way of the mind is activated that contains within it a
degree of stress a degree of pressure a degree of of um narrowing ATT tension or
being a little bit caught in some way and to be uncaught
belongs to the realm of being undefined not undefined so that we're
unimportant or we don't count or but undefined because it's a symptom
of Freedom it's a symptom of not non stress
non tension non anxiety so as we sit today
maybe you can keep as a reference point or as a
question when you're at ease and you cannot not be
aware can you allow yourself to be not defined by any experience that's
happening can you allow the awareness
to be not caught or contracted or defined by the experience it's
having so to assume a meditation
posture and no matter how what do the four main postures you're
in Walking standing sitting lying down can you arrange your
body so it has a balance between some feeling of
alertness in your body sometimes with some sense of
intentionality intentness in your body that's not tense
some slight engagement that requires attention here
in the body so the balance between being
alert and being relaxed to allow a posture that'll
miraculously allows for both a certain degree of Vitality
in awareness and presence and the conditions for which
the tensions of the body can melt away Fall
Away gently lowering lowering your gaze or closing your
eyes and this combination of alertness and relaxation
can occur when you take a few long deep breaths at the beginning of
meditation your alertness maybe comes with breathing
in and relaxing the body on the exhale
on different exhales letting different parts of the body
soften settle
then to let your breathing return to normal and for a few more
breaths to feel
gentle sense of energy Vitality
alertness with breathing in
through maybe as the rib cage
expands and as you exhale continue the process of
relaxing in the body
and as you exhale also to relax the thinking
mind softening the mind
as you exhale relaxing the heart softening the heart
settling the
heart and then notice whatever degree however
small whatever degree of ease that you might be feeling
now could also be a sense of calm or a sense
of
peace and if there ways you feel uneasy or agitated that's
okay ease and unease can
coexist especially if you don't Define Yourself by the
unease by the tensions and issues problems there can be they can be
there and you can place your attention on whatever place in your body
Body Mind heart where there is some sense of
ease peace
calm and to be at ease to be
calm and to see feel feel how being aware of
that doesn't have to be something you're trying to
do that in the calm itself in the ease
itself there's an awareness that doesn't have to be
done there's a way of attending or being
present it's not something you're doing just just
there you can't turn it
off and to Define Yourself by the ease to Define Yourself by the
the simple awareness is to in small small way
to depart from the ease depart from the
awareness it's making something of it
allowing your body to breathe in and breathe out without being defined by how it
is without building up a self or ideas of Me Myself and
mine there's just the experience of
breathing known and awareness not making anything of it
allowing it to be what it
is
e
for e
as you exhale Relax The Thinking mind
soften the heart and in whatever degree of relaxing
softening you
have let yourself be aware without being
defined by what you're aware of
if there is pleasure or pain Comfort or
discomfort what would it be like to leave it
alone and not be defined by it not be
the receiver of it the victim of
it just Pleasure and Pain just comfort and
discomfort known in a field of
un troubled awareness
e
for
e e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting more often than not when we're actively involved in Def
ining ourselves we are also limiting ourselves
by that and all too often defining
ourselves is itself an expression of some attachment
some holding on to something needing things to be a certain
way or some insistent that this is the way it
is and if we can be at ease without defining anything without
defining
ourselves the states within us which come from nonattachment non-
clinging have more room to flow
basic friendliness kindness love Compassion
Care
wisdom or what can flow in the undefined space of
awareness and may it be that as we learn this practice of mindfulness
of easeful
attention that we allow
ourselves to have a warm heart a kind
heart shining on this world to gaze upon
everything
kindly may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be be
[Music]
free thank
you e
so now continuing with this fourth talk on the E worldly
winds and the in the teachings of the Buddha
the fourth one is Pleasure and Pain I've noticed that in a lot of
popular teachings on the four Heavenly will winds uh uh Pleasure and Pain comfort
and discomfort is uh listed first so whether it should be listed
first or not I don't know but um one way of interpreting that the Buddha puts at
last is that maybe it's the most important that um that uh and may be the
most difficult to because Pleasure and Pain is something very personal it's
something that we experience uh things like the the other uh six gain and
loss uh that can be someone personal we gain and lose our ability ities and
physical capacities but often it has to do with gaining and losing things in the
world and uh U but you know especially things like um Fame and
disrepute as deep as that can travel into our psyche into our hearts it's
still so having to do with world of ideas and the external world what people other people think praise and blame same
same thing but Pleasure and Pain is something that we experience intimately
closely uh physically with ourselves and so maybe it's easier
um oh so that I'm hearing seeing people say the sound is going in and
out me too so I don't know
uh fine for me so some people say it's fine yes comes and go no problem with
sound here yes
so it's possible that the problem is here at IMC but that maybe uh those of
you with different um
um devices have a different you know different effect
okay so some people you're probably seeing the
chats so yeah so if you're having problem uh yes refreshing the screen
helps fascinating that the number of people should have the same problem at the same
time maybe it's a a YouTube
problem so okay get lots of uh people saying now
that but some people are still finding it in and out so but repeatedly people are saying
that they close YouTube and then it gets better okay so we'll
continue so this idea that um Pleasure and Pain is uh part of the worldly
winds uh it's something that uh in the world people just really respond to
react to some people are um Servants of Pleasure and Pain that uh
everything they do has to do with being comfortable or un avoiding discomfort uh becoming comfortable they Define
themselves by the Pleasure and Pain there's some people who feel like if things are un painful unpleasant
uncomfortable somehow that's a personal failure it's or it's a uh offense
offense that the universe is providing and it shouldn't be this way at all
uh and um the um
the and uh and then some people because of that when things are Pleasant are
really attached to it this is a sign of success this is a sign that the universe is in my favor that uh that there's I
don't have and you know this means that uh this is exactly how it should be and then there's attachment to it sometimes
Pleasure and Pain is experienced and we Define ourselves by it that uh somehow I
am wrong I am right I am great I'm lousy because there's pleasure or there's pain
and one of the phenomenal gifts that I've received from doing Buddhist practice is U being able to experience
Pleasure and Pain without being defined by it without being caught in it without
picking it up and having it affect the quality of my inner life and I remember
uh when I was young in Buddhist practice that um uh
somehow without somehow the the context of doing ongoing meditation ongoing
Buddhist practice at some point it just seemed second nature that when I was going about my day and remember uh I had
to lift something with someone else something very very heavy and carry at some distance and I remember uh how painful
it was in my hands to hold this thing digging into my hands I wasn't hurting harming myself but it was really painful
and it just seemed like the obvious thing to do second nature almost to do was um to be present for it and not
allow myself to be caught in it or reactive to it be agitated by it be
aversive to it and I had some semblance of of a of a sense of attention that was
at ease a mind that was untroubled that it felt like this is valuable to not sacrifice that
untroubled mind it's valuable to stay at ease uh with this intense pain in my
hands and so it became this kind of uh writing almost a Razor's Edge very
careful attention to watch that the mind didn't react just didn't pick it
up and um so no one told me to do that I didn't tell myself to do it it just
seemed like the obvious thing to do to ride that edge to explore that I think
that part of the idea was that I that I was better off uh it better for me not to get
caught in the reactivity around the pain so it wasn't automatic that pain meant
that I had to uh react contract feel sorry for myself feel upset feel blaming
something and it just was pain and um and then uh uh I was quite
surprised by being introduced to be PNA practice and terad and practice includes
uh clear recognition and encouragement at certain point in practice to allow
yourself to feel great pleasure joy and happiness and um and I was surprised but
I didn't think that we were allowed to have those kinds of experiences I thought it was just uh just be present
and being present meant somehow some neutal Natural State and so but then so then the the
task was how to allow for the pleasure of meditation the happiness The Joy uh
uh without picking it up without congratulating myself without make building up itself look at me how great
I am I'm the one who's experiencing uh some pleasure in my meditation and so there too was this I'm
better off not being defined by it I'm better off not being CAU in it reactive
to it I'm better off just allowing it to be without making it a story making it a
expectation making it a requirement um letting the pleasure and the pain come and go and this is one of
the I feel one of the great also Gifts of a regular ongoing meditation practice
I found it invaluable to uh meditate every day more or less at the same time
and um day in and day out and um and then be present for
whatever life gives me because the consistency of it uh over time there are
times with pain times of pleasure times of uh being sad times of being happy but
the through line the thread running all through it all was U mindfulness was
attention was being really present for it and in doing so learning how how to
be nonreactive non-attached uh to whatever is happening to be present and balanced present and
not going along with the swings of ups and downs elated and depressed uh and just being
present and that is the art of working with the eighth worldly winds to be
present without being elated or depressed without being uh uh the
certain agitation that comes with just being so happy and delighted and excited
that is a setup to crash and go the other direction to being so depressed
and upset that things are not going our way and that happens if we Define ourselves by our
experience and so as we practice to start discovering a certain degree of
freedom of in Awareness certain degree of being present without being defined
by anything and feeling at this is good this is a wonderful deep satisfying kind
of way of being and you can feel and sense that as soon as we start defining ourselves by it anything at all making a
self out of it or this is happening to me or this is that we're actually
diminishing ourselves we're actually uh making something smaller or tighter or
constricted and the idea that we would not Define ourselves have an undefined
awareness can feel frightening can feel what's the point the whole point is I'm
whole lifetime I've been living with this idea that I am I am who I am and I have defining myself a certain way or or
defending or deflecting how you know the world is trying to Define me or or
hiding how I'm I really am because I don't want to Define myself to the world that way this whole social games that we
play around this idea of self and to find the Deep satisfaction of being putting that down letting it
rest and to have the undefined awareness or undefined self and then to encounter Pleasure and
Pain and realize that these two can be the Winds of the world that we don't
pick up on we don't let it push push us around we don't Define ourselves by it
there's something better that we can experience than um than only focusing on the pleasure
and the pain and that that which is better is found in the awareness of the
Pleasure and Pain the awareness is not the pain the
attention the mindfulness The Knowing of it is not the pain not the pleasure but
there's a way of knowing there's a way of being at ease with awareness at ease
with knowing at peace with awareness at peace with
knowing that is better than what it is knowing
knows and that's the art and when we have some sense of this higher quality
knowing or higher quality inner life then it becomes hopefully second nature
not to get pushed around by Pleasure and Pain not to be defining our life or
measuring our life or needing our life to be one way or the other based on whether there's Pleasure and Pain it
doesn't mean naive kind of just letting pain just persist uh because just that
is um it's like it's kind of a natural thing to take the thorn out of your foot
it's a natural thing to take the you know to to in healthy ways to avoid pain
and healthy ways of allowing yourself to feel pleasure but to do so with an inner
life which is not defined by it not dependent on it not conditioned by it
not pushed around by it this is the art of practicing with the eight worldly
winds so I hope that you've understood well enough now that the the the theme I
have around these eight worldly winds is that um to is that there's something
better than them going on as we develop this practice and so we know for
ourselves that these worldly winds are are just that winds of the world that we
don't have to uh pick up or get involved in and um and if we
do then that's also practice that's also we bring our
attention to and um don't let yourself be pushed around twice by the same
worldly wind one by having being caught in it and the other in being caught in
reactivity to it the reactivity to being
caught so uh thank you so we have one more day on this eight worldly wins and
um even though we've done all eight now and uh I look forward to um offering you
the concluding talk thank you