hello and on this Monday and uh happy to be sitting here
and considering some Dharma topics to share with
you and uh sometimes when people sit down to
meditate they're supported by the idea that how lucky they lucky they are to
not have to do anything for a few moments that maybe life is f filled with
respon responsibilities things to do places to
go and for a few minutes to be able to sit and not be so
busy and it can be a phenomenal thing just to appreciate that to take that in
and the appreciation of that can be enough for some people to settle them and help them just relax let go of
everything I'd like to offer you maybe another understanding of sitting down to
meditate that I'm hoping might do have a similar effect on you maybe even a
better effect and that is uh that uh similar to
the idea of forest bathing you know that now is fair it's a common enough exp uh idea that coming
from Japan this idea originally that would spent time in the forest to be
nourished to be uh by the atmosphere of the
forest uh all the different qualities that come through the forest that we almost can take in as a as a bath be
nourish us so meditation it can be
a ethics ba bath a very traditional idea in Buddhism
is that to appreciate being ethical when we
are and when we're sitting and meditating even if you live an unethical
life at other times and they maybe even troubled by that that when you sit down to
meditate it's a time when we are ethical we are adhering to whether we
know it or not to the five ethical precepts while we're
meditating we're not killing anyone hurting
anyone we're not
stealing we're not engaged in sexual misconduct we're not lying to others at
least and we're not uh taking in intoxication
toxicant and I think most people don't Orient themselves that way when
they meditate if a person is unethical they might be carrying with them the guilt
and the heaviness and the fear and preoccupation that and the
self-criticism that that might entail but the encouragement in Buddhism
is to appreciate for these minutes that we are living a good
life my teacher in Burma love to talk a number of teachers in Asia talk about
how sitting and meditation fulfilled the
precepts and um so as we sit today you might consider your good
fortune that for these minutes you you are being
ethical even if it's just a pause in a more difficult
life consider yourself so fortunate that for these
minutes you're not going to actively intentionally be involved in harming
anyone and let that be a forest bathing there's something that's possible to take in in and appreciate and feel some
Joy or something that's very settling ah this is
good so to assume a meditation
posture one way I like I like to think of of the posture and
meditation whether's walking standing sitting or
lying down is one way or the other to assume a posture of
dignity or a posture that you're allowed to exist you're
allowed to show up you're allowed to be here in a full
way and certainly there's no need for these minutes to diminish
yourself gently closing your eyes and taking some long slow deep
breaths to appreciate this moment this time
this opportunity to be here and present and to become
settled with a good fortune being able to
meditate of spending these minutes being ethical even if you're not even
intending to
relaxing as you
exhale relaxing the
body relaxing the
heart relaxing the mind
letting your breathing be normal
simple and relaxing the thinking mind
relaxing that part of the
mind that has any force in
it to be involved in the past or the
future to keep you in your thoughts
relaxing the thinking
mind and like Forest bathing where we're not thinking and analyzing
and justifying the effect that the forest has on our
all our senses we just taking in as a
paath maybe there's a way for you to do ethics
bathing where there's no need to justify it or question it
or just the radical Simplicity of sitting meditating
fulfills the
precepts and to let that bathe you let that fill
you do let let that settle something in
you settling
any doubts or criticism you have of
yourself we are phenomenally lucky to have these
minutes of not involved in any intentional forms of harm
breathing sitting with our ethics in order for
these minutes and appreciating that bathing in
that
e
e for
being careful as you
meditate that you're not allowing yourself to
bathe in harmful thoughts in thinking that it does not
have a good effect on you relax the thinking mind
and instead bathe in the
absence of unethical Behavior
for
e
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting to be able to better
appreciate the ethics the ethical good ethics of sitting and meditating
it's good to remember or to know that the five
precepts are as ethical precepts concern Behavior how we behave the actions that
we do with body and mou and
speech it's easy enough to conclude that some of our thoughts might be unethical
maybe we we harm ourselves with them but that's not seen as so much as
an ethical issue as an issue of the lack of
wisdom for Behavior we want to change the behavior to stop
harming for thoughts in the mind we want to see it with
wisdom and one way to see with
wisdom is to see understand have
confidence at least our behavior is not causing harm
and may it be that meditation this meditation
session reveals to us
how to live with ethical Behavior how ethical
Behavior nourishes us and maybe nourishes others
and maybe that behavior supports us then to cultivate
wisdom about ourselves may all beings
benefit from our ethical Behavior may all
beings be happier safer more peaceful and
Freer that we behave according to the five
precepts and meditation teaches us
that there's freedom for
us and not picking up and engaging in unethical
Behavior it's not so much we have to do something it's
mostly we don't do something may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello on this Monday and to do a new series new theme for
this uh week and maybe for the first days of next week as well that um one of the activities I've
been involved in for this month of August is um continuing with the ongoing
project I have uh of translating and then writing
commentary or introduction to the ancient verses of the nuns poly it's
called the terata and um people say it's uh it's
might be the earliest poetry that we know religious
poetry by women and uh it's reported to be the
the verses the not the Poetry of the direct Disciples of the Buddha though I
think some of them were written later maybe by nuns in the centuries after the Buddha as well and it's a remarkable collection of
poems Buddhist poems for many reasons one of them is that uh the tremendous
confidence of these women they go through they describe some
of them tremendous difficulties that they go through through uh the life
difficulties uh the death of their children their death of their family and
the challenges of abusive marriages and all kinds of challenges that they have
and somehow they make their way through it they become uh they practice they become nuns and they
confidently live in the world and they confidently live uh recognizing and and
uh proclaiming their full Awakening that
they the full Awakening is possible and um and uh I think this uh
this text is a celebration of people who are celebrating their the not only their
potential for awakening but their actually attainment of it and as a and
it makes has greater value when the contrast to uh the very difficult Liv so
of them lived before they became nuns so I've translated this some years
ago and uh and U it's been sitting on the shelf for some time and now I'm
writing introductions to it so hope hope to have some point be able to publish it as a book but I'm I Delight in these
some of these poems and so I wanted to share some of them with you and talk with you about some of them and uh and
this one that I'll read uh is um you'll see that there's a connection to the
guided meditation we just did those of you who are there for it and um this one uh there's nothing in
the poem that the that the person the woman is a nun it's a story earlier in
her life and um probably she became a nun later and it's it's also not clear
that she's the one who wrote it um but uh it's a dialogue between
um a woman I think a young woman here named uh pun Puna and punna is a uh is a
servant of uh a mistress who is maybe quite abusive or seemingly uh quite
ready for to punish her for not doing her job well and uh as a servant what she does
is she's a water carrier and uh there was no running water and so if there was a need for a
household especially a wealthy household maybe with to have a lot of water um it
was someone's job to go down to the river and uh pick up the water and carry it back and and maybe that had to do
happen many times during the day and it's not clear how far she had to carry it and in this poem she's going down to
the river at a time of the year when the water is quite cold and even then she had to kind of
Step into the water the cold cold water and to scoop up the cold water water and carry it back and uh she um she runs
into a Brahman who is down there a Brahman is a kind of like a
um uh a priest of the brahmanical religion and one of the central rituals
of Brahman priests is to go down to the river and uh sacred rivers and bathe and
the ritual bathing in the river was understood to be a purification right
that uh all the bad karma that they' built up uh that somehow if you go into
a sacred River and bathe in it that you can uh you're you're purifying yourself
of that bad karma so that's kind of the background for this poem and um
so uh so she's speaking uh to this Brahman she says I am a water
carrier when it is cold I always have to go down to get
water I am terrified of punishment from my
mistress I am terrified of angry words but
Brahman what do you feel fear that you always go down to the
water with limbs trembling experiencing sharp
cold the Brahman replies to her somewhat politely
certainly lady punna you know the answer to what you're
asking I am doing wholesome Karma and preventing the con consquences of evil
Deeds whether young or old whoever does evil karma is freed of evil
karma uh uh through purification by
water so then punna replies to the Brahman and this is where I the poem
becomes for me quite delightful and uh expression of a woman of confidence
speaking to a Brahman she's a servant woman um and there's a ancient India there was a quite uh uh status
differentiation more than just status there was almost like the servants were all often considered almost impure by
the natures of being servants and shouldn't interact with brahmans who are trying to be pure and um and so uh but she speaks
confidently and clearly and and directly to this man this Brahman and uh so these
are her words so he just told her you know what he's doing going to the river to purify
his evil Karma's evil actions she says what know nothing told and know
nothing that one is freed of evil karma through purification and
water frogs and turtles water snakes crocodiles and other water dwellers will
they go to heaven those who butcher sheep and pigs
those who fish and Hunt thieves executioners and others who do evil
would they also be freed of evil karma through purification and
water if this River carries away the evil you have done then it would also
carry away your good Merit and you would then be out of
both what you do that brings you fear
that brings you down to the water for purification
brahen don't do it then cold water won't shock your
skin so this is the I love this this verse just don't do it so whatever you
need to be purified from if you do that you feel you have to be purified uh because of doing this evil thing don't
do it then you don't have to purify yourself in the river and the Brahman
replies because now he's seeing the light I entered a bad path you've led me
to the Noble Path dear lady I offer you my purification
cloak and she says keep it for your self I do not want the
cloak if you fear suffering if you dislike suffering don't do evil actions
either openly or secretly if you've done or will do an
evil action there will be no Liberation even if you run
away if you fear suffering if you dislike suffering go for Refuge to the
Buddha the dhama and the Sana and keep the ethical precepts this
will be for your benefit and the Brahman says I go for
Refuge to the Buddha dhama and S I will keep the ethical precepts this will be
for my benefit formerly I was a descendant of
the God Brahma this is a belief of brahans that they are direct descendants of this the highest God in
heaven but today I have become a true
Brahman I am now a person of wisdom learning and the three
knowledges now I have truly bathed so um uh he's saying now he
didn't become a real Brahman by learning the three brahmanical knowledges and a lot of brahmanical
learning uh and he didn't become a true Brahman by bathing in the river physically but by going for refuge and
living ethically and that was the message of Buna to the Brahman uh living
ethically and not giving cause to needing to do purification this is the way and this is
the way to be bathed he understands that he takes them he takes his bathing in
the river that he does and metaphorically applies this idea to uh bathing in
ethics so uh it's a wonderful little story maybe a little Fable of um but one
of of uh I just love this directness in which buha talks to him just don't do
it and may that uh inspire all of you to to uh
bathe in the ethics good ethics of don't
do it don't be involved in Breaking the precepts and um nourish yourself bathe
yourself feed yourself bathe yourself in um your ethical
behavior and uh partly because we live in a in a western culture that's so
deeply affected by uh Freud and Yung and Psychotherapy
where we keep looking and studying at our analizing ourselves so much internally that uh it's a almost second
nature for people in the west sometimes to then apply the precepts to their
minds to what they're thinking and find that they're unethical there too and um
I think that that's isn't the orientation of Buddhism that uh that the ethics has to
with the behavior in the world we do and speak um and uh and there's not looking
at ourselves our mind in this kind of unethical way we're rather looking at it
uh through the lens of wisdom and sometimes recognizing that uh maybe
we're a bit foolish in the mind there's not enough wisdom there sometimes and
the issue there is to become wise about our thoughts our beliefs Bel how we see
ourselves and uh and rather than undermining ourselves or criticizing
ourselves or have caused to feel like we're a bad person just because of the thoughts we have and um they might be
foolish thoughts but let's become wise and then we can also bathe in
wisdom so uh this is the first poem uh commentary about it for this uh this
week and I hope that you enjoy appreciate uh these poems that I have um
given myself over to for a good number of years I've been living in these poems and thinking about them translating them
so thank you very much