okay uh welcome uh welcome folks yeah nice to uh nice to be with
you ah very sweet
okay um all right let um let's uh let's
sit following the cicada thread but uh we should
meditate um
so yeah let's uh let's just see what happens here let's um find a posture
that feels uh like the appropriate balance of uh alertness and
relaxation
so in uh the Dharma we
uh we calm down nurture
Tranquility just to enjoy tranquility
but Tranquility is also associated with Clarity clarifying our inner
landscape there's so much happening so much of the
time it's very easy to lose the
plot and so part of why we nurture a factor of
Tranquility is so things
can slow down enough in the field of perception things can slow down enough
that we can perceive more clearly
maybe you're tired already long day long
week so there may be some measure of Tranquility built
in but ad that fatigue sometimes there's another
layer of
overstimulation and so this is a kind of form of awake rest
maybe you elongate the inhalation and the
exhale just a few beats more for the in breath and the out
breath e
maybe you sensing to see is there something in you that's it's
already deeply resting tranquil
letting tension drain with each breath letting tension
drain down into the center of the Earth
do what we can to breathe
into or
clinging the energy of of grasping of aversion of
control it's this sort of epitome of non tranquility
and there's no sin here this is what the Mind Body
does we breathe into the clinging
and soften
widen
e
e e
maybe your body's a resource here you just take your cues from that
which is already resting in your body
some zone of sensation feels like a nectar settling
to a bottom of a glass of of juice tnan
said maybe you anchor to
silence the sound of a
silence or distant sounds sounds as they fade out
there's really a sense not of
inferring Silence from the absence of sound but
hearing silence itself
doesn't have to be silent all around you maybe there's a
sound to your right but if you listen to
the space on the left you hear silence
maybe you just take your cues from the
silence
e
e e
Mother Teresa described prayer
as silently listening to God God silently listening to
her you don't have to believe in God to listen like
that
e
e e
your body
soundscape the visual field even with the eyes
closed my gaze in a very gentle relaxed
way Darkness brightness behind the closed
eyes there may be images flashing by images of your own
body IM of this the device image of
me just kind of gently gaze through that into the
darkness of the mental
screen we rest our visual tension
there take our from the
darkness
e
e e
back to
it but not
now
e
e e
for
okay so uh thank you um it's good to sit with
you is a quote from uh aent suito saw
recently and thought to uh to uh to share it and and just say a
few words about it so uh said
um generosity is about sharing and not just in material terms it's an attitude
to life it's a response to the interrelatedness that is the basis of all
life most importantly you share dhma by advice and by
example aiming one's concern and goodwi for the welfare of others as much as for
oneself helps shift the self view to one in line with codependent
arising action based on the that view of interdependence generates a shared
blessing The Giver feels joy and the receiver feels feels the effects of kindness everyone
gains morality leads to self-respect and the trust of people around you
renunciation draws you out of the grip of the materialist energies that control much of
society discernment cuts through the blur of feelings to tell you cooly and
clearly what qualities are skillful and what aren't at this moment such
discernment is required to Steward and moderate energy so that it isn't frittered away on the
one hand or strained on the other the result is Right
persistence and that brings around patience to not rush to allow things to
move at a harmonious rate and to bear with the tangle of Social and personal
conundrums that we Face patience is great for willful got
to get it done mindsets there's a whole life of cultivation in this param me
alone so um yeah John packed a lot into
that so generosity is about about sharing
generosity is about sharing our depth of dependence is
invisible most of the time like possible to fantasize about being an island most
of the time an interdependence is an
insight and then it's everywhere I remember uh Jack cornfield
telling a story of a yogi who I think struggled with generosity some kind of
you know miserliness whatever holding and uh the instruction was just
uh to pass a ball from one hand to his other from his right to his left and
back that was the first lesson on uh on
generosity relations are are the basis of life everything belongs to everything
else and in a sense generosity is just like our attempt to tip or cap to the
universe thank you and one aspect of course is sharing
sharing the the the the Dharma dma as a said sometimes by advice but mostly by
example most people really if you haven't gleaned this yet most people
don't really want to hear about Buddhism
but they do want to taste the Dharma and in a way you must tellor it
for them wisdom wisdom is always wisdom for this moment for this person this
time and our advice needs to reflect the kind of
uh landscape of their heart Our advice is informed by our own
very deep understanding of of the architecture of of uh the
human nervous system of our nervous system that um we learn a lot about
that right we don't have to know neurophysiology or something to know a
lot about how this body mind works
and we don't give advice to consolidate our faith in practice we're not speaking
as a way of affirming what we are already committed to we're unattached to
view there may be Faith but we're unattached to view and most of the time the generosity
is not in Sharing advice or something right it's our our
evangelism comes in the form of our example our life
and when someone you know when someone sees a deep habit shift in you even if
it shifted just a little bit that's prompts some
curiosity we all know how hard it is to change you know just how hard it is to
move and grow from those habits that are carved seemingly in ground plan
it and when you see it when you see someone making a move you got to wonder
like what's this person
doing so it's my life it's my life I must tend
to it with more energy than yours but how much more what level of privileging of my own
happiness above that of others is ethically defensible that's that the heart of
Ethics aent says action based on the view of
interdependence generates a shared
blessing last uh last year I remember reading it sort of got a lot of press
and so a research on on on um random acts of kindness generosity you know
like where they did experiments you know it' be like they would assign people in the uh experiment to like at an ice
skating rink I think as I remember like go give this go give this random person
a cup of hot chocolate you know and uh and then they would like assess okay how
did The Giver feel how did the rece recipient feel right they both felt maybe unsurprisingly really good and The
Giver systematically underestimated how good the recipient would feel you know and
part of why was that the giver kind of focused on the value of the gift rather
than the value of the warmth the aect the connection The Tipping the cap to
interdependence right and I I was kind of um yeah touched by that that finding
and it resonated because I know I know if a re SE Archer told me to go give a
hot chocolate to some random person at an ice skating rink I would
be there that my shame would come out it' be sort of bashful and you know like
you know I don't know what I would think but it would be something like um here it is here's here's the hot chocolate
I'm I'm sorry it's not a ventti you know or something that would be like the vibe for me right but I know at the same time
if I were skating if I could skate if I were skating and somebody gave me a hot
chocolate I would like that would be like a a mark in my life probably you
know okay generosity then Aon he sort of packed a
lot into this quote you know it like he summarizes a lot of the
path morality leads to self-respect self-respect and the trust of others
it's the path of non regret it it really
feels bad to live out of alignment with one's own deepest values there's a kind
of agitation that's built into that self-doubt that's built into it a lack
of self-trust and then
renunciation uh maybe relatedly said the you know he's elsewhere said the hardest
question for a human to answer is like what's enough because you can always want
more and so we we have to get uh good at assessing the value of stuff things that
you will actually love right things you will actually love and
uh I sat a SAT a retreat with uh with aan suito and you know at the end is was
like I'd love to buy let please let me buy you something you know like I like just overflowing
with sort of gratitude and sense of debt and you know please let me let me you know I had to kind of push let me buy
you something I said he sort of relented he said okay duffel bag you know for
travel so I got a duffel bag in the color of uh his monastic robes you know
it's like okay I trust he will appreciate that you and we have to
discern for ourselves like is this going to work is this purchase going to work
is this hatred going to work is this clinging going to work discernment is
largely about prediction about prediction a prediction about what can work what will
work and this is important to clarify what
might work you know uh because if we don't we Fritter away our energy on uh
what is not meaningful and is sort of amazing and
tragic sometimes just to see people investing in huge projects
that I kind of know cannot work out for their heart even if they get exactly
what they think they want it cannot work out for their heart but there's this sense of like
they can't imagine what else to do what else might be satiating for the heart
and so you just keep doubling
down persistence is the the steadiness of our energy you know
um the uh Dharma Dharma cultivation is very
much about steadiness it's not about these kind of peak moments of intensity
where it's like okay I'm going all in on this that or the other like those can be
meaningful but it's more like the steadiness of our intentional stance is
what is associated with deepening and the path with sustained behavioral
change the steadiness just nursing this
intention day after day week after week year after year
and that involves patience which is not my favorite part ofy not you
know um but it's really Central to the path
patience patience
the we can practice deeply we can there can be some Vaga sense of like deep
practice practice commitment and patience you know they can go
together and the Long View informs the nearer term uh we can discern what's
what's urgent what's not and this patience helps us bear with
the tangle of conundrums we face and that is not like a
rationalization of apathy or disengagement you know it's more like a
way of probing like where can my energy be
effective how do I spend my love well how do I suffer
efficiently elsewhere aan said um something like if I'm getting everything
done I'm not getting anything done
the the exacy of the
checklist sometimes so patience about uh waiting
for the ripness of conditions the ripness of
conditions it's a kind of uh Exquisite sense of of
timing and we um we come to discern something sort of
like like the deeper architecture of causality is not on the surface we're
like perceiving forces intuiting forces in a in a in ourselves in a
relationship in a in an organization
perceiving something deeper about causality and we detect this and
we uh we have a better sense of when it's ripe to make a
move when is it uh a stretch but not exactly a leap
when when are the conditions right get better and better at sensing into that that entails patience
so um in a way um yeah it summarizes a lot
of practice way grateful to uh Ain suito for that quote and offer this for your
your consideration and uh wish you all a good
uh good week yeah practice life whatever whatever it is we call it yeah and uh
see you uh see you next uh next Wednesday okay folks