so good morning hello everyone
welcome so for this morning's meditation I would like to evoke
a maybe an experience from some of your childhoods if you have ever been on a
seesaw as a child but standing in the middle uh and either side of the
fulcrum and uh and try to find the balance so that both sides of the Seesaw
are parallel to the ground sometimes getting there takes some muscles to you know to push one way
or the other but when you find the midpoint and you're able to stand there
with the Seesaw balanced uh there's no longer a lot of
effort needed maybe just a little bit of adjustment um
with the uh um little bit of adjustments with just the weight little bit but it's very
little so in meditation we can find that balance point that stands
between Pleasure and Pain between what's comfortable and not
comfortable where we're not leaning into the pain or pulling in away from leaning
into the pain or leaning into the pleasure leaning into the um leaning
away from the pain leaning away from the pleasure um we're not if you go in
meditation towards the pleasure too much the whole seesaw
tips if you go to attack the pain the cisa
tips but there's a place of standing in the middle the balance point where
mindfulness has the greatest ability to become clear clearing the fog clearing the air
clearing the heart and mind completely connected to either side because that's
where the balance point is so it's not avoiding anything but
it's also not picking it up or going towards it or reacting to
it being balanced in the middle of it all and clearly
seeing and for today it's the midpoint between comfort and discomfort Pleasure
and Pain so to assume a meditation
posture and to
gently close your
eyes and feel the weight of your body against whatever supporting your
body maybe imagining that the support points is the midpoint of the
seaw and maybe be adjusting your weight a little bit your posture so that you
feel more balanced on that those pressure
points maybe as you exhale to settling into those pressure
points of
support gently maybe lovingly taking some little bit deeper breaths
just deep enough to feel a richer connection to yourself your
body and to relax the body as you
exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and continue to relax on the exhale but imagine you're relaxing e
equally evenly on either side of your body so relaxing the shoulders both
together so there's a settling maybe into the midpoint the balance
point between
them relaxing in the
chest equally on both rib cages throughout the
diaphragm perhaps settling relaxing into the midpoint of the
chest balance
point on the exhale softening in the belly
equally on both sides of the body both sides of the
belly maybe relaxing on the sides of the
waist relaxing into the midpoint
maybe if you're sitting in a cushion or a chair there might be some sense of
relaxing into the tailbone where the tailbone gets close to the chair the
cushion the
midpoint
and then on the exhale on the inhale feel your thinking
mind whatever you associate with the energy or tension pressure of
thinking whatever is physically activated around thinking feel it on the
inhale and on the exhale Relax The Thinking
mind and relaxing evenly on both sides of the
Mind
relaxing and thinking mind so you can relax into a midpoint
Center where the Mind itself maybe feels balanced at ease
if the mind is resting in the easy chair of the
brain the mind can know and be aware without getting up from that chair
to look at anything or get away from
anything or follow anything like follow the
thoughts thinking mind resting at the center balanced at the
center doesn't go out and doesn't go in
but stand spanning in and out so whatever comes to awareness is
known without being for or
against
with some sense of a body being balanced on the Seesaw of
Life the heart
balancing and the mind balanced
without become not going towards or going away without trying to fix or
to hold
on there's pleasure and there's pain there's things that feel Pleasant
and unpleasant
stay in the balance point stay rooted in the
Middle where there's balance and a possibility of clarity of
seeing
for
have you already left the balance
point tipping and in the direction of thinking or
reacting stay close to your body your heart your
mind so all three are lined up balanced on the Seesaw of love
life
for
when we're balanced in the playground seesaw we have to have a certain
continuous awareness of our
balance so when we're balanced the Seesaw of Pleasure and
Pain there needs to be a relaxed continuous Clarity of
mind that knows how the system is tipping towards
one or the other and in The
Knowing staying
balanced
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to find the midpoint the balance
point between comfort and
discomfort between wanting and not
wanting and that midpoint to be balanced there is a significant way
to hold yourself in respect to respect
yourself your value your
presence and it's also a very significant way from which to be respect
other people to respect the dignity the value
the autonomy of others where we can care for them deeply
love them but we're not tipping the
Seesaw sliding towards them or away from
them not over involved or under involved but beol in involved with
respect in that balance
point and as we end is sitting to from that place of
balance from a place of
respect care and appreciation of
others to wish them well to have our heart
radiate with goodness generosity respect
May others be
happy May others be
safe may others be
peaceful May
others be free
and may the way in which I stay balanced each of us stays
balanced may we contribute to the welfare and happiness of all
beings may we support others to be balanced and strong in
themselves may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank
you
right
e
so good morning good day to our second talk
on mindfulness of grasping of
clinging and today there's many synonyms or many members of this family of
attachment and one of them is compulsion uh and to be acting on compulsion means
that we're not quite in charge and we're not quite involved with
uh uh the choices we make and in extreme forms it can be called
addiction and some people have addictions with the words they speak
with um the things that they do there's a compulsive quality to them and um some
people lose themselves in the activity they do and so the Buddha was addressing this
very directly and um and he wanted us to be
mindful of the whole dynamics of how compulsion grasping attachment arises in
us and um and so clinging and grasping are not abstract ideas they are
physiological events that occur within us we can feel you
know in some ways or other I'd like to propose that generally when we tense up
in our body we're actually grasping to something maybe it feels necessary if we
want to be safe in some situations but chronic
tension uh is not about the immediate safety in the situation chronic tension
has to do with grasping or clinging or attach M sticking to certain kinds of
ideas or beliefs or attitudes or feelings that we have and uh so sometimes the compulsion
is so strong I can feel like there's we're stuck to something you know we have the
expression in English uh to be stuck to stuck on some topic some idea some
feeling and um so the attachment is strong so uh so the it's a physiological
event as well as a mental event and an emotional event the Ecology of grasping
compulsion is what we start becoming aware of as our mindfulness increases
and develops it's kind of a natural thing as the mindfulness becomes more sensitive we become sensitive to where
the tensions are where the contractions are where the pushings are where the where the restlessness is that's all
symptoms of this compulsion and um so one area of compulsion that's
uh uh very common for many people maybe everyone is around um what's Pleasant
and unpleasant Pleasure and Pain comfort and discomfort and this for the Buddha
is a second of the five bundles of clinging that humans uh collect so it's
one thing to to uh uh have an to want to have um
you know something sweet to eat and that's fine but there's also compulsion
to have it where something takes over and and we just not just have one we have two three four of some sweets
because something has taken over and we're automatic pilot and each Act of compulsion is a
new grasping onto something clinging to it and so we're Gathering Together
these bundles and some people live with these bundles of clinging of compulsion
so it isn't just for something sweet but it's also for um certain kind of
Pleasures certain kind of delights certain kinds of um clinging to
avoiding discomfort at all costs and going to Great Lengths to make ourselves
comfortable in situations some people are more oriented to comfort and discomfort than others
um maybe a kind of sensual sensuous kind of person maybe I don't know exactly
what kind and maybe shouldn't even say it that way but some people are more oriented to this way and but everyone is
to some degree and there might be many things that were gathering together into these bundles of
attachments bundles of compulsivity and uh it just takes the slightest little uh change in the
circumstance we're in where the compulsion is ready to act up and um and
so uh to start becoming mindful of our relationship to the pleasant and the
unpleasant to comfort and discomfort to um uh and uh and in many
ways that's very fundamental to the human um mind is to somehow be reacting
to Pleasant and unpleasant wanting more pleasant getting away from the unpleasant uh attacking the unpleasant
uh some people push away the pleasant um there something they have some association with the pleasant that
that's wrong maybe in some kind of way uh to feel the pleasant experience some
religious teachings seem to get people thinking that they're not supposed to experience
pleasure and so to uh um but in some ways it's kind of always operating you
sit down in a chair and it's a little uncomfortable you want to make yourself comfortable you sit you uh you go into a
room of people you look around to see where is it comfortable to sit and uncomfortable based on the people who
are there and um and might be more complicated assessment going on but for
some people it's just a simple sense of Pleasure and Pain that's is operating there and um and it can drive a lot of
behavior um some Behavior people will spend days sometimes planning ahead to
have a certain kind of pleasure uh or go to a greater extent to avoid a certain kind of discomfort that
they don't want to deal with um sometimes it's more complicated like with people who are conflict avoidant it
might be more complicated than simply avoiding pleasure uh discomfort but some of it just might be avoiding discomfort
they just I don't want to be uncomfortable there are beliefs that people have around comfort and
discomfort or Pleasure and Pain some people feel like they're a failure like some they've done something wrong
that they're experiencing unpleasantness in their life and they have to fix that
at all costs to kind of prove that they're kind of a worthy person or a successful person or having a good life
other people um uh their sense of self gets validated
when there's a lot of pleasure um a lot of joy and then they've uh it kind of masks Maybe some deeper anxiety that
they carry and but they like who they are when there's a lot of pleasure but when there's no pleasure there're then
they're left with something deeper about themselves that they're not comfortable with so
um um and now some people identified very strongly with discomfort some people
actually look for discomfort look for pain want to have it and it's certain kind of odd way because it's so familiar
maybe they grown up in a way that's always their companion and on the surface they don't want to have it there
but they don't know who they are without it that's how they've navigated the world how they've set up even their
social relationships is around their their pain or their difficulty they have
and so people get attached to these things and they're attached to a lot and this is for the Buddha it isn't just we
grab onto one thing we're grabbing onto lots of them over and over again and we
live carrying these bundles of attachments and
um and uh and so the Buddha that's you know the second of the five bundles the
condas often called Aggregates and um and so for practicing
with that uh it's Central to inside practice to start becoming mindful of
how things are Pleasant and unpleasant uh so that we can see whether
or not we're reacting to the Pleasant un Pleasant some because some there's a lot
of human reactivity a lot of human uh motivations that are built on the very
simple idea that something is pleasant and unpleasant um I I kind of suspect that
some political philosophies had their start and someone thought something out
in this world was unpleasant for them and so they wanted to build a whole philosophy to get that to go away and
not be there so that they could be more comfortable um occasionally it's that
that basic to some of the more complicated sophisticated things people are doing I've known people who've done
uh you know great pieces of Science and they said that but basically they're
pursuing pleasure they find a tremendous pleasure and Delight in in their work
pleasure of the mind and that's what keeps them going and that doesn't mean there's attachment pleasure and uh is a
beautiful wonderful part of life and uh when it's there without attachment and
without causing any harm to anyone uh there's no reason not to allow ourselves to feel the full extent of the pleasure
and that comes into play in meditation with a deeper more concentrated
meditation um there's a lot of pleasure that happens and um and the idea is to
experience it without any um for or against without any attachment not to
make another bundle of grasping around meditative pleasure as we would many other
things so to sit quietly in meditation being mindful of what is settling into
what is relaxing into what is here with time we start seeing we start
feeling uh how we're reacting how we're clinging how we're want we're for or
against thing we're leaning this way and that way way how we lose our balance point how we lose that quiet Still Point
in the middle that is where we come Al a certain thing comes alive so if we're balanced on the
playground seesaw and the Seesaw is parallel to the ground there has to be a continuous
wakefulness to staying there present it's uh most people who might be sleepy
probably their sleepiness goes away or dullness in the mind goes away way if they manag to find that balance point on
the playground seesaw and um so there's something about waking up
to that balance point inside of us that can see and know clearly what's
happening um and can feel the difference between leaning forward and leaning back
literally leaning forward leaning back when we're we kind of cringe we pull back we lean forward we feel happy and
there's nothing again wrong with that it's instinctual sometimes but it's the early warning sign that oh now there's
possibility that uh compulsivity happens grasping happens um that we're getting
stuck on something and um so to see
mindfulness as uh being uh being in that balance point
between Pleasure and Pain between the pleasant and the unpleasant between
comfort and discomfort and it's a fantastic thing to
for the wakefulness the clarity of mind to be strong enough that we're not
caught in the orbit of anything it's almost as if we can see clearly what's
happening where the clarity is not caught in what's happening some people
call it observing there's an observing mind that has a balance and
Clarity and so we can find ourselves in the Seesaw of Life balanced and wise
because of that so thank you I hope that
um the the this talk this these talks this week this week will give you some
inspiration to respectfully uh uh
kindly curiously look at how you grasp how you cling how you're attached how
you lean One Direction Another how you lean into for and against things and now for today just a very
simple thing of pleasure Pleasant and unpleasant Pleasure and Pain comfort and discomfort
how do you react to that how do you live with that is there in fact some compuls
compul impulsivity that you have around this and you might think ahead through
the day and and kind of consider where during the day are you most likely to be
caught up in the issues of pleas Pleasant and unpleasant so you prepare
yourself as you go into that situation to remain Mindful and try to understand it
better so thank
you