and I'm I'm trying and I'm going to do a little bit of a different sequence just a settling in meditation a
few minutes and then a a a reflection and then a guided meditation
to illustrate you know and bring into our experience what I'm speaking
about so you're allowing your breath to take you into the
body and arriving here at the
IMC
and you know taking a screenshot and seeing what are you bringing what are you bringing with you
today you feel a little bit you know stressed or you feel tired or you feel
energized just noticing how you
feel
and then I know that you're here with so many others in this welcoming
space maybe you here many many times before maybe it's your first time
here
and a landing
for
and noticing the weight of the body on the cushion or on the
chair the gravity which is you gently pulling you towards the
Earth underneath this building then showing us where the work
lies and know the work is
embodied and our bodies are instruments and
of sensing our present moment
experience rather than thinking about
it
so a few months ago you know an has asked me what I would like to speak about
today and uh I said like to speak about inner activism and response ability you
know the ability to respond from a connected place not from just you know
from the thinking mind but from our full being understanding that our body is
actually a direct line into a much
bigger intelligence which you know we can call
Planet Earth which is a self-
regulating intelligent process and you know at this time in
history it calls out to us in many ways you know to get our
tension you know as we are coming more and more to the
limitations of what the biosphere can sustain with the amount of you know
human beings are living on the planet and how they live and in particular you
know in the so-called U Global North the the
[Music] living style is is taking a
very big toall on on the resources and you know all of us
starting to notice this more and more but there's a lot of confusion around how to meet that
cording and uh you know how to be able to respond to it
from from a connected Place rather than from uh a disconnected
place and of sending us into
numbness into disconnection
into you know just trying to solve the issue from the same level of
Consciousness which created it and there's a lot of speaking about
this these days you know that that doesn't really work and it needs grounding in direct experience and
uh through the bodies we have you know those um bodies which are made of the
five elements we actually have a direct Lifeline into this much vaster
intelligence which we call Planet Earth because these bodies and the planet are
consisting of the same elements Earth
element Water Element fire element wind element space
element and uh you know this is something we might
theoretically know but we have to really bring it into our own experience on a regular basis so that
this can really start to sink in deeply and through this uh direct
experience you know that our assumptions our narrative about who we
are and you know what it means to be alive
so that that will change through direct experience and
uh you know starting to attune with this truth which is always already you know
functioning but it's hidden you know it's kind of hidden in plain view because the way how we are framing our
experience is very much through a narrative of
separation and you know then when we hear these callings you know from from the earth
we get triggered you know triggered into numbness and dissociation and feeling
you know feeling overwhelmed because there's a sense this is all so much you know we don't know what to
do and all of our systems you know are not
really able to do the uh depths of change you know
which is required to turn this around so we have to really work on our
[Music] own minds and the narrative you know we tell ourselves
about what it is you know to be alive
and this you know this inner work you know to do this this connective or reconnective
work this is what I call Inner activism which is the basis for outer activism to
be really working well we have to come
from a different understanding and that understanding know that these bodies are
actually say we can say they are sacred land you know they are they are pieces
of Planet walking around you know as as human bodies because any any life forms
you know we can find here they are all emerging out of those elements and then
when the time comes you know they dissolve back into it it's a
constant process and we need to do what we can to
recognize that truth you know that we are really not separate we like waves you know on the top of the ocean
emerging and then you know existing for some time and then going back into it
and that you know energetic connection through eating
drinking breathing sweating crying going to the
bathroom there's a constant exchange
happening and you know that's easily overlooked because what the eyes show
us is kind of looking we're looking like separate entities walking around but if
we start contemplating it it starts to sink in you know it starts to change us
and that's exactly I think um what's needed right now you
know this willingness to attune to our own bodies in a different way and
starting to resonate more and more with the fact you know that these bodies emerge out of the planet and they are
part of it in beginning it sounds all a bit kind of you know superfici um artificial
rather and but then you know if we do this meditation which we are soon
starting you know it gives us a direct uh taste of that truth and then something else you know
starts to open up just a little bit and then through like a door opening up yeah
or a window opening up and then if you really take an interest and go there and open that door
again and again and uh move into that space more and more it's starts
to change our way of thinking and then if our way of thinking
changes then of course our speech and our actions will change from there as well so it's a it's a training
really and and you know when we start that
training like like any meditation training it needs to be done you know on a on a reg basis and then it will slowly
but surely have an effect you know on the
way we are we are in the world and uh you know in the Canon we
can find the you know the basic teaching of early Buddhism on the four satiana
I'm sure all of you have heard of that the four establishments of mindfulness and the first of those four is
meditation on the body and there is three different meditations
mentioned and one of them is a meditation on the elements and another one is meditation on the body
parts and there's also meditation on death but today in particular I want to attend you know to the meditation on the
elements because it's such a you know really straightforward practice and it
comes to us from ion age India it's a really ancient practice and it had
is a lot of applicability in this day and age you
know where we are meeting the limits of the biosphere of
this planet we are part
of and you know just reading about it in the newspaper or you know hearing about
it on different channels is is not enough we also really need to bring it into a
direct experience because otherwise it's so easy to just numb out because that's
what the system does if it's overwhelmed it just numbs out
and you know that's something to respect and uh bring kindness to but it's
important to notice it that's not necessary Equanimity but it's a
pulling back because of
overwhelm and and we need to recognize that and bring something to it which can
help us you know to do that work of reconnecting
with who we are and what we are called to work with at this point in
history because our practice is always really
connected to what's happening right now in the world in our lives in our
families in our societies it's
about being able to
respond and not react but responding and slowing down and
becoming conscious you know of what is there with kindness and
acceptance and
interest and if there's like a sense of you of numbing and and disconnection to not override that and trying you know
push through it but just noticing it for for what it is because it is an intelligent
response and it's not an you know an a nothing but it is a something it is a
mind state which needs to be noticed the inability
you know to really connect just know it for what it
is and then starting you know to bring in a different way of working with
that so that we are you know more and more able to to resonate
with that truth you know that we these bodies of ours and the planet Earth are
one and the same process and our bodies are so much Huger you know than what we
usually think they're deeply deeply
networked with the planet with the more than human
world and with all and we are all together in this and we are called
to take an interest in that now so that we will be changed you know
from the ground Round Up
basically and also you know passing that on to
the younger generations to the Future Generations which hasn't come yet it's a
it's a new narrative which is wanting to
be integrated is a you know an evolutionary
threshold really
where we start to you know see we can no longer put ourselves into the center of
everything we are just one species amongst many
species and we all participate in the same process and that's
amazing to consciously you know be on that threshold and to be able
to but participate in that shift to be able to support that
shift by just individually personally starting to practice in that
way and to do it also together with
others
you just you know and when we look back in history there's been so many times you know this
very big you know shift in
in you know that the world view the narrative had to change like and know
when we notice that yeah the planet Earth is not in the center of the solar system that was a struggle you know for
that to be recognized and to enter the mainstream but it
happened well you know at the Times human beings were thinking the Earth is flat and then that changed that was a
struggle and now we again on such a threshold you know where there's a big shift building up and and where we are
basically you know forced by by circumstances to go
deeper to drop deeper you know to take ourselves off
the Assumption you know that we can be masters of nature that we can be masters
of this planet that we can control all of this and just coming down to the
ground and and noticing that we are not
different than the planet we have Arisen from
it and we are constantly kept
Alive by it we are actually it we are this one and the same
process and then you know as we are building up
that that resonance by tuning to that truth
then through that connection you know a response can emerge from that which
is more attuned to
reality rather than you know trying to fix it from the same narrative which
created it in the first
place so we can just you know start with uh noticing
the Breath
Again The Wit
element then the wind element stands for movement and for expansion and
contraction and you can sense that in your tsle with the in breath and the out
breath so just let you not let the air come in through the
nostrils into your lungs and
then with the out breath allow it to take you down you know down into the
ground below your
seat like sending down
Roots into the soil
just noticing you know if your awareness you know can can go down with
the out breath no no need you know to put
pressure but just noticing whatever is
happening and just slowly allow your awareness to drop down with those roots you know
meeting the soil any kind of stress or
doubt just let it be received by the
Earth and meeting all of the other root systems and meyum
all of the data flow you know which is happening in the body of the earth which consists you
of so many different ancestor beings bodies of
humans and animals plant bodies mineral
bodies it's an aliveness we are part of
that and if we do not participate in the earthiness of the earth through eating
you know different foods which are growing out of the Earth this body cannot live for more
than one or two months without taking
in that food F building up the
body and you know it said within about seven years you know all of the sales of a body are
replaced so you've had many bodies since you know came to
this
birth you know that in itself is
it's
awesome and just you know allowing that vibration of you know by breathing
up the earthiness of the earth that direct experience allowing that to
resonate with the Earth element in your own body in the bone
the nails the hair the teeth Earth
element Earth element internally and Earth element externally
is exactly the same Earth element Earth element is
empty empty of a
self and just in this wordless way you know just
resonating with
that you know and as we are sending down Our Roots we also meet the water element
yeah our bodies you know consist about 70 75% of water
element all through the body many many different um liquids are cursing
through and we can sense it you know in the softness of the Flesh of the
body and Water Element stands for cohesion fluidity and
wetness and you know the water element in the earth body and also on the surface of the Earth as the rivers and
lakes and oceans is exactly the same Water Element
as we can find in our bodies in the bloodstream and the other
liquids and if we don't you know drink water for 5 days or so the body shuts
down water element is empty empty of a
self and we never cut the umbilical cord towards the planet there's a constant
Exchange you and allowing the whole system in a
in a wordless way to resonate with
that it's like updating a
computer and these bodies you know they are very sophisticated bio computers we could say and have been developed since
over 4 billion years
and but just simply you know changing the framework of how we are experiencing
that something else you know becomes
available information you know starting to inform us our form form gets changed
through that different way
of opening to
experience and then you if we keep continue to go down we also come to the
fire element at the center of this planet there's a lot of
heat and then also we receive a heat from the
sun fire
element which you know we experiences hot and cold inside the body and outside on the
skin where the air you know in the room touches the skin or maybe in the stomach you know
maybe you've had breakfast and you can sense the filament that that chesting going
on this these human bodies of ours you know they can only exist in a certain
temperature range if it gets too
cold freezes is gets too hot it evaporates it's a delicate balance is
needed for the body to live and that balance you know on the
planet is now starting to get out of sink more and
more because of our
lifestyles and we we can uh do something about this when we are
ready
so that's we've experienced the V element through the breathing process
the Earth element through the stability and the
structure of the bones and the vastness and the stability of the
planet the water element which you know stands for
cohesion and for flow and
wetness and then the fire element hot and
cold and then we can come back to the breath
again and really you know consciously
breathing up that energy resource you know which is
just below our seats that huge vast planet Earth which is a
living being a living
process which calls for our attention at this time
and this is a way you know to attend to it with the whole body rather than just
by thinking about it and it's a very
helpful balance you know to getting lost completely in thinking and but grounding
that in sensing the resonance between the body and the planet
and so that integrating more and more the understanding that this is not two different things this is
one process and we
can draw on that intelligence if you have the humility
you know to go there go down on the
ground and the word you know for Earth another word is humus the black very fertile
Earth humus and humility and human those three words you
know they all have something in common and this is the the humility and
needed at this point in history for us to open up to a different intelligence
than the intellect
humus humility and
human so so no breathing up
that the life force the energy
and allowing ourselves to be informed by
it through that wordless resonance by attuning to
it you might you know experience it in your own body as a as a vibration as an
aliveness
just you know breathing that up breathing that up through the trunk
of your
body and then through your organs and your
neck behind your eyes all the way up to the ground of the
head and then you know you could with the exhalation just opening up the
ground of your head
and now we can also you know we put out roots into the sky like branches of a
tree because he is also energetically very much connected with
the space and the
oxygen which comes to us you know from the tree from plant life on this planet we have
also energetic rout into the unmanifest that we can't really
see the
spaciousness and just you know sending out these roots or branches into
the sky
and I'm drawing on that
power which is also there you know beyond what we
can see with our eyes right now
and extending the roots or the branches up into the into the
cosmos there's billions of solar
systems also now reaching into that power that
energy but just you know the tuning do that opening ourselves to
that so on the in breath we can feel the root system in the
Earth the energy you know which comes to us from the Manifest
planet and our body which is deeply networked
into that planet and also from
that which is
beyond and we like a bridge you know between those two Dimensions our
bodies
and we can sense our heart you know as being like the Nexus
point between those two Dimensions the Manifest and the UN
manifest the like a bridge
point you know sensing into the intelligence of the
heart
you know the heart of all of us which feel cold you know to evolve in order to be able to
respond to the situation this urge to evolve you know which brought you all
here that's why you
meditate
and just you know really sensing into that
calling and really honoring that calling in
you and you know I noticing you're sitting here with many other people who all feel C in somewhere or another
otherwise they wouldn't be here today and another beauty of
that and notice if you can you know sense
something in your
heart bring in another Brahma vihara of
compassion karuna may all beings be free from harm
and the intention to
harm may all beings be free from harm and the intention to
harm you know as we are becoming conscious of this
evolutionary threshold where we need to go deeper in order to be able to
respond to so much
complexity
and noticing that we already have the equipment for that you know through
the Buddhist Meditation on the Sati batana and the Brahma
viharas we do have you know what it takes to be able
to start to attune more deeply with this point in
history in which we are
living so now we can't really go back into Iron Age India when the Buddha
lived but we can bring this teaching into the present moment and the challenges of the present moment
for
in the boundlessness you know of the heart which
is able to respond from a place of of
compassion and this urge know to evolve in order to be able
to
contribute to this shift you know which is uh calling
us
you know as we are maturing and growing
not just as individuals but also you know as a species as a
collective
and inviting in the the blessings of our
ancestors you know who have uh handed over this very
amazing bodies to
us so that we you know develop new capacities
of attuning and then you know hand that on
to the next Generations so that they may have
opportunity to all also grow
and benefit you know from this life which we have
got
so you know just the willingness to stand on the
threshold
and through a tuning and developing capacity to resonate we
will be Chang changed and then from that our contribution can emerge from
that not in order know to take something off the to list but in order to be more a
human humility humor human and to also bring him some humor
about all of
this you to see the Precision you know with with all of this
is
emerging the mystery of this uh imported
life
and the choice in know which we have got to turn towards
it so in a minute or so I'm going to ring the bell and then you know when you open your eyes maybe just you know
trying to stay connected with the body from
inside and you know slowly you know noticing with whom you are sitting here
in the room and then you know if anyone would like to to share something or clarify
something we have about 20 minutes or so a bit more
for
[Music]
so I don't know how you usually do that do you hand the microphone around I will I just want seems a little loud um I
especially love the part about that we're pieces of the earth walking around
and I and The Roots going down and branches going up so wonderful thank you
yeah hold it like a rock as such Fortune to meet you in
person thank you um my question is very I think it's s ific which is
about how does the knowledge from the Atma get transferred to the current body
what so if we have rebirths mhm we are learning something every
birth so how do I you know like the current me get all the knowledge from
the previous gmas or the births from what
I don't know Generations did you say no the previous births yes mhm so how do
you know it looks like there is an accumulation of knowledge yeah but she cannot I'm having
difficulty explaining it to no no but the microphone is good okay so I'm talking about the previous births and
the current birth mhm so how does the knowledge from the pr previous births
get transferred or it is consciousness you know Consciousness is
is like the you know the quality of the Consciousness is is the sum total you
know of that uh of the Consciousness which then you know will be reborn into into some kind
of a body and and that that is you know when a child um do you have children no
no I have a dog who you know might like but what I mean you know some people have like two or three children you know
they're all different because they all different uh have different Consciousness you know and that
Consciousness is is what was cated before you know so my question is if we
have been having rebirths so shouldn't we have like you know like smartness not
to do something like repeatedly do stupid stuff what we keep doing stupid things
what we keep doing stupid things so why don't we learn yeah so I mean it's very hard you know it's it's when we are all
here because we all would like to do less stupid things and do more wise
things but we have very strong habit you know and also like traumas you know when
when we had very hard experiences and then those those traumas you know are
still in the body stored you know and then if we get triggered we get
overwhelmed isn't it and then we do something or say something or drink drink something or eat something we
actually don't want to but we feel so overwhelmed so it's a you know we need
to um we need to kind of slowly but with a lot of kindness and also support you
know work through that digest this undigested okay you know which keeps us
disconnected from these good intentions we have you know and this is what I was also kind of guiding Us in the
meditation before you know to to do this reconnective work because we are
generally quite disconnected from the fact you know that our bodies and the planet Are One process you know we read
it and say yes that's true you know but then the way we live is very different you know because we haven't done the
work the the we haven't done the digesting you know because number one is
we we didn't know how to do it and we weren't aware of the harm it creates you know but but more and more we do become
aware you know and when we see for example what's going on in the Middle East at this point you know where there
is so much the spinning you know of the trauma has gone so so fast you
know and we can see you you can't with talking you can't get to that
place but it's it's with sensing you know and this is something you know
which is we are not very good at that you know because we haven't been conditioned in that way but slowly we
start to notice it you know and this is what I also meant with the shift you know we we have to come down try to
solve everything here you know because this is so disconnected so it's it's it's a it's a
daunting kind of a work you know and this is why I I bring this guided
meditation because it's like bringing it down to the very
simple practice you know of of connecting and tuning in and then when
we do that what we meet is all of the undigested stuff you know the landfill
just put it in the landfill and hope it's just going to be gone you know of course it's not gone neither the
landfill is gone nor all of the things which we suppress in the body and now
you know this I think we are starting to wake up to this you know as a as a species really and and that's a great
thing you know but then at the same time it's very kind of daunting isn't it
heaps of stuff you know like internal and external and now we have to find a way
how we going to do this together yep you know I mean nobody knows how to do it
but we know one thing is we know that the planet is is a self-regulating
intelligence you know which is operating since billions of years you know out of Stardust all of that has come to be so
why don't we connect with that more deeply intentionally you know and take our
guidance from there you can call that a dhama really but just with a different
framework you know it's not just about individual Liberation to get away from here you know to somewhere else or not
be born and press for that but also thinking about our responsibility you
know because we can't suppress all of that stuff because it's going to explode out
you know and then it Wars come up which are getting more and more violent you
know because the the amount of suppressed stuff is just so
big thank you m
yeah hi hi um uh you're talking about U
uh uh that we're thinking excuse me uh we're thinking intellectually and you
know we should be deeper in the Earth but I I want to know uh for me conflict
resolution is very important and there have been major people doing things in the Attica prison riots which was years
ago uh afterwards the prison guards said
we would all be dead if this mediator had not come into the prison yeah also
someone Robert Reich uh and Berkeley had a meeting between uh uh Israeli people
American Jews Arabs people with American Heritage they got together and talked to
each other and agreed on certain principles um I know people uh my niece
went to a friends giving a Thanksgiving and the conversation was so bitter the division between people about Gaza that
she walked out of Thanksgiving dinner but there are people already uh they
don't I don't know if those those mediators meditate you know like the person at Atta prison riot or the or
Robert Reich I have no idea what he does but there are people who are able to do that and I'd like to say I'd like to
know more what you think about that there are people who are able to do this and you're it sounds like you're moving towards that too yeah yeah I'm sure
those people you know have some kind of a practice you know they they might call it meditation but it must surely be some
kind of contemplative practice you know yeah yeah sure yeah I think that's
that's what we need you know we need Collective spaces to digest this stuff
together you know because we can't do it all alone because we need you we need to be support we need support you know
community and I think you have a great opportunity here already you know you have a
community and yeah it's about doing that digesting you know of the
landfill or the trauma you know which keeps us disconnected and feeling like waiting
for some big daddy to come and fix it you know that's like the old narrative
you know and now we are starting to grow out of that one mhm
because it doesn't really uh happen I mean and there is some sometimes there's
some really great um figures you know like Nels m Martin Luther King you know Tian and so
on there is great beings who can you know Inspire us and show us you know
what the human potential can be but then we have to bring it back you know into ourselves and not rely on them but we
can do this we can do this together because we already have a lot of
um you know we have the information you know we have the as I said before you
know the meditation on the four saatana for establishments of mindfulness and
the Brahma viharas I mean they are the the two basic building blocks you know
for starting to connect with oneself mhm
and you know and if we do that work it I think it will
become more and more we'll see you know that if we make ourselves available if
really feel like we you know this urge to evolve as I called it you know urge to evolve evolve you know in order to
you know face face the responsibility you know what do we leave behind for future Generations you know then AO if
that if you connect with that I think situations will start
to emerge you know where we can more and more uh do that work you know M first we
have to just you know start noticing it that's what we would want to do you know and then
nourishing that and and attending to it you know and it like to a plant you know
and trusting that intelligence which is the intelligence of the heart I think you know and the intelligence of of
these intentions if you really nourish it and attend to it like to a plant you
know it it it will grow m it's the same you know if you cut your finger if you clean it up and put a banded it just
knows how to do you know if you don't cut every day it's going to heal you know without you doing anything much
other than keeping the conditions right for it you know and I think this is
something we need to more directly understand through the through certain
practices you know which are which are kind of a little bit let's say designed for that you know where you use some of
the very of the ancient uh teachings you know which we have received from the Buddha from Iron AG India but said it in
a bit of a different framework because we live in a different time you know and
and the challenges are principally always the same you know greed hatred and delusion in action but what we are
facing now is different in terms of uh you know the the
globality of the issue you know us all together on a planet which has a limited
biosphere and there's more and more people and
there's more and more polarization is there's like a certain kind of tension building up and we can all sense it you
know we all we all feel it and then it explodes at some of the very vulnerable
places you know and if we don't work with that pressure
you know then we don't know what's going to where it's going to explode next you know do
you think that um uh your teaching could be combined with teachings in mediation
and conflict resolution sure yeah I think it could be a good combination yeah I just not putting down what you're
saying at all yeah no but but combining them that's what I'm saying I mean you know at at theca Earth
room uh you know where where I live M and uh it's in San Rafael you know
that's what we are offering there on on Saturdays you know we have uh in person meeting and we're doing these kind of
meditations and then afterwards we sit in Council together you know either
formal counsel or sometimes more informal practice discussions and
we we you know we try to um work with those things you know yes
yeah mhm has and there's many places who do this
kind of work of course you know but it is yeah it is very important that those
spaces you know come into being I think yes thank you so much for all the great
work coming from Hoka Earth room thank you also thank you for the meditation so for me when we went
through the ments earth water Wind Fire the sense of Peace as well as a
sense of sadness thinking about the wounded planet we live in mhm there's a
lot of pain associated with that also like the theme of um inner activism
MH I would love to hear from you what is it individually that I can
do to bring this sense of inner activism so that it becomes a larger move moment
more people more care higher
prioritization for the planet related activities that I can engage in mhm I think you know to by I
think by really you know doing this these practices you know of of of really attuning to the to the
fact you know that the body and the planet I one process that's one thing and then also really noticing this urge
to evolve you know which we're just wording you know and really uh noticing it you know
respecting it and then speaking about it with other people you know you're part of the earth C group and then you know
by you becoming the medicine you're looking for it's going to be contagious
in some way or another and it's not going to be exactly on your time table you know as you know
already but that's the way to do it you know and and really
um you know it's almost like walking a prayer basically you know we can say and
and and and just continuing to do that work and and trusting in EM mergence you know
but it doesn't mean that that we are not doing anything but we not seeing the opportunities and and uh I mean that's
how I made the Earth room you know by I'm you know I'm interested in all of
that since over 10 years you know so it was like it was a process but then at one point there was the opportunity and
then you know we need to act so it's it's a you know it's it's
it's this Attunement process you know by resonating with that much bigger
intelligence and allowing then that to come forth you know to be informed by
it so it's it's a real it's a it's a mysterious process
but it's also a very grounded process you know
and yeah because it I think the the resonance which can come through us you
know is always in proportion you know to our openness and then that the gifts we
have got you know and the talents we have got they will be used by that process you know
yeah I think we could maybe take one more question and then I think we have to end right yes mhm one or two maybe
depends on how long how long did 10:45 10:45 okay I see the clock there thank
you thank you yes I really want to thank you so much for coming to IMC today
thank you it is really lovely to see you in person thank you and
um I just want to share my personal story so I do a lot of climate activism
and I find that what is so important for me is to replenish my soul and joy and
to take action from that place and the thing that I do that is most effective
for me is I do habitat restoration and I sit in the dirt right now it's the
mud and um as I'm digging around these earthworms come up and it reminds these
fat you know beautiful earthworms and it reminds me so much of your earthworm
meditation and I want you to know that I stop and really meditate on that
earthworm and join in that earthworm and um and think of you and thank you thank
you so much thank you Len even your hair got green isn't it from all of your bir
you're really doing it yeah and I was wondering if you could
just say a few words about um taking action from a place of joy as opposed
from to from a place of of fear yeah I think you know I can't say to people you
need to be joyful because sometimes we are not you know but I think what I can
almost access easier is like a sense of awe you know a sense of awe about the fact that my body and the body of the
planet are one body I mean that's awesome you know and I can go back to that pretty regularly you know and then
sometimes there is a sadness which comes with that or like just like the Mind
goes like wow there's nothing you know and sometimes it is a
joy and yeah Joy is definitely you know there's more buoyancy there and that's
like it's really feels good you know but I think uh if there's no joy you know I
can't steamroll people into feeling Joy but it's more like you know just start
where you are and and connect with that sense of awe because I think that can
help to make more space you know so we can meet the grief you know because
sometimes if the grieving hasn't been done there's no joy you know because the joy is is
um I think it's also a the result of of having done the work you know because
when we have done some of that work then we can be more connected then we resonate more with what is there and
then the joy comes from that you know yeah but great you know if you do
have you know done you know a lot in your life to to get to the place where
you're now and now you know it it it's also the result
of uh of you feeling good about yourself you know having really walked your talk
right to a certain extent and that can really bring joy yeah that is true but
we need to start where we are you know and then we can see you know others who
have done it who have gone through the discomfort you know of rearranging certain parts of their life
you know in order do to be able to walk your talk that that can bring joy you know and there's like a certain
renunciation connected with that and that you know is a scary
thing for a lot of people you know but we need to just uh you know start where
we are one step at a time and and then that can really bring
choice yeah
yeah okay maybe I if if if it's okay I just um end with a little chant yeah I
just would like you know share the the benefits of the Gathering today you know with uh all of us you know so that we
will find the courage you know to to do the work to do the reconnective work so
that we be more in resonance you know with what's asked now from us as we are standing on
this um evolutionary threshold you know recognizing more and more that we are
part of a living intelligent Earth may you have every good blessing
may all the Davis protect you by the power of all the the Buddhas may you
ever be well may you have every good blessing may all the Davis protect you
by the power of all the dhama may you ever be well may you have every good
blessing may all the davers protect you by the power of all the
sa may you ever be well thank you so much and I just want
to show you I've brought some C from the Loca Earth room they outside there where the N statue is on the cupboard you
could if you'd like to take some you you'll be welcome so thank you so much for the
invitation thank you thank you so much