hi um I'm Nikki in Mountain View California and seated ol Nan welcoming
you to this edition of happy hour and as we always do as a part of our tradition
We Begin by uh saying hello um and warming up the space with our Goodwill
with our meta for one another so um please take it
away hi Nikki hi Su this is Don from hi
Don hi it's Kim from Tofino British Columbia I haven't been here for a while
I'm so happy to be here oh it's good to see you Kim welcome back thank
you hi I'm Carlos ditto for me hi and this was
Carrie did I hear that right thing it was Carrie hi welcome
back hi aswara from Los scov hi aswara and David says hi from Fort wor Texas
bill in Dallas Megan from pal Alto KJ from Santa Clara and I see
Neil there he is hi Neil you from San Diego it's great
that's just great and also rejoined from folks on YouTube um tonight so today this morning
whatever your time zone might be many different time zones joining yeah and hi Serena from New Jersey and I
see Amy in the room Amy H how are things in Hawaii there was a storm there over
the weekend north of Oahu hope you're all right from a beach on the North Shore of
Oahu that's great we are good okay thank goodness glad you're good may all beings
be safe including Amy so great
uh vetro says hi from Minneapolis welcome okay sweet I feel like the space
has been warmed up with many greetings and hello so let's um let's transition
so thank you Neil for posting information about happy our Google Groups we have a mailing list uh that
you're welcome to join if you haven't joined and um also if you have a chance
please take a moment to uh look at the breakout room etiquette at how how to uh
be with one another how to support one another uh especially if you're new to Happ hour at this time I'm going to
transition and change the setting so that unmuting won't be possible so that
the space stays quiet I'm going to change the um chat setting so that they only come
to oh it's giving thumbs up it's so interesting I love the the auto detection of of hand gestures anyway um
I'm changing the settings so that uh chat only come to the host but ask you
to keep that channel quiet and last but not least I am going
to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma and recording where are you here we go great okay so hello everyone hello
and welcome to happy hour it's lovely to be with you in this moment moment in
time and um I'm going to start leading the guided
meditation without a um daret ahead of time I'll say more about it afterwards
so we'll just leave us and let's see where we end up so some on some topic
about meta and loving kindness and and it's related practices so not veing off
too far so I like to invite you to settle in your seat in your chair
wherever you're sitting or standing or even lying down if that's comfortable
for you and taking a moment really to
arrive arrive in your body
arrive with the sacredness of this moment of being
alive whatever has happened before whatever is happening in this moment Letting Go
releasing Just Landing with the simplicity what the
Simplicity of this body breathing this miracle of this body
breathing letting go of thoughts plans stories me me
me what I got done what I didn't get done what they said what I said let go
let go let go oh dear mind dear heart it's endless it's endless but we can put it down and take
refuge so let's put it down together and take
refuge a moment of deep rest can only really
rest deeply rest when we put down
all the rigamarole of the stories in poly the word is papancha
papancha just proliferation of the Mind
proliferation putting it down putting it all down deep
rested and if you notice the mind has picked it up again put it down again gently lovingly
sweetheart there's no profit there's no benefit in picking it up right
now like a dog that keeps picking up a dry bone just keeps picking it up it's
so used to but it's Hollow the bone has no benefit no
nourishment put the dry bone down Dear
Heart deep rest an expression of care love
metap for
ourselves and for
others and helpful to connect with the breath in the body because when we put
the thoughts down it's helpful to have something something else to engage the mind the heart with the
idea is not to have a blank mind that's very hard that's not what this practice
is about but to connect with the breath with the Body Sensations the mind will become calm on
its own put it down put it down put it down
be pressed e
relaxing the body relaxing the mind the heart
connecting with the breath the relaxed body and put it down whatever Rises just put it down this is
a very simple practice release put it down gently lovingly
caringly can always pick it up later not
now
e
e e
and let yourself notice the subtle Delight
of putting it down the lightness that comes from releasing putting things down
the heart feels lighter notice maybe even a smile shows up on
your face
and always pick it up later we're just practicing training our mind to be able
to put things down not be slave a slave to thoughts and
ruminations but have more agency putting it down releasing Within
a
smile
e
e e
and as you put down the ruminations thoughts plans maybe drop
in into your heart into your body
a word like yes
yes a sense of openness to life to whatever is here right now
yes or maybe the word that you want to drop in not into your head but into your
heart is thank you thank you or just
thanks or gratitude see what is a word that feels like a wholesome seed to
plant in your heart in this moment when you've put everything else
down the busyness of the mind or maybe just
silence peace maybe the word is peace or EAS
is the one that comes up feel into it for
yourself think so much though it's not about thinking you just let it be
silent
e
e e
notice if the mind has become busy and it's time to remind yourself to put things
down put it down put it down empty empty empty yourself of thoughts and maybe
plant a word like peace as you breathe in and breathe
that
e
e e
as we turn to bring this sit to a close let go one last
time and rest let go and rest
or picking it up again later and trusting that we're planting
seeds of wholesomeness training our minds and hearts for the sake of ourselves and
others and learning how to let go release put down is a necessary
precursor to meta kindness for ourselves we need to make space
need to make space not just a precursor but this equivalent to kindness for
ourselves being kind putting down what's not
helpful at a given time the training some mind
training and trusting that our practice in ways we don't quite
understand supports not just ourselves but others all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves everyone thanks for your practice so
oh so I'm going to say a few words about our practice first thank you first of
all for your practice everyone so so today's theme and practice was very
simple very simple so simple right it's just putting it down putting thoughts
preoccupations plans papancha this word in poly I love the sound of it papancha
it sounds like pops proliferation word for proliferation putting it down
putting it down ever so gently lovingly kindly putting it
down and then if it feels supportive to drop in a word like peace
or thank you or yes or just keep letting
go and this sense of lightness brightness that can come from the as we from putting things
down is is very nourishing ah feels like we've just loved ourselves
like oh thank you sweetie thanks for for letting my mind be simple and and free
for this time so so Papa poly papancha putting down
how to spell in poly yeah so one of you asked how to spell it in in uh B so um
let's see I'm going to enable chat and and send it to all of you so the word is
here's the smell spelling paa so it looks like a c but the C in P
is pronounced as a CH so p a p a n CA papancha is the word papancha
proliferation mental proliferation so the word papancha it
doesn't mean mean putting down it means mental proliferation so we put down
papancha so so so um I know that some of
you uh turn and and um uh don't stay for
um the small groups which is fine but before that I wanted to share something with all of you and it's going to be
shared starting tonight for the next couple of weeks I realize if I wait to till the end that might be a little too
late to share it so we're running a survey and I'm going to put the link of the survey in the chat and you can click
on it but please don't fill out the survey now uh I'm only putting it because I know that some of you might
just be popping up now popping off now um so there's a a survey about happy
hour and it's going to be if you don't click on it now no problem it'll be
shared with with you for the next two weeks uh every night as well as it will be sent to the Google Groups uh address
so again just click on it if you or save the link don't don't fill it out now you'll have time later okay stay with me
maybe that was not a good idea to share it now but here we are trying to take care of all these
different these people leaving trying to get as much data as possible it is what
it is the world is imperfect imperfect impermanent impersonal imperfect impermanent
impersonal so all right come back come back so now like to turn to invite you
to um participate with one another in in uh
um one in a small group practice and um the invitation is what
came up what came up when you uh try to put these thoughts memories uh
engagements you know papancha the proliferation down did you notice a sense of
lightness um did you plant a word would did that bring more lightness or not
just if you want to share a word or two a sentence or two about your practice uh
please share and then the next person and then the next person and then goes round and round and round and please
don't comment on each other's practice don't ask direct questions of each other
just be gentle and kind and caring be kind to yourself be kind to each other
and keep the order of going round and round please um and if at any time um
challenges arise perhaps in groups if you can practice with kindness and compassion for yourself and and the
other people in the group so so let's go uh let the uh order be
alphabetical order so I'm going to create the breakout rooms now be kind to
yourself be kind to one another and I'm opening them now take
care welcome back everyone welcome back and um yeah we have a few minutes for
Reflections about your practice how the practice went perhaps how the groups
went um and um yeah and how was your practice of of
showing up with kindness and compassion for one another and for yourselves
that's really what we're practicing here with one another with patience kindness
compassion Ser ni your hand is up thank you for allowing me to
unmute I'm unmuted okay good then I'll lower my hand lower the
hand yeah you know I want some remedy for
papancha I think the papancha is a major is a major
hindrance and I don't I know in my own life
um you know uh and I don't think it helps much oh this papano does not help
much you know like like you have a thought about something or you need to do something and there's all this
thinking that goes on about it you know um I really would like to have more
freedom from papancha it would really make my life a lot less
painful and stressful yeah yeah thank you seren I
appreciate appreciate you clearly saying you know what what a relief it it would
be to have less Pancha because we know we have this proliferation and sometimes we feel like a prisoner um in the
prisoner of our own mind like a enough already please please can I just have some rest like sometimes it can feel
like that so so how do we go about it um and I also really appreciate this
this wholesome desire that you expressed I really would like to have more tools more more ways to have freedom from this
so it it is a training right it's a training like anything else it's a
training and um as the Buddha has said whatever you frequently Ponder and
reflect upon becomes to the inclination of your mind and in the western way you
know scientific way we talk about neuroplasticity you know if we keep thinking and ruminating about things
that becomes the pattern that becomes so so it it really is a mind training it
really comes back to a mind training and and the word Sati or
mindfulness the translation of it one translation is to remember so we just to
to keep remembering to keep remembering we find ourselves in the midst of the
papancha and to kindly remember okay sweetie it's all right let's put it down
let's put let's come back to the body let's come back to the mind and it does weak can it does the beauty of it is
that it works the beauty is that it does work uh both in the short term and in
the long term we're not um completely um um what's the word I'm
looking for um yeah we it's not like we're resourceless in in in in the face
of it that it's really a pattern are the patterns of our minds in in small moments big moments we just have to keep
doing it over and over and over and over again in in small and big ways it's like
the feather weight that's the other thing I would say it's really important to apply a feather weight because if we
try to hammer like stop a buncha then it becomes a a fight with ourselves but
just ever so gently that's where meta comes in it was this gentleness of okay let's come back this is not helpful this
is not helpful do you really want to be thinking about this right now sweetie no it's not helpful so keep keep coming
back keep coming back and I promise you it works that's it that's the word I was looking for helpless thank you Megan
thanks for helping me out we're not helpless that's it we're not helpless um
and it works it does work otherwise we wouldn't be practicing this it works
Serena so I really appreciate your wholesome desire so hold on to that wholesome desire because that intention
really will keep you practicing in this way and and it works it does work I can
tell you that that it's worked for me I for many many students practitioners it
works over time it does work it does work so thank you so much for bringing that up thank
you Mari Christine I see your head hi Nikki I just wanted to ask you
sp punch of the same as monkey mind um not exactly there's slight
differences so um so the idea of monkey mind is the nature of Mind tends to jump
from one topic to another so monkey mind refers to the nature of mind that but
papancha is the word for proliferation itself so it's not the nature of mind
but it's the word for proliferation so so maybe the better way to relate to them is monkey mind likes to get lost in
the forest of proliferation how is that yeah thanks Mary
Christie I love that word when I learned papancha years and years ago
um as I said I just love the the sound of a panja it seemed like there would be
times when my mind was proliferating panja this thought and that thought and this and that's like
whoa uh it's it's a near cousin of overwhelm but not necessarily always so
papancha any other Reflections practice reports reports
from the field maybe I'll ask you did um when I was guiding you and inviting you
to put down to put down it uh and and then to turn after a few minutes I
invited you to T into perhaps a lightness was there lightness or Delight like yeah this ah this feels nice it
feels a little lighter did anybody experience that yeah I see some people waving I see Richard waving Richard do
you want to unmute is that and I see p Petro also waving I have two different
screens yes there yeah yeah and hanova says yes to so
raise your Zoom hand because it's really hard for me uh for to anyway oh there's Petra okay here we
go as to unmute yeah thank you Nikki I noticed
how wasn't a practice of subtracting that's how I felt you know you're just subtracting from your experience in some
degrees like no don't go there put it down and and the more the more you did
it I need I really no it's like wow it's already fairly quiet here and pleasant
uh so in a sense you don't have to create the pleasantness or the quiet it was just like um a practice of
subtraction you just subtract the prancha and the quiet is already there so that's uh that was my that was my
experience definitely there that's great I love that thank I love how you described the Petro as as a practice of
subtraction When You Subtract all the papon put it like ah it's quite quite
sweet here this is quite sweet it's Pleasant it's peace you don't even have to perhaps plant the um you know the
words that I suggested like peace or yes or thank you it's like yeah this is pretty good here I can hang out here and
and and also what I highlight is what's really important in this practice is putting things down with gentleness with
kindness you don't want to throw things down with hatred or frustration like
stop like it's like oh sweetheart I don't it's okay I'm just gonna put you that is the key if you throw them and I
know you didn't raise this P but I'm just using this as a teaching moment because I really want to emphasize this
that putting things down with gentleness and Care is where this ease comes up like yeah this is pretty sweet this
feels pretty sweet so thank you appreciate your reflection
clear thank you Nikki I don't know if this is is useful or not I use a
technique that's different than the one you're describing I don't put things down I was trained at a Zeno many years
ago to start by picking an object or an
idea that I want to focus on you know say a
rose and I picture the rose and then of course my mind W wanders off into Poncha
but my assignment is to go back to the roads and I just keep going back and
little by slowly my mind stays there and everything there's no no no action going
on anymore yeah yeah yeah to yeah so so Claire there are lots of different
practices lots of different practices in Buddhism lots of them and this putting down to release is one of them oh yeah
and going back to the object is another one so so um and I appreciate the practice you're doing but and I want to
keep tonight with this practice the practice of putting down a subtraction thank you
okay great and let's see oh yes and adelus is to be honest I felt the
imprint of what I just put down perhaps those underlying feelings needed some care um yes thank you for raising that
Adelia um if if there are strong emotions and it's not just just papancha
just thoughts like the usual but but there's some emotion that needs care yes and putting them down may
not be the appropriate thing to do so caring for them is the appropriate thing to do it's so I appreciate the the
wisdom that you raised there absolutely great was there another hand
that I think I saw are we complete Richard you keep waving your hand but I
don't see you [Music]
um let's see Megan okay I'm going to oh there's I
see Megan sorry I there you are Megan okay hi dicki thank you so much for this
practice um I I think possibly you answered the question with adilia
because um when I put everything down um
I felt incredible anger
um and that felt
true it didn't feel like rumination it felt true and and I also just not really
sure how to take care of anger but maybe that's a question for another time yeah
I appreciate that wonderful so very um wonderful that uh you you bring this
forth because this is this is what can happen when when we put other things down perhaps then the clarity of oh yeah
this needs care oh there's anger or there's sadness or there's something else here that needs care and that
becomes clear which is which is great so and then working with anger uh very
briefly um allow the energy of it to move through not to be stuck with the
story and the thought but with um but but let yourself turn towards the energy
let it let it move through let it move Let It Be experienced not necessarily acted out on upon but let it let it move
through yes sweetheart and then bring compassion to it different ways to work with it but here in this container
working with it with confessional sweetheart this is painful this is hard because anger is like picking up
hot a hot coal to throw at someone who gets hurt hurt first you do it's like oh
sweetie this is painful this is hard so caring for the emotion and then later
allowing um the wise action to arise but really taking care of the emotion yeah
thank you and Richard I do see you you you showed up on my pan pain which is very
small okay I'm going to ask you to unmute yourself there okay I just want to
mention is that I I found myself thinking of a of putting of Letting Go
would would trigger defense that I was worried that I could be putting myself in danger if I drops things I I didn't
expect that reaction to your uh directions but that's that was very
surprising for me that I considered it as putting myself in physical danger if
I just dropped all my defenses oh interesting yeah yeah that um that's
very interesting and also I appreciate that Richard you said it was surprising to you
that you didn't expect that and and you know and also I want to point out to you
that you know putting down thoughts or papancha is not
exactly the same as putting down defenses so the mind already took a leap
to put down Def fenses and then felt uh Jarred so that's very interesting that's
very H to have compassion with curiosity oh sweetheart what's happening here
what's happening here so I invite you to have more curiosity about that leap that
your mind and heart took from putting down thoughts to putting down defenses
and then feeling feeling the rejection of no there's something there that needs care um so that's what I invite you to
sit with and and practice with curiosity where was was there a time when you felt
unsafe um and and this suggestion is is is putting
is catapulting the mind to that area whereas it's just about putting down
thoughts not about putting down defenses right you see the difference you hear the difference right sure does that make
sense to have some curiosity about this for yourself I it's definitely a very
intriguing kind of thing that came up yeah yeah I mean because these because I
consider myself as a person who's not that defensive and more open yet there
must be some level down there of there are limits to my openness right oh my
goodness this is so great Richard I so appreciate your curiosity and openness in this like w this is interesting this
this human being which I thought I knew pretty well like there's some things I'm still learning about this human being
who is me yeah do great thank you so much thank
you for sharing yeah so dear ones we have come to the end of the happy hour
uh and then some thank you so much for your practice thank you for sharing of yourself cultivating your heart your
mind for the sake of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
[Music] ourselves thanks everyone I'm going to