we are right at the top of the hour so after you've had a chance to say hello to me say hello to each
other please um settle back find a meditation posture
that works for you this
morning settling in smiling at Old Friends
and [Music] um starting by going
inwards taking a couple of slower deeper
breaths letting go on the out breath
and [Music] receiving receiving the warmth of this
community receiving [Music] air receiving
Awareness on the in breath
tuning into your whole
body your heart your mind
and receiving awareness allowing awareness to brighten just a little bit with each
inhale
here and then on each out breath
giving yourself over giving yourself completely to the
breath to the
moment perhaps with a slight smile
whatever time of day it is where you
are dedicating this time to being present
receiving on the in breath offering
centering giving over letting go on the out
breath e
you find the Mind wandering thoughts
imaginings memories greeting them kindly in the
moment and again offering yourself to this practice this
breath being
here receiving present moment
awareness
e
e e
allowing the [Music] attention to settle to
rest in the
body now I get to follow the breath
be invited to open
up receive Sensations within this
body allowing the breathing to be
soothing natural however it wants to be
today receiving the
fullness of awareness In This
Moment
e
e e
[Music] softening [Music]
allowing resting in the felt scent
of the out
breath giving over to this moment of
meditation trusting this
moment
e
e e
in the last few minutes of our formal practice together this
morning the invitation is to
recollect remember the moments of
goodness mindful awareness peace
fulness any glimmers of goodness that emerged in the
practice today a moment of
patience kindness
trust whatever was there
and to gather it into your
heart receive the nourishment of
it and taking a moment to trust
appreciate your the Integrity of your own efforts today of showing up in the
practice it's not a small
thing and from that
place casting your your internal gaze outwards to the other your life
touches with the wish that the benefits of your practice
touch them as well Ripple outwards
may all beings everywhere be
safe peaceful and free
thank you for your practice
for e
so good morning sa delighted to be with you and
um special warm welcome to those of you who slipped in a bit late into the YouTube s the online
sa and a warm welcome to those of you listening later as
well so happy to be with you really Delight in um reconnecting with this
sa so today I would like to
offer some Reflections on gifts we receive from this practice
and this is based on a few of the Buddha's lesser known teachings discourses on
generosity but um in general you may be well aware that the Buddha's teachings
place a lot of emphasis on giving on offering as part of the beginning of the
path from post practitioners it's less about what is given than
how and this week instead of focusing on giving things we're going to focus on
the qualities we give the how we give to our
practice and the gifts that can be received from it so I'm going to start with a story I
love to tell stories some of you know many years ago I had the benefit of
staying in a um a wat a temple in Thailand and this Temple was on this
little desert mostly deserti is arid island in the Bay of Thailand kosich
Chong and the temple itself had been started by this um very sincere monastic
um who grew into a wonderful teacher and it was just him in a cave for a long time and then gradually as these things
happen there the um the complex grew up around him as people came to practice
with him and I was touched to learn early on that the temple itself the
entire place was named after an enlightened woman so this teacher had seen her in a
dream and was so inspired by her that he named his life's work after
her and it was a very human scale kind of
place it centered around the monastic life the rhythm of the seasons the rhythm of Awakening prce practicing and
gardening and the monastics mostly with some help from the villagers built up
the temple over time and they lived their life as a
Dharma expression dedicating practice to others in fact the one time we would all come
together we actually came together two times a day in the morning and in the evening and in the evening all of us
women would sit in a little um open AED beautiful place um at night and dedicate
our practice to others and there's this kind of symbolic ritual or practice we did which
involved pouring the water from one cup or one vessel to
another and then we would pad out in our bare feet out into the darkness of the
garden and water the plant and it was such a beautiful
practice you know just Starry Night Big Sky but it was also symbolic in another
way on this arid Island there were no Lakes no ponds no Rivers all of the
water came from these very crafty catchments built right into the temple
roofs that caught the water as they sloped and it would um pour the water
down into these sisters beneath each structure and because the place was on a
hill there were a number of different structures at different levels and the people there gardened
with the water they bathed with it we drank it and for many years they gave the excess
water and food to the villagers all around the temple which then they
received back in the form of meals there was such an integrity and open
handedness about trust conviction about their
generosity and I talk about this because that kind of trust and conviction can be
an inherent condition of mature Dharma practice and an expression of the
practice itself they related to the life
Necessities in this generous way the people there treated what they
gave and to whom they gave it with respect attentiveness and this Rhythm was in
resonance with the seasons and abundance that was appropriate to the
context of this place and you could feel this palpable sense of kindness and Care
between the temple practitioners and the village ERS it was really
evident and those sisters those structures were built in a really
intentional way as I said there the whole Temple was on a a hill and each
sstn flowed into the sistern in the structure beneath it all the way down so
whatever water wasn't used for gardening or personal use or given away way flowed
back into the ocean and there in this vast cycle of
oceanic generosity it eventually perhaps returned as
rain so this hints at both a kind of a
trust and relating to this offering through a sense of
of conditionality the people there had no way of knowing when or if the sharing of
their abundance whether it be water with the ocean or food with others would be returned to them but they
trusted that what they gave would somehow offer an intrinsic good whether
to them directly or outwards in all of these unknowable ways
so in the coming days I'll explore a whole range of the way that these gifts
Cascade back to us the Abundant goodness
possibility when we approach the Dharma when we approach meditation practice in
an open-handed way and this is really because in my
experience offering yourself complete complely offering myself completely to the
practice invites receiving even greater gifts from
it in this way the means of Dharma practice prees the ends of
it and there's a beautiful mystery in just what and how we offer transmutes
into this receiving but perhaps as our friends in the Zen tradition say there's
not a real separation between Giver receiver and
gift so that's the overview kind of impressionistic sense
of where we're going and today I just really simply want to underscore the
power of conviction of trust in the practice a place like this Thai temple
represents that kind of conviction that kind of trust trust integrity and the
reciprocity that can come from the staying power of showing up in these
ways there [Music] are three levels of this kind of
trust borrowed Bri and
verified so borrowed trust or faith is experimental maybe based on what you've
heard or seen or read possibly even based on scientific
studies right trust right Faith it's sometimes called is when something has
clicked there's a sense of possibility there's a Tailwind for the practice and
energy wow okay this works I saw it written on a a signboard
outside of a yoga studio years ago this kind of trust or confidence isn't trusting that things will turn out okay
it's trusting that no matter how things turn out you'll be
okay and then there's the third level verified Faith verified trust
confidence which is based on powerful firsthand
experience so to the extent that you can offer trust
Integrity conviction to the practice offer yourself wholeheartedly to the
practice these qualities increase the possibility of ref
receiving feelings of Joy
lightness openness spaciousness they can become sources of
strength a rootedness this kind of Integrity in the practice and can be
very sustaining so that's the
quality that between today and tomorrow I want to invite you to
consider for yourself how does conviction confidence
trust show up in your heart how might it inform you in your life and practice or
how might you like it to what can you do to invite more of it
I'm not going to offer a full outline of the week because this is a journey we're
taking together this week it's alive in my practice and we'll kind of Discover
it together so thank you very much for your
kind attention and I would love to see any thoughts you have about how trust
confidence that kind of Integrity might show up in your practice
now or how you think it might be helpful thank
you may the benefits of our practice here together be a cause and
condition for greater trust clarity
conviction and freedom in the world