so welcome and the topic for this week is
mindfulness of emotions and these emotions are to be respected
and cared for and attended to they're very important part of life but not only
life but they're very important part of Buddhist practice they're in integral to the
whole uh unfolding of Buddhist practice and to
not include our emotional life in the Buddhist practice is to Short Change
oneself in the richness and the unfolding of the
practice and important as it is maybe because it's so important we want to
create the right conditions for being present for the emotions right
conditions for our emotions to um to reveal themselves to
us the right uh way of developing a capacity to hold whatever emotion comes
through and that begins with the [Music]
posture that we assume when we meditate and whether
you're whatever way you you're you're meditating whether it's sitting or lying
down or standing or walking meditation the idea is to find be
careful not to just take a habitual posture not to just uh sit on the couch
and and um not give any care or attention to the posture you're
in but to uh find a posture that's appropriate
for you where you feel that there's
stability and uh a kind of postural
alertness a kind of uh
uh uh intentional capacity
to for the body and the posture to be the temple the container the the
that holds the emotions so it's not just the mind it's
not just our thinking that is responsible for finding a way to be with our
emotions because if it's just the mind if it's just thinking and
reacting we don't really allowing
ourselves opportunity to feel feel the emotions fully to let the emotions be
free within us without us reacting or picking them up or fueling
them so to spend a little bit a Time
adjusting your posture and it could be as simple as the way your hands
are that there's a feeling of being grounded in the
hands a sense of maybe strength I usually keep my hands my
Palms facing down on my
thighs and it's a little bit of a posture of being ready for
anything it's a posture that provides a kind of tripod effect for the rest of
the Torso
and maybe the spine is a little bit
straighter maybe the shoulders can roll back a little
bit even laying down that's possible sometimes to have the shoulder
blades shoulders roll back the shoulder blades going down the back a
little so the chest is a little bit more open
if we're the chest is caved
in there's less room in our torso for feeling and sensing our emotional
life and with that with a stable
open posture that maybe has some modum of
strength one of the first things we try to do with
emotions is to listen to
them and not just for their me not for a message or thoughts or stories connected
to them but a deep attention to how they're felt and
experienced in the body it's almost like we're listening to the
body many people benefit tremendously from being heard having
someone who's a really good listener hear what's going on our body benefits
immensely if we listen but not expecting words or not
expecting a verbal
conversation but listening represents a sensing where we make room for things to
be felt deeply fully as present moment
phenomena in the stable
posture the open
receptive attitude of listening as if your
body has important messages to tell you don't try to discern the messages
just listen [Music] feel how how your
emotions manifest physically in the chest in the belly in
the
shoulders so to gently close your
eyes feel your body the threedimensional
quality of the
body the weight of the
body
and as if you can make more room in your body by breathing in
deeply feel your torso fill your lungs with
air so that your chest expands
even your back rib cage
stretch and a long exhale to settle in to
relax
and letting your breathing return to normal and continue the process
of feeling your torso expand as you breathe
in relaxing as you
exhale and then notice how your your
feeling emotion that are present
mood mind
State the broad general feeling of your state of
being and whatever way you're feel feeling whatever emotions are
present it's allowed for this exercise it's
okay but find where in the body you most feel your
state of mind your inner
state is it mostly in the the
Torso mostly in the
head and your arms or your
legs is it's in your chest or in your
belly in the face or in the
neck wherever whatever wherever the emotion is most
active in your body wherever the evidence in your body
is of how you're feeling trust the feeling it's it's
okay make room for
it and become a good friend to it by simply listening almost as if you're sitting
next to it on a park bench and you're attending you're
accompanying whatever feeling is
there and part of the purpose of listening in
the body feeling in the body with the emotions is to give more room for those
sensations of the body to move to
unfold emotions are always in motion if we
allow them if we give them space listening to the emotions not
to hear a message but listen in such a way
that whatever movement the emotion wants to do physical
Sensations allow the sensations to flow to
move to change whatever way they want to change
for
if you're listening to someone playing music you're
quiet so it's not to disturb the hearing and the
music let your thinking mind become quieter so you can hear the music of
your emotions how emotions are
felt expressed in the
body giving permission for the emotion to live in the body in whatever
way it wants while you
sit stably in posture of stability and
strength that can allow it all to unfold
Within
e
for
as if you're
listening from a place deep
within that has lots of capacity to just
listen just feel whatever the mood or emotions you
have however subtle and if it feels right to do
so you can breathe with your emotional state your mood how
you feel breathe through
it
for
e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a few gentle deeper
breaths relaxing the body as you
exhale breathing in relaxing the
heart softening in the
chest breathing in and
softening the thinking
mind and then
considering in whatever way that you experience emotions and feelings
moods so do
others that the moods and states of Mind inner states of being of
others is an important part of who they are
and regardless of what they do in their
life if we just could be attuned and feel their inner
State we would probably care for them we'd probably wish them
well and to end this
meditation with a wish for the well-being of
everyone that the State of Mind the state of heart the inner quality of being the
emotions that circulate in people may they
be nourishing heal healthy may they bring happiness and
peace May the inner life of
others feel happy and safe and
peaceful may people feel untroubled in their
hearts may they be at ease in
themselves may they be
free and may they know that we wish them
well may all beings be
[Music] happy
[Music]
[Music] thank
you
so today I'm going to continue talking about mindfulness of
emotions and uh yesterday the topic was or the practice was to be able to
recognize the presence of an emotion in a respectful way to recognize it with
some feeling of Freedom not participating not activated
by not reactive to emotions but this beautiful way in which the mind can know
something clearly name something ah it's and in the naming in the recognition of
what it actually is there's a feeling of space or feeling of of uh n non
stickiness non- entanglement oh this is how it is and the exercise yesterday was to
just disco try to discover that just in a in a moment not that it have to last anything more than just a moment when
which you're recognizing this movement to be
unentangled un not reactive to emotions not judging them not participating in
them not um collapsing in them but finding a certain degree of Freedom with
emotions is U supported by mindfulness of the body and this is one of the
reasons why in this series we do mindfulness of the body before doing mindfulness of
emotions all emotions are uh one way or the other are
manifested in Sensations in the body and sometimes we have to be very they're
very subtle and you have to be be very attempted to feel it but they're always there in the body and and um and there's
a way of dropping in and feeling the physical manifestation of emotions which
is a wonderful alternative to uh living in the thoughts about the emotion to
living in the stories of the emotions some emotions are really closely connected to the stories we tell
ourselves and um in fact you we can just be sitting peacefully and then we
remember a story of being hurt by someone or someone offended us and as we tell ourselves the story remember the
story we can feel the emotions arise and um and uh and so the more we stay in the
story of mind repeating and repeating and repeating what happened or thinking about it or caring repeating the
conversation um uh it it fuels the emotion more and more and uh one of the
reasons some people will go distract themselves is so that they're not repeating the harmful way of thinking
that's causing difficult emotions and um so the um uh so to drop down into the
body as an alternative to to the Mind thinking and story making is a very
significant way for uh us to start giving the emotions some freedom freed
uh and freedom doesn't mean that we act freely in whatever way the emotion seems to want to direct us in it's powerful
very significant in meditation we're more or less committed not to move and uh so we don't uh give in to
whatever the emotion wants us to do we feel it instead we feel it with
respect and uh another way of talking about feeling the emotion in the body that I like a lot this idea of listening
to it um all all emotions are
messages all emotions have some you know almost like a purpose to
be there they shouldn't be dismissed but one of for the people who do mindfulness
meditation uh one of the purposes of the emotions is to allow the momentum the
movement of whatever we're feeling to move through us unencumbered uh unencumbered by
attachment unencumbered by resistance unencumbered by preferes and judgments
unen unencumbered by repression and pushing it down to avoid it and to learn
that we have the capacity to feel the emotions of our life without being troubled by
them and that can be difficult emotions and it can be beautiful emotions we can
uh and we start learning that the freedom to feel is better a better
pleasure than the pleasure of good emotions some people lean into the uh
good emotions and hold on to them and celebrate them in a way that kind of is
being caught in their a grip there's nothing inherently wrong with doing that
but there's something better to do and that's the pleasure of being free
in uh in relationship to so it's not just allowing the motion to be there so
listening deeply like we're listening to the body the body is almost like the
transmitter of emotions and so that's where we want to listen and the benefit of that is that
um it takes us out of the story-making Mind the thinking mind which can add
fuel to the fire of the emotions uh or is where we how we get
caught by them and how we identify with the emotions to uh dropping into the
body and allowing the emotion to have its life in the body all emotions want
to move if the if the emotion creates tightness in the body contraction and
and then if we make space to listen to it it begins to relax and open if there
are if the emotions involve some kind of nervous energy as we listen to it and
make space for the nervousness uh it has nervousness has it chance to settle that
it doesn't if we keep thinking about the scary thoughts so listening to the body oh
that's where the nervousness is and now let's listen deeply as if it has a message as if it's a friend in distress
who just wants someone to be to accompany them and listen to them oh that's where it is in the belly the
nervousness or in the chest in the shoulders wherever it might be um and um same thing with anger if
anger is uh uh a feeling of pressure and and forcefulness within us tightening uh
if we you know if if you feel you know if your hand is clenched and a friend
comes along and doesn't say anything doesn't judge you but just holds the clenched hand you didn't even know was
clenched until you felt the warmth softness of your friends holding it and then it
releases so the we bring this capacity
to hold to feel to listen to whatever the emotion might
be if the emotions involve tension of any kind attachment in any kind this
practice of just feeling in the body and letting it like let it letting the body's expression have room and space to
change and be it tends to change by relaxing tends to some emotions some
difficult emotions need to have the chance to get stronger before they can pass away you might feel some anger but
as we feel the anger the inner kind of Wellspring the volcano allow maybe needs
the volcano to the to the U it to become kind of strong anger rage and so we then
we learn we open up to the capacity to feel the rage in this meditative posture
that we have and uh make room for it and learn slowly over time that no matter what the
emotion is we have the capacity to be still receptive open
kind um uh so that it can process itself in a sense all emotions are being our
processes unfolding and there's something very significant about just making room for it in body that's quiet
and still there are certainly other ways of processing emotions and uh you know
sometimes it's good to I like to walk if there's a lot of anger I used to be like to just go for long walks to get it
moving and that allowed me to keep stay in the body there's many ways of processing but for in meditation this is
the way it can be done and then if the emotion is a healthy one a nourishing one um this
making space and listening has a different effect than letting it relax uh then it allows the goodness the
goodness over the warmth or the tenderness or the good feelings of the happy emotion to begin spreading through
the body it makes room for it to become to suffuse the body rather than being
bottled up some good emotions can have a little bit like attachment connected to them like we're excited and we it gets
channeled in some way but to make room for it there's a kind of calmness and suffusion and spreading of that goodness
throughout the body so a huge part of mindfulness of
emotions is um the practice of uh embodiment of feeling the emotion as it
is expressed or felt in the body and um the first step in this doing
so is just becoming familiar with how emotions are in the body um all the different ways that are
different emotions different moods mind States um energetically
uh sensation wise all Sensations that come into play getting familiar with it
as we get familiar with it then the second stage is to make room for it to
make room to see to allow for how those Sensations
connected to the emotion change how they unfold and how they're part of a ongoing
processing that cannot happen if we are living in the reactivity of the Mind the
thoughts of the Mind the attachments the stories that keep fueling
them and um and so
um so for today if you would like um
make it a day to explore this sensations of whatever mind State mood
inner state of being that you have um no matter how subtle it
is uh and chances are pretty high that
there's always going to be something to feel uh and uh but it takes sensitivity
it takes pausing and looking so through the day you might find a way to pause
and to feel carefully respect F what are the sensations in the body connected to
how you're feeling and uh and and if you want to do the Second Step then um just quietly
listen to it as if it has permission to be there uh as if there's no need to
judge it but just make room and listen and feel and sense and and see if as you
do so what changes maybe you want to breathe with it and that's a nice way of connected
sometimes breathing with an emotion makes it easier to stay present rather than drifting
away so uh uh I hope that uh doing this
mindfulness of emotions this way in the body enriches your life U I found that it enriched my life
tremendously and uh it's a fantastic foundation for deepening Dharma practice
which the deepening of practice is through the vehicle of what could be called emotions or
feelings so thank you and we'll continue
tomorrow