so warm greetings at the beginning of our week and I
am happy to be here and uh and to be able to share this
wonderful practice that we have and a practice that has been um one of
the most uh constant
source of gratitude and appreciation for my adult life it's uh the regularity of
meditating for all these years is a through line it's a thread that runs through the life and and forms the life
and uh it's a reference point for my lived life that has been
invaluable so thank you for this opportunity to be here with you all
and
um
so so there's a famous line in po poems called the four
quartets by TSL it that goes something like teach me to care and not to
care and to oriented towards what we're doing today teach me that I'm important and
not important the
um so by and not important
is not that we're unimportant but rather we often see ourselves as important in the wrong
ways we see ourselves as important enough to be attached to our ideas of
who we are attached to ourselves clinging to ourselves clinging to
life and uh sometimes that attachment is negative and so sometimes we treat
ourselves with less respect and care than we would our house plants there's a
lot of uh struggles that people have with their identity with who they are
and criticizing themselves feeling inadequate in some way and one of the symptoms of that is
not seeing ourselves as important as valuable and then the other hand people
will have too much conceit and too uh filled with their self-importance
so it's the importance that we assign ourselves negative importance positive
importance the way they were important enough to judge and hold on to ideas that I mean by teach teach us to
to be not important and then the to teach us that
we're important to know we're important is to know that independent
of our attachments that we can see the
world without attachments we can see the world with
kindness independent of our
we can have a heart that feels deeply and caringly for the others and
ourselves and when we see ourselves as important enough that who we are how we
act how we live in the world can bring into the world the absence of attachment
the absence of hate and greed that we can bring kindness and
goodness then we can also begin seeing that we are
important that each individual is phenomenally important and Buddhist premise is that
we are important enough that we can dedicate ourselves to a path of
practice it's invaluable to engage in a practice like it's invaluable to give it
one's lifetime to doing it uh because we're
important and it's important important enough we're important enough to learn to let go of what
diminishes our Humanity our value and all that which often has which sometimes
has to do with our attachments to self or conceit around self positive or
negative conceit so to
meditate as if or because we are are as important as any
other person important enough for our respect important enough to
feel meditate in a in a field of
worthiness for this
practice with confidence so to assume a meditation
posture
and classically a meditation meditation is meant to be done in a posture of
dignity and there are four dignified postures
they say lying down sitting standing and
walking whichever one of those four postures you think will work best for you for this next
now 25 minutes
please assume a dignified posture that you feel allows your body
your inner most life to reveal itself to
you in its dignity in its worthiness
as if it your your life your inner life is
important closing your eyes and gently in a way that's right for
you take some longer slower deeper breaths and relax on the exhale
maybe on a deeper inhale to have it be a filling of
yourself with a sense
of presence value certainty that here you are an
important person engaged in this practice
letting your breathing return to
normal and feel where in your body
the inhale
begins maybe even a particular spot where the first little inkling of
sensation appears for an instant and then expands and spreads as
you breathe in
and perhaps you can allow the place where the inhale begins be a place that's free of any way
in which you diminish yourself diminish your value and importance
and maybe instead be the
opposite a location with which you can view yourself as least as important as
any other person on this planet you yourself are a valuable
person a human being
and as you inhale let that sense of dignity value
importance grow and spread throughout your
body and then as you exhale let yourself relax
into a sense of embodied value and
respect so that your thinking becomes quieter any self-criticisms or
self-doubts quiet on the exhale
inhaling and exhaling be like
a central a center for all things that
occur to you a central resting place being
place that reminds you of your own importance important
enough to let the thinking mind become quieter and
Stiller maybe a relief from the
fragmentation of discursive
thought
for
e for
to be present here here in this body with every
breath as if here your lived experience
now is the place in which to experience
your tremendous importance your dignity your value
and that
mindfulness is a way of making room for each thing that
occurs within you as an expression of your
value that softens all the ways that we diminish ourselves criticize
ourselves not opposed to those
Tendencies but creating the conditions that those can
relax relax into our fundamental importance
en
e
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to
consider how when we're present with others with a simp simple
unattached sense of personal dignity
value where we don't diminish ourselves with SH shyness with feeling
unworthy don't diminish ourselves by not wanting to be trouble for other
people where we show up with a nonassertive Clarity of attention
then when we engage with others we can meet them more
fully and our kindness can be transmitted more clearly
our friendliness has more
clarity our generosity more impact
then if we diminish ourselves with half
withdrawal so imagine yourself going into this world today into your
life with a nonassertive uprightness
dignity we're part of your gift to the world is the
full way in which you appear non assertively but non
submissively you appear with a kind of personal dignity and value and
importance through which you can convey the dignity and value of
others the fullness of your presence for others indication that you value
them as they are without needing
to exchange or get anything from others or want them to be
different in our own dignity our kindness can spread more
widely and deeply into the world May our personal dignity be the
source of wishing others well promoting the welfare and happiness
of Others May all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may our personal dignity show that that is possible
[Music]
thank you [Music]
So today we're at the halfway point through the 10
Reflections that um are Central
to can be Central to the offering of spiritual care
and I like to think of it as spiritual care to oneself as much as it is to
others and to wish ourselves well to care for ourselves in a deep way allows
us to care for others and one of the phenomenally
important roles of people who offer spiritual care to others chaplains and
clergy and monastics and Buddhist
teachers is to um uh is
to convey to others their dign dignity their value their
importance to be dignifi what a great role it is to be
able to be a dignifi of other people I think of that is being an affirmation of
others a deep appreciation of others to recognize what is is wonderful about
others and not enough people have been seeing uh uh in valuable ways have been
really seen with respect and care as we grow up the mirroring of
people who respect us and care for us is invaluable sometime people you know love
us or they say they love us they think they love us but the love is so entangled with control with wanting us
to a certain way with making us safe and protecting us that there's no room for
us to kind of stand on our own two feet and be fully ourselves in a clear and
full way the excessive parenting sometimes gets in the way of having room
for us to be recognized and seen as autonomous as being as having
agency and so uh to dignify others but
we can do that better if we know that uh we have a sense of our own dignity and
so dignity is the six of the 10 Reflections and maybe you'd prefer a
different word for than dignity uh it could be worth self-worth
self-importance it could be respect uh maybe there's other kind of
synonyms for this territory as well I like the word respect a lot myself that we have a deep respect for
ourselves and yes you I say often that I like the word respect because it kind of
means in Latin Latin origins of it to see again to have enough uh valuing of
others and ourselves that we give a second look we make space to really get to know somebody ourselves other people
the situation we respect it so let's get to know it more uh respect is not the diminishing
diminishing of ourselves it's not a sub submiss ourselves or lowering ourselves
in order to hold someone else up um respect is um with all our dignity and
respect and value importance with that offer others respect and in a maybe in a
kind of American way to see each other as equals to meet as
equals um one of the profound way ways in which I was trained in Zen practice
is that the relationship between a teacher and a student was supposed to grow into uh a time when uh when they
met it was the meeting of Buddha and Buddha only in the meeting of a Buddha
and Buddha as the practice comes to fulfillment and so this the the mutual
respect and kind of dignity and value that was built into kind of cultivating
as Zen student teacher relationship uh was um very impactful for me this idea
that we meet uh with that kind of care and love and respect as if we were
mutually me Buddhas meeting each other so um to there's uh so in the
reflection about res respect and dignity self-importance it might be useful to
begin uh to really understand all the ways in which we do the opposite all the
ways in which we do not maintain our dignity we give it up all the ways we do not respect ourselves there's actually
disrespect all the ways in which we feel unworthy some of that is learned from
the world around us that uh we internalize people's um projections and
opinions and ideas that we're unimportant that we have to be different um and so sometimes uh growing
into our dignity is to is like a snake shedding its skin so we have to shed all
these inherited views and opinions that we received from family our religions
our society so that we can take a stand we can take our seat in a full and clear
and dignified way also uh we have to understand that
the difference between uh dignity and conceit how that uh uh how and we have
over importance for ourselves that we we are asserting ourselves think it has to
be my way and you know and I have to be the one who has my 15 minutes of fame
and and um and somehow we're projecting ourselves to the world uh because we
want to be seen in a certain way and re and held up in a certain way and praised in a certain way um so both diminishing
ourselves and overvaluing ourselves um should be understood deeply and
clearly and so that's part of the value of mindfulness practice that as we learn to stay in the present moment to see the
operating systems that areer operating for us not only do we see it but we also
more importantly we see the cost of it we see how life gets drained from us
when we diminish ourselves we see how we fragment ourselves and stress ourselves
through conceit overdoing it for ourselves we lose part of
ourselves and now so as we begin understanding the ways in which we the
the problems of the different forms of absence of dignity um then we can maybe begin
understanding something about the middle way of a kind of dignity and respect and
value that allows ourselves to be to really inhabit ourselves really be here
fully and clearly without anxiety without fear without
assertion without um diminishing yourselves or feeling
unworthy and uh but to do it in a simple very peaceful way no one no one has to
be afraid of us and I've met people who conventionally seemed
somewhat um I don't know what to say that's respectful for them but maybe I can willing can say somewhat Meek and
quiet and gentle people and uh the last last people I
would be concerned about that they thought they were going to be overpowering for others and somehow they
live concerned that they're going to do that very thing overpowered be too strong for people too much for people
and I don't know what the psychological dynamics of that combination is but uh I
think uh we ideally we want to have a
society of strong people and some of us could do well to develop a sense of
strength to grow up in a certain way and but not diminish ourselves for people
who are gentle or maybe even difficult uh Meek or something but to find a way
to support them to see them with dignity so to help them grow and uh so they also
can be strong and if we feel for ourselves that we are are
somehow I don't know we too much for people uh maybe that's a time for a lot
of attention and study what's really going on there and maybe sometimes it's useful to really recruit friends and
family to get feedback how do this work for me am I too much sometimes we are
and so maybe we have something to learn sometimes we're not and we have something else to learn but to learn how
we navigate in the world and the impact we have on other people um and and and and to be mirrored
by other people to understand our who we are and how we operate so that we can
find that middle way of dignity the middle way of um
where we can stand upright and strong without assertion without being overbearing and
without being under bearing so the idea of dignity follows in a
sense grows out of these earlier Reflections that when we have a sense when we know what we have a sense of
meaning and purpose when we have agency and we can act on it um when we have a
sense of autonomy uh and uh and a strong sense of identity we know who we are all these
build on each other support each other so that when we feel our dignity
it arises out of knowing ourselves well it arises out of um
knowing a purpose a value in our life what's most important and from the Buddhist point of
view uh we we develop our dignity not because we're inherently human as as if
inherent Humanity of everyone is worthy of our respect and and reverence which
it might be I don't want to say it's not but that's not the Buddha's orientation I think the Buddha's orientation is that
um our dignity is something that we live it's how we live in the world how we
speak how we act how we even how we think and so that's why the earlier
Reflections are so important to really have reflected on what is a meaningful way to live what's a meaningful purpose
to live what is our ability to act and to do rather than just sit back and rest
in some kind of inherent goodness what is the way of of uh discovering a healthy autonomy
that then allows us to grow into a kind of dignified sense of
humanity that grows as we know learn how to uh that who we are uh has a lot to do
with how we act how we live our life um and so we try to live our life with
freedom with generosity with love with compassion with care and um and then
start inhabiting a fuller place here on this planet so I hope that these words um
make sense and appropriate for you and um if somehow it didn't quite work for
you um I hope at least that these words these ideas about dignity and value uh
is Catalyst for you to really reflect deeply for yourself how this works for
you how does uh how do you uh live with a healthy kind of self-importance
and how do you avoid unhealthy forms of self-importance and how can you tap into
your Healthy sense of self-respect in order to
support the creation of a better world for all of us starting with the people near
us so if I was off track it's your task to if you'd like to
do a course correction and find how it works for you most valuably for you and
hopefully in that process of finding that for yourself that you um have some
wonderful conversations with friends and family around this topic of dignity and
respect than self-importance so um thank you and
um I look forward to continue this series tomorrow