hello and welcome my friends to this 30 minute meditation here at inside
Meditation Center in Redwood City I'm delighted to be here with you and to
share this and I want to thank you very
much
the so this week uh the overall teachings have been about
different aspects of Love or different forms of love
and the first uh so far are can be primar can be
seen as relational forms of love when we have the first one care it's caring for
someone including oneself uh friendly or
kindness is you know something we do in relationship to others maybe to ourselves at
times and compassion is in relationship to someone who's suffering maybe ourselves
even and appreciative Joy is the joy in relationship to other people's joy and
maybe there's a secondary appreciation of our own
well-being and the third one can be in relationship to other people
but it also to understand how it works uh it's best to see understand
that we have a capacity as human beings to have a form of
love a form of warmhearted Radiance a form of
um of uh inspired appreciation Delight
um goodness that fits into the category the range of what love is but it does
not need an object it doesn't have to exist in relationship to anybody
anything it's something that can just be some people when this kind of love
will assume that it's love for the whole universe or that it's
impersonal that it's the love of the universe that we're experiencing in
ourselves and um but I think in this early Buddhist tradition that I teach
from uh it's uh it just is in our hearts
just is and it's enough we don't have to add anything more or any explanation for it
and it's remarkable how much this kind of
non kind of a non-relational love
comes together with peace it's a love that is very very
peaceful and it's not a betrayal of others it's not a rejection of others or rejection of The Importance of Being in
relationship to other people if anything it creates amazingly
significant foundation for the other forms of
love and it provides us with a certain kind of freedom to love without needing
for it to be in exchange love without needing anything in return Love without
it needing anything from anybody even a body there just
love and um and this love can be peaceful
equanimous because it's not in relationship to anything no matter what
happens uh it doesn't matter to that love that love doesn't want or not want
what is happening it doesn't reject and it doesn't accept anything that happens
it just is maybe feeling like it's there to penetrate
everything so the mystery of love the wonderful possibilities of Love include
this one love that has no object that exists in itself
so to gently close your eyes or lower your gaze if you
prefer feeling your body and adjusting your body a
bit so your body is aligned there's maybe a feeling of
physical Harmony in the position of your hands your arms your legs your
back a way in which your hands your arms your
torso your sitting bones your legs your
head all cooperate to make a
hole in harmony working together
here and in this hole in this
being to take a deep breath maybe imagining your breathing spreads to all
parts of your body and as you
exhale to to relax the whole
body letting your breathing return to normal but continue for two three
breaths to soften your
body a gentling of the
body and then as you breathe in to
feel the the activity of thinking the thinking
mind does it have any Sensations associated with it of being
activated tense their pressure or contraction
constriction so feeling that on the inhale and on the exhale
relaxing the thinking
mind maybe imagining that your thoughts float away as the Mind
softens sometimes a softening mind can feel as if the Mind becomes
larger more
spacious and then to as you breathe in to feel your heart
center to feel whatever Center where your emotional life is active
however subtle it is however big feel the place where your emotional life is
centered maybe the Heart Center maybe the
belly maybe the face or the hands
feeling it as you breathe in and lovingly
kindly relax soften on the
exhale maybe almost as if your emotions are like a gas
that when the lid is taken off the gas spreads
wide no longer contained it spreads outward so your emotions soften relax
spread
and may be there in the emotional Center or somewhere
else is there any maybe subtle not so subtle feeling of tenderness
or
warmth kindness or love
care so you're feeling the sensations of love maybe as tenderness maybe as
gentleness softness and
warmth and as you breathe as you breathe in feel
that
spot as you exhale let it be
free free of expectations ideas of what it should or
shouldn't
be let it exist there free of yourself
a place of warmth or love that exists in and of itself with
no need for an
object no need to be in relationship to anything including
yourself and as you continue
maybe can breathe with this kind
of object free
love and if it's nice supporting for you
you can very softly like a very gentle
wind say the word love as you connect to this
place just
love
e
for
for for
e
for
e for
love without an object is similar to
music traveling through the air before anybody hears
it it's
there but not yet [Music]
heard the Love is
Here radiating
outward but not yet touching
anyone
for
e
for for
and and as we come to the end of this
sitting to see or to feel if there's any degree of
peacefulness in you any place of
Peace any place of ease
where just being alive is enough quietly sitting
breathing maybe where love and
peace cannot be separated too easily they occur together
then staying close to the peace staying close to a love
which needs nothing to be any way different than what it is just
love turn your mind now out into the
world to the people you're likely to encounter today
have conversations
with to the people in your neighborhoods and places of work
and friends and
strangers see if you can gaze upon them with a peaceful love
that needs nothing for yourself or even for
them for a couple of minutes now just peaceful
love in how you take in gaze
upon this wide world
for a minute or so trusting a love which is not about
anything it's just love peaceful love
and then to get ready to end the meditation
now rising out of that love
perhaps aspiring wishing
for the welfare and happiness of
everyone May everyone be
happy May everyone be
safe may everyone be
peaceful May everyone be free
and may your ability to appreciate to
Value to care for
everyone be the
foundation for how you relate to all beings
today may all beings benefit from how you live this
day thank you for
so hello and welcome to this fifth talk on the
different aspects of Love different forms of love and today's topic is the fourth of
the Brahma viharas the Divine abodes the fourth being usually just
called equinity UPA in the in
p and um and it's many people can't quite understand often people can't
understand that equinity can be a form of love because equinity might be
closely related to indifference to not caring um but in fact this equinity
bahma bajara um is definitely comes with care definitely comes with uh
not without indifference not not aloofness or passivity
or but rather it's with a realism it's love that has a realist
realistic assessment of the situation and one of the ways that it so
it's wi it's love with wisdom and one of the ways that this
manifests itself is to recognize that sometimes
um we cannot help someone some you can have all the
compassion in the world you can have all the kindness in the world but people are
going to suffer they can make the choices they do that are going to make their life hard for
them and uh and so rather than despairing rather than giving up love
there is a love that Still Remains there is a love with this it which is aonomus
that is uh doesn't get caught in despair doesn't caught in Anger doesn't get
caught in I should I should I should be able to do something and kind of relating the you know taking
responsibility for someone else but realize everyone has a certain degree of
self-responsibility the Dignity of allowing people to have their autonomy to make their own
choices is uh one of the great forms of Freedom we give to people people who
don't have autonomy um feel somehow stuck and feel oppressed and so there's a way that you
have sooner or later we have to allow people to make their own choices and so the equinity and of this
love that can be present and they're warmhearted to people uh while not being
somehow um disp Ed by the challenge of
the person you're with and um so with this kind of
equinity love it's a love that can accompany people we're we're not rejecting people
we're still there with them and uh we still offer our care we offer our kindness we offer our presence and maybe
our presence is enough uh that we're there with our love and maybe this is
where it's a love that's not dependent on anything in the world itself it's not dependent on the
person getting better not a dependent on the person making right choices it's um it doesn't depend on
anything and uh that it's a love which is stronger than the vagaries of
change it's stronger than all the different possible directions and ways that uh things can un
fold love is there and um it's related to a form of peace I think of this
equanimous love as being a peaceful love a love which uh um is not
ruffled by what's happening in the world and it's very difficult this kind
of equinity it's a considered a very kind of uh it comes with a lot of
practice because with mindfulness practice were slowly learning how to
separate out all the
the uh the the impur impurities the dross the dust
that's in the way of our love there can be kindness that we offer but we want
something returned we want to be appreciated for our kindness we want to be thanked we want to be recognized is a
kind person get a badge for how kind we are or we want to um remember the first
time that I was sicking kind to a young woman was I was attracted to her and so
I was trying to act really kind to make an impression
and when I finished that conversation and left I felt I was a little bit sickened with myself so there's a lot of
extra stuff that came into it and uh same thing with
compassion sometimes com the the acts of compassion is more about trying to uh
take care of our own discomfort and make our own discomfort go away than it is caring for someone else appreciative Joy
can be complicated sometimes there could be joy and appreciation but maybe there's an overidentification with the
other person so we're we're kind of allowing ourselves our happiness to be dependent on the happiness of someone
else and so and so equinity is when these things have been kind of cleared out and
um and there's a very little ego very little um you know uh self-centered
desire self- centered aversion there's no self in the picture of this kind of
objectless love it's just love that's there in a peaceful way and to see it as
a strength and I kind of think of it as an impersonal strength it's it's person
person Al and that it arises from you in a certain kind of way but it's not
personal in the sense it's not something you construct or choose or do it's something you tap into something you
allow something you um can uh
feel and um and then let it be there let it be with a situation and this is
invaluable because it allows um us to love
um in difficult situations and some situations certainly
call on it and it doesn't not you know sometimes it's the best thing we can do
uh and this sometimes this some of equinity Brahma vihara is sometimes called Grand uh they usually I
originally heard it as grandmotherly love grandpar grandparents
love with the idea and I've been a single parent and single parent but a a
new parent and um and as a new parent you know every little thing was a drama
and concern and should we call the doctor or something it was such but um
uh the grandparents they took it uh a kids's grandparents took everything were much more equanimous about things they
had raised kids they'd been around little kids they knew that when a CR kid
fell on the playground and scraped their knee that uh this didn't mean calling
911 this just meant uh to be calm and loving and caring and be present for the
kid in a non-anxious way to stay equanimous the kid the kid doesn't feel
like there's the situation has gotten out of hand because the parent now is losing it the the kid feels like oh
there's stability there's there's a Known World there's a there's a safe
World here and and what's happened here is in the in the realm of the safety the safe world this what's happened to me is
painful but I'm being cared for by someone who's calm and present and certainly cares about me but um you know
offers to kiss the knee and but uh but uh is not activated not anxious not
alarmed by it so this grandpar love that
uh sometimes we don't need to be alarmed sometimes we don't need to be caught up
in what it means to us personally uh we can just have be show up with love show up with and see what
happens and see what emerges and sometimes that's what's mostly what's needed many people don't need to be
fixed many people and they don't need us to fix them many people need to be loved
need to be cared for need to be in the presence of someone who is willing to see them uh with clarity
but with a Simplicity of Love um maybe a love that doesn't need
anything in return and maybe sometimes that might seem a little passive because many
people want an exchange they want something to happen they want to know they want to get praised they want to
have something in return so it can be a little bit a little bit awkward for some people but um generally I think that if
you stay present um in a caring way and um engage in the conversation and that
um um I think that you'll win them over or you'll you'll demonstrate something
power powerful for them so um the love of
equinity and uh one of the phrases that's used for this kind of love is um
the choices you make are your own and I still love
you and um so um may we love everyone and may we
know the appropriate love uh in this different circumstances we're in uh I
think of care as being the foundational from which the other four uh grow I've
heard people who believe that equinity is the foundation equanimous love is the
foundation for the other three bum viharas that the other three arise out of this more fundamental love of
equinity so however it is your way is the right way if you're loving any one
of these five different ways and may the end of this
year be one that uh St stays you close
to your capacity for care kindness compassion passion apprec appreciation
and equinity so that you can begin this next next year having that be one of the
primary characteristics of how you go through the Year may this next
year and be one of love so I offer you these um wishes for
the new year because I won't be here next week and
um um I'm having a little vacation time with my family and um the
um and next week
the oh next week I'm going seeing who who it's going to be next week is Kim
Ellen so you're very fortunate to have Kim wonderful teacher with tremendous uh care and how
she teaches and intelligence and kindness and uh so she is wonderful to
follow up and she'll guide you into the new year I'll be back the following
week uh with the first uh day I'll be at IRC and
um and what the plan is for the beginning of the year is to um in the
last few years I've been given a long series of instructions that basic meditation instructions I did a
Sati batan Su I did the anapan Sati Su for a whole period of time uh
mindfulness four foundations of mindfulness the mindfulness of breathing and what I'd like to do this next uh
beginning of the year is to do uh instructions on concentration practice on
samade and uh samade and mindfulness I'll talk about this I don't see them as being two separate paths but they work
together but there is useful sometimes to just kind of focus on the Samari aspect of it so uh that's what I'll do
and we'll do it slowly uh over these days and weeks uh so hopefully that uh
you'll follow along well enough and uh get some benefit from this very important
topic and finally if I may mention that if any of you are interested in um
supporting IMC and IRC um there is a end of the year letter
that I wrote that you'll find on I think a link to it that you can cut and paste is on the YouTube channel uh for this
this this show this presentation and then um but also on
imc's website and um and um on the Donate
page so uh thank you for everyone for your support and for your kindness and
for your participation here for this last year and um I find it phenomenally
wonderful that we have this time together and and that we'll go forward into the New Year's so thank you very
much