hello hello and welcome everyone to this
edition of happy hour so I would like to uh invite us to
explore the practice of presence um this session and
presence with curiosity not assuming or not
forcing anything in particular but a stance of Interest
curiosity um of of being with and and let me give you a couple of pointers as
to what I mean um so so I'd like to invite us to
explore the way we pay attention in a nuanced way so for example are we paying
attention to our breath in order to make it a particular way and it can be very
very subtle very subtle what I'm inviting us to explore um are we paying attention to
our emotions to our heart space in order
to dampen it make it okay um to get rid of it rather to get rid of it is it is
there an agenda a very subtle agenda and and just to back up um perhaps a
question to sit with is there are two modes of meditation one is noticing
being with really allowing with any agenda simply
noticing and seeing what is and only through this way of being
only when we have really seen the ways we make and we we force we
don't accept reality only after we have um seeing this then then we are able to
master the second type the second type of skillful means of meditation which is
um cultivating which is for example practice of thought replacement there
are teachings in Buddhism on that but the question always comes up do should I just observe or should I change well
changing or or cultivating or shifting becomes so both of these practices are
available in the Buddhist Canon
however not until we have mastered being with we have mastered seeing clearly
With No Agenda or or seeing our agenda that oh yeah I'm paying attention to my
backache in order to make it stop like yeah I have an agenda or or My heartache so that just goes away after you've seen
the agend and softened and really released into being okay with not being
okay then it's it's wholesome it that then the mind is
trained to to shift and turn but if you try to shift and turn before you've
mastered being with it might become an aversion practice oh yeah I want to get rid of this so so
um and not to say that the cultivation
practice the cultivation of the heart in meta is um is an aversion practice I'm
not equating that at all but I'm what I'm saying is there are some
times that that um if we're not careful the practice of meta or any other
practice practice can become a big hammer can become a hammer that we're trying to get rid of uncomfortable
feelings without holding them and being okay with them first so just a very
subtle shift that that um or or subtle curiosity interest that comes up for
many practitioners and I've had this question before and I've seen it in my own practice
before so hope this makes sense
and if it doesn't don't worry drop drop all the thoughts and what is she talking
but I'll lead us into a session of of stability and presence with a sense of
openness and curiosity of of being with what is and
um and yeah we'll we'll start there and we'll see where it goes okay great all
right thank you all oh so let's begin let's formally
begin arriving arriving and landing in our
posture it's helpful to have an upright
posture it's helpful to have our feet flat on the earth firmly planted
to have our chest
open sense of openness to possibility to
life yes this too this
too and allowing inviting the body to feel itself to be felt to be
sensed from the [Music]
inside and inviting the shoulders the neck to be
soft the heart to be soft
so the posture is holding both stability Integrity with the way we sit and hold
ourselves
allall and yet there's
softness gentleness in the heart
strong back soft heart strong back strong
torso soft
belly and allowing the breath to be known the whole body the sensations of
the breath let it be
known in breath and the out breath
and notice the quality of attention the quality of
knowing is the knowing imbued with
curiosity
patience or does it have an agenda to make something go
away or make it a particular
way be curious and spacious spaciously know the quality of
knowing
be more practical how is the breath being known
can it be just as it
is e
and if thoughts are arising so many thoughts past future and
present be spaciously interested in the quality of being entangled in thoughts
are we addictively entangled are we absent mindly entangled
it's the
quality and after we know we see and
recognize inviting awareness to know the breath
simply calming soothing
breath however it chose up deeper
shallow
e
e e
notice that as we spaciously become curious about the quality of
knowing the heart and mind feel more spacious knowing itself
becomes more spacious more stable more
grounded this aspect of gentle curiosity kind gentle
interest maybe the word interest works better for some interest gentle spacious
interest imbus our whole experience with spacious gentle
interest which is an aspect of care meta
love spacious gentle and
interest spacious gentle
interest what is this Human Experience in this moment in this body
this mind and heart spacious gentle
interest without an
agenda
e
e e
if there's any experience in the emotional realm
pleas present or the body maybe pain or
discomfort can we bring spacious gentle interest
do the experience whatever experience is
present maybe just the breath is
known
e
e e
you can explore experiment with substituting gentle with kind maybe
spacious kind presence or
interest spacious friendly interest or
presence it what works best for you
let might shift and
change
e
e e
and as we turn to bring this meditation to a
close meeting meeting ourselves our
attitude with spacious friendly relaxed interest
noticing what's arising and bowing appreciating whatever
is arising knowing it and trusting there
is seeds of wholesome knowing a different kind of relationship
to ourselves and therefore to others in the world these seeds being
planted with kindness and generosity offering the goodness of our
practice to all beings may all beings everywhere be well
happy and free including
ourselves thanks everyone thank you for your
practice [Music] so this way of attending this way of
knowing this practice is very gentle seems like a
very subtle practice but it's very powerful because as we really open up to
this gentle spacious friendly presence interest curiosity is
very spacious very open we start to see we start to see
with friendliness with kindness without judgment some of the assumptions that we
have some of the attitudes we have some of the pains and aches that we have and
it shifts our relationship to them it wakes us up from being in the middle of them caught in them to a different
relationship to them this is very powerful and it it helps to hang in here
with that attitude of knowing and spacious friendly
gentle presence it's not a big bang Hammer approach it's a very
gentle um opening to and seeing things perhaps
that we usually don't see because they're so subtle in our assumptions Etc
um I wonder if some showed up for you anyway before we head to groups I want to ask
you a question I'm going to open chat and ask you was there particular
phrasing of the invitations that worked for you you were invited to shift them
and change them any of the words and if you like to put them in chat that would be nice seaing for the
community the words I had offered were spacious gentle curiosity and then later
spacious friendly interest uh kind oh great kind interest
one one of you said kind is the word that helped great and you can send them
directly to me or the whole Community if you wish kind I love Yeah bringing kindness
was very helpful for me yeah nice thank you the second vote for kind
kindness it's lovely yeah just suggestions for
spaciousness was enough with a gentle kindly
attitude another reflection what worked for me was the repetition you kept repeating
the phrases nice the repetition yeah nice one of you says as it is
great one of you says generous interpretation interest helps spur some
opening nice love it on YouTube one of our friends says
open gentle interest great the word open love it spaciousness says another fellow
practitioner I love it and I love how we've shifted and changed the words to
work for us in any way that that supported us yeah that's great and I
trust there's more that perhaps became available seeing
um yeah things that were perhaps in the midst of or something else that was
holding that just kind of got soft with this with this open spacious gentle
interest to bring more kindness stability to help ourselves support
ourselves and others so now I like to invite us to um enter into the practice
of meta M TTA in uh in small groups so the happy
hour breakout room guidance I will put it in
chat here we go and the invitation is to practice um meta for ourselves and
others mind Yul speaking and listening really treating the breakout groups as an
extension of um yeah of of the sitting
practice um embracing compassion if if any internal resistance or reaction or
discomfort comes up internal external to hold it with kindness compassion stay on
topic and the topic is this first round I'd like to invite
you to share if you would what word or phrase was helpful for you and just
offer that as support for you to be held witness nobody has to be right or wrong
there's no word or phrase that's better than any other it's all whatever works but just a way of being held witness and
the second round in the group The Invitation is if you feel like it you
can reflect out loud if there was something that became clear with this
way of seeing um so I'll share with you that a
few days ago I was practicing and and I noticed the way I was being with my breath was but it was just a little
force was a little even though I was just being with it supposedly the way it was when I shifted to The Stance of open
gentle curiosity then I notice oh there was just a tiny bit of agenda tiny little little bit to make this the
breath you know Fuller more more whatever like Ah that's not needed was
so subtle or for example seeing an attitude in the mind that um maybe the
mind and the Heart were a little cranky or a little midst of you know conversation that or something that had happened earlier like oh wow that's
still resonating not needed not needed so these very subtle things that can see
um when we open um with this ey attitude of spacious so stay on this topic so
first round sharing the words if you like the second round if there's any opening or something that showed up for
you you're welcome to share or if not you're H you're welcome to say pass or hold silent space it's okay
you don't have to talk and please take turns briefly so
everyone can speak and avoiding cross talk and giving each other advice just
oh I see the rest of it didn't get copied but that's good enough avoiding cross talk and commenting interrupting
just staying with your own practice uh Le sharing for her own sake
so be kind to yourself be kind to one another and really the breakout groups
is where the rubber meets the road in these days especially with what has been happening in this country Community is
so important uh finding um yeah finding support and even if we
don't directly offer support about the events of the world just our Our Kind
kind spacious presence is support enough so please stay to the topic all right
I'm going to create the breakout rooms
and open them take care of yourselves take care of one another here we go okay
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed
and um yeah we have time and space for Reflections questions how was the
practice today for you what what uh did you discover either in the silent
practice or in the interactive practice and also apologies I was trying to move
uh combin some of the smaller groups and got a little clunky so if I moved you a little late after you had been starting
to to speak my apologies so I hope it was more nourishing to have more people
to speak with than just one person so Audrey
please thank you Nikki um I was struck
by something that you said about I think you put it as putting aside the
agenda and I was wondering um
how that might be different from an intention yeah yeah I appreciate the
question [Music] so yeah
what um what I mean by the agenda and how it's different from an intention is
the following agenda is kind of a secret agenda somehow that we don't quite see
but it's operating and it's not necessarily very
wholesome yeah is that is that enough does that clarify what I mean
there and how it lands for you oh you're you're muted sorry let's try that
again a yet another subtlety to be uh try to notice yeah yeah yeah does it
land do you feel the difference in your heart I love it oh darn another one I have but
but they're lovely right when you expl when you see them like wow another layer of the onion this is so cool and so
interesting this being human thing right wow the Mind thing yeah yeah and I'll
tell you what one common one that happens a very common one for example
and and again we discover these different versions but one common one is know the intention the wholesome
intention might be um say there is pain in the body and my wholesome intention
is to to learn from it to be with it to cultivate kindness compassion for myself
and for others who are hurting and that's a beautiful intention right and
yet the agenda which kind of Might creep in is like you notice oh I'm
really paying attention in order to make it stop make it go away now because I
hate it and I don't want to be here and I'm afraid of being sick and being in bed for the rest of the week like oh wow
oh I see you so example thank you thank
you thanks Audrey great question
Neil oh at the very beginning you talked about
keeping track of right that when you pay attention to your breath you're not trying to change
it and I find when I pay attention to my breath it almost always
changes right and depending on where I pay attention to depends on how it
changes yeah but I'm not trying to change it
[Music] so yeah so so
yes yes and yes so this is um it is
absolutely true that we when we attend
to when we when we know the breath um and the mind and the Heart settle the
breath shifts it changes of course it does of course of course it does that is that is
different from what I'm saying I'm saying that sometimes we do pay
attention to the breath with sometimes with an agenda sometimes you know if we've had
say training and in parama to make the breath longer and subtle to really
notice the breath in a particular place but sometimes the agenda again could be
very subtle so we can have a subtle agenda so
to notice that but but that's not withstanding even if you pay attention
to the breath without any agenda of course it settles and and it get it
shifts so these these two are a bit orthogonal so so no problem here Neil So
quite I find when I pay attention to my abdomen my breath tends to be
more abdomen that's a word and when I pay attention to my chest it's the
breath tends to be higher up yeah yeah so you're saying and that just happens
of course that just happens not a problem I think what there's there's no
problems here there's no issue here they the this invitation to
pay um to pay attention to the quality of paying
attention is to uncover any subtle unhelpful agendas that they
that might be there there may be nothing right as you're reporting there may be nothing but there might be something
that's sadly shifted it's um does that make sense yes great thank you thank you
thank you and one direct message that came to
me I Nikki sometimes negative story making can be very powerful and knowing
that it's negative I can have trouble receiving it with openness
ah so so negative story making so and feel
free to to write more because I'm going to try to assume what the question is
and comment on it and if I get it wrong please correct me and and if you feel comfortable you can raise your hand but
not to put you on the spot you can um send me a message so so say I'm sitting
and and having this spacious quality of attention I'm realizing oh yeah there is a story
making it's like da da da da da da there's kind of like a negative story making and oh oh ouch can can in that
moment be either kindness you know this gentle kindness that I'm offering when
it comes to the pain of the story making it naturally becomes compassion
naturally becomes is this oh holding the gentle spacious interest becomes a
caring gentle interest can it hold the negative story in ourselves in that way
that would be the invitation another another way to work with it is this gentle spacious interest
when it notices that yeah this is this is kind of a um negative story can it
really hold it with spaciousness like it's okay yeah causes and
conditions lots of spaciousness and then this negativity in the story can soften
on its own and settle so these are a couple of ways to work with it and I
hope that this addressed the question you asking if not please thank you the
person says you are welcome so we' just got a couple more minutes
for any questions Reflections maybe anything that came up in the small groups as you practice
together going on going
toward
friend I know you thank you um so I guess I'm asking
here am I forcing am I forcing something or am I taking the opportunity so last night I
woke up uh 3 o00 and I realized I'm not going to go back to sleep I'm just
really awake um and I thought well I don't want to I
don't want to perseverate about that I I I sort of felt my body as it was and
um I thought well I'm I'm just going to use this time and I'm going to direct Goodwill
to batches of people and I really spent a long time doing that and maybe I fell
asleep at some point I don't I you know I'm not sure but it wasn't really a goal
um and that seems a reasonable thing to me to do you know with with uh an
imperfect situation at that yeah absolutely Fred this is lovely
thank you for sharing this and and the Nuance that you shared which I loved was
you know I did this practice to to you know to take advantage of this
opportunity I'm awake the middle of the night cultivating and it wasn't so much of an agenda I might fall asleep I know
I know having a light heart can be helpful but it wasn't so much like I'm doing this in order to fall asleep so
that agenda wasn't there I'm hearing this and yet what what a wholesome way
to to um to really cultivate do the cultivation practice with with this with
this Hammer of an agenda again intention you I'm going to bring back what Audrey
brought which is lovely you had the intention of of um using this time in
the mold of the night yeah I'm awake yeah what a great time to practice I do this often too I just put away sleep for
a moment like yeah I'm going to celebrate that I'm awake and and and practice and and um yeah it's not
because if there was the agenda of falling asleep then it would be like am I sleep yet I'm doing this meta thing but I'm still awake right that's the
difference that's the difference between wholesome intention and agenda and you beautifully uh brought it up with this
example they may be subtle but they're not not not subtle at all actually to me sounds very
clear thank you thank you Fred I really appreciate you sharing this yeah and I
realized I went over time so I want to thank you all for your practice for your
sharing of yourself with one another for the sake of all beings everywhere may
all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone I'm going to stop the
recording I'm going