so good evening can you hear me okay great sorry to be late
um by the end of these five week series you'll know that there's no need to wait
for anything because you can just practice but that's what you were doing very
nicely maybe I Disturbed you once many years ago when I was kind of learning this
practice I was with a teacher who said if uh if you're waiting for something to
happen you miss the boat cuz his idea was you can always just show up for now whatever that is
but I am sorry to be late and um I'm out of habit of teaching in the
evening I used to do this all the time before the pandemic and this is the first time since the pandemic that I
started this class I started teaching the evening so I just out of habit and I
was busy when at home with things so
um so here we are the second week of this intern meditation
class and uh the second week we talk about mindfulness of the body and uh some people are challenged
with their body right away when they practice meditation as sooner or later most people are challenged in some way
with discomfort in the body but even without having to practice with discomfort uh the body is this wonderful
arena for practice in fact um uh it's maybe the central kind of Arena so much
so that some people will say that the real Temple Buddhist temple or the real Monastery is your own body that uh
learning to kind of live in your body through your body and it was certainly surprise for me when I started
practicing Buddhism how much being in the body being embodied
was uh a was emphasized and um over and over again we
would uh various ways use our bodies bring attention to our bodies that uh
evoked a very strong sense of embodiment and there's even Buddhist texts that say that uh people get
enlightened through the body and the Buddha himself talked about there's no Enlightenment without mindfulness of the
body it's that important so it's not just we have to contend with it and be mindful
of it because it's challenging sometimes the body is actually quite a wonderful place to live and uh and what we'll see
through meditation practice as it develops the relation not only is the relationship the body changes but also
our inner sense of what the body is changes and it turns out that the if you
close your eyes and feel your body that whatever feeling you have of your body the experience you have of your body is
not just the physical body what the the experience of the body
you have is always a uh mediated by the thoughts you
have the Mind states you have the level of concentration you have the level of
distraction you have the level of neurosis you have the the body is very
amenable to the Mind States and what's going on in the mind and it's dramatic
how thoroughly this our experience of the body can change when the ordinary
thinking mind quiets down and um there was a time in my early
years where I I had something I called my caric body which was the body of
tension that I carry around all the time and a lot of what my sense of my body was the body was tense and held and all
that and then when I got into meditation at some point or other it was kind of like I left the car kic body behind and
my sense of body became much more harmonious radiant soft expansive
sometimes like there there was no sense of any boundaries in a way that felt really really
delicious so I say all this to you with the idea that whatever you think your body is and your experience of your body
is it probably isn't what you think um or say it differently it is
exactly what you think let's think differently and your body
experience of your body will become different as well so that was all kind of
introductory for basic uh mindfulness practice uh we are learning to bring
mindfulness to the body a form of attention where it is um we can be
present for our body and respectful caring way without being reactive to it
without shutting down or resisting what's Happ happening but learning how to bring a kind of balanced open
awareness to the to experiences in the body so that rather than Contracting or
reacting we actually are softening and relaxing with whatever is happening in
the body and um so I think what may be nice
to do is to start with an exercise that maybe will give you some feeling kind of for what mindfulness of
the body can be about before we apply it in a different way to how we do it in
meditation and that would be to first um just as you are you don't have to change
your posture if you don't want but just close your eyes in being in a comfortable
way and with your eyes closed become aware of uh your dominant
hand and feel the sensations you have in that
hand on the surface of the hand the back of the
hand the palm of the
hand and the fingers
and and it isn't so much that you're up in the control tower looking down at the
hand it's more like what is the hand's experience of
itself feeling the hand
and the sensations of your hand do they radiate or pulse
or are they warm or cold tingling
or any feelings of pleasant or unpleasant Sensations in
the hand
and if your attention is on the hand but relaxed does your awareness kind of roam
around kind of float between the different sensations of your
hand
so the hands experience of
itself so just very simple very relaxed allowing the hand to be itself allowing
the sensations to be there in a simple way and then with your eyes
closed what did you think about your hand you probably looked at your hand over your many times in your lifetime
and and maybe you've thought about the things that are wrong with your hand and maybe your fingers are too long or too
stubby too large too small maybe your have your hand maybe
has too many wrinkles or too many lines or maybe the color of the is not quite
right sure certainly you can start figuring out how something's kind of not right with your hand or maybe it's not
right now that I'm talking about it wow the
hand how' you get into with that kind of
hand so this is in this is bringing in here now thoughts and ideas judgments
about the hand some of you maybe was a bit painful I'm sorry to through it
provoke that for you but now put aside all those
thoughts and go back to feeling the Hand by
itself the hand's experience of
itself where it has no the hand itself has no idea of how a hand should
be doesn't compare itself with other hands it just it's just there sensations of the
hand and for about a minute or two to maybe accompany Your Hand by breathing
through it breathing with it allowing it to be
itself allowing it to be felt as you breathe along with
it and then you can take a few long slow deep breaths and when you're ready you
can open your
eyes so two different ways of experiencing
your hand one was the hand's experience of itself and one was through the filter of
these stories ideas I sorry I brought along about your hand that's kind of
comparative thinking and judgments of what's a good hand and what isn't a good hand or what finger should be or all
that so two different ways of experiencing the hand what did you notice about the difference between
those two were they pretty much the same you'll take it or leave them or was one how are they
different
nothing yes please when when you're asking us to the
hands experience the hands experience of itself I was mostly thinking about how
it feels how what how it feels yeah and then when you are talking
about um our judgment or comparison I'm thinking of how it looks
and was it and how did what was the what was it like for you the two different ways you prefer one over the other well
how it looks was more a negative for me uhhuh like I was thinking about the dry
spots and the whatnot you know so it wasn't a positive but the other was more
neutral uhhuh yeah great someone else
for me um one was less busy a less busy experience than the other and other was
more um involved let's say so you're more
involved with a hand and mentally involved yes
and the lad is is how I want to be that the latter is how I want to be and feel
always the latter being just feeling the hand receptive and and coexisting with
the hand as opposed to being busy and and thinking about it selecting yeah I wouldn't say it's positive or
negative um they're different uh but I prefer one feeling to the other why why
prefer one over the other well less busy and um from what I'm beginning to learn
about Buddhism is um it's a way of feeling uh Freer
great that's very nice thank you I saw another yes hi sorry I'm over here um
yeah I felt the same way that you did and that you did um I noticed uh uh it
was hard to it I had I kept toggling back to my thoughts and then to the hand and it was hard to like stay on the hand
yeah right that's what I found wasall was it even harder after I told you to think about your hand yeah well then I
was starting to judge my hand and think about what it looks like exactly rather than how it feels or well and which
which way did you prefer to be I prefer the way the way that's not judging my hand and and why would you prefer
that um because it seems much less
um yeah like busy and critical and thought oriented it's it's just being
but given how much human beings judge isn't that like what PE isn't that normal and shouldn't we be spend more
time doing that judging yeah given how much people do it already I know well it
just means it's hard I see why it's hard to to practice to do the practice
because of that mind exactly yeah thank
you so yeah one more here
um with the feeling of the hand I I felt um life in me I
felt alive CU it was full of Sensations and
energy and I guess the other one I I forget that I'm alive cuz I'm so busy
thinking about the spots and so forth great very nice yeah forget you're alive
and um some sometimes in spiritual circles they say some people are dead before they die
because they're so disconnected from themselves they don't feel their aliveness they're lost in their
thoughts so that exercise was meant to offer you um a contrast that maybe you
can find useful as you do this mindfulness practice that as we're doing mindfulness of the body we're being
mindful of what's happening in the body the way we felt the just felt the hand
the hand's feeling of it self very simple and there not a time to
judge or make comparisons or react or um we do that plenty but that often is not
really so connected to reality or it's not so useful and and it's often painful
and often when it gets accumulated or gets more important things in the hand
it can be really really painful that to do that and we don't only do it to ourselves unfortunately we do it towards
others as well we we judge them for their hands or their thing or whatever and um and uh and then because we do
that as Society we do it to each other it reinforces us doing it to ourselves and feeling bad about ourselves
identifying ourselves you know I'm this kind of person and if we get busy in the
mind and thinking and it can be very debilitating to spend a lot of time in
those thoughts spinning mindfulness of the body is to
uh is to drop out of that mind and allow ourselves to feel the body on its own
terms From the Inside Out free of the concepts free of the judgments that we
might normally have in everyday life and then in a few weeks we'll talk about mindfulness of thinking that will
show a different way of how to be mindful of those kinds of thoughts without being caught by them but for now
mindfulness of the body this is closer to what mindfulness of the body is the hand for most of you probably was a
relatively neutral place to feel some of you might have arthritis or your it
might hurt but sometimes in meditation what we're feeling doesn't feel Pleasant
or neutral it might actually be unpleasant might be painful even and when we do mindfulness
meditation you're always welcome to change your posture if you're you feel
your posture is uncomfortable and you're better off changing but if all you do is
change every time that you're uncomfortable you're short changing the power of the and learning what the
meditation is about when you feel like you your morale is good feel like it's appropriate the idea is to within reason
to uh also practice with the discomfort of the body and and and uh and the way to feel
the discomfort of the body is in the same way that you felt the hand and uh and so that's hard to do
because when it's uncomfortable then the thinking mind kicks up and oh no I need to go to the doctor and probably need to
have the my toes amputated and and then how am I going to play you know you know
soccer and things will be hard and you know I should probably I'm getting stressed now and I should probably do
I've heard the meditation can help me calm down and then you realize you're meditating you know the Mind spins out
right so easily but uh but uh the idea is to learn how not to give in that
thinking mind and being able to feel the body on its own terms and I like to
believe that that's a very respectful thing to do for your body that your body is not just I said like I said before
just a hunk of Flesh it's not just a physical thing the body is an integral part of who you are it's part of your
intelligence your creativity your the body is an antenna that picks up the environment picks up what's going on
inside of you you need your body your body body is dynamic and engaged in life
and the process of living in a very important way and to leave the body
behind by going up into judgments and thinking and fantasy uh comparative
thinking uh is kind of to disconnect and it's actually a little bit disrespectful for the innateness or
the the the intercol aspect of this body so to drop down and feel the body
and even if it's uncomfortable the art of it is to how to discover okay my knee
aches now how can I just let the attention just be there as if it's not a problem it's just something to be
felt if you do feel it's a problem and feel like you're getting antsy or feel like something is wrong or you're afraid
by all means move your move your posture change what you're doing but sooner or
later what happens with people meditate they realize that they're better off not moving so much they real realize that
some of the reason they move is because of impatience restlessness because they
feel like they have to call 911 because their their foot is falling asleep and
there's all this excitement um but to just begin to relax and Trust the body
and let the body feel itself um all kinds of things open up that are really
really useful so the way that we practice uh
mindfulness is that here at IMC the way I teach is that the the default the
center center of the meditation practice is the breathing breathing doesn't work
for everyone so it doesn't have to be the center some people let the whole body be the center they just feel their
whole body like you felt the hand and that's the grounding that's how they Center themselves mindfully in the
present moment there's other ways but for now I'll leave those two but here we might emphasize the breathing if it
works and so breathing is a wonderful object for many people it's the the the
rhythm of breathing is kind of soothing if you if you settle into breathing and your breathing gets starts getting a
little bit longer because you're just kind of relaxing with it the longer the exhale um the more it seems to relax
much of our nervous system and in fact some people who are OV excited or panic
attack people will say just breathe deeply and sometimes that can make a big difference to Cal people
down and um and there's something about the rhythm of breathing that for some
people makes it easier to stay present something which doesn't move a lot in the Rhythm it's harder for the mind to
stay focused on and so to ride the waves of the breath coming and going it's almost like your maybe attention is like
a ball floating on the waves in the ocean and just kind of resting with it and following it and then as we practice
more and more that uh we start being able to kind of get um more more settled
on the breathing and the mind wanders off less and that has a lot of benefits because then the mind's not thinking so
much it's not spinning out in these crazy thoughts that I can have that are often
debilitating however in our so some places in some meditation uh Traditions
uh like in Zen that I practiced first uh the all we were told to do was to be
with a breath that was like the be all and end all and so every time the Mind wandered off we came back to the breath
Wonder off came back try to stay there with the breathing when I learn mindfulness I learn a different way and
that is uh when there's something that's compelling something stronger than the
breathing we learn to make that the object of attention and so whatever it might be
and we'll talk more about this as we go through these weeks but for now it' be the body so if the experience some
experience in the body is more compelling than the breathing and compelling means that it's tugging at
attention pay attention to me you know it's and sometimes it's just a lot of energy in the body sometimes it's
something very pleasant sometimes it's unpleasant but something in the body the the then what we do is we stop
focusing on the breathing and let the attention go to this place in the body where that compelling sensation
is and then you would feel it the way you would feel that hand get to know it explore it let the
attention as if your awareness is a kind of kind of very relaxed thing that kind of floats around in that area where that
is you just feel it feel how it's How the body experiences that as you do that
you might notice that uh you're reacting to it or you're judging it or you have ideas
about it this shouldn't be there or this is great and um those are different
those are the ideas so that's how the mind gets busy um and that's extra so the of
course the mind will do that it's not like you can just turn that the thinking switch off but what we're trying to do
is not to live in those thoughts let them recede to the background and live in the lived
experience of the body of the area you're feeling until you feel more or less
that maybe it's just three breaths that's enough just feel it with three breaths four breaths feel it for a while
sometimes you might want to feel something for five minutes if it's really compelling if you find hard to stay like
say your knee aches and it's hard to stay there some people find it helpful to imagine their breathing with or
breathing through that place in the body and so the rhythm of breathing kind of gets
related to that that part of the body and it's easy to stay there to feel it be with it sense
it after it's been acknowledged well enough or no longer compelling then the
practice is to come back to your breathing and continue with the breathing relax with the breathing relax
on the exhale let go of your thinking mind on the exhale and then um and then
uh until something else arises and um and so it's kind of like
uh the the breathing's at the center something happens you go out and visit it and then you come back to the
center something else happens you go out to it and you come back to the center
without any protests without any complaining without just there just one more thing to pay attention to it has
just as much value to feel um you know a warm tingling in your chest as it is to
feel the breathing it's just the next thing to be aware of and and um and to learn how to be
present in a non-reactive non-judgmental way for your body is a
foundation for how we're going to be mindful of emotions how we're going to be mindful of thinking how we bring a
kind of very different kind of meditative or wise attention to the
present moment experience that is not being where attention is not being mediated or filtered through our stories
ideas our memories our judgments all kinds of things that we often get in the way and make things much more
complicated than need to be so that makes sense somewhat do you have any
questions about that or anything you want to before we do a
meditation is that okay you ready so we've been sitting now for a while um
well meditate for a little while so you probably a good idea to stand up and stretch and just kind of uh get
refreshed in your body for a minute or
so
for
this way of including the body as part of the meditation by when it speaks when the
body speaks up and it's more compelling the sensations in your body you turn to it and take that in in
this meditative way over time uh over months and years uh sooner or later your
whole body gets met your whole body gets filled with awareness and attention and
slowly the body wakes up more and more and I think I was very disconnected to my body when I started meditating and
slowly this practice kind of brought my body More Alive more sensitive and so it
became this marvelous field of attention and information and and uh refuge for me
so um so you might also find this way that there a slow process of waking up
maybe most of you feel you're already in your body just fine but uh probably if you do this for a while you'll you the
contrast will be quite strong and just wow this is like really now it's I was
alive before two-dimensionally now it's three-dimensionally or something
so assuming a meditation posture and
and gently closing your
eyes it's good to take a few minutes at the beginning to prepare yourself for
meditation and one way to do that is to take few long slow deep
breaths and as you exhale make a long exhale where you relax in your
body and then letting your breathing return to
normal and continue preparing for the meditation by with a normal
breath with each exhale for a while relaxing the holding in your body
tension in your body some people like to do it systematically starting at maybe the
forehead and the eyes feel feeling what's there on the
inhale and softening the forehead and eyes as you
exhale on the exhale letting the muscles of the face Fall Away From The
Bone
on the inhale feeling your
shoulders on the exhale relaxing the shoulders
softening
on the inhale feeling your
belly and the exhale softening the
belly
on the inhale feeling some Global sense of your whole
body whatever way is easy and on the
exhale releasing the
body relaxing any way in which you brace yourself against life
and now become aware of the part of your body where you usually experience your
breathing some people feel it more in the belly moving some people the
chest some people the air going in and out through the
nostrils some people will feel all of them together in some Global
way but whatever way that you whatever way where you feel the body's experience
of breathing in that
area let it be like the exercise with a
hand to allow the body to have its own experience of
breathing without any shoulds or the way it's supposed to
be doesn't matter if it's comfortable or uncomfortable for the purposes of the
meditation when we Mak room for the body to experience itself breathing
it's kind of like a gift we give the body the gift of it getting to know
itself to know it to feel itself to make room to be
itself make room for the body to feel it feel itself
breathing and you floating on that experience
then I'm going to ask you to shift your attention someplace else and see if you can do it in a calm
way gentle slow so move your attention to some
place in your body that's not your breathing that's a little bit
compelling maybe not the most compelling but a little bit some other
sensation in your body place in your body and like we did with a
hand let's let that part of the body know
itself take time to know
it to feel
it
and then letting go of that place and returning to
breathing feeling the physical sensations of your
body as you your body
breathes
if there's a lot of thinking on the
exhale Relax The Thinking mind any tension or tightness associated
with thinking let it
soften and then turn to
breathing and now move your attention attention to what might be the strongest
sensation in your
body and for a few moments even if it's painful let it be let it be
itself and let the body experience it from the
inside if it helps you can breathe with it or breathe through
it
giving the body the gift of feeling itself without the filter of your
reactions and thoughts
judgments it's an exercise of seeing how simple
you can be to Simply feel the body in its own
terms
for
and then returning to your breathing letting that sensation reced
to the background as you enter into the body body's experience of
breathing knowing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out if the mind is thinking a lot maybe every
exhale letting go of your
thoughts letting the thinking mind be
quieter
maybe the place in your body is slightly
different where you feel the inhale and where you feel the
exhale
and if you find yourself easily distracted from doing
this there's nothing wrong with
that we're doing mindfulness practice it's all about just knowing
what's happening so knowing oh lot of
thinking and then when you're ready Begin Again with your
breathing
for
and then to end this meditation you can take a few long slow deep breaths
again and feel your body more fully more
widely feel the contact of your body against your cushion and chair and
floor and when you're
ready you can open your eyes
[Music]
so there's a very strong almost addictive force that exists in many
people's minds to be thinking about all kinds of things and sometimes our thinking has Us
by the nose and leads us around and directs us what we do and think and makes us Restless or want things to be
different or whatever it can take a while for the thinking mind to discover that it's okay
it's safe to be present to be relaxed it doesn't have to be always busy and doing and spinning things and that's a
wonderful thing gift to give to the thinking mind that it can finally trust
doesn't have to figure out doesn't have to plan all the time it doesn't have to defend it doesn't have to review and
figure out what went wrong or something it's okay to just be here present in a
very simple way and um and one of the AIDS to this
kind of Simplicity of being is this mindfulness of the body so it's
a wonderful area to practice in and what we're learning also is this
um way to actually whatever is happening in the moment to bring attention to
it and um and so right now we're keeping it simple just breathing and the
body with next week we'll talk about now including emotions in it and then thinking and then the whole world in it
and it so that there's a kind of a different quality of attention that goes to being present in this world to
meeting this world than it's possible if we're always living in our thoughts our
judgments our reactivity to it there's a whole almost like we're tapping into a
different capacity of intelligence different capacity of creativity of
Freedom uh by not being so glued to the reactive mind
the thinking mind that's spinning out and that's a slow process and that's one of the reasons why you want to stay slow
in this course just breathing the first week now just the body keep it that
simple we know you're thinking a lot we know there's a lot of emotions and stuff going on and um and that so that's
coming but right now I want to keep it simple just to get a sense develop the capacity to be in your body more and
more so um do you have any I was that like was that interesting for any of you
or revealing anything for you or challenging in any way or how was
it sorry I'm talking a lot because I'm new to this process but um can you hear
it okay um I started feeling sad because
my stomach hurts a lot and um and I'm even kind of CR cying
a little bit right now and I think um I am not comfortable sitting with
like I just cuz I there's nothing I can do about it like I've tried different things and it still hurts so being like
sitting here and being with it kind of made me angry a little bit and then I
felt yeah I wanted to just get up and start walking around or do something or lay down or do something to because I
know there's nothing I can do about it so it's been going on for so long yeah yeah well certainly you're welcome to
get up and walk around you if you feel that's better for you um and the uh but
there might be an interesting to discover a different way to be with discomfort right when you can't do
anything about it um uh even though you can't do anything about it you are doing
something in relationship to it you were not liking it I was not liking it yeah
and and probably a serious of other things hating it afraid of it um
something so you doing something anyway and some of those things are the way
gentleman talked about being busy some of those things are the reactivity of the mind which is
extra and it's a marvelous thing that can happen for the body for the pain
when we can be with pain without any reactivity it's just pain and what it
actually when when then the mind fence gets really strong around something we call pain it's actually starts stops
being pain and how does that happen uh uh pain is uh not a singular thing it's
not like a it's a composite pain is a composite that's made up of many
factors and um and those can can shift very very quickly as some of the
multiple factors get diminished or shift and change so just spend time with
non-reactive attention to pain like in their belly is a gift to the belly because it stops it's it start it
start becomes very different but it's a it's a challenging thing to learn because of how strong The Habit is of
reacting right and then I I like kind of wince because it hurts so much so yeah well I don't yeah I don't know how bad
it actually is I mean it's not it's just it's not that bad it's just it's chronic and it's sort of uncomfortable yeah yes
so but um so I don't know I can't tell you for your condition you know so it
might be it might be laying down I don't know what it is you're always welcome to stand stand up but I think ve I very
very often people who learn mindfulness learn how useful it is to be present
with acute pain with nonreactivity and in meditation you have a choice to get
up and leave always a day will come where you don't have that choice so meditation is the laboratory
you're discovering how to be with challenging situations very challenging life situations in a new way and so the
idea is to when you feel ready to learn to ride the edge of where you're where
you're comfortable to be with things like this and see if you can find a different way and um and not a few times
people discover like with pain it's not just a pain there but because we're reacting there's tension we build up
around it and that tension begins to dissipate and lo and behold the pain hasn't changed
but it's more manageable there's something about the tension that created some of that reactivity so to just hold it and be
with it so I get migraine sometimes and uh and uh I'm kind of
miserable until I go to bed and I put the the sheets over my head lay on my
side and I can then I and then I'm home and I'm happy because then what I do is
I I've learned to bring my attention right into the middle of the P most intense pain and if I put my attention
right into intense pain it stops being pain and then I can my breathing relaxes and I'm just there with it and and I'm
comfortable but I have to keep doing it because if I get distracted and start thinking again and leave that spot oh it
starts hurting again it's fascinating and for me I feel so lucky to have this capacity to just go there and be with it
and hold it and this kind of way so it's not easy to do what I'm saying but that's kind of the direction we're
pointing to here thank
you behind you MRA and then this gentleman here first and then right behind you in in the chair there oh yeah
so I have a um thank you for that that helped address a lot of what was what my
experience was but I'm curious about a different situation which is more than
actual posture of sitting um because it's not chronic and it will go away if I move yeah uh and
I'm just curious some of what you described I experienced which was kind of like the hand exercise some if I'm
thinking about it as pain and uncomfortable and I just want to move it just gets
worse but if I can pay attention to the details of what it feels like there feels like there's some stretching or
some pressure or you know it it has a little bit more physical characteristic
rather than the interpretation of pain but I'm just curious about when it's about sitting I mean like you said I can
get up and walk away um so how do I how do I how do I sit with that do I just
continue to sit and let it kind of practice the tolerance of the discomfort
or the shifting of the way I'm being with the discomfort well two things uh
it's good to have a good meditation posture so to get some really good instructions from a yoga teacher and
sometimes I give much more instructions on posture I love to do that and um and
uh so you're aligned and so you're not you're not uncomfortable because of the posture I mean a little bit you have to
because the money muscles are stretching and getting tired and some of it's just part of a yoga posture you're getting
used to but um um so it's good to kind of find a
good posture and and people who meditate regularly slowly slowly slowly they find their posture and it's really wonderful
to as a teacher to watch people come as a new newbie and you watch over a course of a year their body changes and they
get sometimes you see oh now they have a yogic body just from sitting some ever
in in in uh you know perceptible shifts begin happening and they kind of find
okay like this like this like this and then after a year like wow now the person's really there you can and you
feel the whole posture is like I'm they're here in a nice way so it's it's slowly people tend to learn it and
develop it and then um and then
uh um um so the idea is as I said before
that it is useful within reason to practice with
discomfort and um but you you only should do it when you feel like you want
to do it you know you you know I see you it's been I've been meditating now for a few
months and every time I have you know uh a little kind of ache I move and I move
and I move and I seem like moving every two minutes but you know I don't think I need to move as much you know I'm
interested in this thing Gil says that maybe you should learn a different way to be with discomfort now today the discomfort is
not so bad so today I have this morale now today I slept well I Hade a good
meal I'm a little enthusiastic I want to explore this okay let's let's try to explore it
and then you okay that's enough and then next day a little bit longer and slowly you learn about it so
I'm kind of making this so it's up to you so when you feel you're ready for the learning for the practicing and
training with the discomfort do it but you don't have to it's not like and see and Zen you you could weren't allowed to
move so I know about don't move just sit with the pain and
there sometimes we had literally had to sit for hours I think the longest was like three or four hours so it's a
little bit masochistic and um so we that's not
that's not our our school but this so this is may be a surprise for some of you that I'm talking about this because
meditation is associated with just relax get some calm relax feel good float in a
cloud that's good that's that's great but we're doing something much more important in addition something much
more useful here and that is we're learning how to meet whatever challenges life brings us and find a way to be with
it so we're not reactive so we have a wise way and underscore the word wise a
wise way to stay with it learn from it find out what's going on and maybe hold
it with compassion hold it with Equanimity hold it calmly and that's a
phenomenal life skill to learn because you might have a situation where the
doctors have no pain medication for you it's okay I know what I've I've done this before and I I you know I'm I'll
practice now with this or it's not physical pain but maybe it's emotional pain and so what what I like to say is
that you know Buddhism is a lot about learning to be free but if you're only free when you're
comfortable you're not really free so you have to learn at sooner or later
how to work with discomfort and I'm saying it's up to you when that point
is make sense does that give you enough does that answer your question okay it
does okay thank you um so just want to express some
appreciation for the the teaching tonight and the chance to kind of practice can you lift it a little louder
for me you know I can also talk louder I just have a very quiet voice yeah yeah yeah I um if I put in my hearings AIDS
in in then I even speak softer because I hear my voice and so I S I have such a
soft voice to begin with so I apologize if some of you are straining we could turn my voice up my things up too but is
is this okay you okay um so yeah I appreciated the instruction to kind of
stay with the breath and then go off and visit different Sensations that were compelling yeah and I noticed um and
this tends to happen when I sit I all of a sudden like an itch arises right it's
that wasn't there a second ago and I've noticed too like if I kind of let myself
attend to that and I kind of scratch it then another one will pop up somewhere else right so it's this like funny thing
that happens and so I just kind of did that practice stayed with it and it
began to kind of transform and it actually became this like really marvelous thing and it was
like it's kind of odd experience but it felt almost like a like a constellation
of stars or something like this Sensation that was just arising and it was able to kind of hold it and very
different relationship to it which I hadn't really experienced before so just wanted to share that and say thank you
yeah that wonderful that's very nice that's a that's a way that this can unfold in meditation stars and
constellations and sparkles and lots of space and openness and it's like you've entered into a new universe around the
body so what I said in the beginning we have you know the the body shifts and
changes depending on the state of the mind that's what happened to you your sense of the body changed I mean your
your raw physical body didn't change probably much except maybe stress hormones disappeared in that state but
um but the way we experience the body changes dramatically and that's what you had was one example of that so that was
great it was lovely to hear that report you anything else I questions
or so if I'll tell you a
story that um you might know this is a famous Buddhist kind of par uh kind of
simile so there was um the Buddha was sitting with a group people like you
and and he asked them the question he said if an Archer comes along with bow
and arrow and um strikes you you know shoots you with an arrow will that hurt
you and they said yeah and uh and he said well if he comes
along and shoots you with a second Arrow will that hurt even more oh yeah getting two arrows hurts more than having
one and then the Buddha said well uh life brings you the first
Arrow you shoot the second an arrow so for example if I'm walking down
the sidewalk here and I trip and maybe fall and scrape my knee that's just life
that happens that's the first Arrow but it's right in front of IMC and you all see me and I'm a mindfulness teacher
who's supposed to pay attention be present this is like an embarrassment I'm just like a mess and this is I'm
afraid I'm angry angry that I got seen angry at you for seeing me
I'm just shooting arrows left and right the fir sometimes you just leave
let it be the first Arrow oh I tripped I scraped my knee it hurts I don't have to
add anything to it anymore we add a lot of second arrows so
when there's sitting in meditation sometimes you can see it there's something happens a meditation that's
uncomfortable maybe pain in the body and then you might see the second arrows
maybe you're upset with yourself maybe you're upset with the teacher giving
those instructions maybe you um tighten up maybe you you know shut down maybe
you spin out or something or criticize yourself I must be doing it wrong there's all these second arrows we give
and part of what we're doing here is learning to be present in a very simple way the simpler we can have the presence
the more we start noticing what we do that's extra the second arrows the
reactivity and for now it's very important that you don't
see that there's it's best not to ever think that you're meditating wrong I
want to just like this is like the meditation free zone you can't do it
wrong so if you have a second Arrow
smile I saw that I'm learning the tricks of the mind I'm learning what my mind
does this is really important to see you notice you see what's happening
then you're doing the practice this I've said before last week too if you get distracted a lot in
thought during meditation um that's not wrong what you do then is you see that's
the case look I'm thinking a lot oh no but but you're not supposed to think in meditation wait a minute I think that's
a second Arrow let's just start again and one of the SK one of the
little tricks of doing this kind of meditation practice when in doubt just start
over start fresh just in a moment's notice just okay that did I don't know what to do that's lost I boy I had a lot
of second arrows there and where do I find my way back okay just take a deep breath and just start over again let if
from just beginning so try not to think that you're doing it wrong if you have
thoughts that you're doing it wrong you're still not wrong it's just one more thing to see oh
look at that I'm thinking those thoughts I'm thinking those thoughts and having that kind of
attitude just let it be it's good to see it it's important to see it that's the
path to Freedom start seeing what goes on in the mind in the heart and the body and then learning to come back and be
really simple with everything and right now the idea is to be really simple with breathing which is a bodily experience
it's just not just one embodied experience among others uh and very simple with other
sensations of your of your in your body and um and maybe in for this next
week if there's some uncomfortable Body Sensations that you
might have and you feel some curiosity about practicing with it you might discover
that um interesting to bring attention and feel it really really simple the discomfort see what see if you can just
hold the discomfort as if it has permission to be there
forever as if do hopefully it doesn't stay forever but but you kind of that
attitude and then just be with it breathe with it a little bit maybe go back to your breathing and then if
becomes back go back to it and just be and see and see how simple you can be
and see what shifts and changes see what second arrows you don't add see what extra layers of maybe tension or
contraction you stop doing that maybe you didn't even know you're doing until you started to learn to this radical
Simplicity of just being with it it's a life skill which will serve you really really well in many many
situations and um and sometimes someday it's not just because uh it's
for your sake but some someday it might be because it's time to help someone
else but you have your own challenge with your own pain and difficulty but now you know how to hold it so it
doesn't get in way of being able to be of help in the world it's it's a radical thing we're learning to do
here so um mindfulness of the body if you want to EXP explore this
topic more over the course of this week I mean certainly just make your body be the book some people ask me sometimes
and maybe I irritate them but by my answer they asked me uh do you have a
book to recommend on Buddhism or book to I should read and I said yeah um the
book of your body everything you need to know about Buddhism is found by attention to the body it's that profound
and I have a little bit of maybe credibility in saying that
because I have a PhD in Buddhism so I should know that this is
where you find it not there in those books and so uh this is the
place and um and the um so you know and uh and also it might
shift your relationship to your body I think you all know that uh in this country of ours maybe much of the world
but certainly in this country the amount of suffering people feel have experienc
about their body you know their body is too much this not enough that so I mean the
amount of suffering goes on around is huge huge a lot of it has to do with
comparative thinking reactive thinking judgments uh acquired ideas that we take
in from outside internalize them it's it's and then people make a fortune on
our on our you know you know on these crazy ideas we have about the body that were sometimes told it's supposed to be
this way and the more they can get you upset about your body the more they can sell you or
something there is maybe none of you are doing this but it's a lot going on so this shift from the thinking comparing
judging mind to just feeling allowing your body life allowing it to be
itself your body is your body is probably a lot happier usually than you
are and your body is probably a lot happier with itself than you
are give your body the gift of letting it be itself without the burden of all
these heavy judgments that people have it's a radical thing and in some
ways it's may be a political thing to do that in this country because of so
much you know the society is so complicated around it the the good good
politics to just trust your body and feel it and be with it in a simple way
learn that and you might save a lot of
money and a lot of anxiety or something angst your body will love you the bodies
are great and it's one of the I think people who do this practice really come
to to uh generally come to treasure their body love their body treated with a lot of respect and care and and
becomes a really good partnership though with any partnership sometimes there's
challenges so um thank you for being here and and um sorry to being late I'll try
not to do it again uh next week I'll be here but I'm coming up from Santa Cruz
to next week because I'm teaching a retreat next week down there so you know we know Highway 17 is notorious with
problems so I'll call someone here if I'm stuck in traffic but I'm planning to come over the hill early enough to be
here in time and um or if I really can't make it then maybe Tom Tom teaches this
course also sometimes so maybe you can fill in for me but um so thank you and I'm happy to
stay here a little bit if any of you have any questions you want to ask me or say anything and um thank you for being
here