so uh so welcome welcome folks good to
uh good to be with you um looking forward to sitting together practicing
in one way or another so
um yeah please find your posture
sitting standing L town
and if there's anything that feels good about
stopping anything that feels good about Stillness just uh anchor there
doesn't need to be intense and the pleasantness can coexist
with a lot of unpleasantness but anchor to whatever feels
good in the
stopping
e e
to be uh drawn into concerns is
natural and pleasantness Mild pleasantness doesn't
feel urgent at all and so it feels irresponsible not
to worry or
plan tie up the loose ends of the day
week one facet of equinity is just um capacity to
stay with what feels less urgent
e
e e
maybe there's something soothing about uh your
breathing deliciousness of getting oxygen when you need it
the Ripple of relaxation as we uh exhale what's been
used up
Sati patana says that we uh establish mindfulness
by placing down greed and
distress with respect to the world
in this sense mindfulness is uh
built on the foundation of U something like
equinity we can't turn in words
if we are trying to rearrange the
external we can't truly turn inwards if we're turning inwards in order to
rearrange the
external
for e
we get more comfortable just offering our heart up to the moment
trusting that no matter what happens it'll be
Dharma
e
e e
maybe it feels right to uh open
up the uh aperture of a
attention let me see how much the uh attent can relax around all
objects the attention [Music] can build and make
objects or substanti than they
are the object becomes denser
weightier in our practice we uh
making what uh was Heavy light
in the world it's a little
quieter the awareness a little
louder
e
e e
maybe even your autobiograph becomes a little
light run through with a
space equin allows the attention to uh to move without snagging
on
objects snagging the way a hangnail gets snagged on fabric
just keep
opening
e
e e
[Music]
e
okay I see a comment no I my um that was just hair a cat did not scratch my
farhead a cat has scratched my
forehead that's true
uh I just don't fully understand the difference between cats and
dogs and a dog that you love you just get up get up close Head to Head kind of
thing that apparently is not how one expresses feline love and you might get a claw to the
forehead as I did
um but it was my fault was my fault I should have read the signals
better um it's a little little bit non
seiter on the Dharma theme but this is a
slow process of getting to know each other and so all of that is
true okay me cord that wasn't recorded at
least the audio thank
goodness um okay
so um this
world this world is um is complicated
and we we grapple with it as best we
can and uh the systems we we live in
environmental economic systems they're just staggeringly
complex Economist once said to me like no one understands the economy
and our [Music] brain you know this is um one
uh researcher wolf singer the more we learn about the brain he says the more
abstract will the descriptions become because we shall be dealing with increasingly
complex Assemblies of neurons and the spaciotemporal patterns generated by
these assemblies these patterns are with all likelihood
non-stationary and best described as Dynamic trajectories of a highly
nonlinear system we'll have to consider more than one bra more more and more
that the brain is a member of a sociocultural network and that some of the phenomena
that seem to be so difficult to explain in pure neuronal terms will have their
explanation only when considering interactions among brains or networks of
brains many of the constructs that are so difficult to relate to brain processes like value systems
Consciousness intentionality and so forth have only come into the world
because brains mirror themselves reciprocally in other brains and assign
properties to then uh the then gained experiences obviously the complexity of
these networks formed by interacting brains by far exceeds the complexity of
individual brains and
so even our own life in certain respects is
beyond our comprehension we um we desperately try
to explain our life you know to explain how we got to be the way we are
to explain why we love or do not love another person to explain a mood a
momentary why we're feeling like this right now to explain our moral commitments our
beliefs why we value this or that we give a lot of um a lot of
reasons for what we do and say and believe but those
reasons may not be the actual causes of our actions our words our
beliefs we tell stories we tell the story of our life we tell heroic stories
or tragic stories or we tell stories of
redemption but every story is ambivalent about
truth and what we call my life is much
more mysterious than we tend to
believe and then there's this universe you know
this is from Co cosmological science um we can currently see a sphere
around us extending 46 billion light years in all directions known as the observable
universe light and galaxies beyond the sphere haven't yet had time to reach
us on our leading cosmological theory the rate at which new Galaxy
become visible will Decline and those currently more than 63 billion light
years away will never become visible from the earth we could call this the
region within this distance the eventually observable
universe accelerating expansion also puts a limit on what we can ever affect
if today you shine a ray of light out into space it could reach any Galaxy
that's currently less than 16 billion light years away but galaxies further
than this are being pulled away so quickly that neither light nor anything
else we might send could ever affect
them there's something beyond the eventual even the eventually observable
universe you know and I read that because it's like just a Marvel at how much we'll never
know it's so complex and it's so
simple a yogi walked in to a a one-on-one practice meeting uh with me
on a recent Retreat and um
said something like um it's so
simple there's just love and
heartbreak you know sometimes people speak about insights but this Yogi was
speaking from the inside
and the the budda said um if we if we focus on the wrong categories of
experience the wrong distinctions really we spin out we get confused we cause
trouble praise and blame good and evil self and other if we get too fixated
it's not the right place for our energy and so he offered a much more
fundamental distinction that simplifies is
everything suffering and peace the highest
happiness and maybe love and heartbreak is kind of variation on that
theme and perhaps for for you love and heartbreak is a
useful framework for understanding your life simply it of
it there was so you know so much love in
the beginning as a baby the soft animal of uh your body loving what it
loves and all that love all that need almost
instantaneously running into heartbreak the world has and will disappoint us at
a fundamental level whatever love we've received it's
involved heartbreak whatever love we get it will involve more
heartbreak but we try to grow up perhaps Master the kind of dialectic of um of
love and heartbreak we grow up and we try to figure out what we love or what's actually
worthy of our love and maybe we we find someone to
love and someone uh with whom we dramatize the
cycles of giving and receiving L Cohen said um said
it doesn't um matter whether we found ourselves in the loneliness of
separation or the vertigo of Union everyone finally learns there
ain't no cure for love and maybe that's a
way of saying that something like we can't not love
we must love but that love entails
heartbreak so there's no
cure but we can learn to love and all
let thou the heart to break in a way that's uh imbued with credible
Grace to let that become uh consolidate wisdom
compassion we um must perceive and stand guard over the love and the Heartbreak
of people we care about to actually stand guard to
protect their love to honor their
heartbreak if we cannot perceive the love the Heartbreak of
others our our care for them our own love for them will feel
misat tuned might even be
alienating and we have uh we have goals and
aspirations we try in our lives we try in our work we try in relationship ships
we try in our spiritual practice
and all that trying all that trying is
okay but it better not lose sight of
love and better not forget
heartbreak we grow up and um and
discover to our amazement we should have known but to our amazement that
we must uh yield our life back to
time it's more heartbreak more
love so I offer this uh for your consideration
please uh pick up what's useful leave the rest
behind Okay
um so um so thank you for your attention and
um yeah this is uh the last meeting of
uh this year next week Christmas we won't have class Christmas and then uh
I'll be back January uh January 1st New Year New
Year's Day and um yeah thank you you know
certain Wednesdays we started in uh
April I think and uh we'll keep going hasn't been cancelled
yet um yeah I'm grateful for your uh support and um the Dharma solidarity
over the course of the year so I wish you uh wish you all all well and
um uh I'm going to go check the chat and see if there were any consequences to my
cat comments not trying to add to the divisiveness of our polarized country
with more dog cat dichotomies but uh yeah I wish you uh
wish you all well see you somewhere on the darh campus yeah okay