so hello everyone and Welcome to our morning meditation for some of you it's the
afternoon or maybe the evening and
um there's a wonderful saying about the path of meditation
mindfulness meditation that uh can be very useful to keep in
mind and that is um the saying the fastest
way to go from point A to point B is to be fully at Point
a so of course that doesn't relate not true everywhere but it's something very
true about the practice of meditation it's kind of like
um um little bit like sometimes trying to fall asleep and the more we try to fall
asleep the the harder it is to fall asleep and there's something about
letting go of the effort to try to go to sleep and just allow oneself to be as one is that sometimes creates the better
conditions to fall asleep or to relax certainly we can do some relaxation
willfully but uh there's also a deeper relaxation that comes when we just are
present with ourselves as we are without adding anything without picking anything
up without reac acting and the whole system physical
mental emotional system sometimes can just settle in that process and the fastest
way to settle is just to be relaxed about how you are and so um the analogy the Buddha
gives is uh uh if you stay in the middle of a river if
you're kind of floating in the river and don't grab the band branches don't try to row
upstreams um and just allow your don't try to and don't kind of like you know
sink but stay floating um just be there in the floating uh without trying to go
anywhere the stream will carry you along and maybe carry you along better than if
you try to swim if you try to swim Downstream you'll get tired after some hours but if you just kind of rest in
the current and avoid grabbing onto the branches on the side or um avoid getting
stuck on the sandb bars the current will carry you and so the fastest way to
get to to the ocean on the in the river is to uh stay fully in the current where
it is here so um
so for this to work in meditation uh we have to keep in mind
mind there is an onward leading nature there is an idea that where there is a place to go to Greater freedom to
Greater uh capacity for an open heart and for uh less
suffering there is the Dharma is very Developmental and nature there is a place to go trust that
and trust that there's something about just being fully present here that allow puts us in the current allows something
to unfold much better than if we're trying to to engineer and make it happen
ourselves and uh for this to work then uh it's not just a matter of being fully
here but being fully here in a with
awareness to be cognizant to be have the uh ability to be conscious of this
moment be fully Alive to be um uh feel the Vitality feel the sh whatever degree
of CL ity or sharpness that's possible for you to just recognize oh this is how
it is now and um sometimes it's stepping away from the
fry the chaos all the activity and being able to just step aside and just see it
for what it is sometimes it's being in the middle of it and kind of waking up
and oh this is how it is sometimes we're aware of details sometimes we we we're
aware of kind of the whole party of what's happening but the important thing
is this ability just be here with consciously be here with awareness be
here knowingly ah this is how it is uh and if in that knowing we feel strain we see a
pushing uh trying a lot if it's possible relax that let go of that and if it's
not possible uh just know that clearly and don't make it a problem
so to assume a meditation
posture and the posture Can Begin by feeling where the weight of your body
rests against some surface the chair the floor a bed wherever it is that the
weight of the body rests and this is here this is a this is
the place where you are right now and to let the weight of your body
how it feels resting against the surface to
be the beginning of arriving
here now and then gently feeling
the weight of your body Above This surface you're sitting the Torso in
that's in an upright posture if you're standing maybe the
legs and the joints of the hips that are activated and if you're lying down
maybe it's a feeling of the length of your body
gently closing your eyes and feeling as globally as you
can your body how your body is
now and the idea of a global awareness is one that for a few
moments doesn't focus on any particular place any particular discomfort Comfort
or habit of being with something broad
wide awareness of the body as it is here
now and within this body to take some gently deeper
breaths maybe 3/4 ERS filling the
lungs and on the exhale
relaxing relaxing the body
into here into just this moment just here this experience
letting the breathing return to
normal and is there anything happening for you that keeps you away from here and
now any thoughts concerns emotions which are preoccupying
you and if there
is is there any tension in your body associated with that
concern feel that tension and if and within the global
body as if the global full body supports
you relax that tension
soften the physical tension associated with any concerns that preoccupy
you around the eyes
forehead the [Music] shoulders chest the belly
breathing a normal
breath perhaps the experience of
breathing is at the center of
a point a to be fully here at Point a is
the fastest way to get to B
to feel the body's experience of
breathing and if you'd like you could ever so gently say the
word softly lightly in the mind say the word
here as you breathe in and ever so
lightly lovingly say the word now as you
exhale so that these two words are a
reminder to not try to get anything or make anything happen
to just be awake to the experience of Here and
Now
e
for
e for
gently sing the word here as you breathe in now as you
exhale but doing so as a pointer to the
experience of the body breathing now and
here pointing to sensing and feeling
Here and
Now
for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to imagine remember
maybe visualize yourself being
present with another person maybe a person who you feel safe
with you don't need to act on desires or
aversions responsibility or and there's occasion just to be
present here and now maybe listening to the
person clear recognition of the person where you're not caught in ideas
of Praise or blame or right and
wrong responsibility or
expectations and may that ability to be fully present here in an open clear
mindful way be a vehicle be a
means by which to respect others care for others love
others for people to be seen clearly is a form of
love May it be that the practice of being present supports all of
us to love or care or respect everyone
we encounter especially the people for whom it might be hard to do
this may it be that this practice we do is not just for our own
sake but for the sake of bringing goodness happiness care
care to the people we encounter may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and welcome to this fourth talk on the five qualities of the
Dharma and there's two ways of understanding the word Dharma here one is um it's the teachings of the Buddha
so these are five qualities characteristics of the of those teachings how we can recognize what's
essential in those teachings but sometimes the Dharma is uh considered to be the
inner the processes the movements the development the growth the
unfolding that happens when we practice an unfolding which sometimes feels like
not that we're doing it but that we're being practiced that we are almost getting out
of our own way and allowing something deep inside to unfold to grow to mature
to expand and a lot of Dharma practi is creating the conditions of being so
fully present here and in being here having the right condition for something
to flower and uh practicing the EF path PR practicing ethics learning how to be
present and mindful in a non-reactive non-manipulative way just fully present
with care and attention is phenomenal in setting free some process of maturation
and growth so the fourth characteristic of the Dharma is that the Dharma is onward
leading So It Begins by by saying the D the Dharma is something that's visible here and now it's something that's
immediate it's something that invites you to come take a deeper look and as we are looking deeply as we
see more clearly one of the things we start seeing and feeling and sensing is
this uh that it that uh the Dharma in us the movement in US of practice is not
static it's not fixed but there's a feeling oh here is where it can grow if
I let go here if I bring attention here if I give myself to the practice now
something's asking to grow something's asking to unfold something wants to be born something wants to be released
something wants to be healed uh something wants to be understood there's all this kind of movement of something
here wants to grow and develop and we can sometimes feel that and and and and
then uh allow for it or give into it or practice because of it or in that
direction and um in the sense that that's onward leading and that's Dharma
is developmental is actually built into the Buddhist teachings over and over and
over again his teachings follow a development developmental model that
he's presenting um teachings and practices that are relevant for
different uh point points of maturation and growth and uh even in a single
Retreat for example even a single meditation there's a a variety of changes that happen and knowing how to
meet those changes recognize those changes to allow them to keep unfolding is part of how why it's valuable to
learn the Buddhist teachings in some detail and this idea that it's onward
leading this idea that uh that developmental is not opposed to a common
an idea that in mindfulness practice we want to sit and be really accepting of this present
moment and um and what that means is that we're not rejecting right now we're
not trying to fix right now we're not trying to get someplace now right now uh
because fixing and and resisting and rejecting all those actually move us in
the opposite direction to Freedom they they actually interfere with this growth
that can happen in the Dharma and um and so the idea of being
fully present here for what's here is not for its own sake but uh uh it can be
it's beautiful just to kind of feel this full presence to experience here and now but it's also for the sake of allowing
this process of growth to unfold without our interference and in the and in truth I
think the Buddha never talked about practicing acceptance uh uh he actually talked about letting
go of both acceptance and rejection um that uh both those
interfere with the Dharma and how I understand that is that the active conscious movement of accepting
something is a little bit too much like condoning or a little bit too involved and engaged with the process of what's
happening and there is a deeper more peaceful way of being present that uh
allows things to be as they are but we don't have to take the next step of accepting it um or rejecting it but
seeing it clearly just really see seeing that is not for or against seeing that
is not accepting or rejecting seeing that just see something in a very respectful way that this is how it is
now look at this and then take a deeper look remember that's the characteristic of come and see come and take a deeper
look discover what's here everything you need to discover about the Dharma you can
really discover here in your own experience if you take a deeper look if you're really present and patient and
not trying to analyze not trying to uh fix or but to really tune in and allow
things to reveal themselves show themselves to us and what we do is
adjust how we see how we look as I said yesterday what we're looking for is in
the looking that it's a very profound thing to to uh notice how we're mindful
how we're attending to our experience so the mindfulness the seeing the
attending doesn't contain inside of it um uh rejection or clinging or wanting
or pushing or uh entanglement with experience but it's just kind of very
simple clear seeing and the simplest free knowing of the
experience and as we do that that creates the conditions to know something better to know something without our
projections without our our um our interference with them and that's what
meant by come and see see deeply what he let things reveal themselves to us so I
think it's one of the very uh inspiring encouraging aspects of this D our
practice is that um uh it is developmental it does flow it does move
we do grow there is a maturation um and the ancient language
is um where it's like a fruit that uh matures until it's ripe and something
inside of us that keeps growing and um and we know we see in
children how children develop grow developmentally in stages that kids grow
grow and develop physically emotionally psychologically intellectually and and um and I would
say that uh some of that continues beautifully wonderfully in Dharma practice as we become adults and go into
adulthood but also um uh spiritually there's a kind of spiritually a
spiritual growth and development a development in these beautiful qualities that come as we discover how to be Freer
and Freer and um the qualities of kindness and Good Will and compassion the qualities
of equinity and peace and joy and happiness so the Dharma is onward
leading and um and one of the ways to support that onward leading is this practice I said during
the meditation that the fastest way to go from point A to point B is to be
fully at Point a uh to be in a Hur wor to get to point B maybe we'll never get to point
B but if you're fully at a at least in the meditation practice and Dharma
practice that's can be sometimes the way that something begins to unfold let go relax settle open up um much better than
if we willfully are trying to fix and change and resist and deny and ignore uh
our experience but to wake up here to
neither accept nor reject but to be awake in the
field of awareness in the field of wisdom of course there's a time to change things
field of wisdom and Street smarts there's a time to say no and this can't be or yes let's do this but in the field
of awareness the field of presence to learn to just be present and hold it
wisely and clearly and freely and openly is one of the great gifts of this
practice and that's a gift which we can offer to others and it's remarkable
the onward leading nature of our friends our strangers our enemies uh when we
bring kind open um awake attention to really know them to listen to them to be
with them and um don't interfere don't judge don't try to fix but really be
present in a kind supporting respectful way um listening deeply sometimes you
can watch how people relax and open and become happier and in our relationships
too there's an onward leading nature of moving uh the relationships to healthier
and healthier States and um so this practice is onward leading
and uh and and ultimately according to the Buddha this practice is onward
leading and carrying us along like a current in a river to uh uh to neana to
the the mind the heart's fullest capacity capability to be free of every
single clinging every single resistance to be free of suffering it's one of the
greatest things that uh we can experience and then to offer that to
support others to do the same is also phenomenal so the onward leading nature
of experience so the five qualities of the Dharma the first four is it's uh
directly visible here and now it's immediate it's uh inviting us to inspect
for ourselves to see for ourselves and it is onward
leading and tomorrow we'll do the last one which is um uh to be personally
experienced by the wise and tomorrow uh when we finish uh
we here at 7:45 we'll have a zoom meeting um just a
gathering to meet and uh and I'll answer questions from you um chance for some
discussion we'll probably do a little breakout group maybe groups of four for 10 12 minutes or something so you say
hello a little bit to some of the other people who um are coming to this 7 a.m.
YouTube It's a Wonderful community and it's wonderful opportunity to actually have small conversation with a few of
them and um and that link for that is currently is on the what's new section
of imc's homepage uh I'll post it uh tomorrow uh
here as well on the chat and uh it'll also be in the IMC calendar uh for
tomorrow so a number of places and um look forward to meeting with those of
you want to be part of it on zoom and some of you might want to just remain on
YouTube I'll keep this YouTube channel open and you won't get the full experience but it's a way of
participating without going on Zoom
so thank you