hello my friends and welcome to this meditation
session yesterday for the meditation I offered the phrase no
comment that uh one way important aspect of meditation is
to experience ourselves to be engaged in the meditation without being caught and the
commentary we can make about what's happening or especially a commentary
about anything else in the world while we're meditating and of course it's difficult
to do this because uh having commentary is partly how we try to be safe in the world
partly how we think about and plan what we want in the world partly it's how we
create an identity or reinforce Who We Are and partly it's a way to entertain
ourselves and um but meditation doesn't operate in the arena of
commentary it operates in the arena of direct lived
experience and that exists
independent of commentary for the most part and um so I offer the phrase no
comment whatever is happening Let It Be allow it to be
there but don't be involved in it with commentary don't start thinking about
it if you really get skilled at no no comment uh you would not judge it you
would not evaluate it you would not um criticize
anything you would not Chase anything or seek anything or try to get something
going going away there's a very radical almost a paradigm shift of what happens
in the mind when we start developing understanding what meditation is
mindfulness meditation and so what I'd like to suggest is
that the commentary we make about
life is the arena of how of our
Suffering The Arena the or the field of in which we
grow our meditation practice the Dharma
is the direct experience especially in the body that
is a different feel than commentary and so imagine that you
are straddling two properties one is the huge parking lot of a
huge Factory with Smog and pollution and
noise but the other foot is on the property of a beautiful field a woodland
field field with beautiful grow with trees around it and grass and wild flowers growing up and here your
straddle between these two places and you would like to get some rest you
would like to find a place of peace to be for a while and so you choose to go into the
field the Woodland field and walk across it and find a quieter place in the
woods so in the same way with our meditation and the equivalent of The
Quiet Place Place peaceful place the fertile place is um the what the experience we
have of ourselves especially bodily after a comment after the end of
a comment at the end of a thought before the next
thought at the end of a comment before the next
comment beyond the boundaries of of Thinking Beyond the boundaries the edges
of of comments can you feel or sense the more
peaceful field of The Quiet
fertile Lush Woodland field
Meadow so the advantage of saying no comment is twofold to not be caught in
the commentary not stay involved but also to become
aware of that which is beyond
outside before deeper than
comments the place where there is no comments is a place where things are
fertile is a place where it's a natural area where something healthy and good can
begin to grow maybe after homeostasis as we been
reached a disturbed Woodland will take a while to come into
homeostasis but it will so no comment you might continue
saying that word as needed and then look for that space at
the end of saying no comment where there is no commentary look at the
space the end of a thought before the next one and see what is
there at the source of where breathing begins within
you breathing is the natural spring in The
Woodlands out of which the water flows
feel and sense the source of breathing where breathing
begins and returns so to assume a meditation
posture and gently close your eyes or gently lower your gaze
and perhaps it helps to begin separating yourself from the
world of commentary thoughts is
to offer to your lips the corner of your lips a gentle
small smile maybe a smile of
delight in beginning your medit
meditation and then becoming aware of how the body experiences
breathing you might have thoughts and commentary and judgments about your
breathing but for now let them be in the other field
let them be alone and do their thing but for you step
into the body's experience of
breathing and as you exhale to relax and soften your body
relaxing your body is a way of caring for your
body and it's a way of preparing your
body tilling the soil of of your body so an
inner Health inner goodness inner
well-being can begin to show itself
and for a few breaths extend the exhale without it
being a strain just a few moments of longer
exhale until the urge to breathe in somewhere in your
body is the most natural and immediate issue of the
moment maybe deep inside your
body The Source the beginning of the inhale
experiencing yourself directly listening to your body feeling
your body is to feel something deep in your inner
life without comment
e
for
for e
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate for a few
moments that beyond the field of commentary beyond the factory of
thoughts and ideas judgments their lies
a fertile Field Valley
within from which flows whatever
goodness whatever wholesomeness there is within
us a quality of goodness and wholesomeness that exists within us
independent of our thoughts and ideas of should and
shouldn't and to be quiet still
gentle to be able to listen and feel for these inner Wellsprings of
goodness and maybe to hear to feel
the care that's there for the well-being of others care and love and
respect absence of hostility absence of greed absence of
aggression and from this place this deep inner field of
goodness to let our well wishing silently
perhaps radiate flow shine
outward gazing upon the world with Good
Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may whatever is good within us whatever is wholesome within
us resonate with the goodness and wholesomeness that's in
others may we share the wholesome with all beings
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this second uh talk on The Road Less
taken and uh applying this idea this metaphor of a
fork in the forest fork in the road and that there is a fork that leads to
what is UNH wholesome and a fork that leads to what is
wholesome and what is the path that leads to the UNH wholesome it's UNH
wholesome mental verbal and physical activity that we can get be involved in
what is the road to the wholesome it is the wholesome men mental
verbal and physical activities that we engage in so it's What's Happening Here and
Now that is important here taking the next step on these two different roads
and this idea that there is a division or a or a separation or a distinction
between two very different roads to take in life is kind of inherent in the
Buddhist path Buddhist practice and that
the one that leads to suffering is um very much tied to the
world of thinking not that thinking is wrong or bad in and of itself but
there's a world we construct out of our thinking that if we want something too
much or if we have aggression or hostility or if we have um
fear if we have anxiety there's a way in which that kind of prompt can prompt a
lot of thinking imaginations and thoughts and and those thoughts that we
construct then have a have a um a bounce back on the rest of us so uh
if we're anxious about something and uh
it's all too easy to be caught up in thoughts about anxiety the the ideas and
the story what's going to happen and those very stories maybe imagery that we create in the mind then a tie back down
to the body and evoke more anxiety reinforces the anxiety so the question
is what comes first the thoughts or the anxiety and we don't have to answer that question because it's like a chicken and
egg thing and but the the world of thinking is often the world of
abstraction world of imagination the world of um
distraction and uh and to a great extent that's the source for a lot of the UNH
wholesome ways in which we live our life so uh if I have some idea that um you
know having a really big fancy car was really going to perfect my sense of self
and how people see me and my sense of success in the world then uh when I when
I go by a car dealership and see a big fancy car uh then that desire for that
car arises and so the very kind of thought construct of self that I'm living under
is then the source for a desire for that car and that could be become an
obession uh if I um you know have the same you know desire to be you know you
know be wealthy and therefore we car and expect and have a wonderful kind of life
with people praising me and recognizing how great I am and someone uh you know
crashes into my car uh my hostility and anger to that person is not just because
the inconvenient inconvenience of having a damaged car um my whole self-image is
tied to what this damaged car means and the assault this person has done on me
is not just me as a as a human being but it's me as my ident identity my my
constructed sense of self that I'm trying to maintain and so this reciprocal
relationship between thinking and and identity thinking and desires and aversions uh can become kind of a a
Whirlpool of activity that we get caught in um and then there's another activity
which is a deeper Wellspring of uh that arises from deep inside that the Buddha Likens to not to
something that's constructed by the human mind the the madeup world of thoughts but
it's uh related to our biological life our deep kind of um possibility natural or uh
movements within us where we don't construct things but we allow things to
grow like a tree grows the planting and growing of of a of a plant is a metaphor
for this inner growth that can happen deep inside and for that like growing a plant we create the conditions for it to
thrive but we don't make it TR Thrive so we don't have to make up a lot of thoughts we have to almost quiet the
thinking down because they're just weeds that get in the way but if uh we we we
can uh become quiet enough to feel this deeper world to come up then these beautiful things
arrive so this distinction is big in the Buddhist teaching and one of the ways that uh it
can explicitly place out is when he when he uh contrasts explicitly What's called
the five hindrances with the seven factors of Awakening the five hindrances
are um uh sensual desire and in some list it's covet
covetousness and um and then uh ill will
hostility uh rigidity or sloth toward ER
numbness and then restlessness and uh agitation
regrets and then indecisiveness so I've talked about these five hindrances
recently and um and then on the other hand there's the seven factors of
Awakening uh these beautiful qualities they're kind of like the the the the great wealth of Buddhism
that's the Buddha is offering you def find inside yourself and so these are um
the mindfulness u a Clarity of mind that sees
clearly uh I'll talk more about that but then there's um uh making effort making
engage and being Vitality inner Vitality then we by which we engage in things
there's joy Tranquility Som and equinity
and these are states that emerge from within they're not things that emerge
from our thinking you don't think your way into the seven factors of Awakening you
almost if you use your thinking you think your way out of your thoughts so
that you can allow some this deeper Wellspring of the states to arise from within and um so there's this huge
contrast between the hindrances of one hand and the Seven factors of the other and we see with the hindrances that they
very much involve the world of constructs and thoughts and ideas uh that we have about what we want in from
the outer world uh or the outer world that we construct inside of ourselves
that's not really part of our deep sense of self but kind of the constructed world so uh when this when the first of
the five hindrances is is to covet the things of others then it's clearly about the outer World sensal desire is also
about how to get the senses met by the environment around us and have a good
feeling for you know comfort and pleasure ill will is also externalizing
something where both with desire and ill will there's an object of attention out
there that is the problem even if it's we're upset with something about ourselves or desire something within
ourselves we have objectifying ourselves and there's kind of this um operating
principle of the mind and thoughts and ideas of what things are that's the object of attention and um that it's
operating under and so all all five of these hindrances have a lot to do with this objectification of the world that
uh that we're kind of living with and some of that has to do or a lot of that has to do with how that relates to the
constructed idea of self we're trying to build up or defend or escape from that
uh somehow is coming into play in this objectification uh there's this self
that wants what how it reinforces or builds or threatens that sense of self so again we're into this world of
objectification of thoughts of ideas and people who spend a lot of time in the hindrances spend a lot of time in
thought that's one of the reasons why they're so distracting and um and uh why they're
the hindrance because they hinder uh uh Clarity uh uh intimacy being in
touchness with something deep within where something deep can grow something
deep can be born and Sprout and germinate and flow and expand within us
and the expansive states are wholesome which the Buddha says that we we should
uh cultivate and develop and uh expand and bring to abundance to
fulfill uh he doesn't not say let go of the wholesome states he does not say to
destroy them or uh he actually emphasizes their importance but these
are states that arise from this deep place within and the representative of the wholesome states that can arise are
qualities of mindfulness not not so much mindfulness as thoughtfulness which some people
interpret mindfulness but rather uh maybe think of it more as a a a kind of
a quiet silence um uh capacity for awareness for attentiveness for a deep
silent listening to what's here that's as natural as hearing when if your ears
work natural as seeing if your eyes see and
um and then there's uh the clarity part the seven factors Awakening but the
little word for investigation usually the name for the second factor of Awakening is the
differentiation of states to be able to distinguish between States and what this
refers to is the very thing we're talking about this week seeing the distinction between these two paths the
what's wholesome and what's UNH wholesome and uh and uh so to be able to
feel that almost not just see it not just know it intellectually but to really feel the UNH wholesome qualities
characteristics Sensations feelings that come with UNH wholesome activity of um
mind speech and body and to know and feel and recognize
the wholesome that capacity comes from being really quiet for awareness being really
clear and sensitive to what's happening deep inside and that sensitivity then
also then includes a sense of inner Vitality where the sense of be feeling of being alive and having certain kind
of energy even if we're sick there can be a certain kind of Vitality certain kind of of uh aliveness that we can feel
that actually feels like it's wholesome it's good and then there's joy uh not the joy
that comes from thinking things which are delightful and pleasant imagining our fantasies are coming true
but rather um the a certain Delight or appreciation of the just being alive
just this wonderfulness of a settled he present aliveness that's not caught up
in the factory of thoughts there are preoccupations we have in thinking and wanting and all that that is swirling
and is a labant or is a maze with no exit that spins and reinforces itself
and can feel like there's no way out there is a way out not out from
because the the maze has an exit but if we
can step out of the maze if we can quiet the mind if we can
see the end of a thought before a new thought begins and see in that very
momentary Gap there's another life to be had where we allow this deeper world to
emerge and then that Joy leads to kind of something becoming
tranquil and calm and peaceful the fourth factor of
Awakening and um I think it's the fifth and then the sixth is samade which is a
state of uh being organized coordinated all the different parts of
us become coordinated or organized together or Cooper operative all of us
may become a Cooperative entity it's called usually unification and a state of
wholeness and then there's equinity a profound experience of Peace where we
feel happily delightfully that we're not going to react to anything we're not going to be
pushed around by anything there's a peace that's stable so so this distinction here uh uh
uh between the wholesome and the UNH wholesome these two different operating system is that one operates very much by
in the world of thinking and ideas and Fantasies and commentary and the other
at its root uh has um operates under something not with thoughts but rather
with deep inner Sensations and feelings that we can tap into that can come in to
spread out and grow within us what's wholesome within us and a lot of what we learn to do is to
let go of the hindrances so we get out of the way of this deeper wisdom that resides within
us so um that's why the topic of the meditation today no comment is quite a
profound uh comment that can a comment that leads
Beyond comments so thank you