so uh I thought of starting uh this talk with a
warning and um so that uh because I'm going to say
something that U some people immediately turn off so just pay
attention and just get through this um so I'm going to introduce to you
a poly word ancient Buddhist word so some people as soon as they hear the poly is going to be spoken or this with
ancient words they okay this is not for me but this word is maybe in my mind
maybe the most important word to learn if you want to understand the Buddhism
and little bit the ancient language and uh what's important about this word
reason to use the ancient language version of it is that there's no one
English word that translates it and uh because the word can mean a
variety of things in English but the two main ones in some contexts it means
wholesome in some context it means skillful and it's little not so clear
which of these contexts and you know or which translation so some people just
leave leave it leave it untranslated and uh we might also just
use a a two words wholesome skillfulness or skillful
wholesomeness so the word is cusa k u s a l
a and uh the the the concept of it or the experience of it the the Attunement
to what is skillful and unskillful wholesome and UNH wholesome lays at the
heart of what Buddhism has to teach all of Buddhism flows from this
particular concept this particular Human Experience and um and so as a way of
beginning to introduce it more I would like to use a simile and the simile is that of a horse
whisperer and uh so a horse whisperer is someone who trains horses usually and uh
it's in the in the field of what's called natural horsemanship so where where uh people
who sometimes gone into whereas wild horses and living together and uh learn
to uh see how they communicate with each other how they relate to each other and then they come back and they use
positive reinforcement to work with the horse uh where they approach them with
great Rapport sensitivity in ways that don't intimidate the horse uh that the
horse feels safe and uh and the horse develops a sense of trust of the person
and then there's positive reinforcement where they get trained to communicate with the the human and the human can ask
them to do certain things and they're happy to do it and um and there's also
similar people they're not called dog whisperers but there are natural forms of um training dogs and um and one of
the things they have learned with dog training is that and horses as well is
that to use negative reinforcement to use pain for example to train them actually works
faster you can train them quicker but the results in the long term are not as
good and so for example they have military dogs who are they would need to
bring into maybe places of great conflict and War perhaps and uh and they
found that if they use negative reinforcement to train the dog to do what it has to do the dog becomes uh
chronically anxious and that anxiety doesn't serve
the dog well in a conflict situation but if they use positive reinforcement the
dog has certain kind of confidence and doesn't have the anxiety and so you know can go into the
conflictive uh sit situations and remain confident and more responsive in a good way I suppose I don't know if
that was the best example but uh still this idea of so so
to uh someone who's a horse whisper or has this kind of really has to have a rapport and feel and sense what's going
on Buddhism is similar and Buddhism is
asking you to be a self Whisperer and uh and I don't know all
your names but if I could I would go around the room and say each of your
names and like sveta is sitting right up in front here so I know her and uh so uh
sveta is supposed to become aeta Whisperer an Alex an Alex
Whisperer and uh and so for each of you to become your own Whisperer meaning
that you develop a report a sensitivity that your inner life trusts
you that when you approach and come in you are there to read the person that
you are in some deeper way than you would if you show up with your regular
Concepts your anxiety your hostility your CR self-criticism there's all kinds of ways
that we approach ourselves that um whatever way we approach ourselves we
are training ourselves that's the kind of one of the principles of Buddhism that whatever way
we live our life whatever way we speak whatever way we Act even how we think
that has an influence on us it's in classic Buddhist language it's called conditioning we are conditioning
ourselves and um and if we're a self- Whisperer we're paying attention to
what's being conditioned we're paying attention to what what the consequences
are as we go about our life and we care about that and we notice a difference
between an effect an influence it has on our body heart and mind that is UNH
wholesome unskillful and uh or one that is skillful and wholesome and being able to
read ourselves really well in this way guides Us in how we find the Buddhist
path and in fact the goal in Buddhism is for you to become your own
teacher and how do you do that by being able to read yourself for listen to
yourself uh really well so become a self- Whisperer then you'll find your
way and you don't have to impose on yourself Buddhist beliefs you don't have
to impose on yourself Buddhist ideas of what you should be doing Buddhism would rather have you uh understand this
principle this way of being a horse whisperer so that what guides you is
wholesomeness what guides you is uh so when it's translated as wholesomeness
the word cusa uh I sometimes associate that associated with health so uh so we're
doing that which is Health producing and maybe not physical health which is a little bit more complicated but
certainly psychological Health uh Inner Health for our inner inner
well-being mental health that we're cultivating so is what I'm doing healthy
or not healthy would be the question is um another word I associate
with this word cusa is uh nourishing does it nourish us or does it dourish us
and all these things are things we can feel and sense and a lot of it is being sensing
it in our own body and uh and so the body provides the
evidence for what is nourishing what is wholesome not uh some abstract idea of
morality occasionally the word wholesome has uh ethical connotations and people
think it means you know some uh following some rules of right and wrong
good and bad and there's something like that in Buddhism perhaps it's Not absent
of that but the core thing is the uh evaluation for ethics and Buddhism is
not kind of the moral principles but rather are the wholesome reference points inside of ourselves for what is
wholesome and what is not wholesome and um and so that becomes the
source of our ethics as uh when we see the consequences for
ourselves and so to be to be a horse whisperer person Whisperer for ourselves
means to pay attention to the body signals just like I think a horse
whisperer really pay attention to a body language and how it affects the horse the body language of the human and also
the body language of the animal so our body language what's happening in our
body where is their tension where's there tightness where's there uh anxious energy where does the focus of attention
come what's activated in our body uh where does the body start feeling more relaxed and softer where does the body
behave in feel and to behave in good ways that feel nourishing feel wholesome
feel healthy and um and so for some people that's a
huge uh challenge to use their own body as a reference point some people uh have
don't have never had any practice with doing that they have a lot of practices with paying attention to what's on a
screen and so that's you know everything should be there and and uh and that's
how we learn and change by what's on the screen but uh reading things and hearing
things and but uh but uh and some people the body is a very difficult place to be there's
a lot of pain um physical pain sometimes psychological pain uh in the body that
makes it hard to drop in there and then uh so it's sometimes for example it's like um you know these the dog and horse
trainers have to work with traumatized dogs traumatized horses and so there's a
whole skill in how to approach someone who has that kind of issue and so for
oneself how do we approach ourselves when it's traumatizing to touch into our
inner life and to our body what kind of care how do we help this inner Life
Trust ourselves trust us it's okay for us to approach do we have to approach from a distance I saw a photograph once
of a a person who was I guess a horse whisperer I guess uh approaching maybe
um horse who was part of a wild pack of horses and um and she was uh crouched
down she bent down so to clearly not be a threatening presence and you could see
that the photograph of the horse is coming over to her with its head down because her head was so low comeing
close to check her out and um so how how do you approach yourself with what kind
of compassion and Care gentleness so that what's in there trusts showing it
self to you so wholesomeness skillfulness is also a
nice translation because it emphasizes that it's a skill to develop and um and uh I'm fond of the
idea that when a crafts person is learning a craft and they become skilled
at it they're learning how like a like a Potter can can you know on a wheel can
make pots and that's a a skill to learn and a craft to learn as they're learning
the craft of making the bow the crafts person is crafting themselves they're
reshaping themselves they're learning how to move how to sense how to
focus uh how to hold their body how to be attuned to something outside of
themselves and how to involv be involved in a reciprocal relationship of self and
other self and pot pot and self and uh so there's a change and you can see
someone who's really skilled at a craft for example sometimes there's a beauty in watching how they've been shaped and
their movements and their elegance and their Simplicity and their Attunement and I've I've I've watched people who
are craft and one of the things that has um moved me is um uh their
focus their attention is being right right there and they they can't be too focused they can't be too little focused
they have but they have to be right there and they have to track themselves they have to be able to know when
they're getting distracted they have to kind of recognize when the mind is drifting away and not so focused or they
have to recognize when their mind is interfering by judgments or something and they have to they have to track it
enough to be able to maintain just like on the bowl just the right pressure to
make a thin Bowl you know it's a real skill so to be skillful in in uh in
Buddhist practice is uh to is both to shape ourselves and be shaped by the
shaping by be shaped by how we do it so here we back to how for wholesomeness we
how we approach ourselves is important how we pay attention to ourself how we
attend to ourselves so that this inner life can receive positive reinforcement
and with skill again how how do we change how are we impacted by the very
skill how we doing and building a skill not a few Buddhist practitioners have
been introduced to meditation and uh and they're may be very competent and capable in the world
to get what they want by hard effort and bearing down and uh studying hard and
getting everything and getting you know Furrow and the forehead in the
process and so they're ready to do it in the usual way and it doesn't work uh and
uh I've done that where I've tried to use the old way of getting really engaged that I've sometimes engaged
before and uh sometimes I got a headache which is not very healthy or wholesome
and sometimes uh I I despaired because it didn't work and so there were times
where it didn't work so I tried harder that worked even less so of course I tried
harder until I just like came to Rock Bottom I was so you know it was so hard
for me I was so critical and upset and felt hopeless and uh it was only by reach
rock rock bottom that I was able to give up a certain effort and then only then
could I discover a wholesome way to begin doing my meditation
practice so um so there's a uh so part of Buddhism
then Buddhist practice is to be able to read yourself or sense yourself or feel
yourself and what are we feeling we're sensing and feeling uh does this feel
good in a healthy way does this feel right in a way that feels harmonious
with being a connected attuned human being uh it's not becoming sensitive and
aware of what we want and and what we don't want in and of itself because that
can come from conceit that can come from just greed and attachment we really want to step back
and look more deeply and see what is what does it feel like to want what does
it feel like not to want and sometimes we'll see that it comes out of a place that feels quite
wholesome feels good we're caring for ourselves and caring for the world and
that caring feels can feel really nice other times it's clear it involves a
some place of clinging of being twisted up inside or being contracted or being
tight or where you can really feel that there's an irritation there's a form of
suffering in the very effort to um you know to want something and we can see
the consequence is not so good on us and so so to read ourselves and feel
ourselves and one of the things that why this is so important is we're trying to
also break the addictions of the mind uh and not a few meditators have
come to I'm not an addict they'll say until they sit down and watch their mind and their thoughts you know are so
driven we're so cut up over and over again in same thoughts pulled into the world of thoughts and preoccupations
pulled into certain emotions over and over and over again seemingly without being able to control it like something
has us uh in its grip and uh and some people are so in the in the midst of
anxiety or the midst of resentments or the mist of of um uh complaining and
cynicism or all kinds of things and they've been that way for decades that
they think this is life as it should be it just like you know you don't even see it because it's like a fish doesn't see
the water it's in but as we sit and get quiet in meditation then we start seeing
in some of the habits of the mind and some of them are difficult to see some of some of them invol addiction kind of
really grabbed and caught in something so the question is what do we
do about that that's wholesome what do we do about that that's skillful what do we do about that
that something inside of us maybe the very powerful forces of attachments that we can have uh trust us feel it's okay
to come out and be seen maybe there's a kind of maybe not positive reinforcements for being
attached but maybe there's some equivalent of approaching in a way that
our attachments don't feel threatened don't feel that they're that we're
critical of them or see them as being automatically wrong maybe we approach them with
kindness maybe we approach them with gentleness I think these horse Whisperers and dog whisper spers I think
kindness and gentleness is one of the Hallmarks of that kind of work so how do we do that for
ourselves and uh and some people will protest you that can't be gentle and
tender and and um because we have to be Stern we have
to fight and be aggressive to get our way that's the only way we're going to get our
way so that me so you know certainly Buddhist practice will leave you alone
to do that but if you're paying careful attention you'll start seeing sooner or
later that this isn't serving that somehow the influence on the system doesn't feel
good and that what has a much better influence is care Compassionate Care Friendly care
kind kind care care for this person that we are care for all the different ins
and outs of our complicated in inner life H and how do we approach it and how
do we cultivate it and develop it and so as I said Buddhism
emphasizes the the becoming a skilled at recognizing what is wholesome
and UNH wholesome in ourselves and the emphasis is on cultivating the
wholesome uh and for people who want to meditate in the classic instructions or classic Model
model of Buddhist practice before starting to meditate you would first
learn this topic of of this wholesomeness and un wholesomeness you
would understand how to navigate through these uh these two major Concepts and
you'd learn to avoid what's unhealthy and learn to promote what is healthy
there's actually a choice that's being engaged here in Buddhism choosing one over the other and how that's done uh in
this classic uh teaching that before becoming um meditating it would
be you would learn something about how when there's four four steps
that they say um uh when you're doing something
that is harmful to your self or others something UNH wholesome something
unskillful stop just stop easier said than done I know but
there are some occasional times where you can just stop what you're doing and um and then
uh um if if you haven't if you're not doing anything UNH
wholesome prevent yourself prevent the UNH wholesome to
arise in the future in other words create the conditions in your life so
that some of the UNH wholesome behavior that you have won't get triggered so I know for example that uh
if I'm uh stressed out I'm more likely to get grumpy and say you know unhelpful
comments to the people I'm with and so it's important not to be
stressed is it how easy is it not to be stressed in this life that we're living
because isn't that what aren't we just kind of
like you know the boss of society is asking so much of us
that how can we even think about not being stressed that's just what life is now for some
people to give into it means that maybe then we kind of perpetuate the UN
wholesome because we had set up the conditions for that to happen how do we cultivate some a way of being that isn't
so stressed some people find that meditation helps some people depend on a
daily meditation practice it sets the stage for the day so that they're much
less likely to to be triggered into the UNH wholesome and a reactive way so so
it isn't just a matter of staying in the present moment that Buddhism emphasizes it emphasizes take a good look at the
bigger picture of your day of your week of your year of your life and what are the conditions you need to put in place
so that you're less likely to be triggered in UNH wholesome
ways the third is if you're not doing anything wholesome at
all do something wholesome evoke it bring it forth so if
you haven't smiled at anyone all day try smiling find a stranger anybody if you
can't find a person at least smile at the dog you know or the horse or something
you know do something wholesome uh speak in a wholesome way to
someone in a way that's nourishing for you that feels good for you that there's
a you develop you know a report with a person you're speaking with that's nice
uh I'm fond when I go to the supermarket uh to see what kind of Rapport I can have with the checkout Clerk and
sometimes they're hardly looking at me and sometimes they're clearly present and available for some kind of human
exchange and there sometimes I missed that and I feel bad afterwards wow that person was there and available but I was
so involved with my things getting out of there as quickly as I could and U but
I tried to have a practice of really seeing can I have a rapport and can I say hello can I check in can I have a
conversation and I've had some great conversations with people checkout clerks that um were doing this wonderful
work for us and uh and um you know you
know in a very just you know in a minute it all takes sometimes and um so do things that are
wholesome uh meditate that's considered to be
wholesome but it's possible to meditate unh wholesomely if you spend the whole time rehearsing your
resentments but uh can you find a way then to approach the resentful forces
that we have in a kind way or approach it with gentleness with quiet approach
it as if you're going to be somebody trust trustworthy trusted
by the resentment so you can feel and sense what's going on feel the tension
in the body feel the difficult energies in the body hold it carefully and so how you're approaching
your own challenges if you take a bigger picture at least the how is feels good but what
I'm feeling is really difficult so I think one of the wholesome things is to be patient to
listen it's very respectful to our inner life to approach it with care with love
with tender Ness with gentleness here let me get to know you better let me know you as you do that you're doing two
things just like the Potter is doing two things the Potter is shaping the bowl
and the Potter is shaping themselves so you're beginning to shape
or have some positive influence on that part of you that holds the resentment and you're shaping yourself
as the person who can do that and as meditation practice gets
deeper it's really wonderful to feel the mutuality between
how you're shaping something inside of yourself and how in doing so you're
shaping yourself at the same time the how the how we're doing
something so uh so the Buddha said so then but the reason I wanted to emphasize this so he said there's three
ways so stop prevent the UNH
wholesome uh initiate the wholesome don't wait around till it happens by
accident but what I like is uh the last one and the last one um uh in the first
three when the Buddha talks about it he only has one verb to describe what you
do stop prevent and initiate but the last one has to do with
when you find wholesome States wholesome activity going on within you listen to
what he says about
that for wholesome states that are
occurring um one engages one's mind for the
continuation non forgetting increase abundance cultivation and
fulfillment of these wholesome States that's a
mouthful imagine that and I love the word abundance the idea of abundance not just
wholesome but an abundant sense of wholesomeness isn't that isn't is that
bad and uh and sometimes people have association with Buddhism that out it's about the four noble truths and we have
to suffer better and we have to understand how our our suffering and we have to let go of our clinging and and
that's all kind of good and wise and understandable but it's kind of flat
like you know suffering and the end of it I mean that's
okay but here the message is an abundance of
wholesomeness wow really we're allowed to do that in Buddhism I thought it was just about non-attachment let go let go
let go yes let go in a wholesome way
there's a way of letting go that's so wholesome that you filled with
wholesomeness and and I'll get to that in couple of moments again
so and then we'll then I'll stop um so
um for the continuation so when there's something Hol doing something wholesome
wholesome notice it it feels good for you it's healthy for you
um maybe for others too and keep doing it stay close to it and then it says
don't forget it don't lose touch with it uh stay in touch so that takes
mindfulness to pay attention and then increase it do a little bit more do it more in a
Wholesome Way don't do more in an UNH Wholesome Way uh make it abundant cultivate it and
bring it to fulfillment so we see that in how the
Buddha teaches meditation teaches the path in other ways over and over and over again the way he teaches the
Buddhist Meditation path uh is uh with words like uh developing Happiness joy Delight
gladness contentment that to understand the wholesome is to understand how to find
our way to how to be happy and joyful and
content so to just sit and meditating and wishfully hope one day I'll be happy
if I just sit here if I just sit enough something something wonderful will happen and I'll
be happy because that's what you know and free and free of my suffering it's a little bit magical thinking if you just
think that sitting here is going to do it there's also uh
uh being a self- Whisperer and sensing and feeling and
understanding what you're doing that's wholesome and UNH wholesome what you're
doing that's happiness producing where do you find the happiness how do you evoke it maybe
you're more happy than you realize maybe there's more opportunities for Joy than
you Avail yourself for go out on a nice day now it's blue
sky um do you leave here in a hurry to get to the next thing and not notice the
nice weather and you know I think it's kind of nice out there I hope I go out and notice and feel some delight and joy
and such a simple thing not only is it just good to do that in Buddhism it's part of a strategy
a skillfulness in trying to cultivate more and more of this
so that it it becomes abundant in our lives not polanish not kind of as a
pretend that things are all good but rather so that we can really meet the
tremendous suffering in our world and our society and sometimes in ourselves
in a way that's wholesome and effective and meaningful that's so much more effective to meet it and be with it if
we found some way to develop these wholesome good quality ities inside ourselves including
happiness that's the that's the skill that's the art of what Buddhism is
working with and that's why this word wholesomeness or cusa wholesome
skillfulness skillful wholesomeness is so important so my hope is that by in this
talk you'll never need to come back here again you learned everything you need to
do for Buddhism and it'll take you all the way to Li liberation
so uh we do have a poth today and uh everyone's welcome to come
you didn't have to bring anything it's mostly just an excuse for us to be together in a nice way and um and if
you're new to IMC um you welcome to just walk up to people and say hello and I
think people here are friendly and and just they might get you know absorbed in their conversations but you know and if
youve been here a long time look around and see who hasn't uh you know might be standing there it would be nice to say
hello to him and we do have 10 minutes before the potluck so what are those of you who' willing to stay for a few
minutes uh maybe a turn to next to maybe one or two people maybe two people next
to you um so no one gets left out look around make sure no one's just left sitting there alone and then say hello
and introduce yourself briefly and and what do you think just share a little bit what do you think of this idea of
becoming a self- Whisperer that I talked about today so thank you