so good morning or good day everyone Welcome to our
meditation and today I would like to uh call attention to the Statue of the
Buddha that's behind me here the
um um statues of the Buddha sitting in meditation this way are idealized
depictions of the Buddha and in very
idealized they are symbolic descriptions of something very
significant and it isn't that we're looking at this to see the Buddha as it
is we're looking at it to see something about ourselves and uh what this posture
represents is someone who has an inner peace an inner
tranquility and a confidence where the person is fully
present in a dignified way without asserting themselves onto
others without demeaning others or wanting something from
others but uh in some ways has a certain kind kind of
self-contained Tranquility or peace and confidence at the same time is available
for others usually these statues have the bit of sitting in meditation with his
eyes only half closed or half opened so that he's also available to the world to
see it and look upon it and with a relaxed gaze and so the idea here is that
as we look on on a Buddha statue like this one we have is to be able to
somehow or other uh have it Inspire in us our own dignity our own
capacity for inner peace and confidence our own sense of
self-respect and so there are many ways in which we can feel that and many ways
in which we can express it physically but the idea is if you would
like to have that be expressed in the posture with which you
meditate sometimes there said there's F there's four dignified postures for Med
meditation there is standing there's walking meditation standing meditation
sitting meditation and lying down meditation and each of those to somehow
or other adjust the posture so the posture
itself is in touch with or an expression of a certain sense of dignity a certain
sense of self-confidence
self uh uh you know in
peace and we have the idea these days in our societies of that postures there
people who take power postures before they're going to give a public talk or something to develop some
confidence and I don't know about this power confidence exactly but a dign
dignifying postures dignifying postures to sit in
meditation with a dignity like a Buddha
so to assume your meditation
posture and for today to give a little
emphasis on finding a posture that is an
expression of dignity of your value of your
confidence confidence that just being alive here that you are
important you are invaluable you have dignity
respect and um and you might want to sit if you're sitting you might want to sit
a little bit straighter you might want to sit or even
lie down in such a way that allows your chest to be more
open and open or more full a full chest
as a confident
chest to have your pans in a
position where they dignify us they hold us upright
here and in assuming a dignified dignifying
posture the idea is that this helps settle something
inside idea is that it evokes a sense
of inner tranquility that all things locally here and
now are good locally here in this body and this
mind this heart this person that's
you has self digity
self-respect gazing upon oneself
favorably and if you haven't closed your eyes maybe gently closing your eyes or
keeping them half open and see if you can have your
breathing breathe a sense of dignity
or deep appreciation and confidence into your whole
being breathing in a little deeper and
Fuller maybe feeling the strength of breathing
in moving the rib cage the chest the
belly so it provides a feeling of strength and
confidence and value and on the exhale relaxing letting
go but not letting go of dignity and confidence letting go into it
deep inhales as a way of creating more room for breath for
breathing and for the enlivening effect of breathing in and
breathing out
and letting your breathing return to
normal and feeling it to whatever degree that your body your
posture is the container for your inner life container for your
meditation that provides an atmosphere a
holding of quiet peaceful
dignity that highlights the immense value
you of embodying our present moment
experience that this person this body this heart this
mind this inner life is
precious invaluable
and worthy of embodying worthy of meditating
within worthy of sitting like a
Buddha peaceful
calm careful to not give in to thoughts
that undermine our
dignity let the Dignity of a
Buddha help you be present with a quiet
confidence
e
for
e e
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to consider
how whatever way that you want to support others other ways your gift to
your family your friends your community the world through your
generosity your care your kindness
friendliness your integrity
that whatever way that you have to offer with your skills and your
abilities it carries much more value much
more strength if you do it carrying your
inner dignity with you and if you dignify others in the
process if you're really here in a full
dignified way whatever you're offering carries
more value whatever way you see
others as valuable as as having dignity what you offer
carries more value and may it be that this practice
that we do brings a greater sense of our own
personal dignity and allows us to see others in a
dignified way dignifying others and with
that living our lives for the welfare and happiness of this
world may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
and for those of you who noticed that there were no sound there was a period of time where I turned off the mic and
then forgot to turn it on so it was not your
computer so welcome come to this fourth talk on titled to transform the
world and um it's partly or a big part chosen as a theme
in the given the it's the week before the election that we have here in the United States election that has created
a lot of anxiety and a lot of divisiveness and and election which suggests that the
there might be a lot of conflict in the wake of it and
um and certainly we can get involved in election politics getting out the vote
all kinds of things we can do that together with others can make a big
difference but here I'm offering something different for now and that is uh an
approach to how to transform the world that
um is suitable and may be powerful no matter what the outcome of the election
no matter what happens that whatever way that we want to
respond way we want to deal with it that let it come from these values that come
out of this practice and so for today the emphasis
is on Dignity and respect that uh Buddhism puts a tremendous value
on our dignity our value our
self-respect and as I said in the meditation that the Buddha statues like the one we have here are symbolic
representation of what it's like for a human being to be uh fully in the place
inhabiting in the place where they are so the Buddha's sitting on the Ground full fully grounded fully present in
this spot no question about it he's here rooted here on that spot and then the
upright torso is uh with a chest that's kind of
little bit open is an expression of a
dignified presence the eyes are half closed the head is not leaning forward the Torso is
not leaning forward pulling back it's fully here present in this world
without being aggressive or being passive and uh without staring or
turning away here with dignity and presence and then uh the body that's
relaxed and alert a wonderful these kinds of some of these posture statues
if you looked at them from the side or from the back uh sometimes my favorite part of the statues is um the the
alertness of the spine that the uh sculpture has made it it's alive in a wonderfully
significant and Powerful way like this so it isn't just that we're alive and present with the front of us with the
with our things thoughts and ideas and eyes and what we can see and how we see
others seeing us but from the back we have our own back in a sense with um
standing up um you know this alert posture it's not collapsed it's not
depending on anything it's self-reliant and this is all symbolic and the idea is for each person to find
their own way to manifest a kind of dignity in their very being sit and
meditate show up with it um
so they uh uh there's a you know very important document that came out of the
United Nations some 60 years ago called the uh Universal Universal Decor
Declaration of Human Rights and it begins all human beings
are born free and equal in dignity and in
rights all all human beings are born free and equal in
dignity and so to be able to uh live in a dignified way and to see the Dignity
of others and uh uh people who offer
spiritual care especially like chaplains and hospitals and other places uh I see them as I see them
having a work the work the task the mission the vision to be
dignifi they see and treat people as if anybody they encounter has dignity has
value has uh um
uh is an equal is a someone to make room for they're allowed to be here and we
can respect them we can dignify them we can hold them up and the reason why it's
so important for these chaplain to do that is that and for us to do it is a
lot of people in our world are now treated as if they have dignity as if
they're valuable they're not met with respect they're not seen as full human
beings on this planet and um and if we offered but and
so if we everything we do for others whether speak to them kindly or we speak to them with difficulty because of
differences we have can we first and foremost uh view them as dignified human
beings as respect worthy human beings and one of the reasons for that is then
they'll listen to us then whatever way we show up for them has more value more meaning if we offer kindness the
kindness is more powerful if we offer truth to telling the truth telling
stands more stronger with that unassertive unaggressive dignified way
of carrying it and being with it and if we dignify others they might be more
available to hear what we have to say to experience our generosity they might it
might settle something when people are diminished and belittled and disparaged
it makes people feel terrible and then that feeling terrible
uh is a t creates a tendency to for um uh living in harmful ways harming
oneself and harming others it doesn't create people who are going to support others into this world but if we can
meet others with dignity dignify them then um maybe then there's a chance for
uh cooperation for coordination for mutual respect and
uh and uh maybe that's more important than getting her
away and
um sometimes the word dignity is associated with a inner Tranquility
inner peace that comes together with an inner
confidence confident dignity confident peace as if
we are we are allowed to embody the place we're in as if we can really show up and
be here and we count we're important in and of ourselves but not so important to
diminish the value of anybody else but important so we can value other
people in it as equals in their
dignity maybe separating out what they say and what they do from maybe an
inherent dignity that comes with being a human being inherent
value respect worthy for something profound in who people
are and well how do we do this how do we dignify people well here's a quote from
Elanor Roosevelt again talking about uh Universal human
rights where after all do Universal human rights
begin in small places close to home so close and so small that they
cannot be seen on any maps of the world such are the places where
every person and child seeks Equal justice equal opportunity equal
dignity without discrimination unless these rights have meaning there they have little meaning
anywhere unless our own
dignity and are dignifying others the dignifying of others has no role in the
small interactions as we go through the day then perhaps it's hopeless to expect it
to happen anywhere else in the wider world so may it be that this practice
that we do helps us to sit like the Buddha walk
like the Buddha talk like the Buddha with a
confidence a presence a peace and a clarity
about our own dignity and value and the dignity and value of
others may we share a dignified and
dignifying world with others may all
beings know that they are valued in their fundamental way that
they were born born equal and free may all
beings be free thank you