good evening everyone how's the sound for you okay
[Applause] good well uh as you can tell Diana's not
here tonight she asked me last week if I would fill in for her
so
um for those of you who have been around the Buddhist scene for a while you know we
have a lot of lists lists of uh various qualities and uh
activities and so tonight I wanted to talk about one of the uh lists of eight
called the sometimes called the eight worldly winds or the uh see the
eight uh concerns or conditions or Vic
solitudes so there are eight uh I'll say conditions or energies
or behaviors that um we all engage in we
all experience and
they're outlined in this suta by the by the Buddha called
the locati sua it's un
un a 8 colon 6
so it's a list of eight things that are
four pairs and these are all
uh energies or conditions or experiences that we all experience
continually throughout our lives whether we're
um just starting out in this practice or whether you've reached the
end um they're all going to occur so just to kind of set the stage
for that um so that's why it's important to learn
to recognize these and see
um under what conditions they arise um and how we relate to them how
are you going to um how are you going to relate to these
things that are going to be you know
a what do you call it a ubiquitous part of your experience
and I realized I picked this topic based on something that um Tanya Wiser told
me and then as I went and I looked at talks in the recent past I realized that
Tanya has given five talks about these last month and Gil gave a whole series
of talks a couple weeks ago so if what I say tonight doesn't exactly
click with you there's plenty of talks on audiio Dharma about the eight worldly
winds so I'll start off by describing them the the first pair are gain and
loss so this refers not only to um physical
things things like money resources
um you know possessions but also relationships right
um our our family our friends
co-workers we um gain new family when somebody gets
married or has a child or um something like like that and then we
lose people from our family right there's death is uh a part of life so
there's continual gain and loss on the realm
of uh relationship uh friends sometimes we gain new friends and other friends um
may move away or you may have um you know
some uh uh rupture in in the relationship with a friend and uh things
change that way um so gain and loss can be seen all
the way from you know the very Monumental gains and losses like
losing a friend or a parent to death two very subtle gains and
losses uh as I was thinking about this day I was driving to have lunch with a
friend and I think there were four stop lights between my house and the
restaurant and at all four of them I hit the light wrong you know I like I got to
I got to one just as the left turn light turned red
and normally I would have just you know kind of mumbled under my breath or something like that but I thought oh
yeah this is loss right you know like I I lost a couple minutes because I have to wait for the whole cycle to go
through uh and then one actually one light was was with me so that I felt like I gained a little bit there
so so this gain and loss um
experience can occur at many many different levels
um and often times it goes on the noticed right you don't notice that
um that something is being gained or something's being
lost
um but it it can color our experience so that's
the first pair to look at is gain and loss the next pair is described as uh Fame
and disrepute now probably most you don't use the term disrepute uh I don't but so it could be
Fame and disgrace or fame and
insignificance or instead of Fame you might want to use the word status so you
know Fame and insignificance you know who doesn't want want to be the center
of attention you know to have the spotlight on them to be um recognized
heard um
celebrated like right now there's a famous person going by
um and then the opposite of fame or status is can be either uh
disgrace in which you're still getting attention but it's it's sort of a
negative attention right it's it's attention that you don't really want or
or most people probably don't want um or
insignificance you know not getting paid attention to you know you're kind of out
there on the periphery of the of the crowd or in the
corner and I imagine we could all uh recognize
having experienced Fame and uh disrepute in our lives sometimes
in a major way sometimes in a minor
way I think for for me one of the the times uh that I remember the earliest I can
remember in my life was my senior year in high school the either last or second
to last day of high school we had an awards day you know where you know
everybody went into the gymnasium and they had a stage set up and the head of the math department
got up and announced that this year all of the
Awards being given in mathematics were were going to one person and it was me
and you know I walked up there and I got a prize and I don't know a little certificate or
something and this was many years ago before being a math geek had
any you know cache to it at all you know it's just like so I sort of was famous
but but only to a handful of other people that actually saw that as a uh
valuable uh prize
um you know but nonetheless um you know there is value to being recognized to
being heard to being valued and it can also push us around
you know can also influence how we act and talk and um experience our lives and
the same with its opposite you know
um you know being being disgraced or being uh
marginalized and then the the fourth pair of worldly wins our Pleasure
and Pain and
I don't think that I could even enumerate all of the possible kind of pleasures and pains that you may
experience both physical right you know like when I got here this evening I went
in the kitchen and I found that there was some dark
chocolate and so so that was you know that was pleasurable
um but if I ate the whole bar it probably wouldn't have been so pleasurable right you know it's it's
kind of it has its pleasure has its limits and same way with pain you know
most of the time we avoid pain right it's it's not something that
um that we want to uh welcome in you know on the other hand if if you
practice anything practice sports um you may find that you you need
to work hard enough that there that some pain arises or if you've been injured you know I've had a number of
experiences where I've had to go through physical therapy and
um you know in physical therapy there's I don't think there's any Physical Therapy that you can do that doesn't
involve some degree of discomfort or pain it's just you know you have to see the value of experiencing that to
um to decide to go through
it so you know these are the the four pairs
they're all things that are uh you know prevalent in our
experience all the time so
why if we can't avoid them if this practice doesn't lead to the end of these
eight uh worldly winds you know why talk about
them so um here I'm relying on this this sua
that um tan Jeff translated
and what he what the Buddha talks about in there is the difference
between how an uninstructed mind he calls it an
ordinary run-of-the-mill person responds when they experience these things and
how a well-instructed person a well-instructed mind responds
to these uh eight worldly winds
so I I have to say I'm I'm I think I'm somewhere between these
to I'm not an uninstructed mind and I'm not a completely well-instructed mind at
this point so I'm I'm sort of here with with all of you um working on
this so the the first thing about these uh eight worldly winds is do we
notice when they're operating are we mindful are we
clear that you know praise is going on or that
blame is going on
um actually I think that's a pair that I missed praise and blame so I think you
you get that or or praise and
centure um so
in uh uninstructed mind first of all wouldn't recognize that force or that
wind or that energy going on and as a result they wouldn't
see these three qualities of it which are number one is that it's inconstant
it's stressful and it's subject to change
so I imagine all of you have noticed that you have a pleasant experience you
know you might listen to some piece of music that you love or have a wonderful meal or
um get a great massage and
when it's over it's over right you know it's just that that that's it there might be a little bit of lingering to
it so two of the qual two other things that can
occur uh when the when one of these uh winds is operating are uh hope and
fear so for example when I'll say when
um when gain is is
operating we hope that it stays as long as possible and we fear that it won't
you know so there's there's some hope of trying to hold on to an experience and
some fear that it's going to go away now hope and fear on their own
aren't intrinsically bad it's good to hope for a better world or fear can help
protect us from things but in this case hope and fear can also get in the way of us really
experiencing what's going on you know like if something's Pleasant's going
on if we're hoping that it'll just last longer and longer and we're afraid it
won't then we're missing the pleasant experience we're
not we're not fully there so
um so one of the differentiations between the these two
um uh uninstructed and fully instructed Minds is that uh one is going
to probably go automatically go to Hope and fear and the other will just go
to um seeing it more clearly you know
not um kind of seeing its impermanent nature seeing its stressful nature
seeing its um in constant nature and then
just uh if it's Pleasant enjoying it and if it's
painful um acknowledging it recognizing that it's
there and
um not getting carried away so the F the first element is then
is to be able to be aware when these eight winds or one or more these eight
winds are operating or these eight conditions the next one
is for the uninstructed mind the it the mind can remain consumed
by the wind that is M maintained sort of stuck in it right you know like if
if if somebody's praised you you know and you just get oh that's great yeah
and I wonder if they'll remember to talk also about this thing that I did and that thing I did and just you know the
mind can just um latch on try
to um try to cling to what can't be clung
to whereas for somebody that's uh well instructed
uh their mind is not consumed you know they can they can see it but don't get
caught in the story of you know what does this mean or how
can I how can I make this last longer or how can I push this
away that it just it sees it and it recognizes
it and it experiences it uh using one of the words uh Diana uses basically it
digests the experience it brings it in and it processes
it without getting without getting stuck
um now the the third phrase from this suta I had a little diff difficulty
with and it's that with a for an uninstructed mind they welcome the
Arisen gain and rebel against the Arisen
loss so there can be a way in which the mind grasps on to and clings to what it
wants and Rebels against pushes away what it doesn't
want the word that I had trouble with was welcome because in some ways I like
the idea of welcoming things you know
so in my own mind I I realize well I don't I don't think that the translation
really meant welcome like be open and accepting but more welcoming
like taking in uncritically something that you really
like so the image that came to me was um
being welcomed by a Carnival Barker now some of some of you may have
never been to a carnival I realize that's kind of an old style form of uh entertainment but they
have these games where it's like the ring toss and the coin toss and things like that where there's there's a barker
out in front that's always trying to get you to come and you know come on and you know try out this this
game and they're always a con they're always was you know they're they're the things that you'll never be able won't
ever actually work but um they rely on this sense of uh welcoming people to
their Booth so that's that was the image that came to me on that
one um whereas the instruct the
well-instructed mind doesn't welcome the Arisen gain or
the Arisen praise or the Arisen pleasure um nor does it rebel
against uh the
opposite so again in in reading this it it can
sound a little bit passive like really the practice is just to
notice you know just to not be reactive to just
notice um to recognize what's going on
and I don't think that's what this is talking about I
think it is not only allowable but I think also
necessary when things arise that you do respond to
them what what's important though is that there's
some pause there's some break between seeing what's going
on and then responding in a way with as
much wisdom and compassion as you can find
so so these eight worldly winds can be res can be responded to either in a sort
of a immediate kind of knee-jerk reactive way or you can respond to them
in a more thoughtful wise and compassionate
way so that's uh to me the difference between
uh the U uninstructed and the well-instructed
mind in terms of working with these winds and
the final result you know in in seeing them in not getting the
Mind caught in them in not kind of pushing and pulling trying
to get the ones you like and not not get the ones you don't like is that for an
ill- instructed mind doesn't lead to the experience of
being released from suffering that it is possible if you're not
recognizing what's going on and developing some
skillful um some skill at recognizing and not getting caught by them then you can be
go through life just continually reacting to these eight uh
forces in a way that um it's sort of a NeverEnding
spiral of suffering the image that that came for
me on that was um where I grew up in in the
midwest there's we'd often drive on dirt roads and if it was raining and there
was a a rut or something you could the car could get in a position where the
drive wheel would have nothing underneath it so it would just keep turning and turning and turning and the
car wouldn't go anywhere and so you had to do something right you had to get out and you know
like rock the car or um maybe get a tow truck or some you know something to push
um you need to do something to get out of that rut and
so uh I think this practice this sta practice is really
uh number one helping us to see when we're stuck when the wheels are
spinning and also find the the wisdom and compassion to get
unstuck and so then for a well-instructed
mind and again I'm reading from this text you're released from s Sorrows
Lamentations pains distresses despairs suffering and
stress so that's pretty good right
um so
that's I I suspect that's what all of us want um is
not to keep going back to the same um stuck place that we've been in the
past and not get blown around by these eight winds these eight winds know kind
of pushing us in one way than another um but to be able to see them
clearly and uh
not get stuck there's a at the very end of this there there's this wonderful phrase as it talks about this it
says it it talks about gain and loss status and gra disgrace censure and
praise Pleasure and Pain these conditions among human beings
are in constant impermanent subject to change knowing this mindful the
intelligent person Ponders these changing conditions desirable things don't charm
the Mind undesirable ones bring no
resistance his welcoming and rebelling are scattered gone to their end do not
exist
so I like this particular phrase about desirable things don't charm the
mind that doesn't mean that we reject desirable things but we're not under
their spell we're not Charmed
um I suspect that all that probably all of us at one time or another have been
Charmed by something Charmed by another person you know
Charmed by the latest gadget or you know some
wonderful car or you know you know something some TV show some movie
some celebrity
and you know at some point the spell breaks right you know
that that Charming person you know kind of cheated us out
of our money or you know did something and so part of the practice is
about um seeing through this
there's two terms that I remember Gil using years ago one is um
what was it that sometimes when people first come
to the practice you can be enchanted with the practice and he said if you're Enchanted
it's important to become disenchanted and if you're illusioned by
the practice it's important to become disillusioned
so some of these things like charm and enchantment
and illusion may seem
uh attractive But ultimately they need to be seen
through and learn then the practice can lead to
seeing how things are more clearly so that you don't get caught
the other line in here about uh undesirable ones bring no
resistance and and this I think it for me is a little bit harder
because you know how do you how do you not
resist um loss
or [Applause] um how do you not resist loss or um
disgrace or blame or
pain and I think that that there maybe the the important thing
is that with all actually with all of these State wins
is seeing them as not personal seeing them as not
personal not permanent and not perfect you know that
they're they're impersonal forces and again that doesn't it doesn't
mean no resistance means passivity
it's more no resistance
means no ignorance that they're going on you can still act but you're not acting
out of pretending as though they don't exist or or through aversion or hatred you're
you're seeing that that they're going on but you can respond to them
from a place of uh wisdom and
compassion so that's um my take on on the eight worldly winds
and um I thank you all for coming tonight and I'm willing to take any
questions or comments or um objections
here if you take
that yeah I was um can you hear me is it yeah sounds good um I was at Tanya's uh
uh work on on these and um you know the review is is great I'm things I thought
about um today I hadn't really thought about before so thank you for that um
The Middle Way comes to my mind though about trying to stay in that um that
observation mode and trying to stay in the middle way you know when thinking about these things that are happening
mhm uh you know stay out of the stay out of the the r and be careful on the the high
the high road you know when when these things we we're experiencing these things so
um that's kind of the um I think strategy that I've trying to employ
regarding those things and uh sometimes successfully sometimes
not so uh it's it's a work in progress isn't it
yeah yeah isn't it it's it's uh and the the the the problem is when
you're IM mesed in it IM mesed in the the storm so to speak those skillful
things you talked about aren't as you can't you know use them as as like you
like you could if you're if you're more balanced so I I I think it's
um um and it's hard to recognize when when that's happening you know when
you're mesed in a in a crisis we'll call it um I think that's the challenge is to
to recognize and then start digging your way out of it rather than making it worse I know Gil always says don't make
it worse uh so um yeah there's there's a there's a lot of resources out there
that that I'm glad I have but I wish I was better at uh you know picking the
right one at the right time so well thank you so when something like
that happens um do you review it later and think
about well what could I have done differently yeah about 10 minutes into your talk I started reviewing something
that happened happened today so very very timely thank you yeah well what
what can happen over time is you know first you you recognize like a day later
that yeah you could have done something different and then you know maybe only an hour later and and uh you know
eventually it's like you can recognize it in real time but
um thanks yeah thank
you this anyone else uh have a
question um
okay let you get
it thank you for this opportunity to be here
um I it was just uh uh
another comment uh maybe somewhat uh similar to your observation while
talking about pleasure versus pain and
uh um how one can an instructed mind versus
an uninstructed mind uh can respond uh wherein
uh I I think I uh kind of agree with you
that um maybe the interpretation or how the
it was presented about uh an uninstructed mind
is uh more uh equanimous or more
uh uh quiet about um uh being uh
uh pleasured versus being uh uh not
happy whereas uh an uninspected mind is
said to be uh elated versus uh unhappy in the
other situation otherwise um I I I kind of feel that
it's you I just wanted to share that comment
that that's something that uh um it's okay to be balanced and maybe
that's what is the interpretation that you are also saying
that and uh whether happy or happy whether the
situation is happy or not so happy and versus uh
an uninstructed mind where it is it can be like much worse
sinusoidal if I can use a mathematical expression yeah for that so
which can come across as less balanced um yeah it's like to keep
a equanimous temperament in either
yeah well that's that's a an important point but I think a well-instructed
mind can experience you know highs and lows you know they can enjoy the roller
coaster of life it's just that they don't identify with the
RO roller coaster you know it's like you know cuz I I don't think that the practice
leads to just being flatlined you know what I mean that
Equanimity doesn't mean that you don't you don't experience Joys and Sorrows
but you don't get caught by them and that that's I think
that's yeah thank
you all right well thank you all um and um Diana should be back next
Monday