so hello everyone and welcome and uh this week so far these
mornings morning meditation I'm introducing
um antidotes to the way Minds can often get
preoccupied by all kinds of things but certainly by our stories the Mind makes the belief we
have the the um the biases and preferences we have
what how attention and what attention focuses on and uh attachments to emotions and
feelings and comfort and discomfort Pleasure and Pain all kinds of things
that uh the mind gets locked into and uh an alternative to that is uh
to have an awareness that has some sense of of being part of the whole inclusive
awareness I talked about on the first day and the second day yesterday uh
talking about peace peaceful uh to be attuned to the peace
that's larger or more encompassing than any particular uh Focus or attachment of the
mind and today like the alternative I would like to offer is a primary Char
characteristic of Vasa practice inside practice and that is
Clarity uh vasam means uh uh to see clearly the
prefix V means kind of an emphatic prefix like really see and so we could
call that clear seeing but to have a sense of clarity and often we do not have clarity
uh we're seeing through the clouds of delusion clouds of preoccupations
thoughts memories biases preferences all kinds of things which we see through uh
we also see through our belief systems and our ideas of who I am who you are
self another that uh uh it's so deeply uh integral to our whole sense of
being that we we don't even see don't don't see that we're seeing through
those lenses we don't understand that we see through those lenses and then inside we're trying looking to how to clean
those lenses maybe even take off the glasses so U for those who have good
sight like like I don't to see
clearly and the particular angle I'd like to use for this morning's
meditation is that um rather than
trying to use the windshield wipers of the mind
to to clear away and see
clearly the task is to discover what you can see
clearly and be content with that so if there's a lot of fog a lot of
preoccupation a lot of uh confusion and chaos that um uh we would clearly see chaos
confusion if we are seeing if if there's a lot of anger and resentment and uh everything is seen
through that lens what can you see clearly what can you have be clearly
know and maybe what you can know is that there's anger there's resentment that
can be clearly known uh if there's uh confusion if
there is not nothing can be clearly seen it just just seems like there's a a
broad fog broad stuper or something maybe in a kind of way that can be known
clearly oh today I cannot see clearly it just all it's all
vague and so so no matter what is
happening uh what what can you recognize that seems clean and clear and oh that's
how it is that um so rather than trying to see clearly what is available what
can be seen clearly and um so if we're following our
breath and um and the breath seems vague or distant we can see clearly that the
that that's the that's the case we can see clearly well it's this is vague and distant or
we can see the Mind keep slipping off or um there can be a sense of
um of uh slipperiness around trying to stay with the breath and and so we're
trying to see the breath clearly but that not that might not be the point the point is to see the slipperiness of
attention that it keeps sliding off it keeps sliding off so what can you see
clearly and then when you recognize what that
is spend some time appreciating this I know this is clear
clear enough and that Clarity is always a
factor of the present moment that Clarity is always about what's happening
now and um and so if you have Clarity by
what happened yesterday and some discussion you had had with something that was difficult now you understand
the pieces of it that's not the clarity we're looking for we're looking for the clarity that says oh this is
understanding what happened this is what this is what happened this is the I'm clear that the
mind now has understood uh yesterday's conversation so it's always returning to
the present what what can we be clear about now and then kind of taking refuge
in that Clarity appreciating it relaxing with it resting in it uh riding in it um
stay close to it stay close to finding where it's clear and uh if you're staying primarily
with a breath which I recommend have clarity about how it is
not not how it should be with a breath um and so whatever your way your
experience of mindfulness of breathing is um now just
uh what can you have be have what can you be clear about that experience about
yourself being mindful of breathing and how does that Clarity keep
you in the present flow present moment so assuming a meditation
posture gently closing the
eyes and simply sitting here with the eyes closed
in the simplest possible way without analysis or figuring anything
out what comes to awareness easily with some degree of
clarity what experiences of the body are most clear
most
obvious and the word most can be used with a very low bar just whatever happens to be
clearest even if that clearest is not so clear in some other standard
and what is and what can you clearly know about your experience of
breathing if what you know about breathing is that there are thoughts and
preoccupations that are pulling you away from
it what what Clarity of knowing seeing can you
have about the distracted mind
and as you continue knowing whatever you can know
clearly at some point you can maybe begin
appreciating that you can know
Clarity you can have a feeling a sense that of what it's like for there to be
Clarity in the mind about something not Clarity of understanding
abstract Concepts about stuff but clarity about the basic
simple Sensations experience knowing of what is
and stay close to that Clarity and maybe rest with your
breathing supported by the [Music] clarity that knows
something about the experience of
breathing one breath at a time one in
breath at a time one out breath at a time just here just
now a Clarity that helps quiet the thinking
mind
for
e
e for
when you find yourself distracted caught in your thoughts see if you can know
clearly that that's the case no c as clear as possible as as
easy that thinking has overridden
Clarity that clear attention to the present has been lost or has
been crowded out by
thinking
for
e
e for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting with whatever subtleness or calm
or whatever that's has happened in these minutes of
meditating do you have a little bit more access to the idea of clear
awareness the awareness which is and knowing which is very very
simple the simplest clearest knowing of what is happen happening
now that doesn't require abstract understanding
analysis preferences being for or against
judgments the simplest thing to be clear about
here where the clarity of the knowing
feels valuable feels satisfying
delightful feels like something valuable in and of itself because for a moment or two in
the knowing there is no
entanglement it's almost as if we step back of or
two to look at something a
new without bias without preconceived ideas just
this and imagine offering that kind of clear knowing clear
presence to a friend a stranger a neighbor
to others stepping back metaphorically a
foot or two to be able to see the person as if you've never met them
before as if each time you meet them it's
new where maybe there's a delight or appreciation respect for the person as
they appear in this moment without carrying with
you the baggage of history and
memories person doesn't need to know you're doing
this to know someone else with whatever capacity of clarity
that you have
and where that Clarity is like an open window an Open
Door through which your kindness good will
respect care can
flow wishing
offering the other your kindness your friendly your
friendship living in this world with care for all
beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may how I am present for others with my clarity may it support
Others May this practice be a support for benefiting
this world
[Music]
thank you
so so hello and welcome to this third talk on the eight worldly
winds and um the context I'm trying to offer these teachings is that uh there
is an alternative to the eight worldly winds that we can discover through
doing Buddhist practice through doing maybe many things doesn't have to be pract Buddhism but we can discover an
ability to uh uh feel a deep sense of uh
happiness contentment peace a Clarity sense of wholeness we can discover a
kind of Simplicity of being uh that comes from not being
caught in preoccupations caught in distractions not being caught up in navigating the
world through what's uh good and what's bad for me myself in
mind that uh there's a wonderful uh softening Letting Go
absence of conceit which is possible when we're very deeply settled
here uh when the mind gets involved in all kinds of things of conceit about preoccupations With Me Myself and mind
caught up reactive to what we're receiving from
the world world the experiences we have from the world when the mind is caught up with sense of me the doer and the one
who has to do things and get things and have have things happen all those things can become quiet
for a while we can take a a wonderful mental vacation from the usual
preoccupations of the mind and that becomes a reference point
for where well-being is found where we get our joy and our happiness and our
sense of uh uh feeling satisfaction with being alive so that we have to have some kind
of reference point like this so that when uh the world the worldly winds blow
our way we don't get pushed around by them we don't get caught by them we don't get
reactive to them uh if the worldly winds is how we
Define our happiness and well-being or unhappiness and lack of well-being then
every wind that blows is going to blow us around we're going to be reacting fixing putting up um wind walls to stop
them uh and um uh putting on heavier and heavier uh
uh wind breaks just whatever it takes to try to somehow protect or hold on or to
keep them going um and um but if we have something
better than them then they come along and we're not tricked by them they're not they don't have a big influence on
us so this particularly true for this the the the pair for today the worldly
wins of praise and blame and uh many people really uh uh
cherish praise PE some people depend on it they want it they're looking for it
some people are uh organizing their life and their conversations so that people
are ready to praise them to to uh people boast people explain you know what they
did and how great they did and how wonderful things were and um
and people will present opinions political opinions with the idea that
people would praise you or if you have the right opinion and um and and some people get
uh that's where their Vitality comes from is uh This Joy of being someone
being recognized as someone as as being praised being honored being somehow in
Con in the relationship to others stands out as being special and it you know and
people look up to us and some of that's normal and okay
enough but uh there's a lot lot of conceit a lot of uh challenges that come
from living a life dependent on praise and that is the more the praise there is
the more the pendulum can swing to be blamed and uh and uh the more people
praise us the more they expect us to hold a certain standard to be a certain way and it's a setup uh for the pendulum
to swing it's a setup that we can't always be praised and there are people
who are going to criticize us be angry with us be upset with us not share our same opinions um uh be
critical and so if our sense of Vitality has come from praise then it can be
deflating uh to uh to be uh blamed or be
criticized they or maybe not deflating sometimes it's actually energizing to be uh being blamed or
criticized because then we're ready to fight we're ready to kind of work on
defending ourselves or um you know then we're aroused and we have to kind of be more careful and more
attentive and and so there's this arousal that comes with praise and
blame and the very sad thing socially is that uh uh when situations and people
neither praise us nor blame us then uh that can be boring that can be not
interesting for us that there's no orientation or that we're not getting anything from them they're not kind of
activating us and so there are times socially where the people who neither praise nor blame are overlooked or
ignored because of that's the orientation some people can have so um so praise is not wrong to be
praised uh blame isn't necessarily wrong sometimes it's accurate that people are finding false finding some mistakes
we've made and um and to have the ability to be open to both in a relaxed
open way where are the the the the uh the the quality of our inner life is not
dependent on the praise and the blame where we're centered on oursel in a nice peaceful nice way that um we know
something better than the the than the than the Joy or praise and the
unhappiness of blame uh we're not uh depending on it
for a sense of self for a sense of Vitality sense of happiness and well-being for
peace and so we can watch praise and blame we can be present for it in a
clear way we can listen for what's true uh what might be accurate and appreciate
what's accurate appreciate praise which seems accurate enough and um appreciate
that people re recognize it and appreciate when people point out our
faults the Buddha talked about anyone who points out our faults should be treated as a treasure we're lucky to
have people help us to see ourselves better and I I find it a delight uh to
to someone to point out a fault that I've done a mistake I've made or something I've said that was wrong or
maybe uh was even hurtful for someone and um and uh I could feel a little I
can feel my Challenge and sometimes I get defensive or sometimes I can feel a little hurt or dis uh dismayed uh but I
also feel as Delight oh my chance to open to this it's my chance to kind of
feel this to be present for it to find a way through it to some other way and so
rather than being um uh avoiding uh uh people who want to point
out our faults there's a way of if you know within reason there's a way of opening to it and feeling the joy of it
and sometimes that's the very thing that disarms people who want to criticize us and uh it surprises them some people who
are like but there are people whose way of living is to be critical all the time
and maybe there's little hope then but there are people for whom um they're used to people pushing back and fighting
and and arguing and that's kind of where they get their juice but to uh turn
towards them and open say oh you might be right about that oh there might be something there to what you're
saying uh can you tell me more uh can you explain exactly how that works or
something and PE some people are surprised when someone responds to undefensible
um um because it also means that maybe you know they're not getting under your
skin so this idea of um knowing an
alternative way of being happy being content being centered on oneself in a
nice way an alternative to praise and blame so praise and blame can happen but
we're not caught by it uh we're not pushed around by it we're not um
influenced by it and then there's opportunity to be wise about it and uh the praise
seems you know neutral okay okay thank you for the
praise and and and just let it go right by and um and sometimes there's
criticism which we just let it go right by and um
and uh we don't have to pick it up or get involved we don't have to have a belief system that every praise and
blame is something that we have to react to because every uh praise and blame
somehow defines us we're being defined by someone else and we've given them the
power to create that definition for who we are we've somehow forfeited Our Own
Strength our own independence our own capacity just to be because somehow we're allowing ourselves to be defined
by the other person and maybe we feel and and uh and either we want to get
attached to that or go along with it want more of it and we try to organize our life that way or we try to defend
ourselves or criticize or counter it in some way but in both ways um we've given
some of our power some of our independence over to other people how about having
receiving praise and blame and not giving the other person so
much power over you over us so
um so as you go through to the day the next 24 hours you might see are there
ways subtle ways strong ways big ways that you do receive praise and blame
from people you know from strangers from different situations and um and uh how what's your
common way of reacting to that what's your default when you're not feeling uh
rested when you're hungry when you're a little bit off in your day what is your
gut reaction to praise and blame when you're centered and rested and wellfed
and feeling content what wisdom do you have about how to respond to praise and
blame what is your relationship to this these very important pair of Act of uh
social interactions which are common enough in the human social world how do
you relate to praise and blame and so the the the assignment if you're
interested is just discover how it is for you and the more you understand your
how you react how you respond to praise and blame uh it the wiser you might be
come around them and what wisdom grows for you as you see it
clearly so thank you very much and um and uh so we'll continue with these
eight worldly winds tomorrow