hello everyone and welcome to IMC and this 7 a.m.
teaching and was glad that inz could teach for me while I was gone on
Retreat and I'm very happy to be back with all of you and I very much thought about you
and this last week and I stayed focused on caring for
the treat that there wasn't much room for a second and I'm very
happy e
Okay so as usual when I've been gone for a while the
um I don't push all the buttons right so now I think everything all the buttons
and is set so
welcome and what I'd like to do this week uh is to go back to
basics and uh it's always a good idea to start over Come Back to Basics and build
the practice build our world from the basics so uh for the meditation at least what
I'd like to do is most basic is mindfulness of breathing and um and mindfulness of
breathing in the teachings of the Buddha comes along with three
steps number of steps but the three that I'll emphasize one is uh he says that as
one breathes mindfully and feels one's body one can calm the body calm the
bodily agitation and then he says that as we're breathing we can calm the mental
agitation calm the mind and
by implication it also is well let me say
it differently and the third thing he says that as we're breathing we can please the mind we can satisfy the
mind and one way that this happens is we can please the mind or satisfy the mind
or Inspire the Mind by a third form of
calming and that is we can calm mindfulness itself and calm the way
that we are aware as we know what's happening in the present we can know
calmly as we feel what's happening in the present we can feel
calmly the body and the mind might still be agitated but we can be aware of the
agitation with a calm awareness calm
mindfulness and this is the most B way to go back to to Basics not simply to be
with the breathing but as we're breathing to calm the
body the mind and then more deeply calm how we're
aware to such a point that it just feels good to be aware it pleases the mind it
satisfies the heart to be aware calmly
so to assume a meditation
posture an intentional posture so there's the regardless of what posture
you're in there's an engagement through the
body to be
present and gently close the
eyes and to connect to the B to the breathing more fully to establish a
connection to take a few long slow deep
breaths take a few long slow deep
breaths and relax on the
exhale in a easy way have a long slow
exhale to extend the time which you soften the body for
and then letting the breathing return to normal and for a few
breaths to allow the body to experience the sensations of
breathing maybe almost like a massage that the Torso expands and contracts
the belly expands on the inhale
and and if the belly doesn't expand on the inhale see if you can relax the belly
as you relax soften the
shoulders as you exhale soften in the chest
and maybe as you exhale softening in the face
and then as you exhale to soften
calm the thinking mind the energy or activation around
thinking let there be a soft
in letting go
a gentle calming calming wave through the body as
you
exhale almost as if the pull of
gravity gently
relaxes the muscles of the
body for
as you exhale or if you prefer the
inhale invite the mind to
Cal a calming wave through the mind
as if the mind too responds to the pull of
gravity to settle become stable quiet
and then as you exhale see if you can be
aware of the exhale
calmly a calm knowing
of the
body exhaling
calmly knowing
inhaling to know to be aware without pressure
without
strain each Act of
knowing a lightning lightning
up whatever heaviness
releases in The
Knowing using breathing or some other thing in the present
moment to be attentive to how you're aware
perhaps relaxing any sense of being the doer of
awareness if you're the can't do it
completely then be the allower of awareness making a room for awareness
to operate without being the Doer
perhaps each moment of awareness cannot be not to see it as the
end a punctuation of recognition of what is
with a period but rather the beginning
of an opening to a fuller recognition
recognition of what comes into awareness
calmly feeling what's happening not as the something to
conclude what's happening but as a beginning of
opening to what may arise
next to know and to calmly be available
to know what
follows for
what you're aware of may be
difficult but see if you can find a way to know the difficulty so the knowing is
calm tranquil knowing tranquil awareness
for
e
for e
in being aware calmly can you find a way to know feel
sense your experience that is satisfying for the
mind
that pleases your mind
perhaps because the awareness is very simple
ordinary not looking for anything special simply aware of what's
obvious awareness that's
peaceful
for
e
e for
and and as we come to the end of this
sitting to
appreciate a sense of calm peaceful
knowing that teaches
us that agitation agitated
knowing will make the situation
worse that it's healthy and appropriate to remain with a calm
knowing as we address whatever challenges we find in this world
it's not worth abandoning a peaceful
mindfulness May our ability to be present calmly and
clearly support us to go into the world to work for the welfare and happiness of
all beings may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may we all contribute to this possibility
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this
Monday Dharma talk and for this week's series I would
like to go back to Buddhist basics the the very core insights and
understandings and practices upon which Buddhist life in the world is
built and um at the heart of Buddhism is addressing
suffering and The Core teaching that represents
this kind of direct clear eyed
seeing and working with practicing with suffering is the teachings on the Four Noble
Truth and uh classically it's called the described as uh the Noble Truth of
suffering the noble truth of the cause of suffering and the no Noble Truth of
the cessation of suffering and the noble truth of the path to that ending of
suffering and um and what I love about the way the
classic wording of this there are no pronouns in the wording of it so it's
knowing suffering wherever it occurs not chasing after it but if it's
in front of us if we're paying attention to the world we all account their suffering in ourselves and in
others and then uh understanding the causes of it
addressing the causes of it and one of the ways that Buddhism addresses the
causes which is somewhat unique to Buddhism is not necessarily fixing the
problems in the world but uh directly but knowing something about the root
cause of suffering that arises in the heart the Buddha called it a a dart
that's embedded in the heart that is possible to take out and so to um to discover what is it
that deep in the heart the the attachment the craving the clinging the
the dart that um as long as it's there that uh we will
suffer and this phenomenal capacity to take that dart out that no matter how
much we move the deck chairs and the Titan iic that the tanic will go down unless
and we better learn to swim we better learn to recognize these four noble
truths and how to work with them in our lives and um the um and so I'll be doing
this from the next four talks going through these four steps of the Four Noble
Truths but for today I would like to say that uh we have to be ready for that
that uh we shouldn't just jump into the four noble truths uh because it could be
misunderstood or understood the wrong way or because people are not ready and
so how are we ready for the four noble truths so that they are meaningful and impactful for us and maybe what I'll say
is not so that accessible but maybe uh it'll Inspire something for
consideration reflection for you so to be ready for these teachings
of the for Noble Truths there has to be Faith or
confidence maybe sometimes courage and um and what we have
confidence in what do we have courage about and that is we have to have
confidence that it's possible to pull the dart out of the heart it's
possible to feel to experience an end to what is
called dukka the PO word for translated usually as suffering which is not the same thing as
pain it's not the same thing as emotional pain but rather it's a form of
distress a form of um uh a particular type of emotional
pain that uh has a cause it that can be eliminated be taken
away be let go of that it's a particular kind of distress particular kind of
suffering that has its origin in the reactivity in our own
minds and hearts so we're not trying to get rid of all emotional pain that would be
impossible but we are trying to find a way to meet all the pain of the world
with a heart that is not reactive that a heart that is not um caught up in
aversion or caught up in greed or confusion even and so to have faith that that's
possible to have confidence even courage that it's possible to find another way
than to be caught up in reactivity caught up in reactive distress caught up
in reactive hostility caught up in reactive um greed and and um fear to
what's going on here and now and that's a hard thing to have faith in it's hard
to have confidence both that it's possible and that it's worthwhile and it does some sometimes
take courage and one of the sources of this courage and confidence uh is to have enough
self-awareness to know how we make a situation worse for
ourselves to be able to track that as we encounter something in the world that
the very way in which we react is not required re if we react with
hostility is not really required to even if we have to act quickly and firmly
there's no need for hostility we can feel how that we deteriorate because of
it we add a level of emotional Pain by responding with hatred and
hostility uh with a lot of Courage we can see that uh if we react with conceit
with caught up in ideas of Me Myself and mine that uh it actually makes situation
worse it Narrows ourselves it limits ourselves it it divides ourselves with
others in the world and so know that there's an end of conceit end of
attachment to Me Myself and mine not that there isn't Me Myself and mine in
this world but it's the attachment to it which has caused so much suffering in this world someone has to learn not to
be caught by it someone should learn how not to be caught by hostility and greed
and someone should learn how not to be caught by fear and the Dharma the teachings of the
Buddha is that you're the one to do that work if you come to the Dharma that's
the offering that's the gift of the Dharma that's the in a sense the request
maybe of the Dharma heart is yes don't make it worse for ourselves because if
we do we make it worse for the world don't sacrifice the
good uh in addressing what is bad in
this world don't sacrifice what's healthy in you for
what's unhealthy in this world there are unhealthy things there are tremendous
forces of greed hatred and and uh delusion operating in this world but we
make it worse if we ourselves then respond with greed hatred and delusion
there's a world of tremendous clinging and attachment we don't have to be respond
we don't have to respond in kind the idea is definitely to respond
the idea is to be living in this world to address this hopefully they address
the suffering as I said the four noble truths do not have pronouns associated
with them the suffering of others is in a
certain way our own suffering and uh once we get clear and
and relaxed and have like go pull the dart from our own heart we're actually more acutely aware of the suffering of
the world but it's possible to be aware of it without
reactivity not to be passive not to do nothing but in order to be um an Agent
of Change there's a wonderful expression in poly that
um is a title in a sense of one type of person a role or way of living in the
world and um sometimes it's used as a name there are Buddhists who received
this from their teachers as their name but it's a wonderful kind of uh
um way of living and that's the word Santi Caro s a n TI which means peace
and Caro k k a r o means a maker so
Santi Caro is a maker of peace and um and how can we do this
being a become a maker of Peace for this world and one way is to never
abandon courageously avoid abandoning letting go of
forgetting the fundamental beginning of Buddhist
practice which is to have faith in confid confidence in it is possible to
come to an ending of distress an ending of Anguish an an
ending of reactive pain emotional pain it is
possible it is possible to find an abiding wonderful
feeling experience of calmly being aware
of this difficult world that we in and in that calmness some of the most
important and valuable and beautiful qualities of the heart can be with us to
address this world to meet the world with love with compassion with kindness
and care to meet it with honesty and directness and respect to respect all
beings so um these next uh days we will look at the four noble truths and
hopefully you come to a greater appreciation that um of how invaluable
it is to know the basic Foundation of where peace can be found
the simplest most direct route and least in the teachings of the Buddha and uh
and that you will have have faith in the value of the formable
truths that that you'll hear these with confidence yes no matter how little you can
practice them how little you can how little you can use them to see more clearly to that degree it's
beneficial and maybe you'll even have courage the courage to really take the
four noble truths all the way to their end that you too can find the end of
Anguish despair distress and the reactive pain that so many
people live in so thank you and uh I look forward to um coming
back tomorrow to begin this series on the Four Noble Truths