welcome welcome you know what can we turn the volume just a tiny bit
higher just because I I don't want to I'm I'm getting a little lazy with these
microphones I don't want to project my voice I think this is good thank you thank you
Jim so good evening I was uh thinking about uh this
Bell when the bell rings there was a time when I first started uh a
meditation practice and then I would come to like group sits like this and I would be like holding on for dear life
just waiting for the boring and the bell would ring and like oh thank goodness know this kind of this
feeling I didn't even notice really how much I was like couldn't wait for that Bell to
ring maybe I was in like some physical discomfort or or uh maybe just some
mental discomfort or there would be times when
I would uh realize uh that you know again I'd be in a setting where other
people are meditating and there would be a just I don't know what would happen
but something I like oh I can't meditate and then I just said okay well I guess I'm just going to sit here and I would
just like just totally stop uh meditating pretend to meditate I was
trying not to wiggle too much but you can't help it when you're not meditating you're just shifting your weight around
and I remember um reporting this to a teacher that I would just like give up and then just
wait for the Bell to ring and this teacher told me you know you're not what
you're actually doing there is cultivating a verion just this you know waiting
wanting something to happen that's not there so there's this way in which we can
practice you know with this effort or you know really striving hard or really
just being kind of laxidasical maybe about it or there's way in which we're
kind of present not completely present but not completely lost in thought
either so I'd like to talk a little bit about this uh tonight this uh idea about
about balanced efforting like the right amount we might say wise
efforting and this is certainly part of the art of practice is to know like how much like
efforting to be doing even like the whole notion of efforting what does it mean to apply effort to a mindfulness
practice to a meditation practice and it's not uncommon for
to uh be a little bit over efforting this sense that we're straining or
striving and maybe we don't notice it so much in like a 30 minute sit like uh we
did tonight but when you're on a Meditation Retreat and you're doing sit after sit after sit you just start to
run out of energy like what happened get exhausted and you're but
all you're doing is just sitting and so you start to notice oh
yeah there's this draining there's this quiet
striving this pushing and of course we bring this to
our meditation practice because chances are we've been doing this type of uh way
of achieving attaining in other areas of our life and our professional life and
our academic life with our Hobbies with the almost most Endeavors that we do
there's a certain amount of like pushing that we do to get through to
make it to the end of it or to achieve
something and you know in some ways there is a little bit of having to apply
some effort but it's really kind of we might say it's kind of like riding a
bicycle where you know in the beginning you have to Pedal you have to apply some effort but then you can
coast and there can be a way in which ere efforting then we get out of breath
and we can't go so far on the bicycle but if we are pedling in such a way that
it's sustainable then actually then we can uh ride our bikes further and in all maybe
different types of uh terrain through the city and out of the city and into the country and to the next town and
these types of things because meditation practice I
mean we're here and we're doing a formal 30 minutes and with a beginning and an
end and there's certainly some real benefits to that but there's also you
know mindfulness practice that we're doing in our daily life that is just being embodied for our life being
present for our life bringing a certain amount of awareness a certain amount of attention a certain amount of
mindfulness so there's the amount of effort to do during a formal meditation period as well as this type of effort to
do when we're um expanding the mindfulness to be in our daily
life and they're related of course they are maybe I'll just say in a daily life
there's uh it's less common that there's uh a lot of serious
straining in our meditation practice when I mean by daily life is like just bringing some mindfulness to some of our
activities in particular some people find it easiest to do this on activities that have a that are we do a lot or that
have a certain repetitious n nature to them obvious examples are doing the
dishes brushing one's teeth or folding clothes there's something where that has
this certain uh uh Rhythm to it so chances with those type of
activities we have just this light sense of being
embodied and then part of the question is and that maybe I should back up and say and that light sense of being
embodied it's a tremendous way to really like bring some fullness to our lives
instead of to just be mindlessly just going through our lives as if it didn't
matter what we did we what matters more is what uh we're cooking up in our
minds but there's this way in which this um this more uh gentle type of
mindfulness that we bring to daily life is appropriate for being the more formal
City uh in a sitting meditation
because there is this way in which uh straining we don't we might not even
recognize it but what's fueling the straining is this subtle sense
of whatever's Happening Here is not okay I have to go find something else I have
to go make something else happen so either we don't want to be
experiencing something so there's this very subtle way like we're kind of like
dismissing whatever experiences we're having thinking that the next moment's going to be better so there's this kind
of like this straining this leaning into a certain amount of uh greetin for the
next moment because we don't like what's happening
here and there's this way this I'll use this language kind of like greetin for the next moment
is really also tied up with this strong sense of me like I like things this way
I don't like things that way I like it when it's quiet my body is
uh perfectly comfortable and meditation period is not too
long of course but you know how often does that happen and you know this meditation
practice is so much about being able to show up for our life life no matter what
is happening no matter what is
happening so even if we might have the sense like I don't want this or we might have the sense that I do want that and
that's another way in which we are can be this straining there's a sense of
effort and this often we wouldn't even notice that we're having this sense of effort unless maybe we compared it to
practice in daily life or we pra or we compared it to an experience we have
when we've been on a Meditation Retreat maybe some longer meditation and we have
this feeling like oh yeah okay we've been riding the bicycle and now there's a certain amount of coasting there's a
certain amount of momentum that arises and this is a natural thing that
happens this uh momentum you know just a few moments of mindfulness they start to
support one another and then there doesn't have to be any effort so much anymore it's just mindfulness is
arising so how can we apply the right amount of effort that the practice is
nourishing and supportive and sustainable
and not something that turns into a grim Duty I'm supposed to do this because
it's good for me like you know eating our V taking our
vitamins eating whatever vegetables we don't like but we think are good for us
or some doing some exercise that we think that we should do that we don't really want we don't want meditation to
turn into something like that but then you know the risk is that okay well then we're just and to chase
whatever it is that uh makes meditation
pleasurable so I would say that meditation is about practicing in a way
or maybe persevering in a way that has in a relaxed
Manner and this relaxed manner is a lot about being
receptive to what's arising as to as as opposed to going out and you
know connecting with something and really working to stay with that object there are times in which that
style of practice is appropriate and there's times when also when this style of practice of just
being more receptive like there's a sense of receiving the objects of meditation
receiving the experience of the breath receiving the
sounds and this way of receiving is a way in which there isn't
so much a sense of preferences isn't so much a sense of I want this I don't want that but it's a
more of a sense of allowing and accepting and like just noticing what is
the next thing that's being noticed
this has a very different flavor to practice in this
way this idea of being receptive one way one way in which it's
a different is that really highlights actually how little effort is
required if I were to ask you right now to just feel the sensations in your right hand
what does it feel like to have a right
hand that doesn't take so much effort you just kind of like inclined the mind
there it was just a slight amount of effort and so this kind of more this
receptive style allows this more just a uh a light amount of effort efor that
then we can be uh more continuous or
have this uh um more consistent and perseverance with this with this light
amount of effort that allows this momentum to
build because if we are trying to have a particular
experience for trying to avoid something there's a way in which we will over
effort there's a way in which we will strain or strive to get rid of that
discomfort in the knee or just get rid of the sound of the neighbor's dog
barking have you ever tried to do that there's a way in which we often are
like oh I could meditate if only that thing that sound weren't happening
there's a way in which and then we try to strain even harder to uh you know be
with okay just be with this and not noticing that actually what we could do
is just be with annoyance feels like this and just be with that experience
kind of like receive or be tuned into in a subtle way frustration feels like
this irritation feels like this and just turned it into that's what's
being known next and that way we don't have to fight
with what's happening and we don't have to like over effort we don't have to strain and
strive I I've have told this story quite a few times but there was a time when I was on a long
retreat and I just somehow got it in my mind that I had to work harder work
harder work harder it didn't matter what I was doing like it was not enough for this sense of just being insufficient
whatever I was doing I got a little crazy I just got a little I'll just say this that I just
got so tense and irritated I ended up hating everybody and everything it was
just CU like oh I'm trying to meditate and the teachers uh you know after weeks
they watching me do this they're like okay D just stop just go out for a hike you need to be out walking in nature for
like hours like oh okay okay I just hadn't
realized how like I was just straining and striving and you know I was I don't know I just felt like that's what I was
supposed to do on a long Meditation Retreat but it's it's not like that
instead it's more like no no you just have this build this momentum and then
on especially on Retreats it's not only while you're sitting but it's while you're getting up from the sit and then
walking and then eating and you know everything is like
that so it can be helpful to just have in
mind the sense that with practice to see if the Mind itself is
relaxed there's this way in which we kind of notice what does it feel like when the mind is relaxed
there this sense of spaciousness and this sense of ease there's also but
implicit in that and this is also really subtle is the sense of like trusting
that the next object of mindfulness is going to
arise we don't have to go get it we can just be receptive and it's going to
arise the next sound the next bodily
sensation if we're practicing in this way that's open awareness maybe I should have said that earlier this is a
different with this receptive uh way of practicing we're not
choosing the different objects we're just allowing the objects to arise you can also do this flavor if
your flavor of kind of receptive awareness if the breath there's a way you can incline the Mind towards the
breath but also a way in which which you're receiving it instead of going out
there and jumping on it or grabbing it so if you notice that the mind is not
relaxed what are some of the things that you can do or if the or if there's if you notice there's some
efforting one thing is maybe just uh take a breath like a larger breath like
you know and just kind of like this big exhale and get embodied back into the
feel the bodily experience and then just rest attention
on what's happening in the body this moment because often the straining is
not in this moment it's about I have to get somewhere or I have to avoid
something so that's one things to do maybe this can to re uh mind oneself
that no we just have to take this practice one moment at a
time just have to meet the next moment that doesn't take very much
effort just the next moment for me on those long Retreats
this is something I do not recommend that I was there for uh number of months
and then right you know we just meditate all day so it's hundreds of meditation periods right and I was counting down
like oh 624 more to go and I was just making myself
crazy it says that we just have to just meet the next moment that's all that's
all that's been us just the next moment and there's a way in which that doesn't
feel burdensome and it doesn't feel oppressive just like oh just the next
moment and then it can be helpful to there's a
way in which um with a meditation practice there can
be a way that um the attitude that we have that we're bringing towards the
meditation practice can have a big
impact and so it can be helpful to have a sense of like well why not okay
just just I I'll okay I'll just be present for this like why
not because sometimes often what happens is we might have this little rebellious or maybe I should speak for myself
sometimes I have this rebellious like attitude like I don't want to simply because somebody told me to or because
it's what I'm supposed to do or something I often have this little bit of a
resistance but what would it be like to just like well why not I I'll just give
it a go I'm just going to be present for the next moment why not just the next
moment so these ways are these these attitudes and which can be a big support
and the way that we are I don't know being able to sustain a meditation
practice not only during the meditation period but at home when we bring this at
home cuz there's a way in which um we might have this sense that uh to
practice maybe in English it's often we have this sense of practice is to exert
oneself so even we use this language right you know I have a meditation practice or something like that but
really the having this steadiness with the attention is really
can be really beneficial because we start to see what our our minds do we start to understand
some of the attitudes of the mind or we start to recognize some of the habits and patterns of the mind if we can bring
mindfulness to more and more parts of our life or just even uh more consistently
during the meditation period there's a if there's a certain amount of mindfulness then we're less likely to be
completely lost in thought and you know out in wherever it is that uh the Mind
goes likes to go so to help support like practicing
with a balanced amount of effort I've been talking about not too much striving maybe I'll just say also the
opposite of too much striving can be this uh like a laxidasical kind of sense
of like yeah yeah okay mindful I'll get to it later but right now I having this juicy thought or I have to solve this
problem or I have to remember the grocery list or I'm going to to uh indulge in this fantasy or something
it's not uncommon also to have this idea like yeah a little bit later I know I'm supposed to be mindful but yeah I'll do
it later and I hadn't really noticed how also early in my meditation practice I
would do this until um I Heard a talk by Joseph Goldstein he's one of the elders in this
tradition and he has this expression uh more or less mindful
like kind of mindful like yeah more or less a little bit you know lost in thought and a
little bit present and he was pointing to why not just be completely
present it's there's a way in which it can be really supportive for our life
and for our practice so what can support this
balanced effort is one way is to just learn what what are our patterns what
are our patterns that we bring to tasks in
general often they're like these patterns or some of the attitudes that we bring aren't necessarily obvious but
they're having an impact on us because there might be a way in which
um you could even just uh inquire when you realize that I was going to be talking about
efforting was was there a subtle sense that you said like oh great I I know
that I need to effort more I I want to hear how how much I need to effort more
or maybe you have this idea like oh really effort I feel overwhelmed already
with all the stuff I have to do I have to apply effort to practice or maybe you had a response
somebody like what is she talking about I don't even really know this whole idea of effort I just sit down and meditate
so maybe those three are three different extremes but just notice like what kind
of an attitude you have towards effort I know I I told you about how
like I was over efforting and I see how uh this shows up in other areas of my
life just recently I was uh doing a hike with a friend and it was it was a long
hike for me it was a long hike and uh you know the last bit I was
tired and so I was like walking faster I got to get finish this thing I got to
you know push to get this thing through finished to get there my friend was like why are you walking so fast I just want
to be done so there's this kind of like my way of pushing but some other people you
know might have a different way that's when there's a sense of uh I need to do
something so one way to have balance Balan effort with your meditation
practice is just to be aware of what are your patterns what are ways that you often
are showing up when there's something to be
done and just knowing about it can maybe
help sensitize you to noticing when you find yourself doing something like that
in your meditation practice you don't have to change it you don't have to make it different but there's a way in which
just knowing what some of our patterns are is uh can be really helpful just as
I said kind of sensitize it and maybe I'll say that if you notice
that there's a like a lot of like striving or wanting
to uh attain things it might be that there's some fear underneath that's
fueling that might be might not be too but it might be a little bit of fear of
uh backsliding or fear of feeling regret if I don't really put all this effort in
or a fear of missing out or or a fear of
becoming a slug and people taking advantage of me or something like this
so maybe there's some fear that's underneath the striving pattern or maybe there's doubt that's
underneath uh maybe this more I'll use this word laxidasical
uh pattern maybe there's doubt about is this really what I should be doing is
this valuable is this just a sense of hesitation is maybe I can't even really
do this maybe this is not what's best for me or something like
that and these are just things to consider to be be curious about you don't have to find the answer to this
but again sometimes recognizing that what's underneath fueling some of our
patterns can help uh take some of the authority out of uh these
patterns so something else that can support having a balanced effort is to
remind ourselves of why are you doing this in the first place maybe I should reword that
just what maybe to tune into what are your
aspirations like what is it that's motivating you or inspiring
you cuz sometimes it can be like we're just wanting to feel better and we're
doing anything we can so we're trying to avoid what's uncomfortable and Chase what's
Pleasant I mean that works when it works until it doesn't but most of the time it doesn't
and this practice is about just learning to have some steadiness no matter what's
arising so maybe to have some balanced effort is to tune into again our
aspirations of why we're practicing this wish for greater Freedom this wish for
greater ease or peace or whatever it might be for
you something else that can help with having a balanced sense of effort is to
check in with the way that our sense of our self is tied in with how much
efforting we do again and this is tied in with our patterns but we could just uh drop in a
question we could ask ourselves who would I be if I weren't
making this amount of effort who would I be if I weren't making this
amount of effort I know this is an odd question but it's something that you just drop
in and then maybe just listen to see if there's any answers so we don't have to
find the answers we don't have to look for the answers we're just dropping in a question and it's a way of kind of just
bringing some curiosity to the experience
because there's often a way that our sense of self is really tied up with
well I'm the one who gets things done or I'm the one who often leaves things
undone or I'm the one that procrastinates a lot or there's a way in which we might have part of our identity
is could be related to effort and part of the what this
practice points to is to have a flexible idea identity not to identify just only
one way maybe it's a appropriate to have a lot of effort or in certain situations
but not in other situations and can we have this
flexibility so whatever you recognize about yourself about your patterns or
this idea of who you would be if you weren't making that amount of effort the
point is to just meet it with kindness just to meet it with
uh compassion and awareness like oh okay this practice is so much about just
understanding ourselves better and understanding how some of the ways in which we constrict our possibilities and
some of the ways in which we blame ourselves or beat ourselves up
and that's not the way that's going to support having a practice and having a
life that is nourishing and supportive so with this inquiries
there's no need to be harsh on ourselves we're just maybe being
Anthropologist in some kind of way and just learning
about ourselves and how we're showing up in the
world so wise efforting often it can be this sense of like
receiving objects and that can be just with open awareness with whatever object it
is sound bodily sensation breath thought
emotion or it could there can be a sense if we're doing like a combination of directed and received like I'm going to
do mindfulness of the sensations of breathing but there's a way in which we're receiving them instead of going
out and getting them this is a subtle movement but it allows
some more sustainability with a meditation practice so that when the bell rings there's just like oh Bell
just noticing the sounds and then realize oh yeah that's the end and
opening your eyes instead of holding on like when is this going to be
over so I'll end there and open it up to see if there are some questions or
comments right back
here my question is for me personally I find I'm I'm most at peace
when I'm not making any effort and just kind of like resting chilling out relaxing so not
eorting maybe in a good one eorting a bad way but just not efforting at all and just kind of like being there I find
that at least for me personally everybody's different but that's when I feel the most Mindful and can you describe like what
is the experience of mindfulness for you then resting resting just completely chilling out not trying to be anything
or anyone and and and I find in those moments when I'm not efforting at all all and I can't I don't do it that often
to be honest but every once in a while like if I'm at the beach or there's a sunset or maybe I'm with a friend who I
really care about and there's like a moment where I find like I'm just not eorting at all I'm just resting in that
moment and and I find that's when I feel like I'm the most awake so just being
present for what's happening yeah just just letting letting go of everything and just kind of just being there you
know nice nice so maybe that's pointing to kind of like just the receptive just like just being with whatever there is
right there because sometimes I tend to overthink the spiritual path like think that I can think my way into more peace
and I think it I feel the best one I'm just keeping it the most simple yeah the simpler so great I appreciate that
simple simple is good yeah yeah thank you thank you anybody else have a comment or
question okay hi I'm Jay um and I know I think
this all goes back to a time when there was no writing right it was an oral tradition there was no writing at all
that's right so my question is this which is and I've been sort of I know once experimenting with it with
this when I'm meditating I can track my thoughts on paper right we tend to not
do it in this tradition so I'm just curious if this any value or have people tried it meaning as I'm meditating let's
say distracting thought comes and then I write it down then I go back to the breath wait wait maybe I get distracted
I forget about then I come back new you know and I can so I was wondering if there's any value in that or is it like
there's some inherent value in not doing it which is why people don't do it I see yeah well I I don't I haven't done this
practice so I don't know can you tell me what happens after so you have a thought then you write it down and what happens
after you write it down so then when I finish I going and look and it looks like like a crazy like there's no for me
uh when I look it's there's no pattern or there's no I think the craziness the craziness of it jumps out like my God
what is this all over the map you know and I've done it just like three or four times it's just to see what that feels
like like I was concerned that it would you know I like it would disturb my set
right it's not a solid 30- minute set because I'm going in and out but just wanted to see what the effect was um and
whether over time if I did it it might actually help me be more mindful you know I don't know what the long-term
effect is if I keep trying it and have people done it you know because I rarely hear anybody doing it I it's just like
you know it doesn't matter the reason is because sometimes a whole sit can go and I'm barely there if I don't do this I
feel like I've lost 30 minutes you know and I'm gone like or I maybe I'll come back like three times you know for the whole set yeah I I can see that part of
the value we start to see you use the word craziness the craziness of our thoughts yeah it's helpful to see that
for them to lose some of their Authority because often you know thoughts we feel like oh they're so important we have to
pay attention to them and they're we're going to solve something but when we really start to look at the content we
start to see oh there's a tremendous amount of repetition and there's this tremendous amount of you know going all
these different places and maybe uh you're writing it down helped to see that
um and so in this tradition we don't write them down um
but I could see where it would be helpful to just recognize maybe like the
the I like this word craziness right because when we really
start to pay attention we start to see that so and then then uh then maybe the
Allure of being lost in thoughts start starts to go away starts to diminish and
then we could just say oh I might as well just be here with this moment thank you to I I don't have a
good reason why we don't yeah and the reason I mentioned the original context
was I was wondering if writing was available at the time maybe Buddha would have said write it down or something I
see so I don't know I'm just speculating you know yeah so uh writing existed but
it wasn't uh it was used just by a few people for accounting purposes for like
merchants or you know for taxes or something like this and it was really considered certainly not anything that
people used to share information or certainly not in a religious uh context
or something like that that didn't happen until hundreds of years later
hi so I think uh in the talk at some point you mentioned uh this idea of
there's a time for uh meditations where you focus on you can focus on an object
and then there's time kind of just supposing that there's meditations where you just try and accept what is um I
feel like my practice has been halfhazard sometimes I am uh accepting and then other times I'm
trying to focus um um curious um what's maybe a
good way to think about like you know when is it a time for you know the the more focused
meditation versus the accepting or maybe other kinds but yeah great thank you
that's a good question um I would say that it differs
for different people for some people they uh to be more relaxed and receptive
just works best for them and that's their entire practice that they don't have this more uh focused you choose an
object and stay in the object they more they they might say that the object is
um awareness itself so they might say like the object is I'm using this
awareness and then they're noticing like oh here's a sound like here's a sensation here's a another sound or
something like this so they're just being aware of awareness we could say
and some other people would say no we I'm just going to like choose like the breath for example I'm just going to stay on the breath breath breath breath
so this one aware of awareness is more receptive and the more objectoriented
one is a little bit more directed and so um often people will do a little bit
more directed to help the Mind settle because that takes a little bit more effort so if there's if you're feeling
like oh my gosh this mind is everywhere and I can't settle down they might like stay with the breath for for certain
duration until certain settl ARS arise and then um open up and just like
receive some people will do the opposite they want to just uh like okay the
mind's all over the place I'm not even going to try to direct it I'm just going to notice what's happening and they'll
have a little bit more uh receptive and then there starts to be a little bit of settling and then they want to get
concentrated so then they'll choose a particular object and just stay with that so my answer I guess is like
different people have different uh propensities I would say some people it's easier to be with um with just like
awareness and having bunch of different objects as opposed to just one different object and I'll say it also depends on
you know if you're objectives if you want to get concentrated yeah you know having said
that you can get concentrated both both ways
um thank you yeah maybe I'll also say I think of it that way so I'm sorry what
was that I didn't think of it that way you didn't think you had a different question that I'm not even answering no no you are I didn't think of it that you
could um I thought you kind of pick one type or one style throughout the meditation
and I didn't realize that even like awareness itself could be the object yeah
but great great thank you anybody else have a comment or
question okay so thank you all and I wish you a lovely rest of the evening
thank you