hello everyone and welcome and uh for this meditation today
I want to continue on the instructions of wholeness somehow
our capacity to have the attention be broad enough to some to take in the
whole of the present moment uh it's possible to be
in a natural setting maybe at the beach or a park and be absorbed and looking at
some or preoccupied with some insect or a snake that's right there on the path and and to be absorbed in that maybe
fascinated by it and then um or maybe part of a conversation with a friend
that's intense and difficult and and then uh something there's a pause and
standing up and looking around and seeing wow the whole of this natural
setting includes so much more than the conversation or the insect the particular thing we're focusing on and
there's a sense of kind of the expansiveness and broadness and a wider
context for what's happening rather than what's right up in the details of it
all and much of the ways in which we're troubled uh is because there's something
that we are focusing on something we're thinking about concerned with something we're
feeling and without having to make anything go
away uh there is another way of finding peace and that is the peace that is
broader that's wider and the
particular trouble that we have to expand outwards it's kind of like um maybe
being in a very large room and then somehow becoming a tune to
the empty space in the room none that holds the chairs the tables the people
that are in the room they all happen within that wider space but the space in
and of itself is calm is peaceful even if the people are arguing
or being you know rushing around so the context of Peace The Wider
peace that's here that's there beyond the edges of whatever you're troubled by
whatever is challenging beyond the edges of it in the space space of awareness around it
and see if that can um support you to be here for whatever
is happening mindful in a non-reactive way mindful
without picking anything up or pushing anything away expanding outward into the hole the
peaceful sense of wide attention so to
begin being centered here in the
hole by feeling where the weight of your body is supported by a cushion a chair a
bed a floor wherever the weight of your body
rests and gently taking a little deeper breaths and as you exhale settle into
the place place where your weight rests that your weight is of your body
is held place of
contact gently close your
eyes and as you exhale relax the shoulder
the shoulders G give let them give into the
pool of
gravity relaxing the
belly maybe there's a softening of the fingers and the hands
a softening of the thighs and
legs and a softening of the thinking
mind any physical tension pressure you feel connected to thinking
physical sense of agitation there's
always the calm or peace beyond the edges of your
thoughts that your thoughts don't fill the
universe beyond the edges of the tension and
pressure there's peace and calm as you
exhale let the pressure and tension of thinking relax outward into that
peace and to the degree to which you can sense the Bas around your
body that is not your body but surrounds the
body feel the calm or the Stillness of the space
itself let your awareness be wide and Broad to
include peace the calm that's beyond the edges of your thoughts and your
feelings sensations of your body
and as if that wider calm or
piece holds all things even what is difficult is Nest
nested in The Wider peace and calm
and in the middle of it all is
breathing inhale begins and as the body
expands the sense of attention expanding outwards into the
peace and as you as you inhale
I think I meant to say the inhale as it expands it touches the peace and the
calm all around and as you
exhale bringing that peace and calm
back to touch the depth inside of
you breathing a massage that goes out into the hole of
everything touching the
peace with the exhale returning that
peace to some tender place
within
for
for for
if you become preoccupied with thoughts or feelings
events in your life notice how that is a collapsing or
Contracting or narrowing of
attention and see if you can open up wider beyond the edges of your
concerns notice that there's more Happening Here and Now than you're think thinking you're
feeling not to dismiss or ignore but to include more to put things
in context
and and even expand outwards through the whole the whole experience of the
present moment that includes the Body Sensations the
emotions the mental States all of it working
together the whole that goes beyond any particular thing that includes the calm
or the Peace of nonattached attention
in which everything
swims
for
e
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate or notice whatever way you are more SLE
calmer more peaceful now than at the beginning of the
meditation even if there's still something which troubles
you is there also a subtleness a quieter place within around
you do you have a reference point for some degree of calm or
peace sense of [Music] well-being sense of
being here and now in a way that
feels wholesome or feels right maybe feels better than some of
the alternative ways you can be when you
get up and get involved in your life taking care of all the details and
things the return of your
concerns and what if in your encounters with other
people you stay grounded and rooted in this sense of calm where peace
settl well-being
rightness that it becomes a reference point to not become
reactive aggressive
assertive closed down but
rather being settled on
yourself you can meet others with Good
Will with basic friendliness basic
Simple Kindness
so that whoever you encounter today something inside of
you remembers to have good
will wishing everyone you meet may they be
happy may they be safe may they be peaceful
may they be free of Oppression and attachments and
[Music]
thank
you e
[Music] so welcome to this second talk on the
eight worldly winds and perhaps it's easy enough to
focus on these worldly winds as problems and somehow contend with them
as the problem and we have to do something about them so these worldly winds are the ways
in which the ways of the world uh get us caught get
us push us around or trouble us or get us
reactive and um so these to remind you these are gain and
loss Fame and disrepute fame and disgrace
praise and blame and um Pleasure and
Pain so today I want to talk about this um Fame and disgrace Fame and
disrepute and um but I don't want to start with the idea that they're out there and problems and how terrible they
are and how they cause problems for us and we should do something about them but rather to start with a having a
reference point with in and this is the advantage of Buddhist practice what we're looking for through Buddhist
practice Buddhist Meditation is um a way of being a reference point a state a quality of
being a a a way of practicing that uh where we feel this is
good this is right this there's a sense of well-being there's a sense of Peace sense of at homeness a sense of being
settled here and now a sense of uh being
somehow uh disentangled from all the preoccupations normally were caught
in so there's something like that and it's a wide range of possibility exactly what this is uh maybe it's just a little
bit calmer than usual and that's a reference point to
understand ourselves better to and what we understand we understand how we lose
that calm we lose the peace we lose the being rooted in ourselves at home in
ourselves we learn how we sacrifice ourselves give ourselves up for the good
cause for the bad cause for uh for our resentments for our uh the you know the
um our our hurts our um grudges all kinds of things our
desires our wishes we we leave and depart we ignore we abandon
the sense of being centered and rooted here in ourselves and so we want to understand
this and as we understand it we understand and see that it's not it's
better actually not to be caught it's better to be more subtle than unsettled it's better to be calm than to be
agitated it's better to be um peaceful than it is to be
conflictive and uh and not that it's just a cognitive idea that we should be a certain way but it's uh almost as if
you know put your hand on the hot stove and you move your hand automatically goes away you don't have to have a
philosophy or a belief or a sense of should operating that pulls the hand away standing on a uh stepping on a on a
um on a splinter on your foot we pull we we stop we don't keep walking with it we
pull it out so it's that simple that we are kind
of beginning to I'm going to sneeze so hang
on I hope I turned off the mic in time so um so that um it's that simple
that we have this reference point and with that reference point we can understand these worldly winds better
and our relationship to it we learn that the worldly winds are ways in which we
give up or sacrifice or abandon or lose touch with something that feels uh
holistic something feels good right something that allows us to enter the world in a Wholesome Way in a connected
way in a useful way in a uh rather than one that makes the
whole situation worse and so uh for the
um hang on a minute again
so um uh so this is where we come now to these worldly winds that these are ways
which many people can easily lose themselves easily lose touch with what has been developing in the in meditation
or Buddhist practice with the goodness the wholeness the sense of being at peace with
oneself and so one of the second the second pair is Fame and
distribute and uh Fame uh is well known to really trip people up
when people are feeding on the fame when their sense of Vitality their sense of
rightness a sense of having value as a person depends on having lots of people
uh Focus on you and some people it uh it's even um um Fame you know Fame I
guess I think I think the word fame here doesn't mean um means having a really good reputation in the world um and so
that uh somehow you're uh not the same thing as praise which is the next one
but just many many people know you you feel so there's a feeling of that you have value you're connected you're
Somebody by the number of uh you know friends you have on Instagram or
Facebook or the number of people who log on to YouTube Every Morning to listen
that that's where the sense of Vitality and S of liveness and something when we don't have that we feel deflated we feel
lost we feel somehow uh you know that we're not fully Alive anymore because
the aliveness is fed is be feeding on others feeding on this sense of uh Fame
and and uh what people think of us what people are thinking of us that
we're known we're somebody and uh and then the pendulum can swing to disrepute to being
disgraced to having a bad reputation in the world where again our sense of
well-being or uh is really dependent on what others think of us and how many
people think of this and um and uh and so there what there isn't is
being fed from the inside out what there isn't is uh learning to be alive
breathing in a relaxed Way open way settled way and allowing and feeling
quite content with ourselves quite at home and at peace with ourselves it is
possible to have that and it's very difficult to believe that sometimes when
the whole our whole psychophysical system has been conditioned by Society by our experience by by by being fed
from the outside in and um and so this drive uh that we have to get it we have
to have it and so uh if uh if the fame goes away
which inevitably Fame goes away then or is not there in the same way to
feed us and to support us and to energize us uh and there there's nothing inside to replace it then some people
crash and get depressed and and uh feel kind of lost and feel like they don't
count and and you know sometimes uh um you know it's people lives unwind in
deep and painful ways um and uh or if there's this uh uh
dis people feel disgraced or feel like they now lots of people think that they're aad person
then uh that also something then uh is is challenged inside that uh we're not
getting reinforced this outer validation and um and
so there's nothing wrong necessarily with Fame there's nothing wrong
necessarily with not having any Fame to losing that fame um where the where the
challenge is is how we're relating to it and if we're relating to it as the
source of our well-being then it's a challenge and the one of the one of the
benefits of doing maybe any kind of spiritual practice or anything that connects us to a kind of much more of
a I almost want to say innate sense of well-being a sense of well-being that
doesn't have to have a reason being fed from the outside of um success and Fame
and recognition and all this it just because we're breathing because we're
alive that's enough just being in this world in a kind open supportive way and
not succumbing to the beliefs that we have to be different we have to have
more we have to be known and recognized and do something big in the world so
that we have our 15 minutes of fame uh it's okay just to be alive and
present and here and uh and the one of the
validations of this whole approach of Buddhist practice finding some deep inner peace here that's unconditioned
unaffected unpend not dependent on the world and things and thoughts and
feelings is that um this turns out to be a
phenomenally effective powerful meaningful way to respond and live in
the world in a Wholesome Way with compassion and care and love and and uh
and um and caregiving to this world a caregiving to the world a love and a
compassion where we don't lose ourselves in the process uh we don't uh feel like
we have to hurry and rush and our sense of well-being our sense of personhood is
depended on um the outcomes of our of our service our care our love of the
things we do we do things because it's the natural or easy kind of
manifestation of being deeply at peace and connected not because of what we get
from it or what we should happen from ourselves so that's why Fame and
disrepute is such an important thing to be attentive to because uh uh it's a way
of losing touch with ourselves losing the ways in which we can be fed from the
inside out where we can feel the Deep sense of contentment just to be just to be here
trusting or more than trusting knowing that being at peace and
settled with almost like with nothing you have to do that that is a powerful
and effective uh state from which to
do and and it's a little bit of a paradox to not have to do
anything allows us to do everything peacefully and effectively and uh
without succumbing to clinging in attachment
so um so Fame and disrepute whether it's
Fame locally in our neighborhood or places at work that uh or whether it's
uh you know these days many people have um on social media and count their
friends and the connections maybe Fame is
overrated and maybe disrepute to the lack of Fame is also overrated and we
don't have to base our life on either one so thank you very
much and and um I have one announcement and uh the Spirit Rock
Meditation Center that I'm very connected to up in Marin County uh had asked me to invited me or requested of
me to uh do kind of a event celebrating the publication of my new book this year
called Everything Is practice and I agreed and and then and now they would
like me to uh try to um encourage people to come to it and um so maybe some of
you would like to come it's this coming Sunday it's on zoom and it's at 6: pm
and I'll talk a little bit about my book but I didn't really want to focus only on my book so I want to talk a little
bit about um the great value of retreat practice the book is kind of a manual
for insight Retreat practice so that's what I want to kind of just uh talk a little bit about so some of you might be
interested in going to it there's a link to it you have to register there's a link to it on the IMC homepage on that
little box in the lower right there's called what's new there's an announcement there about it and uh also
if you go on Spirit Rock's website you can probably find it and um it's a small I think it'll be
small somewhat intimate kind of opportunity on Zoom to have a discussion and and uh I'm certainly looking forward
to um having this uh little period of
exchange so thank you