so greetings again welcome everyone we're back today to explore further in the the
five precepts ways to bring attention
to our actions in five common Realms of of
action as Gil puts it in uh oh I can't remember where
uh but that the the practice provides a mirror where
we can come to know ourselves by reflecting on our
actions come to know ourselves in the practice through our
actions uh somehow coming to know ourselves through
our actions removes ourselves as actor from the middle of everything
and as we know that that is freeing today we'll focus on the third
precept I'm sorry where am I Thursday fourth precept
the commitment to support our practice by refraining from unskillful speech
harmful speech and uh this is such a great area
of practice spee being something we engage in frequently without any
thought it just happens um and as we'll
see the Buddha recommends that we think before we speak in a very specific way
without too much more on for on that for the moment let's sit together and let's
do a little practice in the sitting with avoiding harmful speech
and cultivating skillful speech in the meditation I'll show you
what I mean so let's bring our eyes down if that's comfortable invitation to bring
the eyes down partially all the way if that
works settle into the meditation
posture and as we've done in previous days
find balance establish
balance between alertness and
relaxation attentive accepting open to what
arises alert engaged just enough energy to keep
attention Here and Now but also at
ease seeing if we can relax a little bit the the tendency to express preference
or push things away or bring things closer hold on to
things as we begin to settle in we can bring a attention to the
body sometimes it's useful to just start with the weight of the body in the chair
on the bench on the cushion on the
floor and then feel our way into the
breathing right in the center of it all there's this breathing thing
happening and we don't even need to know it as breathing or as the breath we can just notice the rise and fall of the
abdomen the sense of stretching out filling up followed by the sense
of settling down expelling the
breath we can bring our attention to just one breath at a time I'm exploring it
fully what's it like now sometimes we may notice the breath
feels open and free other times tight
quivery
constricted and our task is just to notice how things are right
now don't have to do anything about what we
notice we're just giving this gift of attention and
this this soft question of what's it like right now to be
here every time we become aware wake up perhaps to notice that
we've gotten entangled in thought or that maybe the mind has we can sense is
constricted kind of narrowly focused on a particular stream of thought or spiral
of thought no problem nothing to get overly concerned
about and maybe just noticing that tightness that narrowness we can then
proceed to return to the center of things the breathing happening in the
middle return again to the sensations of the abdomen rising and falling the shoulders lifting settling back
down noticing just this
breath today with exploring together the third the fourth
precept we can bring this idea of avoiding harsh speech unhelpful
speech unkind speech as a way to support our
practice we can notice the speech that may accompany our meditation
when we find the Mind distracted caught up in the future thinking about the past
thinking about other people or ourselves how do we direct it back to
the Here and Now of experience is that voice we use to guide
the meditation internally is it kind is it
supportive or is it frustrated EXA exasperated judging
Etc maybe we can just soften up a little bit around that voice and gently guide
ourselves maybe it's like tugging on the leash of a puppy that we
love and an encouragement to return to here and now no hurry we're going to do
this many times over and over again it's a natural process
the mind gets caught up on things that's the mind's job we depend on the mind to do
that and in the meditation we're just we're just adding to those capacities of
mind that we've so well cultivated we're we're cultivating
another capacity of mind to be a little more still the Mind enjoys this too the
Mind likes to be at rest as well as being busy
so notice the voices in our heads we might say notice what those voices are like
and if they're unkind or ungentle just soften up around that a bit just notice
that maybe it's a little painful to have that voice guide us and perhaps
we can we can use a gentler voice
sometimes we can ask who voice is that
anyway is that a parental Voice or caregiver's
voice the one that maybe chides
us for having lost track of the breath fallen off the breath wandered away from
the breath a voice that hurries us back to the
breath must return to the breath we can be gentle there can
develop a voice of practice skillful speech in the
meditation that gently guides us back to the breath maybe it's something like oh
there's the mind again entangled with the future planning
I like to be grateful for the mind's ability to do that sometimes I say thank
you appreciate it appreciate those skills right now I'm going to head back
to the breath going to sit with the breath for a
bit be gentle with the voice in The
Meditation
for
e
e e
so maybe we can in dedicating the Merit of our practice
today bring forward the voice or voices we cultivate in the
meditation voices that are kind and
supportive and maybe we can as we wish well to other beings we
can notice this voice too make it a central part of our practice
the voice that wishes all other beings be content be happy be
free these voices this voice we develop in the meditation for guiding our
own our own practice our own returning to the Here and
Now can be a voice we share with the world so in the spirit of that kindness
the skill that we bring to our our intimate relationship with
ourselves in the meditation let's wish that other beings benefit from our
practice that all
beings meet with kindness in the world all beings
benefit from the Stillness and peace that the
practice offers through us may all beings be well be
safe may all beings live at peace may all beings be free
[Music]
so welcome again
greetings and welcome back to day four of our exploration of the five
precepts the fourth precept
is a commitment to refrain from harmful
speech and to cultivate kind speech is a way to support our
practice and I would just note before proceeding on to some discussion of the
precept in sort of in the actions of interaction with others and daily daily
life just that as I tried to point to in the guided meditation that the voices we cultivate
or the voice we cultivate to guide the meditation to the extent that it has a
verbal presence and has words that can be a voice that we are attentive to and
bring into the world a lot of times we'll notice that the voice that appears years it may have frustration
exasperation judgment as I noted and we can soften around that so that even in
the meditation we're avoiding harsh speech avoiding unskillful speech
avoiding speech that causes or deepens
harm so the fourth precept yeah uh I think as I observed at the
very top of the hour that speech is something that comes so automatically to
us and of course there's exceptions but uh to to most of us speech comes very
quickly and uh without a lot of thought and I I think perhaps the the central
injunction here in the fourth precept is just to think more
about what we bring into the world world this act through this action of
speech so avoiding harmful speech and it's also useful to note that
as is the case with each of the each of these precepts what we undertake in this
sort of complicated formulation is not just to practice good speech or kind
speech but to avoid causing harm with speech to avoid harmful speech there's
something about the avoiding that's really important among other things I think when we avoid harmful speech we
speak less and we listen
more it's an interesting aspect of our physiology that apparently when we speak
if we were to speak without protecting our ears internally the sound of our voices could do damage to this very
sensitive hearing apparatus we have and so there's a mechanism me mechanism might not be the right word
but there's a when we speak we we close off a bit the hearing is closed off a
bit and so when we speak we literally can't listen or we don't hear as
much and so I keep that in mind just that when I'm talking I can't listen that's true on a lot of levels
but apparently it's true in the physiology as well so um what is the bu in this case
the case of this precept the Buddha actually provides as many of you probably know very specific instructions
about what constitute wise speech what constitute unwise speech and I'll just give you a brief
flavor of this with the story there's a um there's a in in the ancient
discourses that come down to us there's a there are many cases but there's a case where a prince goes to see the
Buddha asks him a trick question as happens I don't know why people continue
to do this because the Buddha was never fooled by trick questions a master of rhetoric a master of debate
um I wouldn't I wouldn't have bothered to try um but Prince Abaya asked the
Buddha a a trick question does the Buddha ever say anything un that that people don't want to hear that's
unpleasant or painful to hear and the Buddha says well that's not a um that's there's no simple yes or no
answer to that and proceeds to give the prince a teaching and I'll just give you a flavor of it I paraphrase I'm not
quoting that would take more time than we have but the Buddha says the Buddha
does not utter speech that he knows to be untrue false pointless that is
disliked by others he doesn't utter speech that he knows to be true and correct but which would be harmful and
disliked and it goes on gives a very careful screening but what it I think
implies for us is that before we speak if we if our aspiration is
to be awake in the world um that before
we speak we should give thought to these things the Buddha gives this
complicated complicated uh carefully delineated screen for thinking about how
he might speak and can be simplified in the following way essentially uh the
Buddha says that if something is not of benefit to others we shouldn't speak
it if we can determine that something is of benefit then we should choose the
right time to express it and I love this I love the more
complicated screen but I love this two-part uh summary or two part essence
of it that because I can kind of quickly go is this a benefit I mean I can tell
in my own mind frequently this is not really this isn't going to serve anybody myself others it's not going to it's not
going to support a healthy relationship so I can I can abstain from
that that speech that would be harmful and similarly if this is speech
that this is something to be expressed that is a benefit to myself to others to
this relationship then I wait for the right time both of these things mean I end up
speaking less and uh in in my particular case to share something personal um as a
as a loquacious talkative person and as a man in our culture and Society
somebody who comes forth as a man um it's very useful to speak less to to
because I found over time in the practice as I've been doing this that when I speak
less others speak more and I hear more I I I'm aware of other people's thoughts
more I already know what I think yeah um so saying it sometimes uh
you know isn't useful isn't of benefit
so uh the um the the story that I may mention
of it ends in a really funny way there's a lot of humor in these old sources uh
if you look for it the Buddha was a funny person could be um so the prince
asks the Buddha you know this is this is amazing this answer so do you as a Buddha as a fully awakened person do you
when somebody approaches you with a complicated question maybe a trick question do you have to think in advance about your answer or does it just occur
to you on the spot the Buddha says to the prince well let me ask you a question you're a prince
you're an expert in chariots a lot of princes were experts in chariots it's one of those princely things you AR
arrived places in a chariot and I I imagine in my mind the boota pointing at a part of the Chariot he says do you do
you know as an expert charioteer do you know what this part's called this one right here and the prince says of course
I know I'm an expert in chariots I I can I know what that part is I don't have to
think about it in advance I just know it on it comes to me on the spot and the Buddha says it's like that for me
somebody comes to me they ask me a complicated question I don't have to think very much about my response it
just comes to me on the spot and this is what we talked about
earlier this week beginning the first day just that as we become more practiced as we become more awake in
this practice more awake in the world there's less and less care less and less
conscious thinking that goes into a response and more and more the response
comes naturally to us it becomes second nature to avoid harmful speech maybe to
be quieter and to engage in skillful speech so that's a theme that keeps
coming forward this week I didn't think about that in advance I'm just noting that this is a this is something
that comes to us through the the precepts that we cultivate them by abstaining from harmful practices and
what becomes more and more second nature to us is responding skillfully to
situations so this is this is how abstaining from doing harm helps us be
forces for good in the world in this practice so it's a very
it's a very powerful training this and supportive of our practice and then
supportive of the way we we expr our practice in the world particularly in interactions with with other
beings so yeah over time as we become really
awake we become as I said on the first day we become unable right like the
Buddha the Buddha is unable to engage in harmful speak because he's a person who's fully awake that's our aspiration
that as we become more awake we become more and are just unable to take life
to um take things not freely given to engage in sexual activity that's not
that's um harmful or in this case to engage in harmful
speech so what might this mean for a daily practice I'm going to I'm going to both
talk and put something in the chat and I don't know if I can do these two things at
once um but I like a practice I didn't make it
up I'm going to tell you about it and then I'm going to push send into the chat but this is a practice um that's
called by the acronym weight w a i t
weight and what it means or what it stands for w a i t i t w AIT T and now
I'm pushing to p it into the chat it stands for why am I talking W AIT t wait
why am I talking I find this a super useful way to take this uh precept into the world
to keep waiting before I respond and even waiting before I engage
in the practice so common that I'm thinking about how I'm going to respond and the other person hasn't even
finished talking talking yet I'm not listening because I'm already thinking about how I am going to have a better
response get my opinion into the world speak my truth any number of things that seem really important to me me
me uh and if I can remember this
prescription against unhelpful and harmful speech I
wait and I like to ask why am I talking or why do do I feel an urge to talk a
need to talk a need to say something a question that I particularly
enjoy in my practice with this is maybe something needs to be said here
but is it I who need to say it right sometimes somebody else might
say it possibly they'd say it better possibly they need an opportunity to speak maybe I don't have to say this
very few ideas that I have maybe I'm different from others here but very few ideas are original and uh I don't always
have to be the person who expresses something at any rate uh maybe that's
something that will be useful to take into the day wait wait without going
through the complicated screen that the Buddha provides for wise speech some of which may be familiar to some of you
simply pausing before we speak and maybe if it's helpful think is this of benefit
what I want to say and if it is of benefit is this the time to say it is
this the best time the most appropriate time the most skillful time I think what the Buddha does with
these suggestions is ask us to slow down with this action right that seems so
automatic um so so easy easily engaged in to slow down and you may also look
around and um think about
uh I'm distracted by something in the chat um may want to look around and think
about um okay I lost that thought I got distracted somebody has pointed out that
uh silent is an anagram for listen okay there's probably hundreds of
these tricks I love them they're great so that's another one listen listen I
think that's another place that weight goes and I appreciate the distracting uh chat very nice very very nice to have
added that to our to our conversation okay so think about these
things tomorrow we'll return and take up the last uh of the five precepts the last five of the five lay precepts that
are undertaken commonly by householders and lay practitioners in this practice that of avoiding what did I call it
intoxicated heedlessness um this is a prescription
to avoid using technically in the language that that it comes to us fermented drinks distilled drinks or
other sub substances that cause heedlessness or to the point of heedlessness we'll look into that uh
tomorrow and uh I look forward to that it's a perfect topic for Friday night
it's a perfect topic for a Friday but it'll bring the week to another nice clothes I wish you all well take care
till tomorrow and I'm going to sign off now and read through the various things
that have been shared in the chat very much appreciate your sharing and supporting one another's practice and
see you tomorrow
bye for