so um let's uh let's settle in we
set
so we just settle into the posture and we see what uh the
silence wants to tell us this morning this
day
maybe it's less like we tell ourselves what to do when we start
meditating and more like we listen to the
silence and take our cues from
that
re relax whatever can be
relaxed Grant permission for whatever tension remains to
remain
as we relax maybe in traumatic ways or subtle
ways the view changes
the view from the vantage point of some Tranquility changes everything looks
different it's not that uh the problems of our life the complexities of it all
resolve but everything looks different from the vantage point of
tranquility and so even if there's just one degree of
Tranquility you notice
this
Tranquility is a supported by uh narrowing the
attentional
field not insisting that other experiences
stop or turning anything into an enemy of
meditation
but the attention Spotlight some
phenomena and leaves the rest of the
world in the background in the
dark
and so maybe the sensations of
breathing or
spotl
and that's like we we just make our home
there not bracing as the rest of the world knocks on that
door but our home is there become more
more intimate with the sensations of uh
breathing our world what we call our
life becomes uh much
simpler
and of course our our worry begs for our atten attention
demands or attention and says there's so
many things to solve contingency of our existence and
each uh demands
attention
and yet if all were ever doing is solving the problem of another
moment and it's very possible to live a whole life only ever doing
that if that's all we're doing [Music] something
the heart gets
fatigued so we consent to the kind of
vulnerability the exposure of non
worry of not keeping tabs on every problem we have or
house we develop a kind of
faith in the
silence
so I'll be quiet for some minutes as we uh deepen
the intimacy with uh this smaller app sure of uh
attention
stabilizing the inner gaze even with our eyes closed it's
almost like uh visual attention
is surveying the landscape for
threat problems that need to be
solved so
we stay stabilize the inner
gaze kind of soft gaze at the the blankness behind our closed
eyes keep feeling being nourished by our
breathing whatever pleasure might might be
there the ways they inhale answers our oxygen
hunger the way our exhale expels what's used
up
often our suffering involves some measure of a
kind of hyperarousal not always but
often so we nurture this uh
Tranquility kind of Refuge of making the aperture of attention smaller
the ways we feel less bombarded by
experience then we notice how the view
changes when there's some measure even a tiny measure of Tranquility on
board
all experience is preceded by mind the
Buddhist
for
okay so welcome ah welcome
folks it's nice to uh nice to say with
you so uh
theme this week uh is uh is facets of uh of
faith in Dharma practice
um that word that word faith uh has kind of like historically evoked some some
measure of uh of Suspicion in me kind of
you know I thought that was what um that word was what people invoked when they
didn't have evidence for believing something but wanted to believe
anyway and early in uh early in
practice I I I sort of intuitively sense the power of the Dharma that it was It
was kind of pushing deep buttons inside me and in sensing that that kind of the
power of it I I sort of felt a little intoxicating you know like I could sense
the intoxicating potential of like giving myself over to
something and I didn't know what I was giving myself over to I wanted to be careful I wanted to be careful not to
give away too much of my mind so I kind of like dip my toe into practice and
then pull my toe out it's
okay and uh at the same time I did have a sense
that uh some measure of of surrender was was
really required to to deepen that that the kind of Gates of
Dharma are closed to those who will not
surrender and that was that was 25 about 25 years ago quarter quarter Century
it's really kind of wild and maybe without knowing it uh
Faith kind of snuck up on me and now just animates Dharma practice
to to a a large extent so what is what is this what is
Faith it's not faith in in Sam S like it's not faith that everything works out
okay it's not um yeah it's not naive a naive some kind
of naive hope and it's not pretending that some data some aspects of our
experience need to be discounted okay I can be faithful if I'm paying
attention to this but if I actually allow all that all that pain in or
something then I don't know the faith wobbles
but when we don't have trust in the path of awareness it seems like some
experiences must be disavowed but that gets us us into a
kind of pretend mode where we we write off some aspects of experience pretend
they don't exist when we pretend when we pretend we
confuse ourselves we alienate ourselves the Dharma never asks you to pretend
Faith your faith never asks you to pretend right it might ask you
to check out a different View but it never asks you to
pretend and so faith is is compatible uh with uh kind of openness
to all data and evidence and I've
uh I've come to associate faith not
with naiv but with a certain kind of dropping of defensiveness dropping of
defensiveness that faith is less a a kind of rigid set of views and more the
heart's gesture of uh of surrender and this is how we let go
into into our
path and so faith faith tolerates not knowing it it's not
uh it's not filling the kind of unknown or uncertainty with with with rigid
views or something like this it's more a kind of trusting
something about one's heart one's heart and
emologic um the the word apparently is some
some uh connotation of like uh uh to to place your heart upon where
where do you place your heart where do we seek our our
Redemption uh where do we invest Our Hope where do we invest Our
Hope Ain U aan suito um said something like you know
generally um generally people say the path um begins with wise view then we establish
wise view that's where the path begins he said yeah fair enough but uh
the path truly begins when the the Buddha walks into your
heart walks into your heart that that is the arising of a certain kind of
faith and I recognize that has uh that language parallels other Traditions but
there's something about that that feels feels right the Buddha walking into
one's heart faith I I realize is a certain
kind of um optimism you know it's an optim that's a word I don't know if I've
ever used that word in a Dharma talk actually optimism
uh but it's weird because it's like we talk so much about Dua I've been
studying comprehend Dua Dua you know suffering in unsatisfactoriness like all
all these years of comprehending Dua and yet at some level it's made me
quite optimistic optimistic about at least about some things it's not it's not uh
kind of uh unwavering optimism about the world or something like that I have
incredible incredible reverence for the destructiveness of greed hate and
delusion for the ways in which that gets scaled in our world the ways in which it
it's being scaled by technology incredible respect for the
power of that so not optimistic in certain ways
but optimism about the heart mind and optimism about
uh about capacity of our own heart and if I had to to characterize them I
might say like Buddhist teachers tend to be a little bit um maybe a little
bearish about the future bullish about human potential
capacity there's uh there's an optimism about
about looking about awareness that no matter what pain is being known The
Knowing of it makes something else also
true an optimism about this kind of longing for veracity like just to this
truth seeking that whatever whatever we discover will make love more
rather than less urgent there's a faith in
that uh knowing that yeah the truth can hurt it can hurt a lot um but um it
won't harm your heart and that's very different that's very different it's a
faith in something like like the uh samada will will um yeah will will hurt
for sure but need not harm your
heart faith is what uh allows surrender to feel safe enough to feel safe
enough uh faith is a willingness to to fall a lot of Dharma about
falling sometimes gracefully often without any
Grace whatsoever but it's about falling it's about
groundlessness but a trust that develops that in the
groundlessness in the falling yeah
love love will catch you awareness will catch you
the Dharma will catch you so faith in
that and when this this arises you
really yeah you no longer Wonder at all if you might be
excluded from the Buddhist Grace and you no longer feel like you're
kind of like following someone else's path that you're assimilating to someone else's path
someone else's tradition no you find your belonging in the
Dharma and so this week
uh aspects of uh aspects of faith
aspects of Faith emerging from doubt faith
in in love Faith confidence in oneself faith and letting go this will
be the theme so happy to to be uh be with you and
feel um yeah connected just knowing you're out there practicing
okay folks wishing you a good
day