all right good morning good day
um it's great to see uh the chat messages flowing in and so feel a sense
of connection with you
all so this week I will be with you um for this 7 a.m.
I want to say a few words about uh the theme I have in mind uh for this week's
um both meditation and um uh dared and
I'll short uh I'll speak about the dared uh later on um but I want to offer
some uh guiding words about um uh the meditation this
morning and some of you may have been on the two we Retreat that just
finished and we were exploring uh the breath and so this week and I wanted to
kind of expand uh our meditation by exploring the overall uh
inner kind of um inner Dynamics or inner dimensions of
our being and the metaphor I use is as if we're exploring
nature and a opening to the nature within ourselves that's
embodied that involves uh various um aspect of mind
and heart and I might be using some of the
nature metaph Force for us to explore this and we'll be starting with the
First Quality and that's embodied um that has a sense of a
grounding for us and will build uh a kind of a progression uh over this next
over the course of the week um in this next few
days and so hopefully I we'll be able to discover something within and that this
nature within ourselves and
so let's begin I'm going to start with the sound of a
[Music] bell riding along with the sound of a
bell to arrive
arriving arriving
here opening to the felt sense of arriving
here maybe the sense of space is
palpable the outer space and the Inner
Space and arriving now this
moment I'm reminded that in Chinese after
often here and now has an
emphatic expression this
place this
moment arriving at where we are
and how we
are without demanding things to be
otherwise maybe feeling and sensing the overall sense of the
body sitting lying
down or whatever posture you're taking right
now if a few long deep breaths allows for deeper sense of arriving and
connecting with Here and
Now inviting a few long deep
breath and as you breathe
out settle down
here
deeper a sense of a mindfulness may become a little more
continuous
with moment to moment meing with our [Music]
experience and there may be a sense of a heartfulness whatever this word might
mean to you you don't have to figure spr
out for me there is just a sense of
opening and easing up in the heart
space maybe the chest torso
becoming available
the momentary experiences are always available to
us are you available to the moment
what's the felt sense of a being available to
you there may be a global sense of relaxation and ease
the sense of a body resting down or resting back
gently turn your attention to the lower half of the
body if you're sitting maybe feeling and sensing the
pelvic pelvic floor connecting
with the Earth underneath
chairs
couch and if you're lying down and
standing gently turn the attention to where the body make the
contact with with the Earth
underneath and sensing the firmness of the
bones in this body there is a Earth element
in the
body that is firm
solid
heavy like the sit bones rooted on Earth
feeling and sensing this earthy body resting on
earth like oders in the
riverbed what's the felt sense of the earthy body for
you you don't need to think about it trusting your own felt
sense maybe it's a
silent the Earth element in the body is a relatively
steady still and quiet
releasing the momentum to try to figure it
out trusting your F
sense sitting like a mountain
within there may be a sense of [Music]
grounding grounding in the Earth element in the body
so fortunate that this body naturally can
ground releasing the body
to the gift of
gravity sitting like a
mountain
e
for
e e
e
[Music]
so thank you everyone for your practice and uh
I feel the kind of quiet and silence here and it's
nice I want to offer a few words about um what uh I was thinking about sharing
this week uh in terms of a darad and so uh there is a short
sutta in samik AA the poly Canon that has been rather alive in
me and this is Samaya
22101 and those of you who are interesting looking it up and the sua has a few very
interesting similes and the Buddha used uh to kind
of describe some of the uh overarching
characteristics of how we cultivate and um develop uh various um capacities and
skills and uh like many of the short sutas the Sam nikaya sutas usually are
rather short um they often start with uh quite
a um dramatic or um kind of empathe and uh empathetic
kind of uh statement and unlike uh so kind of like
all the other sutas in many other sutas in saman nikaya this sutta also started
out with um a um emphatic statement about destruction
of the thingss so some of you may have heard this uh phrase uh which often is kind
of um related to um Awakening Liberation
ending Dua and uh gil on this Retreat that just
finished also used the word sting or removing of a sting in the mind that
kind of block us to see things
clearly and so it opened up with uh this
statement I say that the destruction of the tins is for one who knows and
sees not for one who does not know and does not
see I'm going to pause let the word settle I'm going to read this again see
it's just just kind of um feel what the effect of this statement for you I say
that the destruction of the T is for one who knows and
sees not for one who does not know and does not see
I kind of feel the power of this statement sometimes I would get goosebumps reading it I didn't have it
today um and then um like many of this short
sutas you follow on by saying what is it that one sees and
knows um that LE Le to this uh this way of being and so it is seeing the arising
and passing away of the five Aggregates so this week I won't talk
about the five Aggregates and because this is a quite um ex um um quite a
teaching um on in its own right so what I will be doing is to offer just a few
words about this um um but then focus on
the cultivation and development aspect of what the suut is talking
about and so five Aggregates are uh kind of ways that the Buddha is pointing at
um how some of this major humanly processes that are uh in the body mind
and heart that we tend to get entangled in them
and the Buddha is inviting us to really know and see this humanly processes in
the way they are and that they are impermanent and they're not something
for us to grasp in or clean um and yet
um in this kind of logical intellectually it's not so hard to
understand we all know our body changes our mind changes and uh we have all this
different processes are constantly changing but just knowing
this you know doesn't always seems to take us out from our cleaning to this uh
humanly process thees and that's in in the body mind and
heart and so I want to just kind of pause right now right here to reflect
about back what is this knowing and a
seeing and so in the meditation this morning I was using a
phrase again again that is felt sense or feeling and sensing our way
in and for me this phrase often uh as pointing to uh the aspect of dropping
out of maybe conceptual overlays our ideas about what our
experiences are but rather letting this um embody
a capacity to feel and sense what's here and maybe in fact we kind of
release a lot of this layers of ideas and conceptual
overlays and yet um this kind of a knowing and the seeing are not always
easily available to us and I uh was a flying home this uh
last last uh weekend from a training Retreat and I was uh sitting in the
airplane in the evening time and the flight was taking off and I was wearing
a sunglasses um after a while and I
noticed just right around the wing outside of the window formed this kind
of rainbow color um uh kind of layer and
it was you know quite miraculous uh just kind of seeing it and
being with it it was very beautiful I was just kind of paying attention to this for quite a long while
and then at some point I kind of realized oh I was wearing a sunglasses so I took my
sunglasses out oh it was kind of a brown and a gray
all of a sudden you know the whole rainbow color layer just
disappeared and that was a that was a little moment of like
[Laughter] disappointment um but this is kind of uh
the way that often times without cultivation and development with our of
our heart and mind we can be related to our world through a lot of different
kind of filters uh Concepts ideas views beliefs
that may be formed a decades or lifetimes and not realizing that we're seeing and knowing
through this and so this felt sense allow us to
drop in um in a much more kind of deeper immediacy of know KN and feeling our
way and so in the sua the Buddha went on by saying that this kind of knowing and
seeing is um will become available through kind of
wholehearted and proper cultivation and development and without cultivation and
development uh we will operate in kind of a habitual ways of relating to our experiences
through this kind of a filters that distort the
reality and so in this sutta the Buddha um kind of took a turn you know he did
not elaborate on the five Aggregates and but um he pointed
out how we may have to really give ourselves to a cultivation and
development and the cultivation is and and development that the Buddha point
out in the sua is the 37 uh wings of Awakening some of you would know you
know it includes the four foundations of a mindfulness for right effort and I'll
say dot dot dot all the way to seven factors of Awakening and and eight noble
and um the Noble eight-fold Path and it's so it's a through this
cultivation and uh again this week we're not going to elaborate on this 37 wings
of Awakening um many of you know um various aspects of this and I take that the
Buddha wasn't saying that you have to just you know do all of this but
uh there is a set of specific cultivation and that we must engage in
for us uh to begin to open up to this different way of seeing and
knowing and in fact in the susut the Buddha
said uh if someone develops their mind and heart anyway
uh in this way you know one of the 37 wings of um Awakening one of those
lists um even if they didn't have the wish to awaken it'll happen because this
it's the nature of this cultivation and the development it's very natural uh for
this um way of knowing and seeing that is undistorted to become accessible and
available and so this is a very kind of you don't have to wish that we will kind
of destruct the Anda um but instead if we give ourselves
over to the cultivation in the proper way this will
happen and so that's very different from kind of a goal or result oriented go
culture and then in the rest of the suta I'll give you a teaser right now that um
the Buddha used three different similes to highlight some different aspects of
how we cultivate um and used the simile of a
chicken and eggs and the second simile is using this
the holding uh eyes and the last assimile is this rope
used to Anchor um a ship and uh we'll unpack this assimile
for for the rest of the week and um I think uh you have a little overview
for the sua today and uh we'll end right here
so thank you everyone for your um practice and sharing this precious uh
practice space and so may you all have a wonderful rest of the day