greetings right welcome
back wonderful to be with all of you I'm seeing lots of good mornings
good days Sunshine
rain it's a pleasure to practice
together today we arrive at the fourth Noble Truth and we'll we'll open up open
up the fourth Noble Truth by talking about um a number of the
factors uh of the eight-fold path talk about it from one perspective today and then um look at the final
three factors from the perspective of meditation
tomorrow let's begin with the sitting
and the The Arc of the meditation
today begin in a usual way with some
settling and then we will look closely at uh the quality or nature
of any distracting thoughts that come up identifying their quality and then
and then looking at the way looking at the how different kinds of thoughts
influence the body how they show up as
sensation let's begin by
settling
sh returning to
Stillness returning to our sensed relationship with the
Earth supporting the
body
the air around us becoming
breath
for
if it's available to
you giving some extra attention to abide in the
body in those places in the body it feels particularly
still bringing the attention there sensing
Stillness settling in Stillness
yes
[Music]
e
for for the next part of this
meditation a bit like watching Pebbles falling into a
lake Rippling the surface
you can
try ping close attention to the influence of
thinking
with this Baseline of settledness in the
body when a thought arises we allow it to [Music]
arise no need to pick it up and run with
it but try to recognize what's
the quality of this thought is it a thought with a tinge
of boredom in it or
desire is it a thought with a just a touch of ill will or
aversion
in one word what's the quality of the
thought and then feeling its influence in the
body what's the signature of Sensations that
arises as a thought of ill will [Music] arise with a physical
contraction or
heat
tightening so what's the nature of the
thought is it a thought of kindness or [Music]
generosity
and then what's its
influence
[Music]
if there are times when no thought is
arising and no influence to
observe staying here with the body with
Stillness with peace
[Music]
I
yeah
[Music]
for [Music]
and for the last third or so of this
meditation beginning in [Music]
Stillness and observing the influence of
thinking now is there some way
that the thoughts whatever they may
be can be allowed to arise and
accompany a peace and [Music]
Stillness can that peace and Stillness
embodied be in the foreground of
awareness and thoughts can just come and [Music]
go
[Music]
for
e
feeling peace and feeling the influence of
thinking
may all beings relate
wisely the thoughts and [Music]
impulses may all beings know in embodied peace and true
freedom
[Music]
thank you
so before we begin curious how that meditation was for you how that series of exercises was
for you uh you feel inspired to write
anything in the chat about that I'm happy to know
now let's turn turn directly to the fourth Noble Truth the fourth Noble Truth is itself
this ancient path it said that the Buddha rediscovered is middle
way between uh the Notions of existence and
nonexistence and between um a sort of sensual Indulgence and self
mortification I love this phrase not falling into either of these
extremes the Buddha teaches the Dharma by the middle the middle
way so this week we we've talked about the the first Noble Truth and its task
or practice of understanding we've talked about the second Noble
Truth um as the arising or origin of
suffering and the task of abandoning and then the third Noble Truth the good news the cessation of
suffering cessation of Dua and the task of
realizing um with some discussion about ways to stay encouraged along this
path and now we turn to the remedy fourth Noble Truth
fourth Noble Truth as it said is just this Noble eight-fold Path it's the path
of practice that leads to the cessation of suffering today we will look at um maybe
five of the factors in brief five of the eight factors of the Noble eight-fold Path and then tomorrow we'll look at the
final three from the perspective of meditation just to name them uh the
factors of the eight-fold path uh right or wise or complete
view wise intention wise speech wise action wise
livelihood wise effort wise mindfulness wise
concentration it covers a lot of ground does it not so one way to organize
or think about these uh is inspired by um a paraphrase of AA done by bod um
from the connected discourses of the Buddha and biku Bodi paraphrases it this
way one one time when a monk approached the Buddha and asked for the training in
brief basically a mon a monk uh approaches the Buddha and asks uh how do I do the practice in brief the Buddha
told him first establish yourself in the starting
point of wholesome states that
is in purified moral discipline and in Right
View then when your moral discipline is purified and your view is straight you
should practice the four foundations of
mindfulness this is an important pointing putting Right View and uh what babot is translating as moral discipline
laali is probably CA um Reflections on wise action wise
speech white livelihood having these as the basis because we may know the way that uh a
mind a mind that settled in itself through non- regret um contributes to a sense of
Stillness and for liberating insight to arise for us to be freed of this uh
first Noble Truth of suffering um some great measure of Stillness very deep very deep is
necessary so let's talk a few minutes about right view with a little bit of a
smile I offer I offer this uh quote that I think I picked up from guy Armstrong's
book emptiness and I believe he's quoting Yogi Bara and if you don't know where you're going you might end up somewhere
else so maybe we could say this is the function of Right View wise view bbod
puts it another way he says to attempt to engage on the practice without a
foundation of Right View is to risk getting lost in the futility of undirected
movement maybe we know some of the ways of practices but we don't know how to orient it
it I'd need to do a little bit more research of the word but I I think that the poly word Sama that's uh the right
wise or complete and right right view right intention Etc I believe it has a a
a connotation of orientation I'll have to double check on that but I I like to think that each of these factors is part
of the noble Eightfold Path because it points Us in the direction of Liberation it's rightly directed we know
where going and we move in that
direction so it's said that just as the dawn is
the Forerunner of the Rising Sun So Right View precedes all of the other
wholesome factors and we know that right view as with the rest of the Buddha Dharma it's
not um it's not merely theoretical a Right View has an influence on our on
our actions on our values the way we think the way we
speak so um how do we understand Right
View few a few points one is that uh in summary Right View is an understanding
that our actions have effects and that those those actions can
have beneficial effects or they can have harmful consequences and then this final
important point that we have a say in choosing an action that is
beneficial as best as we can see or choosing an action that's harmful so our actions have effects
harmful or beneficial and that we have a say the
um the there's a I had I had a memory actually while I was thinking about
when I was living at tasahara we're we're 14 miles away from anything
in the wilderness and um sometimes it was you know maybe 40
monks there for 3 months at a time and it was very easy to see in that
cloistered setting very easy to see how an action has a consequence in the
community in some ways you you could um you could see you could see your words
and deeds Ripple around and have an effect it was so palpable the influence
of our actions on others and on ourselves felt a little bit like being a goldfish goldfish in one of those little
goldfish aquariums you can see all the little movements of the fins and the the
way that the mouth opens and closes it was so plain to see uh for
example um one let's say two seconds of unskillful
speech in such a small community that's that's close together like that you
could see the effect just Ripple through beings and then it it could it could take just hours of care to um
address so this is cause and effect our actions have consequences and we have a
say and whether we choose beneficial or harmful consequences
on another level elsewhere the Buddha defines Right View as uh an
understanding of suffering an understanding of the arising or origin of suffering an understanding of the
cessation of suffering and an understanding of the way leading to the sensation of suffering sound
familiar do you hear the four noble truths just our our study this week our
study of the fornal truths is part of this training in Right View wise View and both of the these modes uh thinking
about um actions and consequences and studying the four noble truths both of these contribute to the path of
Liberation so the basis in the Su that biku pointed Bodi pointed out wise View
and then there's conduct so let's talk let's talk in brief about four of these factors of the Noble eight-fold Path
that I'm grouping Under The Heading conduct so wise action wise
livelihood right speech right intention here we can apply a principle
we talked about uh with the first Noble Truth that is um closely
observing our actions and their effects and then making room for new possibilities in our conduct for the
purposes of developing the path of practice you can think about think about
um viewing uh wise conduct under all four of these factors as um um observing
and practicing from gross the gross level the easy to observe level to a very subtle
level on the level of the body we can look at WISE action and wise livelihood this is maybe the easiest to
observe um if you do a physical action you can see it you can see it on my
camera now whereas a an attention for example is not so not so visible take
some greater Stillness the way the training is done in refining our conduct for the purposes
of Liberation is twofold there there's this first aspect of refraining from refraining from what
is harmful in a sense it's a training and restraint it it certainly sounds like
restraint and then uh the other aspect is this this
creative open possibility something some sort of new conduct happening uh there's
the refraining from aspect and then there's bringing forward the
beautiful so we can look a little bit more closely at this if we if we zoom in on uh right
action three of the things that are uh advised to refrain from in practicing with right
action one is intentionally harming living beings two is taking what's not given
and the third is those those uh ways of engaging in our sexuality that do
harm these are the things we we hold we we restrain or we um we uh certainly
observe um and then there are positive Associated behaviors and virtues so
instead of harming living beings or taking what's not given or harming through sexuality we cultivate actions
and virtues based in kindness and compassion honesty and contentment and
generosity and then very briefly just something about right
speech uh Gil has this uh great saying if you want to learn
about about yourself study what it why it is you say what you say
can study where your intention and your speech come together and the training as we're
talking about it is to refrain from that speech that's harmful that's say
dishonest that's harsh that's um divisive that's frivolous or maybe just
untimely and then open the possibilities for yourself of speech that's kind
speech that's needed or necessary useful honest
Timely can be useful to um en Envision those those two sorts of
speech and and sense into our sense for ourselves which ones are conducive to
Harmony which ones are conducive to offering our attention in a beautiful
way and in right intention underlies all of these right action right
speech why is our intentions are so important in the Buddha Dharma because they
influence uh sort of the we'll say maybe the moral weight of an
action we observe the effects of our actions and we observe the intentions of our actions
both so to close I'll just um offer bobot's paraphrase again that first we
establish in starting uh the starting point of wholesome States purified moral
discipline and in Right View and and then when those are established practice
the four foundations of mindfulness so we'll turn to the Noble eight-fold Path the last three factors
in relationship to the four foundations of mindfulness tomorrow please take care everyone may all beings may all beings
be free from suffering and have the causes of Happiness take
care