well good evening everyone my name is Jim padowski I'm
filling in for Diana today she's away this
week uh for those of you who have uh been tuning in for the last month or so
over the last three weeks she's given a series of talks about um asking questions questions in
practice and I think she covered the material very
well um
so it did um spark me to think more about why I do and don't ask
questions I started uh formal education I guess when I was
three years old going to preschool and I finished graduate school when I was 29
so I had a lot of years of being in um institutional settings where there was
teaching going on and there were also opportunities to ask
questions and I think during that time you you
know mostly I avoided asking question questions you that's absolutely
necessary um I was kind of shy uh kind of um
introverted uh I like to figure out things on my own
um and also I had judgments um about myself and also
judgments about the other students you know like there was a saying that some along
the line I I probably heard it a number of times was there's no such thing as a
dumb question I didn't really believe that I
heard a lot of questions that I personally judged as dumb
um including my own um it wasn't until I was in graduate
school that I had a professor uh George Pim tell he was a
world class uh chemist at Berkeley and you know he invented the
chemical laser he sent a infrared spectrometer to Mars to study the
atmosphere he was very involved in um developing teaching methods for U
teaching in chemistry so he was quite an accomplished
person and I often would get to sit in seminars with him you know the physical
chemistry seminar and graduate student seminars and he seemed to have no qualms
about asking what I thought were pretty basic questions you know pretty simple
questions and I thought well he can get away with
that because he's already got this wonderful reputation I can't ask a simple question
like that as a grad student I have I have too much to lose right um but he was a wonderful example for me
you know of if you don't understand something you can ask a
question and I suspect
that um at least some of the time some of the questions he asked maybe ones
that he already knew the answer to but he may have um realized that there were people
in the audience that didn't understand this and that he was willing to ask the
question that no one else was so
um I always carried him around as a Exemplar
of um being willing to
ask being willing to let your curi osity lead as opposed to Your
Ego um some years later in the next decade I
was on a campaign to uh South America we in
Pinas Chile and making the first Airborne measurements of the Antarctic
ozone hole and so there's a big science meeting room probably twice as big as
this full of scientists who you know had been selected to to study this um brand
new phenomenon and the speaker was the
person in charge of this whole group and he kept talking about the Antarctic Vortex and they draw sort of cartoonish
pictures of what it looked like and at some point I realized I don't I don't really get this I don't
you know there's something missing so I raised my hand and I asked this very simple question about this Antarctic
Vortex which everyone had been talking about and it really just stopped his
talk you know he said oh yeah that's right yeah you know we we draw these simple pictures but let me give you more
detail and um it looked like everybody sort of woke up in the room when they started getting
this getting the answer to this question so that's
um encouraged me to keep asking those kind of qu you know to to being willing
to um admit that I don't know it
all
um I was also thinking about Diana's talks she did talk
about um not just the important of asking questions like any old
question but she also talked about
um how not all questions are created equal you know there are some
questions that will help you along you know kind of help you through
the uh I don't know the fog or the mud or ever leading on to a place of Greater
freedom and some questions don't some questions can just lead you either into
diversions or into kind of um getting trapped in
Cycles uh when I first learned computer programming in the
1970s uh languages allowed you to make a a lot of mistakes and so you could you could
write computer code that would go into an infinite Loop it would just keep
going on and on and on and there'd be it would never meet the Criterion to get
out um you know eventually your allotted time would run out and the thing would
stop having just sat there spinning for a long time and so I think the same
thing can happen in practice as well you know you can you can get caught in these uh
Loops um one of one of the ones that Diana talked about I think it was last week was you know
about rebirth you know like who was I before I was born who am I going to become things
like that that you could spend all sorts of time speculating about but wouldn't
really get you any closer to seeing through the things that need to be seen
you know kind of seeing through delusion seeing through greed seeing through
hatred um yeah
so after hearing her talks I started to do a little bit more examination
of first of all things that
uh keep me from asking questions you know the
impediments and most of them they're all internal of course right so the first
one is um not being clear about what the
question is that I have you know sometimes there'll be a teaching and you go well yeah I don't what that that
seems contradictory or it seems to contradict something I've heard before
or it's maybe some kind of a paradox
um uh or just you know defies
logic and so sometimes either in a in a session
like this tonight or maybe in a dayong class or something
um I would know that there was something that I didn't understand but I didn't
know how to articulate it I didn't know how to put it into words to to be able
to ask it and sometimes I wouldn't the question
wouldn't gel until I got home at night or the next day or something like that
now if I was a teacher that I saw regularly like Gil at that time I would
have another opportunity to ask a question um but sometimes like in a day
long if I didn't formulate the question that came up in the morning until the
afternoon kind of the the the most
um the time had kind of come and gone I missed I missed my chance to ask the question so that's one of one of the
things that um I find has has been
a an issue is being able to have clarity
about what is it that I don't understand is there some way that I can um put that
into words in a way that doesn't
um that doesn't lead me into even less
Clarity uh and and you know and that's it's part of being human right we don't you
know uh I like to watch old Sherlock Holmes movies you know and of course he's always like he looks around and he
right away you know knows exactly what's going on uh I'm much more like His companion
Dr Watson you know he's sort of fumbling around
um let's see the the second I I'll call it impediment
is um related to Ego which is not wanting
to look bad not wanting to look
uh I don't know unintelligent uninformed
uh you know like I've I've heard talks about uh not self for
years and years and years and yet at this point I'd be a little bit
um shy about asking a teacher you know I've heard about this for 20 some years
you know can can you try can you try explaining to it it to me again uh you know so you know I I think
it's it's a common human thing I'm just not you know you got a certain sense of
uh oh wanting to look good you know wanting wanting to appear like you've
you've got it together that's one of the things that
that professor professor pimel helped me with is
that he didn't seem to have that operating you know he could just ask a
simple question and um there didn't seem to be any kind of
egoic um impediment to asking a question that you'd think he would have known the
answer to
um let's see then the third one that came to me um besides looking good
is more of a self Judgment
of how good of a question is this you know like particularly like found there
a room full of people and there's other people asking questions should I should I even be
asking this question is this is this
um time worthy
um and that's often underneath that is uh there's often doubt operating you
know doubt about is this
um you know is it is this is this going to be valuable not just to me but to the
whole group or at Le part of the group so these are all things that may
or may not strike a resonance with you um the fourth
one uh has to do
with wanting praise when I first started with IMC in
the in the late 90s back in Redwood City um um Gil was the main Monday night
teacher he's he taught maybe 50 to 70% of the time and often he
would leave time for questions at the end and when I was knew I felt pretty
confident about raising my hand and asking a
question and what felt the best at that time was when he would when he he'd
react with with that's a great question that's a really good question you know that's
insightful that's important you know uh he might even respond with asking me for
more input and that
was well I'll say it was both a stroke to my ego but it was also
there was some element of feeling validated you know that that what I had to contribute was
um appreciated and and
recognized and then after a while I noticed like I would ask a question and I might get just a very perfunctory
response he might just nod his head or he might just you know he he he he you know or
just maybe say a few words but I'd never get the that's a good question that I
was looking for and so after I stopped getting those little strokes that I
wanted I got less interested in asking him questions um you know I wasn't I wasn't
getting the uh I'll say egoic lift that I would in the first
part
and then the fifth one the F fifth impediment that I've
been able to identify um
was that you never know what you're going to get you know like I'd ask him a question
and in formulating the question I knew knew what it was that I was willing to say and what I wasn't willing to say but
then once I asked the question he might ask me a question back like why are you
asking that what you know like how does that work in your life and it's like
well no I I I don't want to go there I just I want I just want you to answer my
question uh so he might answer uh
he might do like the Buddha he might he might what Diana had said earlier was
the Buddha sometimes sometimes he just respond to a question directly somebody would ask a question he' just respond to
it sometimes he would reformulate the question a little
bit and then answer that reformulated question like he thought the question that was asked
was pretty on the mark but you know was straying a little bit sometimes he'd
answer a question with a question um which is what I found Gil
starting to do and sometimes he wouldn't respond at all he just like he he just said you
know like however I respond to that
question won't be helpful so he just wouldn't wouldn't respond
um I've only seen that happen here once that was there was one time there was a
guy sitting up on the stage he raised his hand and he asked Gil
um a question about he wanted to go into a conversation about
rebirth now Gil didn't just not respond at all he just said we're not going to
go there we're just not going to talk about that and the person got really upset and said
some unskillful things
um but you never know what you're going to get you might get a direct response you might get a
slightly a response to a slightly different question you you might get an a question in
return and you might get you know sort of
the some somewhat gracious Blank Stare like yeah that so uh th those are
the five things that have come to my mind about what has what have proved to
be impediments for myself over the years for asking
questions and um I deci well I better not stop there
there must there must be things that encourage you to ask questions right there must there must be reasons that to
uh I mean I do want to encourage you all to ask questions so the first thing that came
to me is it may bring Clarity it might be
that a teacher may say something or a teacher or one of your peers may say
something to you that brings
Clarity um you might need to hear the same thing
over and over again a number of times before it clicks
um there's cases where hearing it from one some teachers
just may connect with you better than others some may just be able to say things in
words and with uh analogies that click for you that um
other teachers don't and it doesn't mean that one is better than the other it's just that one is is you know kind of
has um there's just some
resonance so asking questions so that you can get clarity number one
um well and sometimes I found that even as I'm
asking the question the question
might either become clear or it may um transmute somewhat you know it might be
like oh yeah well that isn't really the you know it's like you might have some
insight even as you're asking the question so that verbalization process can be
very helpful in ways that you might not even see if you're just sitting there
thinking about it
um number two asking the
question may take you deeper you know both in the process of
asking the question you may go deep er um the teacher may ask a
question of you that can take you deeper um in a way that you wouldn't
have even thought uh before you asked the
question
um the third value of asking questions
is that
the more you ask questions it's kind of like a muscle the better the more you ask the
better you can become at asking questions you know that it's
um yeah so you know you can get better
by by asking questions even if it seems kind of awkward and you're not quite
sure what's going on there is some learning that goes on by asking
questions um and then the final two have to do
with connection
um when I first came to this practice I really thought that this was sort of a
do-it-yourself practice you know you came and you heard talks
and then you went home and thought about it or meditated uh over time I started
joining uh camita groups
so where there were other people that you could ask questions of so the the
final two that I was thinking of number one is by asking a teacher a question
you can start building a bond with them you know a
connection
um so that when when times get really tough you've
got you've got an ally that you can go to and say look this is just things are just breaking
down so you know building a connection with the teacher and then the last one is
building connections with other people so you know like if you were
um if you were to ask a question you might find during the night you might
find that afterwards someone might come up to you and say well yeah you know I was thinking the same thing you know I
had that same question um we don't have so much time
to interact with each other uh on Monday nights but they they
do a lot more that on Thursday nights and day longs Sunday mornings so uh
asking questions will um not only benefit you but it it can
benefit many other people in the room that hear the question because they may have the they may have the same question
and not even know it or they may have the question and not be willing to say it
so it's not
the the the benefits of our practice aren't for us alone they're for
everyone so asking questions um about things that are
unclear to you may help others so those are the those are the
five uh impediments that I found and the five
benefits and
I hope you you'll contemplate those and we now have about 15 minutes
to uh if you want to ask questions or make
comments
um yeah
no no I don't I don't well for the folks U there's people online
online anyway uh there's many more people you can benefit with your
question by online well these are just comments what I really hate is when somebody I ask a question and then they
ask me a question in return it's like they're avoiding answering it and that to me is very irritating uh you follow
what I'm saying I ask a question question he or she responds with a question and it's
like he avoids he or she avoids answering the question ah no well I
thought everybody knew that experienced that and the other thing is when a politician gets up there
and he says that's a really good question and then he or she does not answer the question I mean
yeah well next no well thank you for that
that thank you for that I I suspect sometimes a teacher may be avoiding
answering the question no no I'm not talking about a teacher I'm talking about just a normal human oh no I see oh
okay yeah because I don't think a teacher would do that politician yes an
unfriend yes yeah there's
something thank you um very interesting discussion um so I I was drawn to sort
of three things um the first is um I I too am a Scientist and whenever I go to
a scientific meeting and either give a lecture or I'm in the audience uh many
of the questions actually F fall into a couple of interesting categories the first is
uh not really there to clarify something about the talk but actually to add
something that is often to Your Ego Point well well you forgot something that I've done that isn't in your
lecture right that's a probably you know 30% of the you know the questions and
then there are uh and that's not really a question it's a comment then then there are questions
that have nothing to do with the talk and have something to do with something else that they felt should have been in
the talk and those are sometimes useful right uh and and so often very few of
the actual questions are relevant to the talk like your point about the vortex right actually please explain something
uh and and partly because they're not in that student mode they're in the let me show off what
others you know are going to need to know about me rather than about the topic at hand and and to your point
about the professor having taught for a long time too you often want to take the
socratic position which is to ask a question that is often seemingly simple
but opens up what is an important topic that has confused the group or that you
want the group to kind of steer at leasts to sort of the second set of questions that I was thinking about which are those kind of Socratic
questions right and the socratic dialogue which are really a bit of a back and forth and a way to probe a
topic by you know the the kind of tennis of back and forth questions that often
illuminate in other ways right um and then the last
is legal questions and if you've ever been deposed or part of a
deposition um it's a very structured way of going through and
inquiring uh but when done right it's actually quite interesting as a way of probing and getting information out that
you wouldn't want otherwise be able to get out so in the law you only allowed to ask questions you can't you know the
lawyers are to ask the questions to get information out so anyway that you know may maybe three unrelated things but to
me that's where my mind went and and so in my own meditation you know which of these do I want do I want to actually
impress myself as I sit there because I often do that in meditation right you know or do I really want to kind of
probe and get at some really difficult thing that I'm grappling with and spend that time you know focused on it
and what's the best way to do that is it a kind of structured way because sometimes I do sort of resolve math
problems in that way right you know you go and you sort of sit there and just by thinking about it and asking yourself the questions you're able to to kind of
Whittle through anyway just my my thoughts on it yeah well thank you thank
you I can definitely say I have never thought so deeply I've been so mindful
of the whole process of asking questions as I have been through these recent discussions and it's been really
interesting to think about all the topics that have been raised in connection and um I thought it was funny
that you raised one of my current questions which is like the proper
balance of self not self and I guess that's probably a question that a lot of us have which just ongoing because it's
complicated right but um I just uh I appreciate the conversation because as
we've delved in it's become more and more interesting to me as we've gone
along yeah yeah thank you thank you for your
input this is kind of a group question uh I've noticed I I do a lot of
visualization things from the practice stick with me if I have a visual or some
little memory about it so lately I used to think of my thoughts
kind of like a a untrained puppy that I would try to be kind to the
puppy and you know that I was kind of on that image for a while and lately uh the
image that came to mind was for a few weeks is that it's like the junk drawer in my kitchen my mind and so
different stuff pops up and circulates around and anyway so my question is do
other people have these kind of um
visualizations or ideas about the practice it could be your mind state it
could be anything but do do other people have these ideas and do they shift
through time to different visualizations y I
can um yeah like you I have like uh I also like do visualizations and it
shifts from time to time for sure um one that really was very powerful for me um
and I did this for like a a month where every night I would just like imagine as
if I'm basking in the sun which is kind of funny cuz like it's at night so there's no sun um but like kind of just
like Imagining the warmth just like pouring over me um it really helps me kind of just like really calm down and
um it really Mellows like all the thoughts um which makes you know like uh
meditation and reflection on the different things especially the hard things like a bit more approachable um
cuz it Mellows it down and kind of softens it um so that's that's one um
visualization that I think was very helpful for me yeah thank
you was gonna say I was thinking right right brain
left brain or something but that is possible yes so I was listening to your five uh
ways of avoiding questions and I of course could identify with all five of
them especially number four because um when I had this brilliant question in my
mind and I said okay I'm going to ask it and it will be good and I I will look
great asking a question that I don't ask the question so that's but I would like
to offer a six one which I think if if you mentioned it I missed it
and that is a sort of laziness and what I mean is that uh during uh my practice I it never
happened that I asked the question and in the after I got an answer there was a
shift that I was always looking for shift in Clarity shift in Insight shift
in knowing myself better that never happened immediately but it does happen
uh but it doesn't happen immediately it happens as you said when others are questions when when you read the same
text over and over over again and suddenly out of nowhere that shift comes
so but but it doesn't come from a question so I
don't I don't have the um the desire to to ask a question I just hang out and
wait and that's I I see it of laziness because as many people pointed out
asking questions is a good thing not just for yourself but everybody
so yeah thank you yeah I think one something that occurred to me is
um years ago when Gil would talk about doing
um noting practice in meditation you know where you'd make silent mental
notes about what's happening right now in some ways that's kind of a
question right like well what's happening and that can get fairly complicated you
can come up with very you know elaborate descriptions of what you're experiencing at the
moment but one of the questions that was helpful for me is just like sitting
there paying attention to your breath and going going what is
this you know what's happening right now what what is this and it isn't
that the answer is important but it's the
continually continually looking you know continually asking what what's going on
right now you know what is what is this um and that sense of curiosity I
mean that can help build the sense of curiosity at least for some people may maybe for you it's not the same and it's
a different process but you know just you
know years ago I used to be involved uh with with a group and um there was
a mytho poet Michael me and he said
it's not about getting better answers it's about getting better and better
questions you know so finding better and better questions about what's going on
so I'll leave you with that and but thank
you for your uh your share
I don't want to leave you out SP do you do you have anything that you want to say maybe I just have have
one I have a just a comment um I really enjoyed it Jim thank you so
much for sharing this 10 like five five
um thoughts and I'm just thinking right now now like
I am really I've always been very shy uh when when it came to asking
questions and basically I'm avoiding all my life I'm avoiding and I was thinking
you know the kind of the the two things that I think it's
it's a very cultural thing uh it uh like the combination of like what you called
expecting praise or you know and on the other hand um this is very like
the given my background like it's kind of like that that that's what it all was
about you know you ask questions in order to to
shine and not to and and then at the same time um asking questions was considered
to be like you basically reveal yourself as an uninformed you know unknowing
person so it's kind of I'm I was listening to you and I felt like wow a little bit of
a relief that I'm seeing this clearly and um kind of it's not yeah so it's not
it's not just me I'm so like you know never know what to ask or how to do that
there's a lot of that like deep conditioning and heavy conditioning and
I'm very very also want to say I'm very inspired by your last idea by your last
but what you said about how it's it's connecting us you know I'm asking not
just because I want to know because I kind of also want this connection to happen so thank you so much I really
enjoyed it very much yeah thank you thank you
s so we have a few minutes this does anyone else
um want to
share well if not um first of all I want to say I
appreciate all of you I appreciate all of you for coming
and for listening and
um both for sharing your your questions and your comments and for all of you for
sharing your presence for you know sense of being here and and listening
um I have to say you know and Diana sent me
this email the end of last week saying I forgot to get a teacher I was a
little I was a little apprehensive but uh I really like the way it went tonight
so thank you all