good morning warm greetings everyone Global IMC
sa my name is Da and I'm back with you for a fifth day out of five this is a
sound check hope everyone's doing well today it's lovely to see all of your chats to each
other good morning
everyone just love seeing how this community has
gotten to know each other over the years of these streaming
sits warm good morning to friends and on the chat and to people who I know well
by name and thank you for the sound check great okay so happy to be here here with
you you may notice my background is different today I am zooming in from Tucson
Arizona where I'm going to be um on a teaching team for a retreat in um coochi
stronghold a nature Dharma Retreat later today so I am perched in a place right
outside the airport and delighted to be with you all right with that let start the
recording and good morning
everyone the invitation is to settle in to a meditation
posture and this morning we're going to be working with flowing from directed
awareness to open awareness and back a little
bit so perhaps first just noticing any response in your heart in your mind to
the chats the warm greetings the hearts the moving text if you see it the fact that
it's there and whatever those responses are just to feel in feel into your heart
feel into your body and
notice
notice and then more generally to
scan through your whole body and notice your posture level of
energy any feelings of pleasant and
unpleasant and noticing any responses to the way things are this morning just as they
are
and then more globally noticing an internal temperature check
weather check how is this body heart this mind
the general mood today in this moment for
you and with that perhaps taking a couple of longer slower
more intentional
breaths and allowing your body your heart your mind
to settle here in
meditation Shifting the attention inward
noticing if the breathing feels Pleasant or
otherwise and the invitation is to settle in either on the felt sensations
of the whole body or
to zoom in just a little bit the selective attention on the body
breathing allowing the breathing to be
natural giving yourself over dedicating the attention
to these sensations of your
aliveness
perhaps noticing encouraging a little bit more relaxation on the out
breath noticing the aliveness of the in
breath
and a tuning tuning into the details the texture of
each arising sensation of breathing or in the
body the beginning of the breath the body of the inhale of the
breath the fullness of the full inhale
and the relaxation on the out
breath letting
go dedicating the attention directing the attention for
this little
while
now if the attention feels a bit settled the mindfulness feels a little
bit more present the
invitation is to open up into a
broader awareness for example including any
senses of vibrancy or aliveness throughout the
body perhaps an overall sense of the outline of the
body where it meets air skin meets air or
cloth sense of all the little pulsing and tingling
perhaps associated with the aliveness of being present
within this
body noticing weight lightness warmth
cool and opening still f
further to
hearing whatever might be in your visual field be your eyes downcast and soft or
closed the Darkness and Light of the visual
field
perhaps little blips of thought or emotion all of it
included bringing the attention to the full scope
wash of the moment as it flows by as it flows
through if a particular thing becomes
obvious hearing for example noticing that
for as long as it's most
predominant and then as that Fades allowing the attention to rest on
the next obvious thing whatever it is no need to go
looking allowing the moment to come to you
allowing sound to be sound sensation to be
sensation emotion to be emotion thought to be
thought noticing feeling tone Pleasant unpleasant
neither
into the final moments of our meditation together
the invitation is to recollect these last moments of
practice intentionally bringing to mind any moments of
mindfulness patience [Music] calm good goodness of any
kind and appreciate it appreciate these
moments and then more broadly appreciating
yourself your fellow practitioners here for taking the time
it's a cultivated practice it's a beautiful thing to
do and from that place of appreciation allowing acknowledging anything that may
have not been so easy in these moments with kindness
compassion appreciation for the effort of showing
up and with that openhearted
attitude allowing in images or thoughts of the others in
your life the people the other
beings anyone who's life touches yours directly or
indirectly and if it feels right offering the wish that our practice here
together May benefit
them May our practice here together be a
cause and condition for greater
Freedom peace joy and Awakening in the
world
for greater Freedom peace
joy and Awakening in the [Music]
world for greater
Freedom thank you
everyone thank you for the sincerity of your
practice
so good morning
special welcome to those of you who arrived a bit late into the
YouTube sit together delighted to be with you my
name is Da Neil if we haven't met yet and um this is the fifth of five days on
the Essential Elements some other essential element of mindfulness
practice kind of design to complement what Gil Fran's been doing for the last
number of weeks introducing mindfulness and today we've reached the
last of these talks and um it is on open
awareness otherwise known as choiceless
awareness though that's a little bit of a misnomer because the mind is always choosing to pay attention to something
we're not going out and intentionally directing our attention
so I'm going to start this morning as I did yesterday with a little
exercise and the exercise is to notice perhaps your
hand and notice your hand From the Inside Out
allowing awareness to fill your hand soak into it
the way water soaks into into a
field feeling it as if sponge like soil we're
absorbing it and then to expand expand your
attention to your arms
shoulders neck core whole
body allowing allowing awareness to fill your
body the way water fills a
sponge with fullness of
embodiment and
now allowing the capacity of seeing and
hearing emotion mood thought whatever space you're in all of
that to be included in present moment
awareness
without choosing anything in particular
including the screen that you're looking at or the hearing through which you're taking
in this talk but not privileging
anything General presence in this moment of
now so that that's the process of opening to open
[Music] awareness I gave the analogy yesterday of directed awareness being like looking
for and finding a friend in a crowded place maybe at a distance in a plaza or
something and then honing in on that friend as you're walking towards them so
that you don't lose them in the crowd before you get to them and of course
everything else is there but the attention is primarily on this person as you're navigating
through so that's directed attention open attention is being open to the wash
of the whole crowd without looking for anyone maybe as if you're seeing a big
Stadium full of people and you're just taking in the fullness of the crowd maybe the music
the activity the light all of it it's noticing the forest not the
individual trees necessarily noticing the whole
ecology and it's a receptive kind of awareness that then allows anything to
continue with this tree and Forest metaphor if a bird flies by the
attention can take that in but it's not like you're looking for the bird it's a
natural capacity so in open awareness attention
is relaxed you let things come to you and this allows the attention to for
a little time settle on notice whatever is most predom Min most
obvious I'll use one more example here those of you who practice Tai Chi or
Chiang may be already aware of this but this
[Music] um process of right now many of you are looking at a screen so the invitation is
to notice your peripheral vision around the screen or whatever you're looking at
and this can be done done by looking at your hands perhaps in andly or
gsho and then slowly bringing them apart maybe moving your fingers a little until they're further and further off to your
sides and noticing where the peripheral vision
loses the capacity to see the hands but staying in that broad wash of
seeing there's no one particular thing in Focus until something
moves so as someone mentioned in the chat open
awareness can naturally arise with a lot of practice of directed awareness and
for some people it doesn't feel natural at first other people it's how they
start it's the easiest way to start the point here isn't necessarily
to encourage you to do it instead of directed awareness it's to highlight
what meditation often includes anyway or what can develop what teachers teach
about and I'll talk a little bit about the why why it might be useful why it
might be interesting to experiment with now and then so open awareness the practice of
it the arising of it develops a capacity to stay present in a wide range of
situations meditation is the process of cultivating our minds and the cultivation of open
awareness begins to inculcate develop a broader
capacity to take in everything around us in all kinds of situations walking
down the street washing dishes talking to a friend whatever it
is and that's useful it's also so a way in formal sits
of including this full range of the different kinds of objects of attention
mindfulness of that Gil has brought in in the last weeks mindfulness of breath
of sensation and body of emotions of
thoughts includes Vena feeling tone the pleasant unpleasant and neutral all
kinds of reactions impulses and attitudes that emerge from that and that act back onto
it and what all of this can do the attending to this full spectrum
full range of what's arising now is it reveals more about
how our our inner ecology our inner Life
Works in the moment works in the moment so there
is this sense of using your Dharma
intelligence using your natural capacity to notice cause and
effect increasing wisdom noticing in the moment what's
easeful and what's helpful in what's not so easeful not so
helpful one way of staying aware is to
notice if there's tension or if there's stress or if there's
ease relaxation so noticing getting
interested in what's easeful and what's not what's easeful and what's
not and then noticing and allowing every everything to unfold for the
purpose of allowing things to come and go and noticing what things are helpful
to cultivate and what things are helpful to let go of maybe I can let go of
that analysis of thinking about that thing and relax more into my
body so how open awareness shows up it's like softening your eyes like
the exercise we did a few minutes ago and if you soften your eyes that can actually softening The Gaze can help to
soften the focus of the mind too and there's a gentle effort a light
persistence in noticing gentle presence gentle presence
noticing now and for most
people it's really not possible to be aware without a specific any kind of
guidance or any kind of object but to start with noticing the
body and noticing as I talked about before seeing hearing sensing and then
allowing this comes easier for some people than others some people it's totally natural and other people find it
much more natural to start with directed attention on the breath and the body and stay there for a
while as we did this morning until the attention opens up and then it's easier
to feel the flow of different objects of attention coming through and allow them
to come without looking for them so if you've only ever done one of
these you might play around with maybe listen to this recording again or watch
it again and play around with accessing a more open kind of awareness it's like a cross training it
can build a capacity for more
um ways of cultivating the goodness of awareness of
mindfulness so I hope that this was helpful this
week these days this 45 minutes in considering the difference between
directed awareness and open awareness and the way open awareness can open us to the full
range of human experience in the moment thank you so much it's been a
delight to be with all of you this week and since there's not time for Q&A as I
promised yesterday I'm going to put a link in the chat my blog is down right now I'm having website Dua
but um my other website allows a contact form and you're welcome to send questions directly to me and I'll send a
link out to a Blog for answers sometime around the end of this month or the beginning of next
month so that
link is now in the chat
and thank you again s for a wonderful week thank you most of
all for the sincerity of your
practice it's a beautiful thing you're doing may all beings benefit from our
practice here together