welcome good day hope you're doing well and
uh today we turn to the fourth of the five spiritual
faculties and this is the faculty of the the collected still mind that we
cultivate in the meditation and I'll talk today in the
brief daret about how this this faculty this competency
this quality of mind
this capacity of mind is related to mindfulness which we talked about
yesterday and also give a couple pointers about
um how to create sufficient steadiness of mind to see clearly which is the
the particular benefit that this Factor provides to our
practice so I may seem a little uh distracted by the technical
challenge this morning that don't let that throw you
off it's just the
internet so so let's begin by sitting meditation we'll
bring our attention this morning to the Stillness and steadiness that's
available to us in the
meditation and perhaps even as we just begin to sit and bring our attention
Inward and downward we can
recognize the greater Stillness of the meditative
space most of us have been meditating long enough that the contrast between
our what I think of is the walking around world the the getting through the
day in our practice world with the formal sitting practice which we engage
now that there's a greater Stillness a greater collectiveness a
greater focus a greater uh Unity of
attention and we can bring attention to this knowing that giving it the gift of
attention strengthens it cultivates it so once
again in the case of this fourth fourth faculty
wholeness of the mind or wholeness of attention in the meditation we don't have to reach outside our own
experience we can look within and by noticing
any degree of Stillness of collectiveness of calm of ease in the meditative space we can
further strengthen it and a particular instruction that we
can remember today as we come back to the breath over and over again strengthening our ability to return to
be here now we can connect again with the breath
at hand whichever one we first connect with an out breath here and INB breath
there so we come back to Center we can just say softly to
ourselves breathing in steadying the
Mind breathing out steadying the
mind we can add breathing in gladdening the
mind breathing out gladdening the
mind and these soft reminders to ourself Upon Our return to Center
can bring greater steadiness collectedness to the mind and also enjoy that greater
steadiness and collectiveness enjoying it in a way that
strengthens
too to these two phrases we can add a third breathing in
letting the Mind rest breathing
out providing a place where the mind can
rest so any one of these three all of them
together in any particular order can be useful phrases to drop into
the meditation when we return with the breath
steadying the mind gladdening the
mind letting the Mind rest giving the mind a place to
rest
e
e e
so it's a natural thing that the Mind Finds Its way into activity gets
caught up and looking forward looking back looking outward looking
inward it's the mind's job those are capacities of mind that
are welldeveloped we return to
Center to strengthen capacities of mind that are less
developed we appreciate the others and in this practice we
cultivate the capacity of mind to be still to be clear to be
here when we return attention to the Here and Now of our
experience we can drop in these phrases connecting with this in breath
breathing in steadying the mind gladdening the mind
resting the
mind
e
e e
finding our way in the practice
to this breath right here and
then breathing in steadying the
mind breathing out steadying the
Mind breathing in gladdening the mind breathing out gladdening the
Mind breathe in letting the Mind
rest breathing out letting the Mind
rest we can take this Stillness with us this mindful attention this sustained
mindful attention this still collected grounded mind it's
portable we can carry it with us into the interactions of daily
life we can call on this quality of mind this capacity of mind when it's needed
the stronger it is the more we cultivate it in the practice the the easier it is
to find it when we need it the easier it is that it becomes over
time second nature that it arises to meet
life and as we cultivate it we can share it
May the benefit of our practice May some of the Stillness the
calm the ease and meeting experience the sustained ability to give
attention May these Ripple out into the world and benefit other other
beings may all beings share and some of this contentment some of this
ease may all beings be free
[Music]
welcome again friends and so far we've been having
good good internet connectivity I expected to fail at any moment and that's one place my mind has
been going uh if you're just joining now this is Thursday a fourth day of
exploring the five spiritual faculties and we'll talk a little bit about some body wholeness of mind and as I guided
in the meditation the steadiness collectedness groundedness rootedness
heess sustained heess and nness of mind just making up words here
right and left where the language doesn't fit the Dharma let's change the
language I like to say the heess and nness of our experience so
I hope at some point the OED will recognize my coinages in English I
mentioned at the outset of the hour that uh I've received the word from the good
people at Xfinity that the internet's there're going to be outages beginning at 6:00 a.m. so far we're good um if I
disappear I set myself up as co-host on my phone I see all the chats about The
Echoes believe me I heard the echoes what I reflected on is how this is a nice metaphor for
suffering the constant echoing of One's Own voice in one's head uh and the ease that comes when
that Echo is reduced or softened um maybe we come to understand its function
better and we can thus let go of it a little bit at some point in attempting to uh
address the echo which I I I use zoom a lot so I know the echo thing this is a little different issue and I finally um
thought okay I'm going to use an old trick I'll just put the phone under my leg and there will you know I won't be
able to hear the Echo and uh that disconnected the meeting at which point there was this
lovely silence as that Echo stopped and there too I was like oh okay there's
that there's that ease that comes with the relaxing of that echo of my own
telling myself about my experience in the world at any rate I did my best to
engage the technical challenge with with the Dharma and uh make the echo into a
teaching so and maybe I'm going to keep going with that why not yeah so this fourth factor which
is somati and I love the word in poly somati s m d s m a d h i samade it's a
lovely word it has many translations none of them very very accurate um but
the closest literally uh as Gil has probably shared is collectiveness of Mind somadi means a bringing together of
mind collectiveness of mind Stillness of mind and ease of mind
and I'll share this interesting history with
you and uh now that I've lost my other Zoom sign
in if we get cut off I'll pick it up tomorrow uh
but when the people who first translated the word samati translated it they used
the word concentration the word the meaning of the word concentration its associations
in English particularly on this side of the Atlantic um have changed since that time
when they use the word concentr it meant and I'm quoting here um the action of
bringing to a center the act of collecting or combining into or about a
central point and this is a really nice definition of uh of samade this idea of
collecting or combining into about a central point right that's one meaning of
concentration if you think about it from the Latin you don't have to speak Latin to sit in on these 7 a.m. talks
concentrate that is with the center so I like the idea that we're bringing the mind to around the breath around the
center of our spiritual life the breathing the body right our ability to
be with our experience without adding things as I've been talking about the last couple
days and then later the same word concentrate comes to have a meaning which will be familiar from other uses
which is to intensify or condense I think for example of
concentrated orange juice not very common anymore but when I
was growing up um orange juice was kind of an unusual thing fresh orange juice with or without pulp or with some pulp
wasn't really a thing fresh in the grocery aisle but rather one thing
something that one's parents made from concentrate this idea of of of bringing
the mind's ease and the steadiness of mind and the gladness of Mind sort of in
a way that intensifies it also really describes
some so when when thinking about this fourth
faculty I think the best uh the best word to use is samade and the associations maybe
that you can start create with that with that aspect of the meditative
experience so Diana Clark one of my lovely colleagues somebody I teach with uh good
friend uh describes this fourth faculty as if I something like this um a
Stillness of Mind accompanied by a feeling of well-being and these two things together
are really important that there's both the Stillness of of mind and the sense of
ease or well-being that comes with it and this is why these phrases dropped into the meditation can be so so useful
that is steadying the mind gladdening the mind steadying the mind gladdening
the mind as I've been saying the last few days the gladdening is important
because it helps us um it helps us appreciate and it
actually triggers important things in the brain that this pleasure taken in the steadiness of Mind helps us um helps
us strengthen it another way to think about strengthening or cultivating is just it helps us create a path we talk
about the path of practice part of the path is getting figuring out remembering
how to get back here and you know if you think about a well-known path in your life you know to this 7-Eleven at the
corner or to work or to we we we develop a path and then it becomes automatic and
this is true with the practice too that as we go oh this is how the mind is
steadied we become so used to recreating those conditions that support that
steadiness of mind that we forget that there's a there's a path we're following
and part of that path I think the the cookie crumbs along the path or the uh markers the mile markers ERS along the
path that's the gladness oh right right I move this direction because it feels
good and it it it feels good because there's more steadiness of Mind there
and we keep inclining the mind in the direction of that
steadiness so the
um a way that can be very useful to think of this faculty of mind is how it relates to the one we talked about
yesterday mindfulness um Andrea fella co- guiding teacher of
IMC has said in the past that she likes to think of somati this fourth faculty
as a sustained mindfulness that mindfulness are attention to the present
moment when it becomes sustained and when maybe going two days back when the E when the effort involved becomes
effortless right that that that steadiness of mind that sort of
consistent bringing of mindful judgment free attention to what's coming up in
our experience in the meditation for example but also other other points of the
day that this is a way to characterize what what suade can be and I think
that's a really useful idea of Andreas just because you can it's it's another thing where we can notice that happening
we'll notice oh here's a period of 5 minutes 10 minutes half a day half an hour where there's a lot of sustained
mindful attention and we can recognize oh that's this steadiness of Mind
similarly in the meditation itself we keep bringing attention back to the breathing and sometimes we'll notice
yeah there's just this easeful being with the breathing where there's not a lot of maybe stuff's going on in the
mind but it's not it's not getting a lot of attention it's just kind of coming and going um that sustained mindfulness
that sustained gained being here that's that steadiness of mind with as Diana says a feeling of a feeling of
well-being this fourth faculty it's true with mindfulness as well in the texts we
have in the teachings they're both ends and means they're they're they're a
they're a lovely place to sit and abide as as it said and at the same time there
means to an end so mindful attention has benefits in and of itself it's always
more useful to be here now rather than there then in the
mind right present for what's coming up in our experience
um and at the same time mindfulness over and over again leads to this sustained
steadiness Stillness of mind with with ease with a feeling of well-being
and this fourth faculty samade it also is a pleasant abiding as
the text say a pleasant place to be something to take pleasure in because it's a wholesome pleasure doesn't depend
on external conditions doesn't lead to over attachment or holding on we can
try but eventually we learn oh it's just a pleasant place to be without strings
attached as it were um and it too in addition to being a
pleasant abiding in the Here and Now is a means to an end and uh there's a
lovely phrase from the texts that I'll read you where does it where does it go what what's how is it a means to an end
I got to make sure I'm not running over time I could talk about this all morning but eventually the internet
would get out I'd like to think that this profound
teaching could break the internet and yet it's just exfinity service
disruption so this phrase says practitioners you you and me
both this Stillness of mind with well-being it's like a lake in a mountain range transparent clear
undisturbed and standing on the shore of this Lake a person with good eyesight
could see oysters shells and Pebbles and fish moving about and fish holding still
and that person might think ah this transparent Clear undisturbed Lake I Can
See Clearly shells oysters Stones Pebbles fish moving about fish standing
still in shes in the very same way this Stillness
of Mind allows for Clear seeing and in particular it allows us to see all that
extra being added on to experience that causes suffering or that is suffering
and it allows us to see that the mind can be free of suffering so this is the particular
importance and power of this fourth spiritual faculty or fourth Divine human
quality that we cultivate in the meditation I like to sum this up by saying that the still mind the collected
mind the sodi mind to make up another word sees clearly the still mind sees
clearly the still mind can see the arising and passing of suffering without
getting all caught up in it just noticing the coming and
going so this is how this particular fourth faculty benefits Us in the
practice it allows us a way to be very very here with our experience in a way
that makes the subtlest arisings the subtest um creations of suffering
apparent to us and uh little by little maybe
starting with the larger grosser uh disturbances turbulence
suffering selfing that happens in the mind we can sort of um notice ever more
subtle arisings of stress and tension and suffering at that subtle level it's
easier to let go of it it's easier to just let it Bubble Up
and bubble down so may this teaching be a benefit
to you and may we I at any rate learn from today just uh uh I I really like
that metaphor of the zoom Echo that I think we've all experienced whenever you try to zoom with somebody in the same
rby if it's your stunt double in my case this
morning that uh there's a way to uh recognize that really unpleasant chatter
that comes with the echo as a nice metaphor for what it's like to be in our heads when we first sit down and
meditate all this all this me myself and I
reverberating um I think it too related the way when
we hear our voices it doesn't sound like it does in our heads so there's lots of there's lots of nice little metaphors
there that um and it's just a reminder that we can incorporate even the most
random of experiences into our practice at any rate
um may your days go well and uh and uh May that may that
echo of our attachments and um unskillful engagement with the world
maybe may may that be reduced a little bit by our practice today for ourselves and for others and may we have some of
that clarity as some of that uh ability to see clearly that comes with the
unification of mind or the sustained mindful attention to the here and now
may that be of benefit to us and to others all right I look forward to seeing you tomorrow
hopefully Xfinity will have completed its work and uh we will'll we'll take
we'll move on from here thanks very much take care