hello everyone and welcome and welcome here to IMC where
I'm sitting inside Meditation Center in Redwood City and uh very happy to be here with
you so for the meditation today I'd like
to emphasize a very important point and that is
that the the key to finding this Freedom
that Buddhism Freedom that can be found in meditation that Buddhism points to is
supported a lot by understanding or focusing on how we respond to what is
happening sometimes I've done the emphasis that there's always only two things ever
happening what's happening and our relationship to what's happening the way we but even more so the way that we
respond and that we want to kind of really stay close to how we
respond more than being caught up in what is happening so if
um if it's a hot day we could be a victim of the hot day
we could be troubled by it and upset with it and complain about it maybe
and uh or we can notice it's a hot day
the the heat is uncomfortable and I'm I'm going to stay
present for it I'm going to be open to it I'm going to um uh allow it to be there without
reactivity without judgment I will stay present and mindful
of the experience even though it's uncomfortable so we're taking the
initiative to engage in a way to be present that has to do with how we are
relationship to it that we there's a freedom there's a engagement there's a
capacity to know and so always every moment we're
in we have the opportunity to respond to what's
happening instead of reacting to what's happening which has no freedom in it we
take take we we take refuge in that place where we have some modum of
choice to be present to be mindful to be aware it's kind of like U uh in that way
we're always in the present moment the response to what's happening is a present moment it's kind of
like having caught the wave and now we're on the on the front
of the wave being carried by it rather than being in the wave and twirled
around in the Water by the wave so we're there riding it with awareness with
attention and the key thing here is that we're learning to the respond how to
respond in ways that are skillful ways that are
wholesome avoiding the unskillful UNH wholesome responses avoiding reactivity
avoiding uh being caught in the hindrances being caught by greed hate and delusion being caught by negativity
or judgment or conceit around what's
happening and instead to in be respond in ways that are deeply satisfying
respond in ways that are nourishing which is one of the meanings of
wholesome and um so to be able to respond with a simple clear awareness
that's maybe kind maybe compassionate to be present and recognize oh this is
what's happening and do so with a gentleness with an openness without a criticism without a big story
interpretation opinion but always to what's what's the the
wholesome uh response maybe it's a generous response maybe it's kind maybe
it's loving maybe it's friendly maybe it's wise maybe it's
patience maybe it's um meeting it with ethical Integrity maybe it's meeting with um
with uh appreciating the value of Truth telling being really honest oh this is what's
happening and uh and appreciating oh honesty is really a nourishing thing in
itself even though what we're honest about is difficult so every moment
we have the opportunity to respond in a way that is nourishing wholesome
beneficial nice and that's what I'd like to emphasize for today's
meditation try that and if you try too hard and it's stressful to do it or if
you are judging yourself or not doing it well enough all those are unskillful UNH
wholesome take refuge in the wholesome a wholesome way of staying in the
present a Wholesome Way of riding the wave of the of a present
moment experience in this way you can think whatever you think you
can feel whatever you feel what's important is how you
respond to what you think and what you feel can you respond in a way
that where you're free you are free enough to respond
independent of what's Happening free enough to respond with
kindness with truthfulness with
mindfulness so assuming a meditation posture and closing your eyes
and and before anything else just sitting here quietly for a few
moments taking in the experience of your body how is your body right
now and what would be a wholesome
way to stay present aware of your body whatever state your body is in
become aware of your breathing whatever way your breathing is whether it's comfortable or
uncomfortable whatever state your breathing is let it be that
way but know it be aware of it
without any judgments or criticism or self
beratement know it in a way that feels kind
supportive as if you are meeting a friend and you're meeting with
friendship your good will so meet
you're breathing that
way noticing what's going on in your mind your thoughts your thought string
Nam see if your response to whatever your thought stream
is that it's a response that feels nourishing feels
good for you because it's friendly or kind or a simple truth
telling where you are not defined by your thought stream
and then settling into the body's experience of
breathing as if the rhythm of breathing
is the ongoing basis for responding meeting the present
moment in a Wholesome Way not straining not
judging not afraid
you might be all those ways but let the awareness that
knows be something that feels good for
you moment after moment each Act of mindfulness
a relaxed
manifestation of being a friend for all things
okay
for
e
for for
if you [Music] know what it's like to nourish
yourself to bring about a Wholesome Way way of
being something in inner goodness or
a inner
generosity can you find a way of being aware of practicing
mindfulness that carries with it in and of
itself a wholesomeness
where there's nothing you need to attain in order to [Music]
feel nourished feel
satisfied by the effort you
make
for
for for
perhaps a subtle feeling of Vitality
of energy aliveness in your
body can be the wave that you're surfing on gently softly
slowly and the surfboard on which you surf
is kindness or honesty or
gentleness something that feels wholesome a
goodness being carried
along in the wave of the present
moment
for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to turn your thoughts and your heart out into the
world and from the vantage point of sitting in
meditation can you gaze upon the world reflect on the
world in a Wholesome Way way the world that is full of good and
bad the world that's full
of people who benefit each other and harm each other with all its challenges
and all its Joys to gaze upon it in a
way as if your gaze your consideration is the
food on which the world will grow and offer the food of wholesomeness
goodness ethics ethical goodness gaze upon the
world with an an attitude that lets the good of the world
grow gaze upon the
world in what you hope the world can become
and offer your good will through these World these words may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may each of us contribute to a better
world by the way in which we meet each and every person we encounter
today may we meet this person with a wholesome attitude of care
generosity
friendliness so that we can contribute to these qualities growing in this world of
ours may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this second talk on uh an introduction to Buddhist
ethics and I'm trying to pro pro provide you with some of the
foundational attitudes approaches principles that supports Buddhist
ethics and yesterday I talked about
uh the role of harmlessness non-harming today I want to talk about a
very two very important terms I'll give you the PO the ancient Buddhist word for
it first and uh and then and then discuss them and these uh two uh the two
words are cusa k s u l a
and ausa uh so cusa is generally translated
as either skillfulness or
wholesomeness different translators translate them in different ways but if you look
for a poly word ancient Buddhist word that most closely matches the English
word ethics this would be the word there's very hard to find a good word
that matches the word ethics really well uh in p uh with uh kind of the more
sophisticated or way which ethics is understood but the closest I believe is
as Kusa so it's a very important word and it's very significant that the word
for ethics can also mean wholesomeness and it could also mean
skillfulness so skillfulness refers to that it's useful uh it's skillful it's uh uh one
can develop a skill that is onward leading to something
beneficial so uh this is the word skillful is uh the best translation in
the context of meditation we want to develop skill the skill of meditation
the skill of of spiritual practice and uh and it's a skill that we develop over
time it's like a training that uh we're training over and over again we're
practicing to become skillful in something so skillful in attention skillful in concentration skillful in um
mindfulness skillful in equinity just a whole range of things we're de
developing some of them are developing as a byproduct of doing basic mindfulness
practice uh it's not something we have to actively intentionally develop but um
we are slowly developing this skill and
um and the other word is uh translation is wholesomeness which uh uh I I kind of
interpret in as almost same terms as nourishing that which is feels really
good and nourishing for our whole system for our body mind and heart it's
wholesome there's a goodness to it there's a a very satisfying feeling of rightness
goodness that comes when we feel wholesome we feel what we're doing is wholesome there's an inner goodness to
it perhaps and um and so so much so that just doing the activity in a Wholesome
Way is deeply satisfying it's almost enough in itself just that we're doing it in this way and some activities that
we do maybe it doesn't matter so much if we're successful or not what matters is
that that was really to do that um and uh so I mean what comes to mind
is offering our seat and taking a bus and someone clearly maybe uh could use
your the seat B more than you you do and so you stand up and offer the seat but
maybe the person doesn't notice or declines and so you were unsuccessful
and offering the seat however uh so the purpose of the action you failed in a
sense however just the fact that you were uh offering the seat felt nourishing it
felt it came from the inner goodness a generosity a Simplicity of being the
kind of wholesomeness where there was nothing dependent on the outcome it were
looking for praise we're looking for Success it just like was a good thing in and of itself to
offer and there's no disappointment that the person didn't take your seat so uh what's also nice about
translating Kusa as ethics as um as
skillful is that as we um
um uh rather than asking the question is it ethical to do this or
unethical uh which carries a lot of connotations in English which are not so useful uh we ask is it skillful or we
say that was an unskillful thing to do rather saying that was a wrong thing to do or that was a bad thing to do or that
was an unethical thing to do it takes a certain kind of um uh judgmentalism or
certain kind of uh punitive quality out of our statements we're making uh and it
kind of focuses more on the the uh is it beneficial or not beneficial is it
useful and un relating in a good way or is it not so Buddhists will often ask
that question um someone has a difficult and challenging uh decision to make and
someone will they make a decision this is what I'd like to do what do you think and is it right that I do this and
rather than answering that it's right and wrong it's common to answer the question um is it skillful or I think
that's skillful or I think that's unskillful and then you can ask the question you know what is skillful or
what's more skillful or um and then but uh in particular what I would emphasize
today is the translation of Kusa as wholesome uh wholesome has a beauty to
it wholesome has a something nourishing and satisfying feels really good and uh
and to live our life uh with this uh in relationship to this possibility we have
of inner beauty inner goodness inner wholesomeness inner nourishment as we go
through our lives that we can benefit ourselves internally from how we live
our life as opposed to feeling and recognizing that the way I go through my
life um yes I'm right and I'm right to be angry I'm right to be critical I I
have I'm Wiser more Discerning to other people I see what they don't see and and so I'm upset with them and critical of
them and aversive yes you might have you might have a lot of wisdom that allows you to
see that but that attitude of aversion that attitude of criticalness doesn't
produce nourishment for the heart doesn't make the heart smile or feel
feel delighted or feel content in itself and this capacity to really do the
things that act in the world so that there's a feeling of deep satisfaction
contentment happiness for how we go about our life this is possible and this is a
foundation for Buddhist ethics uh considering whether something is skillful or
unskillful considering whether it's wholesome or UNH wholesome and this wholesome quality uh
gives ethics a very different quality than uh a set of rules that either you
you follow or you don't you're breaking a rule you're a bad person because you
did something wrong but rather you're doing things that um are not rule-based
exactly uh in a narrow kind of way as Commandments that you you have to do something this way and it's either or
and but rather your reference point for how to live an ethical life is from a
deep sense of what brings uh a kind of deep sense of Joyful satisfaction some
feeling of wholesomeness a kind of a wholesomeness that has a kind of ethical Integrity to
it but not because we're being puritanical or being holding to uh
holding to rules in a tight way but rather because we know we recognize that
this is actually for our own benefit this is how we grow if you want to grow a plant you
want to make sure that it has sunlight and then it can grow if you want to grow a human being you want to make sure that
it has a the sunlight of our own inner warmth and uh and to be able to
recognize that now it's not all that easy for many of us to find that inner warmth and
inner wholesome attitude that we have but that's one of the purposes of
training that's one of the purposes of learning how to be skillful skillfully begin finding the ways we can maybe in
small steps one of the ways to learn it to appreciate this is to really appreciate
this very precise refined maybe difficult but very
simple idea that um what is what is happening what
occurs in the moment it's just what occurs we don't have to Define ourselves
by it we don't have to be critical by by it but what arises what
occurs how can we meet that how can we relate to that in a way that feels
wholesome so it's kind of like the next step we take if you take a step and you
you move forward onto that forward foot you're kind of committed that's what's happening but the next step is all about
a new world The Next Step you can put your foot down a little bit different direction you can take a longer step or
shorter step step over on a step onto a rock above the muddy ground ground if you wish but you have choices about the
next step so whatever is happening is the ground upon which you're standing
and there's a Next Step the next moment can that be a wholesome step can that be
a step that's you attentive to you stay present for and can you take that step
in a way that carries in it um an attitude of Peace an attitude
of friendliness an attitude of um Integrity honesty an attitude of
kindness an attitude of compassion or love there's a whole range of
possibilities of things which are wholesome for us but can you take the next step or can you meet each thing
that comes your way uh uh so if you have a thought and
your thought is really one of the worst thoughts a human being has ever had once
it's Arisen that's the step the next step is how do you relate to that can
you say oh wow that I feel sorry for that mind or
uh it's okay mind I'll be your friend regardless we don't have to take that thought so seriously we can just see it
h gaze upon it kindly so uh
wholesomeness is a foundation for Buddhist ethics and it provides a foundation is very different than a
rule-based approach to ethics it provides a reference point inside that
we can begin to recognize uh how we want to live the choices we want to make that
can be understood from the outside as being in English at least as ethical choices of how we live but from the
inside they're not exactly ethical they inside they feel like the choices by
which we grow in in uh inner uh Beauty in inner wonderfulness
in inner warmth or goodness inner wholesomeness this is possible and it's
one of the foundations of Buddhist practice um and Buddhist ethics so thank you uh very much and um
so I hope that uh at least for this one day you give yourself the benefit of
doubt you suspend all disbelief all the reasons why you can't do
this and practice the skill of doing what you're doing in a
beneficial way doing what you do so that you see
the beauty of how you live your life maybe today you can be an
artist With Every Act of speech every step you take every activity that you do
with your hands whatever you're doing whatever you're saying for one day
suspend all this belief that you can't do this and see if you can live uh a
life that brings a deeper Fuller sense of wholesomeness to
yourself thank you