so uh so welcome folks welcome to certain Wednesdays certain Wednesdays
with Matthew production by Matthew I'm Matthew it's not really a
production and it's not officially called certain Wednesdays but I like that certain Wednesdays because I'm here
certain Wednesdays and I am not certain about much at all
but uh we're here practicing nonetheless and uh thank you uh thanks for um yeah
saying hi lovely to see you your names and um we'll uh we'll sit and see what
happens for
whenever it would get real uh hot or cold in the
uh meditation Hall the teacher would say as we sat there teacher would say in the
summer the Buddha sweats in the winter he shivers
and so if uh the temperature as a number of people said if
um it's not at the kind of set point for your body just uh take stock of how
it affects uh your heart
mind e
any subtle bracing practice releasing
that e
it's not that conditions have to be just right for us to
surrender let go they're never just right for
that so we actually Leverage The
imperfection as a motivation to stop
fighting and when we stop fighting we become
uh poor to the Dharma
we don't have to say okay to everything
forever but for right now
we give
permission for all the conditions that that comprise this
moment to be as they are all the Loose Ends of any human
life everything that could get better we give
permission for it to be as it is for
and we know that we've actually given deep
permission for that which is to be as it is
when that which is changes softens
the permission
reshapes the [Music] constellation of phenomena of our
life
e
e e
just fill your body with uh awareness for
less like we're pouring the awareness from our head into our body and more
like our awareness uh blooms out of our
body
e
e e
and clinging uh carries a burden of of tension with it a kind of
Whirlpool of tension energy swirling
so we
relax we unify the the field of our body
settle into the uh juicy aliveness of the
Moment undefended
by our stories
e
e e
to uh to pay attention is to pay attention to change
so we practice not pushing or pulling on a
n impermanence
we practice not uh seeking a place outside the flow of
anicha but finding ourselves within it
e
e e
if there is no place to stand you might as well just fall
we fall more and more deeply into
and present less and less
baggage fewer and fewer ways for the attention to snag like a hang nail on
fabric but on
phenomena
e
e e
okay so it's good to uh good to sit with
you um thank you for uh for the the questions great questions
um I uh yeah I appreciate just seeing what's what's on people's mind last last
time if you were in here I chatted a link in to submit uh anonymous questions and um got a bunch
and um yeah great questions about um about Free Will and the self and
Consciousness and awareness and some of the questions are above my pay grade
some will lead me very deep into nerd territory and we might not come out and
we might not be wiser if we did get out
so I got to be selective in what I pick up but I I do really those are a lot of
my questions it's on my mind and so even if I'm not answering the questions it's informing what I'm uh thinking about how
I'm thinking about uh this group so uh so thank you and we'll have time to to
do do more of those I'll pick up more that have been submitted
so the question that uh I selected somebody just cut
right to the chase what's the best way to overcome
clinging and uh that um that's really the question
right Joseph Goldstein I remember some some years ago was asked to sum up his
Decades of practice in a sentence and his his response was simply
the mind that's not clinging to anything it's how he summed up
everything and if you're not clinging right how could anything really be a
problem how if you're not clinging could greed possibly gain a foothold
how could hatred gain a foothold right hatred greed are not not possible
in the wake of letting go but love is and that kind of asymmetry is of
Interest so this is a critical uh question
um but in some ways I can't really answer you know uh anyone
who boldly pronounce is like this is how you let go here's the the algorithm here
are the three steps to Letting Go you can know for sure that
person is a scam artist you know it's like in the trenches of our experience
we're all going to have to wrestle with that we always have to
wrestle with it it's not like we know how to let go and then we just keep doing doing it the rest of our
life and in in one sense maybe we say you know that we want to be careful
in the question not to overestimate the place of willfulness as if there are choices of
how to let go and it's just that we need to pick the right
strategy and in a sense the the the kind of willfulness is a
reiteration of the clinging rather than its
solution okay so that's maybe the Preamble but enough enough of me
dodging a very good question and the first thing that came to mind
really is that uh to know that that certain choices guarantee
clinging you know that certain investments
in relationships in in you know in in a
child in a cause you know ethical cause
like it pretty much guarantees some measure of of
clinging I don't think that's exactly can be free of clinging
it's like the up Upstream decisions guarantee Our
Fate and then the question is like can you actually consent to that clinging
can you consent to that suffering and it doesn't mean we can't
work to free ourselves up to some extent but the fantasy of like Freedom
given those Upstream ches it's it's not realistic the way we invest the way I've
invested various ways um and so we we actually open to that
okay this is part of the
contract Shanti Deva um said um just as
um no one no no one thought
may I now be born no one thinks may I now get
angry and we could add no one ever thought may I now
cling may I may I now suffer may I now be born May I now
cling clinging in other words arises out of out of many causes and conditions
and it's been reinforced in the behavioral sense it's been
reinforced in the sense that uh it's brought some rewards it kind of works
clinging kind of works some of the time a
little and that kind of reinforcement schedule like that is um
very problematic that really uh encourages the behavior the repetition
it it doesn't quite work but it usually works at least a little sometimes it
works really well you know or clinging and maybe it's a little bit like uh
gambling or something it's like we know that playing a you know
slot machine is not like a strategy for getting rich
uh but the casino programs the slot so that we get just enough reinforcement to
keep playing right and of course everyone's heard that one story about
that person that friend's sister-in-law who won big you know right and so it's
like gets reinforced and because clinging kind of
works it's hard to actually believe that we've got to exper with uh with
letting go and
so letting go you know it's it's
um it's hard and I'm very suspicious of a kind of instruction on how to let
go because it strikes me that that letting go is is sort of like the simult
anous expression of many of the the parames
the 10 Perfections you know that's uh that's why no one can tell you
how to do it you know CU it's like you can't can't just tell somebody how to be
you know patient and equanimous and have resolve and all at once right so the
parames the parames um are considered a kind of description
created not by the Buddha but by others of the Buddha's beautiful
qualities right and um and so just like looking at the the
list of you know the parmes the ones that have been highlighted uh non- clinging Letting Go
it involves a lot a lot renunciation you know
um letting go is to relinquish we're we're we're um we're unclenching our
fist right we're foregoing some measure
of the the pleasure that clinging can deliver right anger with its honey tip
and poisoned root the Buddha said right and so okay to let go of the poison we
actually have to let go of the honey too the sweetness varia energy Another Part Of Me
like clinging is painful but it's often actually the path of least resistance
right my clinging does not seem to ask
much of me it's water rolling down a hill right and so to actually change
that to change that habit to go against the stream that takes energy
and uh and Adana resolve commitment a deep commitment to
stay the course you know clinging is part of its problem is
its persistence you know its persistence it's not so much the peak
intensity of one given moment it's just the persistence the return turn of the
longing and patience patience to Bear to bear with the
process willing to to plant seeds and not insist upon
harvesting now
and uh maybe lastly equinity you know this kind of practice of wrapping
wrapping the whole realm of pleasant and unpleasant with um kind of the space of
okayness and so
um yeah and letting go of clinging we will be asked to have equinity
with intense feeling intense feeling a lot of feeling gets res
released in the kind of gesture of Letting Go letting
go uh sometimes to let go we have to do
something new we have to ritualize some aspect of what's come and gone or
sometimes we actually have to find something new to love you know
to and this this has kind of Echoes of Freud you know it's like to to let go
the energy that was invested in one thing gets
reinvested somewhere else that's actually how we let go so sometimes it's
not this pure internal inside job you
know and um letting go uh
is about I would say the wholesome the wholesome
unpleasant a wholesome unpleasant the reward of course is very pleasant but
the process of letting go is is about the wholesome
unpleasant and for the wholesome unpleasant not to devolve
into unh wholesomeness we often need to kind of Leaven the
letting go with some pleasantness we need to find
some you know something soothing some sense of Refuge some sense
of of pleasantness to um make more space for the
unpleasantness as we we practice and
um of course there are certain things that I don't know maybe it's like you
don't let go of them you you find a way uh
for for love to grow alongside the
pain you know some people certain losses
certain rooms I've been in where somebody describes to me a loss one of
those cardinal kind of losses and my thought is not
letting go exactly it's living alongside
the absence you letting that grow one's
love so I offer this uh for your consideration please um pick up what's
useful leave the rest behind and uh
I will be away next week we won't be class next week back on the 17th and so
um that's that's and you can always check imc's calendar it's posted there
um and uh look forward to to re regathering okay thank you uh thank you
all