okay so we'll start with a guided
meditation taking a few longer breaths than we normally
would as a way to just help connect with the body
and feeling what it feels like have these bigger
breaths feeling the stretch and the release of the
stretch maybe there's a little bit of ease and relaxation that comes with the
exhale allowing the breath to return to normal no need to control the
breath just trusting that the body knows how to breathe
then feeling connected to our sitting surface we're
here feeling the pressure against the Bucks pressure from the couch or the
chair or the cushion
pressure on the back of the
legs and feeling whatever the feet are touching
and be really upful to establish this
Foundation of our sitting surface at the beginning of a sit
helps emphasize that we are here and
now and there's a way in which the posture can rise out of that
foundation in the spine
straight and upright of course it's fine if you're
lying down also
if you're using a back rest feeling the pressure against the
back on the and the pressure on the body
and doing a gentle body
scan to tuning into the sensations on the
face around the eyes around the jaw maybe the face itself
the shoulders allowing them to be relaxed away from the ears
and the chest is there a way there can be some
softness in the chest
and the belly letting it
relax soften
now that we've settled in a little
bit I'd like to ask you to feel the sensations in the right hand
there are two kinds maybe the sensations of what the hand is
touching whether that's warm or cool
soft or rough
and the sensations of having a hand
maybe that's more like a tingling or a somehow a
vibratory sense the experience of having a hand
those are what I would call the direct experience
and in contrast you think about
hands think about an evolution having posable thumbs turns out to be mightily
helpful the hands of a child are different than the hands of an adult
different sizes with maybe a little bit softer and
pudgier and then just noticing that thoughts about
hands is not the same as experiences
with
hands distinct from the direct
experience e
we can notice during this meditation
period how sometimes thoughts are
predominant and sometimes direct experience is
predominant e
we'd like to give emphasis to
experience experiencing the sensations of
breathing e
feeling into the body's movements
as breathing
happens
e
e e
the is lost in thought we don't have to make a big
story about what it means us as
meditators we just begin again with the
experience of breathing
e
e e
[Music]
morning welcome welcome today am continuing this um
exploration of this topic of stories and in that guided meditation I
try to highlight the difference between thoughts that we
have and experience like direct experience
I wean can notice that you know thoughts of course are be different places different times Future Past complete
fantasy whereas experience is just right here right now of course it
is and another distinction that maybe it's so obvious that
um it isn't even worth mentioning but there's a way in which thoughts use
language like uh whether it's sexual words or maybe it's images whereas
direct experience itself isn't so much a language it's
just an experience right when we put our hand and touch our sitting
surface and just feel rubbing our hand moving our hand across the surface just
feeling there's just those Sensations whereas if we were to
describe it or something like that you then we're we're a little bit removed we're using language to uh describe
it so as that as an introduction um I'd like to tell a story that um comes from
the poly Canan from the sutas and um I'll talk a little bit more about the
role of stories or how humans use stories after I give a story so this
story is about maluna those of you who are interested this comes from majima 6
three and uh maluna he was a monastic under the Buddha so he had ordained
under the Buddha and one time uh he goes to the Buddha and he says you know I'm
really not happy that you haven't explained everything and I'm going to disrobe I'm going to leave the monastic
life I'm going to abandon this monastic life and become a late person again unless you answer these 10 uh questions
these turn out to be metaph physical questions like an example of some of
these questions are is the world finite or infinite so he just has these
questions about space where where's the how much space is there in this universe or in these world of ours Malia also
asks is the world Eternal or not Eternal he's asking about time like where is
time how much time is there and he's asking uh also like what
happens to Buddhas after they die where do they go do they exist or do they not
exist so you can see that these are the type of questions that are you know only in one's mind in terms like wanting to
know like the limits of time and space and what happens after
death and uh some little like this little detail that I kind of like in this story is I feel like maluta he's a
little Bit Sassy he says to the Buddha if you don't know the answers to
these things then just simply say you don't know so he's kind of like goting
the Buddha a little bit and saying you know if you don't know just say it he's uh suggesting that the Buddha doesn't
know and then the Buddha replies well did I ever promise you that I was going
to answer all these questions if you ordained did I ever did I promise anyone
that I would give all the answers to every single metaphysical question that they could come up with if they ordained
no I never made that promise and in fact if somebody were demanding this of me
that they would not ordain until I had answered all their metaphysical questions then they would never ordain
and they would die they would spend the rest of their life unordained and they would die
unordained and then the G says know I don't answer these questions because
these answers to these types of questions is not helpful and it doesn't
lead to peace it doesn't lead to Insight it doesn't lead to
Awakening so just having the answers to these type of metaphysical metaphysical
questions and I might say having the story about what happens after death
story about the limits of the universe space and time where are there edges if
so where are they isn't helpful instead it's uh about uh what
can lead to peace insight and Awakening which is direct
experience and then the bruda continues within this story The bruda
gives another story it's a aimile which we might understand as a as a story and
the simile goes like this is this is the simile of The Poisoned Arrow this is the
budha talking to malapa and says Suppose there was a person who was injured by a poisoned
arrow and his friends and relatives bring a doctor to help remove the arrow
you in order to save his life but this person refuses doesn't want any help from the doctor until certain questions
are answered and and these are the types of questions who shot the arrow were
they tall or short or of middle height do they live in this city or do they
live in this town or do they live in a village and what kind of bow was used to
show shoot the arrow was it a longbow or a crossbow and what kind of bow string
was on the bow was it made from fiber or Reed or sinu and what kind of feathers
were on the bow were they from a vulture a heron a hawk a peacock or a stor and
what kind of arrowead was it spiked or razor tipped was it curved was it Barbed
was it Lancet shaped you know so all these from a you in modern years these are and I'm assuming also back in
thousands of years ago when this Sim was given these are irrelevant questions
here's a person who's been hit with a poisoned Arrow there's like poison going
into them they're soon to die and they're wondering what whether
the bow string was made from fiber read or
sineu so the obvious like the the teaching point from uh this Su both
maluna asking these questions and the simile of the poison to Arrow is that um
having answers stories I might say about um so many of
the things that we have um are is not the way to Awakening isn't the way towards
Liberation but instead that there's a real encouragement to focus on Direct
experience that we can have through meditation or ethical conduct or the way
that we're showing up in the world so rather than becoming a atted to
having the answers to all of our metaphysical questions or knowing
everything rather than being attached to speculative views
stories there's this real emphasis on no just have some clarity about what's
actually happening some mindfulness about what's happening in one's
life so that's the usual uh framing of this uh story that we find in the uh
sutas but I also want to kind of like zoom out and look at this uh story from
a different perspective and to ask why is maluta and
this poisoned Arrow victim why would they even want to know all these things what's the reason I know that
this is a you know a teaching story but I I want us to maybe like look at things from a different
way why why would they even want to know whether the bow string was made out of
senine or Fiber why would they want to know whether the world has the space is
infinite or finite because they think that if they're they're trying to make sense of
their experience they think that if they have more information they'll find Freedom
they'll be a little bit more ease if they just understood better in some ways we they kind of want to create a story
about why it happened and so maybe maybe malapa maybe
he was just having a lot of doubt maybe he was like a hindrance a doubt hindrance attack and he had this idea
that well maybe if I just had some more confidence in the Buddha and his teachings then this would be easier for
me maybe if I uh he could prove that uh he really was awakened by knowing the
answers to these questions it would be a little bit easier for me and this is what humans
do we want to use stories to make sense of our
world we want to have information we want to feel like we understand maybe
there's some way in which we feel like we can control things if we understand
them and David ly he writes the world is made of stor
and then he's saying like we're creating our world with our
stories and we can even think like in modern times like how we have this current news cycle which you know is
just never ending it just seems like okay something happens and then there's
endless speculation like immediately after it happens about people are you know getting paid to just be on air to
completely speculate about the details and the motive and trying to make sense before any of the data any of the facts
have rolled in they're just speculating and so they're just trying
to uh give some information or trying to help us make sense of like wait wh why
did this happen and David L he points out it's
not just like the news cycle he's talking about here's these other ways of stories that make our
world there's this long list which I I like I think it's uh really points to
how pervasive this idea is of how humans use stories to make
sense the stories that make our world are creation myths folk tales and fairy
tones 17 syllable Japanese haiku and three-day Indonesian shadow puppet
dramas novels romantic fantastic graphic television soap operas
newspaper features oped articles internet blogs talk show chatter office memos
obituaries and birth announcements how to use manuals how you're feeling this
morning what happened during your vacation and what you're planning for the weekend so he's saying that this is all
this ways that uh using stories and maybe we might say it's a narratives
that we're trying to use to pull together our experiences like highlighting the
difference between an actual experience and then the words and the language the narratives that we use to explain
them and so I would say that freedom lies in
recognizing stories as stories so the problems lie not with stories themselves
but how we identify with them or how that we are uh um just believing them
and assuming that what we're hearing somehow is like an accurate representation of
experience because unaware that our stories are stories we usually experience them as well this is just the
way the world is and we take for granted that the world we experience is being
reflected in these narratives and stories these accounts that we're having
because the our stories our ideas about the world strongly affect our perception
of reality the way that we are interpreting or understanding what's valuable or
what's possible or what's good or what's bad are all dependent on these stories
that we are telling about our experience so don't believe everything
you think but but we don't want to also dismiss stories because it's a way that
we are trying to make sense of the world and to make sense of our experiences instead I would say the way
forward is to recognize that there are experiences and then there's the
narratives we create about experiences that both are important they
both have a role and they're distinct and it's helpful for us to keep that in
mind as we practice for more freedom more ease more peace
Awakening so thank you thank you and today you might just have a no notice
like what kind of like narratives are you pulling together and of course we are but can we recognize that they are
narratives that they explanations for experiences that we had and that they're
distinct so thank you and I'll see you
tomorrow wishing you all wonderful rest of the day thank
you e
it's lovely to uh see your comments it's it's so great R to
practice together makes a difference thank you
maybe in the same way that um I know that there's like a little time delay
between when I say something and when it shows up on YouTube which I was thinking
like maybe in the same way there's like their direct experience and then there's the narrative around it there's a like a
little Gap and because you guys might be able to see me but you don't know what
I'm reading what I'm seeing just because they this uh
delay may we all be well