so good morning for some of you good afternoon
for others good evening for maybe another set of you good day for
everyone and um so we come to the last
uh day of this five day series and the topic being today is
liberation and Liberation is often considered to be
an absence of certain mental
States rather than the presence of something which can be a source or
reason or an object of attachment
expectation um comparative thinking
uh it's an absence of greed hate and delusion an absence of clinging an absence of prejudice absence
of bias absence of conceit absence of
selfishness absence of resentment and
covetousness absence of so many ways in which we well human
beings harm each other including
ourselves and an
absence leaves us without something an absence is a simplification
of certain kinds of things and so one of the
characteristics of liberation is freedom from those things which
harm and one of the characteristics of the path to Liberation is that the is that the way
we practice the path should contain within it some of
the goal the goal is to be found in the
means and what what the how to understand that is that the very way in
which we practice Buddhism the very way in which Buddhists practice
meditation mindfulness is a
care maybe a loving care but a real care a
real kind of carefulness
attention is to be paid is to be given that the way in which we
practice is with as little greed hatred and delusion as we can
muster that we practice without attachment or clinging without hostility and without
conceit without selfishness without strain
without complacency or holding back without shutting
down without avoiding in the ancient text they talk
about neither accepting nor rejecting and uh we have to understand
carefully what that means that accepting and rejecting involves
kind of taking and pushing away kind of acquisition
appropriation let's and and
rejection so this absence leaves us in a state of radical
Simplicity awake here just
awake with the same Simplicity of what wakefulness feels like
waking up from a really good sleep or a nap there's something in that waking up
from really good sleep and nap that the wakeful state itself has that has this
Simplicity in it and
finally to become free of clinging free of hostility and craving
cannot be done with more attachment with more clinging with more hostility and
craving so to practice mindfulness with a care and a love and
a devotion maybe even a almost a religious
devotion
to free ourselves from those things that go
against the grain of
freedom and it isn't that we have to do it perfectly it's that we do it to the
extent that we can and for what we can't we hold that
spaciously openly we hope that hold that with
kindness compassion we hold
that with faith that we
can practice with it meaning that we can be mindful of it and finding our
way slowly to freedom from it
but whatever is difficult not to meet it with more
difficulty you can't solve the problem with more of the
problem so assuming a meditation posture and gently closing your eyes
and here you are in the spot where you're
[Music] sitting [Music]
rising out of your seat arising out of whatever place that's holding
you here it's you your body body your heart your
mind it's so precious it's so
valuable you are a treasure
you are wondrous and to sit here caring for this
wonder that you are by being
mindful of whatever arises where the mindfulness
itself contains qualities of being
awake free of all the forces of harm
or as free as we're able to practice with for
today with
faith that this kind of care and this kind of love this kind of
attentiveness is the way to
Freedom
for
for for
there is freedom right
here just outside of whatever attachment you have
clinging just beyond your distraction
deep within below your thinking there is a place of
absence the absence of being
caught for
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a few moments
here to sit with a Wonder Wonder of being
alive The Wonder of being
conscious The Wonder of that corner of your heart your mind
your being which
knows how to be alive without
fear without
craving without
hostility a Simplicity of being free of
conceit free of being
caught in
self here it's possible to breathe
freely here it's possible to sense or live
life easily
here it's possible to have a mind that operates
peacefully and to whatever degree we can int it or feel or sense this
possibility even if we imagine this
possibility to then to from that
place to be open to the world to be aware of people in your life
the people in your neighborhoods and communities the people around the
globe and for you to share with them through
whatever example you can provide
of a life that's free of being caught in forces of
harm forces of hatred and Prejudice and
bias examples of a person who lives with the opposite with generosity and love and
wisdom and may it be that radiating from
you is good will towards all beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so suffering and the end of
suffering freedom from fixed
views the natural functioning of our life flowing freely through us
sometimes taking the form of love or care or
compassion all leading to or supporting or pointing
to Liberation and the path to Liberation a path that liberates us from
suffering brings at the end of suffering so these are the foundations
of the core teachings that I believe I base my teachings on and my practice on
my life on and so today the topic is
Liberation and the path to Liberation and um what's uh delightful
in this tradition is that
uh is the principle that before
Liberation there is practice and after Liberation there is
practice that the practice moves continuously through us even the Buddha
after he was fully awaken would go in the forest to practice
meditation and um they uh and so in a
sense the difference between before and after an experience of a weakening or
Liberation um uh it doesn't matter that much what matters is that we practice
that the practice is sincere and uh the founder of San Francisco Zen Center Suzuki roshi made
this now often referred to statement that uh someone asked him uh um if I do
Zen will I become enlightened and he replied was if your practice is sincere
that's almost as good and so before before Enlightenment
practice after Enlightenment practice and so maybe in a certain kind of way
Enlightenment doesn't matter that much for what we do for what we dedicate our
life to so not to be too caught in the idea of some kind of experience of Awakening but to be kind of devoted to
just keep practicing uh the Dharma the mindfulness the compassion the concentration the
ethics all the different pieces the Eightfold Path now uh one of the things that I
like to emphasize is for the the goal to be found in the
means that uh if the goal is to uh a
radical way of being not caught in anything caught up in anything a radical
way of being free from uh uh being stuck free from being
obsessed free from being um uh oppressed with our own mind our own Hearts fear
and upset and dismay and criticism and anger to really the um uh that that's
the goal that the means to that goal should have some of the qualities of the
goal in itself it doesn't mean that we can just wipe away the ways that we're attached but it
does mean that we can begin finding a way to be mindful a way to be aware a
way to bring our attention to what's difficult in us to our attachments that
that way of attending is is free of attachment free of being caught to some
degree and that even just to some degree uh if it contains part of the
goal that's enough to begin seeing a sliver seeing a little hint oh this is
what it's like to be present without any attachment without any resistance
without any shutting down or any holding on or any uh self-
preoccupation this is what it's like to be free of preoccupation um and we start getting little senses of
it and then to be guided by that oh this is good this is the way forward this is
what the path is about uh and to have some confidence that you can find that in yourself in how you're mindful in how
you're aware and caring for your practice and so then
slowly uh one way of understanding what practice is is that that little sliver
of Freedom that you begin to recognize in how you're aware begins to grow
begins to spread becomes bigger and bigger and so rather than focusing on
having some deep Insight or getting concentrated or like having you know aiming towards something exactly still
the same practice but um it's also kind of uh behind it or in you know in the
very mode in which we're engaging the practice something is growing and
something is growing and BEC bigger and bigger until it fills us until it kind of really uh um uh shows us deeply
deeply the experience of Freedom that's possible and um and in the teravan
tradition um the emphasis of doing this is by talking directly about uh
recognizing what greed hate and delusion is like and attachment is like so we can find a way to practice without that in
some other schools of Buddhism um um they they point to a different
possibility they have some way of pointing or the practitioner to the
place of non- clinging and just to abide in the best they can and then over years
that grows and develops until the sense of non- clinging becomes much more pervasive in who they are
and um but this the growth of freedom and um so well before
Awakening uh there is small Awakenings small sense of being awake and I love
this a metaphor of being awake for this Liberation from clinging Liberation from
suffering because um I don't know if it's true for everyone I don't know what the you know conditions are for people
that might interfere with this but uh some of us maybe have this experience of
waking up from a good sleep a good nap um maybe it's even maybe having a nice
cup of coffee for some people where there's a sense of feeling a wake a
wakefulness that uh is independent of what we're aware
of um if we're tired and grumpy and
things are challenging and difficult then it's almost like everything the eyes set their uh gaze upon it's just
difficult and challenging and everything is kind of seen as a difficult thing um
and even the the our awareness are knowing and thinking about it is just not doesn't feel
good but when we in in waking up from a really good
nap um and uh or sitting on a park bench on a day that we don't have any work or
any respons posibilities and just sitting there uh with nowhere to go nothing to do no one to be just looking
at the maybe children playing or the the squirrels running around or the wind in
the trees there's a feeling of contentment and just being just being alive is enough there's a feeling that
uh and it independent of what we know what we're aware of uh you feel this beautiful feeling of
just being awake it feels so clear and crisp and and content like it's kind of
like it it's a Clarity that's expansive without edges and then we go into the
kitchen and there's a mess in the kitchen sink and it's like wow okay this
is just uh there's no reactivity to the mess in the kitchen sink it's just like
it's this too is happening in the clarity so uh so this so if you have an
experience like this in a park bench on know waking up from a nap or something
this is now beginning to be a guide where you start getting a sense of oh this is what freedom is like this is
what's possible and there might be other things in your life that has given you this kind of uh foraste of what Freedom
Liberation is and um and then to uh to um to uh so it's
we're growing that we're developing it as after a very clear when that's becomes really clear some definitive
experience of Awakening of Freedom radical freedom from all
suffering that that registers deep deep in our Consciousness in our in our
hearts in such a way that now there's a reference point for living
free and um and now the challenge is we still want to practice still that's the
dedication but now we know something we don't want to compromise we don't want to we don't want to uh
give in forces of harm of hatred of fear um because that interferes with
this capacity of Freedom that is the channel which is the open door for the
wholesome goodness of our hearts for our capacity for love and compassion
generosity our compassion to be of service for others and for this world to care
and um and so uh after some experience of Liberation there's a uh there's a
kind of um for a while there could be a debate going on inside of us between do
I get angry at the condition of the world do I get dismayed do I get afraid
or is it okay to stay in this place of freedom is it okay to stay without
clinging without attachment without preoccupation and inevitably if you do this practice
well Freedom wins in the debate greed hate and delusion doesn't win fear does
not win dismay does not win because if we do that it diminishes us we lose
something we harm ourselves and we see that over time we also start harming
others in maybe subtle sometimes big ways there's not a a few uh people who
who have been engaged in the process of U you know to use a choice word
fighting for justice and have used the very forces
within of greed hate and delusion to to to fight for justice that is the reason
why there's Injustice and of course we want to live in the world to bring justice but to to
know how to bring bring freedom our freedom our wakefulness to spread it into the world this is a possibility as
well so before Awakening there is the practice that can be informed Guided by
some intuition of Freedom after Awakening there can be
some intuition of Freedom that now really sets a stage that guides us not
just an intuition but a knowing to Freedom so I hope that uh uh you can
learn to appreciate that the that the goal can be
in the means and that that nourishes you that supports you that guides you that
inspires you in your practice and that through this practice that you can
benefit all beings so thank you very very
much for today and so I have one announcement
uh here at IMC Insight Meditation Center we've been we might we've been given an
opportunity to partner with a local uh Nature Preserve called uh Hidden Villa
where we used to put on Retreats for 10 years and they would like us to come back and continue putting on Retreats as
well and um and we don't know if we were able to do it because of a variety of
factors here at IMC and um the uh so what we'd like to do is
have a meeting here at IMC on Sunday at 11:15 in California time uh to talk
about what interest find out what interest there is in our community in this Partnership of putting on Retreat C
in Villa so everyone's invited it's on zoom and in person here and if you have
interested in this kind of project uh you're welcome to come thank you for