and greetings
everyone happy to be here with you all again and this very sweet to see the
greetings in the chat box
uh here we are again at 7 o' in the Pacific
time we'll begin our meditation with the sound of a
bell
pausing pausing to begin our meditation together
this morning for this
day being very generous with this a process of
pausing what is happening right now with
pausing there may be a momentary mindfulness coming in
maybe momentary kind of
stopping maybe there is a sense of a kind of flow in the mind
thoughts got interrupt it
momentarily staying with a
pausing pausing to arrive at Here and
Now
maybe we can finally take a few long deep
breaths maybe the
sound can move through
us maybe the sensations in the body are the movements of the
breath are bubbling up to the
foreground
pausing to step out of unconscious
flow of the thoughts
planning project
managing fantasizing
pausing to arrive at a Here and
Now embodied
heartfelt the beginning moments of the meditation
may feel a little jerky or
bouncy because of the momentum of the flow of
unconscious mindfulness is a flickering in and
out no
problem or simply patiently
gently staying with this process of pausing to
arrive
letting go of the active
feeding into the
thinking and resting more and
more in a mindful
awareness
embodied
heartfelt what's the felt sense of your experience right
now
maybe the rapid
movements the momentum at the beginning of the meditation is settling
down ever so slightly or maybe not
resting in the present
resting with mindfulness
patiently with a sense of a
commitment Sati may become more
continuous we have a sense of we finally arrived
at the
presence
can you notice some small
ways are big ways of inner
shift from unconscious flow to becoming consciously aware
you feel availability right
here
being available to the felt sense in the
body being available to the
aliveness that's present right
here through the movements of the
breath vibrations in the
body pausing is an
alchemical
process what's the felt [Music]
sense right
now arriving
arrived and
available you feel the heart
opening easing up
the body
softening
relaxing
from this open receptive available field
[Music] ining
aligning and orienting our whole being inner
outer with our deepest intentions
our
aspirations without having
to use the thinking mind to align Can You Feel the
aligning in the body with the
heart aligning with our aspirations feels like
this in the immediacy of your
experience sometimes the images may
come you may have a certain kind of recognition
arising
for me sometimes this spontaneous image of sitting
upright like the Buddha would
arise staying with the felt
sense
being aligned and available feels like
this in your own
experience you may have a kind of a grounding
flavor maybe the heart and mind and the body can feel
safe
protected
from this aligned and available
field you can choose to turn the
attention onto the familiar meditation
object if you you choose to do
that body
breath or you can simply rest
here being present
aligned and
available
if the Mind wandered away remember
remember
pausing allow pausing to
interrupt the cutness of our
mind
pausing to allow mindfulness
sa to come
forth
the last moments of our meditation
together maybe resting and settling on the ground of being
available and aligned aligned with our
values aspirations
allow this be a whole some ground that we can stand
in as we step into the
day
thank you for practicing together I'd like to take a moment to do
something that uh folks suggested yesterday in the chat that is maybe
collectively we send a meta to Nikki who was supposed to be here this week um but
was feeling unwell and wasn't able to be here with you all and so let's just take
a moment to send meta to Nikki and wishing her
well-being and a speedy recovery from whatever may be bothering her body and
heart
so uh today I brought with me a second
practice skill that I like to share and this is what I
called the Alchemy of paing so
pausing is probably not um that unfamiliar to most of us and who
has been practicing with mindfulness and inite
meditation as a lot of teachers would have pointed out that we can
pause and as a part of our practice and so um what may be
unfamiliar is that often we may not have
um paid close attention to this alchemical process of
pausing I want to drop in kind of a um evocative phrase here sentence
here the practice ofusing has a potential to mature in a
radical transformation Here and Now
maybe that's a little radical so I was uh pointed out recently that the word
radical um can mean extreme but it also has a meaning of relating to or
proceeding from a root or
Foundation I love that this a sense of the simple practice of
pausing can have a potential to have a inner shift and
inner transformation that happens at the foundational level of our
being well you know we can see if that's possible but I like to maybe unpack this
alchemical process uh a bit today and I introduce a little bit of
this uh at the guided meditation today um at the
beginning and a little bit at the end also so as we um practice with pausing
what happens when we first start
pausing maybe you can say that our practice mindfulness practice begins
with a momentary pause what I often notice
is the moment of a pausing I can notice
uh one or two things one is noticing that I was going there was a
kind of ongoing flow of my mind that was happening maybe thinking planning
ruminating wondering so that became available to me
kind of visible to me and this pausing has this um effect
of interrupting that flow which usually is
very unconscious and it's kind of we just going with that flow and so that's one effect and supp
pausing to interrupt the unconscious flow and the other effect with the
momentary pausing is the mindfulness becomes
available and so maybe not kind of immediately uh established kind of
available of the Sati but it's a momentary it's kind of flickering in and
out because there is a momentum of this unconscious flow that may be
operating it's like um you know maybe we're going with a rapid current uh
flowing with that uh at some point this beginning of the pausing is like there's
a sense of oh you know I want to step out of this unconscious flow but we're
not taking the foothold just yet on the RO River Bank for example or still kind
of being carried by it a little bit but it's um but we are interrupting
that flow when we're not actively engaging in the unconscious flow Itself
by keep feeding with our thinking and thoughts and plans and doing and project
managing and so the first uh if effect of this process ofusing is it can
interrupt that unconsciousness and then as we stay with
uh the momentary mindfulness little by little what can happen in our felt sense
is a pausing can lead to some kind a felt sense of things slowing
down our mindfulness can become more
continuous may not be perfect continuous but you can feel you're more
present and um uh the rapid fire of the thoughts
might thing out a bit because we're not so invested in
it and um the stories that may feel a little more
floaty you know they're not so gra grip gripping on
us and so this is when uh using that current analogy this is kind of like a
we're now uh being able to have more foothold uh on the river bank and and
kind of not being so carried away um by the unconscious
flow and so this is the kind of a maybe I'm calling it a second phase of of this
alchemical shift and change of the Paw starts with
interrupt and then start and then moving into things slowing
down and we can actually begin to hear some sounds or we can feel that we can
actually breathe sometimes when we're being carried by the unconscious flow we're
holding our breath we don't even know and so that can happen and
then again as we stay with this process more and more the next uh phase that
began to uh emerge is that our mindfulness can
become Fuller and so now it feels like our foot
can actually settle on the River Band Bank maybe both feet are settle settling
on the river bank and so there is a kind of a felt
sense of were more rooted Here and Now
present and the momentum of going two places began to settle down
and so some sometimes for me I would notice and at the beginning of my
mindfulness uh starting to uh kind of come to come forth it can have a
momentum um that's like the rapid fire thinking mind because my mindfulness
would be kind of hopping around you know jumping between the breath and the sound but then when our mindfulness
becomes more established that the momentum of hopping
around from one object to another began to
settle we're not not moving about so much we're simply resting more and more
in this a field of awareness and
knowing and so this is a phase where there is can be a distinct shift that we
can feel oh we're shifting from this momentum of
unconscious doing to a kind of
knowing resting in the knowing we can observe and feel the
flow but we're not being carried by it Carried Away by
it and then with this mindfulness of being uh more and more fully
established this began to empower the unfolding of the next phase of a
pausing which I'm calling pausing to be
transformed as we began to rest uh more fully in this
um uh in um the fullness of awareness
knowing what can happen is that we can begin to see the different patterns
of our mind activities and we can see how the
activities and reactivity ities that can lead to duka or
stress and how we can be free from the stress
oruka and so one of the main patterns that gets
revealed uh in this process by staying resting in this field of
awareness is that we can see that are ongoing
self-centered project managing um reacting and
threshing between the wanting and not wanting they're just tying ourselves in
NS right and Dharma dhapat has this very Vivid verses that describes this kind of
a threshing and that the unconscious mind can and get ourselves
involved it's like the fish out of the water thrashing
about with this unconscious
mind and so resting in this a field of awareness we can begin to see the
patterns very clearly and seeing clearly has a
powerful effect in us when we see when we know for
ourselves the grip on this kind of a pattern or the investment in trying to
um managing our ways out begin to soften itself loosen
itself and so we are more and more at ease so settling into a kind of a being
that's available for us being with the
flow rather than being pulled or pushed by
it and so there is a kind of a through line with this alchemical process of a
pausing that moves us from the unconscious
doing managing to a clear
knowing and a profound sense of a being and that's a radical
transformation it has that potential it doesn't mean that it's always there but
it's a possibility and this form of a being is
not deadening but rather it's alive it has innate
responsiveness within it and it has a capacity to respond out
the depth of our [Music] being and so my invitation for
today yes open to the possibility of
pausing pausing to interrupt pausing to slow down
pausing to get to know the depth of our being and
pausing to see the possibility of being transformed by
it so thank you everyone for your
attention and uh may you rejoice in the practice of a
passing