hello everyone and welcome to this Monday morning meditation and I come to you from having
taught a retreat at our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz I see some of the names
are people who are there and so for this
morning I'd like to uh suggest that you take The Road Less
Traveled two roads diverged in a yellow
wood and I took the one less traveled and that made all the
difference and so the road that I suggest today is as you're being mindful as
you're present for your experience take the road where there's
no comment no comment we live in commentary we live in
judging we live in stories we live in planning the future remembering the past
all those are either disconnected from the present moment or
is some way that we're trying to manage the present moment but there is another way the RO
the way less traveled the way of being aware in a
very simple way without comment without telling
ourselves something what it means telling us what it's
about telling us where it's going the expectation without needing to judge
what's happening come to conclusions about what's happening where there's a emphasis on a
radical Simplicity to what is happening and the reason why this is a
great road to take is that there's much more happening
within you than you can be thinking about that you could be commenting
about and too often we live in the commentary and we believe it and
sometimes of course it is true but we're still living in it and it interferes
with something deeper unfolding some something more precious something more
valuable to it's almost like having no
comment gives room for something deep within us to
show itself to come and so as we sit
today the second kind of phrase that you might want to keep in mind is that of
breathing room we are giving when we bring attention to
breathing we're giving room for breathing room for breathing
to manage itself to leave it alone to breathe the
way we do no
comment and if we're aware of other things as we meditate each Act of awareness each Act of
mindfulness no comment and no comment includes not being for or
against it neither accepting it or rejecting
it so no comment so to assume a meditation
posture and to somehow adjust the [Music] arms the
Torso the head on a neck maybe maybe tipping the head back
and forth or gentle circle with the head loosening up the
neck maybe circling the shoulders a little bit just kind of wiggling the shoulders
a little bit so they can relax
and maybe swaying the whole torso back and forth
sideways finding a relaxed
midpoint adjusting your legs a little bit if that helps
and breathing
in maybe not a deep breath but but for you is a comfortable full breath
and if breathing is
uncomfortable to be in your
body and then letting the breathing return to
normal and with a normal breath to continue to relax the
body soften in the face
soften in the
shoulders soften in the belly
and as you exhale to imagine you're giving breathing
room for the commenting mind the thinking
mind give it space as if
it's all the space outside of your head is offered
to give breathing room to the thinking
mind and as you exhale Relax The Thinking mind
and then for a few moments here see if you can do almost nothing
next to nothing just be present be in the present be with the
present without directing the attention without
directing towards something without receiving anything in Awareness just be for a few
moments and whatever you're aware of no
comment whatever you're aware of allow it to have breathing room
space to be itself without you being
involved e
and if a breathing is the center of attention if breathing
Rises what's it like to breathe knowingly
with no comment No Agenda simply awareness of
breathing and as you continue take the
time take all the time in the world all the space in the world
to be aware with no
comment
for
e
e for
e e
no comment
including no commentary about make making
comments of course the mind will be involved in
commentary from time to
time no need to make commentary about that each
moment taking The Road Less Traveled
the road that's
quiet
e
for
for for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to consider taking the road that is less
taken in a world where that does not know the difference between wholesome
and Al UNH wholesome maybe may we be
wise and not diluted in
in a world where the choice is between hatred and
kindness may we choose
kindness in a world where there is
greed may we choose generosity
and in doing so in a world where people are often
self-centered may we be may we care for
others may we be wise and kind and generous to nourish
ourselves and to benefit this world we live in
may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all
beings be free
[Music]
thank you [Music]
hello on this Monday morning in from in California and and
um the series of talks I'd like to give today little very much based on what uh
the theme of this My Last Retreat weeklong Retreat that ended yesterday teaching with Andrea
fella and uh some of you who heard that will recognize some of
it and I'll call this The Road Less Traveled and uh in Buddhist practice
uh there's often the emphasis on a path path of
practice and um and every time in every step there is a fork in the path there's
a path Less Traveled and the path that is
um that is um commonly traveled all too easily
traveled and in Buddhism we choose the path Less
Traveled sometimes it's called um going against the current um if you're
swimming up against the current of a river it's hard to or if you put something in the river it just floats
down it doesn't go against the current and um but in the commentary in
the in the um in the path model we take the path that is
wholesome there is the um uh UNH wholesome and the UN wholesome
very simple division and so things like um
lying is the UN wholesome Direction being honest is the honest is
the wholesome Direction being mean is UNH wholesome being kind is
wholesome and because of this kind of pairing that can happen and it can seem that almost like it's just one or the
other it's kind of like a pairing of things which are of equal weight or equal something or coming from the same
place inside it's a choice in thinking or intentionality or something that's
kind of all occurring at the same place but in fact in the Buddhist teaching um
there are two different operating systems and that's my language for the Buddhist teachings but there's two
radically different ways of sources within us for
behavior and there's one whole operating system for the UNH wholesome and there's
a a completely separate operating system for the wholesome when the wholesome
arises out of the wholesome if the wholesome arises out of a
decision the the source of the UNH wholesome can be where we live with a
lot of thinking and concerns and stress and there can be a logical understanding
of consequences and what's going on and a decision there can be made to do the
wholesome thing but there's a it's it's not that kind of I I point up is not the
operating system in the control tower but rather the operating system
that's a from a deep Source within and so The Road Less Traveled uh
in this week I'm going to talk is less about a particular choice to do the wholesome thing over the UN wholesome
but the choice or the capacity to uh be connected to a deep Source inside that
is the source for the wholesome and and to not take the road the Common Road that is the source for
greed hate delusion the source for stress the clinging tension
and um and uh and we see in the Buddha's teaching repeatedly this dichotomy
between these two different modes of being without it being named uh so in in
a clear way that it's highlighted that's what he's talking about the
um uh but he does talk a lot about wholesome and UNH wholesome and uh and so one of the
distinctions is appear when he talks about the feeling tones of experience how things experience can be pleasant
unpleasant or neutral he talks about those feeling tones that are more on the
surface that have to do with how we are in contact with the world uh or how the
world is in contact with us so if um
there is um uh you know a called cold
wind uh the body feels cold and then
based on that uh we react we think that's unpleasant and now I don't want
it I want to change to get do something different um and um but it's the outer
World which is affecting us or we're oriented towards the outer world and what the outer world will do to us so
for example eating good food getting pleasure being nourished feeling lonely and thinking the world's going to
provide some some some reassurance by just eating a lot all kinds of issues that ways in
which we are counting on the world out there to be the source of our joy or
pleasure or wellbe or everything's going to be okay if the world is okay our
experience out there and so um this is is an outer
orientation um pleasure pain of the
world then there's the inner and the in inner is deep inside doesn't have to do
with how our senses pick up the outer World it involves a deeper connection
that to capacities within that in Buddhism maybe would be called sometimes
when they people translate this word that Buddha uses for that they call it spiritual I like to call it uh the kind
of inner Source inner um place for our inner
well-being and uh and so to uh know the difference between living a life which
oriented towards our happiness being provided by the the
world versus an inner life or happiness is provided by some deep Source within
that has been set free that has been opened up that is allowed to flow and
that deeper Source can't flow if we're living in the control tower of
reactivity uh to the world and and the world is not only the external world we
internalize the world in our thoughts and so it's some people's inner world is
completely shaped by the outer world if we're com thinking about um the past and
reviewing the difficult things in the past that would also be called being concerned with the outer world even
though it's the inner world that's thinking about it the control tower or
if you have wonderful thoughts about how to do great things in the world it might
just be more of the same might be the ego driven control tower the conceit
World which um and uh and to find a deeper way a
deeper place of connection inside the and in this two different
modes that the Buddha one way or the other is talking about often uh he has
different metaphors for them and that's I want to talk about the metaphors today before go tomorrow going on with this
idea for this uh this uh UNH wholesome Source inside of us and it might all not
always be seen as UNH wholesome because sometimes our attachments are clinging or greed which are UNH wholesome uh can
can bring us beneficial things sometimes they're successful in getting
pleasure if um if I want to um if I'm lonely and want to go to the
refrigerator to eat to kind of sometimes the refrigerator might have some really good food and I'm successful and feel so
good and uh and so we can't see necessarily that it's UNH wholesome what's going on because we don't see the
underlying Drive of the UNH wholesome and how taking that road creates habit
that road takes reinforces this control tower operating
system so this control tower operating system is um or this UNH wholesome
operating system if you may um the Buddha uses a lot of
metaphors to describe it and what stands out in those metaphors is they're all
things which are constructed by human beings and um and so for example he uses
the the idea of a house that's been constructed wooden house that's been built and um there's nothing wrong with
the house but except that it is built by a human being it's constructed and with becoming awakened
the Buddha said he had uh he said house house Builder you are seeing your
Rafters and beams have been destroyed never to be rebuilt again it's a a
little bit of a violent idea but uh but the context of that is that that instead
of living in the constructed World we're now going to live in in an organic world
the wholesome uh Source within is a source that's much more organic or maybe
biological and for that he uses um natural
metaphors and one of the common one is that of a plant growing a tree growing
it there's a seed that seed inside uh germinates it's Sprouts it grows it
becomes a large tree it flowers and then it produces fruit and Awakening
sometimes is called the fruit of practice and um and the language that he
uses for uh what we call in English practice spiritual practice in poly in
ancient language was a word that had to do they're closer to Growing we're
growing something bavana uh often it's translated as cultivation and and they
think of it as cultivating like a gardener cultivating a plant a farmer cultivate doing
cultivation we don't construct the growth of the plant we support it to nourish
it and so over and over again the Buddha uses these uh metaphor of the
constructed things that human beings make to represent how we get caught in
another place he uses the word he uses the idea of a a trap that that a tra
that a a hunter uses to trap deer and again a trap is something we construct
and sometimes we build our own mental constructions me we build these thought constructions that are made of fantasy
of stories that are not accurate and um and or only partially accurate and then
we live in the story and sometimes when two people meet but they don't realize they're both living in this thought
construct that they and sometimes their thoughts constructs are similar enough that they can relate and sometimes they
completely miss each other because of they're not really listening from this deep
place but they're listening through the filter of the constructed world of stories
ideas that uh that we paint reality with world of projection is a metaphor we use
in the modern world we're projecting onto other people and um and it's not
who they are but it they are we're seeing them through the lens of our projection so thought constructs
and so um the idea of a trap the idea of a of a uh the other thing that humans
build is if you want to tie two uh oxen together so they can both pull a plow
you build a yoke and then the two are tied together so the Buddha describes
how human beings in their attachment become yolked not to each other but
sometimes to each other for sure but yolked to uh their what they're attached to and so you know you can't really get
away you it pulls you along and um and so again the
constructed World represents this and now it's the the uncon the world that's
not constructed that's within us that which is biological that grows that
flows and sometimes the Buddha uses the metaphor from the natural world of um a
river or stream flowing to describe um the the how how Dharma
practice how the Dharma begins moving through us and our job is to stay in the
river stay in the current so it can flow along and um so in the beginning of
practice the natural metaphor that's used over and over again is to walk a
path to walk the path and uh you don't uh and and uh path maybe you make a path
sometimes by clear making a clearing but it's emptying something not constructing
something and then uh you walk the path and as you walk the path something grows
you get stronger and you're walking you become more fit for example if you and
then at some point uh you don't walk the path anymore but rather you're in the
river and you allow yourself to flow with the river so these are metaphors
that Buddha uses for this deeper operating system the wholesome operating
system and uh and that'll be the theme for this week uh The Road Less taken the
the road taken from this deep Source inside the wholesome operating
system so uh thank you and I hope that uh hearing this uh inspires you that
there is within you a wonderful capacity wonderful potential
uh natural potential in a sense that uh can support you and guide you through your life thank you very much