greetings dear sa thank you for your kind comments in
the chat yesterday uh But be sure to let me know if you have any suggestions for
improvement this week our meditations will be guided by the Buddha's own
instructions on mindfulness of breathing drawn from his foundational
discourse on Buddhist practice the
anap we started yesterday actually with the introduction to this
discourse which is on the key practice that's at the heart of the Buddhist
path in which the Buddha tells us to go to some place empty in order to
establish awareness some place
uncared and with a mind that's empty of self-
preoccupation the Buddha then instructs Us by summarizing his entire discourse
on mindfulness of breathing as follows always
attentive one breathes in with awareness and breathes out
with awareness so our effort today is to rest
the mind with continuous Awareness on the entire process the
whole cycle of breathing we want to know
intimately how we're experiencing the beginning
the beginning and end of each exhale and the pause after the exhale for the next
whole cycle begins
again of course the mind is likely to wander away from the breath and that's
okay as soon as you see that the mind has
wandered then without any irritation or frustration just come back
lovingly to your breathing always attentive we breathe in
with awareness and breathe out with
awareness so begin by closing your
eyes or if you prefer just lowering your gaze and give yourself permission for
the next 30 minutes to leave all your worries
concerns obligations and responsibilities outside the door of
your meditation room allow yourselves to drop down into
the flow of your lived experience resting in being
here in the present moment and letting go of past and
future for these minutes of meditation the invitation is to drop the
burden of the ego so
now set your intention your aspiration for this period of
meditation perhaps something as simple as may my practice serve as a condition
for awakening for myself and all
beings with such an aspiration is important to
know that you like all of us practicing here have the potential
for awakening so settling into a posture
that expresses your
intention posture that is grounded and balances being being both
relaxed and quietly energetic being friends with this
body offering it compassion as we do a brief fluid body
scan with this body however it is we can offer it our thanks our care
were supporting us and keeping us alive for all these
years so bringing appreciation and care to the body starting from the
head down through the neck
shoulders arms and
hands down through the Torso the
pelvis glowing down the thighs the lower
legs and the
feet our priority is to establish
Sati awareness that is embodied
and as continuous as the predominant quality of
the Mind
taking a deep Long satisfying
breath and connecting with the flow of
breathing then letting the breath gently come back to
[Music] normal and discovering the
Rhythm and the texture of our natural way of breathing
our task during this meditation is to stay connected with the whole process of
breathing and to know the quality of the breath just as
it is letting the breath
itself become our meditation
guide every breath is its own microcosm so see if you can stay with
the whole process of each inhale and each exhale
noticing the moment it starts how it grows then
Fades and finally ends with a slight pause
before the next one
begins as I mentioned yesterday I find it helpful to visualize the cycle of the
the breath as an energetic oval with the bottom of the oval at the
panum and the top at the crown of the head where there's a little
virtual opening in the skull so if this works for you you can
visualize the in breath starting at the paranam then moving up the back as the
inhale begins [Music] and then Fades with a brief pause above the top
of the head where the out breath then starts and Cascades down the
face and the Torso then ending again in the
parum or the whole cycle begins again
we are resting in and trusting the whole process of breathing
naturally we don't need to intervene in any
way just letting the breath breathe
itself e
if visualizing this oal doesn't work for you another way I find it helpful to
stay with the breath is to use the in breath as a
reminder to connect with the body and the out breath as a reminder to
relax
e
e e
knowing the breath feel feels intentional
conscious spacious we start to know the details of
the breathing the texture of the
breath and its
Rhythm by staying with and trusting the
breath we're cult AC ating our capacity for knowing the present
moment
e
e e
we rest in the breath
tenderly as a way of caring for our own
well-being
e
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting we bring our
attention to
this sending loving wishes of
well-being to everyone here medit meditating
together and now we return to our circle of compassion for ourselves and all
beings may all beings be safe and
protected being safe may all beings including
yourselves be happily at ease
PE may we all abide in
peace and may all beings everywhere be
free as I join my hands together and bow to you now I'm honoring your practice
[Music]
readings dear SAA is good to be here with you and
thank you for your kind comments in the chat yesterday but know that I'm uh
really interested also in hearing any suggestions for improvement you might
have so in the early texts the Buddha often describes the
mind as luminous and bright
Gil's teacher in Burma upand once said that the mind is like a
garden if neglected defilement weeds will
grow but if the plot is well tended it will be beautiful and
fruitful and this quote comes from a book of Up's
teachings which is called the State of Mind called
beautiful and the poly word for the noun
mind and the adjective for beautiful are the
same cha so if I were to tell you in P that
your mind is beautiful I would would say it's Chang
Chang in the ancient text there's another word
kalana which also appears frequently and which is usually
translated as good or wholesome however it literally means
beautiful the word k is closely associated with virtue and inner
goodness and it's true that as we get in the habit of following the Buddhist
precepts to abstain from taking life to abstain from taking what is not freely
given to abstain from doing harm with our sexuality
[Music] speech and from intoxicating the mind we gradually do purify our virtue
and inner goodness I'm in utter admiration of the
NS and monks I've practiced with because they all go to Such Great
Lengths to cause no harm painstakingly avoiding even the
slightest things that might cause harm to themselves or to
others and it's no exaggeration to say that they all move through their lives
with Beauty in everything they do or
say I've heard Gil say that we all have the potential
inside for something amazingly beautiful a
treasure that can be discovered cultivated and grown
inside so let me read you a teaching that Gil gave in this forum the 7 amm
teachings he said in meditation practice we're touching into a capacity of the
mind to be beautiful and wondrous something that may border on or feel
sacred the great value of this practice is to discover a rich wondrous beautiful
inner life that can inform how we live in the
world I like to think that as we discover this wondrous inner life we get
turned inside out what was inside is no longer inside but
is something we share with the world around us oh thank you Gil for
that and it's similar in the early texts the Buddha stresses that the
Dharma is Gana in the beginning Alana in the
middle and kalala in the end so literally our Dharma path is
beautiful in the beginning beautiful in the middle and beautiful in the
end we all have this capacity for inner
beauty and we need to trust the fact that our potential is
unlimited we all have the same
Birthright which is our enormous potential for goodness and
wisdom the Buddha also talked about being skilled in the beauty of
meditation and as you know in meditation we train and cultivating
awareness and when we're fully aware the mind is
beautiful and what we do becomes
beautiful my beloved zen teacher shunu Suzuki taught me that instead of having
a deep understanding of the teaching we need strong confidence in
our teaching which says that originally we have Buddha nature
and that Buddhist practiced is based on this faith in our
Buddha nature so let me read you some quotes
from Suzuki rosion Buddha nature and big
mind our original mind includes everything within itself nothing comes from outside your
mind the true understanding is that the Mind includes
everything when you think something comes from outside it means only that
something appears in your mind nothing outside yourself can cause
any trouble you yourself make the waves in
your mind if you leave your mind as it is it
will become calm this mind is called Big mind and to exist in big
mind is an Act of Faith big mind is something you have not
something to seek for big mind is like the great
Sky whatever kind of bird flies through it this Sky doesn't care
so for me existing in big mind as an act of faith means that I deeply trust the
Dharma the practice is supporting me it's taking me in the right
direction and I'm hoping to convey to you that in this practice whatever kind of
bird you are you're okay it's just
fine and then in the world of Buddhist PR practitioners you have plenty of
company the Tibetan teacher PMA children Echoes Suzuki ri's words when she says
our true nature is not semi-ideal that we have to live up up to is who we are right
now and that's what we can make friends with and
celebrate we already have what we need the wisdom the
strength the confidence the awakened heart and mind are always
accessible here now
always we're just uncovering them we're rediscovering them we're not
inventing them or importing them from somewhere else they're
here so this doctrine that our very essence is an unborn and undying
awareness is not limited to Mahayana and Tibetan
Traditions the ter terava Tha Forest teacher aan sha asserts that the original heart mind
shines like pure clear water with the sweetest
taste he often referred to the one who knows as a pointer
to the inherent wisdom within awareness
itself also in the Thai Forest tradition aan Mahaba says of
impermanence this vanishes that vanishes but that which knows they're
Vanishing doesn't vanish All That Remains is simple
awareness utterly pure and another teacher from our tradition
aan buddhadasa teaches that emptiness and mindfulness are
one most of us unconsciously identify as a separate threatened
deficient self but if we trust in the Dharma our practice will reveal the
freedom of our beautiful mind our true
nature our capacity to know and be aware is a beautiful
quality and one of the potentials of the Dharma is to be able to discover what's
beautiful inside and outside us to have eyes the inner eye and the physical eye
which is able to see what's beautiful
the quality of how we practice comes into play when we're looking at the
quality of the mind that's beautiful when we're aware we'll make
ethical choices do the necessary house cleaning and discover more of this
beauty that we already have so I'll close with the story of the
Musketeer very early in her life a musk deer began
to notice this heavenly scent in the air Intoxicated by this Divine Aroma she
set out to find the source she searched the depths of every
Forest smelled around every tree every blade of grass and still couldn't
discover where this scent was coming from
she determined because the scent was So Glorious she knew deep down that she
would be profoundly happy once she finally found it she spent her whole life
searching and one day fell exhausted to the forest
floor and as she fell one of her horns pierced her own
belly suddenly the air was overwhelmingly flooded with this Divine Heavenly
scent after a lifetime of searching in the final moments of her
precious life she realized the scent was coming from her
all
along you may have heard the Navajo tribe of Native Americans have a
concept of walking in Beauty so if you'd like a little homework for the next 24 hours you might
reflect on or try out how it might be to sit in
Beauty walk in Beauty stand in Beauty and lie down in
Beauty what might it be to live in
Beauty may your practice serve you in bringing light to your beautiful
mind and inner goodness thank you for your
attention thank you for your practice