good morning welcome welcome so today is the fifth day the
last day on I'll be continuing this series on the Poetry of
practice and as I've been doing in the earlier days in the week do a little bit of a guided
meditation well and then I'll drop in a poem and
then after the meditation I'll talk about the poem a little bit there's something about uh
poetry in some ways it can be really supportive of practice in that it uh
uses language in a way that maybe has some precision and yet it has can be very
evocative too in some ways there's a a meditation can be like this too where
there's some precision and yet uh be evocative and not in precision and terms
of using the usual language but maybe there's a way in
which it feels like this you know with meditation we're sometimes talking to
that that direct experience like what's actually happening and poetry is
pointing to an experience and maybe not So Much by describing it directly but
helping it to maybe arise in the reader of the
poem I don't know if that made any
sense and there's this way I guess
um part of the Poetry of practice for me is how
poetry uses language to help you listen and
experience but without uh being prescriptive maybe that's what I'm
pointing to and so there's a way in which
meditation practice often is prescriptive but the art of practice is
finding our way with the directions that are given some of you know right there's
these 16 steps of anti or you know all these distinct steps inti Pana Su or you
know I myself I've given plenty of meditation instructions and that's
really helpful but there's also another part of our s that maybe that's the
poetic part that is reading between the
lines that is feeling our way into the moment instead of just following the
instructions okay so with that as a short
introduction we'll take a meditation
posture and feeling into this moment
what is the experience of this moment
can we inhabit the body be present for the bodily
experiences in this moment the thoughts will do what
thoughts do can we just be here now
feeling the foundation of our sitting
surface we're not floating in time from the past and the present the mind
is perhaps doing that but the body is
here now connected grounded
feeling the pressure against the body of our sitting surface
and allowing the spine to be upright reflecting Our intention
to pay attention
noticing any areas of tightness tension in the
body on the eyes or
mouth maybe with an exhale letting the tension drain
away now in the shoulders to move away from the ears
allowing the back to feel supported if it is
supported if it's not to feel the uprightness
allowing the chest to be soft and the belly to be soft
we don't need to armor ourselves this meditation session can we
just be open at ease
bringing an aliveness of attention to the bodily
experience resting the attention on the sensations of
breathing tuning into being sensitive to what it feels like to have an in
breath
and what it feels like to have an out breath
noticing the tensions and the transitions between the
in breaths and out breaths I sit the we tension
but maybe that was a slip a sticky
transition I have a little tension in the body this
morning e
and when the Mind wonders we just very simply
gently Begin Again with this sensation of
breathing
e
e e
I'm going to drop in a poem
just allow the poem to be received you don't have to decide
whether you like it or not or what it means or and it just be received and maybe
allow it to touch you if it does if it doesn't that's okay too
this poem is called in the Moment by Billy Collins In the Moment by Billy
Collins it was a day in June all lawn and
Sky the kind that gives you no choice but to unbutton your shirt and sit
outside in a rough wooden chair and if a glass of iced tea and a
volume of 17th century poetry with a dark blue cover are available then the picture could hardly
be improved I remember a fly kept landing
on my wrist and two black butterflies with white and red wing dots bobbed around my
head in the bright air I could feel the day offering itself
to me and I wanted nothing more than to be in the moment but which
moment not that one or that one or that one or any of those that were scuttling
by seemed perfectly right for me plus I was too knotted up with
questions about the past and his tall evasive sister the
future my churchyard held the bones of George Hubert why did John Dunn's wife
die so young and more pressingly what could we serve the vegetarian twins who
are coming to dinner that evening who knew that they were going to bring their own grapes and why was that
driver that pickup flying down the road toward the lone railroad
track and so the Priceless moments of the day were squandered one by one or
more likely a thousand at a time with quandry and pointless
interrogation all I wanted was to be a pee of being inside the Green Pod of
time but that was not going to happen today I had to admit to
myself as I closed the book on the face of Thomas trahern and returned to the
house where I lit a flame under a pot full of floating brown eggs
and while they cooked in their bubbles I stared into a small oval
mirror near the sink to see if that crazy glass had anything special to tell
me
today
e e
I'll read this poem again in the Moment by Billy
Collins it was a day in June all lawn and Sky the kind that gives you no
choice but to unbutton your shirt and sit outside in a rough wooden
chair and if a glass of iced tea and a volume of 17 Century poetry with a dark
blue cover are available then the picture can hardly be
improved I remember a fly kept landing on my wrist and two black butterflies with
white and red wing dots bobbed around my head in the bright air I could feel the day offering itself
to me but and I wanted nothing more than to be in the moment but which moment not
that one or that one or that one or any
of those that were scuttling by seemed perfectly right for
me plus I was too knotted up with questions about the past and his tall
evasive sister the future my churchyard held the bones of
John George Herbert why did John Dunn's wife die so
young and more impressing what could we serve the vegetarian twins who were coming to dinner that evening who knew
that they were going to bring their own grapes and why was the driver that P up pick up flying down the road toward the
lone railroad track and so the Priceless moments of
the day were squandered one by one or
more likely a thousand at a time with quandry and pointless interrogation
all I wanted was to be a pee of being inside the green pond of
time but that was not going to happen today I had to admit to
myself as I closed the book on the face of Thomas trahern and returned to the
house where I lit a flame and rough pot full of floating brown
eggs and while they cooked in their bubbles I stared into a small oval
mirror near the sink to see if that crazy glass had anything special to tell
me
today e
[Music] here we go
[Music]
good morning welcome welcome as we have encountering a Billy
Collins uh this poet some of you might be familiar with him he was the poet laureate I think from 2001 to
2003 and uh he writes a way that seems like very
accessible and often with a little bit of Whimsy in it and talks about uh like
the ordinary experiences and if I remember correctly this poem I think was published in 2016
so relatively not so long ago this poem of uh it's called in the
Moment by Billy Collins
maybe I'll say uh before I read the poem again something that I love about this
poem there's so many fun things here but one is he's talking about like oh he's
just not mindful he's just not being present and yet he's giving us
details minute details about his day he actually was present he actually was
being mindful but he has this idea about what mindfulness is supposed to look like
what the experience is supposed to be and because maybe it's not matching his expectations he's uh like just kind of
like oh I'm not mindful or maybe he's using poetic license and saying he's not mindful but
then demonstrating that he is I don't know it's kind of fun for me
though to this he's like protesting that uh he's not being Mindful and yet he's
rating how much he notices about what happens in the part of a
day so even just yeah okay maybe I'll read the poem and then I'll talk about a little bit
more so again the poem is in the Moment by Billy
Collins it was a day in June all lawn and Sky the kind that gives you no choice
but to unbutton your shirt and sit outside in a rough way wooden chair and if a glass of iced tea and a
volume of 17th century poetry with a dark blue cover are available then the
picture can hardly be improved I remember a fly kept landing
on my wrist and two black butterflies with white and red wing dots bobbed
around my head in the bright air I could feel the day offering itself
to me and I wanted nothing more more than to be in the moment but which
moment not that one or that one or that one or any of those that were scuttling
by seemed perfectly right for me plus I was too knotted up with
questions about the past and his tall evasive sister the
future what churchyard held the bones of George Herbert why did John Dunn's wife die so
young and more pressingly what could we serve the vegetarian twins who were coming to dinner that evening who knew
that they were going to bring their own grapes and why was the driver of that pickup flying down the road toward the
lone railroad track and so the Priceless moments of
the day were squandered one by one or more likely a thousand at a time with
quandry and pointless inter conation all I wanted was to be a pee of
being inside the Green Pod of time but that was not going to happen today I had
to admit to myself as I closed the book on the face of Thomas trar and returned
to the house where I lit a flame under a pot full of floating brown eggs and while they cooked in their
bubbles I stared into a small oval mirror near the sink to see if that
crazy glass had anything special to tell me
today I know this poem makes me smile it makes me smile when I uh read it I
appreciate like he has this idea okay the conditions are finally perfect I'm
going to meditate here and it's going to be great it's like this Serene summer
day and he has presumably something that's enjoyable this book of poetry and I love this little detail he
gives us the color of the cover of the book so he's definitely present and later when he closes the book he even
tells us that what page he's on he's on the book the page that has the picture
of this person TR Thomas Thomas trahern I don't know who Thomas tahar
is and he notices maybe that um he has this idea
about time it's very interesting for me that the way time shows up in here in so
many different ways I could feel the day offering
itself to me and I wanted nothing more than to be in the moment so he wants to
be like in the particular place of time like just
now and he says that uh he wanted to be this P of being you know P like green
peas snap peas chick peas going to be a p of being inside the
Green Pod of time I don't know when I hear this I
feel like the Pod of time is something that's oppressive I mean that like squishes you in you're like like peas
Sal peas in a pod or I don't know is that the expression that we use that they are like they're snug like in peas
of it peas in a pod but meditation isn't like that it's like you know the moment after moment is
going and we're just uh noticing we're being present as these
Peas I don't know are are going I don't it's something I feel like it he has
this idea about time that doesn't feel quite right even though it's a little bit playful when he talks about uh that
he was um I was too nodded up with questions
about the past and his tall evive sister the
future questions about the past and the future so noticing that the mind is in
these different places time whereas he wanted to maybe be here in the moment
where the body is and he talks about how so much like
some of the things that we think about turn out not to matter I don't know who George Herbert is or
John Dunn but he asks what churchyard had the bones of George Herbert these
things I guess are pretty inconsequential we don't whether the bones are here or there it's not like we
can change them more and why did John Dunn's wife die so
young this is also something else that we can't change to things that uh maybe don't
have a consequence even if we do know the answer to them how often are we thinking about
things or wondering about things that turn out not really to matter interesting you know he doesn't
uh mention like Google in this poem even though this is that he this got
published in 2016 so the internet is there and it's available but maybe
there's some modern day like what these things that we are looking on our phone trying to find the answer to that
turn out not to be so inconsequential and so getting back to
this idea of um time he talks about the Priceless moments of the
day this idea that you know time is fleeting and that there's some beauty of
it maybe the some of the pricelessness of it is maybe the sense of
pricelessness is maybe what made feel him like he wanted to grab on to each of
them so one thing that I will that really strikes me about this poem is the
lack of uh is describing his inner life his inner
experiences all about maybe things that are happening out
there I guess may maybe he's talking about um questions that he has but again
it's not related to his inner life he feels really disconnected from his body
and instead these are all just things that are happening in his mind he does mentioned his body but what it's also
about things that are out there when these butterflies are near his
head and his wrist I remember a fly kept landing on my wrist and two black
butterflies with white and red wing dots bed around my head and the bright air
so that's our only clue that this person even has a body but it's only because uh
there's something out there that's interacting with them I think this is part of the connection between not being
here in time in this moment and not being connected with one's
body right the mind we know this is often in the past and not in the future
so I just get a kick out of this poem there's this uh I don't know you just imagine sitting
in the backyard thinking it's going to be lovely and then trying to meditate or be present and then like I'm just going
to go make some eggs but he's present for that too he's present for the the way that the water
is bubbling and the eggs are brown and that's okay so I'll read this poem
one more time it was a day in June all lawn and Sky
the kind that gives you no choice but to unbutton your shirt and sit outside in a
rough wooden chair and if a glass of iced tea and a volume of 17th century poetry with a
dark blue cover are available then the picture can hardly be
improved I remember a fly kept landing on my wrist and two black butterflies
with white and red wing dots bobbed around my head in the bright air I could feel the day offering itself
to me and I wanted nothing more than to be in the moment but which
moment not that one or that one or that one or any of those that were scuttling
by seemed perfectly right for me plus I was too knotted up with
questions about the past and his tall evasive future his tall evasive sister the
future what churchard held the bones of George Herbert why did John Dunn's wife
die so young and more op pressingly what could we serve the vegetarian twins who
were coming to dinner that evening who knew that they would bring their own grapes and I'm hoping that Zoom is doing
some noise cancellation for me here and I apologize if it's not and there's a lot of noise
outside who knew that they were going to bring their own grapes and why was the
driver of that pickup flying down the road toward the lone railroad
track and so the Priceless moments of the day were squandered one by one or
more likely a thousand at a time with quandry and pointless interrogation
all I wanted was to be a pee of being inside the Green Pod of time but that
was not going to happen today I had to admit to myself as I closed the book on the face of Thomas trahern and returned
to the house where I lit a flame under a pot full of floating brown
eggs and while they cooked in their bubbles I stared into a small oval
mirror near the sink to see if that crazy glass had anything special to tell
me today may you find yourself being
present for some moments today whether they're munding whether you find
yourself asking pointless questions or whether you find some beauty and Grace
today whatever you experience may you be present for your life as it's unfolding
thank you and thank you for practicing with me today it's been lovely to share this
poetry of practice this week thank you
it's say thank you very much for your comments it's very sweet to read your
comments I know poetry isn't for everybody and there were seasons in my life when it certainly was not for me I
wasn't a fan of poetry but I don't know now just uh love it