good morning everyone good morning Global YouTube s delighted to be
with you just want to give a shout out to many familiar names friends on the chat
and um warm greetings wherever you are in the world afternoon evening
day this is also a sound check so someone let me know if you can hear me
and um the sound is all
right great thank
you so I'm curious as we're warming up here um those of you who are silent are
very welcome to remain silent and those of you who are
chatting I would love to hear what you noticed about
wholeheartedness yesterday about respect and
wholeheartedness full attention of course you don't have to
report in but sometimes it's fun for everyone
this is the third talk in a series on dhic reciprocity the gifts we give the
Dharma and receive from our practice and
um we're at 7 o' now so I invite you to
um finish up your warm greetings when you're ready and to to settle in settle into a
posture that expresses
what is in your heart what is in your mind in terms of caring for yourself in
this practice
today start in with a couple of deeper slower
breaths softening the
eyes softening the tongue
and letting go releasing offering the out
breath dedicating yourself to this
time on the in breath inviting receiving awareness
allowing the attention to move to internal
experience your sense experience
noticing sound
temperature
sensation and any object of attention that you know
work for you any anchor is welcome hearing the field of sensations
of the body the flow of everything and I'll be offering some
brief instructions on
breath and internal posture the way we hold our minds and hearts in
relationship to the
practice so allowing the breathing to be natural normal
tuning
in with kind
regard to the sensations of
breathing attending to the in breath
with care complete
attention resting releasing on the out breath
all the way through the out breath and resting
gently in a little still moment between the out breath and the in breath
allowing each breath to be just as it is
noticing the movement of the diaphragm or the chest the
belly In Waves
perhaps and attuning to all the sensations [Music]
within each fingle
breath receiving allowing awareness to
brighten the fullest point of the in breath
letting go into resting in the out
breath
e e
from time to [Music] time checking your internal
posture the attitude towards this practice this
moment seeing how gracious
allowing
non-interfering it's possible to be with this moment
attending with
care there
two
e
e e
each time distraction is
noticed that is a moment of mindful awareness
to appreciate it include it as part of the
practice it's never too late to begin
again
e
e e
in the last few minutes of this
meditation the invitation is to turn your attention [Music]
ention towards the quality the internal posture
stance of how you are in this moment about the
meditation what's the quality of the
awareness the attitude or mood in the heart
and whatever that is to include that too with an attitude of
care respect kindness
and then considering these moments of
meditation through that lens of appreciative
care any moments of
peacefulness calm a finger snap of
mindfulness stretches of unbroken attention
everything small or
large and drink it [Music] in so in the goodness of it
and then turning your attention outwards to the
others practicing in this moment together here or at other times
even in Wishing them well
may they be safe happy
healthy may they be peaceful at
ease and
free and extending these wishes outwards further towards everyone your life
touches directly and
indirectly may all beings be safe
peaceful and free
thank you for your
practice e
oh welcome welcome dear sa especially those of you
who tiptoed in a few minutes late into our virtual
space today is like to offer some Reflections it's
the third of a series of five on dharmic reciprocity what we offer our practice
our lives and the resonance what we receive
which can be direct or indirect and today as I've mentioned to many of you
those of you who've been here this teaching is Loosely based on a little obscure sutta um discourse on the
qualities of Integrity in giving and um today I'll start by just
saying what the Buddha said about this he said a person of Integrity gives in such a way as not to
harm themselves or others even slightly and implicit in the language
this is written in poly is a resonance in the non-harming
term of kind and [Music] caring kind and caring
attitude so in giving of ourselves our time material Goods excuse me this means
self-care is key
self-care the Buddha describes a wise person of great wisdom as someone who
does not wish for affliction suffering harm for themselves others
themselves or others or the world but
rather a person of Integrity a wise person
offers wishes for benefit of self other
and both as well as all concerned so don't leave yourself out
don't leave yourself out from a Buddhist perspective this
means practitioners that's us were encouraged to cultivate a baseline
approach of nonharming that's based on care not just for our common Humanity ity but our
common sensient with all creatures each being's wish no matter
how buried or thwarted is to live to not be
harmed this wish weaves through nearly all sensient life most of the
time the impulse the commitment to care and non-harming appears over and over
again in the Buddhist teaching often it's the first step of
practice and there's this little phrase that appears over and
over again setting aside rod and weapon a practitioner dwells compassionate with
care for the welfare of all living things all living beings isn't that
beautiful that's often used at the very first very first first step of engaging
in serious meditation practice when a person would go to become a follower of
the Buddha and so it's not so surprising that this um emphasis on non-harming
ripples through all different dimensions of Buddhist
practice it's core to the compass of Buddhist ethics to not kill not steal to
not engage in sexual misconduct lie or
intoxicate in ways that lead to heedlessness those are kind of the guard
rails nonharming can include preventing harm through
giving and this impulse is not limited to humans I love this anecdote so in a
2017 study scientists finally looked into documented and confirmed anecdotal
stories this these marine biologists have been hearing for years and the
stories have been that um ship after ship had noticed this mobbing behavior
in humpback whales and what happened was you know humpbacks and other whales hear
through the you know communicate through Quicks and other sounds that transmit through the water and they would hear
another whale in distress or even another mammal in distress from being
attacked by killer whales orcas and they would come and encircle
the threatened animal and protect it from being
attacked and they would beat off these orcas with their Mighty fins and the
scientists even found scarring on these huge fins from
protecting the innocent
this non-harming impulse can also take the form of practical care I ordained
for a time at a monastery in Yan mymar Burma and very early on I was inspired
inspired to learn that the teacher there established the first free clinic in the
city quite a large city donated the monastery donated the land they donated
the material Goods the medicines and the doctors and nurses would come andol unteer and offer their time to the
poorest of the poor people who could not afford any other medical care that same place donated land to
Buddhist nuns running an orphanage and all of this it was kind of just unspoken very humbly done because
it was natural it was an outgrowth this offering out of a deep commitment to
care to kindness
and ripple effects through the local area as you can imagine were
significant and the people who lived in the monastery were loved cared for by
the community in turn this
reciprocity inal practice non-harming this internal attitude the
inner voice of kindness in the mind and heart is a huge
gift to yourself and your
practice again the means Echo the
ends the best we can do to bring an attitude of gentleness care when encountering not so
helpful internal habits some of us have learned it's so common in our culture to
internalize judgment blame self-criticism so to notice them while
all not believing them just
like I remember when one of my nieces was quite young we were at some big
holiday gathering everyone was gathered around the table eating and she told
this very very queer story that she completely bought into in the moment of
a cat driving across the Golden Gate Bridge in a convertible and she had all of us just
riveted because she was so clear about it and so convinced that it happened but
of course didn't believe it this was confabulation
story we could still love the Storyteller even when the stories aren't so nice they're developed through
familial conditioning societal conditioning noticing and kindly
disengaging with a nonharming attitude from any inner
harshness stories even a pushy approach to mindfulness begins to reconfigure
unhelpful mental patterning non-harming includes no
longer feeding no longer fueling unhelpful habits no longer getting
behind them from a Buddhist perspective this friendly positive
regard towards inner experience is
ideal can increase together with
wholeheartedness with a caring attention respect deep listening to
oneself all of that can transmute into gratitude Joy Wonder
another way of inviting these beautiful qualities the Gratitude Joy
wonder even concentration is to reflect on your own
past acts of care and kindness or restraint not doing
harm this can create such joy and resonance in the
practice and if regrets arrive instead it's an invitation to clean up
your own act a commitment to cleaning up one's own act can actually really help
in meditation itself it's a helpful Act of
generosity for your own practice formal practice of meditation
mindful I'm sorry not mindfulness meta loving kindness meditation is also really
helpful there's many many resources on audiio Dharma and here on this um
homepage YouTube channel for that also at sa.org I have a half day on it Kevin
Griffin has um resources on practicing loving kindness and difficult
times and just as non-harming is
fundamental to the Buddhist path this kindness care toward self and others
along the way is also a traditional way to reduce anxiety and fear increased
confidence courage concentration and all of
this has a reciprocal effect on ourselves and others there are in
addition to Millennia of Buddhist teachings about this anecdotal kinds of
teachings there's recent Decades of scientific literature randomized control child
studies about this so today to consider the resonance
the reciprocity of any bit of nonharming
care kindness in your own practice
in your actions in your life and to enjoy them to commit to them
and enjoy and notice the effects on your practice so your assignment should you
choose to accept it for tomorrow is to notice these moments in
your daily life in your quiet moment and reflect on them see what effect they
have for you thank you very much for your kind attention