so good day welcome welcome
welcome so today we'll continue with our our discussion of the Four Noble
Truths I'm taking nourishment from this um chat that I see going
along all these different cities countries time
zones morning afternoon evening here it's just uh just about
Dawn and there's a there's a gentle rain that I can hear on the roof perfect sounds for
meditating so let's uh let's start
there our meditation this morning will be a simple
one
and we'll begin the settling process then once um once the bodies are
[Music] still and the breathing begins to regulate
then I'll just offer a one question for
reflection
let's begin by inviting Stillness from the inside
out
it helps to be settled squarely on your seat or
support
arranging the hands so the shoulders aren't pulled
forward
and for a few times breathing breathing in such a way that you bring breathe all the way
down the Torso as far as the breathing will
go and all the way out
allowing the breathing to return to normal when you're ready
self-regulating and letting go of any any extra tension in the
limbs arms and hands
hips thighs
Knees Down to the heel and the
toes
settling
[Music]
for
you [Music]
[Music]
staying here with what's more
simple simple breathing
simple
sensation in a way that's
peaceful
for
[Music]
for [Music]
right
that's
[Music]
meditating for these minutes degree of settledness may
have increased maybe from a one to a
two maybe a five to a and
[Music]
eight to offer this question into our meditation not for
pondering just to see what responds
right [Music]
now where am I
free
for
where can I sense Freedom just
now
for
[Music]
yeah
for
oh
[Music]
for
m
[Music]
in a moment I will ring the bell to end the
sitting what would it be or how might it be
[Music] possible to
extend any sense of peace or
Freedom beyond the sitting extending
any sense of
Freedom Beyond this this
meeting into the activities of the
day May all beings keep Freedom
close
[Music]
that
so welcome again and this morning continuing with the discussion of the Four Noble
Truths some Reflections on the third the third Noble Truth the sensation of
suffering um part of what I am want to emphasize this morning is uh a
reflection for us and that is how to or Orient ourselves and our practice toward
a radical freedom in a way that inspires inspires
us Keeps Us encouraged so as we've been talking
about the last couple of days the task of the first Noble Truth is to
understand understand the nature of suffering and to observe it in our direct
experience task of the second Noble Truth is um to abandon that craving that
leads on to suffering to becoming and suffering to abandon it the way we might
abandon a sinking ship for our own
well-being and then we come to the third Noble Truth which has the task of uh the third Noble Truth is to be
realized it's to be made real it's to be known known and seen
directly so in the classic suta on this topic the setting in motion the wheel of
the dma the Buddha puts it this way he says
now this buus is the noble truth of the cessation
of suffering it is the remainder fading away and sess of that same craving the
craving of the second Noble Truth The Giving Up and relinquishing of
it freedom from it non-reliance on
it remainder fading cessation giving
up relinquishing freedom
non-reliance I wonder what you hear but I I hear I hear a certain kind of
Independence uh a certain kind of agency something
powerful uh about in a in a certain sense being being
um being freed from the influence of this craving in our lives not relying on
it it it sounds so refreshing just to say the that set of
words so Gil in writing about nibana uh the ending of suffering uh
puts it this way he says a nibana which we could say is the one-word definition of the third Nal truth says it's the
good news of terraa Buddhism I like that keeps us
encouraged so he puts it this way niana literally means to go out like a fire or
to cool and applied to the mind it refers to the extinguishing of the
fevers of greed hate and delusion the three roots of
suffering the Buddhist choice of this term Nana was intimately tied to the
imagery of his famous fire sermon where he describes all the senses as on fire on fire with greed hatred and
delusion it's a really interesting choice to use uh fire imagery to talk
about nibana because in uh in what we've seen uh one of the conditions for the
arising of suffering is clinging sense contact conditions a
certain kind of craving conditions clinging identity and so on to
suffering and there's this really interesting point about the poly word
the Buddha's word for clinging aana is the same as the word for
fuel and if you take the fuel away then the fire can't burn and suffering is
extinguished Gil sums it up by saying understanding how deep rooted and subtle
this clinging is in our own minds our own unliberated minds we come to appreciate the mind of nibana as
refreshingly cool and peaceful
so something about the third Noble Truth a sensation of that very craving the sort of breaking of the
chains of conditions that lead from ignorance to craving to Dua to
suffering something about it is that it's it's utterly radical in the extent
to how free one can be if you look at the Buddhist teaching the Buddha
describes uh the possibility of a freedom that is complete totally extinguished free from
suffering a radical Freedom uh the the old image is like um
one's ignorance is made like a palm stump if you you can imagine a a palm tree that's been cut down for some
reason and then uh no tree will grow from that stump or root again
it's that final so is so is the ending of suffering that's possible in the
Buddhist teaching and this points us right to the what I want to say about the the art of
relating to the third Noble Truth and that is how can we do so in a way that's
encouraging and inspiring for us and for others um without getting discouraged
actually one of the one of the things that can come up when thinking about such a radical possibility of Freedom
one is great inspiration and energy another thing that could happen is the
the um there's a sort of measuring stick that comes up in the mind and measures the the metaphorical miles from oh this
is my mind now to oh that's that's a A Million Miles Away freedom is a
million miles away from here and people can get discouraged from that so so part of the
art is how to stay encouraged how to how to relate to a radical ideal and stay
encouraged we have a lot of help with this in the tradition um one of the
first things is a a frame of mind that that is that um in just the
way that Dua suffering is not abstract it's right here so too can we look right
here for Freedom we can look right here in what's here for uh freedom to this
extent it's not an abstract thing when the Buddha monks were described as the happy
ones and it um in a conversation with saruta one of the Buddhist Chief
disciples we learn that it's it's visible it's evident his freedom is uh
can be seen with our own eyes not abstract but something right
here something tangible
so some of the ways to stay encouraged these are the things these are the things I want to I want to offer
one uh is uh first this principle recognizing that there are Pleasures all
along the way of the path there's nourishment all along the way like we're very well well supported along the path
from here to the final goal of Dharma practice one is a a sort of nourishment
we know well and that those are the pleasures of mindfulness
practice the nourishments of mindfulness practice others might be the joys of
Sana Community I think now of this uh this community that's that's here on
these weekday mornings sitting and reflecting together they're the sort of nourishments of the well-being of
receiving of compassion and of giving it there's the the Beauty and
encouragement and insight also of uh the sort of discoveries the energy that comes from the discoveries and insights
that we have in our meditation and then how those affect us
off the cushion so to speak maybe the sort of lightness and peace that extend into our
day and then of course the happiness of concentration and what they call the
Bliss of blamelessness the the nourishment of a mind free of
regret so many joys so many joys to keep us encouraged along the way from here to
the end of the path one I'd like to talk just a little
bit about are called the the rendered temporary liberations of the
Mind chto Viti chetto is like chto is mind Viti is a
liberation and it's so interesting looking in the looking in the old um the
old texts that there are there are a number of liberations of the mind that actually aren't all the way at the end
of the path like they don't they don't wait for us to arrive however many miles away before experiencing them and being
nourished by them one is related to the practice of loving kindness I mean we get a sense of this
when we practice meta just a just in a moment wishing Wishing Well cultivating an
intention of Good Will brings so much Beauty and lightness into the heart just just a a moment of it feels so good can
feel so good and then that that um that practice
of meta becomes a liberation of the mind when it's when it's cultivated to such
an extent that the heart and mind is sort of suffused with loving kindness and the
mind becomes quite unified without without an experience of
a boundary between inside and outside it's a very beautiful St and a a sort of and qualified as a
temporary liberation of mind uh the same process is held for
compassion and this this is really interesting because it it keeps us in
contact it keeps us related uh with the suffering of the
world our practice our practice happens right here right here with with all
this and the practice of compassion keeps our keeps our our heart alive
awake beautiful and we know that suffering is right
here but there's a way of cultivating cultivating compassion to the extent and
just just as just as with meta that compassion suffuses the heart and the
mind and the mind UNIF ifies in such a way that we have a sort of temporary
liberation of the Mind One of These encouragements one of these encouragements that's available to
us so I I describe these I describe these um just so we know that say we're
say we're walking along quite a long path um you can trust that you're going
to find nourishment you need as you go I'd like to wrap all this up with the
image of a sailing the sailboat uh you can imagine in say say
you're going to Embark uh in one of two ways uh so you can embark on the
sailboat one with this attitude of oh how I wish for the shore the shore is so
far away from me I'm pining I'm pining now do you do we hear the craving
and the clinging and the becoming and the dukka that uh that attitude hurts right
away and then we can turn our mindfulness to that if that's the attitude that comes
up so that's that's the first attitude with which we can Embark and then the other is an attitude that knows that we
have the provisions for the the journey we have the faculties we have the patience we've got the resources and the
resourcefulness we can trust our Ingenuity and our energy we have a map and compass and rope and enough
food and we have this attitude of setting out
that uh we can do this I can um I can set out on my boat I can tack this way
and that I know how to stay safe on the path and I can treasure the
sea yeah which of these two attitudes can we can we take out which one do we
prefer and which one uh which one enjoys the
sea and arrives at a shore of
Peace so may we all be oriented and encouraged prepared and Endeavor
together on this path of the third Noble Truth the final ending of
suffering and tomorrow we'll turn to the fourth Noble Truth and look at some of uh how we put the conditions in place
for the arising of this liberating wisdom take care may all
beings be free and treasure the
path