you know there's that that saying uh if you think you're Enlighten you
know go home spend some time with family for the weekend or something right but
the original saying is if you think you're enlightened leave 2 hours early for a 30
minute commute be styed by an entire closure of
Market Street sit in a basically a traffic
parking lot for 90 minutes while people dressed as Ken and Barbie
and Super Mario Kart just lap you you
know and and remember that the last time you
were supposed to be here you didn't put it in your calendar and completely
forgot it and come from a lineage of guilt prone
people
and I did okay maybe equinom like C see miness maybe
um but I'm uh happy to be here now
so um
okay so the uh the the but
uh placed uh an N anich at the center of
experience and um we said the world trembles in all
directions anicha is um is usually rendered as impermanence
and connotes two things in that way the the impermanence of people places things
that were all ruled by finitude and all it's
all breaking apart and um and so on the one hand
there's the this this level of anich the the dying is in the being
born and then there's another level of anich which is kind of like the micro
micro experience of of change of change being a kind of
Gateway for for understanding for certain kind of insight Pathways anich
figures prominently where we're no longer focused on people places things
the anich of all of this but um focused on the the changing of all of all
phenomena and in the arising the passing and so this is the n rendered as
impermanent but also sometimes rendered as uh as un
uncertainty uncertainty and it strikes me kind of a
testament to the the the sort of Genius of the tradition that uncertainty was
was placed at the heart of all things and now Millennia
later in you know in philosophy and science math statistics it's like
uncertainty is uh Central in you know know in epistemology
the philosophy of knowledge how we know uncertainty is there in all of our
statistical understanding uncertainty is there in in the understanding of our
brain our brain basically coping with uncertainty Moment by moment doing what
it can to uh reduce uncertainty to not be
startled and so this kind of desperate tussle with what the Buddha
highlighted in moral philosophy um we we all have our views about what's
what's right we may not adhere to them all the time but we have our views about what's right we have to have our views
about what's right and yet how do we essentially hedge against moral
uncertainty how do we hedge against the permanent possibility of being
wrong not merely about uh this or that but about goodness
itself about what goodness entails so this is Toby or his
colleagues will M CasCal um every in a in a book on moral
uncertainty every generation in the past has committed TR tremendous moral wrongs on the basis of false moral views moral
atrocities were of course driven in part by the self-interest of those in power
but they were also enabled and strengthened by the common sense moral views of society at at the time about
which what groups were worthy of moral concern given this dismal track record
it would be extremely surprising if we were the first generation in human
history to to have even broadly the correct moral world view it's a
Paramount importance therefore to figure out which action Society takes as common
sensical permissible today we should really think of as barbaric we think and they go on to
conclude we think therefore that considerations of moral uncertainty the value of moral
information should lead us to conclude that further research is one of the most
important moral priorities of our time ideally one day we will have resolved
the Deep moral questions that we face and we'll feel confident that we have found moral truth in the meantime
however we need to do the best we can given our
uncertainty so what what what's a kind of wise relationship to this what's a
wise relationship to uncertainty
um beron Russell said the whole problem of the world is that fools and Fanatics
are always so certain of themselves but wiser people are so full of
doubts the Buddha said that um one of the Wellsprings
of of uh of our suffering is attachment to
views which is attachment to views and it strikes me that uh in some
way our our attachment to views are a kind of defense against
anicha defense against uncertainty and
nuance and the safety of the known the safety of our categories our moral
certainties and self-righteousness so all aided and EDD by a kind of
clinging to view and this plays out in small
personal ways and in global ways in our politics in
our Judicial System the Supreme Court of just starting with a conclusion and then
rationalizing your way to it seeking confirmatory
evidence uh after the conclusions reached
and certainty is um it's a very dangerous kind of state it it's
certainty is a kind of it's almost like a gateway drug for the other kesas for
the other forces of uh suffering greed hate
delusion and so much of the harm we we do so much
of the harm we cause to ourselves and to others a function of of a certain kind
of um certainty certainty we we don't tend to cause so
much harm from the perspective of um of
nuance and so all of this clinging is very uh kind of understandable because
as an animal anicha feels like Risk anich sense of not knowing it feels
exactly like like Risk and information is sometimes
described defined as kind of like the reduction of uncertainty information is
the reduction of uncertainty I hear a sound I don't know
what it is I look over to see oh it's a a person or an animal or whatever right
there's information there's a reduction of uncertainty
and there's a you know a kind of prominent model of our brain where our
brain is is our brain function revolves around kind of desperate e efforts to
reduce uncertainty Moment by moment the kind of brain is an
uncertainty management machine or the brain is a prediction machine trying to
guess where what the tra trajectory of this moment is if I can discern that I
don't have I can navigate I can I don't have to be surprised startled by the
next moment so I keep compulsive sense of orientation what is this where does it
Point what's the vector of this moment
and often clinging to view is is a is um
is a way we try to navigate uncertainty uh so we sort of Are We rely
we could say on the past on Karma as a way of understanding what's
next but that is not the way of Dharma
exactly secret of life Oscar wild says is to appreciate the pleasure of being
terribly terribly deceived yeah the pleasure of being
terribly deceived and on the Dharma path
we we um we come to love our mistakes not
merely to be unashamed by them but actually to Delight to Revel in them our
mistakes and it is if you can kind of get over the egoic blow you know and
the the defensiveness of it it is exhilarating in the way that wild
suggests to discover one's wrongness to find out that we've been
deceived to step out of self-deception the lot of the Dharma path is the path
of stepping out of self-deception the kind of moral pities and self serving
autobiographical tales with which we've kind of uh hummed oursel to sleep
forever you know and um the traffic's still in me a little
bit so when you when you come to uh come to
love love love yourself like really deeply really deeply not loving yourself
for some reason just loving yourself um
are are the mechanisms of self-deception
um uh it's no longer a cause for shame but actual kind of exhilaration
so delusion is described in different ways here I'm kind of talking about it
as clinging attachment to view or uh delusion as being a function of clinging
to view the clinging like seals in some
delusion um some teachers talk about delusion as merely just being lost in
thought you know the the kind of um the
moment when the the bubble of discursive thinking collapses and you realize you've been
you know in a different world not at IMC not and um and and it was deluded to be
focused on some to be living in the world defined by your thought but it's it's non- delusion to
wake up to okay this moment just being here and um and so uh that's one way
delusion is described another is there's the kind of diluted type you know the
greed hate and delusion types um some researchers say even at
the level of a single celled organism Behavior must necessarily fall into one
of three possible categories move towards approach move away withdraw or
neither no response these three basic options cannot be
reduced further and therefore would seem to represent the most parsimonious
description of Behavioral Tendencies approach withdraw no response
greed is approach aversion withdrawal delusion no response right and so from
this perspective Avers greed and aversion or hatred are very strong
motivational States you know strong motivational States we know exactly what
we want we know exactly what we want to go away delusion is characterized by the
absence of a strong motivational stance and the kind of lack of awareness
of pleasant unpleasant neutral um in some ways is a blessing but also it
because it actually is it's sort of like some kind of relative of equinity where
we feel less compelled by a you know a sense of urgency Moment by
moment but it's also associated with um
troublemaking decisions uh kind of manifest as indecisiveness we don't know
what to listen to inside of ourselves it's kind of all noise no signal
another kind of way of understanding delusion is that um there's a kind of
more pervasive sense of it which is something closer to ignorance
of and ignorance is generally said to be about not understanding the four noble
truths that there is suffering that there is a cause that there is an end that there is a path
um but I would say more generally ignorance I associate with ignorance of
like just losing the plot losing the plot very easy to lose the plot in a
human life very easy as maybe our default position is we're losing the
plot we've we've taken our eyes off what
actually matters so um here a delusion is a kind of basic
state of confusion of bewilderment and
um and so greed greed feels like kind of bottomless hunger the the hole in the
heart that one's desperately trying to fill and aversion is the heart's just
unfire you know it's liken to cauldron you know water boiling over
right um grade the whole aversion the fire and delusion what does that feel
like the delusion feels exactly like the truth you know we don't differentiate
our delusion from our wisdom they're if we knew if we could do that we would no
longer be diluted we would put it down right but we live in this kind of
strange way basically in a kind of Katherine Schultz says we live in almost
a state of assuming omniscience you know of kind of
pervasive all knowing because we we just
don't we don't know what we don't know and um the Dharma paath is very much
about unknown unknowns know unknown unknowns not known unknowns unknown
unknowns and so um we we talk a lot
about uh the kind of uh epidemic of self-doubt um
but from a psychological perspective um overconfidence is a far
more pernicious actor on This Global stage it's one researcher called it the
mother of all psychological biases over confidence you
know and so how do we live with the permanent possibility of being
wrong uh this entails a kind of um a
commitment to live life on a as a kind of continuous feedback loop where we we
we are taking in we are relying on uh relying on the kind of the the
things and the people and the the problems we run into in our life as a
way of Illuminating that which we do not understand yet and sometimes it's only
in the collisions that happen you know with with others uh that we can begin to
understand the ways in which the provincial qualities of our view the
places where our delusion lurks you know because it's it's so unnoticed in our
life and yet it will have impacts on others it will we will misconstrue
others we will fail to understand to anticipate to predict and we will cause
problems and so we stay open to um
to uh the kind of surprises and the ways in which um our delusion manifests we
stay open with humility to this kind of feedback loop that is Life Giving
receiving growing
and there are there are limits to our knowing there will always be more to
know and as a kind of image of this I I saw this
astronomical thing where it's like they're right but it's a good metaphor it's like we con currently see a sphere
around us extending 46 billion light years in all directions it's known as
the observable universe light from galaxies beyond the sphere hasn't yet had time to reach us
on our leading cosmological theory the rate at which new galaxies will become
visible will Decline and those currently more than 63 billion light years away
will never become visible from Earth we could call this region the region within
this distance as the eventually observable universe accelerating expansion also
puts a limit on what we can ever affect if today you shine a a ray of light into
space it could reach any Galaxy that's currently less than 16 B billion year
light years away but galaxies further than this are being pulled away so quickly that neither light nor anything
else we might send could ever affect them I found that kind of uh beautiful
that like the eventually observable universe and then there's something beyond that you know that's like will
forever be out of our reach and that is a little how delusion feels to me you
know so there's a a kind of classic experiment where people were given
identical pairs of this is many years ago you know given identical pairs of clothing and asked to pick out their
favorite and people would do it they would say well this one is you know I like this one better the Fabric's softer
or whatever and um and sometimes there's kind of a
model of confabulation confabulation usually in the context of
neurological disease but where um we
give rationals and reasons for having done something but they're completely untethered to the actual causes of why
we did what we did and yet we believe it we're not lying we're not lying Ing and saying
like oh well I just put that there because I thought it would you know need it for later no no no it's like you
whatever you um we just make it make it up we it's confabulated right and and
sometimes it's called on honest lying you know there's no intentional sense of
deception or anything but and yet um we we concoct fabricate rationals for why
we did what we did why we believe what we believe and from a Buddhist perspective confabulation is not merely
confined to neurodegenerative disease it is our way of life in a deep sense
confabulating you know and a lot of what we are doing is uh essentially kind of
rationalizing or defilements The KES say making them look
dignified and our mind is um is very
very uh slippery and many of our you know it's like many of our habits and
the the reasons we give for our lives are often fundamentally different from
the causes and reasons are the best we can do we can't perceive cause ity exactly
in this way we just do our best to narrate it to understand
it um and all we have at some level is what is conscious even though there's a
a billion things happening beneath the radar of Consciousness
right and so in a way we we've become too satisfied with the stories we tell
about ourselves the wise of our life why I did this why I believe that why I want
this why we feel the way we do and so
part of delusion is about becoming more and more sensitive more and more
sensitive to the ways in which we confabulate and we pull a kind of fast
one on ourselves yeah the ways in which we lull ourself into our kind of um
you know Pious certainties and so
we we have to um we develop some measure of Courage for that because it's
actually kind of humiliating to see how easy it is to pull a fast one on
ourselves how easy it is and so we're getting very sensitive
to the kind of subtle movements of our mind how do we begin to perceive that
which we do not yet perceive and
so part of how we begin to uproot delusion is we become uh radically
accepting at the cognitive level we befriend all of the dooka in us we
befriend all of the kind of our quirkiness and defilements we actually
know longer try to sanitize them as something else it's not morally it's not
blaming ourselves morally for it you know it's not it's not this kind of you
know um yeah this moralism about our inner life there's a kind of Innocence
that animates even our greed hate and delusion we want to really actually feel
our way into that otherwise it becomes a kind of object of shame it becomes a
something like a testament about some defect at the core of our being and that
is will lead to many distortions of you
requires us to rationalize in order to keep a sense
of dignity but the invitation is actually to befriend all of the kind
of you know um all of the all of the grizzled bits
in our kind of heart you know otherwise we we um we become ashamed and when
we're ashamed we hide we want to get sensitive to our
body when we kind of lose our bodily awareness and become embedded in
narrative when our words our thoughts our language
when that starts to get kind of like a more and more remote from our ex embodied
experience you know this is a sign and so we we start to get more and
more sensitive how do I stay how do I speak and live in an experience near way
rather than being as Gil describes like in those concentric circles of our being
and the outermost you know circle is very
elaborate mental proliferation and Frameworks we start to like okay I can
feel there's some alienation in those words I can't it's almost like I can't
Channel my body into those words they're just they're out in some other
orbit and once we get out into that orbit we lose contact with this kind of
like basic embodied experience and we can tell ourselves
anything when we get out to that orbit and we'll believe
anything so we have to actually have come back a lot to to V to to to feeling
feeling as the kind of engine of uh the engine of uh so many of our
stories and philosophies and political orientations can be just the exhaust
coming off of an unconscious relationship to affect you know I don't like how this
feels you know uh and we miss that
and then but out of that friction arises a million things and you can just live
in a kind of prison of One's Own delusion as
if that's what matters to begin to actually clarify delusion we want to
come closer back to the body to the kind of urgency of affect of VNA as it
manifests in the circuits of our body and
so um equinity in other words with greed and aversion actually reduces the need
for delusion to sanitize the first two yeah and so sometimes I say like you
know um uh delusion launders our greed and our hatred
the way that delusion functions is to dignify the other
kesas and so to launder something is to take what
is you know take dirty money and make it clean we do that with our greed and our
hatred make it look like um something
dignified and so if we can have equinity with the kind of effec of current of
greed of hate uh we don't have to kind of build and
fabricate proliferate so um so
egregiously and um and so we come to uh trust the V and
are careful not to rationalize the clinging if we're going to cling okay fair enough but we don't we don't um we
don't uh pull a fast one on ourselves by calling it by another
name so this is on my mind in part because um you know just my own my my
own grappling you know with uh the world and um The Suffering of the world and
what feels very close to uh to my heart in various
ways and and the recognition that that
views are are channels into which our
greed and hatred flow our views and the the the the
questions and the issues and the pain points that are most uh ignite us are of
course what we care about but there are also those questions in that make the
the most frictionless channel into which our greed and hatred
flows that's what we tend to notice we notice that into which our greed and
hatred can flow and we ignore other forms of
dukka and so King uh said Justice is love in
calculation love in calculation but
um it's it's um very easy very easy to
ignore Dr King
and in those issues where there's uh no one no one to hate there's no way for us
to channel some of our defilements um even if those issues are actually of
profound moral concern we tend to just ignore those tend to ignore those and
there are many and so the things that um we care
about most on the one hand we want to protect that care but the care becomes
ens snared with clinging and certainty and delusion and attachment to views and
it becom a kind of channel for our greed and our hatred and greed and hatred will
not resolve anything in a durable
way and
so all of this is um it's on my mind in part um
uh in a in a certain way it kind of culminates in
um some some lines from uh the uh always reliable Zade Smith writing about Israel
and Palestine last last couple weeks ago in New
Yorker she says um at the end we've arrived at the point at which I must
clearly state where I stand quote where I stand stand on the issue that is which
particular political settlement should in my own personal view occur on the
other side of a ceasefire this is the point wherein by
my stating of a position you are at once liberated into the simple pleasure of
placing me firmly on one side or another putting me over there with those who
lisp or those who don't with the ephraimites or with the people of
Gilead yes this is the point at which I stake my rhetorical flag in the
Fantastical linguistical conceptual unreal Place built with words where
rapes are minimized as needs be and the definition of genocide quied over where
the killing of babies is denied and the Precision of drones glow glorified where
histories are reconsidered or Rewritten or analogized or simply ignored and Jew
and colonialist are synonymous and Palestinian and terrorist are synonymous
and language is your accomplice an alibi in all of it language euphemized and
instrumentalized and abused put to work for your cause and only for your cause
so that it does exactly and only what you want it to do let me make it easy
for you put me wherever you want misguided socialist toothless humanist
naive novelist useful idiot apologist denier Ally contrarian collaborator
traitor inexcusable coward it is my view
that my personal views have no more weight than an ear of corn in this
particular essay the only thing that has any weight in this particular essay is
the dead let's just sit for a
minute
for for
[Music]
so offer this for your U consideration and um please uh as always pick up
whatever is useful leave uh all the rest behind okay