hello everyone and welcome for this meditation session and
uh the session is uh connected to this five week introduction to mindfulness
meditation series I'm doing on these um 7
a.m. and um so with that in mind the theme for
this week will be mindfulness of emotions and for the first meditation related to
this I'd like to keep it really simple and uh start with an an
analogy that if you are going to cross a
field which I did recently that is
Muddy maybe marshy Maybe easy to get deeply
stuck in the mud and it's a slow going get sucked into the mud and it to pull
your feet out again and over and over again and it's a hard
going but then you discover that right there in the field there are stepping
stones and if you just step from one stepping stone to another there's no
getting stuck in the mud and it's easy going and the mud is still there in fact
now the field looks more beautiful and uh has its own dignity its
own value but um you're not getting stuck in it and so it's nice to walk and
observe and be with it and stepping from one stone to another where you're free of the
mud so the same way uh emotions are very
important for mindfulness meditation uh for the point of view of mindfulness
there's no emotion which is wrong to have and uh there's no condemning of an
emotion but what we're trying to do is not have some judgment about an
emotion but trying not to uh get stuck in the mud to get stuck in it and it's
possible to get stuck both in uh Pleasant emotions and unpleasant ones
and the pleasant ones we don't recognize often that we're stuck that we have kind of but because it's so nice but uh the
idea in mindfulness meditation is to learn how to uh respect the dignity and
value and and circumstances of every emotion we have while walking on the
Stepping Stones while walking uh in a place where we don't get stuck where
it's firm and dry and and uh so very supportive and we don't get pulled into
it so I would like to offer uh one way that maybe you can do this and maybe
experiment and that is that uh uh in this meditation to if it works for you to let
breathing be the center of the meditation and riding the inhales and
exhales staying close to them but when there's an and when
there's an emotion that's present the stepping stone is to very uh
clearly kind of from a dry land from a place that you're not
stuck um label note the emotion it could
be with a verbal note Joy sadness
annoyance peace calm whatever it might be and um but see if you can find a way
to note to be aware of the emotion uh from a place where you're on
a stepping stone where you're not being pulled into it you're not participating in it you're not feeding it with stories
and reactions you're not uh being over WellMed by it you're not being pulled
into its orbit and to find a way to say that mental
note and it's also possible to have a nonverbal note so it doesn't have to be necessarily words but it's some clear
recognition of the emotion that's there but in their recognition uh we're kind of uh not
we're on a stepping stone we're seeing the terrain but not in it not stuck in
it not pulled into it and and um and some of you might have really wonderful
relationship with some of your emotions and think why should I do that but uh for the purposes of
deepening the meditation this is invaluable to do so you might want to experiment with it and um and so make that note or make
that recognition oh this is this is anger this is
boredom and uh and uh but see if you can make that note such a way that the
noting itself the recognition itself is free to add to this it might help with
this process uh make that note either at the beginning of the
exhale or the beginning of the inhale whichever is nicest for you experiment a little bit maybe so if you do it at the
beginning of the exhale make the note uh you know so it might be sadness
it's a sadness and then as you exhale kind of relax as you say it it's just
relax around the sadness or relax with it just relax the stickiness or the
Leaning into or the reactivity that might be around sness just relax with the
exhale if you do at the beginning of the inhale maybe it's more of a uh a being
grounded centered on yourself and making room to feel the emotion more fully
while not being stuck in it so using the and over time you'll
learn how is the simple you know one second act of clear recognition brings
with it a little bit of Freedom or a lot of freedom in relationship to emotions and it's not to
dismiss emotions and will see it's actually to have a deep respect for them
and make room for them that we cannot not do if we're stuck in them or involved in them or caught in their
orbit or participating in them so assuming a meditation
posture and gently lowering your gaze or closing
your
eyes checking in with your posture to see if there's any adjustments to be
made it helps you feel more stable
grounded
aligned gently taking some breaths which are a
little deeper than usual Fuller than usual so that at the exhale
you can have a longer exhale and relaxing
the body as you do
so
then letting the breathing return to normal and continue relaxing the body on
the exhale maybe going through the body body systematically
from top of the head and down through the
body
e
feeling your breathing in your torso the movements of the body the sensations of
breathing in your
torso and the part of your torso that moves as you breathe feel the weight of
it so that as you breathe and relaxing you're settling
in settling your body grounding it here so the weight
settles
relaxes
feeling the sensations in your torso as you breathe so that you're beginning to
be aware without being centered in the
control tower in the head the awareness practice is centered
in the
body
and then as you continue you might notice now whatever
mood or Motion state of mind that's present with
no issue around whether it's a pleasant or unpleasant emotion
mood and at the beginning of the
exhale or the beginning of the inhale whatever feels best for
you quietly have a one word recognition or one moment of wordless
recognition experimenting with how that moment of
recognition stands alone by itself meaning it's
not entangled or reactive to whatever mood or
emotion without preference for or
against a moment of recognition that's
free and then if you're with the exhale to relax with that emotion relax around
it if it's at the inhale allow yourself to fully
[Music] feel the
emotion and with every breath see if you can find that stepping
stone that involves recognition
naming that is above the
mud
e
for
for it might be
interesting to think of this exercise of naming or
recognizing your emotional state as a form of Truth
telling just saying the truth about how you
feel but doing so from a place of
Freedom it's okay it's completely okay to have this
emotion here but recognize it from the Stepping
Stones recognize and then relax with it recognize and
allow its space and room room without being
involved staying on the firm Stepping
Stones
e
for
gently pulling yourself out of whatever state that you're in whatever emotional
state and with respect for the state care for how you
are find a way of naming truth
telling this is how it is simple naming it that put you up on
this Solid Ground free of being pulled into
whatever state you
have
and then coming to the end of this meditation perhaps recognizing or
feeling how a simple Act of Truth telling about how you
are can make room for you to be more than whatever
emotion you you are it's a way of making space breathing
room so that how we feel is not interfering
with an open available way for our care and our
kindness to be ready to meet the world
so there's more space for love for friendship for
friendliness and with whatever degree of open kindness that's
here extending your good will out into the
world for the people who are live near you or close to you
to those far away may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may our openness contribute to that
[Music]
possibility thank you
so hello and today
I begin the third week of this introduction to mindfulness meditation with this week focusing on
mindfulness of emotions emotions are an important part of our
life and mindfulness meditation is meant to offer have a lot of respect for our
emotions and as I've often said that I love the word respect as a synonym for
mindfulness because the Latin roots of it could uh be understood as uh to see
again to give a second look to what's happening so to respect emotions is to
give it it really take a look at it second don't just take it at the first impression but take a second look what's
happening here so one of the principles of
practicing mindfulness of emotions and mindfulness meditation
is in fact to have a deep respect for emotions that uh emotions um in and of
themselves are significant movements within
us they um are things which are we are moved by
something and um and we want to allow the
movement without judgment but also
without participating either reactively pushing it away or judging it
negatively uh or participating in it by um leaning into it and telling ourselves
stories that perpetuate it and keep it going and um I'm fond of the idea that
the word emotion has the the word Motion in it and the E the Latin prefix e means
out emotions are things that are moving out they represent that we've been
touched we've been moved in some way and um and in and of itself it
represents our capacity to um to be moved to be involved in a way
that's to this world with ourselves that something deep gets elicited something deep place maybe I like to
think of a place that's tender within has been has been kind of come alive and it's expressing itself and and somehow
we're being moved and um and certainly some emotions
are unpleasant some are Pleasant some are not helpful for us to live by or
participate in and some are very helpful to live by and participate in but no
matter whether it's Pleasant or unpleasant skillful or unskillful uh emotions can be understood
as providing information something is being
expressed and we want to be able to uh hear or see or recognize what is
happening here what's being expressed what is there to learn with this
emotion I sometimes think of all emotions as messages and we want to read the message
we don't want to Kill the Messenger we want to see okay this too is carrying
some message and uh if it's an unpleasant emotion or one that's
maybe um harmful even for to for
ourselves or for others it's still carrying a message maybe from someplace deeper than what it is itself and so to
respect it and make room for it um so we can really hear deeply what's really
happening here with us that kind of Truth telling or truth finding in this
process and uh so I like to say that uh mindfulness meditation is meant to be
one of the safest places to feel your emotions or or to say it differently
it's one of the places where um it's meant to be where we can allow whatever
emotion we have and allow it to be there so we can feel it see it know it uh and find our
freedom with it now that's a tall order sometimes emotions can be quite
difficult and and um they can be overwhelming at times so it's a process
of learning it's a process of building the skill and the capacity to have this
kind of mindful attention openness to whatever emotion we have it's not something that necessarily can be done
overnight or immediately but that's kind of like the North Star for this practice is to build this capacity to be present
in a non-reactive non um entangled way to any emotion that we
have and so I like to think of it that it's this you know it's one of the few places in our society where it's uh
there's no need to be ashamed of our emotions no need to repress them no need
to um condemn them um and there's no need to participate in
them lean into them collapse into them and um and uh you know so if
there's murderous rage um you know we're committed for duration of meditation to
not move more or less and um and just allow it to course through us without
punching someone out we just like sitting their feeling allowing it to be there and uh if we have great beatific
kind of feelings of Love um you know it might be problematic sometimes in daily
life if we have that in the wrong occasion but um uh what we can learn
that as we learn how to be how to experience whatever emotion it is what
we're learning is how to know it how to recognize it from a place of stability
or calm to be able to recognize it where the recognition of it is
free and one of the freedoms is to be free enough just free
enough um to um to be able to listen
more deeply to the emotion to not be so involved in it so reactive to it so
overwhelmed by it that we have the capacity to see it to know it to listen
deeply what is this and that's where the earlier parts of this uh inned
meditation is very important because um the all emotions are
expressed one way or the other in the body and if there were no Body
Sensations at all it might be hard to really discern that you're even having an
emotion so be able to feel the little movements of of or big movements in the
body the contractions the tightness the agitation the energy the the suffusion
of warmth or goodness that comes with some positive
emotions um that's to feel it physically or to feel how the breathing has come
into play some emotions when they come up strong affects the breathing and makes the breathing tight or shallow or
fast and um or sometimes it's a some some emotions help the breathing relax
and settle and become slow and and bigger and um so to be able to recogn
recognize the bodily expression of the emotion what's happening in the body the what's happening with the breathing is a
support to stay in the present moment with the
emotion what we're doing in mindfulness meditation is seeing any
emotion as a present moment event almost as if for the purpose of the
meditation it has no before and has has no after we don't have to connect it to the
story of why it's there and we don't have to connect it to the the
predictions of what it means that it's there what's going to happen to us we're learning to just hold it be present for
it respectfully for what it is as an event here and
now and that means uh without a lot of thinking about about it without a lot of
analysis or story making or and we're learning without a lot of Association to
self one of the interesting things about emotions is when there's a lot of identification with the emotion I am the
emotion the emotion defines me you know I'm this kind of person who's always has
this kind of emotion and that's an added layer on top
that over time we learn this meditation we don't need to do we can keep it very
very simple even if it's very strong emotion I've sat with meditation with
anger that felt like a volcano and um but uh I didn't identify
with it I didn't make myself the angry person I just made room in my body I
kept coming back to my body and feel it feel it so in this first day of uh
of uh teaching about mindfulness of emotion I want to keep it somewhat simple and I want to suggest uh the
practice of um um the um one one second
or 3 second mindfulness and uh this is something you can do through the day it's a art form
so or craft that you can learn and cultivate until it becomes stronger for
you and that is the the the
the the practice of simple recognition of what emotion is happening
in the moment and it isn't that the recognizing it's not that the recognition of the
emotion is what's important it's that how we recognize it so that we recognize
it with um uh without being entangled we recognize it without being caught or
reactive to it we recognize it without defining ourselves by it or telling us a
story about this means I am some way or other um it's uh stepping out of the you
know the swampy mud of the field that we were crossing up on the Stepping Stones
where there's um you we're still able to cross the field we're still intimately part of this beautiful maybe natural
landscape or where the field is in we're not removing ourselves from the world or
becoming dis dis engaged but we're just stepping
up on these wonderful Stepping Stones where we can walk across the field without getting stuck in the mud and the
stepping stone is the simple Act of recognition
recognizing sadness grief just as that oh this is
grief and not to feel like you have to not grieve or that supposed to be you
know any different or that you're changing it for the next second after
that just for that second oh it's like the sun has come out oh this is
grief this is Joy this is love this is
hatred this is boredom this is calm this is
agitation this is fear this is
um confidence so whatever state mood mental state emotion that we have to
experiment with just naming it taking the moment to almost like you're pausing
for one second 3 seconds oh this is how it
is yes this is how it is and but just clearly enough fully
enough definitive enough that you're almost like stepping
out of the the current of being swept away or involved
with whatever emotion it is but not to stop it but to see it clearly to have a
moment of truth telling oh this is how it is and um and then to repeat myself the
recognizing what it is has tremendous value but in this exercise that what's
more important is how you recognize it and that's where the experimentation is
that's where the training is in this meditation is to is to um see what you
can do to recognize it so you feel like oh for that moment you're free to that
moment you're not identified with it that moment you're not entangled or reactive to it is just very
simple stepping away step stepping back and seeing it for what it is without being
entangled so you might uh do this if you you know through the day
today and I don't know how you know you could set a timer on your device that you know every 15 minutes or so there's
a little reminder check in how you are and see what it's like to just that moment to name it maybe you want to do
that a few times uh over a minute or so just to
experiment you know maybe you can do it five six times over a minute and just experiment what is it Gil talking about
about this recognition that's free recognition that's not entangled or caught and see
uh what you learn from this see what you find from this and if you want a little
if it this this becomes kind of easy or not you know you want a little bit more then um uh do that act of recognition
either at the beginning of the exhale or the beginning of the inhale and just
relax with the emotion on the exhale or if it's the beginning of the inhale allow for it after you've made after
you've made the recognition then almost like you make room to allow forther on the
inhale or once you've recognized it in this nice way at the beginning of the
exhale then just relax with it and see what happens to you and so this is just the beginning
and we'll continue now next 4 days with um developing this important area of
mindfulness of emotions thank
you