so uh here we are um we're at the uh
fourth um kind of I know Force step and
force uh movement of um this week's a Siri and uh today uh we're going to move
through uh the grounding uh enlightening
enriching and then uh today we'll be adding a component which is
um expanding and so I will be using the
metaphor of um the Inner Mountain and to expand a bit more and so that's uh what
we will be doing together so we'll start with the sound of a bell
[Music]
arriving here and
now taking a few long deep breaths as you breathe out
settling down maybe resting down towards
Earth mindfulness front and center and maybe all the way around
and heartfulness may be here
too and the body
fullness sensing this body sitting
releasing the weight of the body towards
Earth allow this earthy body resting on Earth
sensing ground
underneath
studying grounding
releasing
preoccupations
plans let yourself be grounded
sitting like a
mountain and a life Mountain Within
quiet
still and steady
the movements of the breath May naturally come
Force like a breeze in the mountain
sensing
aliveness the breath flows throughout the body
en liening the Inner
Mountain you feel the sensations on the
feet relax
hands
shivering swaying janto s
receiving the felt sense of a life
breath coursing through the whole body for
the waves of emotions may come in
thoughts a rich part of a Being Human
just simply open to receive the felt
sense of emotions and texture of the thoughts
like the weather systems in the mountain
expanding the field of awareness around the edges of the
body and open to include the space all around
just like the mountain surrounded imbued by the
spaciousness all
around and you expand to include the
spaciousness that's right here e
a spaciousness that can [Music] hold Sensations in the body
movements in the
mind nothing is excluded
there is a room for
everything
e
e e
resting in a spacious field of knowing
a spaciousness can hold
conflict
disagreement and we may say it's a kind
space
e
for
[Music] for
[Music]
for
e
e for
sensing and feeling the movements of the
breath when returning to the grounded
Place through the body maybe the sense of earthy body
resting on Earth
all
I
e e
[Music]
e
thank you everyone I feel like I'm navigating this
a YouTube World a little bit cuz the video for me is a bit Frozen but um I
feel a little relief to see some chat messages from you all uh hopefully it all has been going
okay um so I'm going to switch gear and
um offer the third simile uh in this um
Sut that I've been sharing this past week Sam nikaya
22101 and um uh this um last a cup of uh
similes the chicken and eggs and uh uh the ass handle kind of offered
some different aspects of a highway practice and this last last
simile uh is that of uh the rope that ties the ship kind
of you know docking the ship or something so it's got yet another
different flavor so let me read this assimile to you
first Suppose there was a sea fairing ship
bound together with ropes for 6 months they
deteriorated in the water then in the cold season it was a hauled up on dry
land where the ropes were weathered by wind and the
sun when the clouds soaked it with rain the ropes would readily collapse
and a rod away in the same way when a practitioner
is committed to development their feathers or you can
say defilements their tins readily
collapse and rot away I this is very Vivid simile you
know this ropes tying the ship and the ropes soaked in the water for a
long time and then in the cold season when the ship is not
going uh they're hauled up in dry land and the ropes are under the weather in
the sun in the wind and then the cloud soaked with rain
I guess rain clouds soaked the ropes more
and then eventually the ropes readily collapse
and Rod away in the same way
that uh the practitioners when we develop and the tins Fade Away In This
Way um for me it has a very different flavor
um that this simile captured when we compare it to the
previous uh two similes
um you know with the assimile of the egg eggs and the chicken and it's
highlighting that's one way to understand it that it's highlighting that one would uh needed to practice a
sincerity and properly um um and when the hearts and
minds are cultivated that way the chicks would
hatch and the second simile uh the simile as handle you know
the cing T are holding the the handle for a long time and highlights that uh the release
of the strong deep Tendencies of grasping um
is not to be measured you know evaluated but we stay
cultivating now with this simile
uh first uh you know just to feel that sense of the ropes being soaked in in
this weather different Weathers in different times of the day and the sense
I have is that the long Arc of our practice
Journey we will surely go through all kinds of seasons and meet all kinds of human
conditions the gains the loss uh the gains of the different kinds
material immaterial and the loss of all kinds loss of loved ones loss of
physical mental capacities unfortunate Unfortunate
Events um uh experiencing uh uh things that are
individually to us and the collectively and so it's like this
different weather systems uh different phases of Our
Lives um whether we prefer or not
but the practice continues no matter what the conditions and situations we're in kind of like the
the ropes you know keeps on so getting soaked in in all the different
conditions and our willingness and the dedication to stay in the practice field
in the practice stream no matter what situ situation we're in is how our
practice matures and this is certainly not easy
to do um and not just not just easy but at
times it can feel really really
difficult and through the practice um we learn to gradually little
by little um whether it's in the difficult situations or in kind of um comfortable
situations we learn to choose whether to become
reactive which leads more stress and Dua or we choose something that is a kind of
release of reactivity and not add more to
and for me a lot of our reactivities feels more like tying nods
on of the Rope you know rather than releasing the Rope let the ropes loosen
up and soften let the thread be softened kind of released and not tied up but the
reactivity gets us knotted up
and so this particular Sali reminded me of a teaching that a sum sometimes would
say that uh in our practice we choose to stand under
dukka we choose to stand under dukka we're not running away from
different situations and conditions uh in our lives
um but rather we choose to stand under duka we learn from it we need it we
explore them we understand it and then over time we learn how to
empower ourselves to choose not add more
stress and since we've uh done all three similies uh in uh this
sequence I wanted to just summarize a little bit the overarching flavor of
this uh three similes I was struck by the fact
that uh all of this similes together if
you feel into it there is no sense of a kind of brute force of pushing our way
through in the cultivation process right you know first we don't
Tinker with the eggs to kind of somehow uh break the shells
prematurely nor do we try to do something crazy about uh the ass
Handle by force and we just kind of keep holding it and keep working with it and
there is a kind of a timelessness uh in the practice
and in this assimile nowhere in the sutta it would say oh let's kind of I
don't know cut to the Rope up doesn't work like that but rather we let ourselves meet
the situations of life as they are and the
Rope kind of rots on its own naturally
and so in this way I can say maybe we can say that we
are being practiced uh by the forces of Our Lives
by including all parts of one's life in the practice
field and gradually freedom is born our
freedom naturally come forth and so you know the Notions like
shortcuts efficiency speed and those are not the
orientation of the the Dharma practice and so this kind of a patiently
showing up but be really curious to learn in all the
situations and there is a kind of um compassionate and kind attitude to to
build in in here and you may be able to feel this right right
there and I wanted to uh read um in Gil's new book uh everything
is practice even though it's speaking about um Retreat practice but I would
say it can be extended to practicing uh in our life in
general in the forward of this book uh iness one
of our IRC teachers IMC teachers said this uh in this book and
she said Gil points to um mature practice that includes every aspect of
ourselves with nothing left out fostering a deep sense of
self-acceptance and understanding a practice that both
provides for the Solitude of deep meditation and the connection of a
practice in community with others he emphasizes a practice that
points to Freedom possible in every aspect of Our
Lives including in our wider
world so may that be an aspiration to all of
us so thank you everyone have a wonderful rest of the
day um may you all be
well for [Music]