so good evening everyone this is maybe a little bit Loud Let's see if uh so how's
that let's see now this okay okay so
um maybe we can start a little bit slowly and it is because of the weather maybe some people still coming and one
way to start a little slowly is see if you have any questions if those of you are here for the first two weeks do
anything that came up for you in your meditation practice or if you tried it at home or questions from the
instructions last week or
anything yes yeah if you speak loudly for my sake
be here it comes okay um I was wondering about we talked
about like your body and Sensations in your body and going towards things that
are uncomfortable in your body and what I wanted to know was I found myself
um sort of bargaining with myself like well if I pay attention to it long
enough and go deep into it it's you know it'll will dissolve and won't make me feel so miserable anymore and then when
that doesn't happen I'm I find myself you not knowing what to
do yeah so so the wiser so sometimes that can happen we go into it and it
changes and something relaxes but to spend too much time wanting that is a distraction from the mindfulness
practice right because what we want to dissolve is not the pain but our reactivity to the pain right and it's
just so hard to separate that yeah so so today we'll talk about that cool and be able to separate that because that has a
lot to do with the emotional relationship we have to things and uh and so what we do is that uh we
certainly learn to stay we learn how to be present present in a kind of calm way
with pain and discomfort if that's what happens and that's a life skill that's really good for all kinds of situations
you find yourself in in the world where that it's unbearably seemingly unbearably uncomfortable but now you
know how to be with it rather than freaking out or something and um but at
some point as we learn to stabilize our attention enough on some difficult thing
like difficult pain at some then what we do is to turn the attention around 180° and see how am I relating to this
and then you might discover I'm afraid or I'm angry I'm aversive I'm you know I
hate it or I really want to have I thought meditation was about being on
cloud n and just kind of like better than going to Cabo and and you I want
the pleasure and uh so you get to see what your operating operating principles
that's behind the re reactivity and then you can start questioning it or or if
you want to do mindfulness it's very interesting then to bring mindfulness to that reactivity which means that you you
see it clearly without buying into it and just look at it like you your
head a little bit I see you you know my my old friend and and sometimes we get
to see the patterns that we have you say oh I I've been doing this for a while it seemed like my go-to is is um you know I
get bored and that's the way I shut down or how I a little bit aversive or my go-to is to be aversive and blame
someone and uh anyone but me or something so so so and and that begins
so then we it's easier to develop find a calm place if we really have seen the
reactivity directly and clearly because then we don't necessarily have to unconsciously go along with it which is
what many people do is that yeah thank
you there was a if I if you maybe you need to forgive me there was a joke many
years ago of an executive who um um had
this problem when he got nervous in front of big speeches that he peed in his pants so this was not really a good
thing so um the company paid for him to go really really you know highend very
expensive therapist he did that for a while and said all he came back and say I'm good now and
um um oh don't tell us you no longer pee in your pants and he said no now I don't
care so his reactivity went
away so that's not exactly what meditation is
for so anybody else yes I think i' I've had to this if you can wait for this mic
please so I think what I'm what I'm having uh challenge reconciling
is um there's an innate there seems to be kind of this
conflict between Detachment and like desire for example
like I in my day-to-day life I do desire to be the best at what I do yes
and look to achieve aeve um and there seems to be kind of a
conflict between that sense of Detachment yeah and that pursuit
of I don't say perfection because that doesn't exist but um Perfection or
pursuit of improvement yeah um so I'm having a tough time reconciling yeah
those two great well well the fact that you can ask this question is really good the fact that you're seeing there's a
distinction that you have trouble finding in in in practice is really a good thing so you're on the right
track and with M with with one of the benefits of mindfulness is not solving
our problems but seeing them more clearly so we can tease apart the different elements of it and so that
we're not caught up in uh in uh so as we see see the different parts of it then
we can start choosing the parts that are healthy and put aside the ones that are not healthy so being good at what you're
doing in my my book you know that's a good thing to do but there can be a lot
of extra with it it could be there's a lot of needing to prove yourself to someone and get approval from someone or
status but other people's eyes and those kind of things on top that that's more
complicated and that some of that not might not be so healthy and necessary um uh it might be that you
want to do your best you can with what you do but you measure it by the uh by
your success and who you are as a person by the results and since the ancient times a
lot of spiritual Traditions emphasized uh don't be so concerned about the results just give yourself
wholeheartedly to what you're doing so so there's there's all these distinctions that can be made and when
you're when you're calm and settled and not caught up in the reactivity and the desires then you can step back and start
seeing that different people pieces of it and start sorting out that which is useful and not not useful does that make
some sense for you enough sense that you have your work to
do thank you it's a good question so one any more one
more so any more questions because if you don't ask questions that means we're going to miss
meditate which it hopefully isn't that bad so we do
it okay so um so the way this meditation is going
to unfold is we'll start with the breathing which we did the first week
and then we'll expand out to include the rest of the body and then we're going to in this
field this I we call it a field sometimes this this in this container
the body is will then start including the emotions that we have and um and you
you what you normally what you in your in your vocabulary what you might call an emotion um might not be occurring so
you know but it's a mood a mind State um certainly emotion some generalized
feeling that you would some someone says how you're feeling and you say oh I feel tired or I feel calm some positive
States like calm people don't think of it as an emotion some people do but a mind State the General State the way the
state of being the how you are is kind of the territory we're going to go to and it's going to be very simple very
very simple and and it's it's okay if what you have is very very subtle um it's okay if it's powerful and
for this purpose just this just we're going to kind of touch into it kind of uh just gently
and not do a lot with it but get a sense of what it's like to do that um on the foundation of settling on the breathing
opening up to the body and then the context of having those two as a foundation then becoming aware of
emotions as opposed to for many people they have might have strong emotions but they're just focusing on that entirely
by itself and it has no support there's no no container to hold it or be with it
which this uh practice can provide so hopefully that makes sense
enough so to U assume a meditation posture that gives you a balance between
being calm and relaxed and alert with your
body so if you're tense coming here maybe you want to emphasize kind of just
settling back in the chair and relaxing if you're sleepy and tired at
the end of the day you might want to sit up a little straighter than usual so there's a little more alertness in your
spine maybe in your
chest and then gently closing your
eyes and noticing your
breathing just take we'll do a three breath journey to begin with that we
talked about the first class just three
breaths and
now take some long deep breaths to really connect more fully with your
body and as you exhale relax your
body maybe 3/4 full doesn't have to be as full as
possible and it might feel if it feels nice
extend the exhale so that the relaxing can be a
little
more breathing in deeply and maybe beginning the relaxation in the
shoulders but then let it relax wave of relaxation go down from the shoulders all the way
down to your belly to your sitting
bones
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continue for a few breaths on
the exhale softening in your
body gentling yourself as you
exhale
also your might see if the your thinking the thinking mind if
there's any tension or agitation associated with it if it's easy enough as you
exhale Relax The Thinking
mind
for and then a c few more
breaths on the exhale let the you relax from the place
in your body where the top of the inhale is in the chest up near the shoulders
maybe or and as you exhale relax downward a wave of relaxing down
into the stomach letting the belly become
soft maybe the belly hangs forward a little
bit on the exhale at the end relaxing the belly so the weight of
your torso settles towards your pelvic
area
then becoming aware of the breathing in and the breathing
out the rhythm of inhaling and
exhale as it experience by the
body maybe letting go of your thoughts as you
exhale and letting go into the exhale itself the physical experience of
exhaling
feeling the rhythm of breathing in and out in your
torso the rib cage the
chest the belly noticing how that area some parts
of that area expand as you breathe in
contract as you
exhale and imagine your breathing is in the middle of your body kind
of and as you inhale let your
awareness expand outward throughout your
body maybe it grows on the
inhale Global Experience of the body
and on the exhale return to maybe some Center within the
end of the
exhale
almost as if your breathing is giving your body a massage where the influence of breathing
spreads throughout the
body
and now as this rhythm of breathing
continues as your awareness spreads through your body and become aware of how you're
feeling what your emotional state
mood inner state of
being you don't have to know exactly what it
is but let it be leave it alone let yourself be as you
are and allow it to be in your body as you breathe with it breathe
through it almost as if your state your mood how
you're feeling is also being
massaged by the expanding and Contracting of breathing in and
out
as if your breathing and your body is making lots of room for how you
feel allowing yourself to feel the way you are without any judgment or
reaction and without any getting involved with it just allowing it to be
there with the breathing breathing through it breathing with
it
and then to end this meditation
you can take a few long slow deep
breaths healing your body more fully feeling the contact with your
chair or the floor your cushion and
then when you're ready you can open your [Music]
eyes
so our emotions are important part of our life and there are few places in life
outside of meditation or maybe being alone somewhere that we give complete
permission for us to feel whatever emotions we're having you might have murderous
Rage which we hope you don't act on in the world but it's okay to sit and in
meditation and feel it you might have the most beatific Angelic
wonderful feelings of love and peace peace and you know it's just
like you're allowed to feel that some people are have a lot of
trouble feeling happiness and one of the things I in my role as meditation teachers is it's
surprised me the first time I got to do this was told someone they had permission to feel Joy when they
meditated because some some religions it's not really quite okay and
um so this is a very unique place we're not trying to repress any emotions we're
not trying to deny any emotions but we're also not celebrating them we're
also not expressing them we're neither for them or against
them while we're meditating so that's a radical thing to do because in ordinary life we're for
and against our emotions we have good ones and bad ones some which we're ashamed for having some that we we feel
like unacceptable some which we think we're supposed to be having but we're not having them and some we have and we
think that we're This Is We I have it made I'll never be depressed again and that lasts for 10 minutes you know and
so we have this complicated relationship with emotions some of us and uh we have expectations of how we
should be feeling and so some of this comes from our society some of it comes from our family some of it comes from
our life experiences and uh some of them are very painful I've had I've expressed some of
my emotions to friends when I was a teenager and the way that I they responded to me were such that I felt
something in my heart closed just boom okay I'm not going to show that ever
again and it took a few years of meditation to come to a place where that
part that was closed would start opening up again and I the whole capacity to feel certain
emotions came back over time so our emotions are in integral part of what a
human being is and to have a safe place where you can go and really take time to
feel and be as you actually are without any of the extra judgments and ideas
that we might have received from growing up from our society or anywhere is a gift to ourselves and meditation is
meant to be one of those places some people think that Buddhists uh repress their emotions because they're just too
equanimous you know you're supposed to just kind of like be calm all the time well there is something to that that
their Buddhists tend to be Cal and equanimous but many people find when you do this meditation the range of
emotions and their familiarity and the way they learn and and uh tap into the
wisdom of emotions is uh become so much greater what happens is that the r the
this pendulum doesn't swing as far because if we're if we just like hang on
or ready to celebrate and think this is the I'm the best thing since apple pie
because I have a little bit of Joy the excitement kind of will St will go into
like too far if we have some fear some people are afraid or their fear and then they get
more afraid and that produces even more fear and so they're reacting to it and it the
the fear pendulum goes really far the anger Pendulum The Shame pendulum goes
really far and so some of the great range that some people have is not
actually so healthy for them so as we do this practice I would
say our capacity to have emotions grows but we don't swing so far with
them so it looks like maybe we're calmer with it all but it's richer and more you
know it can be richer and emotions are actually very important part of Buddhist practice and and the growing as a kind
of as a this path of Buddhism is is to have an emotionally rich
life but what happens with practice as it with mindfulness is that mindfulness
tends to dissipate the reactive emotions it dissipates the unnecessary
swings it dissipates the emotions that uh are somehow or other connect Ed to
attachment to clinging the emotions that are have no
attachment part of them those are not part of reactivity those grow and the ones that are not attached
uh connected to attachment and clinging are things like love happiness compassion generosity
calm peace all these wonderful things and so there's a kind of there's
a sh as we we make room to feel and give permission for us to feel as we actually
are no matter what it is we start having the better and better understanding of
what's happening and we begin to shift what we are
feeding and we're no longer feeding supporting
participating in the kind of emotional reactions which are actually harmful for
us and we learn how to feed in a nice way those which are
beneficial this is not just but but to make that distinction between harmful and beneficial
emotions is not meant to push the harmful ones away when you meditate or
feel shame or you know or think that if you're a good Buddhist you're not supposed to ever be angry
again medit the mindfulness meditation is the safe place to be who you you are
what's happening and it might seem strange to say this that this as a place but it's a
radical to have disability and one of the benefits as I'm kind of repeating myself is it gives us a chance to see it
much more clearly and as we see it more clearly wisdom is born as we see it more
clearly we understand better how to relate to it how to be with it we can find the wisdom we can find the way
forward in a much better way than if we just kind of live in in it
all so uh so this meditation we did just now
starting with breathing feeling the body and then opening to the emotions in some
way or other how was that for some of you was that do you find that interesting or different than to a way
to be with it and anybody willing to say a few
words
there then got
it um when I was trying to kind of just wait wait a moment while the the volume
goes up okay is that better um when I was kind of opening
to emotionally what was happening I found to kind of get a sense of that I was
going to physical sensation I was going to thought to kind of assemble
emotion and yeah so I guess kind of sharing that
experience and curious like if that's um a helpful way to kind of approach
getting in touch with emotion and was it helpful for you to do it that way I think maybe I got caught up in
the like the second layer of trying to figure out if that was a good approach or not okay yeah so that's the second
layer so you were thinking yeah yeah that's next week yeah you're a little bit of a prodigy
you're ahead of us and uh and so one of what the what
what I'm going to try to convey today is to to be aware of emotions um if without
thinking much about them be before the thinking the analyzing the predictions the stories that are connected to them
so that's uh so to keep it really simple and some people find it to be such a
relief to be with their emotions without having to evaluate them believe them solve them
figure them out um and so just keep it really
simple anybody else up
here um it may be pretty much the same thing she was saying but I guess I don't
know how to separate thinking from feeling like I'm trying to feel but
I'm yeah I'm trying to evalue trying to find where the feeling is yes yes uh
yeah this is hard but that but it's it's uh we'll do that next week the the thinking sorry but uh some people um uh
I I am therefore I think therefore I am it's almost like who we are as our thoughts and for some people thinking
and emotions are inseparable they can't really tease them apart they come together there's a very strong
connection to thinking and certain certain kinds of emotions and so that'll
become clear as as this continues to deepen this this what I'm you know what we're doing here so I think just I think
just the fact that you see that is great that's that that's kind of the beginning
to understand what's
happening um I I kind of noticed in myself that maybe the the pattern goes the other way um rather than the
thinking causing the emotion like the emotion causes the thinking yes um and
for me it's this kind of low seems to be this low low underlying current of fear
or anxiety or something that drives a lot of the have I thought about this did I do that thing I got to plan this and
so I just I notice a lot of the thoughts great seem to come from this underlying thing
feeling and sometimes I'm able to identify that feeling and kind of
meditate with it um put my attention on it and hold it as a feeling rather than as a thought and then other times I'm
thinking about stuff sure sure um but in terms of feelings that seems to be the
one that comes up for me most of the time when I'm sitting so that's considered a very important uh
understanding to get to and some people when they meditate regularly start Dawning upon wow the fear is pervasive I
had no idea but you need to be quiet enough and still enough so you're not distracted from yourself most people
live distracted from themselves and so for I don't know if this represents you
accurately but if if fear triggers a lot of thoughts the thought train can be really
long and you're so involved in the thoughts and theide ideas that we've lost touch with the
fear and uh so we're distracted from what's really happening so um uh there's
one one way of understanding the connection between thoughts and emotions sometimes emotions are first Sometimes
thoughts are first but one interesting way of understanding it is that uh
thoughts are just a messenger don't spend a lot of time with the messenger get the message the
message is the emotions the emotions are the factory for a lot of thinking and so
we have to we want to learn how to be in a useful way mindful of the
emotions before or instead of spinning out in the stories of it all and so
that's what we'll talk a little bit more about now so maybe one more here is that that was that clear enough to end
response okay so I think I'm actually a week behind so because I I don't can't
remember if it's if it's a sympathetic or parasympathetic reaction but I found just in meditating I came in with the
tightness in my back and just being able to
meditate I don't know if I Let Go something or if it just I feel a help a
lot better fantastic and so so feeling hell of a lot better that's a feeling so
how did that feel not in your mind but how did it feel in your body not just in the place where you relaxed did it's a
strong statement to say hell of a lot better how how actually did that feel in your body do you feel lighter or glowing
or kind of happy or well like I let go of something I just
and the tightness that was there was released it was just but was any did
that released that you you seem to appreciate it that appreciation did it boil you up a little bit or inspire you
or did you feel kind of uh well I I felt I mean I just I feel just I don't yeah
maybe lighter maybe just um I feel better feel better fantastic so you feel
better you feel lighter so one of the things we do in mindfulness practice is we allow ourselves to feel those feeling
betters some people can feel better but we have all these things to worry about
important things to think about so so like okay you know I don't have time to feel
that let's you know let's go off and worry about the next thing and then it back tightens up again so one of the
things we do with mindfulness we stop and really stay present for things so when something is healthy like that take
time to let that register how how you feel good from it and what shift it might be very subtle but it's good to
take it's good to let it register deeply and that's one of the things we're doing in mindfulness is taking the time to
really let it register how we are what's happening even when it what what we're feeling is doesn't feel good because
there's something about the deeper connection to it that allows something to shift one of the interesting things
about the English word emotion is it has the word Motion in it
and the E the prefix e in Latin means out it turns out that all emotions are
in movement they're processes that are moving along and they mostly want to
work themselves out or spread out um but we tend to block it we tend to lock them
up we tend to lock onto them or push them or or get tight around them or get
afraid of them or something and sometimes these emotions get kind of stuck in us for a long time but uh part
of what mindfulness does kind of we it begins to unstuck us we're making room for it so that it can start
moving and it's fascinating to watch how emotions start to move and change and shift that's what they want to do if we
can give them space to do it so in that meditation we did I was trying to give you a little feeling for what it's like
to have your emotions with more space for them in your body and more kind of
not not being caught in them because you are breathing with them if you give your
uh uh awareness over to the breathing and breathe with it there's less uh mind
space available to be thinking about it or reacting to it and and so you know
that if the think of awareness as
space and if that space is filled with thoughts very little awareness is
available to really feel and be present for other things one of the reasons that
quiet the mind is so you can be more
aware of what's happening to you without drowning out or dominating all the space
filling all the space with everything so as the think thinking mind quiets down
or as our priorities shift in the mind we become more interested in staying with the
breathing then awareness no longer is caught up in the mind and then we can
start feeling other things more fully I hope this makes some sense to you does
it okay so emotions and
um so one of the reasons why we do this in the third week is that is that um uh
if we just started the first week feel your emotions we'd probably all be mess right away because we don't have the capacity
we haven't studied learned how to be with them in a wise way but uh the breathing is caling it's very
it's a very well-known technique that people who are stressed uh can relax if they just breathe and just hang out with
the breathing tune into the breathing and part of the reason for that if all the mental
space is filled by thinking and the thinking is stressful that's going to stress out the body but if we no longer
if the mental space is not only filled with thoughts but now we're starting starting to fill it with breathing and
the body then um there's less of the energy going to the stressful thoughts
and the stressful thoughts have you know tentacles that reach into our muscles that you know get us all tight so we're
kind of Shifting um and so to start breathing
and especially with difficult emotions to breathe through them breathe with them is a way of not being caught in
them it's a way of doing something different with the mind with the Mind
space with the Mind awareness doing something different that doesn't feed them doesn't react to them but at the
same time doesn't ignore them you know some people if they're really stressed out around their
emotions will distract themselves eat watch TV do all kinds of
things we don't want to distract ourselves but we want to create a different way of being with them so
we're not caught in their grip and so the breathing is one of the ways to
breathe with it to breathe through it shifts a little bit makes makes things a little more
relaxed if in addition to that we are stabilized in the body we feel like oh
I'm really here in my body there's a lot of people in our culture who are not in their bodies and uh they spend much of
the day from the neck up and uh kind of spinning their thoughts thinking about
things and again what I'm if the Mind space is filled with Just
Thoughts there's very little room to really feel the body the body is a delicate
instrument I'm pretty confident that this body of ours is much more
sensitive and has a lot more uh fascinating instruments in it than your
smartphone it's an amazing thing and it works so so much better if you're
present for it if you're not present for it because you're on your smartphone all
the time you're really short changing yourself dramatically for the
intelligence the information the sensitivity the possibilities that are here in this body and so to slow down
and be mindful and be start being aware of your body then you start creating space and room to feel your emotions
that's uh be with them with something different than just being them with your
thoughts and If all we're doing to be with emotions was our thinking thinking about them telling stories over and over
again and trying to you know um it's very limited human thing to do if we
want to expand out to the much more the greater capacities we have as human beings the range of intelligence we have
that operate within us uh you have to uh bring online
all these apps that you have that have been turned off we're full of apps you know and uh
and uh they're really good but they have to be turned on and um and so and so if
the Mind space is filled with thoughts you can't really feel what's going on here but as you start feeling your body
getting more embodied more embodied then it's a lot easier to feel emotions like
the stability the steadiness of the body the the the strength that the body
provides makes it easier to feel what's going on maybe not automatically not
quickly but that's the direction the practice goes and then um what we're trying to do
here in mindfulness is to learn a very simple but simple doesn't mean easy very
simple capacity to know we're having an emotion when we're having
it as opposed to to no we're having it and be upset no we're having it and be
afraid no we're having it and you know that jerk deserves everything he can
everything I'm going to you know do to him you know we we're involved we're kind of caught in it as opposed to
oh there's an I'm angry let me feel the anger no no no you
have to kind of tell the person in piece of your mind he deserves it wait a minute slow down take a deep
breath relax just feel what's happening oh anger my stomach is in a
knot my jaw is tight but but I have to kind
of he deserves to be no no later that
can be for later now just be here feel it be with
it and then something begins relaxing you're breathing with it
the tension in the belly begins to soften as you breathe with it you notice when you start going into those thoughts
but he deserves it that the belly gets all tight again and then you
relax and then you start seeing that when every time you go to your head your thoughts some other kinds of tension
begins when you come back and then slowly the anger maybe dissipates and
you find out after a while that low and behold underneath the anger you're
afraid the Genesis the source of the Fe of the anger is how afraid you are
threatened you feel and now you're in a different world now you can kind of maybe feel
that maybe that's what really needs your attention and so what we're trying to do
in mindfulness is um we're not actually
trying to figure out how to be as we
are as if we can accept ourselves as we are we're trying to be with
ourselves and the difference between being being as you are versus be with
yourself is a difference between um uh
it is like if if you're really having a hard time in your life and you're upset maybe you're angry you're afraid you're
whatever grieving who knows what's happening to you and you know this person a friend
who whenever you're with them they like to go for a walk with you and accompany you and they'll sit in their park bench
with you and just they're not going to fix you they're not going to judge you they're just going to be with you and
listen and it's so good to be with that person who has that ability a lot of friends don't have that ability this
person just seems to care listens
well but you feel you know like this person's not judging me it's not
condemning me it's not this person's not participating I need to I need to
express how angry I'm at that guy but the I go to some friends and
they kind of like get angry too and they get more Angry than I do that I am
that's not so useful but there's one person just sits the person's with me and I feel like I'm being held I feel
like I'm cared for I feel like there's this calm presence and something inside of me begins to relax because the person
is with me not for me not participating but also not judging so this is a basic
good you know good friendship kind of skills to have so we're doing that for
ourselves we're trying to be with how we are as opposed to
being so try be with the anger not be the anger to be with the fear but not be
the fear and that's a huge step to make it's a very respectful thing to do
it's much more respectful for your emotions to be with them than to be
them and some of the more difficult emotions we have
uh some of the reasons people feel shame is because they think they are the
emotion I have so much anger I feel so ashamed of myself I shouldn't do that I'm not supposed to be
angry we're defining ourselves by the anger but if we're not the anger there's
anger but now we're going to be with the anger as opposed to be the angry
person does it make some sense and so mindfulness is this capacity just
to see and be present with what's happening without being pulled into it
without being caught by it just allowing it to be there and seeing it more clearly breathing with it feeling it in
the body so um uh so to to be with your
emotions not don't be your emotions and I keep repeating this so that you can
try to experience expent on your own to see what is it what's the difference when you're in your emotions versus when
you're with them and if you're with them how can you be with them as a good
friend the one who listens the one who really makes space who doesn't judge
doesn't have to fix right away um and just feel what's going
on so uh there is a uh
an acronym that we use here at IMC sometimes that uh hopefully isn't too
much teaching but it's it's a forw acronym that has four different elements
of how we are mindful of emotions and the acronym is raft R A ft
and one of the teachers here who is really specialized in developing this raft simil to is Tanya Wiser who teach
th teaches usually on Thursday nights she loves the fim and is the the
metaphor the acrm and is really she teaches a lot of the raft and
um so um for me she has a little different way of doing it than I do so raft so the
first step is recognize when you have an emotion take
the time to recognize what it is and it might be
obvious or it might not be but there some there something happens with our
emotional life if it's clearly recognized it's kind of like when some
when something is named something can relax I've been upset you know and angry
and didn't know it and my some friend has come up to me and say Gil you seem to be angry and oh yeah I didn't know or
Gil you seem to be stressed oh yeah oh yes I think I am now that you tell me someone names it for me there's
something powerful that happens when we recogn oh just recognize oh that's
what's happening it's part of this it's part of the beginning of stepping far enough
away from the emotion so that when we can come back and be with it if we're in
it we're not with it and so oh I'm
sad maybe you need to say it a few times to yourself oh this is
sadness and you feel yourself collapsing into it or collapsing into no sit up
this is sadness and then um and then uh so that just recognize it
and if you don't know what it is uh start by just recognizing it as some as something a feeling I have a
feeling I remember once the I had a feeling that was the best I could do was
this is yucky and then as and I started there
and then as I just breathed with it and felt how what the sensations in the body
of it and just kind of was with the yuckiness at some point something in my
chest relaxed and I immediately knew what it was oh
depression but then the depression kind of lifted did it with at the same time there was something about recognizing it
that really made a big difference so first is to
recognize the second is to allow it to be there this is very respectful for
emotions I mean if you're angry and you know and doing interesting
things with your middle finger to the other drivers and oh in IMC I was taught L
much allow my anger this is not what I
mean I mean allow like in meditation allow with some
Stillness allow it to be without acting on it allow the anger to be there but
don't act on it just allow it to make space this is the it's very respectful
it's like your friend sitting on the Park Bench with you really respects you
feel they care for you they're with you and um and uh now if your friend is
sitting on the Park Bench with you and you're telling them how sad you
feel and your friend is sitting next to you like this
oh you you probably think there's no hope
my friend is like I've really done my friend in that's that's not going to help
you um but if your friend just sits upright and has a little bit of kind
upright maturity in their posture and they're there and then they feel oh
there's someone who's stable and there's a there's a grown-up in the room there's
someone who's not overwhelmed by what I'm talking about so can we do the same thing for ourselves this allowing is
powerful but since we're trying to be with the emotion allow it and be with it
can you not collapse can you not pull away can you not push away in out of
anger can you just okay I'm going to show up here and this is why meditation is such
a fascinating place to do all this because you want to take a dignified posture when you
meditate and then don't move you know for your emotions don't
give into them we don't collapse no matter how how upset we are we don't make a fist no matter how
angry we are we don't run away no matter how afraid we are we just have this
posture okay and then we can be a good friend for ourselves then we can be with it and
some and allow it okay I'm allowing this it's easier said than done but this is
what the practice is to learn how to do this and it can be learned for
sure and then um the F of raft is to
feel and uh those of you here last week you know remember we did the the um hand
exercise so find out where the emotion is being expressed in the body is it a
tightness in the belly is it some kind of rumbling in the chest in the heart area is in the shoulders is in the face
where is it most expressed where's what's most what part of your body is most activated by the emotion that you
have some emotions are more s diffuse and they kind of spread through much of
the body some people say it's everywhere and then you ask your then you say is it
in your little toe you this happens to me often enough people say it's everywhere and I say is it in your little toe and as soon as I say that
they'll say oh no no it's here and it's torso and now it's not everywhere it's here and then I'll say is it mostly in
the front of the Torso in the back of the Torso it's in the front of the Torso so again it's not everywhere it takes a
while to kind of for people to find where it is and then in the front of the Torso where's where is it the strongest
oh right here and so they need to help to kind of find where it's most
active and um and uh and then like we did the hand last week the idea is just
then just feel feel the physical
Sensations associated with the emotion part of the advantage of this is
then you're with it by feeling it but also the physical Sensations are not the
story the physical Sensations are not the ideas we're spinning and telling
ourselves about it we're trying to step away from the stories to just feel the
Simplicity of the emot the emotion in the moment all all emotions believe it
or not they want to process themselves they want to move up they want to complete
themselves if we can allow them to but if we're participating in telling the
story and why we're so angry and how we were wronged over and over and over and
over again or if we keep telling ourselves you know you know you know boy
am I a jerk boy am I just a lousy no- good lousy person
boy I'm just like a failure as a human being boy I'm just if you keep saying
those stories over and over again it's debilitating it sucks the life out of us
it live in those stories over and over and over again so part of mindfulness to
be present for the physical Sensations is to learn to shift the center of
gravity from the thoughts were spinning to just feel the
emotions and for for me I don't know if this will work for you but it's a very powerful gesture for how to feel how to
be with the sensations and that is to cup your hands together like this and just come from
underneath wherever you're feeling it the emotions in your body and just hold them
there as if they can be there forever just just gently calmly just okay fear
here you are with fear to give you kind of
much easier to say than to do but it's I think it can be a quite powerful thing to
hear when we're afraid we bring mindfulness to our fear
and we're with it we're helping our fear feel
safe it's not the same thing as making yourself feel safe because then you've identified with
the fear but help that place that's inside to feel safe it's okay but if
you're there poking at it and telling it you're lousy and you shouldn't be there and I'm going to fix you and we're going
to figure out how to make you go away uh then it's not going to feel
safe just like you wouldn't be if I came up to you and was clearly looking at you
and talking to you like how am I going to get rid of you you wouldn't feel
good I promise I won't do that but you just you know just you know
it wouldn't feel good right so the same thing for your inner life your your fear needs your respect needs your care you
want to help it feel safe so that your fear can move along everything moves along if
it's given the chance so it is so first
recognize then allow then
feel and the the the um fourth one is a little bit more complicated to
understand it's to tease apart so often emotions are seen as one
big hunk of stuff junk one big ball of something and it's very hard to get a
handle on it because it's just one thing emotions are Composites they're
made up of different things and there's a strong connection to story making mind so if we can set
separate out the story from the immediacy of how we're feeling physically that makes a world of
difference if we can tease apart the emotion and how we're reacting to it how
we're really so oh look at that there's you know I'm
feeling afraid but now I'm embarrassed that I'm
afraid I hope no one sees me I better hide it I better put on an extra jacket so no one
sees that I'm how tense I am so this means that we're we have a relationship
to it that we're embarrassed so we tease apart the fear and the embarrassment
tease apart the liking from the experience the not liking from The
Experience teas apart the aversion teas apart the attachment oh
this is good I don't want to get let go of this so over time we're seeing all the
extra things we're doing and we're kind of becoming allowing things to be simpler and
simpler so each of the parts can be seen for itself rather than seeing as one big
stew and people say I'm stewing but we don't want to Stew we
want to we want to kind of let every respect ECT everything let see everything distinctly for what it
is so probably this is a lot of ideas a lot of to say but it's it's meant to be
simple but um but maybe this idea of raft you can experiment with it
recognize allow feel and tease apart so let's do a little bit of it now in
meditation so I'll do another guided meditation like we just did and then I'll introduce the raft steps in the
middle of it and see how that works for
you so it's often good to think of setting yourself up for meditation kind
of doing the Preparatory steps and over time you learn what this beginning steps
work for you again here I recommend that you just
start really simple and do a three breath Journey just do stay with three
full breaths keep it that simple but give yourself to those
three
and then maybe taking a few long slow deep breaths could be another three but this
time deep breaths relaxing on the
exhale
and then returning to a natural breathing just as you
are and maybe another three breaths but continue to do this relaxing on the
exhale
and then letting yourself just breathe and Center yourself on the body
breathing and so that you're not so much up in the control tower of the head see if you can notice more how your
body experiences the
breathing
as you come to the end of the exhale feel the weight of your
body touching your chair or the floor to feel the
stability of what supports your
body as if you have a foundation that holds you
up maybe as you exhale relax relxing into that foundation so you feel more
grounded and so that you don't fill your
awareness with thinking so that there's more space in
Awareness to be aware of the body see if you can quiet your
thinking soften maybe even slow your thinking
down maybe thinking from a deeper place
within or maybe letting go of your thoughts as you
exhale and then writing on the Rhythm breathing in and breathing out for a
little while here in
silence
for
so now notice how you're
feeling anything at all could be you're
tired could be that you're
calm could be you're agitated could be sad or
happy irritated or
content
worried or feeling
safe maybe it's very subtle maybe it's just hints of what
something whatever you're feeling start and see if you can
recognize it in some way doesn't have to be exact recognition but recognize that
it's there
where the act of recognition allows you to step away from it to be so you can be with
it rather than be in it like you you can say
hi hi sadness hi High
Joy calm whatever it
is and then to be with it as a good friend allow yourself to feel whatever
you're feeling
it's only going to be for a few minutes so for these few
minutes allow yourself to
be but the allowing is being with how
you're feeling you're not being what you're feeling
maybe it's easier to allow if you're breathing with your
emotion breathing with your state that you're have breathing through
it and then whatever way you're feeling whatever way what whatever you're
feeling notice where in the body that feeling is most pronounced
and feel the sensations or the activation in your
body associated with the emotion or your mental state your
mood maybe imagining your cupping your hands
of awareness and holding it gently in your
hands you're being with it as you feel
it
and then teasing
apart noticing how the physical sensations of the
emotion is different from the thoughts the
stories different than how you're relating to it
there's the emotion your state and the reaction to
it the Judgment of it
preferences
interpretations predictions of where this is
going there's the emotion and then how you
define Yourself by it this means I'm this kind of
person tease those apart so that you can be with the basic
Emotion by itself so you can better recognize it
allow it and feel it
and when you feel like that's enough then Begin Again with your
breathing return to breathing and just practice mindfulness of
breathing
and and then to end this sitting take some long slow deep breaths
feel your body get yourself ready to to end it and
when you're ready you can open your
[Music]
eyes so there's a lot kind of instructions
and ideas that were presented today it's always the the default if you
if you have a choice always choose the simpler choice in this practice simply
being aware so the basic idea is to use breathing as if it works for you well
enough let that be the center of gravity for the meditation just going to be with your breath and some some days you can
be with a breath a lot it's really nice some days you can hardly be with it but be with your breathing until something
else becomes more compelling and that'll happen sooner or
later and so we don't only stay with a breath because then you set up a tension between the other thing that's happening
that's compelling and your effort to stay with a breath so you can just let go of the
breathing and and then bring your mindfulness to this other thing that's happening so if it is your neighbor is
really loud then rather than struggling and judging that and being upset with it you
can go and just notice hearing being mindful of listening the
noise and just kind of see if you some people get really relaxed just listening to
sound but what's really happening is not the noise from the neighbor is this is the th thousand time
that you you know you've talked to them 999 times before about how they make too much noise and here they are
disrespecting you one more time and what's really happening is you're angry but you're
meditating okay this is the chance to be mindful of anger that's what's the big thing that's
more stronger than the breath so then you so okay no doubt about it this is anger so
you recognize it might you say that to yourself oh anger oh but Gil said to be with it but
not in it so just step back how do I say anger to recognize it where I'm not
glued to it what does that mean not you know so then you anger anger oh okay now
I'm a little bit apart from it once you're apart from it it's a gift because
now you can come towards it with as a friend if you're like this you you know
you can't do anything to it if you want to if you offer Respect by being separate and come together so oh anger I
see you and then um allow
it no this is terrible it shouldn't be it's
my neighbor's fault and I got to do something I'm going to write a letter to the owners of the apartment building no
no that's later now just allow just allow calm down calm down just allow
just feel it oh anger this is what anger is like you feel the heat you feel the tension oh okay and so so allow it allow
it and then feel it I don't want to feel it this doesn't feel good life is about feeling
good just calm down just feel it just feel
feel like that I don't want to okay let's shift gears then what's really
happening is you don't want to the resistance feel that resistance feel
that oh resistance recognize it allow it
feel it don't make resistance bad just fold it into the mindfulness and then
after a while the resistance dissipates and guess what now you're left with just
the anger now it's easier anger without resistance so you hold it and feel
it and then as you feel it then the tea of raft you can tease it
apart oh yeah there's the story I tell myself the story every time
999 times now I tell the story that my neighbor disrespects me my neighbor
hates me the lame neighbor is trying to ruin my life
life and so what you don't know is your neighbor has gone deaf and this is almost de and they're
desperately trying to hear something and they crank up the music and they feel so
bereft but you don't know that so you think they're out for you and so you start separating out the
story from the actual experience some of your stories are true stories
so then tell yourself yeah I think it's a truee story and then but this is not
the time for the story that's that's let the story be later after meditation or let it be
later so I can just be with the my own experience so that I can take
responsibility for my part of it all really see what's going on so
there's teasing apart so when we did that in the meditation was that was that something
some of you could follow along with was it interesting and anybody want to say a few short words we're almost ready to
stop here but love to hear some comments
up um I was having trouble just staying is it on Fus can you hear me yeah okay
um this commonly happens to me I'm feeling really cold in this room and it's very uncomfortable and so I can't
stop thinking about it and I'm trying to like get I'm like why isn't anybody else
isn't anybody else like I feel it in my bones and so I'm like then I can't stop
thinking about it but then I try but then I like tense up cuz I'm cold this happens to me with the weather in
general when it's hot and when it's cold um so it was hard so I found myself like
kind of trying to soothe Myself by like kind of rocking a little bit right right and then I'm like no I'm not supposed to be
moving yes so yeah yeah so so that so this is an example of how I mean you
don't have to do what I'm about to say mean you know it's a usually a lot of times meditators have Shaws they put on
you know just they tried to try to stay warm but what you can
do if you want to do what I was when I was studying in Zen moners in Japan where it was pretty cold some many times
of the year and really hot in others I was told when cold just be cold when
warm just be warm when hot just be hot and so there's and I've done a lot of that where yes this is
uncomfortable but I'll just be cold and and I I take the cold as the object of
mindfulness I just feel the cold and be with the fold try to relax with the cold
and um and uh the same thing with hot and uh it's possible to shiver and be at
peace but it's also possible to have such a strong reaction to it we're fighting it we're upset with it it has
to be different and we're kind of like getting all activated around it which sounds like what you've been doing yeah
no I do it all the time and I try I'm like no just be with the cold no I can't it's cold I don't like this at
all so so so so it's something I need to work on for for sure yeah so so
um so one one of the things that I like to teach here at IMC and maybe I said
this before in this class is that Buddhism has Lear about learning how to be free in the midst of
everything but uh if you're only free when you're comfortable you're not really free so what does it mean to be free
when things are uncomfortable we'll try to turn up the heat next
week but uh but you but but uh it might be this might be a very interesting area
for you to explore but may don't don't explore it when it's most difficult yeah maybe I'll try to be
warmer I I always think I'm warm enough and no but yeah we'll try to keep it warmer for you but but but the uh but
try to find some situation where you're mildly un just mildly cold and where it's safer to to experiment and see if
you can experiment with the the raft and then judging it like I
shouldn't be so upset about how I'm cold right you know like the whole story that then goes along with that like I should
be able to just be like with the c like you're allowed to be a cold person without you're allowed to be a cold
person without being a bad person being cold that that's I mean you didn't say
bad but you yeah yeah you're allowed to you're allowed to be someone who's you know that's nothing nothing no
shame just just be cold make it simple but if it's easy enough put on a
blanket or something this is not supposed to be forceful aestheticism
here question yeah maybe one more and then
we'll stop uh yeah hi so um when I'm doing a
meditation um you know I'm not getting too many emotions or anything like that unless there's a distraction uhhuh so
I'm not able to practice being with that emotion or even analyzing or you know
being getting into the emotion from a hold right in front of your mouth getting into the emotion from a
disembodied way but in reality in in real life uh let's say I'm having a you
know my boss is screaming at me or something like that I'm having fear and worry and all of that what do you do
then is it that the technique should help you try and extract yourself from from those Pur you could do that uh mean
at at work you have to take care of the work but you can take five minutes time
out say you're you boss did something and you're really angry and then you say excuse me I need to go to the bathroom
you don't have to tell them what you're doing in the bathroom no one asks usually and um but what you're doing is
going to sit on the toilet and just breathe and practice this with your anger for five minutes okay and then see and that you
practice there okay and so if you don't have much emotions when you meditate that's fine
you don't have to have emotions but uh if you can uh stay with the breathing
stay present and come back over and over again from your thoughts you're building a capacity to be able to be with
emotions later so don't worry about it you know if you don't have it here but but take
the opportunity at work if you can step away for five minutes and see what
happens okay thanks okay so I want to say that to
open the arena of emotions sometimes is
opening Pandora's Box emotions are difficult very difficult for some people
and uh and and uh so it's possible that this has been tender for you some of you
to do this uh take care of yourself when you go home and be careful with yourself
I'll stay up here a little bit and if you have questions or anything you want to ask Tom is Right sitting right there
he's available Nana in the back is why woman and you can check with her as well
and Nancy here you can talk to them so there are people here you can check in with and and I'll be here and so so
thank you and I hope that uh this week this coming week that you'll somehow explore a little bit more your emotional
life in a way that you maybe haven't before and if you want to do get a
little bit of extra kind of momentum in this explore your emotions and find a
nice friend that you TR who maybe you can sit on the Park Bench with or something and tell them what
you're learning tell them what how this has been like and what what's you see you know and maybe have a little
conversation about it great thank
you