thank you thank you Martha for that introduction and of course I want to thank you Gil for the invitation to
teach here I have taught at IRC uh but and I've been here a few
times on Wednesdays but not way before the pandemic so it's good to be here
with you all um first of all let's just say hi to each other so turn around bump
fist or elbows or whatever feel safe to you side each other
[Music]
sorry I'm I'm s sensitive
so getting a little bit of Dripping here I apologize about that
and um maybe because I'm Zen but feel free to turn your chairs to face directly so
your neck isn't whatever at the end feel free if you want or bodies
um and um I actually want to start us out with
a visualization so if everyone could close your eyes and of course if you know
that's activating anyway perhaps just keep your eyes [Music]
down all right and um then I'd like you to
visualize peeling a fruit there is a ancient meditation I've made
up so you're peeling a fruit so really visualize it you can feel free to move
your hands while you're you're doing this too uh like which hand are you
holding the fruit what kind of fruit is it and now you're you're peeling the
fruit with a knife so how are you holding the
knife how are you peeling the
fruit all right all right okay
okay sorry you don't get to eat the fruit in this visualization actually go ahead eat some fruit since it's an
ancient madeup one so eat the fruit and then um whenever you're done eating or
ready just open your eyes and come back here my glasses are fogging up all right
and um anyone want to share first what what fruit are you peeling yes apple apple
okay yes banana banana I did banana apple and orange oh
you're very very hungry this morning yeah okay yes pear pear a pear phew I said a bear I'm
going wow okay all right um okay and then with your knife all right tell me
which way you peel the fruit with your knife
go ahead and maybe in fact everyone maybe just do
it all right okay now I'll say a few words for those people online who can't really see us in the room all right I
think I saw your hand first yeah I had a mango so I Wasing it uhhuh with a knife
like that and then what do you do after you do those
lines SCE section and eat it okay anyone else
I don't peel my fruit I'm sorry I don't peel my fruit you don't peel your fruit a banana you just eat the whole banana
with the skin right like I don't feel it ever with a knife oh with a knife okay
all right anyone else want to say yes I went around in a circle around my Apple
uhhuh circle with an Apple trying to do one piece yes yeah that's a fun one all
right I I'll just say I made up this visualization um for for the beginning
of one of these book so I should say I'm here uh my name is uh Reverend kti lad
my pronouns are she and they uh I live in greaton Rancheria land are we still
on aloney land here yes okay uh meant to look at up and forgot and um Gil um was
kind enough and gracious enough to be at Bookshop with me at the one of the readings of my book back in November
home is here practicing anti-racism with the engage for Noble Truths oh no sorry
the engage hatful path we've changed the subtitle um anyone was here for that per
chance no one okay there few all right um there are a lot of people there but
different people obviously um so um he asked me to come and uh give a talk about the book and so um this meditation
or reflection visualization uh came about when I was literally feeling a mango a while back
not few weeks ago and um I peel mango
I'm right-handed I feel mango the skin towards me and I had a memory about how one time
I was doing that and um a white woman said to me that is wrong
that is so unsafe you should not peel with a knife towards you that's if you
slip you hurt yourself you should peel away from you and I was like okay but I
continue to peel because this is you know how I was taught right maybe I brought a little more mindfulness and
carefulness to it um and then I um when this time when I was doing it I
remembered that I used to have a hang out with a friend um in the Vancouver BC
area who's from Malawi and uh one time when I was peeling a mango my way my way
she um said oh this is how we peel it in Malawi and so she took the mango and
with a knife did those lines and then with her you know finger just peeled it
off and so um to me it's a a way of
understanding how each of us are conditioned all the time this book is basically
about how um we are conditioned uh
especially in the system of white supremacy culture to um inhabit or take certain
places within the system with oppression system in general but very specifically
about race here and very specifically from the Asian-American
perspective um because there isn't a lot out there especially in the Buddhist
world right and so a lot of it has to do with how we
were conditioned and in our location how then do we um come to understand um how
to accept other ways of being or not right and and by that acceptance isn't
has to be some you know like rejection lock the door you know black go in the back or whatever it can
be other ways that are unconscious right or um maybe maybe you could say more
mild all right so with that I'm going to um and and maybe I should just say since
most of you weren't at the book reading is this book um rose out of a
response um the first response was in 2017 I was at a Generation X teacher
conf conference and uh another round of sexual misconduct had come to light in
various um Buddhist communities in in North America and um so at this
conference um they brought in right use of power as a restorative model who here
knows right use of power okay it's look it up Cedar Baro really about um up
power and down power I mention it a little bit in here really useful and I really appreciate it it um H and yet it
got me thinking that in my career and in Buddhism um I've been to a lot of
trainings you know and um always something else was brought in for
conflict resolution or any of that and um I was like well what what in
Buddhism uh can we have that as a restorative model and so with the support of the
Hamera Foundation which is a Buddhist Foundation I've been developing the four noble truths to be a restorative model
so in that model the um first Noble Truth you know in life there's Dua um
starts out with that um there is harm and harming has happened because to
restore anything we have to begin that something has been broken right so much
a conflict I will say is about defining that
I've heard of many divorces where it's defining who hurts who in what way and
then that from there what kind of resolution uh Wars are about who has
hurt whom in what way and and and when we can have some in my sense um when we
when there's conflict when we can have some sense of you know where we could meet that we could at least start to say
this is the issue that needs restoration that's how restoration begins otherwise
it's just conflict so that's that's why it starts with that and then second Noble Truth is
usually it's you know their causes or the origins of Dua um and in the engaged
version it's that um understanding fully the causes and conditions for the rising
of hurt and harm so um similar to the the the
classic one however we focus a bit more on the um systemic
conditions uh for instance in racism I know that um for many years when a
racist incident happened to me um mostly my response is why are they being so
mean to me what did I do right and until I took ethnic studies by the way I'm
adopted I lived I'm from Vietnam I lived overseas until I was well I came to the
US when I was n and a half for like a year and a half then I went to Egypt and didn't come back till I was a teenager
right so I didn't understand the structure of racism in the United States
but once I understood that then I realized oh it's not it's not so personal I mean the the effect is
personal without a doubt the impact but there's a whole system that is creates
that and so it's a systemic thing and it depers personalizes a lot it actually lowers my sense again not that the
individual impact isn't important and valid but it also gives me this wider
sense that one I'm not alone and two um and that there there many pieces that
come into being and therefore there are many pieces that um Can rectify the
issue and essentially the premise of this book
is that um we the second Noble Truth is that these are all things that were conditioned right that the the suffering
part like course certain things dooka dooka is just part of life but the dooka that we can do something about is the
things that we've learned um we were taught at times in a way that um
was understood to be for our safety or for our good right our parents do that
um I know in Vietnam M um you know uh my
mother would ask us to move aside when a GI was coming towards us or group of
GIS black children children of color are taught many things to be aware of around
um white body people blue body or cop body people
right so these are things that are taught and and the idea is that what is um and also white bodies taught who
might be safe to you or not right and so what we need to do is examine that and
then think now is this a truth that works for me not only like now as in
this year 2024 but also where I live I'm an adult now I have more agency so the
third Noble Truth is where do we find agency even in the midst of Duca right
in the midst of hurt and arm and then the last of course is the eight-fold
path so um in this version um the eful
path I've re structured them a little bit but I'll just say I'll just leave that for now um because I wanted to talk
a bit about um one of the chapters about how we can
restore um maybe I'll just say in general the book is laid down three ways
and um it it parallels or it echoes um
what I see as three essential aspects of healing from trauma racism is certainly
a a trauma other oppressions are trauma um and that is and and I would
say this is in general right acknowledging what is is the first step again towards restoration so much of our
practice actually it's the first number truth acknowledging what is now I like
acknowledging because because it's not just knowledge it's
really investigating the knowledge how you know the knowledge and in fact the
practice instruction of the first Noble Truth is to investigate that's why we want to be curious we want to lean into
it we want to go and explore it further right is't that true you come here you think oh I'm going to get them
instruction how to avoid my suffering but if you stay for any length of the time we're asking you to look at it sure
we give you tools and the aold path gives you lots of great tools for how to
be to identify more and more clearly what is your Duca and to build a
capacity to be with it right then knowing what shifts are especially
needed right skillful thinking or skillful motivation skillful effort
skillful mindfulness skillful speech are under this category and in this book I frame it as the first acknowledging is
seeing the world as it is that's hard second is what the world needs
now and then the third is learning how to put those shifts into practice I
think it's really Buddhist practice is not a passive practice we we do a lot of you
know a lot of people go oh you just sit there in fact you know when I ordained my um uncle my adopted Mother's old
older brother they're my mother was already 48 when I was adopted at 8 so
they're you know pre pre- civil rights generation for sure and he came to my ordination
and um he he was like uh well one he said do you guys have to chant like that
have anyone been here to a Zen we chant very monotone right and the idea
supposedly is that we chant in monotone because um then there's no you know you chant melodically the Buddha says
supposedly that then you start compare to each other right oh he sounds better I sound worse or I sound better he
sounds worse or vice versa right and so supposedly in Zen we just I'm monotone
so we don't arise comparison and then he also said well you know just you're just
Naval gazing why you just Naval gazing what do you do in the world H and so
it's useful um especially in restoration that we actually
um put shifts into practice it it's not enough to know what is the impact of
harm or to know what is your responsibility from the upow position
for instance it's that what are you going to do about it how are you going to put those into effect right and so
here it's realizing the wholeness of the world which is skillful I call it in
acting which um is my reframing I think it's Kyra duel lingo who said that I
rearranged the furniture of the eful path um to skillful in acting um from
action because to me an acting gives um a sense much more of the vow to do
something essentially the the skillful action is the five precepts right and so
by when we say an acting we to me there's a vow that I'm going to do
something I'm going to put into action and also laws and policies are enacted so it gives it that systemic kind of
framing also and then lastly in the realizing the wholeness of the world is
that they're skillful living how do we use our energy especially after um examining and
realizing what the shifts are and when we do these shifts we actually find a lot more energy isn't that true because
what what happens is we realize a certain thinking that we were taught
certain views that we were taught brought with it a lot of tightness and if we can understand and make the shifts
from practice then we we find a lot more energy and so what do we do with this energy we keep on
validating what we value and hold to be true right essentially restoration to me
is that some sense of our wisdom our values that we thought we agreed upon
like not kill in right um not stealing not misusing
sexuality uh not stealing not lying and no
intoxicants right those are the main five right that these are values that we hold and how do we enact them so that's
essentially the the framing of the AIL path so I today I wanted to talk about
skillful speech which is in the uh shifting part
so this is chapter seven shifting speech to
wholeness I am in a practice period a 90-day Meditation Retreat at at convert
Soo Zen Monastery where I've been living for three years I'm part of the Doan Rio a
selected group of senior practitioners who are in charge of organizing all the activities in the
Zeno or meditation Hall this position involves tasks such
as letting people know when to come to medit meditate and how to participate in
ceremonies leading chants and leading the serving teams during
oroke Zen formal eating in the Zeno a white Mill teacher is leading the
this practice period as is part of the format of any Soo Zen intensive
session each practitioner goes to see the leader of the Intensive for a formal
Doan a Zen word for a one-on-one interview about your practice with the Abbot of the
temple meeting with the leader one time is mandatory after which it is up to the
discussion of the student or teacher to decide if more meetings are
needed the format for doosan I had been trained in thus far was to bring in a
question to the teacher that was about a teaching Point one's practice or how
practice can support a life difficulty on this occasion being the
first meeting with this person I didn't know I didn't have a question for him so
I asked him if he had one for me he did
I've been watching you you go around looking glum a lot what's going
on I answered I'm having a lot of body issues some of it is overw work as head
Gardener the past two and a half years but most of it is that I'm having a hard
time with the racism that's happening here at the monastery he answered
you need to not think about yourself so much you should focus on taking care of
others I looked at him baffled I just started to share a pain
that was a result of the impact of systemic oppression and without having
had any discussion with me this is what he had as
advice I paused then said you don't even know me how can you say that as an
Asian-American woman my whole life is thinking about other
people I've been taught to always put other people's needs
first and what does that have to do with my experiences of racism here anyways
the glum part right your practice he says your practice as a Doan is to take
care of the SA a community of practitioners so you should put so you
should be putting the S needs first he asserted as he had completely ignored my
point twice now the subject of racism and its impact on me and thus my
practice I realized this was going to go nowhere so I politely bowed out of the
room on one level the Abbot was correct
as a Doan my role was to focus on making sure members in the practice period were
taken care of around the forms a Zen word for appropriate conduct in the
various ceremonies and skills that are part of Soo Zen practice however he did not act in
context his Focus would limit it to being an authority and thus
commanding it is true that the Abbott as the leader of the practice period was
technically everyone's boss however if you have a boss with
whom the only interactions are about how you should do your job how good a
relationship would you have with that boss this wasn't simply about
professionalism and job responsibilities I was trying to share how racism was impacting my ability to
practice which I would argue also had a profound effect on how well I could do
my job because he was in a position of authority and he believed the job I had
to do was what was most important he did not listen to me and what I was trying
to share to the Abbot racism was irrelevant
to my practice and he only focus focus on how he thought my glumness affected
my ability to do my job well in retrospect it's a little bit
creepy somebody watching me all this time in the system of racism white
people's point of view is centered bipac are people of the global
majority voices and points of view are considered less than from unimportant at the minimum to
irrelevant also to me there was an intersectionality of Oppression in this
situation I doubt he would have pointed out to a male body that they look
glum the predominant stereotype of Asian and Asian-American women is that we
should always be smilingly
accommodating additionally he did not know me only what he interpreted by
watching me we had never interacted until that moment if he had been my
teacher or was a person I had a relationship with the result would
likely have been different the Abbot on several levels
ignored the context of the situation focusing only on his authority
and what he deemed important the priority in his style of
communication was not about connection or context to live from liberatory agency
in holess we need to shift not just our perspective but also the ways we
interact with each other and the world let's explore how skillful means
excuse me explore skillful means to do so as we um talk about
skillful speech so remember that the eight full path or the eight of them are
broken up into three sections right the first is called the wisdom section and it's skillful by the way the traditional
translation uh is right and and I did read that um right is in appropriate and
that the analogy is that you know if you go up to a cow and you want to get milk
the right way is to pull the utter not the tail so that kind of right right
that's that's what they mean by right however we we tend to think of right and wrong so that's why um very popular for
a while and think so much now is wise right in terms of all the eful path I myself like skillful because it um and I
to me the the Elegance of the AAL path is it actually tells you what is wholesome or skillful classic wording is
also wholesome and then it gives you skills to develop those so that's why
I'm using skillful for the Eightfold Path okay so the first is skillful view or skillful understanding and it's very
specific of the four noble truths and of Karma and then there's skillful thinking
is usually uh very classic uh intention is also and I like motivation because
motivation for me um because thinking in Buddhism is never passive you're
thinking propels you to the next section which is usually called the ethical
conduct skillful speech skillful action and skillful livelihood um and so to me
um motivation takes us into the next section and the ethical conduct I like
to call it compassionate connection or compassionate conduct because it's the
interactive part right how we speak and how we interact with each other how we
live with each other um and then the last is um skillful
effort skillful mindfulness and skillful concentration usually call the amadi or
from Gil I learned I have heard him say that it's uh actually the uh
developmental both the emotional and mental Developmental and it's often well
it's put at the third it's often consider the bridge between the wisdom
section and the compassionate conduct we use the meditative factors to um reflect
right on how the two are working out you sit down and you think oh am I living in
accordance to my values my wisdom which is really your values right the the in
Buddhism as I understand it the a the Four Noble Truth is your set of values
right of how you view the world and then your thinking is how you process that
and how it motivates you to to act in the world so you sit down and you
meditate to see oh is that in accordance or you sit down and you maybe just had a
fight with somebody and so you ooh my speech how does it you know sure we all
think we sit down and especially in Zen we're just you know being with things as they are but I know if I just had a
fight I sit down and I like you know think it through and try to you know so
it's working out right so in this section then if we think about it not
just as ethical conduct as some kind of morality but really how do we interact with each other then are we interacting
in a way that Fosters wholeness that Foster a sense that we're
interconnected now um skillful speech is a great section in the AIL path because
it gives us very clear um it gives us four factors on how to have skillful
speech um and why there are four of them they're set up into two sets so the classic wording is wholesome excuse me
UNH wholesome or wholesome right um and so uh let's see the classic ones are
let's see how do they frame it because I rearranged the furniture there too so let me pull up the classic for you um
the classic is abstaining from lying abstaining from
speech that divides abstaining from harsh or abusive speech and abstaining from Idol chatter who would like to
recite those back to me kind of hard huh so I like acronyms
so I just I made up an acronym so we can have remember them more easily also then
put a little positive spin on it so the acronym is tugs like a little tug in
your sleeve to remind you hey skillful speech is like this h so T is for
truthful and truthfulness is very layered in context um for instance um we most often
think of Truth as being about facts and information you know we've heard just
the facts please but facts can be manipulated or wrong as we are hearing a
lot about these days right in social media um and um it can facts can deny
hurt and harm for instance you know around when this book was being written um when the um Atlanta shooting of the
spa shooting in Atlanta and how then the um Sheriff I think it was a sheriff yep
spokesman um said that the shooter was just having a bad day even though eight
people were killed six of them were Asian uh an Asian-American Wom
women so um facts are not just facts
they're not really objective and in um journalist you know journalism is starting to really sense that there's no
OB objectivity because we all bring a lens and in Buddhism the more and more you practice the more you realize
99.999% of the time you are just projecting because everything is associative we do not see see this as
just this right what right most of us see this and what
you most of us here who speak who would say it in English would say a glass but
some of you might already say more than that you would say oh this is a glass mostly filled this is a I'm sitting
going this is a dirty glass right because I see some some stuff not not in a bad way just just noticing these
things right right um this is a heavy glass I don't
like this glass It's Too Tall it's too heavy it's too whatever right we don't just see it as it is and leave it
alone we see it we make all sorts of Association about oh I have a glass just like that at home oh that's a nice glass
I'll go get one I wonder how much it costs I wonder where they got it right it just goes on and on so so truth right
is really layered and with oppressions truth is really that much
more layered because it's about safety I know before I came out back in the 80s you know on the weekend thing you know
on Monday at work people would say well what did you do for the weekend and I for many years would be using the
pronoun he even though I was a lesbian but it just wasn't safe in my in my
places of work at at times so truth is very layered
I'm supposed to read this part ah as oppressed people we have to reflect on how we may have been taken on valuing
white centered dominant Society idea of what is considered significant truth
over our own if so we need to work with it shifting internalized White Center views
into ways that make sense to us in our lived experiences of course we do need to be
mindful it doesn't mean we can say whatever we want at any time another way
to put it is how can we reenter truth to be more inclusive of our complex
experiences in contemporary life and more specifically as oppression
liberated people I forgot that the my um example is about also how even though
you know in the Bay Area we think we're very open about um being you know people
being queer um and yet in I know in still in a lot of Asian Asian-American
communities um it isn't always safe to be out to your family your family
everyone knows usually but um they don't want to talk about it and so I know that a lot of um uh interracial couples that
can be a real conflict um that you know you perhaps non-asian Partners would
think well you're not you know accepting me by in introducing me to your family
as your you know partner or girlfriend or whatever see so it's very layered now
tugs we on to you is for uplifting right and and in particular in
this book I'm bringing in uplifting as not only how do we talk in a way that uplifts each other but also um as we've
internalized either racism or home homophobia or sexism or ableism or fism
all sorts of internalized ISM how do we work with that especially when we're in
that category all right G is for
gentle it's actually really hard to be gentle when you've been conditioned to
be defensive and with oppressions we are conditioned to be offensive all of us
racism right when I even bring up the word racism probably anybody in the room would probably start to
go because we're all like uh-uh right and that is part of the our conditioning
that we should not be talking about racism or that it's going to be painful
and this is why it's really hard to
approach understanding places and which we were taught to actually not bring our
attention to to give it validity some of us don't have a choice
because we lived in in those areas right and yet part of our practice is not only
opening up to where we're unconscious about our you know you could say everyday suffering our own and
personal generalized suffering but also our the specific spe ity of our lives
and the systemic kind of specificity and so I know you know when
I first started meditation and actually started out in the Insight tradition and
um uh I went to a women of color group um that was off of Spirit Rock and um
for for a while and then one of the teachers said to me oh I want you to do meta recitation regularly and in
particular to use um I say my my favorite is or this is how I always say
it still is um May I know inner and outer safety now safety can be in met
classically in meta phrases or in karuna phrases right but she very specifically
asked me to include that as one of my meta phrases because there's obviously a lot of safety issues for me right and I
did it but it was very hard and I have met many many people of color queers um
other oppressed people where meta is really really hard right because it takes um that kind
of unconditional friendliness to all that you are we many of us some
sometimes think of meta just like going oh be nice be nice but really meta is
a really difficult practice because one remember in all the Brahma baharas we're
going to the point of something maybe simple to expanding it in all Direction
and all time and all things right and for most of us yeah I could be meta
towards you know that uh I have a college degree that I'm 55 that I'm you
know I like my clothes today but oh uh meta that I um you know I don't know
maybe someone's looking at me and going like this right and I'm like oh do I have food in
my teeth am I going to have meta towards food in my teeth right now I'm making this up right now so that's why
that's a really silly example but you know it's harder right I mean in fact
yesterday you know I gave a Dharma talk and there was something I wasn't that happy the way I said it and then this
morning in fact was it this morning in the car or yesterday all of a sudden I went and Deb's like what are you doing
Deb's my girlfriend um and I said oh I was just thinking about something I could have done better yesterday and I'm
trying to uplift myself so I'm just going ah right so when I think about that I you know this is my way of like a
bringing a meta to myself uplifting myself right meta's hard I was at a
two-month retreat at spear Rock many years ago and our friend who was a a a
queer man a gay man and um at the end we talked and he said Oh I thought this
would I would just come out so like oozy in love everyone beside the hardest
practice he had ever done because that Brahma Bahar is actually purifying practice so they bring up all the
difficult stuff also and I'm looking at the time so I will move on meta is hard
essentially all right s is for significant and perhaps this is where it
relates most to the beginning story significant speech is
communication that takes into account what is important for everyone in a
conversation and is in service of connection in the memory at the
beginning of this chapter the Abbot responded in a way that was significant for him but it wasn't significant for
me I brought up what was significant for me but he did not acknowledge at all a
culture of domination such as white supremacy culture centers white people's point of views as what is important and
valid White Privilege carries with it the sense that white people's point of view Trump other racist points of view
and thus they feel entitled to decide or designate value to what topic carries
more significance than others than others a crucial part of anti-racism and
anti-oppression work is to open up our sense of what is significant and
valued our practice needs to actively and persistently emphasize becoming more
aware of what is significant in particular for other people not just
ourselves especially in areas where we have been conditioned by white supremacy
culture to ignore deny or minimize race and
racism I will say in this book I write White suprem Acy culture a lot and the
reason for that is that white supremacy culture is one in which it's like the in
in the United States I'll just say it in the United States it's the air that we all live in right it's the ground we all
live in but we don't have to act in ways that keep on promoting
white supremacy culture just because yes I got
right all right for those in dominant position
deep listening is a practice of not reacting from or centering one's point
of view first and foremost we can practice from a place of understanding that each of us inhabit
our social location in the very systems of Oppression and and the resulting
power differential each interaction carries
all right I'll leave it at that given the time thank you for your attention