a warm and
celebratory hello on this Martin Luther King Jr Dr Martin Luther King Jr
holiday and um I believe it's my favorite uh public holiday national
holiday here in the United States because of the phenomenal values
That animated and guided Martin Luther King and
because of his clear commentary about the
or highlighting of the challenges of our society the poverty the war the
racism and for uh the actions he took to
rectify these problems especially the racism so um and to do it with the values of
nonviolence is uh phenomenal so I celebrate it thank
you
so one of the gifts that Buddhist practice has
provided me is a
clear deep connection to my own
body and that um I didn't pay much attention to my body before I started
doing this Buddhist practice
and without it being so explicit when I was my early years of
practice there was an Awakening to my body and this was phenomenally important for
me and as it remains phenomenally important our body is not
a hunk of Flesh it's not just a bunch of material physical material
that's combined itself to move us around like a car our body is uh a
dynamic organ of perception maybe not every single part
of it but I suspect in one way or the other every part of the body in its own
way is perceiving its environment and perceiving what it needs is perceiving what comes up against the cell walls and
all kinds of things and um every living cell is
nourished by the blood that flows by and um but every every over the body
is is uh there's sensation and some of those capacity to sense and be aware of
the environment are come up to our mind and inform us how we feel what's happening
in the world how we take care of ourselves and so so much of the
experience we have with the body is not the experience of just
materiality it's the experience of how this material body uh senses and feels and interacts
with the mind and the heart and it's Dynamic and there is much more
information available through the senses of the body through the muscles of the body through
than most people Avail themselves of and uh and to be begin to allow
receive listen be attuned to this Dynamic body is a invaluable part of
what practices and for that it helps to not
be preoccupied in thoughts and part of the motivation to
avoid preoccupation and to Center ourselves in the body is that whatever we're searching
for through our thoughts something even deeper is available something even more wonderful
is available through our bodies the vehicle through our body even when body is quite difficult for
us that um uh it's it's a pathway to
Freedom Liberation so um
to assume a meditation
posture which is to engage the
body bring awareness into the body so we can adjust the body and the
posture of the body's in to be most suitable for
us to be aware to be attentive to have a kind of peaceful
alertness to the immediacy of our
experience lowering your gaze perhaps closing your
eyes
and one of the ways to begin heightening attention to the body is to take some long slow deep
breaths comfortably deep or full and as the chest
expands the belly expands allowing the belly to expand by keeping the belly
relaxed with that
expansion feel the edges of the expansion and how it connects you to
your
body as you exhale as you inhale feel it and as you exhale relax the whole
body as you transition to feeling the whole body as
you
inhale relaxing letting go on the exhale is a way of clearing the
feel of preoccupation and tension to be more
available to feel the body as you
inhale
okay and then letting your breathing return to normal but continue
gently as you
inhale to receive the influence of the
inhale on your
body and relax let go on the
exhale so you can be prepared to start fresh and
new with receiving the sensations of
body in in a global kind of way as you
inhale
for and then for a while
now if You' like you can let go of any attention primary attention to your
breathing and instead be
receptive to whatever Sensations in your body
appear without lingering or getting focused on any particular
sensation a light touch of awareness that can
float from one appearance to another of different
Sensations a gentle moving of awareness around the
body do whatever Sensations calls next coming and going of
Sensations
less focusing and more receiving in a relaxed
way for a few
moments allowing different parts of the body to
reveal themselves as they do and
you receive and
feel
if there's a lot of thinking feel the physical Sensations
connected to thinking in the same
way
and if you keep getting pulled into thoughts on the exhales let go of
thinking Relax The Thinking
mind maybe relaxing how you're troubled by the thinking
mind
otherwise allowing your awareness your attention to drift around the body in
whatever way it wants whatever way it's called so that you
begin Awakening a richer grounding in the
body
for
feeling the weight of the
body the three-dimensionality of the
body maybe the solidity of the
body so that P awareness so that
you come to rest in the body in the
Torso instead of being Swept Away by
thoughts you're nested in the
body
for
as your awareness drifts or opens to the
body if you become aware of your breathing that can be part of
the whole
no need to linger or focus on the
breathing let it the sensations of breathing come as they
do being equally available for whatever else wants to
show itself in your body almost as if your body is speaking to
you and you're
listening listening equally to what is painful in your body and what
is pleasant and what is
neutral not lingering with
anything
for
letting go of thoughts as you exhale let go of any fixations of
attention as you
exhale and open broadly to the body as you
inhale
for
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to take a few
moments to feel what it's like to be in your body right
now how are you from the point of view of your body
how are you from the point of view of your
mind how are you from the point of view of your
heart one of the values of mindfulness of the
body is that we're more closely connected to the
physical sensations of care and
kindness love physical sensations of tenderness
or gentleness or warmth
and as we come to the end of the sitting to gaze upon the world with kind
eyes to orient to the world with a warm open
heart aspiring that whatever benefits come come from
meditating is for be for the benefit of yourself the benefit of
others for the benefit of the relationship between self and others
others and self and for the benefit of the whole
world may it be that this body of ours supports us
in the kind of presence and openness and
warmth that aspires for the welfare of all beings may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be
[Music]
[Music] free thank
you
so good morning or good day on this Martin Luther King
holiday and
U and uh instead of Del light that's my
favorite holiday and I love that Martin Luther King's
expression Soul power was his translation of satyaa which is uh Mahatma Gandhi
uh um term which literally means holding to the truth but sometimes is translated
as power of Truth and
um and so today we'll continue the this five week introduction to
mindfulness meditation and last week was the foundation of it the way I usually teach
which is with the breathing and this week it's um mindfulness of the
body and for some people mindfulness of the body uh in the way that this last
guided meditation was done works but better than mindfulness of breathing there's something about um narrowing
perhaps or focusing on the breathing or something about the breathing which some people um evokes challenging feelings
emotions and so it's not necessarily useful to Center on the breathing um but uh to kind of be more
Broad and just feel the body without focusing on any particular part but
letting it be a gentle drifting and opening and receiving of the different parts
sensations of the body as they appear um is H frees up the mind that is
usually fixates and then maybe becomes reactive to what's happening um and um and this ability to
be grounded in the body to become more embodied is a central feature of the
Buddha's teachings on mindfulness he his classic instructions um uh in meditation
always begins with mindfulness of the body feeling the whole body and relaxing
the body are his two explicit instructions around the body um to uh to
feel the whole body and to relax like like a calming of the
body and that prepares the ground for further practice and the the unfolding
of meditation uh he also made very strong statements about there is no Awakening
without mindfulness of the body and he said there's one passage where he says that in many different ways there is no
experience of the deathless there is no U freedom without mindfulness of the
body and um uh so um it's a fascinating topic
to become more sensitive to your body I think for many of us in modern society
there's a lot of momentum and forces in our modern society that um disconnects
us from our body in some ways excessive screen time takes us away from really
being present here in our body uh sometimes sedentary life lives
um we don't benefit from all the different ways the body can move and awaken itself and and um and inform
inform the rest of us form our mind but all the different uh um you know uh
parts of the body and how they interact and play and come alive um the uh it's you know it's been
known that uh for many of us um particular there's usually some of our
stores which are underdeveloped that if we go to um that to people in in some societies where
they emphasize uh put much more emphasis on certain uh sense doors are much more
attuned to the environment and those sens stores are much more acute just like um many of us in the modern world
use as a small part of our capacity to me to remember to memorize uh back in the ancient world
where there were no books to store things and no internet to look things up and so you don't have to remember it the
only way to store and um information knowledge stories
songs um was to memorize it and so
people had a much better capacity to memorization than we have today uh people sometimes had a much
better capacity for sensing the environment around
them and um so uh to meditation practice is
partly a a um developing cultivating a greater
capacity for attention through all our senses not just through kind of the
Mind's Eye not just through cognitive knowing what's happening but uh
heightens the capacity to feel the whole body and to awaken the whole body
people who' have had very difficult experiences trauma or very difficult emotional trauma
challenges sometimes will um uh uh it becomes too difficult to feel the
intensity of their emotions and so that they will shut down their body and uh
shut down sensing and feeling parts of the body some people because of their
their professions there kind of the way they're erased because there was Prior
prioritized in society mostly live in their neck up in their thoughts and ideas and in their
eyes um and um and uh but so much of our emotional life lives in our full body in
our torso especially in our chest and our belly and uh by not really cultivating
and developing a heightened sensitivity of our torso uh we receive so little so
much less information about what's happening to us and uh the impact the
world has on us the kinds of responses we have um a zen teacher many years years
ago kageri roshi uh said that um our body is an antenna and I love that idea
it it's it's a it's a body is just uh primed to take in information take in
Sensations and from the environment and process it it it's also Prime to take in
or to express um what's going on with us emotionally what's going on with us reactively what's going on with us in
the mind and there's an intimate relationship between the state of the mind and the state of our
body as the state of the Mind changes in meditation the experience of the body will change as well um if um sometimes
when the mind is really peaceful and calm and spacious the body will feel the same way and then if the Mind suddenly
remembers um you know some um slight
some offense that someone did a long time ago and suddenly things contract you can feel how the body contracts too
we have a thought the memory and the body just tightens up in response to that or gets hot or tense and um as the
body relaxes and softens so does the mind and the advantage of mindfulness of
the body is that as we it provides so many subtle cues of what's happening in
the mind and those subtle cues are not just cues but as we feel and are open to
receive them and allow them um things tend to relax and soften giving
breathing room to our experience uh allows something to soften and relax
it's kind of like if we were tense in the shoulders and really tense somehow in a friend friend who cared for us we
trusted and a lot just gently kind of came over and put their hand on our
shoulders only then do we realize how tense we are and then something relaxes
it almost like you don't have to think about relaxing oh okay something relaxes
there's something about bringing this kind of kind available awareness receptive
awareness to what's happening inside of us in our body that moves ention to
relaxing and moves um um the the the
emotions the feelings that are emergent that don't come with tension but come with kind of a feeling of suffusion or
flow or um Radiance uh to grow and spread out so uh
you know so um um you know as things get
uh when gases get warm they expand and um the
um so when ice warms it melts so that
which is Frozen as as the warmth of attention that opens up to us then the
places where we're Frozen begin to thaw the places which are already soft
and open expand outwards so anger greed hatred are all
parts of kind of being frozen or tight or constricted that as we bring attention to it uh they tend to relax
anything that involves clinging can relax uh anything that involves
suffusion kind of a gentle warm kind of Radiance like love or kindness or
generosity that grows in that space of awareness so to more we can be in our
body this receptive open uh way the easier it is some
people find that it's easier to be with the sensations of the body if there's a
the the the Rhythm or the beat of breathing is keeping us there in
centered in the body just so breathing in breathing out breathing through
whatever is happening breathing with whatever is happening in the body kind of keeps the grounding Keeps Us centered
other people find that it's just not useful to be so much with the body with the breathing but it's easier easier for
them to just kind of be relaxed and not focused or not not inclusive of the breathing the breathing may be
Sensations may be in the background and for the time being it's they're not useful to feel and so just feeling the
rest of the body more globally is what is helpful and then eventually the people
who find it best to avoid being with the breathing because it's triggering of something fear or something um uh at
some point there's a shift and at some point they're ready to kind of take in the breathing and I've been that way
sometimes where I would ignore the breathing uh but then some point the breathing kind of came in through the
back door and then I was able to stay with it and it was nice to be with and
the breathing itself is a very rich ecosystem that in itself kind of is a
some some way kind of a aggregate of all the different uh reactions feelings
Sensations that are happening in the rest of the body and so they it's it's almost like a meeting point of
everything so it's a the breathing itself is a really an invaluable part of
this exploration of the body so this talk now is was meant to be
a to provide the the reasons why it's so valuable to be connected to the body
of course it's not always easy to do this the body can be a difficult place for many reasons but to begin opening up
to the body begin being interested in it and and um and listening to the body in
a deeper way like you'd listen to a friend is invaluable and very important
part of this mindfulness practice so much so that I feel that's unfortunate we translated Sati as
mindfulness sometimes I wish we had translated it as body
fullness so um if this meditation was interesting that we did today you might
practice it one more time today before tomorrow and if um and as you go through
your day today you might uh do a very simple thing and that is um
periodically uh maybe with some reminder uh check in with your body and say
What's Happening Here what what's happening here and uh maybe if you're maybe alone a little bit so you don't
trouble other people if you have a device where you can set a timer for and
you decide how often once an hour once every 30 minutes once every 10 minutes so that uh you get a little ping and
then you kind of check in it doesn't have to be more than a 5-second checkin What's Happening Here in the body
oh and that regular check-in into the body oh that's what's happening that's what's happening um will slowly over
time provide you with a uh greater literacy of your body greater ability to
listen and recognize what's happening and I'm pretty confident um that
listening to your body will uh provide a lot of wisdom that a lot of wisdom come
in Buddhism comes from this grounding in the body so uh thank you
very much and I appreciate a lot uh this chance and um look forward to it
tomorrow