hello and welcome to this week where
we're considering the what the Buddhist early Buddhist
tradition considers the primary hindrances obstacles to meditation
practice and these uh five are also U many of us can recognize them as
one of the primary may be obstacles challenges that we face in our daily
life as well so first ones are desires sensual
Desires in particular or a certain kind of greed avariciousness wanting
something so desperately and uh and the second is uh
ill will aversion wanting something to go away or
be destroyed or not exist and with a certain degree of everlight uh
animosity and uh both of these desire and aversion anger for example are
energizing and there can be even a sense of uh pleasure in the in the energy of
Life the energy of being Vigor vigorous and engaged and and
um and some people maybe even part of their addiction to anger and maybe
desire is uh how it helps them feel alive and therefore that they count that
they're valuable that there's purpose or something the next hindrance is um
usually translated as sloth and torper and I'll talk more about this later
and that these might not be the best translations or the there might be Alternatives that that are interesting
to look at but uh this is where uh the Life
Energy dissipates where the caffeine of the Soul desire and aversion is no longer
there and without that caffeine there can be withdrawal there can be dullness
toror sets in complacency a kind of giving up and that
can happen if things are comfortable in meditation the complacency of pleasure of bliss and
we stop engaging in the mindfulness because we're just enjoying it in the way that certain Vitality dissipates the
Vitality of the inspiration of I'm here fully
here and uh it can be complacency it can just be a shutting down it could be a uh
no longer kind of applying ourselves to what doing because we're enjoying it and
it could also be the shutting down from it's too difficult that um I'm
discouraged I'm bored and uh this is not really doing me much good and I'd rather
be doing something exciting follow the dictates of my desires and
aversions and um and so there's a shutting down so one of the things we want to do and as we meditate is to
notice the es and flows and I use that word carefully the es and Flow
of the Vitality or the energy that we are engag in as we meditate we don't
want have too much and we don't want to have too little just the middle just right um
just right means there's no striving there's desires haven't you know
clinging desires greed or pushings hasn't uh taken over at the same time
giving up hasn't taken over over shutting down or getting too calm and too complacent hasn't taken over just
the right amount and uh it doesn't have to be so dramatic how much that is but uh I don't
know what a good example for you is but in the best circumstances when you're not really
tired um uh the kind of alertness you need
to um drive a car on the freeway where it's not so much traffic but you have to
constantly stay present and you can't shut down you can't drift off or taking an
exam that you really know the subject well so it's not like a strain but you
have to stay present and alert so you can be you can be relaxed but also alert
and but it continuously it's just right so so what I'm suggesting for this
meditation is to watch watch the es and flows of the energy the level of Engagement you have with the practice
and see if uh just to see how it shifts and changes maybe not try too hard to
get it just right um be content that uh you're kind of gently swinging just past
the center and maybe occasionally you feel have it right but just
watch the ABS and flows of your engagement so to uh assume a meditation
posture and gently close your eyes and just straight
off feel the Vitality or the energy level in your body whatever it might be
low or high
medium and there might be in any single person's body different parts of the body with
different degrees of Vitality and we might over identify
where it's most energized active or
least see if you can find some place in your body where the sense
of Vitality engagement is medium middle
maybe it's the effort to keep the your lower back
upright or the sensations of your arms
positioned in your meditation
posture or maybe there's something at the base of the stomach
that seems like it's alive and vital the Vitality there but it contains no
striving no no complacency just
there and in the same way there might be in your mind your
awareness different degrees of of energy or
engagement some things arise and your mind is straining and pushing or alarmed
energized excited other things happen and you're
discouraged deflated or
you just love just to settle back and float
and almost drift off can you find that place in the
mind find something you're aware of right now that's medium just
balanced no excitement but
no deflation easy to be
aware maybe the tingling in your
fingers the contact of your hands against some other part of your
body maybe the beginning of the
inhale the beginning of the
exhale so notice as we continue now in Silence the ABS and flows
of how energized you are
in practicing mindfulness without being concerned that
what you're doing is right or wrong just see
clearly how it is and if you find the
medium trust that trust being with that for how as long as you
can
for
e
as you're practicing now is your mindfulness
compromised by desires by
aversions or with a shutting down giving
up letting go that
is letting go into
torper
complacency
where is The Middle
Way in engaging
mindfulness
for
e
and as we come to the end of this sitting
considering the end of the sitting and the next time you'll get up and go
out into the world world we being the presence of other
people what occurs to you does that activate
more the realm of desires wanting
something more the realm of aversion not wanting
something or is it a a way aaken the opposite of Awakening does it shut you
down does you free something of you
sinks something of you shuts
down maybe from overwhelm or maybe from boring
but if you're able to gaze upon the world the with the middle
way without the strain of any desire without the strain or tension of any
aversion just gaze upon the world kindly gaze upon the world
with a aliveness Vitality
Clarity either wanting or not wanting
except to see clearly G be
still and gaze upon the world kindly
let your awareness be calm and
settled so that your heart's
well-wishing your heart's ability for friendliness and
kindness can be expressed or come alive through these [Music]
words may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
e
so hello and welcome to this third talk on the the hindrances the five
hindrances today we do the third hindrance and the hindrances are that which
compromises our capacity for a useful engagement with our activities
whatever we do whether it's meditation or life itself and other ways and I use the word engagement
because uh being mindful is also an engagement that something is activated or comes alive when we're
Mindful and um to only associate mindfulness with calm uh might actually encourage a kind
of dullness in the mindfulness it's possible to get
overcome and and uh but to associate mindfulness with uh uh making effort for
some people means that we're trying too much we're straining or uh we're
agitated in certain kind of way and so this a classic metor in Buddhism of the
middle way that where's that middle and um so in terms of the five
hindrances the first two um kind of a gr
desire uh compulsive desire clinging desire and then uh uh uh uh hostile
aversion uh that these kind of desire and verion are both
energizing and some people even if they're really hostile love to be
hostile and angry because now they feel truly alive and otherwise they don't
feel much maybe they feel maybe they feel unworthy or dull or bored or
something and being angry just makes them feel kind of like energized and they feel so you know that's what
they're attached to not necessarily the aversion but the the being energized they love it or same thing with desire
that the uh sometimes with fantasies of different types um it might be a
pleasant fantasy but of Desire but it's the sense of coming alive and what it
does in the body and the feelings and that we feel like there's purpose and meaning um and sometimes people spend a
lot of time in fantasy because it it's there's a pleasure of feeling
alive and some people uh it's kind of operates as kind of caffeine of the Soul
aversion and desire caffeine of you know it's kind of a caffeinated thing where we using something to keep us energized
that's not really natural in a certain kind of way and um
and so when we find ourselves no longer caught in desires and aversion some in
meditation some people don't know how to be alive energized engaged without
desire and aversion and so there can be dullness that sits in there can be a
kind of a withdrawal caffeine withdrawal and it can be awkward in time of boredom
and feeling dull and feeling maybe headachey or feeling kind of uncomfortable and we have very important
to realize that just like with um uh withdraw withdrawals from caffeine it
takes a while to kind of work it through the system that the withdrawal from
desires a life of constant desires or constant diversions or both
um there's a period of withdrawal awkwardness for a little while and we don't know quite how what foot to stand
on or we don't we feel dull or bored or we feel uh shut down or
something discouraged even and um and so we have to kind of have the wisdom to
know how to go through that so the third hindrance is usually translated as sloth
and torper and uh these are English words that probably I never used until I
came to the Vasa tradition and teachers were using them for this third hindrance and um and it's not the same
thing as tiredness and uh you know physical and mental tiredness um can come from overe
exertions come from just not having slept enough and that can have a big effect on meditation as all as well and
there we have to be careful that maybe it's more important to take a nap than it is to meditate uh
if people are asleep derived you know it's probably better to sleep than to meditate ideally you get enough sleep
and um and then you can um Can meditate without that kind of dullness that's
there sleepiness some people however when they're sleepy but can't sleep find
that meditation helps that that set settles something so they can go to sleep but so sleepiness is not sloth and
torper sloth and torper is um is a psychological condition that compromises
our capacity to be mindful in in a balanced engaged
way and there's a variety of things that can do that uh one is uh as I said uh
the withdrawal symptoms of not no longer being caught up in desires and
aversions sometimes it's because the meditation is going well and uh we're
getting fairly concentrated and calm but we're getting too calm and so we're kind
of the mind is kind of going into a dreamlike state if there's a lot of uh dreamlike images and things feel
basically Pleasant in meditation then that's uh people get complacent they get
kind of lulled into kind of a kind of dreamlike state that's usually a sign
that there's not enough engagement not enough Vitality in the mindfulness and
then the art is to turn it the dial a little bit just enough to get that engagement you know bring in more
clarity more Act of recognition and and really seeing what's happening in a
little bit more kind of energized way sit up straighter sometimes it's enough
for people uh maybe do walking meditation instead of sitting meditation and um so the imbalance of
energy and calm is uh you know sometimes it's called concentration and energy
another reason for uh this sloth and torper is U uh it's a kind of uh uh
variation of aversion we don't like what's happening and so we we want we want to kind of there's a version for
sure but it manifests as a shutting down uh really getting really tired and and
uh dragging our feet and you see see you can see this in Spades sometimes in young children where they'll and I
remember very well how I did that with my mother uh when she pulled me through department stores and uh when I was
young and and I just really disliked it and even the smell of them I you know which kind of set me off as that this is
associations I had and I would drag my feet and tell my mother how tired I was
and and um and uh and how hard it was and I must have been miserable for my
mother to be with me the way I was so tired um and then all she had to do was
say let's go get some ice cream and boy the tiredness just vanished and then like oh then it was worthwhile being
alive so it was a kind of resistance to tiredness and uh a strategy of um
aversion and uh so so sometimes uh but sometimes U the sloth and torper can be
uh what's called sloth and torper can be a shutting down down uh out of fear or
shock and it turns out that the first word that we translated as sloth if you
go and look in the poly English dictionaries uh one of the meanings that they give is
rigidity and uh and this uh uh I think works really well for some of the
compromising ways in which we trying to meditate we were compromised in meditation and that is um fear can
operate in such a strong way that we shut down we we we
freeze we um don't know what to do we just kind of you know just kind of uh
maybe even give up or something and um and that's what compromising
awareness is a kind of rigidity or Freez uh freezing up or dullness and that is a
response to things being overwhelming and that can also happen meditation because sometimes meditation
is kind of like taking the lid off Pandora's box of our emotional life there's a lot of unresolved emotions
that exist within us and meditation as we quiet down um the active way in which
we keep them repressed or keep ourselves avoiding them can um can slow down can
quiet and then these deeper Wellsprings of the anger or the grief or the despair
that we might have shows itself and that can be overwhelming
and so then people will shut down and uh and some people will shut down so
thoroughly that they kind of just kind of not really even aware of what's going on and they might believe that they're
meditating well because they you know nothing really happens you know until
the end of the sitting and they hardly knew where they were during the sitting and so they think oh well boy that was
fast or boy that was uh you know I must have been deep meditation or something
um but uh so a shutting down a freezing and so uh all these things that go on uh
and then you know then one more thing reason for sloth and torper is um actually Bliss some people get such joy
and well-being and happiness in meditation that they Bas in it they kind of give up their e energy they kind of
lean back and just kind of kind of indulge in it in such a way that the the
mindfulness goes out the window and uh and then there's even no desire to kind of be mindful anymore but
things are really dull just kind of um and a certain kind of dullness because
it were just kind of Basking in this in the sun of of the Bliss that might be there so all these things need respect
all these things need to be care and love anything that fits in the category of sloth and Tor torper uh rigidity
freezing up all these things are not enemies and and uh there's no need to be
afraid of them but we need to become wise about them and uh and to understand
exactly kind of a little bit understand why were sloth and toror has come up and
um because simply kind of increase the level of energy or engagement that we want to do might not be the appropriate
thing for some of the reasons for sloth and torper and so uh
it might be that we want to stop our meditation if we're really afraid and that's why we're freezing up and maybe
do walking meditation maybe just walk gently around the block uh so there's a
different context for feeling what's going on that we don't feel trapped by it meditations for some people people
feel trapped but if they're walking around they might be willing to kind of be present for what's happening in the
easier way way or maybe even meditations counterindicated um if we're up against
this the some really deep Challenge and we have to be really careful and considerate what's the best way to uh
appropriately address the reason for the freezing up that might be going
on um and um but uh in the in in the
bigger picture what we're aiming towards over time is to dial up the efforting the energy
the Vitality uh just enough so that we feel engaged in the mindfulness but not tired
engaged in the in the uh in the aware in Awareness so it's not we're not not
caught in desires not caught in aversions but uh just that middle way
that's sustainable and um and so it might be that um you know just you feel tired you
feel like you don't have much energy but you um you turn the corner and and there
lo and behold and in there some big parking lot nearby
there's never before event there's a circus has come to town and you've never
seen such a thing and now uh you know you're just kind of amazed and just kind of in a relaxed way you're not tired at
all anymore you're just kind of like wow you're present to study the colors of the tents and I don't know what I don't
know if my examples are the right ones for you for this middle way of dialing up the energy when there sloth and
torper but that's the that's the goal and sometimes we can do it directly and
sometimes we um you know take our time as we address what's going on and
appropriate way so for today uh what I'd recommend
is that this what what I did in meditate the guided meditation is that um the es
and flows of how engaged how present how clear our mindfulness is has a lot to do
with whether we're caught in desires or aversions or whether we're caught in
sloth and toror and to watch the ABS and flows and see what is compromising your
mindfulness and is it desire is it aversion or or is it a kind of shutting
down or a giving up or a complacency all of the above
um can operate but watch the the uh the es and
flows uh that's the assignment if you want to for the next 24
hours so um thank you and um we'll
continue with the hindrances tomorrow