good morning good day here we are again on our week of meditating with the
Inner Mountain and so we've been going through
uh this metaphor in various ways and um yesterday we did uh expand
this sitting with the mountain uh in a way that expresses the whole ecosystem
within like the mountain mountain ranges it's um a whole ecosystem with its trees
the forests uh Earth rocks
streams and so today uh we are going to uh expand even
further um to include
space the mountains don't exist uh separate from the space that's
all around and that's within and it is so for uh this body
this mind and heart and there is a space within and that there's a space all
around and so meditating like a space
including uh the whole ecosystem of the mountain
within so um with that uh let's meditate
[Music]
allow the words to
settle arriving arriving at the Temple of this
body mind and
heart coming here and now
with a gentleness and a
care without demanding for things to be otherwise
arriving with a few long deep breaths if you
like arriving with a sound and a silence if you like
arriving with the global sense of the body sitting lying down
whatever the measure of a disease or
pain is included arriving with it
not dismissing anything
sensing the lower half of the body if you're sitting
upright the pelvic floor feet
legs settling downwards towards Earth
underneath and if you're lying down you're sensing the whole body
resting
down like the mountains
rooting in the earth
underneath stable
steady our mind can become
steady with the
feelings sitting like a mountain
sitting like a aive
Mountain the trees
breathe the streams in the mountain
flow the creatures
are alive in the
mountains feeling sensing
including the movements the
livess in addition to the stability and Stillness
including the waves of emotions if they're
present
moods like a weather systems in the mountain
feeling and sensing without having to comment on
your
experience noticing space
or a felt sense of a
spaciousness that's within this body and all around
my vast space and the mountains are not
separate here too in this
body we can feel and then
sense the space ious
nness that holds
everything softening and relaxing into the spaciousness
the space doesn't have
conflicts with our emotions
thoughts it offers vast
room for things to float
through
e
e e
no spaciousness and the spacious
knowing holds all aspects or all parts of
ourselves
the whole of ourselves our health
give yourself a [Music] permission to
soften and ease
into this spacious
holding
e
e for
as the sound of the Bell Rings notice what have shifted within
yourself maybe the breath has changed
Sensations in the body heart and mind
[Music]
so today um I brought a reflection based on a sua
in De AA there is this sua called
parasa and the assuta documented the last days of the Buddha in his life um
there was a very touching exchange between the Buddha and his personal
attendant uh for a few decades uh Ananda and the Buddha was in his last
days of his life and the Ananda was stressed
out and so the Buddha said to him so
Ananda live as your own Island your own
Refuge with no other Refuge let the teaching be your Island
and your Refuge with no other refuge and how does a practitioner do
this it's when the practitioner meditates by observing the aspect of the
body King aware and mindful read of
covetousness and displeasure for the world and that goes with the
feelings mind States and the Damas and many of you would know and
this is the teachings of the Sati and so this is how a practitioner is
their own Island their own Refuge with no other
refuge and this is how the teaching is their Island their refuge and with no
other Refuge so today I'd like to speak a
little bit about um this aspect of Refuge um that the
Buddha called live as your own Refuge refuge in
oneself in the past few days and I shared some Reflections and about the
Refuge in the triple Jam the Buddha Dharma and
S and I pointed out that each of this ref huge um has an external Dimension uh
kind of this protection we go to or shelter we go to and and there's also an
internal Dimension and so each of this triple Jam
um as we practice aligned with it they come alive in
us and so towards the end of the Buddha uh
life he's pointing back to one's own role in the
practice and note that uh the Buddha said live as your own refuge and let the
teachings be your Refuge back to back to me uh this two are not separate
uh they are connected refuge in one on self and
refuge in Dharma uh are kind of um you know kind
of like a two sides of the coin uh in some way and they each highlight some
important aspect of the practice and I wanted to teas apart this
a bit uh today and so first uh this an aspect of living as our
own Refuge it highlights uh our role in the
practice uh it's helpful to remember that the Dharma uh was taught by the
Buddha um but we have to practice it we have to do
it and um no one can do it for
us and in uh ad damata there is this verse um it says
it's up to you to make a diligent effort tatas simply tell you
how and so um and it's interesting to feel into this and it may seem quite
obvious and you know there's a sense of um and we have to practice it but in
reality it's not always easy to do so often we
don't always trust our own capacity to practice practice with what's difficult
practice with what's hard you know we have a lot of um only y kind of conditions you know
if the weather is bad you know then it's really hard it's too hot it's too cold
or our neighbors are having party it's too loud and
uh you know all kinds of things you can think of the Milling reasons that we
feel we're not up to the practice and and I know that feeling
myself at times and sometimes it can feel like oh
you know we're just going to wait for some magical situation to come
in so that doesn't really sound like a refuge does
it and I remember when I was uh when I um when my son was just born and that
was a time that I um was really King on going on Retreats and and clearly I
couldn't go to retreat and so I had the thought wow you know well that means
that I I can't practice sounds pretty straightforward
unfortunately I didn't quite believe that thought and I was very fortunate that I
came across the book on about deep and who a amazing householder
practitioner that he in she instructed all kinds of uh lay householders to
practice in the midst of things happening nursing babies kind of
just exactly kind of what I needed uh cooking washing and working all kinds of
things and that was so opening for me and all of the sudden that there is a
whole new uh Paradigm of the way of a practicing that began to open up to me
and so this also leads to this a second aspect of uh live as our own Refuge
refuge in ourselves and that is I liked that the
uh Buddha use the verb uh in this that live as your own
refuge and there is um uh there is another sutta that also says make an an
island of yourself or make yourself a
refuge somehow this verbs uh live or make signifies that this is an active
process that we're engaging in it's not that somehow automatically
you know we're just you know we're our refuge um but this heart and mind can be
trained we often uh look for external conditions
as a resort because we don't quite feel safe within
ourselves and the different parts may kind of fight fight against each
other um and uh uh in our meditation I invited this
possibility to make space for all parts of
ourselves and so they can exist together you know whether it's the part that
feels pain and uh want to be uh relieved
of pain or whether it's the part that feel depressed or um
frustrated they are there with a reason or with the reasons that we may not even
know but the fact that they exist ask for our permission to allow them to be
there and so there's a process of making ourselves a
refuge is to cultivate a way to allow all this parts to be to have a room to
have a space and so there are not to be denied they shouldn't be here no they are here
welcome welcome the them
in and so this um process of live as our
own Refuge making uh uh ourselves a
refuge um is for us to begin to learn and cultivate this kind of Inner Space
inner safety inner well-being and inner
ease uh where the whole of ourselves can
belong and that takes a cultivation and little by little with a humility and
with a dignity and it's not easy you know I'm not saying this is
easy um but the invitation is to uh not
too quickly and easily resort to the
tendency of saying oh no this is too hard but staying with the
hardships staying with that which may be
difficult it reminds me of another sutta um that um the Buddha pointed out the
noble disciples uh uh there was a dialogue between uh a
deity with the Buddha and the deity was complaining that the practice path is
hard and the path is rough and hard to travel and the Buddha
says uh the noble disciples um walks the path even if it's
a hard and difficult they do it even when it's
hard and so this process of making and living uh the
practice that the Buddha is pointing out so making yourself a refuge and let the
Dharma be the Refuge through the sincere
practice and including every everything including
everything and so that's the invitation uh for your contemplation and for your savoring of
um how uh ourselves might um be a
refuge and so thank you thank you
everyone and I'll see you tomorrow