so hello everyone and welcome
and happy to be here so
to continue into our meditation there's a
wonderful important
kind of complementarity between two things to do in meditation and that is on one hand to be
committed to being present and uh be committed to being
mindful here and now in the present moment to be aware to stay awake
aware so a sense of commitment a sense of choice making a decision yes this is
what I want to do and I'll stand behind it I'll I'll be um involved with this
this is what I'll put my life energy into for these minutes so that's one
hand the other hand is uh to have the
awareness practice the mindfulness practice be
calm be light be easy
going be maybe even have a sense of happiness
or joy as part of it to feel the goodness the
wholesomeness of being present so putting those two together
it's a commitment which sounds like a heavy duty word a commitment to being light
commitment can seem like a word that requires us to Bear down and be
serious but it's a commitment to be easy to be
soft to be happy even if it's accessible to have a
joy so it's hard then to make the commitment be heavy and
a serious and kind of there's a there's a lightness and a
forgiveness a willingness to start over again and again where commitment is not so much
holding the course but over and over again in a light happy engaged way choosing to
start over again and again where the choosing over you feel so fortunate to
be able to do this because the alternative maybe is is
worse so commitment to being present in a calm
way so assuming a meditation
posture and there so much that can be expressed in the posture and now today a posture that is
expresses a commitment to be here be rooted here in a relaxed
way and it's for each of us to find the posture that has to balance between
those two and then gently closing the
eyes and as a beginning of this
commitment you know the word commitment in it uh I understand the Latin root has
the word to touch in it to touch together to stay connected stay in
touch and that works very well for mindfulness a commitment is to stay in
touch with our present moment and to begin by being in touch
with breathing by taking some
enjoyably Pleasant deeper
breaths and relaxing on the exhale
adjusting the arms a little bit so that the shoulders can relax
more then breathing Norm normally and as you breathe in a normal
way scan through your body to see what you can relax soften
and sometimes it's possible to do a global relaxation and a sense as you
exhale to relax or calm the whole body
and similarly to relax the thinking mind maybe there's a gentle way of
scanning the mind for the places where there's
contraction or tension or pressure as
agitation and the relaxing calming of the thinking mind with every exhale
and then find some sensation in the body maybe in the
hand that is relatively neutral doesn't have any pain in
it uncomplicated place of
sensation and for a minute or two to be aware mindful of the this part of your
body experimenting to see how you can be aware
calmly lightly a light touch
not so much activating the thinking
mind but rather activating the calm
hand so the awareness almost flows out of the
hand being aware of Sensations in a calm soft way
where awareness has no agendas around being aware of the
hand where awareness is maybe receptive and open open and soft to the
hand or you're whatever you're paying
attention and now in the same way to be aware of the body
breathing finding a location where it's relatively easy to be aware of the
sensations of the body connected to
breathing and to be committed to being in touch
but the commitment being soft and relaxed and
calming being committed to as continuous as
possible soft
awareness that has a very light touch to
it and if the mind wanders away don't rush back to the
breathing reestablish a calm awareness soft
awareness and invite the breathing back in
and
for
for for
whatever is agitated with within you know it
calmly a calm light awareness that is not
reactive it's simply knows simply
aware
for
e
for for
a gentle soft
commitment to being present more than wandering off in
thought
e for
and if you can touch into a calm
awareness light
awareness is there any feelings or
sense of wellbeing in the awareness
itself any goodness
any Delight or Joy however
mild in this amazing capacity we have to be
aware here and if there is
breathe with that open to that
well-being make room for it to be here
too
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to take a few moments to feel whatever degree of
well-being that might be here for you maybe together
with something that's a little more troubling where's the
well-being some sense of calm subtleness
some sense of happiness or
inspiration some sense of rightness or goodness of being present with what
is in whatever way degree we can it's good
soon enough we'll go about our day and we probably will be less present
less aware in this intimate close way of Our momentto Moment
experience it's good to have time to do this to feel the goodness of it
and then to consider is there any appropriate
way of offering this out into the world to support
others is there any appropriate way
to bring with you your this practice so you can make this world a
better place for
others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all being beings be
free and may we contribute to that
[Music]
possibility thank you
for e
so hello and welcome and uh this will be the
beginning of a four-part series following the five-part series on the
four noble truths which are the truths of suffering and now I'll offer you uh four
truths of happiness and uh these don't come directly from the Buddhist teachings but
hopefully uh I've been so involved in the Buddhist
teachings for so long that this can be a kind of
a reformulation reformulating it in some way that is useful for you
all and begin with theide idea is that happiness is a very important part of
Buddhist practice that uh it might be overlooked if the emphasis is so much on uh
suffering some people are quite inspired and maybe even inspired in a happy way
when they've people have told me this that they've come to hear heard a Buddhist teachings some Dharma teacher was
emphasizing that uh how much suffering there is in the world and aiming it directly
and that it was such a relief to have someone say that that there is suffering in this world there's lots of suffering
in this world that we're suff we suffer a lot because so many of the people around
were denying it or trying to pretend otherwise or painting it over with some
kind of you know bright picture of how things
were you know wonderful and inspiring or always just ignore it and something like
that and so to hear someone name it so that we say that
um you know I like to say that we in Buddhism we stop for suffering we stop to look at it to spe with it to be to
see it for what it is to study it to find our way through it but not so that
we can suffer better but rather so we can become free of suffering and in that
freedom to find Happ and one of the primary description of
someone who has matured in this Buddhist practice is uh emotional description is
that they are peaceful and they're happy and uh in the time of the Buddha
there was people who were surprised to be around the the Buddhist monastic
Community to see how much they smiled how happy they were the joy that was there
and uh and so to come to a place of Happiness to come to a place of Joy uh
without denying that they're suffering without becoming the victim of the world's suffering without becoming
the the uh reacting to it but finding a whole different way of being honest in
the middle of it and finding some way to have a genuine appropriate kind of
well-being there is happiness in this world so
that's the first truth of Happiness there is happiness there's possibility of
Happiness it's U it's U it's healthy to
experience that happiness it's okay to experience that happiness there are religious traditions
and cultures including time on time of the Buddha that mistrust joy and
happiness and I've had people come and uh asked me explicitly uh as a Buddhist teacher is
it it really is it okay to experience Joy because somehow way they G grew up
Joy somehow belonged to the world of of um I don't know of
indulgence and to really be a good religious person you're supposed to suffer better actually you know supposed
to suffer and if you suffer well then you know something good will happen to you after you die in the time of the
Buddha uh he this was something like that was happening time of the Buddha that when
the Buddha discovered a deep meditative joy that uh uh one of his first big
insights was this is a healthy Joy this is a joy that's onward leading to
Greater freedom and he said this is a joy not to be afraid
of so this there is happiness and to not
dismiss it to not Overlook it to not think that there's other things that are
more important um it would be like saying that um
um there are really important things to do in the world people take care of do all kinds of things that we don't
shouldn't really stop to eat any meals we shouldn't stop to eat any meals
and enjoy the meals while we're eating them um but in fact it's healthy to eat
we should stop and eat take care of ourselves and it's actually healthy to stop and eat calmly and clearly in a way
that enjoys the food enjoys the occasion all kinds of things can kind of go
better physiologically for us if we're not living in a stressful hurried
way and so happiness is a phenomenally important possibility for human beings
and it's a condition it's a support for all kinds of other things happiness is
almost like opening certain kind of joy and happiness dharmic happiness is
almost like it opens the door to the depths of our hearts depths of our inner
life recently I saw someone Define the soul not in a in a religious way but
more of a psychological way as uh the soul is the um is the inner depths of a
person and inner depths are often not uh experienced and felt and made time for
and uh and part of the function of being settled and calm peaceful and happy is
to have it the conditions in place to receive and sense and feel our depths
the wisdom the creativity the challenges the processing the unresolved issues
that are there that um all uh do well to be seen and received in Consciousness in
a deep way and uh and so what is the happiness
you have in your life can you Avail yourself of more happiness joy
well-being uh is there are there small Joys through your day that you you are
overlooking because you have such important things to do or you're in a hurry Hur or you're on a on a device
that you know uh surfing the web and maybe with a little bit of addictive uh
mindset you know going to the next click the next click looking and not quite able to get off when time is to get
off and um so uh and what how does that
limit you could you stop and just look out the window and uh and enjoy and feel happy
about what you see uh some people now are experiencing winter starting and
there's snow outside the window or there's a foliage of changing color or
all kinds of things it might be a squirrel that's bouncing around but the
um uh there might be small Joys there might be small Joys and to experience
with the food you eat take time to eat it and appreciate the fact that you have food not everyone does and not to feel
guilty for it but to feel a certain kind of um uh
well-being joy happiness safety to take time to
walk when you you have to walk from a parking space with your car to some place you're
going um to show up a little bit early and take your time to walk even if it's
just a couple of hundred feet maybe take a longer walk than the most direct walk so you can walk uh close to some nice
trees and just appreciate the trees or appreciate a little view
or see something that's kind of enjoyable for you to don't overlook the
small Joys the small enjoyments the small Pleasures when they're
available don't have to chase them don't have to Crave them don't have to try to
make them up too much but there might be through the day all kinds of things that
just slow down a little bit look around pause see and there might be much more
well-being than you usually allow yourself to feel even in emotionally
difficult states that are quite you know difficult and maybe emotionally painful um there are things we can do to
bring some joy and happiness in in in with us I suspect that um this is part
of the function of cat videos that some people it really takes them out of their
own um difficulties because it's so they so delighted by kitten Behavior or cat
behavior and so I'm not necessarily recommending that but there are things we can do that um we can bring sprinkle
more Delight joy happiness through the day and not just that but as we
experience it to allow ourselves to experience to let it register in a deep
way so the first truth of s of happiness is there is
happiness there might be more happiness and well-being that we can Avail ourselves than we usually do and it's a
good idea to do it has a good effect on us to do that it supports other good
things to come that there is a happiness that opens the doors of the heart and uh
and maybe you'll discover your heart more deeply so happiness happiness has a
place in this world in this suffering World difficult world we have and um so then we'll move on to
tomorrow to the causes of happiness that uh is a kind of a
parallel to the causes of suffering which we was last week's theme so thank you and um I look forward
to continuing and and I kind of feel delighted by the prospect that many of
you might be a little bit happier today experience a little bit more joy Delight
or well-being today with this assignment to Avail yourselves of more joy and
happiness that's available to you it's already available that you're overlooking and in doing so maybe you
your joy and may your joy and happiness be contagious for
others thank you