good evening welcome
welcome so tonight I'm going to continue on this uh series I've been doing on the
introduction to mindfulness and this is not exactly
mindfulness I'm going to be talking about but it's such an important teaching that's uh part
of maybe the whole picture of mindfulness practice and that is to talk about like what gets
in the way like why is it sometimes hard to be mindful why is it that we can't be
present all the time and many of us begin a meditation
practice with this hope with this idea that we'll find more freedom and ease in
our lives and then we discover that it turns
out not to be so easy so so it can be helpful
to discover or to look into or investigate or be curious about what is
it that's getting in the way of more freedom and ease and peace these kinds
of things so part of the finding our way to
more freedom and ease is running about what gets in the way
so I'm going to start with an analogy and that is this analogy that
the brudda gives of U when it
rains espe in my mind I'm thinking of the monsoon season in India there's a you know when it rains
on the Hills it's just natural that the water Ro rolls Downstream and it goes
[Music] from Little vets maybe to streams to
rivers to the ocean right and it only goes One Direction right it only goes
downhill of course you don't need me to tell you this we all know this it's like this it
just goes downhill but when we think about
rivers or streams often what we notice is that there's a bunch of uh H there's a bunch
of uh Boulders or even Banks or you know something that's in the way it's not like the water just goes straight down
in the most efficient and fast way that only exists in amusement parks right where we have but instead you know this
the river is um encountering these Boulders and then turning and and uh
encountering maybe Fallen branches in the Fallen Tree Trunks and moving around
them in this kind of way it's not a problem that the Bold ERS
are there it's not a problem that the tree trunks are there it's just what the
water is encountering as it's continuing on its way
downhill and in some way we might even say this water is having like this intimate contact with the boulder or
tree trunk or whatever is finding there and then it just goes around or goes
over or does whatever it does
so in some ways we can think about uh our practice in a similar way that
mindfulness practice has this momentum it goes a certain direction and it
encounters obstructions Boulders tree trunks on its
way towards the ocean of I don't know maybe I'm taking this analogy too far but uh maybe the ocean is you know
vastness some real peace and
ease so I appreciate very much that the Buddhist tra tradition just recognized
these what we might call Boulders in the way the Buddha talked about them quite a
number of times thousands of years ago they were recognizing oh yeah it's not
so easy to always be mindful it's not so easy to be consistent with this practice
it's not so easy to always be in the present moment or be doing loving
kindness whatever one's practice is and the Buddha he gave teachings
about this so one way that we might consider these
Boulders and tree trunks in this analogy that I gave is as hindrances things that
are hindering obstructing or getting in the way of the
the uh this movement of the water it doesn't prevent the water from going it
just impacts the water the water goes around or something like
this so this idea of hindrances another different analogy but
another way to consider these things that are getting in the way so to speak is these hindrance are sometimes called
veiling factors that is they cover something they hide or conceal or
obstruct what's actually happening in the present moment or what's to be done
next or just get in the way of a Clarity any kind of clarity clarity about
anything get in the way of seeing ourselves clearly seeing other people
clearly seeing the situ situation
clearly and then these obstructions these hindrances these veiling factors
it's not just in meditation practice in meditation practice we see
them more clearly often we're using the meditation as a laboratory to see and understand
what goes on in our minds but they show up in our work our
professions our relationship ship or creative projects or service projects
that we might have and as well as in
meditation I mean it makes sense right that because if something were to only happen in meditation that would suggest
that there was like a different mind and body that meditates than the one that goes to work and has a family and has
relationships it's you know just one mind and body so of course things show up and meditation are actually showing
up in other areas of our lives and hindering in some respects so meditation is an opportunity
for us to explore these so in these teachings there's a
way in which this is maybe simplified and classified like all the things that
get in the way I don't know if that's the best expression get in the way but I'll work
with it for now and
so there's this typical list you won't be surprised to hear about this that
there's a list of these hindrances and I going to talk about
them a little bit at a high level and then I'm going to talk about one in particular I'll do some little
meditation there in the middle this evening so in General these
hindrances we can say there's two that are about pushing or pulling like this
idea of like like this kind of leaning forward and like um like uh like go away
like this push away kind of thing aversion I don't want it go
away maybe I did this wrong so you're it's the pushing but the is uh I did
this with my body I leaned forward but it's we'll just say pushing it's like pushing away or there's things that
we're like pulling we want more of it kind of like energetically we're doing this maybe even
literally so pushing and pulling I want more I want less aversion
desire two the two more about energy I have too much energy feeling restless
and fidgety and the last thing I want to do is sit still here and I want to get up and run with away or do anything pick
up my phone or whatever it might be or the opposite is like oh my goodness I
can barely stay awake kind of like you know falling asleep too much energy this
restlessness or this like not enough energy this sleepiness or
torper too much energy not enough energy and then the fifth one we can
think about it as a uh way as I often kind think about it's more like a
spinning like not quite sure what to do this vacillation this hesitation maybe I'll do this well no actually maybe I'll
do that I I actually I'm not sure maybe this thing over here is better well maybe that's over B maybe I should do
this this hesitation this uh not clarity about what to do and ends up not doing
anything but instead just kind of spinning spinning our wheels so to to
speak and this fifth one was called doubt and I'm going to talk a little bit
more about that uh this evening because I think uh it's so
powerful and it's so Insidious it's so uh often veils so many different things
and likes to masquerade and camouflage itself and so I'll talk about doubt and
ways that we can work with it so I'm talking about these hindrances
pushing and pulling too much energy not enough energy or spinning so kind of
like Di's versions of uh describing these uh hindrances but they are
Spectra like they they occur on a spectrum it's not like binary yes it's
there and yes or no it's not there and one thing as we begin to
meditate more and more we start and as the mind and the body really start to settle we start to find more and more
settle versions of these
hindrances things that you didn't even know were there was didn't even know were kind of like operating um
underneath maybe the usual way of seeing things or doing
things so this also means this idea that it's not just binary on off present not
present or you know it's it's you know really settled to really obvious I mean
I think we all have this experience of sometimes like feeling restless and just getting up when we're at home and you
know not finishing the duration in which we thought we were going to meditate but then we start to see like
in a really subtle level there's a way in which the mind can always be like looking for something looking for
entertainment or looking for the next thing or what's happening next it doesn't want to be just with what is it
wants to be you know titilated and some kind of way so that's a more like subtle version and then there can be even a
really really subtle version of that when the mind is really quiet in some
deep concentration States we can sometimes see how there's the mind is sometimes very quietly like probing
trying to find something and so the way that we work
with them of course isn't I mean we have to kind of like respect this uh that they arise and they
pass away and sometimes they're obvious and sometimes they
aren't so I'd like to do a little guided
meditation where we'll explore these a little bit again I'll just say uh this IDE well
maybe I'll just say all of us have all five of these it's that's just the way
it's part of the human experience and I'll talk a little bit more about that after the guided meditation but often
many of us have one that tends to be a little bit more predominant that tends to be something
that uh shows up more regularly and also to be clear there can
be all five at the same time too like you just a we call this like a hindrance storm
but there's also as I said can be way in which there that one that's the most
common like the the mind and the body's favorite way to uh
to not to be present and I'm using this word favorite like in with air
quotes so again just these five if you don't know them and we using I'm using
this kind of language because um I like us to like feel into the experience of
them as opposed to getting too much about the concept or the notion of them
so there's pushing and pulling or we could also say uh leaning forward which
is you know like a desire or leaning back which is I don't want it or there's pushing I don't want it or pulling I do
want it these two oppos iits or this with energy maybe there's
just so this restlessness this feeling like I want to be anywhere but here or
this strong sense of it's really important that I you know take care of whatever it is we feel like we have to
take care of or this sleepiness like as soon as we start to
settle down the mind starts wants to fall asleep and then the fifth one maybe will
say a few more words here which I'm calling like spinning is this hesitation it's about uh well okay so maybe I
should be doing mindfulness practice and we'll do mindfulness of breathing yeah but my breath I don't know I shouldn't
be with the breath maybe okay I'm going to do mindfulness of sounds but gee I don't really like those sounds and then
you know maybe my breath is more uh stable now I'll do mindful breath well yeah I heard that loving kindness is
good I'm going to do loveing kindness practice so there's this way in which we just kind of don't quite settle down
because we don't really decide on the practice instead there's this hesitation
or vacillation or not a commitment or not a like okay this is what I'm going
to do instead we just spend all our time trying to think about or consider or
philosophies about what we're going to do okay so with that is an
introduction Let's uh we'll do a little bit of a guided meditation here
taking a meditation posture a posture
that expresses your intention toity and also has some
ease has some uprightness and some relaxation
and feeling the pressure on the body from the sitting surface whether that's
a chair or a
cushion feeling the contact with the sitting surface
we're here right
now and then maybe just do a general
body scan is there any obvious any areas of
obvious tension or holding or
tightness it can be that bringing attention to those areas allows a little more ease or
softness
and then letting the attention rest on the sensations of
breathing whether you feel the or sense the experience a breathing in the belly
or in the chest or in the
nose just feeling the experience of breathing
giving yourself over to the experience of breathing
what is it feel like to have an in breath
what does it feel like to have an out breath
and what about the transition between in breaths and out breaths
what do they feel like
and we'll stay here for a little bit resting Awareness on the sensations
of
breathing e
when the mind wanders just very simply
gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing e
five hindrances just the tradition holds this as the
list pushing away and
experience including
thoughts pulling towards
wanting more of having of energy
restlessness in the body or in the
mind having little energy feeling sleepy or
foggy lethargic in the body or in the mind
or this sense of hesitation vacillation
spinning which one of these is tending to come
up as we
meditate Maybe you see all five maybe only
one so resting attention on the sensations of breathing
and then when you notice that you are no longer on the
breath a little bit curious is there some pushing or pulling or energy or
spinning and then begin again with the sensations of
breathing e
if you recognize one of these five can you just allow it to be
there this is what too much energy feels like for
example this is what aversion feels like
and then come back to the sensations of
breathing e
is it the same hindrance all the
time maybe it's
changing e
can you notice the absence of any of these
five maybe there's pulling but no
pushing or maybe there's
both
e for
I'll say that when I first learned about these hindrances I felt such a relief I had taken this uh you know
introduction to meditation class and I thought that I was the only one that uh
couldn't keep my mind uh settled I felt relieved to discover you know for
all these thousands of years you countless individuals have uh done this practice and have had these
experiences because it can be easy to think that we can't meditate because our
mind wanders too much or we might uh think that we can't
might idealize the teachers or the teachings in such a way that we think that uh nobody else is having any
trouble with meditation ever or I think you know that idealize what we see around us people are sitting quietly and
to think that oh I'm the only one that's feeling restless or sleepy or has doubt
or something like this but the hindrance is um we don't
have to take them personally they don't mean anything about you as a person they don't mean
anything about you as a meditator this is just what happens when people
sit down to meditate this is what happens these hindrances arise and sure they
Abate and with a more meditation experience maybe the severity and the
duration of them uh changes but it's uh I think until fact I know I would
say I I should say I would say that a person who's completely awakened is the
only person who doesn't have have hindrances and said there's always a
certain way in which we are working with these different energies or these forces in the
mind and we might even say I mean we could actually say meditation practice
is hindrance practice of course it is we don't talk about it that way maybe it's not as fun
and interesting but uh of course it is we it say especially the
concentration practice is hindrance practice working with
them and then maybe also say that you know we want to have respect for these forces in the mind that uh are making it
difficult for us to be present because meditation it touches uh
some of the things that are really deep inside of us and that are important to us
and that uh maybe we are identified with or we feel like are a core part a core
aspect of who we are or what makes us tick or something like this maybe some
of that kind of stuff gets touched in meditation so there's a responses to
that and the responses often are a form of a hindrance like you know preventing us
from getting deeper and deeper into there so there might be this challenges that are getting touched
in into like this these unresolved places these places of pain or
uncertainty or maybe deep doubt or this idea of our purpose or the value we have
or these types of things might get touched into with a meditation and then there's a hindrance that can show up as
a way when we something inside of us like
oh no no that's going to be painful I don't want to go there that's not necessar that's not a
conscious thought so much but often it's kind of what's underneath these hindrances not always sometimes so we
want to have a lot of respect for them and care for them instead of thinking like oh I have to get rid of this
thing maybe just like the bolders in that uh analogy that I gave at the beginning it's just part of practice you
know practice we just encounter these Boulders and as it turns out these Boulders so to speak turn into
doorways absolutely it's an integral part of practice for us to start to see
like what what is getting in the way what is uh what is it that uh affects our
practice and then we just bring mindfulness to it so
we start thinking like mindfulness is going this way just like a a river does it encounters a boulder so then we just
turn like okay nope now I'm going to be mindful of this experience of this pushing and pulling or the energy or
something like this so in that way it's not a problem it's no longer a hindrance it just
becomes the object of meditation object of
mindfulness so now I'd like to open it up and I'd like to ask you guys how was that that guided meditation and I asked
is there a particular one that you felt uh more obviously or more often or more
readily or anybody have would like to share or maybe you're like
I don't know it's perfectly fine whatever whatever experience you
had yes can we send the microphone back there thank you
Jim I found that uh when I really let go of
eting it helps me feel very clear cuz sometimes I try to effort in the
right ways to do the right things like trying to be mindful trying to be but when I let go of all everything and just
kind of just be still and be be be natural that's when I feel the most
Mindful and clear I see so and what helps uh you
remember like oh yeah maybe I can lessen up on the effort a here just to let go yeah just to consciously stop trying
yeah even in the right ways if I think it's a right way to try don't even just don't try just be natural and when when
I feel like I'm in my natural state I always see my most mindful yeah yeah thank you thank you and this is such an
interesting place to practice it's kind I would say like the art of practice like how much effort how much is too
much and how much is too little so that we just go off a dangering yeah great thank you thank you anybody else have
something you'd like to share of this list of five do anybody
recognize that yeah we can maybe we can run the microphone here
thanks yeah I wonder about your thoughts on working with
sleepiness um especially because your awareness of the
sleepiness itself decreases the sleepier you
get that's right and so at a certain point you can you can no longer be aware
that you're sleepy I mean maybe maybe in a subtle way you can but uh yeah I'm
curious about your perspective on working with that yeah and I appreciate so much what you're pointing to here
that because one way is to be aware of the experiences and you will fall asleep if you do this and maybe that's okay
maybe part of being aware of sleepiness is to like wow and see how that image is
I don't know exactly how it is for you but I've done a lot of work with this and like just how like the hypnogogic like the images kind of get a little
swirly and they start to get a little dreamy and then maybe the shoulders heav and the eyes are heavy and then you
often will kind like fall asleep and then you wake up like oh yeah I supped to do that meditation thing and then you're just following it can be
fascinating just that just to watch that experience that's a legitimate form of
practice so there's a way and often we can um feel like oh I shouldn't be
sleepy and it can be a hindrance but if you're just being mindful of it and exploring
and investigating it doesn't have to be a hindrance but sleepiness but I will also talk I'll say a few words about how
to not be so sleepy not fall asleep and maybe you know these but I'll mention a few of them first of all I'll
say this is very common this is very common right I think uh in today's society especially right we're
accustomed to like go go go do do do then then you know the only time that we
kind of uh sleep is when we just relax and then when we relax we associate the Mind assoc associate that with
sleeping and B we're sleep deprived very often and sometimes we just actually should sleep rather than meditate
because if you're really sleep deprived you can't meditate your way through very well any
yourway so here we go um one is to meditate with your eyes open and just uh
you know down you know at a at an angle so letting the light in and that kind of helps remind you that you're
here two is um like I was leading us on mindfulness on the sensations of
breathing but you could give the Mind something a little bit busier to do that keeps it more awake so for example it
could be um mindfulness of the sensations of the
lips touching then the sensation of the seat against the body and the what the uh
hands are touching and then what the feet are touching and you do maybe one second each and just kind of rotate
through lips seat hands feet and then just be going
through this and so that can um give the as I said give the mind a little bit more something to do that's something
else that can be helpful some people have talked about uh
imagining a really bright light I haven't myself had success with
this maybe other people do I offer this in case it's something to that's really helpful like to I don't know I have a
bright light so like it maybe in the same way that you're less likely to fall asleep if you're looking at a lamp or
something like that some people stand up for their meditation period you're less likely to
fall asleep if you're standing and maybe I'll I'll stop there
but those are some things to to do great thank you you're welcome you're
welcome anybody else have a question or comment about uh yeah so maybe uh can we
send it back to I think to the person that was
sitting right next to you Jim thank you thanks um I have an answer to the
original question of like reflecting on the medit meditation also um something
thing to the question that was just asked that's work for me is imp is improving my posture um I actually
didn't do that this time and kind of suffered for it so that's something I'll be better about next time like the
straighter your back is the more awake I am but if I slouch then I often drift off um great thank you but yeah I guess
a reflection was that like I tried to not ruminate too much on whenever I like
got distracted by thought um um and not like be too hard on myself and be like oh you're bad at meditating you should
you should be better by now you've been doing this a while um and kind of just like breathe it out so to speak um I
guess to the Five hindrances Point like what I noticed the most was probably doubt in that sense but I tried to like
kind of not sit on it for too long and kind of just like say oh that was just a thought
you know on with it and just like Focus back on whatever the an ER was nice very nice I'm going to talk a
little bit more about doubt and including just recognizing thoughts or just thoughts yeah great great thank
you can I can I also yeah make a comment so I noticed something it was very very
nice and I noticed um I don't quite know maybe it's it's a
version it's very subtle what's happening so you know let's see like I'm like let's see what's going on here when
we're trying to be on the breath and then there's this quality of like give
me a break I want to do what I want to do and it's a little bit like has the
quality of maybe a little bit resistance even rebellious like
no um it's good for you to want this but and then next next thing that happens is
there's a little bit of you know I'm somewhere else so the Mind goes and and
it's not because it wants to but because there's maybe what Matt said it's like effting let let me do this
thing um so it's kind of like I don't know what it is maybe aversion right or
like not wanting can you tell me how it feels in the body with this uh this tension this
this tension like I almost like feels like we don't want this this is a little
like artificial right now it's not it's not it's the quality of just overall
not clear aware but like a little bit of like some kind of constraint or
tension in the body so not relaxed this kind of thing and yeah yeah
so it can be restlessness it also could be doubt to the sense of yeah maybe is this really worth the effort is this
really what I should be doing now or the Mind wants to or so I kind of like I have this memory of me as a child uh not
like really not um kind of when somebody is not convincing the teacher or the parent and
I really like just okay just don't don't buy into this
yeah yeah so it's kind of and then I'm going to do my thing and this is not the
yeah we're not going to be on the breath because it's something about it is fake so that's what happens maybe doubt I
don't know and do you stay so then the mind wanders but then do you come back back then I come back and maybe the
coming back is a little like again the way I come back there's a quality of
like let's let's do it and then the mind is um I don't know no we something is
not quite nice here so so I really like I'm curious about this moment and I try
to be gentle right and try to be like let's be a good
parent but but I guess it takes time uh the Mind needs to be reassured and yeah
cuz it occurs to me I I don't know if this is actually right spet up but it occurs to me that there like a little
bit of trust is needed like oh yeah okay this is contrived it is artificial but
it is uh something that um is going to take me a direction that I want to go
yeah that that is I think that's what uh there's a little bit of yeah lack of
that lack of like yes I I'm and that's where I'm thinking about it me as a
child so you know I don't know if I can trust you guys so this is interesting
this is a very interesting because I'm curious what happens where why do I like
why most of the time this is the same pattern right yeah maybe it's some doubt thank
you it was very nice very helpful do anybody else have a a comment
before I uh continue
here okay so I want to talk a little bit about doubt just because I think that desire
and aversion may maybe I'll just say a little thing about desire desire itself is not a problem we're talking about
desire when it's a hindrance when it's getting in the way of what you want to do of course we need a certain amount of
deser to you know fuel our movement towards greater and greater Peace and Freedom
and ease and these kinds of things so I don't want to uh kind of like say that
all desire is a terrible thing and we shouldn't have any it's just often sensual desire this pursuit of uh
pleasure pleasure pleasure which gets in the way of uh our meditation practice our spiritual
practice so doubt is this feeling of hesitation or maybe this vacillation or
this wavering or maybe even resistance we might say this uh resistance to practice where and we end up not going
anywhere like I was saying earlier we kind of like are spinning because we have this endless it can be like this
endless speculation where we can't quite decide as I said earlier like what um
what practice should I do or even this feeling of I don't feel like it
it sometimes the C doubt can show up that
way so doubt is a expected and natural
part of practice and I appreciate this so much that this practice is about you
know like come and see come and see for yourself experience for yourself it's not come and believe it's not like here
we're just going to believe this and you'll be fine go on your way it's this uh invitation to experience for yourself
and to explore for yourself and to see if these teachings are true for
yourself and so a doubt of course there's going to be a certain amount of Doubt like I'm not sure I haven't
experience some of these things that are being spoken about or that are being
pointed to so it's a natural part of
practice and I will also say right there can be really healthy doubt too I mean
the obvious ways in which there's healthy doubt in our life is uh when you
get this uh email from the bank out of the blue
oh we' we're changing our uh systems please send us your passwords your
social security number or you know something like this right that's you know natural to be like I'm a little
suspicious about this I don't think so right so there's that kind of doubt it's perfectly health healthy and natural and
will help us to um maybe to examine things or to really engage with like
wait is this really the bank and you know look at the email address it's from
or the URL or you know something like this these days something that we do but
it's also um it's healthy to not just believe
something because somebody told us or not to just disbelieve something because
somebody told us it's really about you know finding our own way and finding our practice
finding our own practice our own version of it each one of us practice will unfold a little bit differently and I
know that I used to think that you know what I was experiencing was what everybody was experiencing and it wasn't
until that um this was years ago but did some um like small grp groups where
people would talk with the teacher would put us into groups and we would talk about something or other and I realized
oh there's lots of different ways to consider this or to experience this and
that was like a a big eye opener for me because in my mind I was thinking like oh the teacher said this so you know the
way that I interpreted it was the only interpretation but of course that isn't true so each one of us will will
bringing hopefully like all of ourselves to this prti practice and that means
that it will all kind of unfold in a certain flavor in a certain way a certain
manner so this uh doubt I'm is to have some curiosity about what this is and
not necessarily just to believe everything and to um swallow everything I guess in some
kind of way but instead to learn something about ourselves
to learn about what is it that we are unsure about and what are those things that we are just believing and assuming
that what we um are thinking or interpreting is the only
way so doubt is definitely a healthy part of practice just like in the same
way that desire is a very healthy part of a normal human
life and there's desire that gets in the way and there's doubt that gets in the way
and so part of practice is to you know be Discerning and notice when is this
helpful and when is it getting in the way so we might say that healthy
doubt is uh asks this question does this teaching or does this
practice does this help does this bring me closer or increase the amount of
freedom and ease and peace and well-being that's the direction we're
going and even Sometimes some teachings are uncomfortable and some practices are
uncomfortable absolutely but there's often a part of us that recognizes like oh yeah it's
uncomfortable because it's this greater self- understanding I didn't know that part about myself and kind of
disappointed now that I see that about myself and that's really uncomfortable but there's yes so there's a part of us
that recognizes even though it's uncomfortable it's pointing us or creating the conditions or creating a foundation that
there can be greater peace and ease so healthy doubt is asking this
question does this help me is this supporting greater
freedom is this supporting greater ease peace
wellbeing because when it's unhelpful as I said we may be just lost
we may be lost wondering I don't know these teachings Diana is talking about thousands of years ago she's talking
about like it's a good thing but maybe they're completely irrelevant because they're so old maybe there's a part of
us that uh might be think what does that have to do with you know my life today or you know how can I what the Buddha
was talking about back then Modern Life Is So Different or maybe we have this
idea yeah it's these practices or these teachings they sound nice but can I
really do them maybe it's other people can do them but can I do them in a way that's uh
what's expected or in a way that is a support for my practice so we might have doubt about
our capabilities and we might have doubt about the teachings and of course we might have
doubt about the teacher how do we know that this person
who's currently sitting right here knows what she's talking about or you know or the Buddha or any
book you read or drama talk you listen to right we might have like H I don't
know so it's perfectly legitimate right to have some doubts we don't have to believe everything all at once so how
can we practice with it or maybe I'll say bit more talking about how to
practice with it one way to recognize when doubt is I
might say like up and running so to speak is when it's really strong there's
this way that um it's experienced as being very
authoritative and there's this way it can be really like powerful and it starts like questioning
everything we're doing and it starts um like vacillating or hesitating or not
having any any confidence in what we're doing either like that's a waste of
time that's not right you can't do it anyway you know these types of things
and there's often the way that I'm like vocalizing this is like clear sentences and saying out loud but often there are
Quiet niggling Little Voices in the back of the mind that might even be familiar
they might be showing up in all areas of our lives so it sounds like it must be true because we hear it so
often but doubt it's is just a another
hindrance it can also it doesn't mean that it's true that we have these questions we're just
questioning and it may show up as not being able to make a commitment like okay I'm going to sit for so long or I'm
going to whatever our practices go on a retreat read a book listen to Dharma talks come here to IMC whatever it is
they're like yeah I'll just do it when I feel like it which is you know it's a legitimate
way of practice but that's different than like you know making a commitment it's also this sense of while
you're sitting or there's got to be another way I'm sure there's an easier way there's got to be shortcuts and and
there's to be sure like there's a whole group of you know neuroscientists that
are trying to find shortcuts for a meditation practice and when it's strong we don't
do things that are beneficial for us like are actively like undermining
ourselves and we're giving up on things uh unnecessarily or giving up
prematurely before the practice has really had an opportunity to show some of the
fruit okay so how can we practice with this one just
recognize recognize the wavering the hesitation the vacillation the sense of
spinning the sense of uh not wanting to make a commitment this kind like being
like a little bit dis engaged and you can just even say those
words yep there's wavering here there's this uncertainty this vacillation there's
confusion or whatever the word might be just just to recognize that right and then then
all of a sudden we can have mindfulness of that experience and we're in the practice as opposed to it being a
hindrance something that's in the way it just starts to become the
practice we might even um depends you know what else is happening and the the
uh surrounding situations or the conditions we might even uh notice the
fear that is often underneath doubt and then we can work with that
maybe recognize that and maybe even just name it and can we feel the fear in a
way that's supportive not in a way that's going to tip us over into overwhelm but like oh yeah there's this
uh feeling that if I stay with this practice I'm going to lose my important
relationships or I'm not going to be as productive at work because I'm going to spend time uh
meditating or I'm going to lose my Competitive Edge or whatever it might be whatever it might be
so recognize it and sometimes that might be enough to is there a way that we can
allow the experience to be there yep there's a lot of hesitation
here and one way we can allow it to be there is to feel it in the
body is to One Way feeling in the body is to get out of the abstract thinking
and the philosophizing and the trying to figure it out to find the right answer which you know we could just spend you
know or we could spend our whole life doing that but to kind of like uh interrupt the momentum of that kind of
thinking and figuring out and trying to get the perfect practice or the perfect answer feel in the body the bodily
experience of restlessness or uncomfortableness or this feeling of
trying to figure things out which often is associated with maybe with a confusion like I don't know I got to
figure it out and how does that feel I notic when I said that I like leaned forward a
little bit to my body there's a way there's a I got to get it I got to go find the answer it's not here it's
elsewhere so there can be this uneasiness or a sense of heaviness
or this way in which um yeah not there's maybe not a sense of
uprightness but instead there's a a tension and a sense of uh pushing
maybe so one way to allow the experience to be there is to feel it in the
body and the second is to remember that thoughts are just
thoughts and what are thoughts they are in substantial
ephemeral they're just coming and going and coming and going
the same way we imagine pink elephants is the same way
we imagine a better practice it's the same activity right it's completely uh
in the mind imagined and sometimes that can be helpful to say like okay it's just
thoughts don't worry you'll have another thought another second from now so that's two ways we can allow the
experience to be there is feel it in the body and kind of like pull the rug out out from under the authority of thoughts
thoughts are just thoughts we don't have to believe them we don't have to let
them push us around and I talked a little bit about thoughts uh I guess it was three weeks ago a little bit I did a
whole day a whole evening on thoughts and the third thing that we can
do to work with doubt is to we might call this an antidote you know like to apply an antidote to um undermine the
doubt and one is to
investigate the opposite of Doubt is actually investigation because doubt is this way
we're like disconnected and we're not sure but if you're not sure
you can lean in kind of like roll up your sleeves and like well what is it exactly that I have doubt about is it
the teachings is it the teacher is it myself and just you know have this uh
have some bring some curiosity to it bring some curiosity like what is this
doubt about and sometimes that can help instead of this vague think like yeah
I'm not sure like what what is it that you're not sure about what are excuse me what are you
sure about do you are there some things you do have confidence in maybe you've seen some of the benefits of meditation
practice or benefits of loving kindness practice whatever it might be yeah so one way to an antidote is to
just investigate some people will say faith is an antidote to doubt I would
say if you have faith that's fantastic you can use that as an antidote to doubt
but for a lot of people that's not so easy just to like oh I'll just to have faith maybe some people have devotional
practices chanting bowing these types of things that can be
a fantastic antidote as well but uh investigation is a antidote as
well maybe I'll say a little bit more about uh investigation because you can also investigate just
inquire directly is this doubt you can just ask let's kind of like Drop in that
question and then maybe the one way to answer that is to say is said was there
like an uncomfortable experience that uh started this Cascade sometimes doubt gets fueled by a
little bit of uncomfortableness and then there's this disengagement and then the disengagement
justifies Itself by saying well I'm not sure this is such a good idea anyway and all these other things but not always
but it's often uh initiated within some uncomfortable
experience so that might be uh part of the investigation that we're
doing or maybe we could uh ask this drop in this question do we have this view do
we have this idea that things should be a certain way if this meditation practice were any
good I would be experiencing a b and c and I'm not experiencing a b and c therefore I'm not so sure about this
meditation practice there's these ways in which we bring beliefs and Views into our practice our expectations of course
we do and then sometimes when those expectations aren't met
then there starts to be doubt but maybe one way to work with doubt is to just investigate what are the expectations
what are the beliefs and the views that I've uh brought to this
practice and then also you know so drop in some of these questions and then we
have to be open to finding answers so sometimes that answers if we're in the
middle of meditation we're dropping in questions the answers will bubble up
maybe they won't but if we investigate and we discover yeah you know actually I do
have a specific question what's this business about rebirth I just don't get it or there's not supposed to be a self
but then who's getting reborn and then you know this is the usual question that comes up I don't have a good answer that
will satisfy any of you just just a heads up about that so be uh willing to find answers
maybe it's reading a book maybe it's uh talking to some other dma practitioners
maybe it's talking to a teacher maybe it's going on a retreat and uh having some extended meditation period this is
something that can help with doubt too to not only to
um uh determine what a question is but uh be willing to find some
answers and then maybe there's this way that uh with doubt again is being uh
experienced as this hesitation or asolution maybe we could uh investigate
this uh way we can settle back and open the question or ask the
question what is happening right now that I'm not open
to what is happening right now that I'm not open to sometimes
like as I said an uncomfortable experience can like initiate a sense of
doubt and then whether it uh maybe it's
not even an antidote to doubt maybe that's just more mindfulness practice
what am I not open to right then that just brings you right back into the present moment yeah well what is going
on that I'm not tuned into that I'm not uh that I'm trying to to avoid or I
don't really want to pay attention to and that's mindfulness practice so now maybe Doubt's still
there but it's no longer a
hindrance and then maybe the last thing that I'll say here is maybe it's kind of an antidote to that I spoke about a
little bit is to bring to mind what do I have confidence in with regards to this
practice what do you know that's been beneficial or what has been
uplifting maybe bring something that to mind maybe a memory as I said maybe some
devotional practices a way that kind of like opens the heart and relaxes the mind that
allows you to be with whatever is happening so then you're no longer
hindered you can be back into the practice so doubt often is masquerading as wisdom
it's telling you I don't know about this and it's uh can be something that
you know causes us to abandon the practice or to turn away from
it so it can it's a hindrance that actually can be quite powerful not only because it can cause us to turn away but
also because it's often not recognized or we might have this idea
okay yeah it is doubt but I'm supposed to have faith some people think that the faith is the antidote and for some
individuals faith can be an antidote but for others maybe investigation is an
antidote and we know that investigation is a factor of Awakening and there we are right in the practice
again so maybe with that I'll end with doubt and open it up and see if there's
some questions we don't have a lot of time I'm afraid but is there a question
about doubt that's somebody would like to ask do you have doubt about
doubt maybe you should doubt your doubt that's actually the way forward just doubt
more doubt the
doubt maybe in the back there
um my question funnily enough kind of like ties in with your doubt the doubt pun um how do you balance
between like questioning things as you're trying to
learn something new and like kind of have to ask certain questions to like
build upon an incomplete understanding um with like not wanting to ask too many
questions that you're just like always kind of afloat and like without grounding like like in saying doubt the
doubt like you do need some doubt but you also don't need some doubt so like how do you strike that balance yeah so
the question is is it getting in the way is it hindering so do you feel like okay
um I'm disengaged from the practice and I find myself hesitating and vacillating
then that's something maybe to work with but if you're feeling like you know I'm not sure but there's a certain
willingness to still lean into the practice or to do the practice then that's the that's that's the doubt
that's helpful and supportive for practice does that make sense yeah
yeah okay so thank you all for your attention and you're welcome to come up
here and ask me some questions if you like afterwards but I wish you wonderful rest of the evening thank
you and then maybe I'll say next week we'll be a different format we'll do the uh a sit and then a talk so we'll go
back to the other format thank you