yeah so welcome is anybody here for their first time ah nice welcome welcome
yay yeah you know IMC welcomes everybody
so yeah
yeah I um was anybody how many of you listen to Gils talk last
week yeah I I have been I mean it's kind of nice tradition he has of starting the
year with a formable truths and um I've been teaching on them and
other people have and I really liked what he offered and I'm going to kind of fold in some of what he shared to what
I'm going to offer and I'm going to but I'm going to start like who who here
doesn't know about the four noble truths is anybody here who not doesn't know what the four noble truths
are yeah okay great great so um then I'll put a little
context around before I get started um and uh let me say kind of
the one thing I want to do is kind of differentiate um what I'll call for the moment Noble
Dua from heedless Dua
Noble Dua from heedless Dua and I also want to talk about you know Duca and
well-being because they really come together or can so the four noble truths were are
said to be the first teaching of the Buddha and it's said um I have a I'll
come to it later but there's a a sua quote where sarauta who's one of the um
main teachers uh students of the Buddha and the teacher a teacher of the
Dharma compared the for Noble Truths um to an elephant um
footprint and he says just like any animal in the whole Kingdom's footprint
can fit inside of the elephant's footprint so too can all of the
teachings of the Buddha fit inside the for noal truths so it's a very uh significant
teaching and essentially um the way it's traditionally taught is there is
suffering which I'll talk about what that is how to interpret that there's the cause of the suffering there's the
end of suffering and then there's the way to end all suffering and um so I like to pair the
first and second truth and the third and for so maybe call them two noble
truths and the first two are really about um the direction of um UNH
wholesomeness and un you know sort of not doing well and so the Dua and which
can be translated as Gil likes to translate it as pain and I'm going to
incorporate that into my talk today but it can be thought of as super subtle
disase I think the volume needs to go down just a teeny bit more um irritation
to Total distress so this huge range volume still
okay okay a little louder again wasn't quite yeah it needs to go up a little
bit it's really hard balance sorry yeah okay so
um just this huge variation so let's just say that that you know just like pain can be maybe super mild just this
little rough patch on your skin you feel is a little bit sensitive to the cold or
something um to you know your leg is broken to
worse um so Dua and the cause of Dua and
uh the word in poly for Dua I mean for um the cause is tanha which is
classically translated as craving and today what I want to talk about it as um is resistance and
compulsion resistance and
compulsion so this resistance and compulsion
cause pain that's pretty relatable right is that relatable for you guys to you
understand that sort of like when we resist things things it can even slightly just think about that just the
subtlest resistance oh I don't want that just a subtlest
pain and the compulsion has just when we feel compelled there's a a discomfort to
that to extreme discomfort so these two um kind of can move us if
we are heedless and unmindful toward more and more difficulty the second
truth or the third and the fourth truths are the end of suffering and it's what
leads us to the end of suffering and that is the Noble eight-fold
Path this is the teachings of the Buddha um that guide us in how to engage with
our life and our practice
so Noble Dua and heedless Dua unheeded
Dua and well-being and so maybe I'll take a minute to talk a little bit about
well-being and maybe two kinds of well-being I'll say that um there can be
hedonic well-being and honic is a term that is used to describe sort of like
the the treadmill of life where we're always trying to get and do and feel better sort of like me trying to get the
sound just right you know there's this like trying to adjust and you know kind
of always moving towards sort of trying to get things right and um do things
like you know go to the spa and do all this extra extra stuff to make ourselves feel good and um and so you know it can
be really helpful actually and but when it's heedless it it just leads back to
Dua um and then there's udic well-being honic is kind of a well-being
that's the result of what the Buddha really talked about in terms of happiness is things like um the Bliss of
blamelessness it comes from showing up for others and ourselves in a way that
um we feel is blameless it's not dropping our garbage
on the ground and instead putting it in a trash can and you know being able to walk by other garbage and go like yes I
didn't do that you know in a simple way it's uh
you know ethical action it's wise action the result of those
things I'll talk a little more about that too but I kind of want to give you these this idea because when I start to
talk about Dua if all you have in your mind is something that's very very unpleasant
and not helpful and something you don't want you might not hear my words the same way I'm hoping that you will so
there is Noble Dua duka that leads toward well-being
actually so
um I have learned to listen to Dua
and I have learned that I often feel very happy when I recognize
Dua and when I see Dua I know that there's I'm seeing it so there's an
opportunity to suffer
less when I don't listen to my Dua I'm not heeding my
Dua it can become heedless Dua and that can be where we're trying
to do things to make ourselves feel better but we just keep making it worse and worse or the we we're ignoring the
suffering and it just grows and grows because we're ignoring the problem like
the pain we're ignoring the pain and and the cause of the pain gets worse and
worse cuz we're not listening
so Dua if we're listening to Dua it can Inspire us to move toward honic pleasure
it can Inspire us to move toward getting a piece of cake or shopping or something
like that that is using sense Pleasures to try and make us feel
better and that's not really the kind of um well-being or the usefulness of the
the that of Duca that would be maybe considered
Noble there can be noticing Dua and turning inward instead of
outward and meeting that Duca with uh intimacy and
curiosity with like this deep faith and understanding that
it's there with a message it's there inviting us to notice how we're
causing pain how we're engaging with our life in a way that's causing
pain I think that one of the things it's a little bit hard to to think about when
I'm trying to differentiate these two kinds of well-being is that um it's much easier
for the mind to focus on something than nothing so if you look around this room
right now try and find empty space a space where there's not
inhabited and I'm going to have you pause and try and keep your mind on that
space for several seconds so just see what
happens if you try and just like look at emptiness nothingness what happens in your
mind did anyone notice that it's hard to keep your attention focused in that
space for me I could feel the there's like a tug you know I just I want to look
around I want to find something more solid to look at and um so I think that it's easier
and more compelling for us to try and look for something to help us feel
better than it is to practice letting go and renouncing or you know turning
inward that make sense
okay so pain so if we think about um pain is
caused physical pain is caused by injury right some kind of
injury and so maybe we think about you know
resistance and um compulsion as causing
injury and as I was thinking about this my mind thought about the term moral injury has anybody heard that
term it came up a lot in the pandemic because of doctors and healthc
Care profess professionals working in hospitals with people dying of covid who were refusing vaccinations and denying
that they had covid and um and and it can happen in Sim similar
ways where you know
you're well the here's a definition moral injury is the Damage Done to one's
conscience or moral compass when that person perpetrates
Witnesses so this was an example of witnessing or fails to prevent Act acts
that transgress one's own's moral beliefs values or ethical codes of
conduct and this is actually to me a kind of a definition of what the Buddha
was teaching and I connect this with Dua
that we experience that kind of pain when we you know when there's Damage Done to
our conscious when our awareness what's our Clarity what our moral values
are
so here's a thought question what would happen if we
didn't have Dua What would life be like if Dua
didn't exist
when I was asking myself that question it occurred to me there are people who don't feel pain there is a syndrome
medical syndrome called congenital intens insensitivity to pain or
CIP so I looked it up a little bit and the article starts by saying
pain is the body's way of telling us to be
careful but there's some who get their entire life without feeling
it wow right wow and it goes on to say people with
CIP would love to know what pain means and what it feels like to be in
pain and and then it says people C A say people assume that feeling no pain is
this incredible thing and that it almost makes you super human
but with for people with CIP it's exact opposite exact
opposite we would love to know what pain means and what it feels like to be in pain without it your life is full of
challenges so we think that often when people are talking we think that our life is you know when we have Dua that's
the problem but maybe it'd be a lot worse if we didn't have Dua
I feel pretty sure it would be so to me I I really do want to
inspire you to have a different relationship with Uka by saying this kind of thing to kind
of Imagine can you appreciate can you come to appreciate Duca as a guide as a
messenger as something Noble
thinking about Dua like um a feed you know feedback
mechanism so some of you may have heard this example before but it kind of I like to use it for me it works really
well but I think about
um dooka a little bit like um rumble
strips you know what rumble strips are on the side of the highway they're
little divots in the cement and if you drive on them what
happens really noisy and it's a lot of
vibration and when you hit those what happens in your
body yeah tenses up reacts and then what might happen in
your mind fear anybody get angry
annoyed yeah yeah
upset so we can drive on the rumble strips we get startled it can bring up
fear and then we can have mental reaction right
and then we might um harp on ourselves for being so
careless I can see some nodding heads or and and then we might be
thinking to ourselves a little bit later that we should probably call calr and report a complaint about these rumble
strips because you know there it's really there could be a better
way there could be a better way maybe it could be soft jingly bells or you know something that is nice and
you know beautiful and helps us stay on the road instead of this terrible awful
feeling of these rumble strips so we can be planning what we're
going to say and craft this letter and contact the governor and do all this
stuff right and then or at some point we can finally kind of recognize that we
hit the rumble strips because we were driving off the road cuz we weren't paying
attention because we lost our mindfulness and then we can kind of go
oh and what would have happened if I had kept
driving and then there might be this sense of relief and appreciation and
even gratitude for the rumble strips and maybe this is what happens with
Dua maybe this is how we start to you know we react to the Dua but we can help
ourselves we can walk through this and come back to this place of being oh my gosh I'm so
grateful I'm so grateful that my finger hurt so I didn't keep cutting with a
knife I'm so grateful I'm listening to this Dua so I'm not continuing to cause
harm to myself or
others
I'm uh deciding what to share
next so um Gil has a quote I'll
read in Buddhist shorthand addictions compulsions obsessions and attachments
are referred to as clinging and craving tanha when the contraction of clinging
is pervasive it leads to stress which makes us vulnerable to such human instincts as fear aggression and
greed when these qualities are activated it can be easy to behave in ways that further harm ourselves or
others Buddhism emphasizes that craving is a condition for further craving and
that intentions to harm tend to motivate more of the
same so kind of pairing this harm this idea of injury and harm and how when we
don't listen to the dukka those other Energies
grow so coming back to me when I I I
like these words resistance and compulsion I feel like they're relatable
I often feel my mind gets kind of lost when I hear the word clinging or
craving so I like this and I encourage you to find your own liking words you
know whatever works for you that helps you feel that direct connect with oh I know what this
means and if I'm resisting something if I recognize resistance oh what don't I
want what don't I want what do I think should be different than the way it is and then I can kind of get in there and
figure out what it is I'm clinging to which is an idea a belief often or a
wish right and compulsion you know
this feeling of I want I want I want or
push um push and pull at the same time maybe
even it's um really can be quite tantalizing because there's this sense
that if I just get myself what I'm wanting it'll go
away I'll feel better and this is where we get into the honic well-being that I mentioned
earlier oh if I just go get this if I just give myself that I'll be
relieved but generally it's uh it's you know we're being
Bamboozled because you know it doesn't last very
long you know how often do you reach for something because it just sounds good and then you find yourself reaching
again and again and again and again for the same thing just another hunger and another
hunger and another
[Applause] hunger so just to say a couple of words about working with this the the
resistance or the compulsion I got a lovely uh email from
s utan this morning he has a daily daily mindfulness email that goes out that's
short and it was sort of the perfect little quote for today um and uh so just to to name
number one that when we're struggling with resistance and compulsion he says
if desire or aversion are overwhelming awareness needs to be built
up first before tackling them directly in this case it is better to
use a neutral object to build continuity of awareness for as long as it takes so he might mean
you know breath or walking or knitting
could be something that we're paying attention to and feeling as we
do and we do it for as long as we need to for as long as it takes to build up
our capacity to be present stay
aware he said we don't have to deal with anything in the mind until awareness and
wisdom are ready so it's kind of a nice to keep it
simple right and to take care of ourselves to get the quality of the Mind in the place so that we can relate to
the dukka as Noble Dua and not be heedless with it
as we as we start to relate to the duka as Noble we will grow trust and faith
confidence we will start to feel um that joy and well-being that
comes up when we recognize the presence of that pain of
duka and as we do that something inside of our our El inside of me grows wiser I
can feel it shifting and growing and it's like almost like
something inside starts to trust have more trust trust even in in me whatever me
is and then there's more relaxing and more ease more earned
confidence
I'll say just um there's a poem by Rosemary traumer you know on dealing with what
she calls it oh the longing because that compulsion right and the
resistance and how do we deal with this how do we deal with this and um how do
we Let It Be she says let longing be
longing though it rises in me with incessant hunger though it clutches for my heart with outstretched hands pins me
with pleading eyes let longing be longing never has it worked to pretend I
don't hear it as it shouts and demands or charms me with its silken
promises in a vision I said no to the longing and the longing only grew
but when I said yes longing I see you she says some other sweet words but
essentially the longing just becomes longing and I am a woman who sometimes
Longs for what she cannot
have so this is all about kind of getting into that right relationship
with dukka so that it can be Noble for us
and um there's you know the Noble eful Path
is a path right and duka lets us know when we're on that path like the rumble
strips lets us know when we're on the road and going off the
road and here's another Gill quote the ancient Buddhist metaphor of a
path draws on the idea of a cleared passageway that allows one to move
through an otherwise impassible Forest just as a person brings their
entire body along when walking on a forest path a spiritual spiritual
practitioner enters the Buddha path by engaging all aspects of who they
are yet while this physical path exists whether we walk on it or not in the
story the Buddhist path exists only in our engagement with
it so Dua only becomes Noble when we engage with it the path only becomes
available to us when we engage with it he says we create the path with the
activities of our minds hearts and
bodies so there's this great really really great book I really liked it read
it several times this last year it's called um the lion trackers guide to living by Boyd
varti and it's uh he grew up in South Africa and his family ended up creating
a a reserve and they take people on tours to track animals but they don't
kill the animals it's a long story but
um of a lot of different things but essentially he really talks about becoming a
Tracker so I have this idea of becoming Noble du
trackers one of the lines that he says that I really like is I don't know where I'm going but I definitely know how to
get there I love that I love
that and last week Gil gave this talk right on the for formable truths on the
three levels of heart body heart mind and belly
and so I like to call listening to the full range of Dua as a tracking
exercise and so we have to start by becoming aware of when Dua is present
right and it requires us wanting to recognize Dua wanting to track it
wanting to learn about it so from the book I'm going to read
you some some
excerpts and this first excerpt for me is about the level of Dua on the Mind
level that Gil was talking about and so he says tracking is very
much like learning a foreign language single tracks are words you might see a few as you walk
the trail and they create a jerky first phrase if you stop speaking and don't
practice practice the learning recedes while the more you do it the more natural and fluid it
becomes so for me in the beginning when we're trying to track Dua it's it's a
little awkward it's not a language we're used to to speaking we're going to our mind's going
to shift around between seeing you know Dua as a friend and sometimes as a
foe but the more you do it the more natural and fluid it becomes
and he goes on to say one afternoon the short phrases became flowing sentences I was out alone he's tracking
as Alex one of his mates had some other work to do back at the camp I came
across the tracks of a large Rhino bow that had wallowed in a water hole his
body caked with a thick black mud the track away from the water hole was fairly easy to follow because as the
Rhino walked through the thick bush bush a slick of mud had scraped off on the
trees and bushes his body was Dripping with it a Hansel and gredle trail that I
could easily follow from Bush to mudded Bush so often with Dua when we first
connect with it it's pretty easy to see over time maybe it gets more subtle
and that's when we start to move to the level of the heart so he says after a few miles of
tracking this I knew the mud on his body had begun to dry and the dripping Trail became more and more faint and then
there was no more mud my eyes seamlessly shifted from the mud to the three Road
Clover tracks he had left three toed and suddenly the iterations of the track
that my brain had stored as search images began to pop I saw the track with
ease I noticed compressions scuff marks smooth bark where his Thro ton Bonnie
had brushed against a tree I saw the grass laid flat in the imprint of a side toe the half moon of a front toe I was
moving on his track fast and fluent the easy Trail had helped me to get out of my own head so I could relax into
myself so moving into like a more relaxed relationship with
Dua where our heart can start to resonate with what's going on we don't feel contract Ed and pulled
back we develop trust the faith right that the duk is Noble if we
relate to it in the right way our heart starts to
trust and then we move into level three the belly the level of the
belly so he goes on to describe it was easy and natural that I had the feeling
that I had gained entry into an entirely new dimension I could anticipate the subtle
shifts of this path picking up the faintest of tracks like they were elaborate
signs in the same way that after months of being an outsider on a French
exchange the language comes and you suddenly belong to France to the place
to the culture to the people suddenly I was part of the story of the
Bush no it is possible that engaging with the fornal truths can lead you into
a whole new dimension a whole new way of being in this
world you become the eful path in the words of the Buddha you become
free
I'm I feel moved by the my own Reflections on
freedom you just feel it in my body I'm at the belly level in the
moment
e I think I'll just try and summarize and end with a
poem and sort of emphasize that really what I'm talking about is our
relationship to and with our
experience that we can have a a noble relationship with life and our
experience or we can have in Noble relationship with our life and
experience and I find a huge part of creating a noble relationship with my
life and experience has to do with recognizing what I can and cannot
control because has so much of having a noble relationship with life means to
allow life to to allow what's happening to
happen and to see it and show up for it in a non-reactive way but with
responsibity and this is a hard thing in in in AA they have the Serenity
Prayer it goes like this God grant me the ability to accept the things I cannot change the courage to change the
things I can and the wisdom to know the
difference and there's a version of this that I like very much which is useful when one wants to
have compassion for others which is God grant me the ability to accept the
people I cannot change the courage to change the one I
can and the wisdom to know it's me
yeah so this is a noble relationship to
life and it requires allowing allowing life allowing
others and I hope you know that our already talked it's not that we're passively allowing right it's not that
we're not engaging with mindfulness it's necessary we need to be in Wise relationship Noble relationship to
what's happening but to do that we have to first acknowledge and allow what's
really going on not to be in conflict because then we're resisting it or we're compulsively
moving to try and change it so here's a poem by Dana Falls it's
called allow there is no controlling
life try corralling a lightning bolt containing a tornado Dam a stream and it
will create a new channel resist and the tide will sweep
you sweep you off your feet allow and Grace will carry you to Higher
Ground the only safety lies in letting it all
in the wild and the weak fear fantasies failures and
success when loss rips off the doors of the heart or sadness veils your vision
with despair practice becomes simply bearing
the truth practice becomes simply bearing
the truth and the choice to let go of your
known way of being and the choice to let go of your known way of being the whole world is
revealed to your new
eyes so there's a lot more I could say but I think that's a good place to end
and thank you and if anybody has questions cuz I let you confused or
disheartened please come and talk to me afterwards thank
you may we all become Noble Dua
trackers thank you