all right so let's get started
together today I would like to invite you to start with your eyes
open for the meditation and just take a moment to
orient to the space that you're in so you can look around just briefly
but we're not looking at any particular object it's just feeling the space that you're
[Music] in and have a sense generally that there is
space and then there are some things in it in the room including
you and just let the Mind feel into that
space and now I'll invite you to close your eyes and
begin to find the meditation
posture maybe there's still a vague sense of the space around you that you're sitting
[Music] in but you're also aware now of the
Inner Space and how the body feels from the
inside sense of whatever posture you're in perhaps you're sitting up
perhaps you're lying down perhaps even [Music]
standing so having a general sense of this
orientation you can notice that the space in the mind is somewhat like the space in the
room I'm tuning in more specifically to your
posture finding a balanced posture so sometimes I even Rock back
and forth slightly or forward and back just a little bit to really find that
Center Point that's
balanced and when the body is balanced in an upright posture it takes really
almost no muscular effort to be
upright or if you're lying down you can sense into the straightness of the
spine and I know there are variations for different bodies so we're doing this
within what works for our
body but finding balance ease
it can help to sense into the places where the body is in contact so the seat
against the chair or the cushion or the bench or the body against the
bed really being aware of that contact point and softening at that
place not not holding yourself rigidly against it or somehow holding yourself
up but just letting yourself be
supported you can seem detailed
to focus in that way but I've been amazed to find small
places in my mind where there was resistance
or holding or pushing just in the Physical
Realm softening the eyes in the eye
sockets releasing any tension in the jaw
throat letting the shoulder blades slide down
the back so the shoulders
drop the drop without rounding
forward softening down through the belly area
a place where we tend to hold
tension and then tuning into the arms and
legs and letting them be EAS
ful
balanced for today we'll be inviting an opening
to many different aspects of
experience so opening the mind to the
sound sound in the room sound of my voice just the world of sound including
that the outside sounds are coming in from that space that you oriented to
first space in the [Music]
womb and each thing that we include is something that just we allow
to come into the foreground and everything else to be more in the background so it's not that
we're adding on more and more and more and you have to pay attention to so many
different things just let each
thing come forward and have its moment so we're with the sounds
generally now opening to the s stions of the breath letting those come into the
foreground we're not eliminating sound but it just Fades a bit so that we can
sense the sensations of the
breath the breath is a series of simple Sensations
of touch of heat and
coolness there are internal Sensations as the lungs fill and
empty and then also Sensations on the surface usually the clothing shifting
against the
skin there can be an energetic sense throughout the body
so opening to the Kaleidoscope of Sensations that is the
breath
e and it can be quite natural to just open
to all Body Sensations the breath is some of the
Body Sensations there may be others so we less focus on the breath
itself and more on the totality of Body
Sensations wherever they are some are Pleasant some are
unpleasant we're just noticing how it is to be in our body at this
moment
e
[Music] the awareness to include also the
emotions feelings
present we let the body be more in the background but many emotions have a
bodily component but also a mental one
so we open what is there is there some feeling
of Joy or sadness
grief
ease appreciation
impatience
we just open gently to that [Music]
Realm as the mind gets broader we can begin
to imagine it like a giant Canvas OR
sky and these things that we're adding in are just more things that are
included in that space of
mind so including now the realm of
thoughts not thinking the thoughts and falling into them by noticing them as
movements in the
mind so the mind is getting very large and Broad it includes the sounds the
breath body emotions various thoughts coming and
going it helps very much to relax in order to
allow so much into
awareness I'm including even the more subtle movements of mind like
intentions background
attitudes and let all these things come to
you you don't need to go chasing them all [Music]
down and opening our heart to all of this all of the real of Human
Experience
providing the possibility of being with whatever
[Music] arises and letting whatever wants to pass away pass
away
I'm seeing if there's a possibility of finding a form of peace
that is possible in this broad room the way the sky is at peace no
matter what weather is passing
through and sometimes there isn't much weather it's all just quite [Music]
C
at any time if it feels right you can focus in on something that the Mind
wants to gather around as long as there's still awareness
there we don't force the mind to be in particular way at the intention is to try
experiencing this skylike
mind that can hold anything with
peace
e
and now gently bringing the body
a little bit more fully into the [Music]
foreground connecting or reconnecting with the sense of physical
presence the posture that the body is [Music] in the breath coming in going
out
sense of contact or pressure where you're sitting or lying
[Music]
down the awareness of the body as a an aspect of
mind we are embodied
that's what allows the hearing of sound opening to
sounds around you as well as my
voice considering the unification of Mind and Body In This
Moment
would it be possible to walk through the
world in this way being
open to any experience coming [Music]
in grounded in a physical
presence aware of emotions and thoughts as such able to engage with them when
needed but not
entangled it's a peaceful way of being
having this broad kind of mind that's also
flexible able to turn toward anything in the foreground or relax back like being the
sky and this is a way of being that can emerge through
meditation and it's a great gift to the
world sometimes the Buddha was called the
peaceful
Sage that's also sometimes applied to a person very deep on the path the sage at
peace may not be something that we literally embody very often but when we
touch into it and even in a small way through meditation we get a sense of the
possibility that we carry as humans everyone dies and that we can foster that through
our practice and it will be helpful in our relationships in our job
in our family and in our understanding and way of being in the
world
the great blessing of
peace
so this week we are considering four foundations on which
our practice can be based that are both simple and deep
things that we can do right away from any stage of the path and that will
carry us far on the path if we let them keep unfolding and
blossoming and today we are on the fourth of these which is to train for
peace and the word for peace here is Santi or Shanti in Sanskrit some of you
may have heard that word and this is the kind of peace that is associ assciated
with letting go and with Liberation so there's a lot of levels of
that of course and for today let's let's not
take this one incrementally at the beginning let's start right off with the kind of deep peace that can even
surprise us that really opens us which can occur
at times at any point along the path so we might call it utter
peace does this resonate in any way for
you it could happen in meditation can also happen in physical
or mental exertion can happen through a poem a painting a piece of music a walk in
nature there's suddenly a clear feeling of Peace inside and outside
and the sense of self drops away and one experiences no separation from the world
and all of its wonder and strangeness and there may even be a
sense of awe or reverence that such a peace could be possible for
humans and it gives us a new reference point in our practice of remembering wisdom of
opening to truth and learning to let go the other three things that we've talked about this
week A friend of mine who practices in the Tibetan tradition was drawn to go
visit the Quan Yin statue at the Nelson Atkins Museum in Kansas
City it's an amazing piece I've only seen pictures of it um but it's
strikingly beautiful and apparently quite large Onan is the bisa of compassion in
the Mahayana tradition and this friend of mine actually went and stood before this
amazing sculpture and he said his mind was just was stopped by its evocative power and
in fact he was moved to tears in that moment but surrounding all of that
emotional response was a deep sense of utter
peace so if you've experienced something like
this it's a landmark for you it doesn't mean that you're awakened necessarily
and certainly not that you're special compared to other people but it's worth letting such an
experience kind of seep into your heart and work in your heart over the
years so I wanted to point to that right away so that we have a
context sometimes these things can happen to us but with no context we can't integrate
them so now let's dial back to the more
ordinary experiences of peace that we tend to have we could have even every
day so every time we let go of greed or aversion or delusion there's an opening
to some kind of Peace in the wake of letting go and this release we can learn to
recognize that that release itself is what includes the Peace So as an example
Gil tells a story of becoming realizing that he was getting um kind of agitated
around getting his kids off to school in the morning that was his task for a while in the household and you know he
there was always kind of a rush he couldn't get them to get their jackets and shoes on and get to the car without
getting distracted along the way um and he realized that
um you know he his children weren't responsible for that he was the one feeling agitated and he thought what is
going on that I keep getting agitated doing this and eventually he realized
that what he was doing in the mornings was lingering over the paper he wanted
to read the paper he got interested in it and he wanted to read it more fully than there was really time for in in the
task of have dealing with the kids also so once he saw that what was really
underpinning his agitation was or wanting to be with the paper at that
moment he decided consciously to let go of that you know I'll read that later and um with that he felt more at
ease and it was the wanting that was the issue it wasn't that the kids weren't doing it right or something so often
it's like this we can identify somewhere underneath our agitation what is it that
I'm wanting and holding on to or not wanting and pushing away or what is it that I'm not seeing clearly and the
release of that will suddenly make the situation much easier I sometimes use the phrase if I'm
struggling what would I have to let go of at this moment to be more
easeful what would I have to let go of to make this easier and often it's something simple
something that I hadn't seen or sometimes it takes longer to unfold what's really going on there but
it's a nice practice question so we can ask them you know how
do we get there with this uh instruction to train for peace the forth of the foundations to
train for peace what is that training so largely the training is to
use the qualities of the goal as the path that is kind of a skillful
imitation if you will essentially it says if you want peace be
peaceful similarly more specific things if you want to be a more generous person
then start being generous so what would I have to let go
of to make this easier what sort of how can I bring
peace to this very moment so we can you know for the
specifics we can look to one of the sutas somebody once asked the Buddha about what a peaceful person is like and
it's worth hearing his response it's kind of long um but I hope you'll allow
me to read the whole thing or at least most of it I I slightly
excerpted so the person's question is how does one see how does one
behave the one who is said to be peaceful they ask the Buddha that's a
nice question how does one see how does one behave the one who is said to be
peaceful so the Buddha says devoid of craving before death not
dependent on the past not to be reckoned by the middle for him there are no
preferences she is Without Anger unafraid not
boastful not regretful speaking with reflection not
Restless one is truly a contemplative controlled in
speech one is without attachment to the Future one does not sorrow over the
past one sees seclusion in the midst of sense contacts and is not LED astray
among views withdrawn not scheming without longing
not miserly courteous not morally repulsive not
intent on slander not swept up by enjoyment and
not swollen with arrogance gentle gifted with
Ingenuity not credulous not growing
dispassionate he does not train from a desire for gain nor is he irritated over
a lack of gain not hostile because of craving does not hanker after tasty
food equanimous ever mindful in the world she does not
conceive herself to be equal Superior or inferior for her there are no
[Music] swellings they have no dependencies having known the dham they
are independent no craving is found in them for existence or
non-existence I call them peaceful who is indifferent to sense Pleasures in
them no knots are found they have crossed over
attachment in her there is nothing to be found as either taken up or
rejected one who takes nothing in the world as one's own and who does not sorrow over what is
absent and is uninvolved in doctrines that one is truly said to be
peaceful so just let those words settle in your mind it's too many to remember
them all so see what is still echoing for you maybe just one word or phrase
felt it
meaningful one overall comment is that many of the
items named are things that the peaceful person is not right there was a lot of not in
there not this not that mostly were becoming free of various
things the suta where the Buddha names the four foundations that we've been talking about this week he says that the
Supreme peace is the Pacific ation of greed hatred and delusion we are
pacifying the forces in our mind and heart that contribute to suffering that's what peace is this path is the
ultimate peace movement pacifying greed hatred and
delusion despite all these words there isn't actually much to say about
peace as noted it's mostly an absence It's always important to notice absences
notice the releases notice the endings notice the letting go that we talked
about yesterday do we notice that often we rush on to the next thing that's
present the next thing that's arising the next thing on our to-do list that's just
habitual so linger with the Letting Go linger with the space that's there when
something ends linger with the feeling of release which is the
Peace So peace is available now in some measure in some
way and notice that and make it your training to encourage peace wherever it
appears this is how we train for Peace So the growth of Peace in one's
life I would say depends on valuing it on really wanting to protect it wanting
to preserve it wanting to feel into it that's a kind of wanting that's
skillful so it's interesting to check in our mind
you know what are the forces that don't value peace and why am I investing in
those mostly out of habit and is there a part that really does value peace and is willing to to
enact that and embody that and that's the training that's how
we train for peace we become peaceful by being
peaceful whenever we can
so not neglecting wisdom preserving truth cultivating
relinquishment and training for peace the four
foundations that we can start right now at any level and if we keep unfolding
them they will go very far maybe all the way to
Liberation tomorrow we'll step back and we'll at the bigger picture around these
and I'll tell you the story that goes in the Su up with these also so have a
peaceful day take care