um yeah good to be with you good to uh come back and practice kind of um you
know just the rhythms of a weekly thing just okay check in with our heart now
how is it to be alive now
so friend of mine Dharma friend fellow teacher
um said something like um she's very direct with me and she's always right so
she can kind of say whatever but she said
uh some people like the in breath some people like the out
breath you like the in breath like okay what does that mean I
thought I like the out breath I thought I like relaxation I thought I like Tranquility I thought I liked non
vigilance but she said no no there's
some int you like the intensity you know
and um there's some part of you that's very ambivalent about actually relaxing
at a deep level kind of took that in
okay maybe so what's maturity in
practice I think it's coming to love the in breath and the out
breath the kind of vitalizing energy intensity of the in
breath and the soothing surrender ease
of the out breath no control and we maybe all have a a pred
ction you know um where we're more comfortable
perhaps but some of what we're doing is uh learning
to um to Revel in the in breath and revel in the out breath to Revel in
alertness to Revel in surrender and tranquility and we can do that I think
at um at Great depth you know I do kind of know how to relax I do talk about
surrender right but we're always beckoned to let go more deeply to wake
up more brightly so let's um let's find our way
uh between this uh enlivening and soothing rhythms of uh
our body breathing
so finding your uh your posture just
uh getting cozy
getting
bright
e e
we breathe
in kind of Rush of energy into body and mind
sense of brightness and not wanting to to miss our lives it's possible
actually very possible to miss our lives
the in breath helps break the [Music]
monotony the Assumption of
permanence brings a certain kind of poignancy into our lives e
but the in breath must uh end
sometime sense the tension of having
a used the o
oygen and then uh soothing the Opera
it's almost like breathing out the
vigilance and the fear in the sense that it's
irresponsible to neglect our worry
concern Breathe It Out
e e
all the subtle ways we try to grab hold of
Life of this
moment all the subtle impulses towards
ownership we breathe out
e
e e
the cycle of breath the in breath
the perfect complement to the out
breath out breath a compliment to the in breath
Moment by
moment
Clarity release
brightness and darkness
e
e e
letting the out breath wash away the impulse of uh becoming bat
tanha copying and pasting our being into the next
moment just a little
better we breathe
out the softening and becoming
the in
breath we shake off the notion that
uh this moments just a dress rehearsal for the rest of our life
sense uh the the
vividness The Human
Condition
e
e e
can feel like when we're meditating some our life is elsewhere our real
life lies in the other 23 hours of the
day but it will only ever be in breath and out
breath thought and
feeling seeing and hearing
in this sense uh this is our
life
e
e e
okay it's good to uh to sit with
you um so in meditation practice
we sometimes talk about the the aperture of
attention uh if we think about um think about uh attention as a
spotlight you know the question would be how wide is that Spotlight and focusing on our breathing
at the tip of the nose say is a narrow aperture right whereas doing open to all six sense
Gates doing choiceless awareness that's uh large large
aperture and um with um with our with the pupil if our eyes brains working
okay you know when there's a lot of light the pupil contracts when you enter a dark room pupil
dilates right and there's no rule for when to meditatively to adjust the
aperture no algorithm for exactly how to do that but
generally excuse me generally in the process of settling in settling into Tranquility
Clarity um we make the aperture small you know and it's like the rest of
the world of experience is is too much it's too much light too much light it's
too sticky too open to it is to be pulled
under and the changing and uncertainty is um is
intense and so we need a kind of smaller pasture we need to perceive to
see less and the risk of going too wide to
early is that the line dividing awareness and thinking can get
quite fuzzy and so when we start um a retreat
or or even just starting starting a Sit sitting um on one's own or in a group we
often begin with a kind of with the breathing or with some kind of um
limited narrow aperture and then when there's some
stability when phenomena are a little less
intoxicating maybe we open wider and
so there's this sense of uh of of space
expanding Contracting and it's not a hierarchy you
know of this is the beginners phase and this is the advance it's not like
that as we cultivate our uh our practice we we find we can
move easily between the kind of comfortable
secluded home of the narrow to the
open homeless centerless of uh of
awareness and um this Dynamic this kind of
like what's why's attention now in my practice um
that uh that same Dynamic it strikes me that our life our life in the broader
sense not just meditation functions a little bit like
that what's the kind of aperture for the rest of our our
day we open and we uh we close you know
we're um in in the world and we Retreat we
love and we rest and what's the the kind of rhythm
of um the small and vast aperture in our
lives to what ought we attend where do we draw the line around the kind of
focus space in this moment or on this day right we draw the line around tip of
our nose maybe in one sit or around the body in a Sit well around
what are we drawing that um that line on
this day and I think typically we Buddhist types
have the assumption that our life its scope of concern needs to be expansive feels like contraction is just
self-absorption the small aperture to cannot pay attention in a sense to
samsara that's that's a species of self-absorption
and um and we have the sense that maybe when we're grinding or there's something
some internal friction we're struggling in some way we tend to get small and I
think that's true that suffering is inherently absorbing um and then we have the sense of like
okay we feel better we open the aperture the big aperture we tend to
think is compassion caring for others for the world for
society I get that fair enough fair enough but I think we want to be careful
in concluding that the contractive energy is bad and the expansive energy
is good the question is much more like what is skillful what is
skillful we do grow over time so that the our life the self system it absorbs
less energy it absorbs less energy and it's natural for us to turn outwards you
know when the when the the self is not such a preoccupation the project of our life is
not such a preoccupation The Gaze naturally turns
outwards but um everyone sometimes needs to get small
and that's actually not a sign of cowardice but
Health to simplify the rhythms of our life and to focus
what's right here just this book or this
nap or this person or this whatever this TV show and so that the sense of like oh
it's a sin to get small to take our gaze off of some
Sor I don't know right just like it's not meditation
detention to go back to the breathing the Buddha went back to it
very often right and some times it's um it's
very skillful to be small when the alternative of open
awareness is overwhelm and confusion it's skillful to get small
when any attempt to open runs into a kind of debilitating
helplessness and um and it feels like okay you should be able to do something but
you just can't see how that's not like a productive way of suffering it's not an
efficient way of spending your
love right marinating in certain cyclical forms of
pain is not onward leading narrow the aperture back to the breath
metaphorically and so I um I say this in in part
because you know I um I want to be careful you know like how much of the
ignorance coursing through the country's veins gets into my
bloodstream and I only want to take that into my bloodstream if it will help
others and I fear that much of the time it does
not uh and so in in
2016 without knowing it I was sort of like trying to do Tong Len at the
national level that was not an explicit thing and I don't even know how to practice Tong Len really I a year
practicing in tibetan tradition when I first started practice I don't know the
practice but the the sense of like breathing in the pain breathing out
love I was trying to do it and failing
mostly failing not only failing but mostly
failing and it was like okay narrow the
app
now there are other times when perhaps counterintuitive when meeting one's own
distress or smallness actually requires that we get much much
bigger right it's like I I think of that example sometimes people early in
recovery from addiction are given the instruction like go Ser care as out of your
mind you know heal yourself through giving
right and so sometimes we address our our depletion through love through
getting bigger right and the aperture actually needs to expand
radically but we want to look look for the ways to uh to spend spend one's love
wisely now nothing I'm saying about
um the contractive side of practice of just pulling the energy in is about
passivity or resignation it's not that I'll be in the
streets you know like I was but um we want to be careful with
our mind you know and um we we want to be uh respectful of the
limits of our equinity and the ways in which we subtly
devolve into a certain kind of marinating in pain rather than holding
it in Awareness metabolizing it and that line gets fuzzy gets fuzzy
sometimes so we're careful
careful small aperture wide contraction dilation rest and love and
service we look you know what's wise attention now
what's appropriate attention now given the state of my heart given what's needed given my
energy given my stability what's why's attention
now offer this for your consideration and uh we'll keep going
I'll be here uh next week is holiday week for some but I I'll be
uh I'll be traveling but I'll be uh I'll be online next week with you all if you
wish to join and um yeah I wish you all a good uh
week of of practice and all the rest okay