good morning good morning YouTube SAA International IMC meditators really
lovely to see you today well see your chats anyway happy to be with you it's a real
privilege to be here this week I enjoy this sit so doing a
soundrack and there's a couple minutes delay so I'm going to be waiting for some of you
respond really great to see all the chats coming
in okay great thank you folks glad that you can hear
me nice to see some familiar names either from inperson interactions or
having been part of this community over the last several years so a warm welcome
warm welcome to you this day whatever time it is for you and delighted to be here with you
I'm about to start the recording here we
go so the invitation is this morning to settle
into meditation I'll do a very short review um just the context of this week
I'm covering essential elements or core elements of mindfulness that kind of
aren't part of the normal IMC intro to mindfulness series Gil has been doing
over the last number of weeks and this week that's been on Vena or feeling
tone attitudes of mind on Tuesday and Wednesday and today I'll be talking
about the capacity our minds have for directed attention
so with that the invitation is to settle into a posture that's a good balance of
relaxation and alertness whatever that means for
you it can be helpful if you're sitting or lying down to have your head aligned with your
spine balanced over your shoulders front and back and side to side
and check and make sure that you're balanced left and right over your hip
points sometimes people like to sway a little bit forward and back side to
side and just check in make sure you're
grounded then taking a couple of longer slower deeper
breaths as an invitation to come into your body touch into your
embodiment releasing any excess tension on the out
breath and then allowing allowing the breathing to return to
normal if you haven't already softening the eyes or closing
them and as we've done this week scanning through very briefly scanning
through your body noticing any feelings of pleasant or
unpleasant and just acknowledging them no need to hang out
there but just feeling any tension or
relaxation any other kinds of pleasant or unpleasant that want to reveal
themselves
and then more globally perhaps just checking in how am I
today what's the overall [Music]
mood so we've been talking about the frame of mind or attitude today starting
this meditation and allowing acknowledging whatever that
is with as much kindness graciousness as
possible and then settling in settling into whatever object of
attention makes most sense for your mind heart body this
morning I'll give instructions on the breath today and the invitation is if the
breath doesn't work for you whatever reason to adapt those
instructions to a more Global sense of Your Body Sensations or to
hearing so again tuning into your
body noticing any sense of motion or
Stillness especially ATT
tuning to the motion sensations of your life's
breath noticing any soothing or
pleasurable sensations of the
breath and acknowledging if the breath isn't that way right now it's just
neutral neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant allowing any kind of sensation of breathing to be
okay
resting on the rhythmic in and out of your body
breathing tuning in to wherever the breath feels most noticeable obvious for
you perhaps H the chest the subtle up and down or the
nostrils the difference between the exhale and the
inhale or what for many people most relaxing
the gentle rise and fall wave like motion of breathing in the belly
diaphragmatic
breathing noticing the subtle differences between the beginning of the
inhale the middle of the inhale and the top the
fullness of the inhale and then noticing tuning into
that moment the exhale
begins allowing the exhale perhaps to be a
little bit longer noticing the middle of the
exhale and perhaps that tiny pause at the end of the exhale resting in
that allowing the breathing to be
natural becoming a dedicated
Observer companion with all of the tiny
Sensations in each
breath
de father sounds
Sensations arisings pull the attention from the
breath or your primary object of focus
the invitation is to gently acknowledge whatever has
arisen be with it for as long as it's
predominant as an
event and then unpossible
returning to the primary attention on the o object of
breathing this
breath each breath like no
other what's this breath like
in the final moments of this meditation the invitation is to
open open the lens the scope of the mindful
awareness to include everything everything arising In This
Moment noticing in
particular overall sense mood
what's the overall feeling
tone and resting with that acknowledging any
moment in this meditation that we're challenging with as much kindness
and graciousness as [Music] possible and soaking
in steeping in any moments of Peace
subtleness mindfulness and in your own good
intentions coming to this period of
practice and from that place turning your internal gaze
outwards to all the others this life
touches known and unknown seen and unseen close and
distant and wishing them well perhaps making the determination
that in some way small or large our practice here together can
benefit them as
well and all beings everywhere be safe peaceful and
free thank you for the sincerity of your
practice
oh good morning again everyone warm welcome wherever and whenever you
are and um I'm feeling so settled I almost don't
want to talk but um I'll talk I promise to talk so here I
am this um this week this context for this week is that it's a series on kind
of essential elements of mindfulness that support the growth of our practice and
even the beginning of our practice and I'll do a quick review
later but I'm for now I just want to jump into today's topic which is directed
attention so rather than talk about what directed attention is we'll start with a
brief exercise so Focus your attention on one of your [Music]
hand not the image or the concept of your hand but the felt experience of it
from the inside out tingling pulsing warmth or
cool aliveness and allow your awareness to
fill your hand perhaps the way water fills a
[Music] sponge
now shift your attention to your
foot same way inside out how hard was
that really easy right so the capacity of placing our attention
in a certain area of the body or even other aspects of our
experience that's directed attention sometimes a metaphor can be
used like looking through a people or looking through a telescope versus looking out an open
door or an open window in reality though directed
attention in meditation or in life is less like looking through a small
cylindrical object and more it's a form of selective attention which we as
humans simply have most of us if we have our correct neurology and everything's
working okay so an example here if you are in a
crowded Plaza and looking for a friend and you find your good friend
and she or he is a long way away so you start walking towards them you aren't totally unaware that
there are other people around or other objects around but the bulk of your attention is on tracking where that
person is so that you can arrive to be with them that is the kind of directed
attention that helps many people settle in to meditation we're putting the bulk
of our attention on one thing and allowing other things to kind of be in the periphery
right it's a kind of filtering process filtering of less Salient information
and it's a natural and necessary part of human cognition
right so for the purposes of mindfulness meditation as I did this morning we
often use breathing as the object of attention
sometimes Body Sensations work better for some people or sound in meta meditation the object of
directed attention is the intention of meta perhaps the
phrases this directed attention is a powerful capacity it's essential for Learning for
Life and for meditation and as many of you have
already discovered it helps many people settle faster or or subtle at all in the
meditation process faster than just letting the mind kind of roam around and be and do whatever it wants which often
results in daydreaming fantasy checking up
so it can help coax our minds away from this wanting and not wanting this greed
and aversion that I've been talking about this week and eventually it can help
attenuate the those Tendencies to glom on to whatever we
like or don't like in a moment by repeatedly gently placing the
attention somewhere normal soothing perhaps
neutral-ish though that can shift as we've talked about another feature of directed
attention that's helpful to know about that's not as often talk talked about is
that sometimes directed attention that filtering can allow other things that
come up to shape experience without you noticing
so that's why it can be helpful to start or occasionally check in about whatever
else is present so you may remember at the beginning of the
meditation I as many meditation teachers do encourage you to just check out
whatever the mood General frame of mind was before directing your attention to the
breathing this is to acknowledge anything else that might be coming along with our attention into our
experience it's really um possible for these other dimensions of experience to
kind of slip in and get cultivated along with stability of mind if there's a
general sense of unpleasant for example and I don't acknowledge it that next
layer after the V the feeling tone of unpleasant could be a
general about meditation that day you know general not wanting or
grumpiness so this is part of the review of the last few days Vena feeling tone was what we call on
Monday and if it's unseen it can kind of filter tint
experience in a way that isn't so helpful for example if I'm having hip
pain and I don't notice that it's just hip pain or I do and the mindfulness isn't
that strong I might be averse to it and stay averse to it I want to shift and
make it go away that's the unpleasant and the not wanting boom boom in the
chain of events so that feeling tone can be very
simple and if I just acknowledge oh pain sometimes it can just stay excuse
me with the unpleasantness and I don't have to build a story about it of like
oh this is cancer and D D D D D or you know oh I need to go back to the doctor you know doesn't have to take me away to
this whole story this whole house of cards the acknowledgement of the simple
feeling tone of what is can cut through even very elaborate stories unhelpful
stories projected outwards so then there's that next layer
that happens for most of us common reactions in this case it was
the not wanting these can become overall attitudes or frames of mind
oriented to wanting or not wanting otherwise known as greed or
aversion all forms of craving it can be for example a habitual
wanting of a nice experience or a nice view or a nice breath and then I'm
judging all of my experience through that filter of well it's supposed to be like
this that's also maybe not so helpful and the beautiful thing about
this is that shifting to mindful awareness of the
attitude helps develop greater discernment and helps attenuate move the attitude to be less
less informative or authoritative about my
experience and as I talked about yesterday the attit ude of mind can also
influence the feeling tone so
if I go into a room every day to meditate and it's Pleasant it's got sort
of the perfect lighting and Ambiance maybe there's a pleasant scent in the
background a perfect place to sit that conditions a certain kind of
attitude and once my attitude is
set I'll have a pleasant association with that place conversely if it's a place I'm not
explaining this very well um basically what I'm saying is our attitude about an
experience can inform how pleasant or unpleasant it is let me give another example I gave this earlier in the class
if we feel the touch sh someone's hand on our shoulder it's a completely different
experience if it's a good friend or a lover or if it's a presumptuous
acquaintance who's a little bit obnoxious so our attitude towards the
situation towards the experience can actually shift the perception of
it finally Wednesday we talked about wholesome or beneficial attitudes of
mind for meditation generosity of spirit simple allowing contentment appreciative
interest inquiry
equinity all of those are onward leading for the practice and all of those can be practiced in relationship to anything
else that's arising if I have appreciative inquiry about my version
it can attenuate it or at least lead to Greater discernment greater wisdom about
it so mindfulness can transform even unpleasant experiences and
predispositions into information food for
awakening so back to directed attention all of this matters because if we're
meditating on a specific object it's really helpful to intentionally
cultivate positive openhearted interest allowing accepting
non-c contention to allow experience to come in the full full range of
experience to come into our mindfulness versus be left out of it and
accidentally come along with it so it's helpful with each meditation
to make maybe start by checking the attitude or frame of mind
unseen predispositions attitudes towards greed or aversion can be subdued by
directed attention attenuated by them or sometimes they can tag along if our
attention is developed elsewhere so the encouragement is to take a few moments in each
meditation and notice notice whatever the of mind or
mood or general inclination is so it can be seen clearly and develop greater
discernment thank you for your practice a delight to be with you today and we
have just a moment or two I'll answer one or two questions and then um be back
with some of you tomorrow it's been enjoy may all beings
benefit
oh Brian very bad tontis that is
um that's unpleasant I'm sorry to hear that I have heard two different schools
of thought on this I rarely experience it myself so these are both from other
people um one is to let your attention
be much broader than just one object to allow to allow a broader wash of
experiences so that the hearing is just one thread within it so that's
one I know one person for whom it worked to
completely merge with the hearing experience and found it to be a great
concentration object that may or may not work for you so I would experiment with it with a
little Caution and then finally this kind of taichi move that I've been
talking about this week which is to really notice your attitude towards it
and focus more on that maybe sometimes there's aversion maybe sometimes it's
okay that to take a step back I hope that's
helpful so some other great questions coming in here um how do you distinguish
between attention and awareness so Greg I'm not sure if you were here at the very beginning of the talk but I didn't
frame it this way but this is indeed what it was so when I asked people to place their attention on their
hand that's the capacity of attention especially if it moves from your hand to your
foot the fact that you're aware of the movement of your attention from your
hand to your foot is the awareness so the attention is what moves and the awareness is what sees the
moving Peter can there be too much control of attention from the control
Power Tower of the Mind absolutely can the real encouragement in this
practice is to settle in to the embodied experience rather than controlling the
experience from the mind mind so that filling of the hand with awareness by a
Spong like a sponge that is a very different
experience than Imagining the hand and trying to control my experience at the
hand so you may experiment
with rather than um having the locus of attention be in the
head checking how it feels to feel from the belly or the
body just going to check here I think that's a little bit about each of them
I'm also going to be offering um some Q&A in my blog on my website at the end
of the month so um I will do my best to capture the questions I haven't had time
to answer and address them now I'll put that link in tomorrow
one more from Mary L this will be the last one troubling situation is very
prevalent in the heart how in meditation to keep attention on the
anchor so sometimes you can't if it's really up then it can be helpful to turn
the attention to your heart the feelings under the
situation the feelings under the situation so noticing the sadness or the
anxiety or the resistance or whatever is there and attending to that with
kindness with awareness it can be really helpful not
to allow the thoughts just to proliferate and instead come to the
embodied part of the emotions and give yourself breaks
give yourself breaks so thank you everyone for your attention and look forward to being with
you tomorrow