good morning good
day nice to see uh the uh messages coming
in it's so nice to get a feel of
Sana forming
together yeah greetings greetings
so good morning good day everyone and so we are gathering here to practice
together and this week and I've been using a metaphor of um sitting like a
mountain uh as a a way to ground ourselves and then today I'll be
building upon uh the metaphor sitting like a
mountain uh to evoke uh something else in addition to
being grounded here and so and join me along if you
like I'll offer some guidance at the beginning and then we'll be sitting
together uh in silence so I'll begin with the sound of
[Music]
bowel so here we are gathering together
practicing
Dharma if you like you can take a few long deep
breaths as you settle in feel that we're practicing in community
and coming here arriving here and now in the present
moment knowing that we we have all this
fellow practitioners practicing together maybe we feel
uplifted inspired and
happy so we arrive here with a measure of
happiness in the midst of all that is here in the body and mind and
heart allow mindfulness and a heartfulness to come to the foreground
feeling and sensing the overall posture of the body
sensing contact of the body with the floor our Earth
underneath there is a gradual sense of of gathering
collecting composing
inwardly releasing the weight of the body towards the Earth
we don't have to do anything it's
natural for this body to settle itself
allow the earthy body resting on Earth
the earthy feeling of the body is
grounding or
grounded
stable you may feel a sense of a root otness of this body on
Earth sitting like a mountain
you adjust according to how you
feel resting here in the quietude of the mountain
with in
you may hear a
sound you may feel a
temperature
smell for
it's natural in the quiet [Music] Mountain we can feel and sense the
breath the movements of the breath
the breathing Mountain
within including in your lift
experience the movements that comes with the breath or
breathing
sh
e
e e
sitting like an alive Mountain breathing Mountain
Within
e
e e
being curious about this alive Mountain
within like a
naturalist being curious about the nature of this body mind and
heart
e
e e
in this last few moments of the meditation
together if you like maybe
inviting to open to a kind of
vast inclusive
field that includes all of us that are practicing
together we're sitting in the Refuge of
aanaa and a feel like
this gratitude May naturally
arise connectedness
[Music]
and when you open your eyes and imagine yourself being a a live
mountain in the range of Mountains
mountain range alive
vibrant in its own Own Way each of
us thank you thank you for the
practice so um this week I've been sharing some
Reflections about uh Refuge uh today I like to bring this
notion of Refuge in Dharma and some of you have probably
done this before um but I'd like to kind of invite
us to uh feel and Savor this sense of
Refuge in Dharma uh in our daily life the word Dharma has many
meanings um and so as such refuge in Dharma can have
many different aspects to it one of the many meanings of Dharma is
teachings the Buddhist teachings is called Dharma and Dharma also means nature and
so in our meditation I was pointing or hinting a sense of nature
within and we can say say that the Buddhist teachings are related to clear
seeing or knowing the nature of our body mind and
hearts so in practicing Dharma we're learning to come to know
this nature the nature the Dharma within
ourselves um so what did the Buddha teach and some of you know that in over the
years of this 7 7 a.m. there are many lists being offered and so yes the
Buddha taught a lot and there were some huge volumes of poly Canon text that
gathers the teachings and of the Buddha and his disciples and yet
um if I had to summarize what the Buddha taught we can also say that there is a Core
theme to The teaching the Buddha is concern was concerned about suffering
and the end of suffering and that was what brought him
to his own path and also what motivated
him to teach after his Awakening and so many of you probably
know that this is a shorthand um form of the teaching of the
Four Noble Truth there is suffering or the poly term Dua there is the origin or the
cause of the suffering and there is a seizing or a cessation of the suffering
and there is the path practice path that leads to the cessation of the
suffering and so there is this Core theme uh that uh the Buddha had taught
many of the lists all the different lists you've heard um one in one we are
another are ways to elaborate the different aspects of the Four Noble
Truth I as I was reflecting about this and remembered that the first uh very
first discourse that the Buddha offered after his Awakening to his first five
disciples uh was the Four Noble Truth teaching and uh and then towards his
last days of his life and as documented in Parana
suta uh you can find the for Noble Truth there again
and so that's the Core teaching but how would this teaching or
this Dharma be a refuge for us how do we
understand this and how do we feel into
this so for most of us if we are fortunate enough to have lived long
enough to have experiences of of a wider range of Being Human living this humanly
life going through a lot of up and ups and downs happiness distress and the
worldly wings that um guil spoke about a few weeks ago pleasure pain gain and
loss praise and blame Fame disputes you know all this kind of
swirling opposites of um Our Lives
sooner or later we may begin to ask
ourselves is this it you know just kind of endless going around from wanting not
wanting um having not having or good or bad right or wrong I like I don't
like and we know um at some point
maybe even under the best circumstances of Our Lives this kind of spiraling patterns
can persist in small and big ways and so it can begin to stir our
hearts what is all of this what is this about right and so if the questions are
not being touched in or answered in some way it can be very unsettling for us I
felt this kind of stir in my own heart uh at some point of my
life and so inevitably we'll begin to
seek and um we'll also notice that this kind of pattern not happen not only
happens on the larger scale of our lives and it can happen in kind of micro
moments uh Moment by moment uh in our day in our
days uh if we observe Our Lives just in a day
closely you may begin to see that you know there are some times that you're
very comfortable physically but after a while and there is a discomfort and pain
or I'm very satisfied content with the things and Then followed by
discontentment so it goes on at uh endlessly throughout the day if we begin
to kind of notice this so how do we relate
this um is there a way to meet
this is there a way that we can live with this without getting caught in the
SW ing patterns and this is where the for Noble Truth teaching comes
in and it acknowledges the viudes of life and it points out the root cause uh
that's craving of this viudes and there is a possibility to be
free from being caught by the ups and downs and and uh
pain and pleasure and most
importantly there is a practice path that each of us can engage in that
naturally leads to the possibility of being freed from the caught upness you
know being caught up and this word is quite important
being caught up is what is being being
freed it's not that we won't have pain or pleasure but rather how we relate to
them becomes different when I heard this first time
boy it's like light in the dark night I had the sense you know sign me
up I'm in maybe that's one way to experence experience The Refuge in
Dharma you know I'm in I like to I like to give myself over to this I wanted to
know this I want to practice this this path and so taking refuge in
dhma on one level just means that we give ourselves
over to the teaching we learn we practice it and we immerse ourselves
into it and we let the teachings and the practice come in life come alive in us
and so they become real in our
lives and so the Buddha had offered the practices that we can engage in like all
of us have been practicing and this is 700 a.m. and many other ways on retreats
in our daily life so that we can see that it is possible to break out of this
locked in pattern of reactivity wanting not wanting pushing pulling demanding or
avoiding and this is down through gradual gradually gradually getting to
know the nature of our mind and um
heart and so we can get to know the patterns of duka and we can deeply understand how it
manifests in big ways or in very subtle
ways and we get to know how it arises and how it passes
away and so in the way it's a good news that when we're feeling anger
frustration jealousy happiness or feeling depressed
we are not too quick to dismiss them but this is the the nature that
we're to explore to understand to see to really know what is this
pattern and in this exploration the Dharma the wisdom
naturally flows the care The Compassion naturally flows and that's the nature of the
Dharma and that the release of this caught upness of the
swirling becomes available to us it's through our curiosity in getting
to know this nature deeply and so for me taking refuge in
such a process a practice is like homecoming
you know I bow to this I give myself to this as best as I'm
able and trusting this gradual shifting and changing that may become available
to us through our sincere
practice and so I and uh I'll end this uh
darat by uh inviting you to save her a
little uh what does it feel for you to be in The Refuge of
Dharma maybe dropping that as a inquiry in your day and let yourself a feel what
does that feel for you what gets
evoked so thank you for your attention and May our exploration uh be
a source of a benefit to all beings so have a wonderful rest of the
day I'll be there tomorrow with you again