hello and welcome to our meditation session and one of
the descriptions of meditation practice is to be
undistracted and collected so one of the purposes
of avoiding distractions is so that our mind our
awareness our very sense of being
alive can begin to collect itself here in a composed unified
way often the mind when it's distracted is scattered it's concerned with other
times and other places and our emotions can
be scattering can be distracting ing can be uh fragmenting can be
agitating the sensations of our body can be something we're reacting to and
wanting and avoiding so not everything is not
collected together and this unification collectedness that happens in meditation
changes the orientation of the Mind
changes how we see ourselves rather than
seeing a particular thing and then defining ourselves by it or judging ourselves by it or pushing against it or
pulling away from it grabbing it or there is um a sense of some larger
hole a larger immersion into our totality of our
experience and while we might be very clearly mindful of the details it's
clear the details are being seen in a much wider broader
perspective so we're not fixating on anything everything works together as a
whole so this collectedness of mind collectedness collectedness of mind and
body so to assume a meditation
posture and this assuming the posture is the beginning of collecting
ourselves collecting all the varied ways in which we're scattered and preoccupied
and and uh our energies and thoughts are elsewhere
and we begin to bring it here invite all of who we
are to come together in this spot this place of sitting so we assume the
postures beginning to do this beginning of doing this
physically and to no longer focus on looking at
anything the eyes don't have to be focused on something so either lowering
the Gaze and an unfocused gazing on the
flooor or gently closing the eyes and the closing of the eyes can
feel like explicitly another step towards arriving
here collecting ourselves into this experience so the eyes are not the
outwardly focused away from
ourselves
and then to take a few long slow deep breaths as a way of saying hello to this
body this being that you are clear
contact with the body here with a deep in
breath and a deep relaxation as you
exhale tension is
fragmenting it pulls together certain muscles so they stand away or contracted
into
themselves relaxing our muscles softening
allows our muscles to work in harmony with the rest of the
body not frozen or locked away relaxing is part of the process of
collecting settling in
here letting the breathing return to normal
and to continue this process of relax
relaxing but every part of the body that relaxes is invited into the
whole collecting together maybe joining the sense of the
whole body here so you unified field relaxing the muscles of the
face tension in the face is often a place where we represents how
we fixate or get caught up
in the social dynamics
concerns fears
letting the muscles of the face fall away from the skull so they can be at
ease softening the
jaw relaxing the shoulders
if they don't relax easily you might try a subtle adjustments of how the hands and arms
are placed to give the shoulders more room to
relax or if there's no relaxation in the shoulders as softening around the
shoulders a softening that's okay with how things
are softening of the
belly feeling the weight of the belly and letting it relax downward into
the pelvic cavity pelvic
[Music]
Bowl and then taking a few moments to feel your
body as globally as is easy for you is WI a sense of being
embodied as you
can with the inhale breathing into that Global
body on the the exhale relaxing the whole
body and composing yourself here means nothing is left
out is there anything that's happening for you that now that you're overlooking
or denying trying to get away
from that you can recognize gently
softly and let it know you too have a place in the larger
hole letting the global body make space for everything
where the breathing in is a acknowledgment of all that is
here breathing out a relaxing
opening
for
e the waves on top of the ocean the swells that move
through are just a surface of a vast collected
ocean that's whole that works
together so the waves of breathing in and
out so the Wisps and currents of thoughts and
feelings stay present here with your
breathing but open to all things within the ocean of your
experience pray present and open so all things can gather
here and have a place in the unified composed feeling
of being alive Here and
Now
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to feel whatever degree that
you're more settled
calmer any degree to which now that I'm speaking you can be more aware of
yourself and how you
are any ways in which you feel
more collected or
whole content just sitting here with your
own lived experience of
now
if it's possible to make room for all of who you are either is an act of
imagination as if your very being is vast space that holds all of
who you are or as a gathering
together all the pieces of a puzzle here breathing together being
together feeling and sensing knowing all of that's
here not by thinking about it but more like feeling
sensing open no part left
out and to whatever degree that this works for you stay
there stay quiet enough as you are as you now turn your
attention out into the world around you this world that's full of suffering
and joys conflict and
friendships War makers and
peacemakers lovers and haters
for a few minutes for a minute or so hold it all as one large
hole because for this this minute or so it's
whole within your
awareness within the scope of your knowing of your
imagination all things are collected
together in a way that all things are safe with you right
now and then considering that whatever Ben benefits that this meditation has
brought you any way of being that it reminds you
of how to be that wish that you can bring a sense
of safety to all the people you meet that
they can feel safe at least from you you don't assert yourself you don't
run away the gift of safety
may it be on this day that I walk in the world a safe
person for all that I meet may it be that in that field of
safety from me spreads out a wish a sincere desire to see the welfare
and happiness of all beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music] free
[Music]
thank
you
e
so hello and welcome to this fourth talk on the five
faculties and the five to to translate a little bit more
literally from P maybe the five Divine forces within us
Divine um guides within us the literally the the qualities or
the aspects of Indra the great supreme god of the ancient Indian pan
Pantheon so this idea that we have Divinity within us um that somehow our capacities are
potentials are faculties of faith and making effort energy and
mindfulness and today concentration that there's something Divine about them they're special
they're may I dare say the word sacred we can take them for granted we
could take them for just of course it's just being human nothing special about them but in fact in Buddhism all we can
do is special this is where the world of the Sacred or this of liberation of
nobility of dignity of uh begins in our
engagement and so hindrances we talked about last week are those that prevent
us from engaging in the world uh in a free way in a liberating way and a
beneficial way they they hinder the capacity for engaging with mindfulness
mindfully or with with um a sense of real
purpose and um and so these faculties kind of are they
alternative and so uh faith is the alternative to sensual desire
greed um courageous effort is uh the antidote
or the alternative to um ill will yesterday I didn't talk about about
it but uh that um mindfulness is uh the alternative to
sloth and torper rigidity freezing up and um it's not exactly an antidote but
uh uh it's clearly uh the alternative to being sloth and torper it's a shutting
down shutting down becoming dull and the alternative is to wake up and be clear
but and mindfulness has a quality of peacefulness to it whereas and torper
has the opposite a resistance or shutting down uh it's it's uh it is kind of calm
mindfulness so that has that in common with Sloth and torper kind of it's not
activated and then today the topic is samadi often translated as
concentration and that's the antidote or the the the Cory to um restlessness and
regret restlessness and regret Keeps Us fragmented Keeps Us
agitated um samade is that which unifies and makes
peaceful uh quiet steady brings things together in a nice way so things are
operating in a harmonious flow rather than an agitated jumping around samadi is more than a laser you
know laser focus of the Mind in fact we probably shouldn't even think about it that way uh it's more the uh
one of the translators of these ancient Buddhist text biku suata sujato he um translates somat as
immersion and I love this idea of immersion because uh one of the classic
metaphors for somadi is a beautiful multicolored or many you know lotuses of
different colors lotus flowers floating not on the surface of the water but
opening up and floating uh under in the water under the water and um and the
idea the image is that very peaceful calm very clear and pure body of water
and just floating uh there peacefully completely immersed in the water and you these
metaphors are kind of very common even to this this in the modern world that some meditators will talk about it feels
like when they get immersed in the practice it's like they're dipping underw and if the mind starts thinking as they
go up and the head comes out and we start thinking and we let go of the thoughts and we sink down under water
and that I think that metaphor comes that idea of being underwater comes from a feeling of being immersed in a wide
field of well-being of Peace of subtleness where everything is collected
everything is held together in a peaceful quiet settled
way uh sometimes I like the word composed for uh somebody being restless
and and filled with regrets usually we're not very composed we're unsettled
we're we're um you know we're you know quite
unsettled and uh samat is to be deeply settled here with all everything
included so to have a laser focus which people sometimes can do um uh can
actually push things aside too quickly and you people can get really focused
and deeply concentrated but they have done that by pushing aside uh their
distracted Minds their feelings their emotions thinking that that's the problem and they shouldn't you know we
want to get away from it get concentrated which is the better place to be but that continues the process of
fragmentation or or an exclusion of parts of ourselves from the whole the
value of mindfulness practice is that it's an inclusive Pro practice
everything has a place in mindfulness that to be included just to be seen to be allowed to be there and to be known
but to be known so we're not troubled by anything easy to say more difficult to
do but to be present for all of it and in that state to become settled gathered
together to that from everything included not so much a lab are focused
but uh a deep settling into the into the bottom of the ocean and this beautiful
kind of soft peaceful sea or lake around us um refreshing holds it all
or and um so uh so when we're Restless when
we're agitated when we're filled with regrets um we can feel how we're uh um
you know divided up and maybe even uh troubled by ourselves or agitated about
ourselves and this kind of relaxing settling allowing things to settle back
together not grabbing things to hold them and make them whole but relaxing softening seeing being mindful of
everything so that in the mindfulness there's space there's breathing room for everything to be there and everything
wants to settle wants to come together nothing wants to remain
agitated and so samadi is an
action of inclusion an action of
unification so we start with faith confidence which is the desire to
practice sometimes we practice mindfulness with courageous effort to really this is you know the the C
courage say well this is really important clear that this maybe is the most important thing I can do because of
where it's going and then we practice with um uh a
clear Clarity of mind that's clearly accompanying our experience here to accompany everything to be present for
here to stand close to our lived experience all of it and find a way to
stand close to it that's calm the good friend not bothered but offering this
clear respectful attention to how things are that allows things to begin to
settle come together allows that kind of and then we gather things we steady
ourselves we practice continuity of mindfulness and um and so the
persistence the continuity that allows things to gather together gather
together um come together um um little bit like um you know a snowball that is
rolling down the hill just gathers more snow and becomes bigger and bigger and maybe the cold analogy doesn't it's not
so nice but but the idea that we're we're we're we're everything is coming
in uh here because of the continuity of practice the steadiness staying here
staying with the practice mindful here every moment of mindfulness being
a breathing room for what's there so there's space for things to settle into
this big ocean of
samade and um so
um samadi is what provides mindfulness with a feeling of uh deep contentment
satisfaction happiness peace and so it becomes easy and easier
and more and more inspiring to practice mindfulness of whatever is
happening uh without being bothered or judgmental or reactive to what's
happening and that reciprocal relationship between mindfulness and a deeper peace a deeper making space for
everything everything has a place then creates greater greater satisfaction contributes to greater and
greater sense of a wholeness the wholeness of
somebody so thank you and um so we have one more of these faculties Divine
qualities if if you don't mind that uh we'll do tomorrow which is usually
translated as wisdom and uh and it's the Corel to the
hindrance of uh doubt or indecisiveness or in
action so um thank you