so good evening my name is Maria stratman hold on a second
here so what I would like to talk to you about tonight is
um the attitude of mind and awareness as tools of insight sounds
very pedantic doesn't it but I really have as an
intention to share with you a way of thinking about mindfulness that makes it
touch how we are in life we all have things that happen that we're
dissatisfied with you know that you think of it for a moment of the many ways in which there are things that you
wish were different the many ways you wish things were different we lose someone or
something we lose our keys we lose someone close to us we stumble and fall on the path the
metaphorical path or you know we trip over the sidewalk and we fall and we break
something or we hurt someone or when someone or something
disappoints us are the Solace that we used to feel
in meditation somehow has left us and what's wrong with my
meditation or our bodies age and betray us and we wonder what happened to that
juiciness and that resilience and that get up and go
and somehow that movement is no longer reachable or maybe we're unable to
forgive or we feel unseen or dism miss or just plain
Passover or we see or experience Injustice these are common things that
happen to us all the time they're a normal part of life and how we're able
to meet them and interact with them determines whether we are miserable
unhappy suffering or whether we can encounter them with
equinity and we'd all like to have the secret for how to do that right I meet
everything that I don't want to be true with total balance and equinity and I'm
happy and how do I get there so what I want to talk about is
how do we get there
because suffering exists in the world but we don't have to suffer
pain exists in the world unsatisfactoriness exists in the
world I don't know when you last lost your keys but we had keys missing in our house this this last week and it was
painful whose fault was it that the keys are missing what are we going to do about the keys we've torn the place
apart how important are the keys and of course in the overall scheme of these
things keys are not that important but they can become a source of great
irritation and of course we have strategies for dealing with things that aren't the way we want them to be we can
ignore them we can pass over them we can substitute something else in place of worrying about those
things we can say well I'm going to take care of myself and I'm going to go off and distract
myself we can develop self- Improvement plans okay I know how I'm going to deal
with this I'm going to take care of that bad habit I have and we're going to fix this as if by
fixing this particular case everything's going to be
better or we become we attach mindfulness to it and we attach great
intensity of intention and I'm going to be here with this I'm going to measure it I'm going to know everything about it
I'm going to analyze it I'm going to understand understand what's wrong with it and we just make it
worse and it becomes ever more a source of suffering and pain for
us or we get down and we roll around in the papers on the floor and really
really get miserable or we become
self-righteous this is not my fault and we enter into the world of
praise and blame it's not my fault it's your fault if you were better if I were better self-criticism
judgment and none of this is absolutely necessary it's just the way the mind
works all of these suppose we see these sources of
dissatisfaction as experiences that don't need to be fixed changed managed
massaged suppose we just see these as experiences that actually don't have
anything to do with our selfworth your
selfworth meaning in life the end of life they're just things
that happen suppose it is actually possible to see things just come and
go without attaching great meaning to everything that happens
can we actually do that how so I want to call your attention to
two aspects of how we experience the world and those are the attitude of mind
and our awareness so by attitude of mind what I'm referring to is the the sort of
context that we carry around with us that can be very shortterm or it can be
it can last days months weeks years which is sort of the uh the container
for how we experience the world you know the interesting thing about it is
it's usually what we ascribe to ourselves and say this is who I am well
I tend to see the world with judgment I'm J I'm a judger or I'm a fixer or I
am I'm really depressed so I see things this
way and we we decide that there is a way to look at the world and that's how we
look at the world and that tends to color the experience now it's a little bit
different than mood it's it's really just what we expect to
see and then we place our awareness in such a way that that's in fact what we see
and what I'd like to do is distinguish between what's actually happening and
our attitude or our opinion about what's actually
happening so I want to give a few examples and and see if we can look at
what's the raw experience versus what is it that we describe and decide is the
experience so they're kind of so so I'm GNA I'm going
to tell you why I think this is important first so on my mind lately has been a lot to
do with uh grief I've recently lost somebody very very dear to
me and I have been contemplating a lot about the intimacy of that relationship
and the loss of that relationship and what that means and so
one morning I was very conscious of of thinking about
well I'm going to think about all the wonderful times we had and I set myself
to thinking about memories of things that we had shared looking for what is it that has led to this great
intimacy and what arose were times of great
pain things that we shared around
events that were really quite painful and the memory brought to me at
what I was experiencing were pangs of ow oh that
hurts and at the same time I realized that those were those were moments when
we were really really close that we were there for one another that we were very
present for one another that we were vulnerable and
present and the intimacy that I recalled in those moments brought me
Delight so here I was in the present moment recalling pangs of grief feeling
pangs of grief and the pleasure of the intimacy of just being there for one
another and the Insight that I had was not
that intimacy requires pain or pain gives rise to intimacy but that intimacy
has to do with vulnerability and trust and I said oh that's really
interesting I came out of that few seconds of
experience with a sense of ease and relief in my
grief that didn't have anything to do with getting rid of grief or changing
the nature of grief but understanding that there was pain and
joy in the present even though this person is now
gone and I could focus on I could put my Awareness on worrying about oh those moments will
never arise again or I could just be here with this experience this Insight
this comes and this
goes it's possible to get caught in the place of the story and go I could have
gotten in to any one of those grief stories around the pain stories that we
were talking about I could have gotten worried about why can't I find
any happy memories to feel very intimate about I could have gone on to how I'm
going to miss these in the future I could have been lost in thinking about or having opinions
about what the experience was but the raw experience was just pain and joy following close on one
another and the Insight that
intimacy was because we really trusted one another and how wonderful that
was and how grateful I am in retrospect that we were that we had that
trust now that was described being an experience that lasted less than a
minute less than a minute of my life which has gone on for many
decades but it actually was a portion of my life that was very free and easy and
flowing we very often get caught in the in the place of thinking that pain has
to be fixed that discomfort and dissatisfaction
needs to be managed fixed tolerated
somehow we have to do something about it it can't just be
there unsatisfactoriness just is not
acceptable but in fact why
not it just is it doesn't mean
anything it just is like a thought coming and going so in the last couple of weeks
I've spent a a lot of time watching the Olympics I sprang for the $13 in butt
you know a month to watch peacock so I could really get into watching everything on the
Olympics and I watched a number of these super Elite athletes do their thing and
there there two two events that that I want to call your attention to because they illustrate basically the same thing
one was uh Steph Curry doing those Final Shots in the basketball men's basketball
in the last few minutes of the gold medal game and somebody asked him afterward
there were ridiculous ridiculous three-point shots and somebody asked him how did that feel and were you thinking
about at the end and he said I was just looking at the rim I was just looking at the rim and I
didn't see those two much taller guys standing right in front of him blocking the shot that he threw
over you know you can imagine the hands would be up like this in front of my face and they would go up the ball went
up over and a distance to the basket right just he said I was just looking at
the rim I just saw the rim and he's talked about this in other times where
for him it was so he he had done a lot of skill
development but also he was just in the moment I'm just doing this he wasn't
thinking about comparing it to something else he wasn't trying to be better than
he wasn't worrying about who was going to what people were going to think about it he wasn't thinking about he he had a
goal which was to make those baskets and to win the gold medal and he had a determination but he wasn't pushing
through something he was just totally in the moment totally in the moment I was just
looking at The Rim the other one was uh Katie leeki who
who got a gold medal for the 1500 meter swim and she said that after a th000
meters it just hurts and she'd been practic practicing practicing practicing practicing and and
it was uniform after a th meters it just hurts but she didn't think about the pain she didn't try to push it away or
tolerate it it just pain was there and she just kept
swimming because that's what she was doing she was just swimming so in both cases they were just doing what they had
trained themselves to do and they weren't focusing on those things that we
tend to think you should think about that you have to pay attention to that you should really be mindful
of yeah the pain was there but it was you know that's that's yeah the Pain's there and she just
swam that's what she did that's what we want our mindfulness
to be like we don't want it to be a task we don't want it to be something that we
have to always have an object for we don't want to spend our time walking
around saying okay okay now I'm going to be mind mindful of this so we have to develop the skill so that it's like a
muscle memory so what I'm encouraging you to do tonight is to become very aware of your
attitude of mind that's that's the thing that
determines that's the the sort of uh container for your
experience if you're walking around saying you know the world is really
crummy or you're an eternal optimism a person totally focused on
optimism and you can't see anything bad you won't see anything bad you also
won't be very realistic and things will happen to you you'll lose your keys even
if you're optimistic you'll still trip over the
crack in the sidewalk
but if you come to really understand your attitude of mind that attitude of mind that you have now then it becomes a
tool that you can use you can check in with it and you can you can say okay this attitude is here
today you don't have to change the attitude by the way you don't have to make it different than it is you just
have to be aware of it so that you know how it is coloring your experience
so knowing that I'm carrying around a certain amount of grief right
now I'm aware of it it's here but it doesn't have to color
everything I can still notice other things I can be aware of it and use my
awareness elsewhere as
well it's like knowing it's raining and wishing it wasn't raining R in but okay
it's raining but you know it's not the only thing
happening but it helps to be aware of it because things are still kind of
damp it's going to affect
you it doesn't have to surprise you so that's one aspect of it the other
one is you can also cultivate an attitude of mind mind so you can decide for example I
want to understand what it's like to have the attitude of
Mind of generosity how do I cultivate that attitude of
Mind well when I notice that somebody said something hurtful instead of
deciding there's something wrong with that person I can say I wonder what's bothering that person
I can be generous in how I think about or respond to people I can deliberately
give something to someone and say how does that feel come to understand what it feels
like to have an attitude of generosity there's value in knowing how
it feels or to develop an attitude of
renunciation what does that feel like not to learn how to deprive myself but
to know what it feels like to be able to let go of
something what does it feel like to let go of something so this afternoon I read
um I was trying to think of a poem that might illustrate the idea so I read a
Song of Myself by Walt Whitman and there he just talked about
how wonderful it was just to touch people just to feel
that do you know how wonderful it feels just to touch people just I we you know it's kind of
not PC to touch people these days so you got to be kind of careful about this but you know choose
carefully the other night we had an event here for for volunteers to
celebrate volunteers at IMC and it was absolutely
delightful just delightful people that I hadn't seen since before the pandemic I
got to see and I reveled in that
delight and I carried that Delight I experienced that delight and I was still
aware of this grief hanging over here and people say what's new with you think
well I don't really want to dump on this
story but it really felt different I could feel how lovely it was to see old
friends that I hadn't seen and to experience that in your body
and say ah yes so that you recognize it and you
don't develop the attitude of mind that this is the only way to be whatever that attitude of mind is and
you don't identify with that attitude of mind and say this is who I
am it's possible to be many kinds of people you are many kinds of
people and when you see that you can use your
awareness and any situation to say what's going on here what's going on here how can I see
more clearly and in seeing more
clearly we become disentangled from all the ways that we
decide this is the most important thing in the world and I am really caught in
this suffering the way we become
uncaught is be by disentangling ourselves by seeing clearly this is
what's operating this is what I this oh this is what's happening just this not
more not what used to happen not what's going to happen not what's going to follow from this but just this just the
rim just the rim the closer we can get to just this
feeling just this moment just this the closer we can see oh this is
what's happening it doesn't say anything about who I am or who you are it's just
this happening as we become disentangled we
become dispassionate everything falls away we
don't hold on to it it's not like we have to let go of things or push things
away oh this is what's
happening and the ease that we are looking for
arises ah and we see things coming and going
and coming and going
sometimes they're happy things sometimes they're sad
things but they don't say anything about this is who I
am they're just things it's just raining it's just not
raining I notice I seem tense today tension
tension tension what's happening what's
happening okay it seems like this okay could be what else is
happening so that we get don't get so attached to our first thought we don't
get lost in the story of the first word that we attach to what's going on
we don't decide meditation sucks because today I
just can't seem to to relax at all we can actually allow things to be
just as they are and when we can allow things to be
just as they are we get over the suffering that
arises out of wishing everything was different wishing it was better wishing we could be
better we just say Ah that's the way it is right
now and then we look at our intention and we take the next
step and we don't allow the attitude of mind to determine what our life is
we use the attitude of mind to see things and to understand how it
influences our experience and we cultivate alternative
attitudes of mind so that we can understand what it feels like and
cultivate that oh huh that's interesting
developing a mind of curiosity if you want to be
free cultivate
Freedom allow yourself to see things just as they are without an opinion
without judgment just this
I have no idea whether I said what was on my page but those are my thoughts for
this afternoon so thank
you and may all of your attitudes be joyous ones and when they are not as
they will not may you see the world through
Clarity because then you will be free thank you so if you have any questions
or observations or demands I'd hap happy to entertain
them would you here's the microphone please it's my first time here um we
talking about the feeling um that's that's like something that that I've
been uh working on a lot and it's about for me it's
about just like being able to like feel it like in in every breath like to just
have like just like the excitement the passion like it's just you have
to it's it's it's it's all about feeling the world reflects back to us what we feel whether whether we know it or not
it's our subconscious it's it's it's what we believe in our subconscious and what we feel so it's a combination of
both so like you're saying the thoughts that we're thinking during the day we have to be conscious of the type of
thoughts that we impress into our subconscious because then when we express it out it comes out with those
things attached to it so we reflect it back to ourselves in our reality but it's
about like you said detaching from from from those negative thoughts and just
being at peace like said just not so um so you've said a
lot uh and it's very very complex but basically I if I can reflect back what
I've heard we are impacted by our experience and we uh reflect that back
and we in reflecting back to others we are also it's it's changed somewhat by
the attitudes and and thoughts that we have and that impacts others as well and
so there's a feedback mechanism between us and others one of
the one of the criticisms of this practice is that a mindfulness practice
can lead you to become self-focused all I'm thinking about is what's going on with me
and it is one of the reasons for cultivating an attitude of generosity that you begin to understand that that
you you really are not paying attention if you don't notice what's going on for
the other person out here as well and how that impacts you because there is
there is a lot of sense data that you're aware of that your mind maybe isn't
processing yeah and and absolutely obviously we have to be conscious of of
other people um I was just maybe just saying like in the sense of like even just experiences or things that we that
that come to pass um that that we we don't realize that that we're um that
much in control of of what's going on here it's it's really all inside of us
and how we feel is what we're projecting just I mean if you don't smile if you look at a mirror you don't smile at it
you're not going to get one back okay so I'm I'm not quite sure I'm clear on what you're just saying so are
you saying I'm I'm not sure how you use the word control
there you said something about it's it's did you say we do control or we don't
control we're I think we're in more control than we realize um we influence
but I don't think we're particularly in control well yeah we yes influence we we I mean in a sense uh yeah we influence
our our experience we we we we we influence our experience you know um for
sure but I think it's we influence it a lot more than we realize with our feelings and with our thoughts okay yeah
yeah so so what conditions our experience so the experience comes out
of the conditions that are set and so if I have ill will in my heart then I'm
going to generate a lot of ill will if I have loving kindness and peace in my heart I'm going to generate quite the
opposite uh so I think that's the context in which you're yeah speaking basically what I was say yeah thank
you um so you talked about the generosity but I want to know how can we
know how much generosity is we need to have um we okay because
I'm going through hard time and because I had I think too much generosity that
it hurt me at the end because of caring too
much um about other people of giving too much yes to other
people so I want to make a distinction between an attitude of generosity and A
Generous Heart a Compassionate Heart and the act of generosity and the act of
compassion which is different than compassion the reason I'm making this
distinction is compassion is the movement of the heart and generosity is
a a an attitude of mind that is open and
giving the act of generosity is a Step Beyond that and
there's a different um distinction to be made so an act of generosity that has to
do with giving somebody something take needs to take into
account whether the generosity towards
someone is ungenerous toward oneself there needs to be a balance so A
Generous Heart is also generous toward oneself it is a kind of a a spirit of
loving kindness that doesn't have anything to do with giving somebody something that giving somebody something
is um uh like
um a a measuring stick I'm going to measure my generosity by how much I give
away and if I give you everything then you're going to love me you know there's a kind of transactional feeling to it
whereas A Generous Heart is just plain open and free free flowing okay
so when we're in a position of saying I don't know how you could say the same
thing about generosity and vulnerability so if I say that I value
vulnerability in an open heart to the extent that I make myself
unsafe that's unskillful and unwise to give to the point where I
am harming myself is unskillful and
unwise how to determine where that is is a matter of
balance that one has to Det determined for
oneself I don't know if that's helpful but I I want you to think in terms of of
a generous heart is not measured it's
open it it has nothing to do with the act of generosity although acts of
generosity help open the heart thank you okay
there's there's a stage where people can become
um uh you we've heard of codependency
where where someone supports somebody's bad habits as I'm going to support you
forever because I really believe in you and then you know they're they're really causing harm in the end you know that's
not being generous it feels like generosity but is not so often times
it's possible to masquerade an intention and so then one
has to step back and say what is my intention is my intention to be loved is
my intention to give love is my
intention is my intention to be seen is my intention to
encourage and to look very closely at what the intention is as a way of measuring
that um balance to help to find that
balance yes can we have the
microphone thanks for the talk um got a lot out of it um can
you maybe share a bit about so this concept of attitudes of mind um you shared examples like
generosity I think Freedom um just curious if there's like
kind of a a guiding principle or how do I expand my vocabulary of like the
attitudes of mind that we want to have um well see that's the thing I don't
want to put a good and bad label on any attitude of mind now if if if you talk
to my husband well actually he probably I don't know if he knows this but the very things he likes about me are the
very things that in extremist he doesn't like about me right
uh and we could say that about anything uh a knife in the hands of a a
surgeon is a tool for good a knife in the hands of a a robber is is probably
not so good so any attitude of
mind
um exists it doesn't necessarily have to be considered bad so let's take an
attitude that is um let's take the attitude of Revenge Revenge is on my
mind okay this is a an ill will right so so I would say that this is an
an unskillful attitude of mind because revenge is likely to
generate more suffering and therefore I suspect is it's not going to
provide anything
useful if I have if I can look if I notice an attitude of Revenge
I can say what is what else is here besides
revenge and it can be a way of saying is Revenge the right word am I just hurt do
I really want to hurt the other person or do I really want something else what
is it what is it that I really want because sometimes uh one of my
favorite teachings from Gil was he said you know if you can't get rid of ill will at least be the kind of
person be the person who wants to get rid of ill will because it it softens
and opens the heart right that
so a um a characteristic that is uh a negative
characteristic greed hatred and delusion are the things that we want to get rid of in life because they are the do give
R to suffering so an attitude of mind that supports greed hatred and delusion
you really want to let go of that you want to you want to see as clearly as possible so that you can let go of that
attitude of mind because it's going to give rise to
suffering so I I don't do it anymore but I used to have
uh engraved on my iPad the opening lines to the do a
Ada all experiences preceded by mind led by mind made by mind speaker act with a
corrupted mind and suffering follows like the wheels of the cart behind the Hooves of the ox all experien is
preceded by mind made by mind led by mind led by mind made by mind speak or
act with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never departing
shadow I routinely repeat those words to myself to remind myself to
check what's in my heart and if it is tight and twisted
and full of ill will I say I don't like that feeling I don't want that feeling
can I let go of that feeling has nothing to do with whatever
is happening but only what I carry in my heart because that's what conditions the next
moment that's the power of the attitude of mind so so Revenge would be one I'd say
I'd try to lose that one but I would use it to try to figure out what else is there what what what
else is happening is there some way that I can can change that Revenge word to what I
really want is for the world to be better so I'll give you an example of how that might work somebody presses you
on the freeway Cuts you off and I wish there was a cop here right and instead
you say wait a minute that's not what I want the truth is it scared
me May nobody be hurt now I've moved from Revenge pretty
quickly the thought arose but I don't have to hold on to the thought I can let go with the the
thought but seeing that thought gives rise to another thought like that this
is what else is here well it scared me that was the whole thing it scared me that's why the thought arose but I don't
have to identify with the thought and own the thought and hold the thought and justify it and know I don't have to I
can let go of it and then there's room for something else to arise which is the habit
cultivated by I want to keep a peaceful heart that's why we cultivate skillful
attitudes of mind so that we can just look at the rim and keep
swimming because we've cultivated the muscle memory to do
that so any last thoughts
I wish you all joy thank you