hello and am Monday here in California at the inside meditation
center and uh so we just finished the 25p part
introduction to mindfulness meditation and I have in mind to continue with that and with that series
or part two of it and uh we'll start here with this
meditation and um so the simple idea simplest idea of
mindfulness meditation is to be aware of what's Happening as it's
happening and not to do a checklist approach but to take the time to connect
to whatever is predominant uh to really know it well
and that can be in over a course of one breath a few breaths where we allow
ourselves to feel and sense and know what's happening and sometimes it's
panoramic and just everything coming and going and sometimes it's um centering on
something for a little bit so there's a settling a concentration that here so
the breathing works this way that we're here centering ourselves on the in inhale and the
exhale um knowing the inhale and exhale and uh and feeling it being with
it sometimes it's Body Sensations sometimes it's emotions sometimes it's thoughts sometimes it's
sounds and then I as I recommended in the intro series to let the breathing be
the default the place where we're cultivating stability in addition to that being
present for being mindful of everything one very useful thing to be aware of as
you're aware of anything as you're aware of breathing the body emotions thoughts
is to recognize if there if there's any wanting of something or wanting not
wanting something the movements of wanting and not wanting so even in the middle of
being aware of something is there some subtle or maybe not so subtle wanting wanting a better
breathing wanting to get concentrated wanting to be a good meditator if there's
a ache in the knee is there a not wanting and the idea is to really take
time to recognize that to feel it not be troubled by the wanting or not
wanting but also not give preference to do it not let
it uh influence the simple moment to moment
awareness and how not to make it influence it is to include it as something to be
known oh so just simply to note
either note in the mind or just a non-verbal recognition this is wanting wanting is
present and um and then continue to practice so
the wanting also is in the domain of everything sometimes wanting or not
wanting is kind of like the stage director who's off stage and the
audience doesn't see what the stage director is telling people to do but uh the stage director is somehow in charge
the idea is everyone's on stage and so wanting not wanting is also brought on
the stage so we can see it clearly so that's the instructions for today so to
assume a meditation posture
um and to gently close your
eyes and sometimes wanting is
useful so as you sit here and begin see if you
can bring forth a gentle
wanting to be here present to be at this place at this time
aware of your
experience to enter a deeper relationship with
present moment sitting
here and gently taking some long slow deep breaths relaxing as you
exhale relaxing the shoulders with a long
exhale releasing the belly and a long
exhale
letting breathing return to normal and continue to relax relax on
the exhale softening throughout the
body
and then centering yourself on breathing as if the breathing is the
center of all
things
and then as you sit here meditating
today keep a lookout for the the arising of
Desire of wanting and not
wanting it maybe each thing that you're aware of in the
moment check it out and see is there any desire wanting or not wanting in
relationship to it and if there is
know it clearly that desire is
present and know it in such a way that you are not caught in the
desire so the desire is just a part of the landscape of your present moment
experience
for
e
what wanting or not wanting is operating in the foreground in the
background and what i' like to know it
clearly instead of going along with it by thinking about
it
e
for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to maybe take a moment to distinguish between different kinds of
desires you might have in relationship to other
people there's the desire to want something from
them and there's also the desire to want something for
them might be easier to see that the desire
to want something from them serves
yourself desire for them serves
them and the feeling of the two the way these two operate in our bodies and
minds and hearts can be very
different and for the next couple of minutes to consider the the desires you
have for the well-being of others how you wish them
well where does that desire come from within
you how does that desire arise so
that it has a healthy feeling to it a goodness to
it a Simplicity that is a
wishing but not a needing a desire but not an
attachment and as you breathe maybe breathing through your heart center and imagine that in your
exhale you are spreading your well-wishing into the
world in front of you behind you to the side of you in all
directions may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of us are well wishing of
others be good for our own Hearts to have a
[Music] healthy generosity of care for
others may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you
for
so welcome to this Monday a Dharma talk which is now beginning of part two
of the introduction to mindfulness meditation and um for this week I would
like to talk about the hindrances there's five hindrances and people who do mindfulness
meditation one of the kind of standard things to do is to become um well
familiar with how the hindrances work in us and the value is that we want to
understand what hinders our ability to be aware to be mindful and this is a
wonderful principle that the very thing that is the obstacle uh is becomes
the the practice so rather than letting it remain the obstacle that Hinder
awareness because we get pulled into trained thoughts of the
hindrances um we turn around and make the hindrances the object of the
mindfulness and what's brilliant about that is that it doesn't require the hindrances to go away to reestablish
mindfulness we establish mindfulness on the very challenge we have and this
is one of the important principles of aasa practice in general is is not an avoidant practice but rather a practice
that turns towards uh that stands near stands stands next to what's happening and able
to accompany it to see it to know it without becoming it without being
entangled with it and so um so rather than being upset
when we can't be mindful it just uh not being able to be mindful is an indication that we need to
turn our attention to something different than we have been paying attention to to the very thing that's
making it difficult so if there's a lot of thinking for example that takes people
away then we want to practice mindfulness of thinking but sometimes even that's not
enough and sometimes what's propelling the thinking what's propelling our caught upness is some form of Desire
some form of hindrance and there's five hindrances uh desire is the first uh
more technically it's sensual desire the second is aversion so not
wanting something wanting something to go away and the the third is usually
translated as sloth and torper but uh in that that kind of fits the hindrance of
the of fear quite a bit it might be more appropriate to translate it as uh uh
sloth and rigidity rigidity and torper
and um and then there is restlessness and
regrets and then there's doubt so these are the five seven actually but two of them are pair two of them are
Pairs and um so
desire desires are important part of life and they the very thing which trips
us up in our lives desires free us from trouble and desires put us
in trouble and so desires are multifaceted and beginning to recognize
desires as desires is phenomenally helpful if you can recognize the desires
as desires then you have a chance then to feel and sense and experience what
it's like having the desire and some Desires in and of
themselves feel like our freedom is compromised feels like that we are
caught in something we're being compelled being pushed it's almost like we lose our
self-determination because a desire overwhelms us so you know compelling us
to act in a certain way other forms of Desire do not limit our freedom doesn't limit our
capacity to stay grounded and centered here uh actually supports it supports us
to be centered supports us to be present and be and the feeling of those desires
can feel even nourishing they can feel right they can feel like they're part and parcel of a centered grounded way of
being alive and present and the second desire is
connected to mindfulness that what we're trying to do in mindfulness is to
establish awareness here the Foundation of mindfulness Foundation of awareness
is stability this uh being here in a clear way so that we're abiding living
in Awareness not living in abiding in the desires not abiding in the thoughts
that we're having and so when and when thinking and desires get
merged then we can be in trouble because then the mind gets Swept Away in thought
propelled by the desire uh and if um and if there's a lot
of attachment together with the desire then there can be the thinking can be comp compulsive and when the thinking is
compulsive then sometimes the behavior becomes compulsive too uh the pressure is so
strong and one of the things that happens with his compulsive desires and that compell thinking a lot
is that uh we get caught in the hindrance of desire and as I said it's often
translated as the hindrance of sensual desire sometimes it's it's in the
ancient text it's also described as the hindrance of acquisitiveness wanting to have
something and um to acquire something for myself and um and of course there you
it's okay to acquire things uh that are healthy for us and when we acquire them in healthy ways but it's the uh the
greed the clinging the grasping the compulsion the pushing that um becomes
the hindrance that makes it difficult to be present diff difficult to be centered
here difficult to stay aware as opposed to being pulled away into the train uh
the trains of train cars of of thinking over and over again so what we want to be able to do
is begin to recognize when desires are there and um and desires are there a lot
so it shouldn't be too difficult to begin recognizing Desires in the course
of your daily life you might stop a few times maybe on the hour every hour and
just um have some kind of alarm that goes off and then say what what desire am I involved in right
now um in you know if you find yourself in a supermarket well there is some
desire to cut you there you're looking for something to buy you want something there it's maybe every aisle aisle
you're on you're looking for what you want you're based you know they searching there's nothing wrong with
that but what's the quality and the nature of that desire does it feel if
you really check in about how you're Desiring does it feel relaxed and easy
does it feel nice and comfortable or is it uh is it tight and
stressful to have it uh if you find yourself driving your car
what is the nature of Desire there and if you're driving fast does that tell
you something about how you're living in your desires um and uh if you're driving with
a lot of impatience that's tell you something about nature of your
desires if you um you know are doing anything at all if you're uh talking on
the phone phone or answering an email what desires are operating there and is that desire you have does it feel good
to have or when you really pay attention to it it's stressful and strain full
there's desires all the time and you can get tied up in knots if you're look at every desire carefully but to begin
becoming cognizant of desires so that you can begin centering yourself on
desires which are healthy and you'll learn to recognize when they're not good for you or for other people and then you
learn because you learn to become familiar with them and you know them well what they feel like slowly you learn how to be free of
desires and ideally we're free of both good desires and bad desires healthy and
unhealthy ones the healthy ones too is possible to have clinging and grasping but we want to even healthy ones we want
to hold lightly and present act on if it's appropriate so sitting in meditation
then uh one of the things to become aware of is the functioning
desire and part as I said part of the reason to sit and become calm and centered and stable here maybe something
that happens over the course of a meditation session one of the functions of that is so once we're stable then
we're going to be in a have a vantage point in which to feel or sense or
experience desires when they arise we can see then there oh now there's a wanting there's thoughts not just
thinking going on but there's thoughts driven by desire fantasies are thoughts driven by
desires usually and so you might from the beginning of this just keep it very
simple just recognizing oh there's a desire as opposed to deciding exactly
what the desire is um maybe that can be for later but see what kind of Freedom
comes for just really clearly recognizing this is a desire I'm not proposing this to make
your meditation busy a lot of searching and looking and analyzing but the idea is once you're
kind of arrived and centered and stable here then you might want to be on the
lookout uh keep an eye out for it or it might be most useful before you become
centered it because the very thing that's keeping you from beginning into the present moment and makes it
difficult when you sit down is because the spinning of your thoughts is driven
by some strong desire and uh it might be useful to sit
down and see oh look at that no wonder it's hard to be settled right now
there's a desire that's very compelling and compulsive that's still caring with
me desire to think something or figure something out or plan something planning
is a is you know is a usually a desire and um
so in order to so I'll repeat this very important principle that the very thing
that makes it difficult to be mindful that's the thing to be mindful
of and one of those things can be desire and that's one of the key places in
meditation where you want to check in and see where's the desire here that is
when you're not able to be easily present the mind's drifting off a
lot then check in what's the desire that's operating here there some way of
clearly recognizing knowing the desire feeling it in your body that uh where it
begins to lose its grip on you and maybe then becomes easier to continue with
your um with your meditation so thank you very much and uh
so we'll continue with the ances this
week