hello and
welcome and for this meditation
today I'd like to start with a kind of
a simplistic statement for the purpose of
making a point that some that we want to be careful that we're not using meditation
as a customer as a consumer and overlooking that in
meditation we should be the producer now that doesn't mean that we
have to work a lot but we have to create the we have to
bring forth the conditions that
allow uh the practice to mature and develop the the practice does require
something from us but it's a it's a unusual thing it
requires and one way to understand it is that
um uh our hearts our minds our inner life our spiritual life is very
influenced influenceable that uh and what we're trying to do is to create the put
together those influences in good Buddhist language is uh we
are uh conditioned the it's it's the uh
we putting together the conditions that allow something to mature and
develop and our role is to bring along to produce to make happen
the conditions and then we have to make room and time for those conditions to
condition us so like a farmer or Gardener who uh has a role in creating
the right conditions for a seed to sprout germinate and to plant to
grow uh once the conditions are in place uh The Gardener has to make room and
give time and be patient for everything to develop and grow
and so the question is what are we what are the conditions to put in
place many years ago I met um um a young
monk one of the first monks I met in Thailand when the first time I went there when I went to a meditation
Monastery and was clearly it was had a reputation of being a very very deep practitioner realized
Buddhist in some ways and it was remarkable to look into his eyes very deep
peaceful so I asked him uh what he had attained uh through his practice not
knowing at that time that that was somewhat an impolite question to ask a monk because they're actually not
supposed to um they're not allowed it's very uh uh strict rule for man ICS not
to talk about their spiritual attainments with a lay person but I didn't know that so I asked
him what had he attained through his practice and uh his his answer struck me
very deeply and has affected me ever since um he said nonc
contention and uh and so this idea of living a life of
non-c contention is one way of saying to live a peaceful
life to live with peace and to sit in
meditation leaving alone other aspects of our life for now to sit in meditation
and create the conditions for the plant to grow create the conditions to be
influenced in a good way uh it really helps to practice non-c
contention it helps to practice peace ease to be at ease with what's happening
for us and that's what we bring that's what
we need to in some ways produce as hard as it might be
to bring at least a mind form of mindfulness a more a form of relating to
our exper experience that is peaceful or easeful nonc
contentious and so of course we have contention in our life but the task then
is to hold the contention with non-c contention hold it peacefully so that uh the peace is what
influences us and shapes us and grows in us we don't want to have contention
growing we don't want to have hostility growing conflict growing and not a few people are
cultivating conflict with themselves
and if we concerned with the world around us let's not cultivate more
contention let's cultivate wise contention let's cultivate the capacity
to be peaceful at ease as we engage in difference differences in opinion as we
engage in the challenges of our life not only is a good for ourselves but it
creates good conditions for the world so to assume a meditation
posture ideally it's a posture of nonc
contention I've known people who have come across a meditator sitting in a a
classic meditation posture and there was something about the peace
Stillness of that person that changed the viewer for their
lifetime one person I know uh became a meditator and a
practitioner someone else that I read about became a Buddhist
teacher because I was so struck she had lived such a contentious life a rebel
life angry with the world and she saw someone sitting in this
posture that she thought this is a posture of Peace how do people do
this gently closing your eyes
and breathing in such a way that you spread a
calming a calmness through your
body maybe breathing longer slower
Fuller maybe on the ex exhale longer
exhale having like a wave a shower of
calmness flow through your body from the top to the bottom
and letting your breathing be normal as you
exhale to whatever degree you can can you set your body at
ease releasing any ways in which you hold the body body
tense ways in which you brace yourself against life for what's
coming as you exhale setting your heart heart at
ease the wave of calming the
heart enveloping the heart with a care a
calmness a peace so the tensions of the heart can
relax soften
and relaxing the Mind setting the mind at
ease and if you feel uneasy in any
way see if you can be easy with
that hold it
lightly and can you find within body mind or
heart some reference point for being at
peace being peaceful or
calm or at ease
and to breathe with a
peace or imagine that as you exhale or
inhale that you're spreading the peace the calm the
ease through your body
breathing breaths of
Peace where you relate to your breathing very lightly
softly gently
and if it's helpful for you if it's nice you might ever so
gently say in a peaceful way the word peace
as you
exhale
for
e
for for
recognizing whatever Cal or peace is in your body your heart your
mind and allowing that to have a influence fluence on
you allow that
to spread be received in the rest of the
body let it be a rem
Remer that you can feel calm or
peaceful and it can spread through your body mind and
heart spreading with every
breath
e
for
e for
as we come to the end of this
sitting may we consider is there any way that you
feel now having been meditated that could be a gift for our
world where there is
agitation may we bring our calm where there is
conflict may we bring our peace
where there is struggle let us bring our
ease where there is hatred may we bring our
love where there is suffering may we bring our compassion
pass where people feel
abandoned may we meet them with respect and
dignity seeing them clearly
and where there is need let us find a
way to support Others May this practice give
us the strength and the
inspiration to live for the the welfare and happiness of
Others May all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so good morning and welcome to the second talk in a series called to transform the
world and um one of the purposes for me being a
Buddhist teacher dedicating my life to Buddhist practice is
um to support this world to be able
to teach a path of practice that leads to the end of
suffering and the more that I know their suffering in the world the more I want
to meet it and address it and my particular way is through
Buddhist practice primarily that I understand to
be um pointing to the root causes the very Foundation of where suffering and
conflict arise and that uh I feel like it's very
important that we address suffering and conflict in all
the ways that can alleviate it but that we shouldn't neglect the root
causes and since there's very few people who do that uh I think I try to
specialize in that in some way or that's what the specialty of Buddhism is not to diminish the other ways the
extremely important but what what does Buddhism
have to offer what does this practice have to offer the world and
um it offers a profound example of a way of living not in
Conflict Not In Contention not in despair or anger or
and anxiety because we've seen the roots of
those we found what gives rise to those difficult emotions we've learned how to settle
Beyond it we've learned how to let go in a very deep way but not a letting
go that removes us from the world many years
ago I a teacher of mine said that um the
Buddha taught the world to sit and meditate Mahatma Gandhi
taught the world that it uh it's uh significant where you sit and
meditate and so I understood this statement to be that it's one thing to go meditate
alone now to develop peace for oneself it's another thing to uh
sit um uh and meditate in front of of
uh tanks approaching violence in the
works sit and be peaceful in the presence of those who are
contentious so the idea that we would not just be alone and practice for
ourselves but to practice for others to be the kind of people who can be agents of
change but how do we change the World there are many ways the world
changes and I don't want to diminish any of the values of the wholesome ways of
ethical ways of changing the world for the better but uh I think that uh to do it
with love and to do it with be with being um
carriers of Peace agents of peace and these two are so important
and uh one reference point I have for this is raising children and children who are not
loved uh grow up in problematic ways that it's a huge impact on a child
not to be seen not to be loved to feel it's almost a form of trauma to not have
that if a child grows up with parents are always anxious the child learns that
the world is a scary place and there's reasons to be anxious if a child grows up with angry
parents maybe the child grows up afraid maybe the child grows up shut
down maybe the child grows up to be angry as well and uh there's a phenomena where
people who are bullied people who are oppressed people who are
um will then turn around and do the same to the people who are lower than them on
the social picking order and just perpetuates the
cycle and um and so but if children grow up with peace they learn that there is
peace in this world it is possible to breathe at peace and be at ease if
children learn to uh uh see generosity see caring for others then
they learn that that's valuable and it's possible for that that what they learn
growing up the conditions in which they grow up in has a huge impact on children
that can affect them their whole life human beings are conditioned
creatures we are conditioned we are influenced by the things that come our way that how we
live and so the same thing is true for us that uh if we live angry we are
reinforcing anger and developing within us if we live peacefully or with love we
we enforce that and one of the characteristics of this is that some activities that are
object focused that are so much about hating someone so much about wanting
power so much about getting something thing um uh it Narrows the
attention it it disconnects people from themselves there's other ways of living
that open up a connection to ourselves and others that doesn't narrow it and uh
and put blinders on so love without Need
Love Without craving or clinging is the one that opens us up to see more widely
ourselves in the world being at peace is an experience
that opens us up to see more widely and be present for what's happening to be mindful to be present to
be respectful to be caring to be compassionate all these have a very can
can have a very different movement that uh is opening and spreading rather than narrowing and
Contracting and so ites makes a world of difference which of these we take and now either one conditions us
either one has a influence on us if we live peacefully it creates more peace in
ourselves if we live peacefully it spreads peace if we live in Conflict it
spreads conflict and some of these things are self-fulfilling if we live in conflict
and in Anger it's more likely that people will be in conflict with us and be hostile towards
us people don't like to have hostility directed to them and they'll turn away or or bark
back if we meet the world with peace with love with care then um that doesn't
give people as much occasion to be angry to be hostile it might even make hostile
people peaceful um and
um I've had conflict with people where the conflict seemed to you know have no
end in sight when we stayed apart but when I go towards a person sit with a
person and I sit that with peacefully and uh attentively and caringly and
willing to be open to our conversation to find out what's going on for the other person more often than not it's
settles things it creates more the conditions for some kind of
Frank and careful conversation of course there's no guarantee and maybe some things are only
happen in the long term some things happen in the aggregate over time with many
people but to a very important way uh we create the world uh according
to how we are if we want a world that's peaceful it's important that we live
peacefully if if we want to have a world where
love where the power of love is stronger than the love for
power we need to trust the love and live with love and give strength to our
love so to find a way to live to find a way of
being that is the message we want the world to hear the influence that we want
to have on the world and we should never succumb to the
belief that our singular individual efforts make no
difference they're not big enough they're not important enough we should never hand over the authority of the
wellbeing being to others others have to change others have to do
something others have to stop if we're waiting for others to
change we will never be agents of change that changes the world for the
better if you're waiting for others to change change the world then in some ways we are showing
the world a resignation a p I ity a giving up our own
agency may it be that as we
um uh may it be that you all become agents of
change not in a way to exhaust you not a way to stress you not no way to um um
maybe even change your life too much but that you go through this world in a way
that gives love kindness peace
care respect a prominent role in how you meet
the world don't be distracted don't find yourself narrowing
your attention around a desire a fear and
hostility so you're not available to open up to the all of who you are so
that the fullness of you is what
conveys peace into this world the fullness of you is conveys care non-c
contention everyone can do this
and uh I hope that meditation is one way that teaches us
guides us to this possibility may we be agents of
Peace in every way we talk and every way we walk and every way that
we um
meet others may we be agents of peace
thank you