to this morning meditation in
California and as a gathering of a community here to meditate together and
a gathering of each of us uh Gathering all the desperate parts of who we are
into some kind of hole some kind of uh Gathering into the present moment
so all of us is included
and the way that we include it all is um different ways but I like to suggest that um the
most valuable place to uh at the kind of a maybe at a
center of our inner life that can grow in a certain kind of
warmth or pleasure or in kind of an inspired feeling
of of um The Source within us the
home is not something to focus on
directly but rather somewhat indirectly kind of like it's on the periphery of
awareness and that on the center of awareness is is uh a number of different
experiences within of stability to feel stable here and
now and it can be a stability in the
body and it can be a stability in the
mind and it can be a stability in Awareness that thew awareness is softly
gently stable here without having too much of a sense
of awareness is focused on something if anything it's focused on this feelings
of stability and then on the
periphery as we breathe the source of breathing the or
this or some inner sense of where the source of Life source of
of uh Vitality of Love of warmth some inner place of goodness that
we might have and if we have no such place then
maybe just a uh uh a simple kind of
peripheral awareness of breathing where the breathing what we kind of become
aware of in breathing is an easy breath a soft breath
the parts of breathing that just that breathes itself even if you control your
breathing and breathing is forced or whatever kind of rest with where the
breathing feels relaxed maybe not forced it could be in
the movements of the back rib cage it could be the movements of the
shoulders as you breathe or something deep in the
abdom so hopefully uh as we go along here you'll understand what I
mean so to assume a meditation posture that for
you gives you a feeling of stability so if you're sitting in a
chair or a couch adjust yourself so that
some parts of your body are against the surface maybe the the chair the seats of
the chair that you feel some that could supports you as a stable
base if you're sitting on the floor maybe whatever way you're sitting
maybe cross-legged that you feel the stability that the three points of the cross-legged
posture provide at the base
if you're sitting on a couch resting against the back rest maybe there's a way
of sitting up a little straighter still resting your back
against the back rest but sitting a little straighter so that the chest is a
little bit more open rather than
collapsing if you're laying down then to adjust your body in such a way
that you feel the points of contact with bed the
floor provides kind of a feeling of strength or stability or
groundedness if you have your knees up uh and your SES of your feet on the
floor The Souls of the feet can provide stability as The Souls of the Fe feet
can for people sitting in a chair so feel the physical
stability that's available to you doesn't have to be dramatic could be
subtle stability
steadiness and then as you exhale let go into that
stability almost as if all the tensions of your body can
soften and help with a settling into the
stability spreading a sense of stability through the body
and then as you exhale see if you can do the same for
whatever tension agitation restlessness there might be
in the thinking
mind let the thinking mind relax
soften so the mind also begins to rest and spread out into some kind of
inner mental place of stability or
steadiness or a sense of supportive Stillness
you don't have to let go of your thoughts as much as behind the thoughts
or driving the thoughts together with the thoughts any tension
pressure tightness activation in your body
associated with thinking as you
exhale soften relax let the
Mind settle into a stability as if gravity
gently receives pulls on the mind
and then without ambition or idea that you
can actually do this maybe it's just a little bit an act of imagination for some of
you turn your attention around so that you're aware of being
aware
and the kind of weightless weight of awareness can the awareness be somewhat
still not jumping around not chasing
things maybe this Stillness of an open window where
whatever Breeze or wind or warmth or insects there might be
outside comes to the window with no effort from the
window so let your awareness be still and open
and with these three reference points of stability
Stillness either all three at once kind of like they're a
big something big circle of stability that work together
with your peripheral awareness become aware of breathing but
don't focus on the breath it's almost like you're aware of
a shy cat on the edge of your peripheral
vision and you know you can't approach it directly or stare at
it so you kind of ignore it and kind of aware of
it and so become aware of
breathing becoming aware of the source of breath where it begins
in the way that one way or the
other the body breathing is caring for
you is is engaging you in a process of
respiration which keeps you alive and then that peripheral awareness
of breathing maybe you can feel the inner
goodness or warmth with
breathing staying at rest with the stability in the body mind and awareness
not making the breathing the central focus of attention but more as something which
you see on the edge of
awareness without expectations of breathing or trying to make it
something without trying to make anything out of
it just allowing yourself to
breathe so that cat can become comfortable and feel safe with
you
e
for
e e
leaving your breathing alone but
peripherally aware of how breathing the experience in your body of
breathing moves through your body touching
moving Awakening different areas of your
body with each in breath and each out breath but not focusing
directly
e e
letting your thinking mind become quieter Stiller
so that the shy
breathing like a shy
cat feels more comfortable to be present to show itself to
you without you looking at it directly
for
e
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting to once
again feel whatever degree of stability or
Stillness there is in the body and take a few moments to breathe
with that
and to take a few moments to feel whatever stability or Stillness is find
in found in the mind maybe in the thinking mind underneath your
thoughts and breathe with that
and if it uh it makes sense to you feel whatever stability or
Stillness steadiness there is in attention in your
awareness and not so much focusing on the breath but allowing
breathing to arrive and gently
touch awareness
and feeling the overall the wholeness of stability
within with your peripheral attention the edges of a
awareness be aware of whatever
inner well-being there might be or feel the
source maybe a little dot or
spot of tenderness or warmth or goodness
that's within you
and let that softness warmth goodness the feeling of
it gently have room to grow in your
body without focusing on or
trying almost allowing the peripheral awareness to make more
room for a natural process
and without focusing on some inner place of
well-being but allowing it to be there trusting
it turn your gaze out into the world with your
imagination of the day the people you'll meet and see and the strangers you'll
pass by andage upon them with Good
Will with well wishing that each person that you
encounter you wish them a good day you wish
them happiness and love and friendship and
peace you wish that they able to have a day that's
satisfying and meaningful
and may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be
[Music]
free thank than you
so good morning everyone or good day and welcome to this third
talk on the road L uh taken and and uh the idea being that in
Buddhist practice there's always we're always standing at the
junction of two directions we could take we could either do something in the wide
realm right variety of ways that are wholesome or we can go in the direction
that's UNH wholesome and it's rare that there's a third way right down the middle of
neither wholesome or unome and even if there is it's a lost
opportunity every step we take can be done with a kind of attention and warmth
and uh that it makes it wholesome it makes it good nothing we do needs to be
either neutral or UNH wholesome everything we do that with the step we
take what arises within us that we have no
volition personal volition they didn't choose to do it may be UNH wholesome um but then to meet that with
wholesome to recognize it wholesomely to avoid participating in it in a Wholesome
Way not to reject it or be aversive or just oh this too wow I'll think I'll
leave that alone and that would be could be done wholesomely out of care for
yourself so we always have this so learning about this this uh the path and
that here we calling the road L less taken but it's also can be understood as a whole different operating system
there's two operating systems within us and uh and one is has to do a lot with
the world we make up and live and the constructs of self and the future and
other people that uh is not really there but is a projection on to ourselves or
others and there's a whole different world we can walk in operating
system and here I'm going to read a story from my my my book of tales called
a monastery within the title of this uh this story
is inside out an engineer had been a regular and devoted
visitor to the monastery for many years the meditation practice taught at the
monastery was the only thing that made sense to him in fact the pragmatic logic
of the meditation teachings gave him hope that he could overcome his chronic
unhappiness and deeply felt pain he tried all the meditation practices that
the abbis taught him he began each practice technique with
enthusiasm only to have each end with the same frustration he would encounter a wall he
couldn't pass the closer he came to the wall the more he would recoil back into
trying to think his way out of his pain offering him much support the abis
encouraged him to relax trust the practice and simply feel his inner pain
without reacting to it after many years the abbis decided a different approach
was needed during his next visit to the monastery the abis told told him that he
wanted to continue being her student and to be able to return to the
monastery he would have to take on a special practice once he had completed the
assignment he could then return for deeper teachings once more feeling hope the
engineer quickly agreed the Abba said for 2 years I want
you to volunteer 10 hours a week at the Maternity Ward at the local hospital the
hospital needs people to hold babies who are born prematurely if these babies don't
receive enough physical contact the babies will not grow healthily when you have finished these
two years please come back to see me the man was quite perplexed by this
instruction but because of his trust in the abbis and his failure to find any relief elsewhere he plunged into
volunteering in the maternity ward he was surprised by how small and
fragile the babies were that he held he would hold them ever so carefully he
would watch their every breath because they all seemed in danger of stopping breathing he spent a lot of time
thinking about how he could more effectively care for the babies he held
but there was nothing more effective than simply holding them against his chest
after about 6 months he started feeling something quite new he started to feel a
little spot of warmth and softness in the very center of his being since this
was a foreign experience that didn't fit any of the ways he taught about
themselves he ignored it ignoring it was the best thing he could have
done because it prevented him from interfering with the warmth by thinking
about it too much over the following months this tender spot grew until it
pervaded his body as it did the cold dark wall around his heart slowly
relaxed thawed and dissolved when he had completed his two
years of volunteering in the Maternity Ward the engineer returned to the
monastery the abis saw immediately that he was a changed man he was no longer
desperate and he was no long longer trying to fit everything he experienced into a conceptual
framework now he wanted to learn what else the Abus had to teach giving him a new instruction the
abis said to him when you meditate don't think about
what is happening rather let your awareness be
seated in the tender warmth you feel in your body if you do this any meditation
practice you do will be fruitful and the man found this to be
true so uh there's this other operating
system within us there's the operating system of consentual conceptual Frameworks um uh ideas madeup stories we
have about ourselves judgments the swirl of kind of the mental activity that is
an an operating system that often can be based on things which are not healthy for US based on fear and anxiety it can
be based on conceit and delusion it can be based on Greed and and uh it can be
based on hatred and anger and these things uh come from an operating system
which tends to kind of reinforce itself the more we do it and create a lot of tension and fragmentation within us
there's another operating system system that um is the one that was operating for this uh
engineer that uh he didn't know about that uh he was he was offering his
tender care for these little babies and there's something about that contact
that touched something deep inside of himself some source of of of um of care
of Love of warmth of simple tenderness that um because it kept re
returning there started to grow and expand and open and this other operating
system that he didn't know about began to fill him and uh and uh he became a better
person because of it he was able then to learn to meditate um he learned something about meditation that was not
doing meditation like an like a uh technical problem to accomplish um to
meditate by the numbers and to focus and and put everything into place like an engineering uh
construction um there's nothing wrong necessarily with doing meditation by the
numbers by having a technique that we do but as he learned now any meditation
practice he did will be successful any meditation practice you do if you have
this other source other operating system in which you do it from which it uh it'll be
successful and this second operating system uh is less to do about doing than
it is about allowing less to do with uh accomplishment than it is to do about
appreciation less to do with um striving as it is to do about being soft and
accepting and um and it's so it's not just doing this naively and you can't do
this necessarily with the this second operating system uh you can't think your
way into tenderness you can't think your way into it necessarily if that's where the
solution is you might have thoughts that allow to touch into this deeper place
even just imagining you're holding pries might be enough for some people to kind of drop down and really be here in a
tender way um but uh uh you can't construct all that you have to allow
something within and each person will have a different Source inside for this
other this is inner operating system some people might feel it intimately connected to breathing some people it
might be in the heart some people will find it deeper than the heart um that
there's a long history in Budd to find something really uh valuable
deep profound somewhere in the belly area deep down the abdomen Japan they call it the
Hara um maybe it's okay to call it uh you know associated with where the Boom
is in the body that the place of there something gestates something grows and
that you can't make a human being uh a um
a mother cannot make the child grow in the womb but
creates the conditions for it and allows it and can feel tenderness and warmth towards it but um and then it then the
thing Grows by itself the person grows so it can be
um uh so may it be that today that uh
every thing you touch with your hands the the keys of a computer board
or a device the utensil in the kitchen steering wheel of your car what
everything that you're actually touching with your hand touch it be with it with a kind of
care that you would be with a prei if you were holding it uh and see if that's kind of
everyday in your everyday activities that the objects of touch what comes into your hand if you be with it
caringly not casually not off hand not pref not kind of kind of doing it you
know half consciously you know you're thinking of doing doing it for another purpose and just doing it opening a door
to get someplace else you know you can do it you open doors so many times
Everything You Touch today let it be a place for your care for your attention for something deep
inside to come forth uh as you live your life of course the other things you're
doing might be important and so it's easy to overlook the opening the door
but nothing can be more important than Awakening this beautiful
operating system we have and having that come forth in into our life so that
everything becomes
sacred so thank you very much