good evening welcome welcome I think I moved oh there we go
it's okay I was going to say I moved the microphone but it it's still all
right nice to see you all it's nice to sit
together so tonight I wanted to talk a little bit about uh the holiday season
it's not uncommon to see reference to or hear reference to or something about
this idea of a wish list this idea of you know things that are
wanted if this exists year round we often have wish list we even have a you
know organ Amazon right just has a little wish list make they all these uh
online I shouldn't say all many of the these online things have just make it as easy easy as possible for you to just
clickity click click and uh there you go you can make a list of all the things
that you wish that you had that you wanted and so this way there's and maybe
in particular this time of year I don't know there's this like this valorization of Desire like it's really held up oh
what is your wish list what what what do you want whether that's because of the new
year because of Christmas or for other uh
holidays what is this sense of uh what do we want or or maybe it can be uh
interpreted as well what should I give you so that you'll be happy or what am I going to give you so
that I'll be happy so that I'll feel good about myself or something like that
this uh intersection of desires and objects being exchanged and happiness
and or maybe that we could just say this time of year maybe there's we could just
highlight the beauty actually of uh opportunities to reflect on and maybe
act on you know those people that we care about that are important to us or part of our
lives and to express care love
appreciation in whatever way that shows up I I was helping my mom with her
Christmas cards my family celebrates Christmas and uh it's really sweet right
you know she's been sending Christmas cards to these same people 50 years you know and there's a little newsletter
that goes with it you know this year we did X Y and Z and stuff like this it's a
beautiful beautiful gesture I think I think and of course you know she receives some too and it's
nice but this idea of what you want or desire you know often has a bad rap
guess a bad rap in Buddhism this idea of that okay you know desire just leads to
suffering and I remember um somebody this was years ago when they discovered
that I was a Buddhist practitioner this is something that they just first thing what they wanted to say is oh yeah I
heard that Buddhism I don't like desire but how crazy is that I mean you can't
even desire to not have desire or you can't desire to be
awakened I was like no no no it's not like that it's not like that but you know that was their kind of idea on the
outside looking in and certainly maybe in the when we first start practicing and maybe I had that idea too I can't
remember this idea like oh yeah we somehow we should be free of uh all
desires and that's not quite how it works that's not quite how it works and
so today I'd like to unpack a little bit this IDE IDE of desire and partly of how it can be a big
support for our path to Greater freedom and peace and ease as well as you know
it can be problematic so maybe I'll start by saying you know of course in the broad
sense in the very broad sense that uh desire is just a natural part of the
human experience of the desire to eat when we're hungry desire to use the bathroom when
the body needs to eliminate waste right these are just natural things that happen we also have you know just these
like leanings we might say or inclinations or aspirations or you know
this uh going a particular direction of course we do of course we
do there not a we're not trying to get rid of this or deny it or somehow turn
ourselves into machines that would be awful we're not machines we're
humans and we have uh human bodies and human temperaments that's just the way
it is and it's a beautiful thing so but there's also a way in which
we also have cravings and addictions and some uh clinging that are
harmful harmful to ourselves harmful to others that's part of the human condition too very
often and so that Buddha of course he didn't teach that all Desir should be
eliminated these healthy ones that desire for food or connection or the desire for not causing harm or for the
desire for greater ease greater Freedom greater peace of course those should be
cultivated and worked with and instead of trying to eradicate
all the ones that we feel like oh I I shouldn't feel this way or something
like this can we understand them and transform these desires into something
that can be helpful so as you might imagine uh
classically in the Buddhist tradition that the desires are put in two camps those that are helpful and those are
that are not helpful cusa is the PO word I'm translating it as helpful it's kind of
our experience of it is as helpful there's all kinds of other English words that we could use but I'm going to stick
with this idea of helpful helpful for more ease in our life helpful for more
peace helpful for more freedom helpful for more ease uh equinity all all kinds
of this things that we really want in our life so the helpful ones we could say
are those that are aligned with well-being that contribute to well-being maybe
that's just a simple way to think about it and it's not only well-being for ourselves but contributes to well-being
for others and I am making a distinction here between wellbeing and
pleasure you know well-being is a sense of that promotes health and balance and
some stability and spaciousness as opposed to just pleasure that just leads
to wanting more pleasure and can lead to heedlessness and things
that make our life go arai or can make our life
go so those not only that promoting a sense of well-being but they're characterized by the experience of some
spaciousness or some
lightness I mean this is like such a small example but today while I was out for a walk
um apparently it's the conditions for lots of mushrooms to pop up and I it was just so fantastic I'm walking like whoa
wow and just some of they were just ginormous this huge like white uh
mushrooms and I just took Delight in them walking a little further and then I saw some that were a different color and
they were so small they were so cute and I just felt my heart like who knew that
underneath the ground were all these uh risom of uh you know these fun dry and
uh and then there was this desire to well how many different types of mushrooms are here so while I'm walking
along I'm keeping an eye and I don't know it was just fun and it just made me appreciate like wow what you know these
are here all the time under the soil and we just don't see them until uh it's
dark and rainy and I don't know exactly what the conditions are but apparently the conditions are being met right now
at least in the some places so this desire to like feel that Delight again
when I'm seeing all these different mushrooms different types different
colors and different places and so there's this sense of lightness and a little bit of a uplift uh we might say
Associated that's just it's harmless uh desire and maybe that's a silly
example but we could say that desire for spiritual growth
desire for Liberation from suffering or we could say desire for not
causing harm to ourselves or to others to live an ethical
Life One in which we're you know being sensitive to the impact that we're having on others and uh in the world
that can show up in so many ways and then in contrast we could say well this unhelpful desire is the one
that we might use the the expression craving that falls into like I got to
have it I got to have it I don't care about all this other stuff I got to have
this and there's this way this craving has a this un Like It's associated with
a contraction in the body and this uh maybe this compulsion that's uh moving
us forward towards I I got to get this cigarettes
shopping gambling alcohol food it's amazing the things that we can
crave right the things that we can really want and have this sense of okay
well as soon as I get this then I'll feel better I just got to
get this and I I don't care how I feel right now I'm not noticing how uncomfortable it feels I just got to get
this thing whether it's a brownie or drugs or whatever it might be alcohol
it's it's just there's no end to the things that we can become addicted to or just
crave so not only like made things that we're addicted to but there's a way that
which we can crave or maybe I'll I could use a different word also like cling
to and this can be this maybe even material possessions this idea is that there's
some objects that okay as soon as I have this then that'll be a source of lasting
happiness we don't use that language but that's what's underneath it we think okay not only will it be pleasurable for
a moment when I get it but it'll be a source of lasting happiness so I want to just do a little
experiment a little uh with you guys or a little um uh exercise
here because there's this way in which exploring
desire can be enormously helpful very powerful way to find more
freedom not always easy not always comfortable not always fast and neat and
tidy but powerful so let's like just bring to
mind something you want and for now let's focus well I'll
give some examples so something you want it could be something significant it could be like objects a
car house different place to live or maybe a relationship if you don't have one
right now or whatever you know something something like something significant to you like that would different job to
live in a different place place or it could be just something minor or
small like a grande skinny half
CF I wrote it down here pumpkin spice latte with two pumps extra hot you know
like it's impressive right all these things that uh you can have at your favorite uh Barista can serve
you so it can be whatever you want you know something like this it could be a long-term goal like a degree a
certification payoff loans you know something like this or um it could be
something just fleeting like you know what I'm just didn't have enough dinner earlier and I'm kind of hungry and I'm thinking of having some burritos or or
some cookies or whatever it might be so just bring to mind something that you feel like you would
want and maybe just I I don't know feel into
uh how you what it feels like oh yeah I'd like to have
uh I finally get a new car that uh can impress the neighbors and demonstrate
that I've uh finally made it financially successful or or a car that demonstrates
that I'm ecologically minded I get an electric car or something like
this and then just notice how your mood changes when you start to thinking about
oh yeah as soon as a loans are paid off or as soon as the grandchild is uh born
or uh you know whatever it might be whatever it might be and there's this
way in which we start when we start to think about what we want there's often this little bit of an
uplift there's this way in which this sense of s sadness or heaviness might
shift to oh yeah it's going to be great as soon as I
get this thing that I want can you feel into that this maybe a sense of uplift
that happens maybe there's a sense of some
tension goes away or maybe there's some sense a little bit more calm as you're
fantasizing about how great it's going to be when what you want finally
is has arisen you have
it there's this way in which you might feel lighter or happier or maybe even
more connected because when there's this way when
there's a sense of a future promise future promise or something that's
bigger that's about to happen it somehow can make our life seem promising Ing and
exciting can make it I don't know like there's some juiciness to it in uh some kind of
way and this can be a nice feeling it's not surprising that we often are lost in fantasies about uh what we're going to
have we don't call them fantasies but this is completely 100% fantasy right what you were just thinking about is not
here right this uh moment
so there's this way that maybe we can stay with
this uh what we want noticing how the mind and the body
kind of liked to have this sense of wanting but now can you have a gentle
inquiry what is the subtle belief that is underneath it like what do you think
will happen once you obtain whatever it is that is the object of your desire is
this I'm assuming that there's this implicit belief that achieving it will
improve your life I think that's a reasonable
assumption but can you be a little bit more specific I want to promotion because
then I will earn more money and have more respect
and then when we say that it's often really
subtle is this sense of lack I don't have enough
money I don't have enough respect they should respect me more I
should have more money and that doesn't feel good that does to have that like
sense of lack doesn't feel good or maybe there's this place I want to have a bigger place to live a better place to
live because then I can invite people over and I can have parties and uh
there'll be room for lots of people and then I won't feel so lonely
maybe it's like ouch like to feel into the sense of
loneliness or the sense of lack or whatever it might
be and so there's this way that uh
often it's these subtle feelings of things not being quite
right I want more that's actually fueling our
desires but if we can recognize what it is that's fueling these desires and to
be with it as best we can this will lead to Greater
Freedom this will lead to Greater peace and ease not just getting one more thing
whether it's the promotion whether it's the degree whether it's the
cupcake because there's this way in which it's so easy to live our lives
just chasing desire after the another our whole life could be nothing but this
just trying to get the next thing I got a feel better I got to feel better and we're just completely ignoring this
Dua this uh things have sensed not being right this can be subtle or it can be
really loud this is not easy it's not
comfortable it's not fun but there's a way when we just
simply acknowledge oh yeah there's loneliness I feel lonely
and can we acknowledge it and still have some uprightness and feel the loneliness
maybe in the body the heaviness in the shoulders or tightness in the
chest maybe some pressure behind the eyes and then can we just loneliness
feels like this we don't have to say it should be different in fact
it's just the way it is humans feel lonely sometimes even people
who are very um gregarious and you know extroverted and are surrounded around
people they feel lonely sometimes can we like normalize and
honor and respect our experience instead of thinking like I
should be different looking at all those other people they have lots of money surely they're happy
how many really rich people do we know that are in the media all the time and
are clearly not happy you can see by all the weird things that they do if they
were happy they would not be out there doing that weird
stuff so there's this way in which recognizing
desire and there's you know it brings some uplift and part of this uplift lift
is recognizing that or maybe part of us um
in the present moment we can just recognize that the
illusion of this fictitious Bliss this fictitious Bliss this completely thing
that's a fantasy that okay as soon as I get that it's uh going to be fine will
never let's say let me say it a different way our present moment experience
will never be as wonderful as this fictitious Bliss it just won't here's one key reason there's a
number of reasons here's one key reason this little thing called
anicha impermanence things change the Buddha pointed to this as well right
there's that what we gain we eventually lose including like this hedonic
treadmill something that makes us happy stops making up us happy and there's this way in which Joy
turns into sorrow soy sorrow turns into joy as well I
don't know what soy turns into I guess but well I guess it depends if you eat
it well okay we could go down there but so it's just things are changing
that's just the natural way things are but in our fictitious Bliss it's just
like okay I'm going to get this and it's going to be a source of lasting Happiness full stop right it's just not
going to happen that way and there's this way in which actually this um there
can be a little bit of a relief to realize oh it's not that I'm failing
it's not that I'm doing everything wrong that I had these fantasies these ideas about how things should be and I'm not
quite as happy and this is my story I'll say of how I find myself here
having a PhD in Biochemistry and yet here I am being a Darman teacher like how did that
happen and I'm a very slow learner because uh I went to school have all
this hyper educated and uh was a biochemist I love biochemistry but
somehow you know having a lot of professional success and yet oh yeah
yeah okay that that didn't quite make me happy and I'm a slow learner because then I went back back to graduate school
think okay I just have to learn something else and became you know in Buddha studies and I have another graduate
degree in Buddha studies and then realize oh yeah okay that that didn't quite make me happy in
the way that I thought it would either right there's this way in which we just for me it was this idea that I just have
to learn more I just have to learn more it's not surprising you know having
this coming from my family background and stuff and so how many things have
you just thought okay well I just maybe that wasn't the right car or it wasn't the right whatever it
is it can be a relief to think like no actually our ideas about things they're
I kind of like this word fantasies which you know is a little bit pejorative but the truth is they're just
thoughts they're just ideas they're just uh
imaginations we have they have a place they have a role but our actual
experience will never match sometimes it'll be better
sometimes it'll be worse but it'll never match what we're imagining maybe we'll be a happier it'll
be more pleasurable than what we were imagining but it will
change this is something about fantasies that don't really take that into
account so what are the what are wants this is part of you know working with
them or being with them or honoring and respecting them they're just simply a thought that's arising from an
underlying belief they're just thoughts often uh they're very quiet
maybe we'll call them beliefs that they're maybe not you know articulated so clearly as thoughts but you know
they're completely you know insubstantial but these ideas that
promise a different imagined future but when we look at our desires
what we want we can kind of like look underneath to see okay what are the underlying
belief will make me feel secure uh I'll no longer feel afraid
people will respect me I will other people will love
me and then we can just pay attention to
that we're complex beings humans we have all these things under there and so much
we don't want to acknowledge but paying attention to our desires and what's
underneath it and can we be with that and sometimes it can be helpful to
not and to drop the labels yeah I want to be loved I feel
unloved can we feel that in the body and then drop the labels and just
be with the bodily experience right now it feels like this
it feels uh heavy it feels like really tight
feels like uh wanting to hide or something like
this so we might reflect on is are we trying to escape from something are we
trying to reject a part of ourselves are we dismissing a part of ourselves is there something we're trying to avoid
and then just to be with the experience to stop
avoiding as best we can and even if it's just for a fleeting
moment just to acknowledge it can we hold the space for
this for the bodily experience for the belief and then there was a uh
underneath that was like I want to be loved and then the bodily experience that's associated with wanting to be
loved can we just be with that hold the space with it
and this will lead to Greater peace this will lead to Greater Freedom this will
lead to Liberation a Liberation from being pushed around from always chasing
our desires chasing the next thing okay well
as soon as I get this next thing it's going to be fine we have those ideas When We're
Young until we get a number of things and we realize oh yeah I'm still not happy
so some we it doesn't help that you know somebody to tell you for somebody like me to be sitting here and to be saying
oh yeah uh it's not going to be satisfying we all have to have that experience ourself but as we get older
we realize yeah what I thought was going to make me happy
wasn't the pleasures that we seek they evaporate
quickly and we overestimate how much happiness they will bring this is part
of the human
condition so what I just described is not easy it's not fast it's probably exactly
what you don't want to do instead it's so much I nicer to think like okay as soon as I get uh this car
or as soon as I retire as soon as uh I move to that other place I I don't know right we our lives are filled with these
things that we can want but here are some things to do to make it easier or to be a
support bring curiosity to desires this is a starting place okay I
really do want this whatever that list was half calf extra hot um pumpkin spice
latte skinny I don't know there were some other things there lower two pumps oh
two pumps that's right I said two pumps thank you three pups I guess if you really
want it [Laughter] right that was so great thank [Laughter]
you so just bring a curiosity to it you
can bring curiosity to like oh yeah how we're so often focused on the object
that thing out there but can we bring some curiosity
well how does it feel both we can curiosity about that
thing but also what's our experience we have this idea um um it'll be soothing
it'll be comforting I deserve it it's the holiday season pumpkin spice latte I
did go into the particular coffee shops website and try to get some ideas here
and they have like gingerbread lattes peppermint lattes is quite something right for the
holidays but so this brings some curiosity to what do
I why do I want it what is what is the why do I want it
and what is the experience of wanting it like is it feeling like oh yeah like
we're dis completely disconnected from our experience often instead we're thinking about okay what are we going to have
you know as soon as I get that that'll be great I'm going to maybe um share it with a friend we're both going to get
something and spend some time and I can connect and like oh okay there's this idea of comfort and wanting to
connect so just bring some curiosity to that experience and then the second thing
that we can do which is really important really important in our lives can we
just in general and small little Jes cultivate
contentment there are times in our life when we just things are fine maybe we're
going for a walk and we just notice there's mushrooms there's a little bit of
delight everything just perfectly fine nothing has to be different and just to
acknowledge right now nothing needs to be different there's this way in which we
kind of like uh to honor and respect those human experiences of
contentment as uh maybe uh orients the mind and the body
towards oh yeah this is possible it doesn't require that we get everything that we have or that we want sorry it's
about you know appreciating whatever is arising there in the moment and there's this way that
contentment can feel like the booby prize like okay if I can get what I want
okay I'll practice contentment you know there is but it turns
out that freedom is radical
contentment freedom is feeling like yep it's okay it's not being a bliss blob
it's like yep everything's okay this is what freedom is because the lack of
freedom is being pushed around by our desires I have to get this I have to avoid this other thing or whatever it
might be and we don't talk about freedom in this way we tend to think that freedom
means that we can have whatever we want but it's actually a radical contentment
like everything is okay it's not pretending like there isn't pain it's
not pretending like there isn't terrible injustices and pression in the world
it's not pretending that all that doesn't exist is just recognizing this moment just this moment
it's okay and maybe my life situation allows
me to help others maybe my life situation right now
is a tremendous amount of difficulties and I need to uh pay attention to my
responsibilities and what I can do to alleviate some of those difficulties and
maybe I'm have this inclination this wish to help others I can't support others as much as I'd like right now
right now I need to also pay attention to what's happening here but I have the contentment that right
now this is okay this is
okay so cultivating contentment allows us also to be with
desire because we start to really understand that oh I don't have to get
everything I want in order to feel
okay and not only that with this contentment is a a little taste of
Freedom maybe it's a big Taste of freedom and it's so I know when I first
heard this idea contentment I don't know it didn't sound so
appealing but now I love it it's turn turns out to be so great I've you know
done a lot of meditation and uh had a lot of meditative experiences but
there's something about contentment that is enormously
satisfying and this is what humans really want contentment
satisfaction a stopping of that that nagging like oh I got to get something
else it's not quite right so
desire wishless we might have a wishless that's
fine if you find that you really want something in particular an object you
can practice use that as like oh yeah there's a lot of Desire here and just use that as an opportunity to to maybe
understand yourself a little bit better look into what is the underlying belief that's uh fueling that desire that want
and can we just honor and respect that it can be a way of uh finding more ease
in the moment or maybe you have desire for world peace for yourself to not
cause harm to yourself to not cause harm to others maybe you have desire
for having compassion and loving kindness and these types of things the world some wholesome
desires and celebrate that cultivate those and can we cultivate
contentment as a way to help us have the steadiness that we can work with desire
so we're not just automatically falling into desire after
desire so I'll stop there and I'll open it up for some comments or questions
thank you
anybody have something they'd uh like to say or make a comment
on hello great talk thank you so in my experience uh when I
practice um with contentment uh and desire sometimes but not always
I can't quite distinguish between a wholesome
contentment uh and a not so wholesome apathy or disinterest or
disengagement or on the flip side of the spectrum distinguishing a wholesome
ambition um the kind of ambition that produces excellence in relationships or
career or um or art uh the wholesome ambition
from UNH wholesome egoic uh
desire and so uh contentment or ambition yeah distinguishing wholesome from UNH
wholesome I wonder if you have any thoughts on that I do I can this is a
great topic I should I could give a whole another Dharma talk on this uh um Al so I'll give some bullet points uh
here sure so one is um I use this uh for myself I use this uh feeling and you
this and uh you can kind like maybe transla into something that makes sense for you it doesn't necessarily what I'm
going to describe work for everybody the way I'm describing it but things that um are supportive so
like wholesome they have a sense of spaciousness I'm doing this with my hands there's this uh as opposed to a
contraction and so contra action feels like literally sometimes the muscles are tight the shoulders up near the ears or
there's a furrowing of the brow or but sometimes it's subtle there's a feeling like in the Torso like in the gut or in
the heart area there's like this tightness so the wholesome supportive
has this General sense of openness and ease so I'll say that's one one
thing um a second thing that is um a little bit more cognitive is if there is
a a certain uh clinging to particular outcomes I'm doing this in order that
this happens of course we do things we often have like an idea about what's
going to happen but there can be a way in which it's I got to get this and then
we're not in touch with ourselves or any harm we're causing to others or to ourselves or anything like this instead
we're just so focused I'm getting this thing dang it whether that's a ambition
or there can also be um a way that subtle uh contentment that is not
helpful turns out not to be contentment it turns about this apathy or disconnection or something there's this
subtle way in which the outcome is I don't want to
feel I don't want to feel as opposed to I feel this contentment
and so that that outcome is uh often subtle but there often if there's this
apathy or disconnection or something there's often can be um a lot of
avoidance behaviors like we're distracting ourselves with something and or there's some uh fogginess like they
just like just not clear we're just kind of disconnected Spacey or something like
that so spaciousness versus
constriction and uh uh clinging to particular outcomes as opposed to oh
yeah this is the next right thing to do I'm I I imagine it's going this direction but I'm just doing the next
right thing to do is what I'm focused on is is that helpful yeah that's helpful thank you
you're welcome I I I also kind of wondered about energy level in there as well where
contentment if it's really relaxed you there isn't a great
drive a compulsion to act if you're if uh with with spaciousness ease
relaxation there can be a nice contentment in a settling in such that you don't feel any
particular urge to go and create a great work of art or create a great project at work or yeah overcome a hurdle in a
relationship you're just so relaxed and at ease so I wonder about that
energy where does that energy come from and perhaps I want to challenge this
actually I want to challenge this idea I think with contentment for me it kind of like frees up energy that otherwise is
associated with trying to avoid things or something like that things are happy then it's also like inspiration like
there's new ideas for art or or for oh it's often when insights can arise like
oh right oh okay this problem can get solved by doing X Y or Z and then off
you go so there can be some energy with this too because often when there's
strong drive you know what's fueling it sometimes is some discontent right it's
like okay this has got to be different so and the drive comes
from yeah I guess so there can be energy with contentment as well cool yeah very
interesting landscape thank you yeah you're
welcome well maybe I'll end this evening I want to say something cute
um about wish lists checking it
twice I don't know see I don't know just this uh this idea that you know desire
is just part of our experience and is there a way that we can use it to
support greater Freedom peace and ease for ourselves and for others and for
others so thank you and on my wish list is for you all to have a safe travels
home and uh nice uh I guess New Year's is next year a week from now so a nice holiday
season if you're celebrating holidays thank you