all right welcome everyone nice to see you
arriving let's go ahead and start with our sitting together this
morning finding a posture where you'll be able to sit for half an hour or
so and just have the sense of arriving you know we can sometimes get
doing other things on the computer or we had to rush a little bit
to get here and just acknowledging that now we're now we're
here maybe allowing the body to settle back a bit the computer can be a a leaning
forward kind of activity so just allowing yourself to settle
back allowing the body body to be naturally
aligned closing the eyes if that's comfortable for
you and just having the sense of being here being in the place where you're
sitting
and sensing first into that contact where you're sitting or lying
down so your seat against the cushion or the chair or the
bed and noticing if that's a simple kind of contact where you're just resting and
allowing yourself to be held
up softening any EX extra muscular effort so that you're mostly just held
up by the structure of the body the
bones releasing extra muscle tension and allowing yourself to be supported and
you may notice then that the body naturally aligns Sometimes I rock back and forth a
little bit or forward and back just to assure that I'm in that
middle place of most
balance it makes a difference in the
sit and then
softening the face the muscles of the
scalp down through the shoulders and
torso arms and legs just inviting ease
sensing the full three-dimensionality of the body can you feel the front the back and
the sides of your
body with most of the sense organs on the front sometimes that's all we
feel but the body is quite three-dimensional
and we have senses toward the
back the idea of this initial part is to put the body in a position that is both
relaxed and and alert and that supports the
mind also to
maintain being relaxed and
alert I'm just inviting some ease in our connection to the
present there may may be places in the body that are painful there may be something present
in the mind that's not so much at ease
today and those things are fine as they
are and we can still have a stance of ease in relation to any unease or disease that's
present seeing if you can tune into to that
so I'll offer uh a few questions to drop
in to the sit and just see what the response is as
if we've dropped a stone down a well and we're listening for the
Splash and this is only if if you'd like you can also continue with your meditation if you would
like but it's kind of an invitation to tap in a little bit more
deeply with where we're at right
now so the first question is am I willing to meditate right
now and let there be any answer am I willing right now possibly
there will be more than one answer from different parts of the
Mind perhaps you've never asked that question at the beginning of a sit
and we don't need to do anything with the response except to
feel it what's the level of willingness right
now and then the next question there will be three the second one
is what is my current capacity to meet experience with
wisdom how much capacity do I have right now
this isn't a question about how much experience you
have necessarily even a very experienced
meditator could be having a tough day could be strained in various ways
such that there isn't much capacity or someone quite new to the
practice could be fully aligned have quite a lot of capacity at this
moment what is the capacity to meet experience with wisdom right
now what's
available and again we just feel what comes back from that question
and then the last question is do I know what to
do do I have instructions I'm intending to follow in order to meet experience
if I were silent for the rest of the sit would you know what to
do all right and then releasing this um question asking state of mind and
settling back into perhaps feeling the breath or the
body in the present moment and maybe
sense what kind of shift there's been from these questions for some it brings
in a sense of confidence or orientation at
least kind of knowing where we're at
and then open open again to the experience of the
body various energies Sensations the breath coming in
and
out open to how the mind feels their emotions or thoughts present
and the invitation for this sit is to have a fairly open kind of
awareness where we allow anything really to arise and pass
away and be felt but without getting sucked into it finding that
balance
e
for
e e
and when you find the Mind wandering losing connection with the
present moment flow of experience you could re-
evoke these questions of willingness
capacity and knowing what to do just reminding yourself where you're
at there just
briefly seeing if that helps realign or adjust somehow what the mind is
doing sometimes with an open type awareness
if it's too open the mind can wander off
easily and so we could bring it back touch to the breath a bit stay with one
thing a
bit starting to develop wisdom in working with the mind in relation to
experience
so that we're able to be with things feel them fully and yet not get drawn in
completely e
for
for e
e
e for
as you continue to sit one subtlety you may
notice is that these qualities we invoked change
throughout the course of a Sit the willingness to be
present may be strong at the beginning and then fade out as the mind gets
Restless or you may be a little reluctant to start but now that you've settled in
you're very willing to be
present capacity changes and sometimes we have more capacity to
be with certain experiences than others we may also know what to do in
some cases and have other situations in the
mind where we have no idea how to meet that
experience have you noticed changes throughout this sit in those three things we talked
about
for
e
e e
and as we approach the end of this time of meditation
I'd like to offer that one of these three is particularly
helpful in our daily life being
aware of in particular the second one our capacity to meet experience well
with wisdom and care that's something worth tuning
into as we go throughout our day
and we'll notice that as we're tired or stressed or busy in some
way then we have less ability to connect well with what's
going on and that's normal we don't have to control that too
much but if we know it then we have greater ability
to connect well in our relationships and we can also have the
compassion to realize that others May simply not have the capacity
at this moment to be as we want them to be or to be as good as we think they
should be something there's a lot of wisdom around
knowing where the mind is at in that
regard and having some gentleness around it it's not easy to live in this
world all the inputs and changes and things we have to do as
humans so just bringing in that simple bit of wisdom can greatly increase our
compassion and help our relationships to be more smooth with
others and with ourselves so may that guide you today
[Music]
okay so this week we are talking about
letting go and cultivation these qualities that people
these actions let's say that people think about around the Turning of the new
year and we're being Guided by the suta
from the dhap the verse that says I'm changing Gil's translation
slightly not doing what is unskillful engaging in what is skillful
and purifying or clarifying one's mind this is the teaching of the
Buddhas but the question is how do we do that wisely so we're talking about uh
different perspectives and aspects of this uh that are relevant in our wanting
to direct our intentions well in the world and for the new
year so today we're going to talk about three qualities that support being able
to succeed at any spiritual aim um any one that results for example from the
three wise intentions that we talked about at the end of yesterday renunciation non-ill will and non
cruelty which effectively amount to letting go and non-harming so you know we can intend or
wish all we want but without these three qualities that we'll talk about today uh
it may not be able to come about so if there's something that you want to let go of or cultivate you might consider if
these three are in place and we've already previewed them in the meditation
but we'll go ahead and go through them in a little bit more uh detail now uh the first is uh
willingness right so um I see a link here to the foundational spiritual
faculty of Faith sat some people don't like the word faith but the five spirit
spiritual faculties underly our ability to develop anything and the first of
them is some kind of confidence or trust or faith or the word I'm using is
willingness the simplest form of faith is willingness are you willing and you
might think well of course I'm willing I'm you know I'm making an aspiration to
let go of something or cultivate something aren't I but actually probably
quite likely there are some parts of the mind that are not actually on board with that and that's the reason that many of
our resolutions Fade Away fairly quickly because something in US isn't actually
willing to do that so it's worth checking just how much internal
resistance there might be to whatever we are intending and it's fine if there is
some you know that's to be expected we're making a change
going against maybe some kind of habit that we've developed um so what's
important really is to be aware if there's any internal resistance so that it can't kind of sneak in sideways and
um you know change whether or not we're able to fulfill that so as an example I remember a time
uh hearing a nun a Buddhist nun talking about uh wrestling with her desire for
food so nominally she was on board with this wish because you know she' become a
nun that's a lot of that is about um living in living a life where you're not
acting on desires um but nonetheless she felt like um in the corner of her mind
even though you know in the front of her mind she was very willing not to be connect not to be attached to food and
worried about that uh there would be this continual Fascination coming in with what she would eat tomorrow you
know and and Buddhist nuns uh receive all of their food from others so you don't know what you're going to eat
tomorrow and there would be this interest in it and concern about it and so she started looking at her mind you
know what's going on with that and she described it as seeing a fire burning
before her and trying to put it out you know being very willing to put the water on it calm it down but then kind of
looking off to the side and noticing that there was a part of her mind that was throwing wood on the fire from the
side so I really liked that image that she gave and it's like that isn't it um
so check out you know is there something that's right in front of you and you're very willing to work with it let go of
it cultivate it but on the side there's something undermining it so sometimes it
helps to kind of expand our vision and just take in oh yeah there is a part of me that's really not very willing to do
this and to acknowledge that and to have compassion for that part so that we can
include it and you know have everybody eventually getting on
board that's kind of the top level of willingness but more deeply this quality
of willingness is also about willingness to meet the
unknown willingness to embrace this process of the Dharma that's unfolding
and changing Us in ways that we can't completely predict how willing are we to
undergo a transformational process this path is not so easy and certainly the
ego and other you know parts of us that are very concerned with safety and predictability are probably not fully on
board with with that idea so it's a process for us to work with these parts
and it's okay you know just just keep at it gently but the willingness is
important you to have some degree of willingness and then the second capacity
thing that we talked about is capacity right so even if we're willing to LEAP
across a Chasm if we don't have enough strength to get to the other side it's not going to work so we need the
capacity to actually do what we're intending to actually do the letting go or the cultivation that we're interested
in and this capacity is typically developed in meditation so that's one of the main functions of
meditation much of the capacity that we need is simply the ability to stay with
experience without getting sucked in or reacting to it that's it just being able
to stay with strong emotions with bodily pain with storms of thinking that's a
lot of what we develop on the cushion that kind of capacity basic mindfulness is enough to
start us off so we learn to be able to see experience know what's happening
without just getting immediately drawn into it and becoming it
essentially and then we also have various practices like um rain or at IMC
we talk about the acronym raft which stands for recognize allow feel and
tease apart these are techniques for working with strong emotions that come up
and then eventually um we want to develop the capacity to have open awareness where everything is allowed uh
everything can come and go and there's some way that we can develop our capacity to really be with anything that
really helps a lot when we can start to be willing have the willingness to be
open to anything and start to develop that capacity so you know the cushion is like
the spiritual gym it's the the place where we strength strengthen our ability
and of course all the time we fall off and um get lost or find that we can't be
with something that's fine um that's fine the idea is that we're kind of
working the edge without going over into the realm of overwhelm or stress or too
much so then you back off oh that was a little too much okay no problem but we want to keep kind of working that edge
in the way at the gym you keep trying to live a little bit more and if it's too
much then you go back but eventually you'll get stronger and so this is the
development of capacity and as the mind even as the mind gets calmer and more tranquil more
concentrated more able to be with a lot of things there is still the need to develop different kinds of
capacities such as the ability to be with experience that is very subtle or
that is unfamiliar that's also Al a capacity to develop you know can I stay with
experience when it gets very very fine and there's a tendency to want to know
what it is or do something with it and then we have to learn oh okay now I can also be with experience that's very
subtle one teacher uh said that we're eventually developing capacity in
non-conceptual knowing so trusting the knowing that doesn't involve the rational mind that's yet another
capacity to develop so there's all kinds of capacities we'll need to learn on and
off the cushion so practicing off the cushion also helps develop capacity you
know we can learn to sustain some level of mindfulness throughout our whole day or throughout our whole drive to work
for example can we refrain from unwise speech with a person who triggers us all
kinds of capacities so that's a lot of what practice is
about and then the the third though the third thing I mentioned is knowing what
to do or we could call it maybe knoow so even if we are willing and we have some
kind of potential capacity we do have to have instructions on how to do whatever it is
that we're wanting to do I suspect that many of you have the knowhow already here in the west we get
a lot of instruction and um the instructions are actually pretty simple the problem is that
they're hard to do right um and yet you know there are also times where we need
specific instructions for a particular thing that we're meeting and that's why it's important to have a teacher to talk
with a teacher um you know a basic principle of Dharma practice is to learn how to fully
experience something without either expressing it or repressing it there's kind of a middle way to walk and this is
not intuitive for most of us we like to go onto either of those extremes so we
might need to learn this way of practice and talk about it and U Get Specific Instructions from a
teacher and then you'll find that as you get more specific instructions we might
again have to deal with willingness you know if a teacher says to you you know Kim what you really need to do is X
because they've seen something in me that I haven't seen something in me might say no I'm not willing to do X I
don't want to do that wait a minute I didn't think this was going to involve letting go of that right we're back to willingness so
these three willingness capacity and knowhow are interrelated and we have to
keep checking where we are in each of those areas so you might check out in yourself
in regard to whatever feels important at this new year time
do you have all three of these in place are you actually willing to do you know
what it is that you're intending uh do you have the capacity and if you don't
what might need to be cultivated there and do you know how to do that uh do you
have instructions that will help you when you realize that you're going off course or not uh not being able to
achieve that so I think these three um are kind of an
interesting reflection to do around any kinds of intentions in letting go or
cultivation that we would have do we have the willingness the capacity and
the knowhow and I wish you very well in that
reflection and consideration because it helps support you know being able to
move forward on the path with what we want to do so on this last day of
2024 may it be a day of joy and care and
consideration of your own heart and mind so that you can direct it well and we'll
continue for the next few days to talk about the unfolding of that remember that you don't have to have it all
worked out by midnight tonight so happy New Year be well