here we go great awesome well hello hello again and welcome everyone it's
lovely to be with you um yeah it it brings up happiness and joy and
gratitude for me to for this space of happy hour to exist for us practitioners
to come together from different places in this world from from our homes
don't have to drive anywhere and we can practice together so I'm I'm feeling
gratitude so so given that tomorrow is
Thanksgiving in in the United States um seems like an appropriate
theme to be practicing with gratitude so couple of words I want to
say and you might have heard them before but I want to invite you to listen to them with beginner's mind actually you
may not have heard them before so first of all gratitude is not a should is not a must
it's don't practice gratitude with a stick that I should be grateful for what
I have because there are people who are suffering that o ouch that's that
doesn't really help that doesn't expand our heart um instead ask a question can
I can I be grateful for this and this could be anything can I be grateful for
this and could be something uh good or Pleasant or a blessing in your life and and as we
continue to practice uh in this way with a sense of curiosity and interest and
open-heartedness then it actually becomes this practice becomes can I be
grateful for this challenge can I be grateful for this difficulty can I be grateful for this pain or something that
I usually am not grateful for I have perhaps an adverse of relationship with so this practice of gratitude in this
particular way that I'm offering inviting us to consider can be so
opening so expansive in to our heart in mind in
ways that we may not have considered in ways that maybe we just limited ourselves in the box of like yeah I
should be grateful for you um you know perhaps a tagline that is kids you might
have heard you you know be grateful and eat your peas because their kids starving and XYZ so so that's not very
helpful as as a perspective as an adult so I want to bring this this opening
this sense of curiosity can I be grateful for this can I be grateful for
this and let's start with things that are actually immediate um yeah two Dimension
so being grateful as I mentioned for things that are are blessings things
that are challenging so let's start with with things that are blessings let's
start there not we always start the meta and Brahma vhar and graditude practice
where it's easiest and then we build to where it's maybe a little more challenging so that's one dimension one
quadrant easy more difficult and then the other
quadrant the other axis is what's immediate what's right here right now
present in our bodies and in our Yeah in our bodies in our present environment
and then the other the end of the axis is what is in general in our lives or
has been or will be Etc so it's it's not immediate so that's another AIS so so
it's best to start in the quadrant which is right here and it's easy right here
right now we sense it feel it and it's really really easy um and it's
lightweight it's not heavy-handed and I also know many of you have had gratitude practice for a long
time um and yeah let's let's practice together it expands the heart it expands
the heart to possibilities to seeing goodness and countering our negativity
bias which all of us human beings do as part of our um yeah as a part of what
has been passed down to us genetically we all have negativity bias so let's uh
yeah gratitude helps expand the heart to see what's good for the benefit of
ourselves and others all right enough of a set up so let's uh let's
practice let's arrive in our bodies and if you need to
shift and move to find your be
allow yourself to sit tall allow
yourself to have a torso that is reaching up to the sky on its
own also allow your base your sit bones to be well
rooted and the
Earth and relaxing the Mind relaxing the
body invite in inviting the abdomen to soften and
relax receiving the breath each in breath each out breath
softening and relaxing some more especially the out breath letting go
with the out breath
and releasing releasing whatever is not helpful right now whatever thought or
story so continue to come in from what was happening before thank you I see you
I'll come back to you after this it going to give my heart to it
wholeheartedly and Landing Landing with your whole body in the space in the Sacred
Space of practice
together honoring your own
presence with each breath
inviting each in breath and out breath to be calming
soothing like a lullaby for your
heart like a massage for your body internally
can I fully can I fully wholeheartedly open to this breath just this one not
last one not reaching for the next one right here this one can I embrace
it will open to it
right here this one
softening and relaxing every out breath e
nothing to do nowhere to go then just be simply let your heart be
in this moment your body be just as it
is e
now inviting the reflection dropping it dropping in this
reflection into the body not into your head head drop it in the body as if you
dropping a pebble in a pond and see what comes up with
gentleness curiosity interest
patience as I'm sitting here lying
here feeling the chair or the cushion with my
bottom my feet on the earth clothes on my
skin air on my hands on my
face can I be grateful for this chair that's
supporting me is cushion and supporting my weight
very light-hearted almost humorous can I be appreciative of
this this chair this cushion sofa whatever it might be
zahu
zutan and as if you were bowing to it in your heart thank you serving for serving my
body for supporting my
body and not to go off on stories how long I've had this
or whatever it might be let let all those go just stay right now with the
sensation with the feeling of feeling supported feeling supported right now
grateful for this right here not
past or future right here
maybe after lingering with it for a while not feeling the sensations of your
body being
covered kept warm or cool whatever case might be with the clothes you're wearing
feeling the sensations of them on your skin
can my heart open to simple lowkey
appreciation for these
clothes but are providing protection right
now appreciation and not thinking about
stories
simply
appreciative a light
touch can I be appreciative for this breath for this air
air I'm breathing right now just this breath just this one so
intimate the air I'm breathing is so intimate
you can expand further perhaps the space you're sitting
in the shelter
that in this moment I'm protected from the
elements allowing the heart to have simple uplift
uplifted gratitude appreciation bowing to the
universe thank you all the causes and conditions
have brought this sense of protection safety from the elements
now we can expand further if you
like sense of appreciation for some of the people in your
life just bringing to mind or heart maybe one or two people or pets it's
okay we are interconnected
with and one person is enough doesn't have to be an expansive
list but if more people show up that's okay
too hang in here with gratitude for this web of mutual support interconnection
not to be taken for
granted
e
e e
in your own time you can expand further staying with each item that
arises maybe gratitude for health as much health as there is right
now
available stay with each blessing for a while so we're not
jumping from one thing to the next which can get the Mind
unsettled wherever your heart feels most
expensive there are no shs here
let expansiveness be your guide
and now if the heart and mind feel stable and expansive
enough maybe bring to Heart something that has been a little challenging lately not the most challenging thing
please don't choose that something a little of challenging and drop in the question in
your body not your head can I be grateful for this for how
it has stretched me or is stretching me
stay with it and if becomes really difficult in aive Let It Go come back to where it's
easy and if it's available to feel into it then
stay feeling into this reflection in the
body let the answers arise
remember don't push about gently
stretching but not
breaking
e
e e
as we bring this period of sitting too close
together can we be grateful appreciative of having showed up
for the sake of ourselves and others no judgment reading how the sitting was or
wasn't we've planted seeds y can we
appreciate the seeds we've planted and ourselves and the community and everything
that it takes and has taken to be here practice
together and trusting these seats of whole heartedness and goodness
planted sharing this goodness with uplift with all beings
everywhere with generosity as if we're throwing confetti
bursting confetti all over the world may all beings everywhere be well
happy free including ourselves
thank you everyone thank you thank you thank you
thank you so much appreciation for you and your practice yeah our
co-created space of goodness so I just wanted to quickly
review what the invitations were we started with getting embodied a bit and then
started with opening up to the breath as a way to soften
relax the body while we're sitting upright and then opening to appreciation for support of the chair the support of
the air the various supports that are available and then we expanded further
to to appreciate the support of the interconnections that we have with
people and we lingered there for a while we lingered on each of them for a while so that the mind doesn't get too jumpy
you know jumping from one item to the next it can become a thinking practice if we don't really have patience and
linger at the end I invited you to stretch a little bit and and if it's
felt okay to to bring a question of what uh can I be grateful for this
challenging thing that has been difficult for me uh recently and uh see
see what that might bring up so so
um so as uh as now we have the opportunity to practice in small groups
I also want to invite those who are on YouTube if you want to to hop on Zoom you are welcome to participate
participate in small groups you can go to IMC website and and get on Zoom or
happy hour so um yeah so the invitation for the
practice is uh is this I'm going to uh H in let's see oh yeah so we're
going to practice MTA meta practicing together and The
Meta practice mindfully uh speaking and and speaking
speaking and listening considering the small groups as a continuation of the practice embracing
compassion if there's something reactivity comes up to um to bring in
compassion for yourself and whatever might be happening in the space and um taking turns briefly
staying on topic and the topic today is this so the
first round so we'll go to round first round
is one thing you're grateful for one thing just could be very simple you
could just say actually I felt really grateful for this chair that wow it's supporting me it's comfortable could be
just simply that or it could be oh yeah this this person in my life I'm grateful
for them that would just really that was what's was coming up in the practice just one thing that's the first round
and we're going to go um alphabetical order according to first name and the second round is if you did
experiment with the invitation can you be grateful for something that's challenging and and if there some
Reflection from that that you want to share um so maybe something like oh at
the beginning I broaden maybe I'm having you know some
health challenges or something and I can be grateful for that I wanted to go away and then I kept staying with it and
sitting with it and realize well actually because the pain is waking me up at 4:00 a.m. oh I'm getting to read
more I'm reading more W that's nice I'm grateful for reading more so it's uh
that's my practice support there there's always something to be grateful for right there's always something to be
grateful for so so that's the second round if you tried it if there's something and if it didn't work if there
was just reactivity like no no no I don't like this I'm not grateful for it it's okay totally fine totally okay so
that's the that's the second round so the first round what are you grateful for second round something challenging
perhaps and then you can do more rounds of either what you're grateful for or just more rounds if there is time and be
kind to yourself be kind to each other and um
okay I'm going to create the breakout rooms and I trust the instructions are
clear enough uh let's see here we go okay I'm creating the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of each other and enjoy enjoy the community space all
right opening the rooms here we go hello everyone welcome
back so we have time for any Reflections you'd like to share any questions and
chat is open too you can either raise your Zoom hand or um what you type it in
chat so what uh what did you notice how did it
go bill
so when you talk about being grateful for challenges I picked just some minor conflicts at work not nothing
really big but I was truly grateful for it because I handled it well and it's because of the
practice and again I can compare I guess that's the comparing mind I shouldn't do that but no I can
look back years ago and I know I would not have handled it as well so I'm very
grateful ah I it's lovely thank you Bale thanks for sharing this this is so
lovely especially looking back that which is this is a actually a a wholesome comparison what you're doing
which is looking back at the Arc of your practice wow I'm not the person I used to be I've I've come a long way I'm um
yeah I I'm handling this better yay yay celebrating and letting it be a source
um of of gratitude for you and and happiness for all of us we celebrating
with you I see so many Smiles in the space it's very
sweet Neil says we should do gratitude every night it makes me all happy he's
got the happy emoji that is very cool right K I see you have your hand up and I'm almost willing to guess what you're
going to say are you going to talk about the pr gradal practice you've been doing for years
you we always talk about please unmute oops oh wait do it
again you're still muted my dear I thought about that just a minute
ago before that I thought of the fact that I have something that's falls into
both categories yeah on Friday I am bringing into my home three Pomeranian
puppies wow okay exactly so on the good
on the positive I'm really grateful to have them they're just absolutely adorable um and full of love and they're
going to really light up our little home on the other hand there's awful lot of work coming down the pike to train them
and get them ready to be adult dogs so it's the other it's a very Mi
mess oh I get it so so but I had to talk about it because yeah it's both c yeah I
get it so it's both categories say you're both grateful for all the gifts they're going to bring these Pomeranians
yes sweet yay and then oh my God I'm so it's it's gratitude you know it's it's
yeah I love it thanks Claire but I will grow I will be stronger after having
done it so that's great thanks
Claire yeah and Tom I see your
hand all right so uh so you may have noticed there's someone with me here
yeah so this is oh you just got to wave Barbara just waved at you and then Nikki
did too oh bunch of people waving thank you so uh so uh Timothy Timothy here has
been uh listening to you Nikki for many many months and I sent you a note once
about him yes with the with Mr Roger the the one that you did probably about
a year ago and how much he loved that one and so he likes going to sleep
listening to you every night the happy happy hour and listening to all of your questions that everybody who's
participating in this SAA has for it and if you think about the bombardment of
different things going on in a seven almost 8-year-old's life that's pretty
amazing that he's actually remotely interested in this so so I'm grateful
that uh that you and the sa are here to do this oh thank you Tom just oh my
goodness you made my day you made all of our days this is so sweet and Timothy you yes i' I've read about you your dad
wrote to me about you listening to happy hour wouldd love to hear your voice too would you would you be willing to bring
in your voice into the space and tell us yeah how you doing how how do you like
listening to all these Reflections and meditations I'm doing
well doing well yes yeah yeah a you know
it's it's quite amazing and beautiful thing that you're doing that you have
interest in in in cultivating and listening to these wow thank you for for
what you're doing both for yourself and everybody else in the world thank youthy thank you thank you a it's
so sweet oh my goodness so sweet I see so many hearts in the space a so sweet
thank you Timothy thank you Tom thank you thank you Bo a so
sweet a I don't know what to say after that I it's it's
feels complete to me after what Tom and Timothy just shared
a yeah you know what I thinking this might be a good time to end happier I
mean I don't think we can top that Tom and Timothy this is just like it's mic
drop so we're just gonna end it now yeah oh it's so sweet that's so
sweet oh Tom says in chat this like he's getting to meet his Superstars oh my
God he's our Superstar he's totally our Superstar oh my god well let's
celebrate Tom and Timothy for as we close this session of happy hour ah
let's as you guys can um have um not uh my view have for for privacy I have to
have me spotlit but you can have you can Spotlight Tom so that you can see Tom
and in so that you can see Timothy because we're going to do a meta for Timothy right now we're go and Tom both
of them so we're going to ah hold Timothy in our hearts with appreciation
with gratitude for his 78-year-old
heart that is listening to to happy hour meditation s who likes Mr
Rogers dear Timothy may you be happy in every way may you be
healthy may you be safe and may you have lots of ease in
your life lots of joy and bring so much happiness to yourself and everyone
around you thank you for being one of us thank you for practicing with us we love
and appreciate you
thank you Timothy thank you Tom thank you sa I'm going to stop you