yes good morning is that loud enough for you the volume so I'll do one announcement and
in my mind uh it's been interesting that what I'm going to announce also kind of sets up my talk as a contrast
almost so this uh evening at 6 PM I'm going to do an online Zoom teaching
meeting uh for Spirit Rock and then asked me to do a kind of a book reading
I suppose I have a new book that came out called Everything Is practice and uh and it's a manual for
sitting inside Retreats especially a manual for our at our Retreat Center in
Santa Cruz and uh so I see it not so much as an opportunity to talk about the book
but to talk about my enthusiasm for uh Insight Retreats and uh even more so for those
that are the longer ones the monthlong and I think it's one of the great things that Spirit Rock offers is the monthlong
or the two-month long retreat every year so that will be the topic and uh but in
uh thinking about that and happy to do this um uh there has been a bit of a
problem with teachings like that that I do and that is that uh people will
assume that what the teachings are for a retreat are how we're supposed supposed to practice in daily life and um and one
of those has to do with walking meditation and on Retreat walking
meditation is very particular generally there's many ways of doing it but there's a kind of sometimes we call a
formal way of doing walking meditation and so people get the idea that this is the way we practice walking
in this tradition just walk you know very slowly and back and forth and um and uh another way is to
see that Retreat practice meditating every day at home whether it's formal
Med sitting meditation formal walking meditation is a
laboratory for walking in the world both metaphorically and
literally uh uh bringing discovering the
that the temple is not at IMC or IRC or anywhere but we live in a temple we live
in a sacred world and that we can walk in a way that um gets us connected to
that but not you know slowly walking down the street you know and you know lifting moving placing looking at the at
the sidewalk and everyone like has to deal with our slow walking
and you know stand that get up out of the way and this person doesn't seem to be noticing me and it's we you know they
look like we're walking zombies but um you know this practice we do is a
kind of a preparation for living our whole life and walking is a powerful way to
practice in everyday life but the way of discovering how to do that is different than this kind of the more detailed way
we do it maybe on Retreat so walking so uh one of the uh
very significant metaphors in Buddhism is the aide of the
path and with that metaphor a path is a place we walk so the metaphor of
walking and uh one of the very significant places where that appears in that tradition is uh with the poly word
for walking which is literally is gachami in the ancient language but that's used to talk about what's the uh
for many people is a very important phase or very important uh uh expression of their
Buddhism which is called um uh going for Refuge going for refuge in the Buddha
Dharma and the sa going for support going for inspiration going for orienting our life around the values the
practices and the teachings that Buddha Dharma sa represent and and the word for going is
literally walking one walks with the three refuges one walks
in the three refuges walks by the three refuges they of walking to the you know
go going to The Refuge puts it out there somewhere uh but we're walking in them
we're walking with them we're walking by them puts us much more here and so this idea of walking the
path and in Buddhism the path doesn't exist in the
external world uh per se you don't you don't go find the Buddhist path someplace and you
don't you don't come to IMC please to look for the Buddhist path and you come in you open the door you look in where's
that path and um must be the blue tape on the
carpet the um the um the path is something that we
create with every step we take we we it's our job to make the path
in every breath we take and every step we take literally and uh and so walking becomes
a powerful both metaphor but also a reality for where we discover and how we
find the Dharma how we find our peace how we find our freedom our Awakening
how we find a lived life that's valuable as we live it it's not like we're
looking for in the future that we're trying to get someplace place and not a
few meditators will engage in meditation with the idea that uh if they just
meditate um you know sit quietly and meditate every day that somehow that's
going to be the solution for their life and they they meditate some people meditate very diligently sincerely and
thinking that's what's going to do it and then they get up from their meditation and then they just run around like crazy you know just live life as
usual without they giving any more thought to it expecting the meditation is sometime somehow it's going to
magically you know affect the rest of their life you know provide the key if you just have the big bang Thea of
Buddhism I'll sit there until I get that big bang of Enlightenment and then I'll just everything will be happy ever
after the um but rather meditation it teaches us a way of being that then we're
responsible for living that way in our life and it and it's not a matter of
then you know this magic thinking that somehow we're going to be just be calm forever if we do meditation but it's
rather okay now I've touched into something here in meditation I've discovered something and now how can I
bring that into how can I discover that or be that live that in my life how can I discover the path be the path create
the path every step I make every conversation I'm in every activity that
I'm doing and to do that is to discover something very special that the lived
life as it's being lived is invaluable the lived life as we're
living it is a miracle the lived life as we live is a
wonder and there's a lot of thoughts a lot of forces a lot of emotions that
tell us otherwise and some of you are already going to debate me you know this can't
be so and you don't know about my life you know how difficult it is or something
but again one of the things we learn in seated meditation if those are people who do it and uh we could also learn in
Walking meditation anytime you start doing mindfulness we start disc discovering this and we discover that
how easy it is to live a disconnected life how easy is to live an ungrounded
life how easy it is to live a life that the body and mind are
separated how easy it is to live in our thoughts to live in the future to live in our imagination to live in the past
how easy it is to kind of live through the filter of
desires how to live through the filter of our fears through the filters of our
aversions and resentments and there's a kind of narrowing and a selectivity of our
attention around particular themes ideas thoughts fantasies projections
imaginations that um uh we disconnect from ourselves we live in that that
world rather than the lived world of the wholeness of who we are and I would venture to say that I
think probably more true what I'm going to say than not true that um the way
that modern society is set up in the modern West
especially uh is so many ways in which the whole whole activity of this life
becomes more and more disconnected so just the phenomena of
devices screens that we have I mean screens have opened up a fantastic world
and they're kind of a miracle what these computers and the web can do for our lives and they should be
celebrated and at the same time they're almost deadly something gets shut down
something dies in people to spend so much time on the web and on the computer
and and I see it in myself that I go and look at one thing and then I go check something else out and then I go check
something else out and pretty soon my mind is on its own drive like next
what's more more there let you know and I'm losing touch with myself I'm in this head world of this
this this this and my posture changes and I'm not really connected to my posture anymore and my feelings change
and I really don't feel what's going on and but if I bring my mindfulness what's happening as I get pulled into the world
of the screen I feel how much I'm getting disconnected for myself and my body and my feelings my emotions the
wholeness of the moment and disconnected from the environment around
me I I venture to say that most people who spend a lot of time on screens do it indoors
and that's a very limited world the time of the Buddha they had
indoors but I think most people lived in one room indoors they you know they didn't have
malls I had a friend who used to live in Phoenix and it was so hot there she would go her morning walk would be
walking in the you mile long Mall because that was air
conditioned but you know so along hallways you know and there are people who can seldom go Outdoors anymore
because their work is just big building and just complex and it's not necessarily wrong
to live that way but it's an easy way of being disconnected to the Earth
disconnected to the Natural World the sky the air the outside
and and that's not just a disconnection to those things but it's a disconnection
to how we can be a tuned to that world how we can be sensing it and feeling it
and as human beings we've been designed to be attuned to the natural world to
the temperature and air and smells and tastes and and the terrain and to be
reading and taking it all in and not a few people find it so healing to go to a
park and going for a walk go outdoors and something uh it
settles the preoccupations of the mind that we caught in and spinning out in it
helps us feel reged and uh the the expression that I've come up with is we feel uh
reared and many of us live deared we don't live connected to the
ground and the Earth walking if we can especially if we can walk outside gets
us grounded it can get us grounded it can get us reared even if we walk on fa
or C in sidewalks there's something about being outside something of walking and um and there's there's a way
in which ordinary everyday walking in our lives can be can be a profound
activity and we can learn that again from meditation because we can learn the
opportunity in walking outside is to just like in meditation sity seated meditation is to heal the
Divide between the body and the mind to no longer live so much in the mind
and thoughts that were disconnected to the body and it's almost like gu for many of us the body and mind are in two
different places at this at that kind of the same time the mind is thinking about
tomorrow or another place or other situation the body is
here and um now occasionally we bring we take the body to where the mind is but
the real task is to bring the Mind into where the body is which means here and now to discover how to be here so that
the mind and body are operating and working together and that's such a phenomenal thing to have happened that
we can call it a healing we heal that split between the body and mind and
that's hard to do because the thinking mind the feeling mind the mind that gets
preoccupied and cut up has a lot of publicity that it sends out a lot of
advertisements a lot of lawyers a lot of politicians a lot of
that are arguing how important it is to stay preoccupied and caught up in that
world and uh and it can seem so important the authority of that mental
world that we get lost in uh can be you know the authority is huge that we Grant
it and the cost is we lose ourselves we lose not just ourselves but we lose
sometimes a a deep connection to this world that we live in so if we
walk walk down the street and we're starting to bring together the body and
the mind so that every step we take we are making the path every step we make
we are discovering something that we can may be deeply respect and value every
step we take we are waking up to this moment in the fullness of the moment and
what the fullness means means the whole show it means includes how we're
distracted but not to just keep being distracted but to wake up to all this
whole picture here's a body walking here's a body that doesn't feel seen and
recognized here's a mind that's caught up in thoughts and we open this is what's happening let's walk now with all
this going for Refuge with the Buddha Dharma and the s means to going for Refuge with all of who we are in this
moment and something can begin to settle something begin shifting when we're not
caught in the world of thoughts something begin shifting if we begin
being attuned to the the whole body and mind as it operates
together our body and Minds were designed to work together and our bodies are kind of like
a miracle the walk just you know we take walking for granted those of us who can
those of us who can walk and um I read recently that um one of the
first first thing that characterized homins hom you the homo
kind of class of mammals was that they
walking upright in two legs it's one of the first things and slowly over time
these kind of beings that evolved into homos sapiens uh they um or nowadays as homo
homo consumers consumers um is um uh the very efficient
walking we do apparently we walk more humans walk more efficiently than chimpanzees and other things that walk
with can walk on two legs and and um and there's amazing it's amazing engineering
feat that somehow Evolution has shaped this phenomena of walking and we do it without thinking about
it and um but it's an amazing thing and and we're walking in the Footsteps in a
sense of three million years of hum of you know humanid humanid
Evolution so we walk and uh and we walk and we feel the ground there's a so
that's as a feet touch the ground we walk in a speed that gets us connected to now
rather than disconnected it's easy to just walk around so fast that we're not connected
it's another thing to consider what's the speed of being reared what's the
speed of mindfulness what's the speed of reverence what's the speed as if each
step we're in a sacred world and maybe that sounds kind of
romantic or silly to talk about every step being sacred but there are places
we go where it feels special it feels like really like that it do feel sacred
or have a kind of reverence uh those of you who've been been to M Woods
especially if you can go there early in the morning before everyone gets else gets there I mean you you'll probably be
OD into kind of Silence being there it's and actually one of the Groves of trees there is called the Cathedral
Grove and um and then another one called The Bohemian Grove and if you go to the
Bohemian gr Grove read the sign for the Bohemian gr actually don't read it you
don't have to read it even look at the picture at the behemi gr Grove because
it's a picture that in 1892 the Bohemian Club met there and
there's a picture of the 62 foot Buddha they put in that place
1892 United States a Buddha a 60 foot Buddha in Mir Beach Mir Woods anyway I
mean that's a sacred place or a awesome place or a wonderous
place um and um sometimes there're religious places temples that or
Cathedrals literally that feel sacred the beauty about this mindfulness
practice is we could have that feeling that sense in every step we literally
take in this world and so to walk to to find that and uh there is lots of people
who love going for walks and one of the opportunities if you walk long enough is
uh is over time in the walking uh there's a kind of coming into harmony of
the body and mind it settles together again just like in meditation it settles
especially if you're walking with that in mind walking coming back to your body coming back to your steps just like in
City meditation we keep coming back to our body back to the breath and walking becomes over and over again doesn't have
it can be ordinary walking just walking around but to have a walking be a place we discover a whole different way of
being in the world and and this is what I'm about to
say now is very important walking in a way that's we're
walking mindfully we also discover all the reasons we think we
can't do that all the reasons we feel pulled into something more important or the value our thoughts or confusions or
all this stuff and is that really true and this is where you should have a
debate with yourself you should have sit down with yourself or go for a walk with yourself and take this seriously and
question the forces the beliefs the attitudes that pull you into your world
of distractions pull you into the concerns and preoccupation of everyday life that you have that these are so
important to be there and do this and be thinking about that that you become deared dis disconnected
here and uh and the arguments your arguments your Your Capacity to kind of
hold your own spiritually against this all this force of the profane profane
world of Destruction to return to the sacred world of here is
helped if you've discovered how invaluable it is to live in a world
where you're grounded and settled and present for
yourself so you have available to you the full capacity of of uh intelligence that
comes when the body and mind work together the full capacity of being really here with all of who you you are
not just from the eyebrows up or the neck up or
something and um and so walking is one of the great places to discover this and
one of the real Great uh proponents of walking meditation in daily life uh was
tikn Han and uh he's famous for taking these 300 people for a walk and he would
be in the front and he would just walk every step he took like you could almost feel like he really was there for the
step and he didn't do the next step until he had completed one step and
everyone would slow down and just be with him and it was profound people had the experience of walking with
tianan and he had um he has he has you know he has one of the best Buddhist
book titles that I know sometimes I got his books just for the
title but uh there was um uh peace in every step was one of his bestselling
books peace in every step what a great title and uh the Mira the subtitles is
the miracle of mindfulness in everyday life it's also a great combination and then uh he has another
one called um The Long Road turns to
Joy uh a guide to walking meditation so the long road
my wife is a through hiker if you don't know what that is a through hiker is someone who goes and and walks for a
long time like she goes for like right now she's just finishing up a relatively
short through hike which I think it was 18 days she was trying to walk from Oregon
to Canada but she had to stop halfway because of all the fires up
there but one of the things she talks about is uh you get into this Rhythm by
walking and walking until the body and mind are together it's a meditation practice for her that puts her in the
present moment and she's really here uh you know because she's walking all that's what she's doing all day and
there something about walking that really helps us to be present you know
this sitting meditation that some of us keep champing it's pretty wonderful but um we
don't move we're sitting still and that has value but walking the body
is there to help you the kinesthetic Sensations and feelings activity of the body moving and waking up and expressing
itself and there's something about the fluidity and the moving of the body that can be a great help to loosen up the way
the mind is stuck and but and to keep walking and I sometimes am stuck in my thoughts and my
feelings I have big things going on and I find it invaluable to go walking and
just walking and I find it helpful to walk with all this because I allow how I am to be there but the walking protects
me from getting um um uh unconsciously caught in it all it keeps me kind of
kind of fluid and kind of moving and kind of you know not caught and so I can
let everything be there but then it all begins to move it all begins to find a way and I can respect it and be with it
and just let it be held or all held by the walking so um walking
meditation uh being grounded not ungrounded being embodied
not disembodied connected not disconnected reared not
deared so I so in thinking up this I I think it's a new word in English de
earthed and then I I looked at that I wrote it down and I said well if you just take out one of the
E then you have dir and then I looked up what what's the
atmology of the word dir which means like the absence of something right the scarcity or something so I looked at up
and it turns out that the English word dir comes from the word dear
with a suffix th that means like a state of the condition of the condition of
being dear so how do you get from the condition that something is dear to the
English idea dir means scarcity so the theory I don't know if anybody knows for sure the theory is
that uh when there were famines in England and places like that that um uh
uh what was dear was scarce and so somehow that got kind of turned
into dir meaning scarce but so isn't that kind of can't
we kind of revive the original meaning of
dir and um so that uh we go from being deared to a state that's that's um dear
a world that's dear living in this dear world where we value you we love we care
for every step that we do and every conversation we're in why
not do you have something better to do do you know something better than
just being present for this moment for what you're doing to be here
fully if you do question that sometimes maybe there's an
emergency you have to take care of it but but don't live a life of
emergencies live a life of emergence where something can emerge
here in the present moment something that who you are what's this life is let
life be lived live the lived life don't live the imagined
life and the lived life it turns out who would have known only happens in the present moment
and you're only alive for a short time it's amazing that we have all been given
this opportunity to live remember to live
it don't imagine it don't live in fantasy for it don't
live in projections and don't be caught in the memories don't be caught in the
futures where we don't we lose the lived life so walking meditation just walking
just not even call it don't even call meditation just walk walk the lived
life and let that be a life that sacred every step is a sacred step every step
is how we discover the path of Freedom there's no Buddhist path outside of
that if you want to discover
Buddhism don't go get another Buddhist
book Walk go walk
instead and Li and discover the lived life of walking and see what that book
teaches you what what comes alive what emerges
what's there for you if you walk rearing
yourself walk on this Earth we're we're made for it we are the
Earth walking on the earth and so this wonderful activity of walking that's
both meant literally and also figuratively some people can't
walk and um so I'll end uh maybe partly thinking of the people who can't walk
um that um one of the wonderful ways kind of to to um maybe
um tho thoch charge you know kind of this called movement towards a lived
life is um if you
walk go walk someplace in your city your place that you've
never been to before go walk someplace new maybe without a
map maybe following the trail of the trees or the butterflies or
something there's something about going into new environments that wake something up in US takes us out of our
distracted world and um so so if you can't walk
then maybe drive to a new place go someplace
new sometimes there's a wonderful quote from teacher named uh Cham truna if you
can't meditate travel so that sometimes brings out the
lived life we we're suddenly paying attention and we feel and notice much more what's going
on but maybe you don't have to go even to a new place maybe every place you're
in is a new place maybe every step is a new
world and as we step it mindfully uh we are authoring our own
life each step is a new life
emerging so um I hope that that inspires you to walk
more and or take your walking kind of more seriously for its
potential and with that if we have some time if anyone wants to ask questions or
comments or would like to make have testimonials about the value of walking I'd love to
hear I do a strange thing um I go walking sometimes with my cat with your
cat with my cat and and she actually leads the way it's very very slow what
happens to you when the cat leads you way leads you I just follow her and but what happens to you internally it's it's
wonderful yeah it's a new adventure every time even though it's the same street you see the world in a different
way yeah that very nice yeah going going for a walk with a little kid toddler is
also fascinating to see the world in a different way so there so there and then up in the
stage where then Martha maybe up SEC you're up up
there okay yeah so this isn't a question it's a testimonial as you know Gil I
lived in trucky for three years and just got back a few months ago
and um every day was an incredible Delight uh I felt like a child in a
candy store it literally would think what which which hike am I going to take today I had about six
favorites and what I didn't like as much was hiking with people and I didn't want
to be antisocial but I didn't know a whole lot of people when I live there it
I was much more present when I walked alone and um this is really a
continuation from last week cuz you were talking about Forest walking and I have felt grief and loss
since I've been back even though I you know they wonderful places to walk here it's just not the same as in the sieras
and being surrounded by the mountains and the smells and the reservoirs and the
lakes um so the idea is not the same for sure and it's inspiring to be in those
places yeah but the task is to do those walks and discover how you could be
different and then and then and then bring that let that emerge as you walk through the city yes and the city can be
just as awesome yeah it can be amazing wow yeah there's so much Wonder here and
if you want a little help they now had here in R City there's now created a they're starting to put a path that goes
like from the library almost I think it is uh under uh 101 out onto the the bay
the bay land there and that's a it goes along that Redwood City Creek they that they kind of revived that was kind of
covered over or abandoned or lost it's kind of fun to see the Old Creek that's still there so that's kind of I did the
other day and that was kind of cool to walk can see something new I've you know in redid City I've been here for 20
years and wow see that hello
um my question is uh not pertaining mainly to walking but it it's uh
something triggered based on what you said and uh so I do a lot of walking and
trying to be present is easier when you're outside and when you're moving so
when I'm trying to be present for me it means that I'm fully absorbed and aware
I'm trying to be aware of what I'm thinking what I'm feeling and this is just a daily
practice now one day it so happened I was in the outdoors and I was by a beach
and I saw a little gopher come out of a hole okay and I just started playing
with it and giving it some little bits of whatever sand uh whatever was growing
on the sand and this game continued for I don't know how long but then at some point he got bored and just put a lot of
you know mud sand up in the hole and just blocked me
out but what I realized because when I
was playing with that gopher all I was aware of at that moment was this
amazing encounter and I was aware that I was aware and I was aware of the Sea and the
sand and the breeze but I all my friends everything else was just blocked out so
I'm wondering what was that quality of presence that I had at that moment
because I'm still going back to that to see was my noticing different was my
presence different and how can I bring that Wonder into my everyday life it's a
great question and I think one of I think hopefully good answers is um that
that uh points to something for you to look at is um you were not
distracted and uh and maybe even when you're walking in your in touch with your feelings and emotions and what's
going on for you there might be U still even there you're a little bit distracted by it you're a little bit
selecting you have priorities you have think this is important to notice and you're kind of zeroing in in a way that
is a little bit stressful or a little bit too choiceful but uh to be undistracted
and and and then absorbed in what you're doing without any stress it's almost
like a self forgetting and this this idea that you're aware that you're aware but maybe
the more you can almost forget yourself the clearer awareness of awareness
is sorry I didn't hear that would you just repeat the last B uh the the less
you're thinking about yourself the strong the the more uh clear can be the
sense of awareness aware of itself and uh and there's a lot of ways
in which many ways that seem so M second in nature that we are oriented around
the idea of me myself and mine and it's not necessarily wrong but it's a little
bit stressful and uh and it's wonderful to have a non-distracted state we're really
present but without the distraction of self and that's probably was so the go
for it was so fascinating that you know you know the fact that you hadn't done
your taxes was not important or something like
that yes please uh I'm a I love walking
um and I agree with you there's something special that happens in fact that I I try to walk every day at
lunch leave the office and my energy definitely shifts when I come back
and I'm also a lover of connection amongst us that gives me a lot of energy too and in my experience I have
found uh walking with a loved one is
magical to me and we open
up the the the the walls crumble and I do believe you know nature gives us that
energy and the experience of walking alone is wonderful I also have
found that the experience of walking with a loved one is just as powerful so
I don't think it's a necessarily a practice of solitude but it's a practice of
connection uh to yourself connection with the natural world and then
connection amongst us and it's wonderful topic today and it's wonderful wonderful and just to add a
third option is to is to walk in Silence with others and know we I've done these
the Buddhist pilgrimages where uh a group of us are walking together but walking in silence and it's been very
profound to share the walking and share each other and sense each other together on this uh you know this kind of a it's
a way of making every step sacred and then sharing that thank
you I'd just like to give a short testimonial about um doing the walking
meditation on treat a lot of people I've noticed um take it as a time to go get a
cup of tea or take a nap and and I I do that sometimes but um I just love
walking meditation I really recommend you try it um um this is terrible but
sometimes I like walking meditation better than sitting meditation especially if your back is kind of
hurting it's it's it's it's fun so I just I just want to really recommend to
people that um that skip it and it's really great to go up and do walking
meditation during that 15 minutes when everybody else is standing in line for food um kind of sneak in another walking
meditation anyway I just really recommend it and um thank you yes one
one of the things I've done on Retreat um I love walking meditation on Retreat as well um it's a I'll I'll follow an
alternate schedule to everyone so when everyone's sitting I'm walking so then
I'm quietly by myself and then when they come to walk I go and sit sh don't tell
[Applause] anyone yeah and the opportunity of
walking meditation and Retreat is is uh that's a situation where you can really
get absorbed in it and there into the Simplicity of it and simple simple simple and um but sometimes to try to do
that that that level of concentration in everyday life that then is then
something is lost actually in everyday life um but uh I I mean Some people
prefer doing walking formal walking meditation like this uh at um as a daily
meditation instead of sitting meditation every day different different forms of meditation work for different people and
some people every day will walk for 30 40 minutes and that's what they that's their primary meditation practice
other people at sitting practice and some people it's both when I was in
Burma I was doing a lot of sit sitting meditation but my very Stern
strict meditation teacher in Burma he said Gil always do walking meditation before
you do sitting meditation it was kind of like it's okay you're sitting so long but you should
always start with walking so for many years that's what I did I would do at least 10 minutes before before I would do sitting
meditation can I add one more thing sure okay so what you have to get over is
thinking you're being judged by the person by the person that's walking next to you the first thing is you think
you're being judged and if you're being judged that's their practice and your fear of being judged is your practice so
once you can drop that um then it you know it's it's just helpful fantastic
yeah it's their practice and it's your practice ice and know to know what's your practice is to know where to
discover the sacred in every moment so thank you very much and uh yes
oh today is tea time so you can walk over
to good s uh great so uh maybe as a way of breaking the ice for some people who
are new Maybe just turn next to to to people next to you say hello and say your name and it can just be that simple
if someone has to go but it's nice to kind of break the eyes a little bit