lot of people from the West Coast here the west coast of this
continent yeah but all over nice to see everyone
welcome welcome and
uh yeah we'll continue today with an
exploration of what are known as the five faculties five spiritual faculties
what I've been calling five Divine human capacities I was just reflecting as I
sort of watched people come in for the chat just how remarkable it is that
these the ability to be awake in the world is something we're all we're all
born with um we don't have to go acquiring anything or looking
outside we we we look Inward and there we can find
the capacity to to awaken so the second spiritual faculty
is energy viia and the there's times when it seems like
the whole path of practice is about finding an appropriate a skillful balance of
energy and in the guided sit we'll kind of bring some attention
to noticing this balance establishing balance rebalancing and then in the daret we'll
we'll dig a Little Deeper to look into three aspects of the energy that we can call upon to
strengthen our practice support our practice so let's
sit as uh I've been doing I'll guide I hope just just lightly enough to sort of
bring people bring people some some
support so we can find our meditation posture find ourselves into it maybe
make some adjustments to the posture and as we do so we we balance
our energies the first thing we do I think is sort of notice where the energy
is and and as we close the eyes or bring the eyes down or unfocus the eyes if we
keep them open focusing them in the middle distance we can notice a
rebalancing we move from the visual
attractions of our experience to the inner inner World our inner life
and typically we rebalance a little bit from the head to the heart or the head to the body bringing our attention
Inward and downward into the body and then we connect with some
aspect of the bily experience in which there's Natural Balance the breath
being a typical go-to the breath just doing its thing
finding it's Natural Balance and maybe we can just notice
this morning or this afternoon this moment at any rate how
the breath is maybe it's a little quicker maybe it's a little slower maybe it's shallow
maybe it's deep maybe as we bring attention to it
it shifts toward a more relaxed state
in all of these ways we establish a balance of energy between effort and
allowing and if we notice that we get a little drowsy a little
dreamy we can in various ways add a little more effort a little
more alertness a little bit more
energy and if we notice ourselves getting kind of caught up in the mind maybe wrapped around a thought
pattern typically we'll notice that that involves a quickening and a tightening and sometimes a subtle or
obvious sensation of being a little off balance off kill
and in that case we can maybe take away a little energy open up a bit soften a
bit maybe softening the body letting the shoulders L lower back
down relaxing any tension around the eyes
noticing any holding or bracing in the upper body or in the
jaw and in this way
rebalancing as in riding a bicycle pushing a scooter flying a kite sailing
a boat walking we never just establish balance
and then it's fixed it's a practice of always
rebalancing coming back to balance
so as we sit and the mind gets entangled in things looking into the
future considering reconsidering replaying the
past thinking about other people thinking about ourselves as we bring our attention back
to the breath as we open our attention maybe back if it's become tight around ideas and thoughts
opening it back up to the breath opening up to all that's available and
experience we can be aware today of the rebalancing that
happens finding again our way back to a place of balance between alertness and
being at ease between the effort that's needed to
maintain attentiveness Attunement and the ease
that is Central to the
practice
e
e e
so coming to the end of this said noticing where the energy
is and once again reestablishing
balance between alertness and ease if we've gotten a little dreamy a
little foggy a little unfocused we can add a little Spritz of attention of
Attunement and if we've gotten a little tight and
over over efforting we can relax back
into a more skillful balance between alertness
and
relaxation let's bring the sit to a close by sharing the benefits of our practice
which some sometimes we hold a little close sharing the benefits of our
practice with
others when we give freely of the benefits of practice it doesn't diminish the
store seems to increase the
goodness so wishing all beings well wishing all beings
safety security good health wholeness in body and
mind wishing all beings
Freedom wishing all beings freedom from suffering may all beings be content know
happiness and live at ease
[Music]
welcome again
somebody has added to the chat love the silence and it made me hesitant to break
the silence to to say
anything it was indeed for me as well kind of a nice
quiet quiet time so this week I've been revisiting
the five faculty IES I I uh again I'm certain I I know for absolute certainty
that Gil has talked about the five faculties and I think he's spoken at
length about the second one which we'll just explore just a little bit today energy
Ria the uh the way we bring energy to practice and the various aspects of
energy that are available to us and again I would emphasize before plunging
into a little discussion of this second faculty this
second uh competency or or quality of mind or
capacity that all of these things are found within and uh something just strikes me
as very wonderful about that today that the capacity to awaken is is
within don't have to go looking for something outside and maybe that's an important aspect of
effort we we expend or energy we expend so much effort trying to get things
trying to acquire things trying to and this is true I think for Spiritual Goods
as well that we we put a lot of effort in and so how we use the energy we have
and particularly how we balance it is a is a critical part of the of the
practice and an important support for practice so let me just
mention three aspects of energy that we're all probably aware of but by
spending a little time thinking about them and perhaps more consciously
bringing them uh into practice noticing their role in practice we strengthen
them and I'll emphasize that too that sometimes the mechanism of the practice
can be a little unclear uh what what what is it that we do when we bring attention to things when we're mindful
of things when we in the case of energy seek to establish a sustained sustained
mindful attention to our experience one of the very important thing that's that's going on when we do
that is that it's by bringing attention to those things that we strengthen them
this is true of bad habits of mind or unskillful habits of mind and UNH
wholesome mind States as well that when we give attention to them they're
strengthened and um over time in the practice we seek to balance and increase
the increase the attention we give to Wholesome States skillful
actions knowing that as we do so that those capacities are
strengthened so a first a first really important
aspect of energy is what we can call uh initial energy and obviously
maybe most obviously there's a there's quite a bit of energy and skillful
effort that's needed just to begin practicing this is true dayto day sometimes it takes a lot of a lot of uh
a lot of energy just to sit just to get make that time and uh get to the get to
the cushion and once we're sitting it can take
additional energy to keep bringing attention back to um back to back to the Here and Now
of our experience and maybe for each of these we can emphasize a particular aspect of
energy for the for the energy needed to
said um sometimes it's useful to uh in
in terms of bringing the energy to a place of balance to start to think about the sit maybe 10 minutes before it
starts and start to um start to bring
the energy down to a place where it's easier to sit you've probably noticed that if you're rushing around doing
things I'm going to sit at 7 a.m. with Gil or David this week y last week and
you're rushing around getting a bunch of stuff out out of the way so that you can actually make the sit at 7 and if you
you know if it doesn't happen right on time maybe you can get there by 7:30 that creates a certain certain
energetic uh imbalance that can be addressed by starting to practice maybe
15 minutes before you sit down starting to uh starting to let a little bit of
that energy go and so by the time the butt hits the cushion there's already
there's already a rebalancing happening and then within the
practice the um the the the this this kind of energy this initial energy
that's needed shows up in that this commitment to begin again when we return
to the breath when we've gotten knocked off the breath you know or when the mind's gotten all tied around something
we can spend a lot of energy beating ourselves up about that it shouldn't have happened I'm not it's not working
and it's not happening today I'm no good at this this practice isn't any good any of those kinds of doubts that arise can
be addressed by which doubts which by the way take a lot of energy away from
just getting back to Here and Now that can be addressed by just beginning again we begin again and again
new in this in this practice and it's true each time we sit down that we can
balance energy by thinking a little bit be kind of bringing the Mind into mod where this is the first time I've ever
sat in meditation similarly each time we go back to the breath it is in fact the
first time we've returned and met this breath this moment of experience and to the extent we can just begin again
without any baggage about anything that's just happened anything that might
happen what other people might think what we think letting all of that go and
just beginning again is an important aspect of this initial the initial um or initiating
energy that we bring to
practice so a second type of energy I'm only going to mention three three is a good number easy to
keep track of um time constraints but also the constraints of mind and
attention so initial energy and then continuous
energy the uh the wellness known translator of many of the ancient texts
that underg this tradition biku Bodi uh says somewhere you know this
practice is very straightforward there's really only two two steps one begin and
two keep going makes it sound very straightforward but this keeping going
part you know initial energy maybe is this taking that first step sitting down preparing the mind to do so and then
each time we return to Here and Now beginning again the the second the
keeping going part the sort of energy that is more sustained over time is um
is super important and I think it's where the faculty we talked about yesterday the confidence that comes from
meeting our direct experiencing knowing that this is true for for this moment that this is happening that it's like
this in my mind bringing that confidence um forward in a sustained way provides this sort of
energy of return so that each time we REM we come back to this moment we're
able to um do so in a way that creates momentum if you think about it
rebalancing energy on a bicycle on a scooter flying a kite walking sailing a
boat whatever metaphor uh is is useful in your life um whenever we rebalance
we're also taking advantage of the momentum that's there this is true on a bicycle it's true on a scooter sailboat
walking that we're not just in Walking for example which vast majority of us do
with some facility we're not just uh balancing in a particular in a um three
what would it be three-dimensional space we're actually also moving forward and creating momentum as we go so this the
second kind of energy is that is that way of balancing energy that creates momentum in the
practice and this is a lot of the rebalancing that I mentioned in the guided meditation where we're constantly
sort of noticing oh getting a little foggy here or getting a little tight and doing whatever it takes we get very it
becomes very second nature to go oh I need to ease back this way sometimes it's physical it's in the posture the
shoulders have gotten hunched up around the ears sometimes I'm like I become aware that I don't think it really looks
like this when I'm sitting but basically in my body my shoulders are up around my
ears and I can simply on an usually on an out breath just notice and without
doing very much the shoulders go back down and the the momentum and the sustained balance of energy is is re re
recreated this sustained sort of effort or energy is is
attracts all sorts of wholesome Minds States the ability that we the capacity
we begin to develop of bringing mindfulness to everything is sort of it's it's an outgrowth of this ability
in the meditation to keep sustaining that momentum so that when we meet a new
situation um and in the meditation it may be a snippet of conversation a door
slamming a disturbing thought a memory we get we get better and better at sort
of just coming back to to balance and similarly in daily life practice when
you know an energetic conversation happens at work at home something comes up something happens while we're heading
to IMC on the 101 for those of you in the in the immediate geography around
IMC we have a way to just kind of keep keep sustaining that sense of balance
without getting thrown off so this is the kind of sustained
attention or balance of energy that allows us to stay here to stay
open to remain receptive to what's going on in experience to continue to be
connected to our experience um to be very much um a
member of this moment you know a member of the community of of this moment
instead of kind of floating off into other other moments the past the
future and like I emphasized yesterday this sustained kind of energy is very
pleasant very pleasurable and that is to be enjoyed because it helps it helps
further strengthen our ability to get back here we know something very um that
builds confidence we know when we come back to this feeling of restfulness and ease that this is good and that that
helps us drawing on that confidence that comes with it it actually also helps strengthen the balancing and rebalancing
of energy we go oh this is right now now I'm back here now I'm back here in the center of things because I can feel it
now I'm more more at ease but also very much here very present very
alert um finally at least for today because one could go
on and on the third the third aspect is um
something that you we might call effortless effort we get to a place where the energy hardly needs attention
and we really get in a flow of it the kind of flow that maybe we associate
with playing a musical instrument if we play one or being engaged in a hobby
where we lose track in a way of things like time and the self very profound actually
those flow states in the meditation we actually can harness that sense of effortless energy to really be very
easeful around things like time the constraints of the past and future or around self all the baggage and the ways
we the energy we expend and possibly waste to some extent defending the self
aggrandizing the self creating new selves all of which are useful or not
all of which all of which are um have their let me put it this way some of
which have their place some of which are skillful but all of which have stress in them all those all those identities we
create and use
um each of these three in the final minute each of these three forms of
energy ways of thinking about the capacity that we have to to to bring
balanced energy to our practice involves some letting go and I just mentioned that in the case of the third one but to
review them in this way that first one that initial sitting down and then in as
we meditate beginning again and again has this letting go of it in terms of
sitting down just letting go of other activities but also letting go of
our sense of um preference or judgment coming back to the present moment
without any sense of having done anything wrong or anything having gone wrong we're letting go of a certain
something important there with the continuous or sustained energy we're
letting go of a lot of preoccupation with things a lot of worry about about things where we're just um floating back
to Here and Now keeping connecting with it uh in a way that's sustained constant
quite soft and then third this idea of effortless effort or energy that's
extremely well balanced that here there's a lot of letting go around things like self and holding on to
things attachment uh even if it's momentary even if it's brief it's extremely
easeful and restful for the Mind these these small moments of freedom from
attachment freedom from suffering freedom from holding on so these each of these five faculties
and this one in particular today has within it the seeds of freedom and when
we connect with it when we bring our attention to it when we notice the balancing when we're um explicitly and
consciously aware of the energy we're actually bringing our attention to the letting go that happen happens in the
practice too so it's not just something we're trying to build to strengthen but also
something that has within it the um the the teachings of the Buddha around
letting go and being present for the letting go of suffering in
particular so that's it for today tomorrow we'll talk about the third faculty third divinely human faculty as
I'm calling it that of mindfulness you may have heard of mindfulness um and yet we'll we'll we'll
take a look at some because everybody's heard of mindfulness I'm going to kind
to take a look at some different less thoughtabout less considered forms of
this very important faculty which lies in the middle uh of these five for good
reason it's the fulcrum it's the center point it's the point of balance um so
look forward to looking into that with you tomorrow take care everyone today take take care of one another take care
of yourselves and see you tomorrow bye