so I'd like to mention the obvious
that we're kind of coming into an historical moment in this country that
we're all participating in with the election on
Tuesday and um I wanted to say some words about that relevant for this times
that we're in and um I thought I would like to start where
I've never started a Dhat talk before is start with a
prayer but then I thought I should introduce the prayer with another
prayer or at least a poem and
uh and the reason for this is that um coming out of the meditation
now uh it was so clear to me how meditation can provide us with a
radically different orientation for how to be in the world than if all then it
is if we're only being pushed or LED or by the world of
our thinking if we're only swimming in the Labyrinth of thoughts the Maze of
thoughts and ideas and Concepts uh there's a kind of a way in which there's no way out
uh it's kind of an endless um you know imagine the on wraps and
off- wraps of a freeway that we're just a figure eight soon as you get get off you're on again and it takes you back
and around and around and there's no exit and there's rush hour traffic and
you're slowly making your way around and around there's something about getting caught in the world of thoughts ideas
Concepts which um uh leaves us in a very difficult
world uh very difficult world of the projections we have about the future the
memories of the past what we think our needs are a world in which we're
focusing on objects of attention objects of our hostility objects of our desires
objects of our fears and to have that thinking mind quiet BEC Stiller and
quieter so that something deeper can arise from the wells Springs within we
have we're amazingly um wondrous
beings wondrous beings of emotions of feelings of
Heart of uh sources of wisdom creativity and to be able to meet the
world with the wondrous parts of who we are rather than the scared parts of who we are the wondrous parts of who we are
rather than the parts of us that are consumed with preoccupations that we
have and uh and to be oriented to this historical moment from this deeper Place
rather than the Maze of thoughts and ideas and projections and fears and just
that you know the the media the social you know the way that we could relate to often to uh our news these days or the
way we can so so many people now connect to the whole world through a screen I think it more
often uh puts people up in the Maze of thoughts and reactions and ideas that's
place where we get caught and we're kind of maybe even working on on the habits
of mind that keeps us caught and so to step out of this screen world out of the maze world into this
deep wondrous world that we are is the is the shift of orientation that gives
us a very different understanding of what it means to be alive what it means to be participating in our
society so in preparation for
the poem that I'll read and I'll tell you the poem that I
wrote there's a prayer that I wrote or write I adapted it so it became a prayer
in the the 20 00s there was a presidential candidate running for
president by the name of Dennis kusich congressman from Ohio and he was a one of the great proponents of Peace
work in the world and and uh he wanted to there to be a peace core like a like
a Peace Corp but it was people got trained like in they got trained in military to fight they get trained in a
kind of a peace military for doing peace work in the world and uh and he wanted a peace award
in 2010 I think but he anyway he was running for president and a friend of
mine invited me to come have dinner with him he was going to be in the area and
if I would do kind of a prayer for the at the dinner so that's all I knew and I'd been to her house and it wasn't that big of a
house so I I'd been had eaten at her at her dining room table it wasn't that big
so I didn't think there'd be that many people there it turned out I didn't know she had a big
backyard and so it turned out the whole backyard was everything was in the backyard with you know was a whole
catered with tables and PE and there were a lot of people there it was a political event you know like she'd got
all her friends to come to hear him give a talk and all that so suddenly I you know I don't know about
prayers you know that's not my forte and uh but I I was asked to do it
so what I'm going to read you is for what I read kind of for his sake running
for president and um and I've adopted it a few times now but in preparation
for for that I want to read a poem by Joy harjo the eagle poem it's called and it
says something about prayer to
pray you open your whole self to Sky to Earth to Sun to
Moon to the whole voice that is you and know there is more that you
can't see can't hear can't know except in moments
steadily growing and in languages that aren't always sound but other Circles of motion
like Eagle that Sunday morning over Salt
River circled in Blue Sky in Wind swept
our hearts clean with sacred Wings we see you see
ourselves and know that we must take the utmost care
and kindness in all things breathe
in knowing we are made of all this and breathe knowing we are truly
blessed because we were born and die soon within a true circle
of motion like Eagle rounding out the morning inside
us we pray that it will be done in Beauty
in Beauty so Joy Hardo is one of the great
Native American poets in this country so this is a very different
understanding of prayer what it means to pray so in Beauty in
Beauty so this is a prayer now for civic involvement
as we participate in our democracy may we be guided by the 10
virtues of Civic life may we be
generous so everyone is supported may we have
integrity so everyone can trust us may we renounce selfish interest so
everyone benefits may we be honest so everyone hears what
is true may we be kind so everyone can
relax may we have self-control so everyone everyone may be
safe may we be free of ill will so everyone can speak
freely may we be nonviolent so everyone feels
valued may we be patient so everyone can participate in their own
way may we not obstruct obstruct so that we can learn how to
work together so this so those are 10 10 uh
qualities that in that classic Buddhist uh tradition are called the 12 uh
qualities of a uh ruler of a monarch and um but there's a certain
kind of way that in the United States that uh we're all meant to be
participants in a democracy that uh as equals in a way
that makes us all in a certain kind of way uh
monarchs makes us all somehow participants in this life here
and so in the civic responsibility Civic engagement and uh and so what are the
principles that guide that kind of involvement that are not simply the
pursuit of power not simply the pursuit of being right and O and conquering
others winning over others is there another way is there a way of
cooperation is there a way of having differences and finding a third way that works for everyone
I've kind of staked my DOT Life as a Buddhist on the idea
that if we spend enough time in in conflict and difficulties that you can
find a way that supports everyone it's not a win- lose situation
but it takes it's a challenge to find that I've been in situations where I've been in conflict with people around
something and we're having a maybe a somewhat intense conv ation about it and the other person some point says
well have it your way and I said no we can't do
that um this is actually very important I think if we stay in it and stay in the
intensity of it without being hostile long enough to see if we can find a way
that is a Third Way something that we haven't thought about yet not your way
not my way but maybe there's a way that fits fit us fits us both and U because I've seen that happen
repeatedly if you're willing to stay in the difficulty and sometimes it takes a long time but this idea of a third
way that has everyone's well-being in account is it
naive but I've seen it work in small ways I've seen it I've seen this kind of
these things are possible and uh and so not one where power and being right and winning is the
first and foremost effort of the thing but rather to be cooperative to have conversations find a
way so um some people you know can they come to Buddhism they're hoping that
Buddhism has important things to say about everything in life and the Buddha didn't have much to
say about Civic life that's relevant for our our world today unless you take some
of the core ethical principles and apply them to Civic life but the Buddha uh was
alive at a time that was radically different than our life I it was the Bronze Age just to hear you Buddha lived
in the Bronze Age and uh there was no democracies in India at that time maybe there was
burgeoning democracy in Greece at that time maybe but even that was kind of very different than what we have
today and um and you know there were there were kings that ruled back then
who were kind of like dictators uh you know to stand up and
protest to a King back in the time of the Buddha there there the ancient texts
give graphic depictions which I won't provide you with um of what the king
would do to you you know with no hesitation and so the um you know there
was no democracy there was no courts per se that we have today there was no laws
in the same way we have today that you can rely on it was all in the whims of a ruler and what happened to the great
extent and um and U you know there were no social
services for you know to go to and no and uh no social security no retirement
money you know there was people weren't provided for by the government there were not no nonprofits that were there
to set up soup kit and take care of things in some ways um it was so
radically different and so and also the the ways people communicated in the ways
that people affected each other was to a big part what you could see was the
human human interactions human connections to each other and so when the Buddha talked
about how to live together he talked about the visible world the the behavior
the conduct that we had that everyone could see they could see if they killed each other
and he said don't do that you could see if they were stealing from each other and he said this is not a good idea you
can kind of see or know in some ways unless it was done too secretly uh you know uh uh with the sexual
misconduct that's a form of behavior between people there was
lying not telling the truth people could hear it and then there was problems that
came from intoxication which generally you kind of see it if people are too
intoxicated so it was all that that's the world that they were swimming in back then in the Bronze
Age but now we have a society where we affect each other by how we
vote and uh it can have huge impact we have we can affect each other by how we
participate in social media and what we add there what we say and the effect that we have on people in the world
around us now is invisible it's we don't even see the effect we have we affect
others by what we consume and then we affect the world by what happens when after we flush it down
the toilet or after we put it in the trash so most people don't think about once it's gone it's gone we don't think
about it but how we live our alive has an effect that if that is not visible to us and so it gets more and more
complicated how this all works and so this comes into play with
civic responsibility phys Civic Civic involvement where the effect SP spills
out in all kinds of different ways and so uh to be careful is not just
to avoid killing stealing sexual misconduct lying and intoxication it involves some deeper
principles some deeper care all in Buddhist point of view all
Guided by the wish to not cause harm and how do we not cause harm in unseen ways
how do we not cause harm and that's the primary motivation around ethics and
Buddhism is to live a life of non-harming so these uh 10 principles
that were originally designed for encouraging Kings to to rule well which
that had then um uh adapted for 20 years
ago so for a presidential candidate and and um the best thing that happened
out of doing that was Dennis kinich did ask me for a
copy what that happened to that copy I have no idea but um but so um to not harm but instead
to be generous but why be generous so everyone feel supported and
and for there one of the primary kind of messages that Buddha seemed to have
wanted to give to monarchs in his time was to take care of the poor and he has
uh the Buddha gave a lot of teachings or some teachings uh that described if you don't support the poor and bring take
them out of poverty that it's going to be deleterious for the whole society the whole society will start unraveling was
his teaching so take care of the poor but take care of the poor uh so that
everyone is supported uh don't have it a win lose situation but Prosperity so everyone
prospers uh I think it's a fair probably a fair assessment of our of our world
that there's there's enough abundance in this world for everyone to live well but most people don't live well
because it's not shared equally and evenly even in this country here United States there's enough here I mean it's
probably the wealth of 10 people certain 10 people we have that could probably
reduce poverty in this country dramatically but the concentration of wealth into a very few hands is it's
unprecedented I think and um and is it healthy for us I think there's a
plentitude so that can make everyone feel supported Pro certain certain prosperity for everyone except for those
people who have to lose maybe a few tens of billions of dollars they'll we'll feel sorry for
them I guess but they'll still be left with a lot but there is a you know this they of
support and everyone's in it together this they of we how do we support everyone so everyone thrives is what's
behind this this principle of be generous so everyone is supported may we have integrity so
everyone can trust us trust is probably the biggest wealth
that we have or or one of the biggest wealth what if we call trust a form of wealth as opposed to money and bank
accounts being wealth uh I think that uh most wonderful
things in our society with our closest friends with our closest Family if it's healthy and well are based on the
foundation of trusting each other and Trust goes a long way if we have
integrity and people trust our integrity integrity and perhaps Integrity then
becomes contagious uh renouncing selfish interest so
everyone benefits so again this idea that not hoarding not just concern for
ourselves but concern for others and there's a way in which benefiting others
will come back and benefit ourselves uh maybe there's no economic
models or theories or data to show this directly but um there's a classic thing
in some some culture some of here California the Native American uh polash
cultures where they've studied theologists have studied and pointed out that what how the economics and these
cultures work in a healthy way is that the gift keeps being given and the and goods are kept in
circulation so fash culture was one where people would come together periodically and do a huge gift giving
kind of uh festivals rituals where they'd give to each other and lots of giving but as soon as someone then
stopped giving then it got constipated so there has to keep going
and keep going and so how do we keep a gift economy how do we keep generosity
how do we keep benefiting the world as something that keeps flowing we benefit
tremendously how do we keep the gift of how we benefit from our society uh going
so we it doesn't get bottleneck or stuck in US uh but keep keep benefiting let it
keep flowing there's something about the cycles of generosity of giving that uh
that is makes for a really healthy Society um may we be honest so everyone
hears the uh what is true nowadays true is truth is relevant Rel Rel considered
to be re relevant relevant relative it's still relative relative
relevant the um and um but the uh but the in Buddhism to be
uh to say the truth is to be true yourself to be a true person and a true
person doesn't lie doesn't manipulate doesn't try to uh get their own way at
any cost at all uh a true person is someone who has integrity and is able to
speak from that place may we be kind so everyone can
relax imagine there was a society where no one was kind would you want to live in that
Society imagine all the
kindness maybe I shouldn't use all imagine what you'd be like today as
a person if no one had ever been kind to
you growing up was anybody kind to you did it happen
occasionally did it make a difference for you that occasionally your parents were kind your teachers were
kind your friends were kind imagine if you received nothing of it what would it
be like I suspect that a lot of what's good about you was partly shaped by the kind
this you received from others and maybe from strangers even it's inconceivable to have a
society that isn't based on kindness and there's also the gift of
kindness can we keep it in circulation can we keep doing it and offering it
back may we have self-control so everyone may be safe one of the ideas in
Buddhism is that um we restraint is a fundamentally
important practice because we can't necessarily know what's going on in our
mind or we can't control the mind sometimes the impulses of the Mind the mind is a tricky
thing but we H we can have the principle in Buddhism we can have control about
how the mind gets expressed in action and the actions are actions of
the body the things we do with our body and what we say and now what we
type uh that uh the phys what we do physically we can have some we have more
control over that than what we you know our capacity to control the mind and it
counts a lot to have that degree of self-control so that you don't cause harm it does whatever is difficult in
your mind doesn't spill out and one of the reasons that not have to difficult in your mind spill out and affect others
in harmful ways is that what goes out comes back or what go what goes out
becomes a habit gets reinforced creates more discomfort more problems inside so
to have enough self self-control so that our behavior is not causing harm our
words don't cause harm is one of the really important principles in
Buddhism and it's not we not we're not meant to repress our elves that way but
uh but rather meditation is a way of really knowing ourselves well enough so
that we can really understand how to be with what's challenging inside of ourselves in a skillful way in a useful
way and one of the things that I've learned to do when I have difficulty in my mind and my my inner life with what's
going on is uh not to act impulsively from it but to tell people you know I'm
challenged right now you know this is really difficult for me what's happening now and and you
should probably know that I'm grumpy so you know just let's let's be careful now you know me I'll be careful
maybe you can be careful with me and until this mood that I have changes but
the ability to just be honest in a way that doesn't harm people but actually protects
people so self-control so everyone may be safe Maybe we may we be free of ill will
the word translated here is ill will is the ancient language probably is a stronger word than ill will it's
actually hostility so maybe they're the same or
just little variations of each other but um to not to not have hostility not act
from hostility I would say that's one of the Cardinal principles and Buddhist
ethics never act on hostility if that's in terms of self you know
self-control restraint if you have hostility restrain yourself bite your
tongue whatever it takes you know don't don't speak it wait come back if you
need to work something else with someone um go and process your hostility
on your own or in some with a friend or something until it's settled enough so
you can come back and um and have a a good conversation once I was had I was doing
a program here at IMC with a colleague and uh and I I got really
angry or we had a difficulty between us so we went into the conference room there and uh to have a little chat about
what was going on and um at some point it was hard conversation at some point I
said to my friend um can we pause I I think I need to calm down a
little little bit so I can come back in a more useful way in this conversation and she was fine with that you know that
they just I asked for it so as opposed to just feeling I had to keep fighting
back or fighting and going and going and going which probably would have been harmful for both of
us so I recognized the the ill will that I had and I said this is not good let's
lets me find a way to settle down and calm down and it worked out fine in the end
may we be nonviolent so everyone feels
valued how many people in our society don't feel valued there it's
epidemic I think in our society here and there the people don't
feel valued there's some people who who it's really chronic they almost anywhere they go they don't feel valued they
don't feel respected they don't they're dignity is not allowed and
um I talked to someone recently who was a hospital chaplain who met someone a
homeless person who' come into the hospital and and um it seemed like that
person had never been respected and never had a friend in his whole life and
that's what he most wanted was to have a friend
may we be patient so everyone can participate in their own
way everyone can participate in their own way that's dangerous isn't
it but this is like the this is the ninth of the 10 principles so you're
building on all the others mutual respect so everyone can
find their own way and may we not
obstruct may we not hinder so that we can learn how to work
together if we offer obstruction to people if we hinder them and stop them and try to silence them then then
there's no cooperation there's no working together so how do we have conversations
so it feels like We're In It Together how do we learn to respect people how do we learn to find a
way so I would like to propose that
um in my reading of what's happening in this country right now there's way too
much emphasis on who's going to become the president as if that is the crucial
issue that's going to make or break the country I'd like to propose something
different I think we're coming to a a a crisis maybe for each of you what
what are you going to do how are you going to participate in the Civic life are you expecting the Civic life to
be solved by someone else out there who's going to do it all for us make
everything fine and you can continue on your life merily as it is I don't think that's the right way to
live in a democracy I think of to live in a democracy is to be participant in some
way and so how you you are is very important and and so these 10 principles
of civic participation doesn't mean you have to join a political party doesn't mean you
have to go and get involved in so-called politics but these are the ways that we
can make a better society and to start there and then if that's understood then
you can run for president I'll come and do a
prayer for you so so those are my thoughts for
today as we go so no matter what happens on Tuesday remember these 10
principles it's once in the scenarios different scenarios that people are
predicting so probably in all the scenarios that people are predicting or imagining might happen they all need
this they all need individuals and people who rely on this and maybe this will give
you some strength and some inspiration encouragement to how to go forward and U
and all of us contribute to a better world better
Society so thank you those are my thoughts on this historic
times and uh we have about 10 minutes before the end so now uh we could try to
um if you have any questions comments Reflections on what I just said
testimonials Gil thank you so much can you post that prayer or pass it out or
something I want to be able to reread it it's already posted on the homepage
im's weite there's a on the bottom right there's a section called what's new and
then there's Reflections from Gil as part of that and there you see it now it's already already there excellent
what oh the poem Joy Hardo is um it's
called The Eagle poem you can find it online I don't want to post her it's h a RJ o harjo
I think she's Cherokee a wonderful woman wonderful wonderful poet and
um and uh so Joy harjo the eagle called Eagle
poem and you can also actually uh find her reading her poem
online um Gil um so I I'm aware that uh
American friends or Quakers they make all their decisions by consensus but how
they do it I have no idea well sometimes it takes them a very long time and uh there there I don't know if
I have the DAT the time exactly right but I've I've been told that it took them 200 years to decide to be against
slavery you know it's kind of heartbreaking to hear that but at least they came around
wow but yeah consensus is really good we tried to do that things on consensus
here at IMC there have been times on the times on the IMC board where we've taken a
vote for something and one person one person doesn't isn't that they're opposed even they say you know
they just choose not to vote and I've said no no look let's not make a decision today then let's give
time for this if want we want to have everyone feel like everyone particip Ates and so at least let let's make the
effort at least so then we maybe reach out to that person during the before the next board meeting and just find out
what's going on and see if there's some way that we can make it work whatever we're going to do here so that everyone
feels they can support it and you can't but we can't expect that always but at
least we can make the effort for it that's respectful
yeah thank you that was a nice talk um what what kind of came up for me when
I was listening to your remarks was um the fact that I I think we live in a
time when there's an exceptional amount of fear and I think a lot of what we're
seeing um behind it is is fear which is usually
a very um unhelpful emotion when it comes
to you know doing all the the wholesome things you describe and I wonder if you
could comment on that especially you know the tension between wanting to
engage positively um and at the same time maybe being a little afraid for ourselves of
what could happen you know there are thank you for
the question there are many many ways that the fears in our society can be and
maybe should be addressed and um and you know small Buddhist organization like us or a
Buddhist practitioner by themselves uh cannot address all the different ways that can be or should be done but one of
the special is that Buddhism offers is the ability to come to terms with our
own fear to really be able to look at it deeply settle it come to some place
where our fear doesn't no longer blocks us no longer gets in our way there still
might be fear but we now find learn how to be free uh so we can be wise with
whatever fear we carry uh or our Fe our fear is sett
settled uh and we can live without any anxiety and uh there might be some fear
but no anxiety that's a kind of radical thing so the idea of looking really
knowing ourselves and learning how to become free of our own fear is a part of
the gift of this practice that we do the other side of that is um to
become a person who others don't have to fear to be someone who can walk through
the world World safe A friend of everyone someone no one no one is afraid and sometimes people are afraid for us
even though we're a safe person they don't know that they might see you as belonging to a group of people that
historically has been harmful to them and so it's hard for them to distinguish between uh who's safe and who's not but
to really work on not taking for granted that people feel would think that you're
automatically a safe person but how can you be a safe person how could you show
up in a friendly way or in a so that so we give people the gift of
fearlessness and um and I think it's a great gift gift to our society and um and again uh you know to
expect that other people are going to make the everyone safe you
know it's a bit I think it we can expect it if you want that
someone else is going to do the work um but uh you have to do it
too so how do you come to terms with your fear how do you develop yourself in
such a way that you can walk through the world and be safe for people you have the confidence to be able to show up in
a way and and feel safe even if people are angry with you you know you have some way of being how can you do that
that it's not easy but that's why this practice can help that
tremendously so uh to go deep into this practice is part of the answer for
you is that is that adequate to
answer
can thank you hi well as you just said what well
what bothers me sometimes is when I talk the people I talk to about this sort of
thing there's an overwhelming sense of I'm one
person I can't do anything and can't make an impact and I just want to say that when I sit on the cushion I have
kind of a ritual where I set my intention why am I there and I say to
myself may this meditation make me stronger so I am a Force for good in the
world and better the life of everyone I come in contact with and everyone they
come in contact with and it just goes on from there nice but um I I just like you
just said we can make a difference even though we're only one person yeah every
every individual can make a difference and um there's a lovely story that I
love of um it's a Sufi story story of some I guess some kind of maybe God or a
Genie or something some Spirit offers this this man um two wishes you can have
anything you want and um and so he says well wherever
I go I want to benefit the people around me that's the first wish the second wish
but I don't know I don't want to know that I'm doing it
and so he's given a bag uh of a big bag that he carries over his shoulder filled
with seeds and there's a little hole in the bag and it's always being replenished by the spirits or something
but wherever he walks those seeds fall out and they germinate and grow to
something flowers or trees or fruit apple trees or something and uh so it takes a long time
for that to happen he's long gone you know he keeps walking and and so symbolically you know we can always make
a difference but we don't necessarily see the actual results of making a
difference um the um I've Been Changed by total
strangers who spent five minutes with me and their kindness and support just wow
I felt like that was inspiring that's possible can be done this way and um and
they never knew that they had such a big impact on me we don't know when we're gonna have an impact we don't know when
um you know that uh we we're kind to a local kid who's kind of having a lot of
challenges maybe no one's ever been kind to the kid and there's a glimmer of hope
for that person than they never had before so this we don't know what seeds we're
planting but let's plant seeds anyway and who knows what'll happen
who knows the influence you have we have more influence than we realize if we are
kind if we're supportive if we're friendly if we're safe for others so
many people in our society are afraid and probably the people who are saying what you said you I'm just in
just me somehow how could can I do I suspect that behind that is
fear and or are some others kind of feel of feeling somehow
unworthy everyone is worthy
so I wish you well and uh I have the idea that um we
don't know what's going to happen this week of course but uh hopefully it's all smooth
and harmonious and everyone realizes everyone realizes in the last minute what how good it is to cooperate and and
support each other and we'll live happily ever after uh but I also have some thought
that if if there's enough um challenges uh going on that maybe we
should have some kind of meeting maybe be available for some discussion or some context or it all and
so maybe it can be maybe a Wednesday evening if some may be some kind of Zoom meeting that maybe if it's necessary or
something I don't know what what's going to happen and um so I don't know I guess
the only place to really announce that is on uh what's new on the website if
you know in short notice like that the Google Calendar if we put it there it sometimes takes Google many hours to
update to make it public what we put on the calendar so just look at what's new and we'll see what makes sense and um
I'm teaching a retreat next week so for the next week I'll be thinking about the
retreatant know how do how do we care for them um but um anyway so so that um if
you're interest in such a things if it looks like we have the need for something um look at what's
new so thank you very much and may you all
be civically responsible in these 10 ways