good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all so tonight I'd like to start with a setting a little scene that happens at
on the Buddha's deathbed he knows he's going to die so
he asks for a special bed to be made for him between these trees
out in a on the outskirts of a town and then right before he's ready to
die just moments before he
asks he has this question that he asks and the quote is from this if even a
single monastic has any doubt or uncertainty concerning the Buddha Dharma
or SAA or the Dharma I'm sorry or the path and the
practice ask do not afterwards feel remorse
thinking the teacher was there before us and we failed to ask him when we were in
his presence so maybe he was thinking like this is the real thing I am going to die this is your last chance you have
you have any questions there's so many things here that is you know it seems maybe mundane
but but it's kind of special in some way he's not saying okay I only want to talk
to my little Inner Circle as I'm dying right he's not saying that and later on that it talks about there's 500 people
there there's 500 monastics and he's saying is anybody out there have any
questions doesn't matter if they're just like a somebody who's newly ordained or the most senior he's like to have any
questions but then he also qualifies it do you have any questions about the Buddha Dharma SAA and the path and the
practice and I'll talk about this a little bit more like what are some of the questions that he didn't think were
so suitable at this time so he's kind of like confining it
to okay do you have questions about what I've been teaching what uh all this teaching has
really been about we could say you know suffering and the ending of
suffering Buddha said this on a number of occasions that was all his uh teachings were oriented this way and we
could say Buddha dmaa path and practice is about suffering and the end
of suffering and maybe in the fact that
he's saying this on his deathbed moments before he dies makes it uh kind of like
highlights that he wanted there to be Clarity he wanted people to understand and it wasn't like he was trying to be
enigmatic and have secret teachings or anything like this it was more like okay
I've offered what I've offered is it clear do you did you get
it and then monastics in response to this question say
nothing it's silent then he asks it a second
time it's still silent and then he
asks perhaps you don't ask out of respect for the teacher so let a friend
tell a friend I kind of like this like I'm asking for a friend is this blah
blah blah right you know this goes all the way back to the time of the Buddha this whole idea and it also kind of like highlights
you know we talk about this you know having community and having friends in the Dharma and this is part of you know
we often don't think about this but maybe there's a way in which we have a question and we don't feel comfortable
asking but maybe one of our friends does and they could ask but I don't know I
appreciate this very much the Buddha saying okay maybe you're embarrassed or May for whatever reason just tell
somebody else and they can ask it like he really wants to make sure that people
understand he wants them to ask questions if there's anything that's not
clear and they're still silent so nobody asks a
question and then Ananda who was the Buddha's attendant um said wow it's amazing that
nobody asked any questions and the Buddha says to
Ananda which I it's for me is a little bit perplexing but we we won't get into that uh Buddha says to Ananda well
that's because everybody of these 500 people have at least the first degree of
Awakening which means that they no longer have doubt so that means they have enough clarity about all the
teachings that um that they don't feel like they need to ask
questions and then maybe in a subsequent teaching I'll say like the next sentence he says which is the very last sentence
he says and then dies but I'm not going to talk about that one to right now I want to stick with this idea that that
Buddha he was asking like okay what are your questions this idea that he's uh
supporting and encouraging this whole notion of asking questions and he's
pointing to one way we could think about it is saying that uh having some understanding on suffering and the
ending of suffering is important and it's important for all of
us to you know understand it in a way that we can
and if we don't understand it to ask questions or maybe
investigate because he didn't this in contrast is uh a teacher that might say
okay here are these Creeds uh memorize them and you're
good to go you know just like you know here's something memorize it and who cares if you understand it you you just
have to memorize these things no he's saying you need to understand and if you don't ask so this
is so different than just kind of like passively receiving information and then just buying it
wholeheartedly and it's so different than just being told okay just memorize
or believe these particular statements and that's sufficient it's a really different way of a a spiritual teaching
it's a really different way of uh engaging with one's spiritual life
especially at this time in India it was a radical
idea to really um discover for oneself and to engage with
oneself and uh in another uh Su the Buddha talks about that there's these
communities where there's a people who don't ask questions and people who do
ask question questions and he says those communities in which they ask questions of each
other is the foremost Community it's the community that's doing the best and he
says um they question and examine each other asking how is this what is the
meaning of this and they discuss what is obscure and elucidate what is unclear
and dispel their perplexity about perplexing points
so if there's any confusion this encouragement to ask one another even if
not asking the teacher so as I was saying there's a way
in which having a question really points to some involvement some engagement with
the teachings in a way kind of like rolling up our sleeves and kind of like really thinking about it or getting into
it as opposed to just uh hearing maybe
is that is that right well just hearing things does often just touch our hearts too but there's like practices to be
done and um contemplations perhaps and
cultivations and you know so there's a certain amount of Engagement and questioning is part of it
but also questioning even if you have a question like underline that is this
assumption that there is a logic behind it like why
is that what is this that implies that there's an answer to those questions as
opposed to somebody saying okay well this is just magic believe it and uh you're good to go but if you're asking
questions is this uh understanding like okay well what what's the reason for
this and what led to that and what are the consequences of this going to be and how do you know and how can I know these
types of things which I appreciate very much of course right I'm trained as a
scientist so I love this kind of stuff like I kind of like to I don't know like
understand things it's a I come from a family of scientists so this is just you know kind
of the the way that I was socialized and so it feels comfortable and fun for me
and familiar it doesn't have to be that way for everybody but uh for me it is
but also asking questions suggests that uh that you're willing to hear an
answer that is you're willing to learn something you're willing to say I I
don't know you're willing to be told something by somebody else I've known a number of
people and perhaps you have too who really don't want to learn anything from from anybody they already have it all
figured out and they're all happy to tell you all the answers but they're not
going to admit or even suggest that you know I I'm not clear about this point
here I have perplexity about this point let's talk about it do you understand it
I'm not sure and maybe I'll say that uh for me
personally a big part big part of my kind of like path of practice is I had the Great Good Fortune to meet um a
number of people uh when I was first starting on this path of practice and we
sometimes would like go to Pete's Coffee that's not just a right over here and we would just like wow what what was that
did you get it what do you think and we would just talk about it it was so much fun to kind of like just talk about these ideas and and I know here on
Sundays I think they do that on some Sundays that's done on Zoom I think it's done in person on some Sundays
also I'll play around if maybe we want to do that here in some of these days but sometimes it's just nice to talk
with other people about some of these ideas because it's different right when
you hear yourself saying things out loud like when you have to uh create a sentence and put a group of thoughts
together you realize kind of like where some of the gaps of the knowledge
is sometimes happens to me I'm reading the sutas I love reading the sutas and
um sometimes I'll say to somebody else like oh there's I discovered this new little teaching that's has X Y and Z
it's often it's skill I'm telling this to you and he'll say oh but what about a b and c I'm like oh H I didn't think
about that yeah and then just realize oh yeah put it in context and add it on to
some other teachings it's it's a way in which uh we make the teachings our own
and make them come alive instead of just passively receiving
information so this whole idea of asking questions maybe it's obvious but um I'll
say it explicitly it helps us with doubt like this hindrance of doubt doubt
can show up as a hindrance when it's a shows up as this vacillation or this
hesitation like I don't know I'm not sure I I I don't know what to do
and we find ourselves kind of stuck a little bit like some obvious examples or
if you sit down to meditate and you have this idea okay I'm going to do mindfulness
meditation you do a little bit of mindfulness and then you notice that that you're actually pretty grumpy and
then you think okay well I'll do some loving kindness meditation and then you do a little bit
of loving kindness you know a few minutes oh no that doesn't seem to be working well maybe I'll just do like listening meditation opening up and to
the sounds yeah okay I don't like that sound of that dog okay maybe I'll come back to the breath and this way of kind
of like this doubt is a way of which we kind of like hesitate and we don't know and we often are just like bouncing
around whereas if we had a little bit more I'll use this word
confidence that we could we would uh say okay yep the mind is a little bit uh
busy right now and it's I'm grumpy and that's just how it is right
now and we would just hang in there and then we would have the opportunity to see how the mind just settles on its
own if we give it time sometimes we have to just give it time but often we have
this uh um impatience or it's uncomfortable what we're experiencing so
we want to do something else so that's one way that doubt shows up
another way that doubt shows up is like I'm not so sure about this lineage
of Buddhism it seems like they're having more fun over there the Tibetan Buddhist people they have colorful things and fun
hats and different words and you know all this stuff and the Zen they have this beautiful aesthetic right with this
kind of like Simplicity and this beauty so there might be like this real
hesitation about even this particular lineage or this tradition that could be doubt also
there could be doubt in the teacher does she really know what she's talking about any teacher Dharma books me
sitting here you know whomever there can also be doubt about oneself like okay it seems like this is
a good uh tradition seems like the teachers seem
reasonable and it makes sense to me the teachings that I hear but I don't think I can do it I have to go find something
easier or something else that's another way that doubt shows up and the
teachings the teacher or in oneself and so this
um doubt so that's doubt as a hindrance but there can be doubt that's really
healthy and helpful and this kind of doubt it could be this one of hm I'm not
sure and then there's a thing like a thinking of okay what is this specific question what is it that I'm not sure
about and to kind of like pinpoint the doubt or you know like uh make it uh
more specific instead of just a hesitation or a vacillation like do I have to believe in
rebirth for this tradition what do they mean when they talk about not
self or was a Buddha really awakened are there awakened people to day I don't
know I'm just saying these questions that sometimes people have but it can be helpful to really kind of like um even
like write down okay what are the questions that I have and then to go back and look at
those questions and and see okay which one of these questions if I had an
answer would really support my practice because some of the questions are maybe things that we would like to know but
whether we know the answer or don't know the answer may not impact us very much it's more of a
curiosity but is there a question that really has a impact on your
practice on you the way that you show up for yourself for this
practice which one is like the most significant for you
personally I know for me one that I had uh earlier I felt so touched by the
teachings and it uh really spoke to my heart and meant a lot to me and when I started to read the
sutas most of the uh individuals not all of them but most of them are
monastics and I really felt like oh gee okay if I want to be serious about this
I guess I have to shave my head and give everything away and go live in a cave or something like this I didn't really
understand what monastics were but this was a real concern of mine like I I didn't want to you know shave my head
and become a nun and you know live in a monastic lifestyle somewhere and a
somewhere you know far away or something like this that just didn't really interest me I have a family and you know
to take care of and you know these types of things so I just asked do I have to
ordain is that how one is becomes a serious practitioner here and the answer answer was a really
resounding no at the at the time of the
Buddha it wasn't possible to attend a day long there were no like meditation
centers where you could go and meditate there weren't books that you could read
there weren't uh things that you could listen the only way that you can have the teachings is if you heard them by
somebody and if you are a monastic you are more likely to actually hear them if you weren't a monastic you were most
likely busy all during the day doing what one did in Ancient India to
survive so it's just like very different now now we have so much more Leisure Time and we have a lifestyle that uh
allows people to go on Retreats or come to a meditation center in the evening so
just in case any of you had that question to you about the need to ordain some people feel really cold and want to
dedicate their life and want to ordain and that's beautiful but it certainly isn't
required and maybe I'll just say also as it happened for me I ended up spending
one year which I was spent more time on Retreat than off Retreat so this is
something that I could do not as a monastic right just as a lay person just a I had the great Good Fortune my life
at that time allowed me to do that so there's a way in which I think in modern
times if you're want to dedicate your life to practice there's many ways in which one
can do that but it might be you know worthwhile
to ask well in what way does doubt or questions or unresolved
questions affect my practice maybe it doesn't affect my practice or maybe it
does maybe there's a way in which it holds you back this could be a question to ask
oneself excuse me so then this whole notion of
questioning is we might say is part of Investigation D
Vaya some of you will know that uh investigation is one of the factors of Awakening so one of the elements that uh
is a part of the whole Awakening process it's a we might say a necessary part is
this investigation again it's the opposite of just kind of passively receiving or just
believing it's instead actually kind of being curious and being present for
what's actually happening and what is the meaning behind what's said what is
it what's what's being pointed to with the words with the sentences with the stories what's being pointed to what is
it that they what's the meaning trying to convey not just the exact words but what's the
meaning and so investigation is the second factor of Awakening it comes um
after mindfulness and so it's part of a helps lay the foundation that can lead
to it leads to equinity which is the seventh of the seven factors of Awakening I'm not going to go through
the whole list here but which is a big part of help creating the conditions for these uh big Awakening experiences a big
shift in one's perspective a shift in
one's I'll just use this word perspective of have of the of uh the way
of viewing the world and viewing
oneself and so there's a way of which uh
investigation can be something like um just asking in meditation or in everyday
life just dropping in the question what is
this seems like a simple question like okay it's a a bowl or it's could be a
hat or it could be a bell or it could be a an ornament it can be a weapon you can
throw it right it it's all these things but this idea just to ask like well what
is this what or yeah what is this and then there's a way to just drop in the
question and then open up and an answer might Bubble Up it
might not bubble up but the point is to ask the question not to find the
answer it's the being the open and receptive that uh changes the we might
say the ecology in the mind and the heart this this uh willingness to learn
something new this willingness to have a new understanding this willingness to
let go of the idea of like okay I got it all figured out I just have to keep on
doing this or something like that and to be sure often we want to feel safe and
in order to feel safe we want to feel like okay I know everything I got it all figured out here I know what it is
or but there's a way in which we can be like closing down or shutting ourselves
off from maybe some surprises or some unexpected or some maybe settle things
that could be really helpful for us to understand understand about the world
understand about ourselves or maybe another way
investigation can show up is what's underneath this or why am I
doing this just not again not to find the answer but just to open up to having
some curiosity about what are some of our patterns it could be like I don't know
why I do I'm doing this I always do it this way or it could be well I now that
I think about it I guess I'm doing this because I really really dislike it and I'm hoping this is going to go away this
thing or this experience is going to go away so I'm bracing myself against it or I'm
uh yelling or I don't know whatever it might be whatever it might be so just to have some Curious curiosity about why we
do some of the things that we do it's kind so like asking this kind of
question why am I doing this because there's a way in which our
patterns I mean there's a reason why we have them but we don't have to be stuck with them
for our whole life they can be undone and that's part or loosened up and
softened and that's part of what meditation practice allows is for us to
allow the mind to get quiet and not being pushed around so much and then we
can start to see some of our patterns with more clarity and then we can start to
recognize is oh it doesn't have to be that way I don't have to respond with
anger every time that I'm feeling uncomfortable or I feel like I have to wait for something and my impatience
makes me feel angry at uh whomever it is I perceive is causing to make me wait or
something like this so there's this way that um
investigation is the factor of Awakening and it can also uh be a
hindrance in the sense that um it's a way in which a version often can hide
behind what is this you know this kind there's this tone that's okay I got to
figure this out so I can get rid of it there's this or I'm only asking what is
this so that it'll go away and maybe if I ask it enough times this thing will go away I've done a lot of that in my
practice thinking like okay I know what I'm supposed to do and and I was you know questioning or investigating and I
didn't even recognize how I had this little agenda I think uh Joseph Goldstein he told me this one time and
it was very impactful he h said well you're investigating with a in order to mind
you're only asking in order to make it go away or in order to have a different
experience there isn't a completeness of just asking for asking so this is part
of the way in which investigation can be uh just a way that aversion shows up or maybe greed shows
up maybe you're only asking because you want more of something else or something like
this so there's this way that can we just ask or investigate again just kind
of just for the act of
asking instead of like always pursuing something where we feel like we have to find the answer we have to solve a
question we have to fix a problem there's a way in which just asking allows us to
just kind of like open up and be curious about what's
happening and then here's a a quote from Michael phen who actually I don't know
who this is because somebody else that I was reading quoted Michael thalen so
whomever Michael thalen is I bow to you but here's this quote answers don't arrive if you are
afraid of sitting in the empty Dark Room of not
knowing so there's this way of sitting in the empty Dark Room of not knowing
that's when answers can arise and sometimes this empty dark room feels
uncomfortable but I think that's the invitation here is maybe to you know
find the spaciousness and the beauty that's present in not knowing all the
answers something different can arise something new can
arise something else about investigation is that it can turn into I sometimes
like to call this like an archaeological dig like we're just trying to figure this out and maybe it's because that
thing that happened when I was eight years old and then my mom did this and my brother did that or you know there's
this way in which we can really try to figure it out and do kind of like a psychological
dig that has value and it has its place but that's not what we're doing with
meditation meditation is doing something really different it's just asking what is this and it's
allowing things to Bubble Up it's not digging trying to find them because
that's more rumination or or contemplation or something that's very
different than um investigation but because they're both questioning maybe
there's a way in which they can get conflated and we can feel like oh that's what I should be doing while my eyes are
closed and I'm quiet is trying to figure this out but I would say in this tradition that's
not what we do during our meditation we're just creating the conditions for the answers to find us we don't have to
find them and it's quite something it's quite something how this happens we all
have this experience where like in the shower like oh right and figures that
out or out for a walk or something like that it's the same type of thing where things just uh the answers
arrives so maybe I'll also say that not all questioning is
useful not all questioning is useful there is
a in fact there's a these 10 questions that the Buddha he didn't even bother to
answer he just didn't even think that they were worthwhile and I I'll just say
um and he didn't answer them because he thought you know this has no bearing on
supporting one's uh suffering and the lessening of suffering if you want to
understand suffering and your particular suffering suffering in the world and how to alleviate or diminish or delete
suffering it wouldn't help with that and not only would it not help with that but
it also had these assumptions underneath it that would lead person the wrong way
it would just coming from a point of view that uh would not be supportive an example is something like
this do unicorns have green eyes or blue
eyes right it doesn't help you with your suffering or not and it just assumes that
unicorns have eyes that they exist you know all these kinds of
things and sometimes when we hear these 10 questions that the Buddha didn't bother answering we might not understand
these um or appreciate maybe some of the assumptions that underly them I won't go
through all of these 10 questions I have in some other talks and maybe I will again at sometime but um two of these
questions are is the world Eternal is the world
infinite so is the world Eternal talking about time does it have a beginning does
it have an end and then implicit in that question is it only matters if there's a
self or a soul or something that would last forever otherwise it just is a
completely irrelevant question so there's this assumption underneath it that there's some continuity of a of a
of a being through time and the same with a infinite it's the same idea with
space too that's only a relevant question if it assumes that uh an entity could go
through all space or something like this so the Buddha he was pointing to
that uh some questions they're just lead there's like e
help don't help uh with suffering and not only that that they we could spend a
lot of time worrying about them or thinking about them we trying to figure them out and they're not
answerable and they might even be causing us more suffering and he really wanted to
highlight that going down that road isn't the road that's going to help us with our life and this is part of why
with meditation practice with this practice we're really focusing on What's happen Happening Here and Now like
what's knowable for ourselves here and
now that's the beauty and the power of this practice it's really about what all
of us as individuals can discover for
ourselves each of us for ourselves it doesn't
require some special
um teachings or some special maybe it doesn't require
anything special it does require practice though I will say that it does require
practice so this whole idea of questioning AB
Buddha right on his deathbed was does anybody have any questions and he talked about uh in how
community that question one another and spiritual friends who support one another with questions are an important
part of practice and it's one of the factors of Awakening this investigation this questioning mind this uh approach
to not having the answers but some questions are more
worthwhile than others so it might be worthwhile for us to see are there some questions that we have some doubt that
we have that is affecting our practice is affecting our
engagement with the practice and if so you can read a book
listen to Dharma talks ask a teacher ask other people with these questions and
find some answers that hopefully can support you in your
practice so I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there's some
questions thank you
let's see is this on oh yes um well thank you for this talk it
definitely uh feels like an invitation to ask something that I've been wondering about for a while but I
haven't asked because I didn't want to be like challenging or kind of come off the wrong way um I
think something that has given me pause at times has
been the conversations about um like desire and
diversion um because well I came to the practice um
feeling very like out of touch with myself at first um and found that as I
meditated I started to develop actually more awareness of my own uh desire
desires and aversions and uh you know the boundaries that I need to move in the world and things like that um
and I find those things important to know um
especially like as a feminist and things like that where where are those boundaries what do I say yes to you know
um and I guess I to distill it into a
simple question Maybe there's a part of me that's just like
what's wrong with those things what's wrong with desire or aversion uh or
both yeah do you have a sense or does it seem like they're all good or does it
seem like there's any downsides um I mean they can go too far
they can be um you know obsessional or sort of uh
compulsive um some aversions I would say I definitely ruminate about
you know my desire to avoid certain things um yeah so maybe there's a
line yeah so what happens often is that uh we have an experience and then we
have a reaction to that experience desire or aversion and then we're often moving through this like desire
inversion and we're completely lost contact with actually what the experience is but instead we're having a
relationship with I like this I want more of it therefore I got to do something this and then in the future I
got to remember to stop at this door and do this thing or like oh I don't want to make
this happen Okay so I got to make sure I got to do this and I got to do that so there's this way in which uh desire and
aversion kind of like disconnect us from what's actually happening can disconnect
us from ourselves and kind of like insulate us from what's happening in the world or that's part of it is is that
help yeah yeah that makes sense thanks yeah and then maybe I'll just say one thing
about desire there is a desire you know for greater Freedom less suffering that's really healthy and helpful and
then there's desire you know to protect oneself and have boundaries really healthy and helpful and stuff like that
yeah hi I have a related question um
that I've been wondering about which is well how do you let go of clinging or desire without any
aversion toward it yeah gets a little complicated doesn't
it no it's well it can it's not the it's not letting go out of aversion it's more
um letting go because this recognition that this isn't going to be a source of
lasting happiness just like oh yeah this isn't I thought that uh my having this I was
going to have the best Bell ever and it was people were going to be so impressed look at Diana she's a great Dharma
teacher because she has a good Bell so I better have this Bell but then when you realize oh no that's silly then it's
easier to let it down it's Let It Go and so there's a way in which our identities
are often I exaggerated it for that point but our identities are often associated with
um object things people and so the letting go is
more about um not having our identities uh associated with them does does that
make sense yeah that's helpful thank
you maybe I should have left more time for questions if I gave a talk on questions I didn't think about
that thank you I mean it's an interesting talk and and so I have a question about questions okay
uh so um uh assuming that uh it very rarely
happens that one asks a question and gets an answer and that's life-changing it can happen but as you pointed out in
your talk real answer sort of bubble up uh over time probably practice several
years and suddenly there is a one question is answered and two more years and another question something like that
uh however questions seem to be valuable for
practice and there are other traditions where students question each other or
students and teachers question each other back not so much to get an answer but as practice and I wonder does IMC
have something like this I'm not familiar with the practices yeah well not so much in the mindfulness uh
tradition we don't as much but there is um
I that would be more like talking about a uh a topic and then the teacher might
say well um during your meditation drop in a question and they'll like suggest a
question that would be a support for whatever topic they're teaching about specifically so it's not often given as
a as a practice itself and certainly not like a practice there isn't uh
anything like that here but so sometimes questions are but it's more dropped in
drop them in and then I'll see if anything bubbles up kind of
thing anybody else have a
question there's maybe back there and that will be
that um can you say a bit about what Buddha meant when he said uh you know
those 500 have reached the first stage like would there be any actual indicators one is you said no doubt
right no doubt about the uh are other specifics where one can say you I have a
similar question regarding also like you they say oh entering the stream right yeah at what point do you feel like I'm
in the Stream that kind of Yeah question yeah so there stream enter stream
enterers right is the first stage and uh the tradition holds um that
there's uh the ending of Doubt but what's uh most evident you can see is uh
people's their identity view has shifted so their sense about themselves is
really is different in some kind of way and that's noticeable and the Third Way
is no longer believing that rights and rituals alone will be sufficient for uh
greater Freedom so that's the the three marked changes that happened with that
uh first
shift okay okay well thank you all for your kind attention and I wish you a
lovely rest of the evening thank you