greetings greetings hello hello good morning good afternoon good
evening even greetings to those of you in the future who are watching this or
listening to this so a warm welcome a warm welcome as some of you as many of you
can see from the title of the YouTube video that I got posted here I'm going
to do a story on I'm a series on stories I could also do a story about series but
today will be uh this week will be a focus on stories and of course as you know that
stories are mental events things that we uh construct in the mind and if we're
not in stories like maybe we might say the opposite is to be
embodied be you know here in our physical experience and I'd like to start with
this guided meditation this morning about focusing on body like being
embodied and you could say as a contrast of being lost in
stories so and take a meditation
posture maybe a few long slow deep
exhales [Music]
as a way to maybe release any obvious
tension and signal that we're going to orient towards meditation
now allowing the breath to return to normal recognizing that the body
knows how to breathe we don't need to do anything in
particular with the
breath and then resting our attention on the experience of
sitting if you're sitting in a chair or a couch feeling the pressure against the
body that you might feel along the
back of course if you're lying down you'd feel that pressure against the back
also then all of us no matter what we're sitting on
feel that pressure against the back side or
bum feeling connected to our sitting
surface pressure against the back of the legs
and our feet whatever they're
touching feeling that place of
connection with our sitting
surface feeling grounded connected using this as a
foundation upon which we're sitting
connecting with other areas of the body places where we might hold
tension around the eyes or the jaw
Bing into the shoulders moving them away from the
ears letting the shoulder blades slide down the
back tuning into the experience of having a back upper back the lower back
the chest is there a way that the chest can
be just a tiny bit more open moving the shoulders back just a
tiny
bit and relaxing the belly letting the belly be soft
feeling embodied like
inhabiting the body we're
here now in this experience of the body at
this moment however it
is if you have some tension or some
discomfort can you be in a body that has some tension or discomfort
and setting the sense of direction the orientation of this meditation period is
one of kindness warm-heartedness towards ourself towards
our experience
and then resting our attention on the sensations of
breathing feeling this stretch with the inhale
and the release of the stretch with the
exhale breathing at your own pace
in a natural way with a natural
Rhythm we're just tuning into different
aspects of breathing
and then noticing the transitions between inhales and
exhales how does that feel we don't need
words we're just
experiencing e
tuning into and sensitive to our experience of
breathing in this moment
whether we experience it in the chest or the
belly for some of you feeling the air going in and out of the
nose e
it's lost in thought lost in
stories doesn't have to be a problem we just very simply
gently begin again without adding any extra stories
about what it means as for us as meditators we just begin again with the
sensations of
breathing
e
e e
right now there's nothing else to
do nowhere else to be we're just
here with this experience of breathing
e
e e
[Music]
good morning or good day or I'm always saying
good morning for me it's morning here but uh whatever time it is and wherever you are
warm welcome it's uh such a delight to uh to practice together to know be part
of community for those of you who don't know me I'm Diana clerk if you're
watching this on YouTube you might know that I'm on YouTube uh on Monday nights as part of IMC
and oh maybe you've uh seen me before on your screen
and I'm going to I want to introduce this idea of the uh a series this week
about stories and like our stories the stories that we tell in some ways we might say
that uh humans are storytelling creatures that we use language and
narratives to make sense of our experiences you know to like have them
uh to organize them in a way way that makes sense to us and you might even say that telling stories is just a
fundamental activity that people in all cultures you know maybe All Through Time
have been doing as long as there's been language there's been storytelling but you don't need mean to tell you this of
course right anybody who has sat down to meditate just like we did might notice how the mind is like getting caught up
and telling stories or these entertaining thoughts or fantasies or maybe the stories are about planning
okay I'm going to do this and then this other thing is going to happen because that other thing is going to happen I'm
going to feel more safe or whatever it might be whatever it might be it's a lot
of Storytelling is happening and uh I like to look at this uh this week
different aspects of it as well as including different stories so I'd like to start us off with
this uh a teaching story that is from Jack cornfields book uh path with heart
you know I I say this I'm pretty sure it's a path with heart um I do know it's one of Jack cornfields
books and uh he tells this story about a poison tree a tree that
has a poisonous fruit and he tells this story that uh
when uh first discovering this tree that has this poison fruit people often are
like afraid and they want to avoid this tree and or maybe they even try to convince themselves oh no it isn't there
this tree like like this one here it's not there it doesn't exist or maybe if we
discover that there's a poison tree maybe we become angry and we start
blaming others and that this tree is here and if only the neighbors hadn't done this or those crazy scientists
hadn't done that or something you know we have these ideas of you know why this uh tree is there and we start demanding
like okay something needs to be done about this poison tree some ways their reactions might be
let's cut this down let's get rid of it this is you know we don't want this to
be here and before I get hurt otherwise I might get hurt or we might uh let's cut down this poison tree before anyone
else gets hurt and eats this poisoned fruit and so we might recognize that
what I'm describing here is what Jack is describing in his book that this
resembles often our initial response when we discover some difficulties that
are arising in our life when we encounter aggression or we see in
ourselves this maybe some compulsion or some fear or some greed or maybe when we
just have some stress or have loss or conflict or depression or sorrow in
ourselves or into others there's this way our initial
response can be this way that you know this poison quote unquote is afflictive
and let's uh uproot it let's get rid of it let's cut it down let's make it go away and we do that by avoiding it or
pretending it's not being there or distracting ourselves or something like
that but the story continues so Jack says in his book that you know
other people who have journeyed further along this spiritual path they see the
same poison tree and they don't meet it with a virgin they aren't trying to get
rid of it or instead they have maybe um realized that in order to open to life
open to this present moment Experience open to how our life is unfolding this
requires some compassion some heartfelt compassion for ourselves and for others and for
everything that's around us and maybe they recognize oh yeah this poison tree
is actually a part of me and so let's not cut it down let's
not get rid of it but instead let's have compassion for the
tree so out of kindness out of care they build a fence around the tree so to
protect others so they may not be poisoned by it and recognize okay so the tree so that it can be still still be
alive so the second way of the same facts are happening there's this encounter with a poison tree but there's
a different way of relating to it just going to build a fence around we're not going to cut it down we're just going to
build a fence around it and allow it to uh be there and to
continue and then the story continues it's third uh type of person
maybe somebody who's traveled even further along the spiritual path uh sees the same tree and says oh a poison tree
perfect just what I was looking for and this person like picks the fruit and
looks at it and investigates its properties mixes it with some other ingredients and uses this poison to make
a great medicine that maybe heals the sick and transforms the ills of the world and
this way through respect and understanding this person sees a way
different than a lot of other people and finds value and what might some people
might say difficult circumstances of poison so there's a number of ways that
we can interpret this story that I just uh told and there's a way that um one is
that experiences that are difficult qu quot unquote we and tree might actually
be beneficial um just because we label something a difficult doesn't mean that we have to avoid it or get rid of it but
instead it might actually become a great asset for us and I want to use this
story to say something about the nature of
stories that is there's more than one way there's more than one story that is
possible with maybe a given set of facts quotee unquote in the same way that different
people have different perceptions about something we can have
different perceptions about an experience about some facts and but the narratives we create
the stories we create and believe they actually deeply influence us and
influence how we perceive the world and how we experience the world
and David ly who is a zen teacher he writes one meaning of freedom is the
opportunity to act out the story I identify with one meaning of freedom is the
opportunity to act out the story I identify with another
freedom is the ability to change stories and my role within them in this way
person can move from a scripted character to the co-author of their
life so another freedom is the ability to change stories and change the
roles and then a third type of Freedom results from understanding how
stories construct and constrict our
possibilities recognizing how stories construct and constrict our
possibilities so the the way that we um work with stories the way that we hold
stories has such a big impact on our lives and I'd like to use a specific
example of this comes from Kim Hamlin har she gives an example of how um using
like one I'll just use this word facts uh and then just there's so many
different interpretations of and the different interpretations really can have an impact on our lives the amount of
Freedom we have in our lives so Kim Hamlin Hart um she uh tells a story as
this assumption that her mother was distant and unhappy and then she had some different
stories about it and here are some of the ones that she said again this is Kim hinhard I don't want people to think I'm
saying this about my own mother but this is somebody else saying my mother was
distant and unhappy she didn't love me and because she didn't love me I am
unlovable that's one story my mother was distant and
unhappy she was broken and incapable of giving much love and I didn't get the
love the type of love I craved but I am worthy of love and belonging regardless
of my mother's inability to love the way that I need it that's a second
story here's a third story my mother was distant and unhappy it was because of
something I did and I am responsible for her unhappy life and I need to do
everything I can to make her and those around me happy very different third story here's
a fourth story my mother was distant and unhappy and I didn't get the love I
needed she ruined my life I can never be a whole or happy because of the love I
was denied as a child ouch right such a different fourth
story here's a fifth Story my mother was distant and
unhappy because I didn't have a model of how to interact emotionally I can't get in touch with my emotions and express
them in a healthy way and I cannot sh change that's a fifth Story and here's a
sixth story my mother was distant and unhappy because I didn't have a model of
how to interact emotionally I struggle with my own emotions however I can learn and grow
and figure out a way to get in touch with my emotions and express them in a healthy
way so you can see how there's so many different meanings can be created around
the same facts quote unquote and this one is about a mother being distant and
unhappy but how we interpret them and we could say which stories we apply to them
have such a big impact on our life and I want to be clear there's not like one
right story here or one wrong story here some of the powers actually to recognize
that there can be more than one story and that they can change maybe early in our life we have this story about
something that happened uh ear when in our childhood for example and then as we
grow as we mature in our um spiritual life and then just in our adult life
then the stories can change so it's not that there's no right or wrong story
here but maybe part of the freedom is to recognize that whichever story We
believe um it like affects us it has an impact on us it becomes like the frame
of reference and it can uh affect the way that we interact with the world and
the views that we have about ourself and our possibilities or our
capabilities so small shifts in thinking we might say can lead to significant
changes and these significant changes can change can influence you know our
behavior and our behavior and of course it impacts how our life
unfolds so rewriting we might say our personal
narratives isn't about changing facts it's more about changing our
interpretation of them changing our stories recognizing that as humans we
make stories we need we want to interpret and have meaning for our experiences so we great
narratives but these narratives are fluid and dynamic and can
change and part of our spiritual life is maybe to see the
stories and then uphold stories Loosely to recognize that they
change and to be able to find the freedom there so I hope you'll join me for the
rest of this week as we continue this exploration of stories and how we create
them how they change and the impact that they have in our
lives thank you thank you very much and see you tomorrow