all right good morning and good day uh for all of you from all around the world
I'm seeing it in the chat
message so today uh we're going to um go
into the second simile of the five Aggregates or five bundles and the human
process yesterday we uh practiced with uh the
first uh Sim of this five Bondo which is
using the lump of foam on the river
ganes uh to uh liken this sense the felt
sense of this embodied feeling material form and this body kind of this
form and um today uh we're going to use
yet another Sile uh that's also used to illustrate uh some embodied aspect um of
Being Human and this uh second aspect the poly term is
Vena many of you may have heard of this and this term sometimes gets translated
as feelings or feeling tones um in Sati patana this is the
second um satiana second aspect that's often being practiced
with and um uh often when we're speaking about
feeling tones um uh we may be referring to what in there's a whole Spectrum from
unpleasant to neutral to Pleasant kind of feelings they're not like a black and
white lines drawn but it's really a spectrum uh there is a whole Spectrum
from being extremely unpleasant and painful and all the way
to just Heavenly pleasantness um it can happen both in
the embodied way and also in the way that may be related to a mental being in
some way and uh I was looking up at the PO
dictionary of this term sometimes um the translation of a v is just a Sensations
so it may be included here too um and and the suta uh described this
feeling tone a feelings or uh feeling
tones um as if they are the M ring or
Autumn rain uh in India uh that you know they hit on the
puddles and to make water bubbles popping
because of the rain contact of the rain with water and and the water bubbles pop
up and burst away and it's quite a visual again and I
will'll practice with it and uh and then I'll offer some more
words uh when we switch to the daret and again if you like to stay in your
meditative bubble uh please do so even as we're
transitioning uh to the darat session D darat part later um so here we go let's
[Music]
practice maybe taking a few long deep breath
as you breathe out arriving
here and now as if you're entering into the
Temple of this body mind and a heart
arriving with a sound
arriving with a breath
entering into the posture you're in
a sense of irreverence may come
in maybe a sense of safety entering into this meditative
bubble kind of a protection of our heart and mind
allow mindful awareness to be on the foreground front and the
center there maybe heartfulness is here too
whatever the word heartfulness might mean for
you you don't have to think about
it there may just be a kind of a bodily response to it
being mindful one moment and
another and yet another
the momentary mindfulness can form a chain of
mindfulness
maybe there is a sense being more and more
present at some point the continuity of
Sati maybe strong enough
such that we feel or more
available available to the lived experience here and
now and the momentary experiences are available to us
us there he is a sense maybe more and more rooted
stabilizing in
mindfulness the F sense of a [Music]
breathing may become Fuller
are more fully registered received
allow the mindfulness to
expand throughout the
body from inside or all around
as you
breathe the breath enlightens the body
a sense of aliveness may come
forth as if you're melting
into the f sense of a dancing Sensations in the
body tingling
puling vibrating
gentle expansion
contraction rising and
falling
Ric e
experiencing this body from within
itself releasing Concepts ideas
feeling and
sensing quietly
you may began to notice Fe enough
feelings feeling
tones maybe pervasive kind of pleasant
Sensations like a light drizzle of the rain drizzling
[Music] rain hitting a peaceful
Lake making tiny water bubbles on the surface of the lake
maybe bubbly
present bubbly Pleasant
Sensations or maybe there are big ring
drops hitting the surface of the
lake or the big water bubbles burst up
like a occasional sharp unpleasant
feelings e
resting in the felt sense in the sea of Sensations
a spectrum of pleasant unpleasant May shift and change
just like the
raindrops hitting the surface of the lake or the puddle may
change the shapes the intensity of the water
bubbles
e
e e
as you stay connected with the immediacy of the felt
sense of your experience it can
highlight how the mind might
react where the likes and dislikes
cleaning aversion judging
fixing and you can know is our
extra
e
e e
and in a minute I'll end the meditation with the
sound of a bell but if you like to stay in the meditative
bubble please please feel free to do so
for
[Music]
and I'd like to read you this part of the simile from the
sua suppose practitioners that in the
Autumn when it's raining and the big raindrops are
falling a water bubble arises and it bursts on the surface of the
water a person with good sight would inspect it ponder it and carefully
investigate it and it would appear to them to be
void Hollow insubstantial for what substance would
there be in a water bubble so too
practitioners whatever kind of a feeling there is whether past future or present internal
or external gross or subtle inferior or
Superior far or near a practitioner inspects it pund it
and carefully investigates it and it would appear to them to be void Hollow
insubstantial for what substance would there be in feeling
tones so as we were meditating I was inviting us to
imagine that maybe in the fall the monsoon season in some parts of
India there are this kind kind of rain um
maybe sometimes ongoing drizzle or sometimes this kind of periodic pouring
ring with the gaps in between and sometimes maybe it's kind of
sparingly for a while with a big raindrops hitting the
ground and the water bubbles arise out of all the contact of
raindrops on the surface of a water and they burst
away and the Buddha likened this as kind of a feeling tones emerging out of the
contact with the body and sometimes even the
mind and so sometimes this may feel Pleasant maybe in the
hot um hot day uh when the uh cool
raindrops falling making contact with the skin
face neck that's kind of a pleasant feeling
you know Pleasant Sensations um that can emerge
and just like the water bubbles um that quickly make contact and
they um arise and pass
away and in the meditation and I was having a uh
somewhat of a more kind of um quiet kind of pleasant Sensations
uh in my body and are very energetic
Pleasant and I felt like this uh pervasive layers of um you know thing
water bubbles um on the surface of the lake and other times uh if there may be
a prolonged um Intense or mild uh
unpleasant Sensations and that can also feel like like a rain maybe a bigger rain kind of
non-stop raindrop hitting a water surface and the water bubbles are kind
of a pervasive uh sense of unpleasant and they may be harder to
tease apart and yet other times the water
bubbles may feel kind of distinct kind of like you know this kind of pleasant
Sensations that may be more more um
sparkly or unpleasant unpleasant Sensations that may be more
sparkly uh kind of like you know occasionally you have this sharp ping um
happen in certain kind of the body certain parts of the body but it just
kind kind of comes and goes like this big water bubble that
gets formed and Pops away and that they are
distinct and so there are are all the the flavors of um feeling tone that can
emerge in us um the Buddha used this simile of
water bubbles and pointing at the fact
that all of this uh Fe tones the Vaden us they come and go whether they feel
like a pervasive or whether they feel like a sparkly you know kind of one moment at
and the next yet they're all kind of a bursting away in one way or
another and so this is the way and that the Buddha was pointing I feel like this
more like how we're experiencing it uh in our own F sense it's quite
immediate and yet often uh when we're sitting in our meditation what we may
also observe is when there are Pleasant and unpleasant feeling tones
arising often there are kind of uh habitual
tendencies that are kind of reactivities that arise immediately with it as
well you know the unpleasant we may have a sense of not liking it or we want to
push it away uh we have certain kind of aversion to it or uh even worse when the
unpleasant don't go away we can blame ourselves we can shame
ourselves and we can try very hard to try to fix
it and when the pleasant Sensations come and we can try to hand on to it and
when they go away we really want to to Ling in and uh
get them back but this image of water
bubbles we can't really Gras grasp at bursting water bubbles right and that's
very Vivid to illustrate this aspect of
um uh human experiences in its own nature they're
not graspable they're not cleanable and yet the
reactivity um can uh feel like they you know wanted to grasp at something that
is actually inherently not graspable and I I also like to point out
um that this doesn't mean somehow that uh there is no appropriate
response uh to our feeling tones to our
Vena for example often and there is a lot of pain
in the body maybe um you know unbearable
pain and uh the invitation is not just to say you know we're not going to be
able to do anything but rather uh when we're
staying with our experience in the immediate way we're
not covered by the layers of reactivities in our
mind um there is more room resource and
space for us to tune in to what may be
needed here what is the skillful response that can emerge and become
available to us there is a deeper kind of embodied
intelligence that may be available available that is much more
intuitive and much more immediate so when we're not tuned in
this kind of immediate emergent um intuitive kind of uh uh
intelligence or response they don't have a
chance because we're so often uh getting caught by how we want to fix
things and we don't allow this deeper kind of a care and a uh a wise response to come
forth and so when we're staying attuned uh to our immediate experience those are
become wiser and a more compassionate aspect of our being being becomes more
available to us and that's also the nature of this human body and human mind
too and so we're not just um um somehow
believing that we needed to just bear with the pain sometimes that may be
appropriate and other times there may be wise responses compassionate responses
that can come forth and similarly uh in relationship
to the pleasant uh Sensations and pleasant state of a being and so often
The Habit Tendencies are to Ling in you know I want to Ling in to this again and
again I wanted to hand on onto it and when we don't get it we get very
frustrated I remember
uh uh the past uh when I did self- retreat at home and sometimes I would be
in a rather quiet uh sweet kind of a state of a
being but then all of a sudden it occurred to me oh it's time for me to go
pick up my son from school and that often you know uh I would notice this
momentary aversion coming oh I don't wanted to to let go of
this and it took me a while to notice this momentary aversion um that comes and
gradually learning to let go of this say
ah this experiences are uh situational it's a lot more important
for us to learn to let go of this different forms of a cleaning and
aversion than trying to hand on to the pleasant
experience and so this are the teachings on the water bubbles from the
rain and so my invitation is for today as you go about your day maybe allow
this simile to come alive in you and um enjoy the rest of the day
[Music]
we'll see you tomorrow