so I think it's a coincidence that announcement than what I'm going to say next I'm going to talk about a topic
which uh is a reputation of being unpopular in the Buddhist West and I
hope by the time we finish it becomes popular and um so I'll begin with uh an
analogy to get to the topic if you are really
tense you something's going on in your life you're really tense you're kind of beside yourself in tension and
preoccupation and concern and and you're starting to feel like you're not really being efficient getting any anything
done just kind of like going in circles and you know or you know you're trying to cook but you're dropping everything
and you more time cleaning up than you spend time trying to cook and it's not really cooking is not even working but
just just imagine you're so tense and so finally it Dawns on
you you know maybe I should meditate and you sit down and you're not
really ambitious in meditating you just sit down to just sit there and be present for all this tension all this
agitation that's there and maybe you close your eyes maybe you sit
upright and as you sit there something begins suling some of the tension even
might even feel like it's draining away and something gets a little bit quieter and you feel your shoulders
release maybe your belly releases and oh this is kind of nice and so you stay and
and something begins coming back uh to what might we might called a
homeostasis and if you do it long enough maybe you get really relaxed you're out slouching a little bit it kind of feels
good to finally just be relaxed but then you keep staying it and then something in inside of you it not not your desires
exactly but something almost physical inside it feels like there's an upwelling of wanting to be up upright
more not to slouch and so there's a movement to then come into a kind of
homeostasis where we're not tense we're not overly relaxed but we're kind of
here in a nice balanced full way and a number of things had to shift
for that to happen ands things had to be quieted down relaxed certain
preoccupations faded away from being preoccupations there's still issues in the life that be dealt with but we're
not obsessing about them and making us tense about all of them and and it was in just a very nice
process so uh that could describe
some and if you decide at the beginning of that when you're still running around you know I really need to settle down
and let go of some of this stuff I need to quiet down I need to kind of release a lot of these things I'm caught by and
and that's the thought you have when you first sit down it could still work just as well from a traditional Buddhist
language what you were doing was renunciation that's the unpopular
topic if we think of renunciation as let you know giving up your house your home
home your spouse your you know everything in order to go off for example to be a monastic you know they
have to you live a life of radical Simplicity maybe you know that's why
it's unpopular just like why do I have to let go of all these things uh when the Buddha talked about
this word he word he called renunciation it doesn't have the same kind of
negative connotations obvious negative connotations that I think the word pronunciation happen has in English Eng
because renunciation in English is so closely associated with leaving something behind with uh with uh getting
rid of something uh relinquishing something giving it up and the Buddhist word that's
translated as renunciation uh might have that
Association in Buddhism as well but it has also has a positive Association
positive meaning it uh it literally the the poly word literally means to go
forth to go out into the open to leave a confined space to go out and and walk in
the open air and um and what's emphasized in the poly word is more what's gained in the
process of renunciation rather than what is lost what you know so it's not meant
to be an act of deprivation to renounce it's actually meant to be something positive that brings you something
really good so in that exam example I gave earlier uh you know if if you felt
running around and someone came say I think you should just renounce you probably get more tense or angry with
them but if you understood that what that meant was to allow you to go forth
after a period of meditation go out back into the world refreshed with the open
air of a clear heart a clear mind um your friend advice might be really good
oh I just have to settle down and relax and just be present and there's actually a natural process inside that's not my I
don't engineer this kind of settling down I just have to be still for a while
and just being still for a while it quiets the momentum the fueling of
tension that the obsessive thinking creates And the emotions that go with it
but still there's a quieting there's an emptying out of of obsessive mind States
tense mind states which don't serve us which actually limit us hinder us um
they're the ones that are are depriving us of something really valuable we're
being deprived of a natural healthy way of being and the process of settling and
quieting is a process of uh letting certain things go so that we could come
into this Healthy Home stasis healthy way of being and we're actually enhanced
by it not deprived by it so uh part of the reason why the PO
word NE the poly word is NE which means to walk out to go
forth um is translated as renunciation is that it's actually the word used for
someone who uh becomes a Buddhist monastic they they go forth and the idea
is they go forth from maybe this is an unfortunate Association but from the the
dusty confines of home life which may be meant in a small little hubel with 13
kids and just you know all the struggles and all that and somehow as a young person you could enough of this I want
to go out now and find a whole other way of living that clears the heart that clears the mind that frees it all and so
it's going forth and um so then because the I think in Christianity um the word for a
Christian monastic Catholic monastics becoming becoming a monastic is they
renounce and so they there's a then taking that westernized word and then
applying it to a Buddhist monastic calling that word going forth translating it as
renunciation but in um but when the when uh this discussion about renunciation as
a practice what's being focused on over and over over again is not letting go of
any things or people or activities per se and of themselves the focus is always
on on a renouncing or or a going forth
from unhealthy states of mind it's always these unhealthy states
of mind which are the primary Focus so there's a lot of discussion about renouncing uh uh
sensual Pleasures in the English translation of the Buddhist teachings
but it turns out that the word for that's translated as sensual
Pleasures because you can't really renounce sensual Pleasures you'd have to go I don't
know go live someplace that's always unpleasant or something
find some place like you know hell or something and then maybe you can renounce sensual Pleasures because I
mean they're part and parcel of life that the sun is shining and it's nice and I had a lot of pleasure walking down
here today just the fresh air it was so nice to breathing it felt Pleasant so you can't really renounce sensual
Pleasures but the word that's translated as sensual Pleasures is a a Sanskrit
word poly indic word Kama k m a which has a dual meaning
it means sensual pleasures and it means sensual desires and desires a product of the
mind and so what's being let go of is sensual craving sensual
compulsions those can be let go of because there might be one or two of you
here that maybe once accidentally in your life uh You Were Somehow caught and
trapped by some kind of sensual compulsion it might have been known but I don't want to assume anything that
that might have happened to any of you but it does happen to some people that sometimes they regret what they do
afterwards and sometimes they make a mess of their family and all kinds of things because of that particular you
know drive for sensual pleasures of some sense some sense or other so what what
the Buddha was talking about a lot then is not letting go of central Pleasures
um and to make to to make that clear in one of of the texts The Bu Buddha is
described as capable of or or or in actuality uh experiencing more sensual
pleas Pleasures than anyone else in the world just with the food he eats and uh
and with just walking down this down the street somehow in the Sun or outside and there's graphic depictions of the Buddha
just kind of he he's there's no no there's no um hindrances or no no
obstacles for him really taking in and experiencing sensual Pleasures to a great degree so it's not sensual Pleasures but
it's sensal compulsions that's what's renounced but why is that going to make your life less
interesting it certainly will make it U you know less suitable for a soap
opera which might be really you know I mean most of the books we novels we read I mean someone is doing something
kind of unethical that's what makes it interesting so if we want our our life
to be a novel then you know maybe sensual compulsions are how you make it exciting
for everyone but maybe it doesn't go end very well those
novels in life in real life so the idea to but to renounce them
renounce compulsive desires sensual Desires in an unhealthy
way um is not meant to deprive us but is meant to give us something
better so the act of renunciation is always a movement to something better and um and what is that there's
certain kind of Freedom certain kind of allowing something from within us to come forth
to go forth with the with a healthy wonderful
um uh inspiring kind of feeling and movement just as with sitting down to
meditate when you were so tense uh what after that period of meditation maybe was inspiring now to go
forth to go on and continue your way and you find yourself surprised because it's
time for lunch and uh you and um but it's not even time for lunch but you you
you've been away from your phone for now 30 minutes 60 Minutes I mean that's like
a record I mean and so and normally you would like it's sitting right there
because you don't want to be too far away from it and so the normally you would just
grab it to look what's happened in the world what's happened with email what's happened in
text what's happened with phone calls what's happening on social media what's happened and um but you're so settled
you're comeing into kind of a balanced State of Mind balanced State you're so content here sitting here with the
tension is no longer there and you can feel like why
bother why you know the compulsion to look is not there you know what that
happens if you go for the phone and you know that right now you're connected
you're here in a nice way so you don't pick it up for that moment you renounce
your phone or the desire to do it because you know you're going to lose something that you've gained it's going
to diminish you in some way and then you go make your lunch and
you sit down to eat and you're so content it's so nice the colors are so good you're so content
and happy and the phone is there but you know you're alone eating
it's a waste of time you could you could be doing two things at once you have a lot of things to do you might as well
check your emails while you're eating and you know but it's so nice to sit and just eat and feel the food and no wonder
the Buddha had so much sensual pleasure when he ate because he didn't have a
[Laughter] phone and um and so just and so there's
something gained and in fact having meditated felt so good after the
meditation sitting down and eating without looking at a phone and doing anything just being there with the food
actually something settles even more it feels even nicer and
better and then you get the phone call from your neighbor saying you know oh something
tragic has happened and I feel really sad and and you know I could really use
some company and you go over there and you're so glad you did all those things
beforehand because now you're completely present and open available you're not to
having to be torn away from your phone you're not caught up in the anxiety of what you have to do and you're not going
over there I'll just go there for a little while and I wonder how quickly I can help the person with the grief so I can get back to my
phone it's like now you're so happy that you enter this nice quiet homeostasis
healthy way because wow you were there for that person in a nice way in a good
way and um so so this renouncing
letting go is not meant to be deprivation it's meant to actually enhance us and that's the movement if a
Buddhist teacher SS Reen tells you to renounce um they should probably change their
English they say go forth come out of that shell come out of that prison
you've created for yourself come out of that how you're caught in preoccupations
concerns that you have come forth I'm here welcome come out join me here in
this Freedom so this the poly word for that's
translated pronunciation uh it kind of implies both movements it implies a kind of letting
go leaving behind something but it also implies the beautiful feeling of going
forth going out into Freedom both meanings are there
um but it's kind of similar to if you're in a house and you go through a door to
another room simultaneously you're leaving one room
behind and going into the next room so this idea can happen together you're
simultaneously a letting go of some previous way of being caught and trapped in your mind preoccupied into more of
experience of freedom and this dual meaning that goes on is is really explicit in other words
for letting go in in the Buddhist language uh there's the word that
sometimes translated as relinquishment and um and I don't know how often we use the word relinquishment
in English usually but usually it's not a good thing like relinquish control something or something but um
but anyway it's used for this translation into English and uh it sometimes it's has a it's only used to
describe the times uh a really high level of spiritual maturation and really
high levels of strong meditation uh when things are really good you enter into a
nice wonderful homeostasis some of the deepest attachments are relinquished given up Let
Go however this the word that's being used for relinquishment actually several words that translated as relinquishment
in English they have dual meanings sometimes what they mean is
giving generosity and so H so what do we you
know how are we supposed to do on one hand there's relinquishment it means and the other man it means generosity or giving Which do we choose maybe it's the
same thing going through the door in the house both things are meant and so we have a positive
Association also with the word relinquishment that means to give the the two of these words that
translates relinquishment um uh are U are
used to translate a a phrase in ply describes a person who's still living at
home like a lay person who um is H is uh
their mind is free of stinginess who Delights in giving
practices giving uh and
uh and uh freely gives open handedly gives and the word delight is used
repeatedly but and because Delights in giving
away so sometimes they translate one word as giving and the other one that's
giving away that both of them other situations are translated as
relinquishment and so we do that little bit in English we have this dual meaning as well when we have the expression uh
to give up give up kind of means like to surrender like kind of kind of you kind
of collapse and kind of abandon something but um I think originally it
meant offer up on the altar to give something up it's kind of a sacred act in the religious sense and so we say
giving up or to give away giving away can be have all kinds of meanings but it
could also be a beautiful thing to give away something in a generous open-handed way and and so this act of giving
contains within it this two these two sides of going through the
door uh if you gave something with your own hands you have to relinquish it Let
It Go renounce it with your hands by giving it to someone
else but what happens then now your hands are free for the next task whatever life
comes with you can now free to do something else and you're so glad to not be carrying this thing around around
anymore that was such a you know limiting you you give it away maybe so so giving
has both these qualities in it's both a letting go and kind of in that letting go
there's a movement of freedom in the hands maybe freedom in the heart as well so back to this word
renunciation it has this positive Association that that uh that we gain
what do we gain in this process and so back again to the analogy
at the beginning of the talk is um one of the things we gain is
homeostasis is a healthy inner life and that's we come into
balance and part of the purpose of surrendering or renouncing or relinquishing and all these powerful
English words is to enhance something about ourselves not to become less than
what we are to maybe come back into who we really are in a certain kind of way
in a healthy basic way free of compulsions Free of addictions free of
of hostilities free of the ways we're caught and to feel how good that feels
from the inside out to feel how we become better by it it because what's waiting in each of us is a healthy heart
a healthy mind that's and one of the strategies for coming back into that is
to let go of all the forces in the mind which are unhealthy which keeps us tense
Keeps Us in hostility Keeps Us reactive and one of the means of doing
that that's I think is a for those people who meditate is um is to
meditate and meditation is one way at times where you don't have to do the
renouncing it does it for you if you sit quietly and peacefully with time
everything that's being held on to will release will
settle but there's nothing wrong with you helping out so from time to time you might want
to consider letting go and certainly let go enough so you can
meditate I know some people who have a hard time getting to the meditations uh to their meditation because there's that
phone or all the things that are like that like I have to do I have to you know and the momentum of you know always
checking the device or the momentum of certain kind of attachments and preoccupations makes it really hard to
slow down and stop and so when it's really really hard
to stop that's when maybe renunciation becomes an act of
Courage okay I kind of really have to I really have to do this let me at least
let go physically of what I'm doing I don't know if I can do with my mind but
at least physically I'll be sit down it'll be a little bit like being in the rodeo I know the wild
Bronco but I'm going to sit there and see what happens and chances are
something will settle in quiet chances so
renunciation so is that make it a little more popular a little bit more welcome and um I thought it was kind of
funny to give this talk because today because um right after Thanksgiving the
neighbor started putting up Christmas lights preparing for Christmas and I thought oh good I'll give a talk
preparing us for Christmas [Laughter]
renunciation so so do we have a few minutes before the end if any of you
have any comments or questions or testimonials I see it someone's hand way
out in the back
thank you for this talk uh Gil um I have a question about the topic of
renunciation uh and that is what is the difference between renunciation and surrender or is there
no difference it's not your exactly in your
question not in your question but um I love the word sacrifice uh because it has the word sacred in it it literally
means in Latin to make sacred and uh though a sacrifice the way it's used is often again a diminishment or often like
you kind of have to give something up and get nothing in return but there is something about giving doing the act of
Letting Go or uh that can make something sacred for ourselves so surrender I don't know you
know um uh I oh so uh again not asking your
question direct answering your question directly um in terms of um
renouncing the Buddha said um when
renouncing something is
unhealthy if if renouncing something makes unhealthy State stronger and
healthy States decrease that kind of s renouncing you
should not do when renouncing makes healthy States stronger
and unhealthy States go away that's the kind of renouncing you should
do so ex your question is a good one is you know how do these two compare I
don't know how to answer that question because it's a little bit of a linguistic semantic question but this
what the this teachings of the Buddha applies to both of those if surrender ing makes things healthier for you and
the unhealthy inner life go down do it surrender but if it's not it's the
opposite don't do it and you can ask both and maybe then you don't have to compare the two that each thing can be
its own thing in your vocabulary thank you yeah is okay that I
not quite answer directly um so the way I interpret this is that it is not um it's not a
vocabulary question but it's it's something you have to feel within yourself perfect okay thank
you yes so it's more like a testimonial so I came here few weeks ago I was very
disturbed and uh I spoke to you I said that I'm being tired of being my own cheerleader and you said you'll be my
cheerleader that meant a lot and I said I want to give up before that you know that was one sentence before that and
you said don't give up so thank you for doing all this for all of us thank you
thank you very much
here in back in the corner here
now so this brings a memory of mine that I haven't thought about for a long time
um I was um before my husband and I got married we took a trip to Nepal as an
experiment to see if we could get along well enough for in that kind of you know camping and you do that after getting
married no before before getting married so we
before we got married we went to Nepal um to you know as a test to see how we
could be together in that those circumstances and um two things happened
that were um Remar we were in the the kumu area going up towards Everest and there
my husband is um he he's just fascinating he's he's he loves anything to do with Nepal and the
Everest area and everything um he he studies it he reads you know just absorbs everything and there is this
book that he that of that had a picture um of this one from the from one this
run Monastery up towards Everest that he wanted to replicate so we were hiking by and he took this
picture and he um then I said oh can I borrow your camera you know this is this
this is in um
198 86 so we you didn't have phone cameras right so um so I borrowed the
camera and I took some pictures and I put the camera down and we started hiking again with
the group it was a small group and I'm a little ways away I'm oh my God I forgot the camera and we dashed back and it was
gone um and with the picture that my husband really
wanted and he said it's okay and that was such a pivotal moment
in our relationship that he relinquished gave up that
picture and in that stepped into you know this basically an expression of
love for me and forgiveness um
also on that trip I had this was later on we were I we were we had gone into
the tent i' taken you know i' always like to put my boots outside the tent
and so I put them out there and in the middle of the night I was
dreaming and I dreamt that somebody needed those
boots and I said yeah go ahead and take them and the next morning my boots were
are gone and I didn't have another pair of
shoes um so my but my husband did and
his feet are much bigger than mine but and they were a pair of sneakers but that's okay we made it work we put in
extra socks and I hiked the rest of the trip in pair of sneakers that were too
big for me but um I hadn't thought about those two experiences for a while I mean the
camera when I we we think about a lot we talk about every every time we meet somebody we say yeah you know this is a
really important time moment in our relationship but um yeah I just it it's
perfect for to Fe put it in context of what you're talking about Gil so thank you very much for that very nice very
nice so he let go of the camera and what came
forth from that was 40 Years of a good marriage Maybe
well we try to remember that time and then it helps us in the other times very nice thank
you so it's wonderful thank you all that's very nice to have you and have
this time together I appreciate it a lot and um if you want to talk to someone
next to you for a little bit before you go it's often a nice thing to do and and um and look forward to seeing you next
week