good morning or for those of you
on the live stream whatever time it is for
you I'll start with a little bit of a guided meditation this
morning and I'm going to offer perhaps a style that may be a little less familiar
to some of you it's an open awareness style of
meditation and so we won't be at least for the first few minutes in my guiding
of it I won't be um inclining you towards stabilizing with the breath
it'll be more of a stabilization of awareness with whatever is
arising and then after some time I'll I'll I'll suggest if you feel more comfortable you can shift back but you
might just go along for the ride for the first few minutes at least see how it how it lands for
you in any form of
meditation relaxation of body and
mind are very supportive
condition for the connection of mindfulness with
experience and so I often find it helpful at the beginning of a sitting to take a few moments to
consciously relax
this can be done in a kind of a systematic
way starting perhaps at the top of the
head relaxing the head and
face neck and shoulders
arms and
hands relaxing the chest and upper
back all those muscles around the rib cage
sometimes as I relax that area quite naturally a deeper breath
happens maybe allowing a deeper breath to expand and stretch those
muscles and then notice the softening of those muscles on the out breath
exploring a softening across the stomach and abdomen middle and lower
back maybe the hips can
relax the legs the feet
and then perhaps there can also be a softening more deeply
inside the body maybe the inside of the throat can
soften maybe the area around the heart can
soften maybe the stomach and intestines can
soften allowing there to be a kind of a relaxation a letting go
in all of those organs inside the
body we don't have to hold them up our body naturally supports them
as the body softens and relaxes
whatever however much it's softened
or relaxed that supports a mental
relaxation so you might have noticed a little bit of relaxation of mind a
little bit of less pull to thoughts or worries or
concerns and we can also explore relaxing the
mind one of the best ways into that has for me been a
encouragement by Gil as if the brain were a
muscle maybe the brain can relax
as we've been exploring a conscious relaxation we have been aware
mindful of this process at least at times
perhaps noticing the body noticing the mind this is
awareness and so now there's a kind of I'd like to encourage a little bit of a
shift to recognizing are you
aware you don't have to think about it if you're hearing my
voice knowing the sound knowing Body Sensations you are
aware you may not know how you know you're aware but
just open to that awareness is
here and awareness will connect quite
naturally is connecting quite naturally already with some aspect of
experience maybe Body Sensations
with a breath or
sound maybe thoughts even or a mood or an emotional tone
having a sense of settling back and
receiving whatever is obvious In This Moment
awareness will be receiving something we don't actually have to aim
or point the
attention I think of attention attention is a factor of mind
that connects with some aspect of our
experience it's a little different from awareness awareness is that aspect that
receives experience
attention connects with some part particular aspect of
experience and while attention is amenable to our conscious choice we can
choose aim the attention at the breath or the body or
sound any experience if we don't choose to do that
and kind of let go of the active choice of where to aim the
attention the attention will connect with
something so what is obvious without you're trying to find
anything relax
receive often it is something like the body especially at first because the
Body Sensations are pretty
obvious and as we receive step back from aiming or
choosing where to place the attention we will notice that the attention
shifts new experience are received in each
moment maybe a breath and then another body sensation a
pressure maybe the Sound hearing
receiving it's okay if the experience changes we're
cultivating awareness being aware with whatever is arising
and also if the attention lands in a familiar place like the breath for
instance you don't have to keep it from being there if that's naturally where the attention is going that's
fine receive the breath
receive whatever the attention is naturally connecting
with and the attention is likely to shift at some
point do a sound another body
sensation a thought and noticing that be curious
about the shift of attention and let the attention then
receive let the awareness receive wherever that attention has
connected with we don't have
to let go of that and return to any particular experience
if we notice the shift and allow the connection of awareness with whatever that experiences
we are
aware relaxation really supports this kind of exploration
what is obvious In This
Moment In This Moment
sometimes the attention will connect with something very
specific a specific sound or a body sensation a breath or a
thought very clear sometimes what the attention is connecting
to and other times the attention feels more Broad
it maybe feels like connecting with the whole
experience or something more diffuse something less specific or
precise we may not even know what it
is but there's the recognition that we are
aware we don't have to find a specific clear
experience if we know we're [Music] aware that's
enough are you aware
maybe have the sense of following the attention that shift of
attention and of course the mind will
wander as with any practice we'll get lost in some
experience get start thinking about something and not be aware that we're
thinking and at some point awareness will return
in that moment you know when awareness returns can you
recognize aware again aware
again awareness has returned and it's knowing something in that
moment it may be knowing something about where it was wandering to the
thought or an emot an
image so awareness of
that relax and
receive now you may feel a pull back to thinking
you may be able to notice that pull that's just another experience arising
that pull it's kind of where the attention is wanting to go you're noticing how the attention is drawn you
might be able to recognize that
pull and sometimes the pull is stronger than our capacity to really
know it and if it feels that way then and it's fine
to relax and connect to some very easy
experience maybe the breath for you or hearing or body
sensation as a place to kind of remember awareness refresh the connection with
being aware
and continuing relax recognize
awareness what is obvious in this
moment and this moment settling
back and
receiving this flow of human experience we can be
aware with all of it
if this receptive awareness of Just moment to
moment experience of what is obvious feels easeful for
you you're welcome to continue exploring
that if it feels more agitating or
chaotic you're welcome to return to whatever practice or style
of connecting with experience is most supportive for you
right
now
e
e for
for
[Music]
so we have a few
announcements good morning I just want to mention that Dharma Sprouts is not
meeting today uh instead next week at Stafford Park at 11:15 that's the
kindergarten through second graders and and next Saturday we are going to have a
dayong retreat we call it an intensive uh bruny will be teaching it and it
starts at 6:00 a.m. and goes to 900 p.m. I'm sorry no is that
right I uh 6:00 a.m. to 9:00 p.m.
yes I have actually done this before it's been a while uh and so we will be offering a
light dinner a light supper uh for the Retreats and so if anyone would like to
help to offer soup salad bread a cookie something um to if you'd like to offer
to cook for that or just to help set up uh please let me know I'm Hillary let me
know after the Dharma talk uh we would love to to have some volunteers thank
you thank you Hillary can you hear
me and so I'm like to introduce warmly welcome Andrea fella
co-founder and co- guiding teacher of Insight Meditation Center and the
Insight Retreat Center she has been practicing Insight Meditation since
1996 and teaching Insight Meditation since 203 she is particularly drawn to
intensive Retreat practice and has done a number of of long Retreats both in the United States and in Burma during one
long practice period in Burma she ordained as a nun with saadu janaka
Andrea is especially drawn to the wisdom teachings of the Buddha her teachings
emphasize Clarity and practicality Andrea is a member of the
Spirit Rock teachers Council and teaches residential Retreats for IMC and other
Retreat centers around the country thank you thank
you I want to make one correction I'm not a co-founder of
IMC I was a
student
here so in this um style of practice I offered in the guided meditation the
receptive awareness settling back and just receiving momentto moment
experience not aiming or pointing to stay with one particular
object people often will ask how does concentration fit in to this practice
how does it how does it work and so I'd like to respond to that question in in a
little talk here um so kind of talking about different form forms of
concentration in general concentration I would say
there's different ways we can think about concentration we often think about it as Focus that's that's what I think
we we tend to think about the word as what the word means but in terms of um a
quality of mind we could say it's a stability of mind and in terms of the
meditation practice it's a stability of Mind a comp
osure a sense of collectedness of non-d
distraction those are some some other words that resonate with what
concentration is unbroken attentiveness another another
word concentration um
arises it's not something we do so much concentration arises as a natural
condition it arises when we explore energy and mindfulness
together making the effort to stay connected with experience moment after
moment and often we do that by staying with one particular object the breath
for example so the the um concentration I would say
in in terms of these these words non- distraction composure
collectedness unbroken attentiveness another definition we could say for
concentration is mindfulness present moment after
moment now it may be present with one particular experience the breath moment
after moment or it may be ex uh present with changing experience moment after
moment so these are two different kinds of
concentration and I'll talk a little bit more about those two different kinds
just to kind of highlight some of the differences and how they're practiced and how they're cultivated but
concentration itself comes about through cultivating
mindfulness with some effort you know with making energy to stay connected to the present moment
there's a couple of places in the sutas where the Buddha points to concentration being
a natural consequence of practice so there's a a
statement it's to be expected that one who has Faith whose energy is
aroused and whose mindfulness is established will gain
concentration will experience concentration so we don't make concentration
happen we do connect with experience moment after moment we make that effort
we make that kind of we engage in that way and sometimes that's a kind of an
active engagement and directing or aiming of the attention to the breath or some
particular experience and sometimes it's more of a connecting with awareness
itself knowing that we're aware and receiving experience moment after moment
that was the way I was guiding the first 15 minutes or so of the guided meditation today that
receptivity we're not choosing to um aim the attention at a particular experience
but we are connecting it takes some effort to connect what's obvious now
what's obvious now or maybe noticing when the attention shifts from one experience to another
so we make that effort we engage with energy and mindfulness as the as the
suta quote says whose energy is aroused and whose mindfulness is established will experience
concentration so we don't make concentration happen we gently encourage mindfulness
moment to moment and concentration the purpose of
concent ation isn't the concentration in and of itself concentration does feel good it
it uh creates a sense of ease in the mind it creates often creates a feeling
of Tranquility there's sometimes experiences of delight or um Happiness
joy that can arise with the arising of concentration but all of that is not why
we do it in this in in Buddhist
practice we look at establishing mindfulness and cultivating that
concentration so that we can see clearly we can understand our minds we can
understand how our minds struggle how they get caught and how
they can move in the direction of more ease more peace
more happiness less suffering and so the concentrated mind
allows mindfulness it's kind of like a like um sharpening a knife we could
think of mindfulness kind of being like a a a knife that kind of clearly can see
what's going on in our mind and the uh the concentration is like the sharpening
of that knife it creates more capacity more
clarity perhaps
so the recognition of what is skillful what
is unskillful the the qualities we begin to see with mindfulness we begin to see
what's going on in our mind sometimes patterns related to Greed aversion and
delusion and we feel we see we we see those patterns we feel them and we know
directly in the moment wow those things do not feel good they are
suffering they create tension they create stress they create contracted
those qualities of heart and mind and then when we also see our a mindfulness
can also see other qualities of Mind open-heartedness connectedness care
patience happiness Tranquility calm and when we feel those with
mindfulness we feel the ease that's associated with
those we feel a a spaciousness we
feel openness non-constricted
and so this difference we notice this
difference between these habits and patterns of greed diversion and delusion and the arisings of with non-
greed non aversion non- delusion love compassion wisdom patience Tranquility
Joy the light we feel the difference between
those and we don't have to turn away
from those challenging states of mind the the the teachings of the Buddha
point to the first the first Noble Truth
there is Dua there is suffering and the Buddha's encouragement
around that Noble Truth understand it we should understand
Dua so this understanding of Duca is precisely what concentration and
mindfulness together support so when we see the arising of
anger or frustration or confusion or or desire
greed when we can see that with mindfulness and concentration yes we feel the dooka of it and the one of the
beautiful things about mindfulness and wisdom together this mindfulness
concentration and wisdom as they come together when we
know and can see these UNH wholesome qualities of Mind arising these
qualities based in greed diversion and delusion when we see them
arising it creates the conditions for them to get weaker mindfulness and wisdom do that we
don't have to turn away from it if we can know it if mindfulness and concentration
are established concentration is present and
there's this stability of undistracted attention
knowing the arising of those UNH wholesome states of mind is no longer
UNH wholesome because it's being witnessed
with wholesome qualities of mindfulness wisdom and concentration so we're cultivating those
wholesome qualities and learning about those habits and patterns of mind
and when mindfulness wisdom and concentration recognize
suffering they understand this is not the way to happiness this is not the
direction and so it begins to support the mind letting it go now Maybe not
immediately Maybe not immediately but it it inclines in that
direction and then when mindfulness concentration and wisdom meet those
wholesome qualities of Mind states of Mind based in non- greed
non aversion non- delusion those ones that feel expansive
feel beautiful feel uplifting there's a s there's a sense of
well-being when mindfulness wisdom and concentration meet those they understand
this is the way to happiness and those qualities are
strengthened so mindfulness wisdom and concentration are wonderful supports
they are we we don't have to try to
weaken those qualities of mind that are UNH
wholesome or try to strengthen the qualities of mind that are wholesome it's natural that these quality these
the UNH wholesome qualities diminish and the wholesome qualities increase as we
cultivate energy mindfulness concentration with wisdom with this
curiosity about what's here
so the the um the concentration there does not need
to be just on one experience as we turn as we as we open
to what's arising in our experience we will see all kinds of things going on in our
mind frustration confusion anger hatred love compassion kindness we'll feel all kinds of things
going on in our bodies and so there is a form of concentration
that allows for that so there's I'll talk about two
forms of concentration just a little briefly here um the the one we're more familiar
with perhaps we could call one-pointed concentration that's where we aim the
attention to one particular experience like the breath the practice there and
cultivating this kind of concentration well this kind of concentration I would say um it results from a focus on on a
particular experience where we turn the attention to it could be the breath it might be a
particular body sensation it might be um an
image and we we give preference to that so the the stability of mind with a
particular experience what we often call Focus we focused on one experience and
the practice around that I'm sure most of you are familiar with you know when we notice that the attention shifts away
from that we we as best we can let go of what is not that and come back so if we're
attending to the breath and we notice that the attention goes to a thought
we try with as much ease as possible to say not now and return to the breath and
so we let go of anything not the focus of attention in this form of meditation
practice that creates a stability of awareness or mindfulness on the object
itself on for instance the breath moment after moment that's where the attention
is and that we let go of what is not the breath and come back to the breath the Mind tends to begin to
gravitate more to the breath we're training the mind to come back to the breath and so that be you know begins to
be more easeful we can just stay with the breath and the kind of concentration that's developed
there is uh very stable because
we're we're stabilizing the object as well as the mindfulness
but the the the the concentration itself is still simply a continuity of
mindfulness moment after moment it just happens to be a continuity of mindfulness moment after moment on the
breath when that concentration deepens and it can deepen very
very to a lot of Stillness a lot of depth the the the the movement of that
kind of concentration is towards more and more Stillness Tranquility can be a Hallmark of that Stillness a Hallmark of
that kind of
concentration the hindrances fade away there's much less reactivity in the
mind and there's a lot of stability it feels pretty good A lot of the feeling
of it feeling good has to do with that the fact that these hindrances are not arising desire the sense desire ill will
sloth and toror restlessness and worry and doubt are not arising and the absence of those feels pretty
good so that's a the one-pointed concentration it becomes very very still
very quiet and and we like it actually it it feels really good
it's such a relief not to have so many things going on in our mind
sometimes and there is this other form of concentration it's called momentto
moment concentration this kind of concentration
is it it has many of the Hallmarks of the other form of concentration it
there's a lot of stability of the mind it's not distracted it's not being pulled out into non-m
mindfulness not losing um the connection with the
present moment experience there's a but there's a stability of the awareness that we're
cultivating here rather than a stability of object of
experience so we're cultivating a non-judgmental
non-reactive awareness moment to moment with whatever is arising in the present
moment staying present with a flow of
experience so this kind of of concentration it it it also brings a lot
of ease the hindrances fall away when we're not when we're not involved in
what's arising by thinking about it or reacting to it the hindrances will fall away also in
this and that feels that feels quite lovely when the hindrances Fall Away
there's there's ease with what's here also I'll say that this form of
concentration is available not only on the cushion but in daily
life in the midst of whatever is happening it's possible for this form of
concentration the stability of mindfulness to carry through the day now it's it's it's not
easy we have to work at this there's a kind of an intention we need to to set
to be curious about how how can we carry mindfulness through the day how can we
cultivate that continuity of mindfulness which is concentration throughout our
day this kind of concentration has a lot of similar qualities in the
the feelings that arise the Delight The Joy balance of Mind ease
non-reactivity and yet what it is what's very different about it is that it
doesn't have that same Stillness of
object The Experience can feel very Dynamic with this form of concentration
now we can tune in a stability of the awareness that can feel quite
still but a lot of the what what's happening in experience is
changing and yet we're not distracted by that change
so I'd like to take a few minutes to talk a little bit about this form of
concentration and how it can be cultivated not only on the cushion but
in daily life because to me this is a lot of where the rubber meets the road
in our daily lives we so often get you know caught by what's going on in our
minds so what can support look if we think of
concentration as being the continuity of mindfulness moment to moment not so much on one thing you know
the continuity of mindfulness moment to moment what can support
that with changing experience with the flow of our lives with just what what's
arising on the cushion a gentle effort to recognize
awareness I would say is one of the first the first
things we're exploring trying to just remember remember awareness when I when
I learned this technique most fully I was practicing in Burma with
Sania and the first instruction that he gave me was the only thing you need to
do with your mind is to remind yourself to be
aware everything else will follow there's a little more than that
but that's that's a a kind of first level of exp of of practice
just reminding yourself to be aware he would to say remember yourself just remember yourself not as a
turning back and looking at like this but more of a opening oh yeah I'm aware awareness is
actually quite obvious so recognizing awareness I'd say beginning to learn
what awareness feels like is one of the main supports for
this for this kind of practice and one of the easiest places to begin noticing that
difference noticing the quality of being aware is in the moment when after you've
gotten lost awareness returns that moment we often are judging
ourselves about that moment because we think we should have been staying
mindful but you know conditions arose and we got caught by something and now
conditions have new conditions have Arisen that mindfulness is back let's
celebrate here it is what does it feel like what does awareness feel like what
is it like to be aware now there's a there's a contrast in that moment there is a contrast between what it was like a
moment before when the mindfulness was not there and what it's like now for the
mindfulness to be here be curious about that difference we can't we don't
actually know you know what it was like when we weren't mindful we can't be mindful of when we're not mindful but we
can remember in the moment when mindfulness returns there's a lingering memory of what it was like for the mind
not to be mindful and so there's a contrast so get curious about that
moment of mindfulness returning when I started this exploration
it was it was really fantastic because because I was just curious about well
what is it like for mindfulness to come back you know and so it did not matter how many times my mind
wandered in fact every time my mind wandered gave me another opportunity to notice what is awareness
like so you know just practicing like that you know maybe the mind wanders a 100 times in a 40 minute sitting that's
100 opportunities to notice what's awareness like when it comes back and as
I shifted to that Curiosity of what's awareness like when it comes back the judgment about the
mind having wandered really diminished so that practice was really helpful for
me in in the in the sitting in the form of sitting you know just maybe take a
sitting sometime where that's your practice you don't try to stay mindful
you just notice the return of mindfulness just notice that and see
what it's like I don't I don't recommend that as
your only mindfulness practice but you might explore it just to kind of get the flavor of mindfulness returning of what
awareness is like what it's like to be aware what it's like to be mindful this
you can also do in your daily lives this recognition of mindfulness
returning it happen happens a lot more than we think it
happens what happens often when when mindfulness returns
is we start thinking about what we've become aware of we do something with it and so we
don't really uh connect with oh this is awareness I become
aware so you you can just it's kind of like just setting an intention or curiosity kind of like I suggested for
the sitting you know sit down and and you know don't try to be you know staying mindful but notice when
mindfulness returns you could start with a little stabilizing so that you you you have a
little bit of a container to start with and then let go and then then see be curious about that moment of mindfulness
returning so there's an intention to to connect with that moment of mindfulness returning you can do something similar
in daily life now it's probably not going to happen as frequently but when
when you begin to get familiar with it in daily life you'll find you know mindfulness returns when you're walking
down the street crossing a sidewalk opening a
door washing the dishes hearing a dog dog
bark talking to a friend mindfulness can
arise you can become aware that you are aware in any activity
and so some curiosity about that you'll you may start you know if you if you set
that intention so you know this is one of the supports for the cultivation of
concentration because we don't make concentration happens we set the conditions up
for energy and mindfulness and one of the supports for
energy is an intention to notice when my mindfulness
returns so have that be an intention remind yourself about that intention and
any time you notice that mindfulness returns it's like oh here it is as you
begin to get familiar with what it's like in daily life for mindfulness to return you will start noticing it more
because the Attunement to that quality of it kind of feels like the light is coming on there's a brightening in the
mind mind as you start to get attuned to that it will Point itself out to you more and
more so this is this is one of the the ways to begin to to cultivate
mindfulness and it's so simple you you don't have to work actually that moment that mindfulness returns it's great
because you didn't make it happen you didn't have to do anything to make it happen it just
happened there's a little bit of effort to connect with the fact that it did
happen that moment when mindfulness returns also can give you a flavor of how easeful it can be to be mindful to
be aware and that we can be aware with anything because mindfulness will arise
in the midst of all kinds of activities all kinds of states of mind so curiosity
about that moment of mindfulness returning and that you know in the sitting practice really supports the
recognition of awareness which then once we have a sense of awareness itself what
it's like to be aware that that recognition helps us
to not be so concerned about the object of awareness and the shift of attention
the shift of EX of the mind moving from one experience to another we can know I'm
aware it doesn't matter if there's some other object that's
appearing the other key piece I'll I'll point to or another
piece is um is around the attention and again this may be a little bit more in
in the sitting practice but it it's useful in daily life as
well in the guided meditation I pointed to how we can Rec recognize the
attention shifting from experience to experience attention is the factor of mind that
connects to some aspect of experience mindfulness is the connection
the knowing the the receiving of experience these are different functions
of mind I used to think that if I was not consciously directing my atten ition
that I was not being Mindful and that's not
true so beginning to understand the difference between attention and mindfulness is useful and we can know
this actually you know if you're walking down the street and you're lost in thought entirely not
mindful often you know we're navigating the street fine
we're seeing we're hearing we're not like running into trees or walking in front of cars even though we're lost in
thought even though we're not consciously aware attention is
working attention is noticing seeing and
hearing and mindfulness is not present so we can see that attention and mindfulness are different things now
when mindfulness is present it's connecting to whatever attention is
noticing also that example points out that we don't have to make attention happen you know when we're not
mindful we're not choosing where attention is it's doing its thing
conditions arising pointing pointing out various things that are useful to attend
to as we walk down the street that's happening it's not
self it's an arising so attention does not require us to aim the
attention and so when mindfulness is arising it's basically connecting with whatever attention is connecting with in
that moment so that um recognizing the
attention and noticing when attention shifts from one experience to
another that that um
recognition there's a distinct quality you know there's a feeling of when the
attention shifts from one thing to another and I think we know this too I mean from meditation the we we kind of
get attuned to this shift if you're practicing in a a more focused way with
being at with the breath we know the shift away from the breath that's a
shift of attention in our concentration practice
and our more focused practice when we notice that shift of attention
we let go of what the attention has shifted to and come back to the breath we aim the
attention in this more receptive practice when we notice a shift of attention we get curious about
that what's that the attention has shifted we're mindful of the attention
shift why not know that and this kind of quality of the shift of attention as we
get familiar with it we can kind of have a sense of following the attention moment after moment and again
the mindfulness can stabilize if you're more familiar with
the bring the attention back it can feel a little bit unstable at first
to just watch that shift of attention you can feel a little bit
jumpy or or you know wobbly or something
like that but over time we can begin to
appreciate we are aware so that the stability of the awareness and noticing
the um where the attention is moment after moment and notice the the non that that
that we we can be with experience moment after moment without reacting to
it because of the mindfulness and the stability the concentration
together so this shift of attention noticing that
shift and in daily life this also I mean you know we might we might
recognize we're we're focusing on something and something happens out outside or something and we we get we
may get annoyed right I mean it's like oh the attention is shifted I'm supposed to be doing this and and if we don't
notice the shift of attention we're not consciously aware of the shift of attention reactivity often arises
there and I'd say too that not noticing the shift of attention is one of the main reasons our
minds wander in sitting meditation practice so familiarity with that shift
you're getting curious about it and then you know there's a choice if you're doing a more focused practice then with
that noticing that shift of attention you can let go of what it has shifted to and come back to cultivate that more
stable one-pointed concentration but you can also be
curious about oh I'm aware of this at one point I was doing this in um
or I was doing more focused practice at one point um and noticed that the kind
of It kind of felt like the mind got really broad or kind of felt like a drop and a spread or something like that and
it was like oh come back it almost felt like falling asleep you know just
like and um and so every time I felt the beginning of that drop I would come back
come back come back and at some point in this process I noticed that I was quite
aware at the beginning of the drop it's like okay I'm aware let's just see cuz
it kept happening it was so you know it was almost it was like
almost a pull towards something a mindfulness was being pulled toward
something it's like well let's see where is it going and so you know in that moment of
feeling I felt the drop and the spread and was completely aware and and found
the I did not fall asleep I was completely aware and mindful and the the space was
vast expansive it was a completely different space and it it almost startled me it
actually pulled me out of it he like whoa what was that but that was the kind of the
Curiosity of following the attention and since I've understood and
have been able to follow that more it's like a deepening of it was a deepening of letting
go and this kind of noticing the shift of attention can also be
very valuable in daily life because as we begin to get more
familiar with that there's much less reactivity that can enter Because the mindfulness and the concentration are
more present and there's so much learning
the this the the still concentration pra the still concentration practice where we're really stabilizing the body and
mind on one experience depends on how deep or how
you know how you know still you're going for but the the direction of that is to
kind of stability not a lot of change
in that space And so there's not as much opportunity to learn about the comings
and goings in our mind in that space now the the the movement to cultivate it
going into that state and coming out of that state there's a lot that can be learned about the changing nature of our
minds and that's typically the encouragement with one-pointed
concentration practice that we're learning you know about letting go of the hindrances as we go in we're
learning about stabilizing the mind and um as we go in and then as as it ends as
it falls apart we're learning about the impermanence of that state itself we're learning something about
that so it is in the space of changing experience that the Learning Happens the
learning about wholesome and UNH wholesome the learning about what our minds do can cause and effect
impermanence in this momentto moment concentration practice we're
learning all the time it's it's um you know we're we're
starting and we don't have to we don't have to some people feel or think that you know it's it's um
you need to settle the Mind first before you open up you know settle into one-pointed concentration before you
open up to this changing nature of experience and that's definitely one way
to go you know that's a that's a way to cultivate the Vasa practice the Insight
practice into changing experience but it's not necessary to start with one pointed
concentration the one-pointed concentration kind of takes us down deep and then we
open the open awareness practice we're kind of learning as we
go uh about everything that's going on in our minds and so it's a little bit of
a slower settle can take a little bit more time to really
settle deeply but we're always learning
about what's happening in our minds learning about the suffering of
reac ity learning about the beauty and well-being of the non-reactive
states so the cult the point of cultivating the concentration is this
understanding whichever way you come at it it's not the pleasant experience of
concentration itself it's what can be
learned and it's time to stop so thank you for your attention