yeah good morning good day everyone uh from all around the world and here we
are gathering again uh in this uh 7 a.m.
Pacific time meditation and
Dad I just kind of feel a sense of warmth coming in so uh maybe you feel
that way too kind of sense of
a so I want to orient ourselves on a little bit for our meditation uh for
this days for this week I'd like to evoke a nature-based
metaphor uh as we meditate and it builds up and uh you
know from one day to another it doesn't have to be that way so if you're join in between it's not a problem um but I like
to to to start today with this metaphor or a simile of sitting like a
mountain maybe that evokes some kind of a stability or have uh some different
associations you may have and so I'll drop that in for meditation today and
then in the next uh few days and I will build up uh this this metaphor and so
here we go and I'm going to ring bell and we'll
[Music]
start taking a few long deep breath as you breathe out
arriving arriving here and
now maybe there is a kind of a familiarity a sense of a coming
home coming home to ourselves
this moment
here face this place where we
sit or stand or lie down
being patient to arrive so we're not jerking our
minds simple presence
mindfulness front and a
center mindfulness all around
mindfulness receiving meeting what's
here to be known
maybe the overall sense of the body
sitting or sense of the contact of the body with the Earth
underneath gentle turn your attention to the
contact between the body and the Earth
underneath maybe you feel the weight settling down
hardness of the sit
bones stability of the pelvic floor
softening and releasing the body towards the Earth
there is a natural relational pull of gravity
allow this earthy body resting on Earth
sitting like a
mountain quiet Mountain
allow your attention to rest here if you
like steady
still connected with the Earth
underneath
e
for
e e
in this last few minutes of the meditation
together allow yourself to
feel feel and sense the community practicing
together like walking into a mountain
range maybe you can feel the
potency of the vast Stillness and
quiet maybe the Stillness can
expand to become back
fast the silence can
expand that become
vast and a silence that includes the sounds all around
and the Stillness that can include
movements feeling and sensing the good goodness of a practicing in community
together so as if we're offering blessings and
gifts to ourselves and to each other
[Music]
maybe this bowing is a expression of gratitude to practice in
s gratitude yourself to show up here in this
way so with that and I'm going to
transition um for this week's
topic I'd like to share some Reflections about this uh word
refuge and refuge is a prominent Buddhist concept since the days of the
Buddha and The Refuge itself um you know may evoke different um feelings for
people and I want to offer some different words that are also associated
with this notion of ref refuge and so I'm going to drop in some
of those words so
protection shelter sanctu our
safety a refuge being a place to rest in or a safe
container a sense of a home or a ground to rest
on and so all those words for me kind of evoke a sense of Refuge uh in some
way and um the Resonance of Refuge has grown more and more uh multi-dimensional
and came alive over the years of a practice and learning and so I like to
make attempt to share some of this different Di Dimensions uh different
aspects and I'm also calling it uh kind of different flavors of or textures of
Refuge uh for this week and so touching in this into this uh sense of Refuge in
different ways and today I kind of hinted in uh
towards the end of our meditation together I like to start with refuge in
s s this PO term means a community that
practices and learns together learns together the
Dharma and so like uh how we've been doing and this is 7 a.m. um
Gatherings we're forming a sa uh even though it's in a virtual field and uh
we're practicing together and I like to speak about Sana
first because for many people uh Sana is where we began to find a sense of a
refuge a spiritual home a shelter a protection or a safe container a
sanctuary and that's how I began so my first exposure to Buddhism and Buddhist
practices were not based on a books or doctrines or teachings and there was no
YouTube back then and there was you know I didn't know about the recordings
and and uh so some of this didn't even even existed uh didn't didn't even exist
um back then so for me and it began when I first
encountered a group of Buddhist uh in my uh College
time uh when I met this group of people I distinctly noticed something
very different and this is a group people that expressed qualities of a generosity
kindness and Care in so many different ways uh that um was quite intriguing for
me and I was drawn towards it immediately and so that was the
beginning of my Dharma journey and
um reflecting forward you know all the way to this day throughout my Dharma
Journey Sana has been a refuge um for me as a potent force uh to
this state uh in the realm of Buddha Dharma s
specifically refers to the community that uh learns and practices a Dharma
and so it's not just any social Community which has its own
function um but the SAA has a specific function and specific
purpose as a Dharma practitioners each person in the s
learns to cultivate wholesome qualities of a heart and mind and the body uh in
the way that the supports a well-being a deeper care of ourselves and for each
other and for the whole world and that is so for the generations
of aanga that um came from ancient times all the way
till now and for me uh kind of reflecting and
observing this 7 a.m. sa uh over the
past few years since the beginning of the pandemic I'm feeling this growing sense
of care connectedness and
warmth and the deeper kind of resonance with each other in some way
and this kind of a collective Force inspires and sustains us and support us
uh in our in our own Dharma journey and support each
other maybe what has been uh surprising for some of us uh
is that somehow this virtual world would have this kind
of palpable sense for us that I don't think I had imagined
this no one probably could have imagined this um some decades ago and how how is
this possible you know in our meditation the last few minutes of a meditation I
invited for us to kind of tune in to some of this
Collective sense a kind of a field we're in the field of a practice together even
though we're not physically together we're quite geographically dispersed all
over on this planet and yet we can have a sense maybe a hint of
it wow we're together here
practicing that's truly something
and for AA to be a refuge a sanctuary a home for each of us I also wanted to say
that uh it also had to go beyond being an external entity that we go to whether
it's virtual or not one of the most important function
of a refuge in Sanaa is that it helps each of us to turn
inward to look within and so there is this outside in
kind of effect here when we're affected by the S people who practice Dharma we
are changed by it and so it invites us to touch in
inside for us to feel and sense what is being
affected and how does it shape and enchange us from
within the Buddha said to his disciples that when you're when you're with good
com companions when they practice the Noble eight-fold Path then you will do so
too and so that's that outside in kind of effect that I'm speaking
about and at the same time there is
also uh a kind of inside out
effect when we are changed by The Refuge in
Sana our Behavior our heart and mind learn to stay with what we aspire to
cultivate and more and more this have effect on the broader
world we live in maybe start with the environment we're in maybe it has effect for the
people around you and so in this way um practicing the Refuge or savoring
in The Refuge of a s it has this kind of outside in and inside out kind of
movements so Refuge inanga is not static and it's Dynamic
alive and kind of um like a living
stream uh have a constant effect coming all the way from
2,600 years ago all the way to present within and
without so it's up to each of us to learn to turn in to this inner outer
living Dynamic um such that whatever goodness
or challenges that arise within us that we Leverage or
incorporate this field of Sana to allow us to move through and allow the
goodness the benefits to rippo out into the broader world so that all beings
have a possibilities to live with goodness and to live with
well-being and that's the power being in the Refuge of Sana
so I leave with you to for the rest of the day maybe do some
Reflections uh of your own Journey your own spiritual journey uh what are the
roles of Sana and the community what has been changed what how
are you shaped and what is your relationship with
Sana and so I'll end there and um let's
together being in this s feel and Savor a little the potency of
Sana in whatever way that it manifest for
you may whatever goodness and benefits that arose out of us practicing together
may it be shared with Open Hearts and open mind to
beings around you and to all beings
everywhere and may all beings find Refuge may all beings find a refuge that
supports the onward leading towards freedom and liberation
thank you everyone be well and I'll see you tomorrow