so I welcome you on this second day of our exploration of
thinking and in a way it could be very helpful if you also
welcome yourself that meditation is
a welcoming well your welcome here
to yourself and one of the themes for today
is that the mind is not just a mind the body is not just a
body that these are deeply connected to each other and one of the analogies the
Buddha uses for this connection is uh that the mind the
thinking mind mind is a puppeteer and it has all these strings
in the body and pulling on the muscles pulling on the
limbs and this is a way of speaking to how the connection between
thinking and Sensations in the body tensions in
the body movements in the body that um
uh we can think one kind of thought and it tugs on the belly in certain kind of
way or activates it if it's fear maybe there's a
hollow uh kind of tension in the in the belly if there is a sense of uh warmth
and love it might be a suffusing feeling maybe feeling of
warmth or vibration in the chest what we think of course is very
connected to how we what the emotions we feel but for this uh day I'd like to
emphasize the physicality the physical activation the physical expression the physical in
Impact that thinking has and uh and the physical Source from
which thinking arises and so sometimes it just feels that
thinking is disembodied or pervasive or just uh coterminous with the
universe but um as we settle down the meditation often we can feel or sense
that there's a location for where thinking is occurring and uh it might be a
difference different location if we think in words or if we think in IM
Imes uh where's where's the projector projecting the
images where's The Voice or the speaker system that's coming up with the
words some people kind of think more somatically so there it's already deeply
connected to the body and um so we'll guide you through
this little bit and and um hopefully you
can develop a see and value the Deep
connection between thinking and the body and discover that through that
connection you can you can have an influence on the thinking Mind by relaxing the body quieting gentling the
different parts of your body that are activated settling holding
and being able to be in relationship to thinking some aspect of thinking that is
not the content of the thoughts the ideas the stories the images but rather
the physicality of that process so
to assume a
align posture that allows you to be in some way or
other even even if lying down to be a bit
alert and create the conditions in the body that you feel and sense your body
more fully more globally in an aligned
way gently closing your eyes and taking a few long slow deep
breaths
relaxing as you
exhale and then to breathe normally and continue on the exhale to
relax maybe relaxing some of the common places is maybe not for you but
generally for people where the Puppeteer creates tension in the body as it
thinks activation maybe around the eyes and the
forehead on the exhale softening relaxing
there
and the
Jaws a very common area that thinking
influences is the shoulders if you can feel your shoulders
and it's easy enough to relax them please
do but if you just feel the tension and they don't relax see if you can soften
around the tension
some thoughts reach down into the chest the heart
area maybe a pulling maybe a contraction
tightening relaxing the
chest sometimes the whole arms are ever so slightly tensing
up relaxing the
arms
and then the
belly
and then if it's easy enough can you find the place in your body that from which
thinking occurs the projector the [Music]
speaker it might be a wide area but maybe it doesn't include your feet and
your fingers maybe it's above the waist
maybe it's generally above the neck maybe it's behind your forehead
or wherever the thinking mind the thinking activity seems to be
centered on the exhale
relax
and then centering yourself on your breathing
maybe remembering to relax by relaxing with every
exhale feeling every
inhale and if you find yourself pulled into to the world of
thinking so you lose touch with your breathing or if thinking seems quite
strong even if you're aware of breathing find where there might be some
tension in the body connected to those
thoughts in the thinking mind
elsewhere and in a sense take the three breath
Journey every exhale for three breaths relax that part where the tension
is and then Begin Again with your
breathing
for
e
if you find yourself thinking relax
relax the whole
body if you find yourself thinking but can't find but cannot find someplace in
the body to relax see if you can soften
or open up beyond the edges of your
thoughts
for
e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting take three breaths with the exhale
relaxing as widely in your body as is
easy relax
soften and then take three more breaths relaxing the mind the thinking
mind and perhaps Imagining the thinking mind
is spreading out beyond the edges of
thought beyond the edges of your body a softening and
opening emptying
for
and then feeling or Awakening inside of you in your mind your thoughts your
heart your body the kind
of openness kind of softness through
which kindness travels Good
Will through which simple care ordinary care of
others caring about them caring for them doing them a
simple Act of care like putting on a bandage
or offering them some tea
at a time when they're maybe a bit
stressed and imagining that that form of kindness or
care can spread out in all directions from you to the people Close to You
Neighbors people in your communities out across the
lands and wishing Maybe by repeating my words
and relaxing into the meaning of the words
wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all
beings be free
and may each of
us the 400 plus people who are here today may it
be that we use our care capacity for care and good
will to care for at least two people today in small ways tea
bandage do something so something doubles here
today out of this community goodness out into the
world [Music]
for
e
so hello and welcome to this second day on instructions of
mindfulness of thinking and one of the
invaluable ways of getting a handle on thinking so that it doesn't pull us we
not get swept away in the currents of thought and the river of thoughts the the Train the train cars of
thoughts the image that's sometimes given of thinking is that we standing at
um a train crossing watching a whole bunch of trains go by and and at some
point we find ourselves on the train and we've been on it for a long time and didn't know
it so these thoughts will come and the idea is just let them go let them come
and go don't get on the train don't get involved in the train and one of the ways that can
support this uh while still clearly knowing that the trains are coming and
going without getting on is to feel the body to be well connected to your body
the body is all always in the present moment and uh and the body is
itself um not exactly a thought however the body is influenced
by the thoughts that we have if the thoughts are very mild and soft and
wispy maybe we don't feel any connection to the body too much or at all but at
that point we don't really need to because it's easy to let go of the thoughts it's easy to stay with
um with the breathing as we breathe stay in the present moment but if it's hard to stay with in the present if it's hard
to stay riding in breath and out breath over time because we get swept away in
the trains of thought then we need some help in
practice and one of the principles of mindfulness practice is everything is
food for mindfulness everything is something that we use can turn to and be aware of and um so we want to learn how
to be mindful of thinking so that we're kind of standing on the on the ground
watching the train go by and clearly know we're in the ground field the stability the strength of that and just
kind of know that's the train okay we don't have to get involved we can just let it be the train and
um and one of the ways to be present for thinking is to be aware that thinking is
more than just the thoughts we have the images we have those are often what help
us get what we get entangled with is to um is to uh feel the connection the
thinking has with the body and then you're part of the Ecology of thoughts and so uh some thoughts clearly
trigger tension in the body tightening in in the body and I find it fascinating to sit in meditation quietly and feel
some modum of a relaxed body and present and then to some kind of really exciting
troubling thought arises in the mind and immediately the body Trigg it triggers
something in the body it tightens it the belly tightens or there's a place that
gets all hot or or the the the activated
part of the body gets moves up into the head so to to start feeling what is
activated whether it's tension or some people call it energy some people say
it's where the uh FOC focus of attention really wants to go and be
centered um you want to uh notice what's the physical
coraly with breathing with thinking and um and if there's tension
that's connected uh you could do one of two things you could relax just soften if
possible a more kind of uh kind of
developed form of mindfulness is not to relax but to bring your attention into
the place of tension into the place of activation and feel your way to what
wants to happen there you can ask a question what are these what does this tension want or if it's like an
activated feeling of heat or agitation what does that
want and uh you might feel with tension you say oh it wants to relax Sometimes some like an activated
Place uh sometimes the feeling can be oh it wants space it wants space to spread
out into and um and if you feel that physical Sensations and what they want
or the direction they're going or the sense of how they're if they're left alone in given room what direction
they'd go um give them that room relax if they want to relax make room for them
to relax if uh if some fear in the heart is more like a vibrating tingling
agitation um and you feel that what it most wants to do it wants to become spread out make it wants to have room to
be agitated make room for it kind of relax around it and you might discover that
that helps it relax that helps it dissipate it's not so concentrated and eventually it might
actually dissipate entirely by just kind of spreading outward and um so to find the Coral in
the body and um and occasionally it might feel the whole body is
activated if you uh like an interesting way of practicing with this is don't
spend a lot a lot of time uh being mindful of some kind of thinking that's
captivated you find where there's some tension in your body find where the activation in the body is relax it or
make room for it or just feel it for a while but do it experiment with doing for just three breaths kind of like the
three breath journey and you might even uh Fe you
know kind of count as you go along and there's something about the limited span of three breaths knowing that's as long
you're going to do it it's not open-ended so it's easier for the mind to get focused this is what I'm doing if
it's open-ended the mind kind of is not quite committed maybe and it might be long enough to do
three breaths because uh with the you know being mindful of the thinking that
way and it might be long enough because anything more has the danger of actually
work somehow interested fascinated somehow engaged
reactive to the thinking and like we're trying to get rid of it and the odd thing about
thoughts is that uh even being bothered by it even wanting to get rid of it is
fueling it gives it more energy uh being bothered by thoughts is the food for
more thinking so just do three breaths and then settle yourself back on the
breathing again like you've done your you've done your task to be mindful of thinking what's going on and maybe
that's enough to acknowledge it with three breaths relaxing for three breaths and then Begin Again with your
breathing if the same kind of thinking arises again or seems to be predominant again then do the same process but maybe
don't spend more than three breaths with it um if you can really stable mindfulness then maybe you can just stay
with the experience longer but uh see if this three breaths is long enough to
acknowledge it well enough that it takes away some of the fuel for that kind of
thinking some of the fascination with it or interest in it and part of this um physical
mindfulness of thinking is to feel the location where thinking is
arising and it might be somewhere behind the eyes or somewhere in the middle of
the head I've had different places at different times but often it's the upper half of the head for me if I'm caught up
in thoughts and um sometimes in the back of the head sometimes in the middle sometimes near the front between the
ears someplace sometimes it's not exactly so clear exactly where it is but
it's kind of a vague kind of generalized area someplace in the head some people might feel it in their
heart and their chest some people might feel it someplace else if it's uh uh
images we have where's the projector where's the energy of the that's fueling the the um the images appear and um and
uh and so find the location and if it's not easy to find that don't you know you don't have to keep trying but U maybe
you have to wait to really you know first class high-powered anxious
thoughts or angry thoughts that you can really you might really feel oh that's where the center of gravity is that's
where I'm constricted or tight and that seems to be projecting the
thoughts and um and find the location of thinking and then do the three breath
relaxation there as well or three breath opening sometimes just making lots of
space for for thoughts um room around it makes it kind of dissipate and spread
out and good quiet sometimes I'm emphasizing relaxing today but sometimes relaxing in if we do
it with a version or as an engineering feat like we have to do it right all
there's all kinds of ways in which we actually are uh feeding the thoughts and giving it more
energy sometimes just kind of like just making space for the thinking and and feel the physicality of the location and
maybe what it feels like it wants to do is just kind of spread and out and so
what happens with thinking it doesn't disappear but slowly it dissolves it
softens and um and that's uh and as we settle and get more and more
quiet uh the uh the thinking becomes more wispy and more softer and um
there's a classic uh teaching that I first heard in Zen but I think it's often in a lot of places in Buddhism um
where they refers to clouds like a cloud in an endless Sky drifting Cloud that
just drive it is no more substance than a cloud it's very light and
floating and um and then it might be easy just kind of in that softness to
softly kind of rest the attention on the breathing and get absorbed in sensations
of breathing so um so the task for today if
you're interested is um through the day see how your body is AC AC at by the
kind of thinking you have and there might be as you go through the day something occurs that uh evokes a
particular way of thinking you're driving and someone cuts you off and now
you're activated by that and you have all these angry thoughts how could they and and uh and uh and oh I'm now
thinking furiously about that rather than you know continuing uh you know you
know without paying attention notice what's happened to your body with those
thoughts um you know you get an email and there's new thoughts and notice
what's happening to your body with those thinking and where your tense uh make it a kind of a
specialty what is the connection between thinking and your
body so thank you um very much and I look for to
continuing talking about thinking
tomorrow