okay so uh so welcome uh happy to to be with
you uh I don't know how your day was yeah curious feels um yeah good to
uh close the day with uh with some practice
sa so um yeah that's it that's it
so if you're sleepy breathe some life into your body
mind and if you're Restless breathe some soothing into your body
mind e
if you're sitting the spine reaches ever so gently
Towards the Sky
you give the rest of your body to
gravity the body kind of longing for the
Earth heaviness groundedness of our body
e
dropping down into your belly out of your head
it's like the center of gravity of your own [Music] body moves
down to the belly
it feels like our point of view is up in our
head that sort of headquarters
what's the point of view from the perspective of your belly
soft belly releasing tension
belly
relaxing
e
e e
if there are uh pockets
of hyperarousal little zones of your body
the emotional circuits of your body firing
off very
active just gently massage those
zones with your
awareness your breathing e
forever our bodies have been convincing
us that everything is
urgent something must happen
we're no longer willing to
listen if there's a true alarm we'll know
and in the meantime we treat all
phenoma it's false
alarms is unifying our body in a field of of
Tranquility
e
e e
it seems like problems find us the Loose Ends of uh our day or
week but uh sometimes there's not so much problems finding us but our
agitation finding a placeholder and so we withdraw the
projection
out and become uh radically accountable to what our body mind is doing Moment by
moment radically accountable
but
blameless we keep unifying our body into a kind of
field of
Tranquility
Vitality tranquil yet
vital
e
e e
if there's any thread of pleasantness follow
it rest in it abide in it
let the pleasantness and the
Tranquility being in a kind of virtuous
cycle
e
e e
[Music]
for
e e
okay folks so
um new uh new biography I saw of uh just reviewed of Leonard
Cohen who uh I sat with a little bit at a at a Zen Center in
LA and uh so this is what uh this is how the
this biography begins uh Leonard Cohen's art
derives from a very specific visual ACU he sees men fall and with them women
Saints and Angels hence a Fascination for falling
bodies in a career devoted to a methodical and quasi Amorous exp exp
exploration of the laws of gravity his subject how and why we fall from what
Heights along what trajectories his stated goal to assert
with required rigor the unfathomable beauty of falling
bodies armed with the Visionary force that alone makes you
see the world exactly as it is he sharpened his tools along the way a
voice so deep it leaves us charred a tur and increasingly lethal writing style
and his unique combination of angst Jewish mysticism and Christian and
Buddhist flirtations along the way he fashioned a world that
is uniquely his own yet a lot like ours quite predictably the result is
ferocious songs that Comfort us with little waltes but are also spiritual weapons
that aim for the heart and never miss what do they say what we already
know the Invincible Gra gra ity of existence that we die that our heart
cooks and sizzles like shishkabob in our breasts that the apocalypse has begun
and the flood has already happened that God has summoned us for a
game of hide and seek that he clearly intends to
win in a word that we hang
dangerously between gravity and
Grace so why do we
practice we've all figured out by now that it's
not reliably fun can be
but it's definitely not always fun between gravity and
Grace the Dharma was never plan a you know no one
none of you not one of you when you were a child said when I grow up I'd like to hear
Matthew Bren silver talk about Dua not one of
you it takes uh time and
effort and while practice is not meant to be humiliating sometimes it is it's
just like you can't really sit with yourself look at your
own heart mind you look at that long enough and you'll be humbled at least sometimes
and at uh at moments it feels like we're we're
swimming against the stream of like a million years of evolutionary
conditioning and it's confusing practice is confusing the question can linger for
a really long time am I getting it that sense
of kind of defective person longing for something
remote where is it little homesick lost something how do
I find it that can linger for a long time and it's almost like the basic
worthiness the kind of inocence is so big we can't see its edges it covers
the entire field of vision and so we we can't even see our
innocence Cohen wrote uh about 25 years ago about his zen zen master zen
teacher um said I I never really understood what he said but every now
and then I find myself barking with the dogs or bending with the
irises or helping out in other little
ways no one can understand uh what the Dharma is at the
beginning how deep it runs how wide its
scope what it might
strengthen and what it might tear down in our so-called
lives you you really don't know what you're consenting
to gravity and the grace and it's a little bit like going
into the doctor and giving you know inform
consent to remove a tiny mole or something and then she's
like we're gonna operate for like
decades and so here we are here we are you know somehow
like together the blessings of the Dharma raining down through the
centuries and we're here together somehow on
YouTube so why do we practice we each have to uh we each have to answer that
question we'll have to ask and answer it many times we outgrow old intentions
maybe the question was immature maybe we
solved that we have outgrown it maybe the problem
dissolved and then it's like okay what now and no teacher can really answer
that question for you the the practice is
uh purely about intrinsic motivation and that isn't something
anyone else can give to you for
me you know why do I practice it's a little bit like
asking you know why do you love someone you could give answers you could cite
their characteristics you could say oh their kindness or their humor their whatever but that doesn't really capture
the Love Somehow love feels um beneath the level of conscious
awareness we cannot specify why we love someone something it's like that with
the Dharma there were some points when I really didn't know why why why seemed
besides the point in a sense I just knew I wasn't going to stop
practicing sometimes the Dharma is simply about having ruled out the alternatives to
wisdom and love yeah the the path it's hard but the
Alternatives unbearable and so auna said the right
the cup the cup you know the cup is already broken the flood is already
happened and I really don't know how people live without some practice some
relationship with the sacred and it's like you develop enough
sensitivity and Clarity around suffering and then you know you need a path
something doesn't have to be this but something is needed God summoned us for a game of
hide and seek that he clearly intends to
win and as a kid the the life in front
of me um even
when you know when I could imagine it even when in those fortunate moments I could
imagine it going pretty well it didn't look like a path to me really
didn't looked maybe like pleasure but no fulfillment no heart
satisfaction hanging dangerously between gravity and
Grace and it was like okay is it supposed to
be this hard am I doing something wrong even with all the good fortune in my
life is it actually supposed to always feel like
falling and something in life just felt cyclical
and they kind of so fatigued by an ambivalence that was so pervasive I sort
of lived just in the shadow of
ambivalence and I wanted my heart to point in Just One Direction give me
something that allows all the arrows of my being to point in One
Direction and of course uh I could sense
even when young kind of the
aging sickness death the Heavenly Messengers losing everything how utterly
unprepared my heart was the body Cohen says
ferociously insists on gravitational rights just before he died the body
ferociously insists on gravitational
rights the Dharma is not a perfect consolation for all of
that uh but nothing
else except wisdom and love seem to matter at all at all in in the
end not a perfect consolation but uh enough
enough and so I was uh I began practice I maybe say
stayed with practice because I was Desperately Seeking a path where wisdom
and love could coexist with the Deep
honesty about the
fall and we open to
this and perhaps we find find ourselves helping out
in other little ways I offer this for your consideration