hello and welcome
and for this uh meditation session continuing
to practice with mindfulness of breathing and one of the important
uh elements of mindfulness practice is not doing the mindfulness
exactly what we're mindful of but rather how we're
Mindful and that uh the attitude with which we are bringing attention to our lives is
very important and that attitude can be can come along with all kinds of uh
mindfulness can come along with all kinds of attitudes there can be fear as
part of of it they were worried about how we're doing or what's happening or what's going to happen and so there's a
heightened kind of alertness um that uh is fear-based there
could be desire and we want something to happen we're looking for something to happen
we're trying to make something happen there can be aversion that we're want to
avoid something we don't want to feel discomfort we don't want to be in the present moment because it's boring so
there's an inversion or pushing or resistance there can
be straining there can be um
complacency there's all kinds of things that come along with mindfulness and over time these
attitudes that are extra and not needed Begin to Fall Away we start seeing them at first we might not notice them but
the regularity of practicing begins to slowly reveal and relax and to settle
all the extra attitudes that uh make mindfulness more complicated than needs
to be and so um and it takes a while to
learn it and so today I'd like to offer two attitudes that are
often um seen as very nice alternatives to many of the ways that
the extra attitudes people bring uh they are attitudes which are on
the way to having mindfulness be very clear and simple almost as if it's
attitude free they just kind of a Clarity and open it's like a a window that's been so thoroughly cleaned that
you don't even know there's a w window there you can almost feel like you can put your hand through
it and um so uh so around mindfulness or
breathing and these attitudes for today are
um uh allowing and
receiving and it works fairly well for some people to do that uh with the
allowing with the exhale allowing the exhale to go allowing the
release and for the inhale receiving um the
um the um inhale you're receiving
oxygen on the exhale you're exhaling releasing
C2 and uh on the inhale uh we're the diaphragm is moving
down to mix space and we're receiving and filling and opening and on the
exhale there's a release a letting go that we allow for as a diaphragm comes
up again and by diaphragm is released and it pushes the air
out and um and so this gentle these gentle attitudes as we move
along and um and I'll offer one more uh little technique maybe halfway through a
very gently uh using thinking to keep you present rather than
have your thinking Wonder take you wondering off and that is to use a mental notes to very simple note and to
the note that notation that i' like to recommend today is on the in breath just
say in and the out breath out or the classic way of saying it is that the
belly Rises on the inhale the the word rise
Rising the the exhale falling and these don't have to be words
uh they could be kind of subvocal recognitions or subvocal kind of
thinking the idea is very light touch very relaxed and for some people having
that very simple thought is uh keeps the thinking mind occupied just enough with
the breathing to stay there rather than all too easily wandering
off so assuming a meditation
posture lowering the
Gaze and gently closing the eyes
and gently taking some deeper breaths as a
way of feeling more of your body feeling connected to your
torso your shoulders maybe your back rib
cage and as you
exhale to relax let
go letting your breathing return to
normal and on the inhale receive in
Awareness the different tensions and holding in your body as if it's okay to have
them let them be known or received during the inhale and then on the
exhale allow them to
relax allow them to
soften
and the same thing with a thinking mind on the
inhale receive the sensations the tensions the
agitation the energy that might be there the thinking
mind allow it to be there in a receptive way on the
inhale and on the exhale soften the thinking
mind relax the
mind
and then
calmly find how your body experiences breathing
and where in your body is it most comfortable most
inviting to experience the body's
breathing the movements of the body the sensations connected to
breathing
for
and as you inhale relax and
receive the inhale maybe letting go of straining
and but a sense of wide open space or window that receives the
gentle breeze receive the
inhale maybe as if the body is receptive awareness is
receptive and at the top of the inhale a moment or an instant of
pausing before you exhale and then allow the
exhale as if you're giving the exhale its
freedom allowing the release the Letting
Go allowing it freely let go freely
release and if it's not so free that's okay allow that
too
at the end of the exhale a moment or an instant of
pausing so that you can be ready and switch
to receiving the inhale
for
if there's a lot of thinking the thinking fills the space of
the mind so there's less room for receiving experiencing
breathing see if you can quiet the thinking mind or let it recede in the
background don't give it much attention so there's more room in the
mind space to receive the
inhale space into which to allow the
exhale
for
and then ever so lightly the
quietest maybe even subvocal ways of
thinking gently have a single
word recognizing the inhale maybe it's
in or maybe it's using the word
receive and for the exhale
out or allow
least amount of effort just enough to help you stay on
track breathing in and breathing out
all receiving and
allowing
e
for
e and if the practice of receiving the
inhale and allowing the exhale is nice for
you the next step almost like an extension of
each is to no longer
receive and allow
but let
awareness be there be intimate with each inhale and
exhale with no extra attitude just
breathing in
awareness
for
and then coming to the end of this
sitting to gently take some deeper
inhales as if you're opening yourself expanding yourself to now receive the
world around you the room you're in the building
you're in the
neighborhood the extended communities the
world and on the exhale to send out
your respect your good will love
compassion some form of positive regard out into the
world receiving the world on the
inhale sending positive regard on the
exhale may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings everywhere be
liberated [Music]
thank
you
so good morning or good day for this fifth talk on mindfulness
of breathing and
um I've spent pretty much my whole adult
life some 50 years now um practicing mindfulness of
breathing and it's been a wonderful Journey it's been uh not something I've
really gotten bored with ever seems like it's always being renewed always
something new and um and I think the part of the reason for this is breathing is so
intimately connected to so many different parts of our lives and how we breathe
um what we breathe with as we breathe with our body and our emotions and thoughts it's always changing it's
always a process of deeper deepening understanding or deep greater Freedom
greater finding ease and the uh the word that I like a
lot to associate with Brea breathing is breathing easily having an easy
breath being at ease in breathing and it's not always that way
for me but when that's there uh it just seems so wonderful it's like a
homecoming it's a settling and part of the reason for that
is that when for me when the breathing just easy and relaxed and just doing
itself breathing itself uh the breathing has become freed of all these attitudes or all these
other uh psychological and physical activities that will often influence the
breathing change the breathing and uh emotions will change
how we breathe uh attitudes and desires and motivations will change how we
breathe um what's happening around us will change how we breathe the temperature
will change how we breathe there's so many things that come into play that influence
breathing and uh and some of those have to do with
uh being the agent being the doer being the one who wants something or trying to
avoid something or has to succeed or has expectations and uh the one that I can
measure with ideas of success and failure and to learn to put those aside
and not to live in those um maybe they still operate in the background but to
live with the breathing to live in the present moment here with this this kind of proof that we're alive and present
and and um at times I feel so grateful to be breathing it's uh you know it's
why not see it as a gift that we're offered all this oxygen from the trees and the plants that produce it and uh
isn't it a gift that when we no longer need it there's this kind of the carbon
dioxide we have a system a way of shedding it so it doesn't build up and poison us and um and so to sit here with
appreciation and gratitude and to sit with appreciation for being able to do
this practice uh even when uh it's Challen alling even when I'm challenging
uh in doing the practice where my my I'm caught up in trying to do something or measuring myself or such
things I feel so fortunate to have the practice of mindfulness which I'm confident is a path to Freedom a path to
this ease of breathing as um so the way that I've
introduced it this week is to not emphasize staying so much you know one
pointedly on the breath just not just stay on the breath without wandering off
but rather to offer you a kind of wider context of being mindful of the ecology
around thinking the the forces of distraction and learning how to fold
them in in a way that maybe brings us into the breathing in a simpler way
rather than uh kind of tightening up to over override the distracted mind um learning
to relax the body in the mind that uh the more distracted we are uh probably
it represents more some kind of tension in the mind in the body maybe in the
heart uh something that's holding on some tightness or some contraction or
some zeroing in on something and so this uh learning how
these pieces work and learning to relax and and um and not override how we are
but learning to appreciate that mindfulness just recognizing how we are in any given moment and and to know that
in a very simple way without uh judging without criticizing without being for or
against and then to um as we as we go um
but further at some point there is a kind of centering ourselves on breathing and being able to stay with uh breathing
over time and and over time might mean three breaths and just that might be
enough because it's enough for interrupting what is often non-stop
which is this the mental stream of thinking the rumination that the the
preoccupations of the mind which when they run wild more often than not are
not so healthy for us and so to have something that interrupts it that uh
that doesn't allow it to just kind of build its build up and do more and more and that's one of the functions of
breathing even coming coming back and just feeling one breath fully is an
interruption in the freedom in which the distractability can operate in
us and um and then be content with that one breath be content with three breaths
the three breath Journey that I said yesterday it's so useful and um I will often have a kind
of in nature now as I go through my day to uh to be in touch with my breathing
and see how it shifts and changes and sometimes when my breathing changes and
gets tight or shallow it's the early warning system for me that oh now I'm
getting tense I'm getting reactive to something and because uh this wonderful
close relationship in breathing and our attitudes and emotions and motivations that uh staying with the
um breathing is uh is a way then to kind of relax just come back and relax and
not give into um the Mind streams so I want to offer you a u
metaphor or an image for how to practice one-pointedness on breathing it's such a
classic idea in meditation to have a one-pointed focus on breathing and uh really stay present for it
and um and the the image of doing it then it may in often times in an unhelpful way is um if this if this uh
upright finger is the is the breathing and the my my other hand here
is the mind and if I think I have to focus and be one-pointed I've had a lot
of experience of getting tense and kind of pulling everything in and being kind of tense and focusing on it like this
and this this movement like this to be one pointed this way is um uh creates
tension and I've even at at times when I was younger got headaches from doing
this um rather uh Relax The Mind soften the
thinking mind and let it in a sense feel like it's open no no tension in it at
all and then with a mind more like an open hand bring the breathing and the
mind together together right at the middle sign at the place where if you do it with finger here it comes to the most
sensitive part of the hand for me so sensitive right there at the middle of the
palm and then to stay and so that one point is right by where these touch the
one point is not by by narrowing and and and
um and piercing it's by touch touching and feeling in this most sensitive part
of the hand and then with time sometimes I start tightening up but I've learned
to pay attention to that movement and then to relax and to feel and then as
this uh one pointedness right at this most sensitive place um pulls my
attention or I allow for it and enter into that world then it
um it um the rest of everything else begins to Fall Away the room Falls away
the sounds around me the sometimes even the body seems to fall away and thoughts
fall away and things get very simple uh in this right in that little place just
there being with it so um so one of the things you might try with mindfulness of breathing is
these what I've offered in meditation today this attitude of receiving on the
inhale and allowing on the exhale this is a a way of learning to keep the Mind
very open like when you receive something in an open hand when you allow something to be free same gesture with
the open hand so open mind the Fist of the mind gets
opened and with that openness um and you almost don't have to
go go to the breathing um yeah let the breathing find
awareness um there's no need to move the mind and have the Mind move to and focus on the
breathing um breathing will come to you if you're open and are receptive to it
if you set your mind you know if you open uh you know the window when a day
when there's a breeze the breeze will find its way in through the window if you open your
awareness to welcome the breathing the breathing will find you
and then so that way the mind doesn't do this doesn't Focus doesn't kind of have
to work so much it's more of a allowing and then
um and then uh the mind will wander off and um be aware of that that's not a
problem for mindfulness just one more thing to know and what's important for meditation
is not how often you wander off but how often you begin again on the breathing
and I say this in a very Choice way to begin again the breathing as opposed to
um uh bring your mind back to the breathing the the idea of bringing it
back for many people can be this tightening up and this kind of tension
but uh to begin again with the breathing the mind doesn't have to do anything it just opens and allows and makes that
connection here and then we stay with it and then maybe if it's helpful to use
Mental noting and I like to think of it as the simp absolutely the most relaxed
simple non forceful non-ex expecting a mental note that kind of opens the
fields almost like an each notice invitation feel this more fully
in out so
um so I hope that what I've taught this week about
breathing uh is maybe not easy to do but maybe has made you curious to experiment
and look into it and pay more attention to breathing in daily life pay more attention breathing
as you wake up in the morning as you lay down to go to sleep um as you eat as
you're in conversation with people um kind of make breathing kind of a theme
them and get wiser and more knowledgeable familiar with how your breathing
works for some people mindfulness of breathing doesn't work very well and um
so this week might not have worked so well for those of you who that's the case and there's no nothing you know
wrong with that um uh there are perfectly good other ways of meditating without using the breath and I'll talk
about some of those next week when I do mindfulness of the body and um and that
will include a little bit of mindfulness of listening which is one of or mindfulness of the body itself that
those two can be a nice alternative for some people for people for whom the breathing doesn't work very well as an
object so thank you very much and uh I
hope you have a that you some of you will have a breathing weekend and um
uh and um and you'll come to enjoy your breathing thank
you