so welcome to IMC for all of you who are here in person and welcome those of you
who are online and um as Hillary said um when we
finish here we'll have a uh as usual the Second Sunday of the month there's a tea
or kind of social time to hang out to have tea and chat and then at um 11:30
those of you like to stay will have uh the beginning of the year Refuge ceremony
where we uh chant the refuges I'll talk a little bit about refuges and the precepts and we'll chant the refuges and
precepts together and and it'll include a um a uh what's called a refuge cord
that like I have here in my wrist little red cord you tie on your wrist or some people put it around their neck and um
and so that'll be given to you and and U so if you want to stay for that ceremony you're welcome to stay and and um
so so for the talk so it's uh the custom
for me at the first Dharma Talk of the Year here at IMC to talk about the four
noble truths and this is my first full Dharma talk here and I found myself uh quite
happy walking down here today thinking about this is the topic and um so you
know it's a a little bit of a paradox to be happy to be talking about
suffering so uh because it's such a deep part of the Buddhist tradition this Four
Noble Truths some people say it's really at the heart of it um I want to uh just
maybe for my sake just say um the the central words of the for Noble Truths in
poly and then say them in English and then give a talk about it
so in poly uh it's um
Dua samudaya nirod and Dua
nirod so in English I translate this as suffering the first Noble Truth arising
the arising of suffering the second Noble Truth the
cessation the cessation of suffering the third Noble Truth and then the practice
leading to the cessation of suffering and
um the um and there's many so these four noble truths are both
a teaching and a practice and as such especially since there there a teaching that's meant to
be practiced and practice is very personal and each of us it's our task to
understand the teachings and practice and personalize it in sense understand how it applies to us and our
circumstance our life and how it can support us and so there's many different
uh meanings of the Four Noble Truths there many as there are people here today there's that many
meetings or applications of them and um and so they're quite Rich
what they can be understood in many levels and ways and what I like to do today uh is to talk about three levels
of understanding the four the four noble truths and um and so there're kind of
more the Mind level the Heart level and the belly level so we'll go through take
you through this and they all work together that's one is not supposed to be better than the other but they
integrate together so U there was a um Buddhist
monk at the time of the Buddha who came to the Buddha complaining that uh he had not uh
demonstrated any Miracles and then any self-respecting Guru maybe back there in ancient times
was supposed to kind of demonstrate Guru Miracles because that was somehow proof of something
wonderful and uh the Buddhist basically said well I don't do this and not for this
purpose and uh at some point point this monk disrobed because he was so
discouraged in the Buddha the Buddha did say when he asked for miracles he said did did I ever tell you to become a monk
in order to become for the sake of Miracles and he said
no and um so anyway at some point it was it was so discouraging for this monk
that he disrobed and then he went went to town went to city and he was going around
disparaging the Buddha and he would uh tell the town's people that all the
Buddha teaches is the end of suffering and um and so the news of this
came back to the Buddha and uh and he said even though he's thinks he's disparaging me he's actually praising
me so you know it's that you know the the end of suffering is really the heart
of Buddhism and there might be other worthwhile Endeavors in life and there might be other worthwhile
spiritual experiences attainments to had in this life but uh from a Buddhist
point of view um uh don't short Change
yourself around suffering really get to the bottom to the heart of suffering and
bring it to an end uh and don't let other experiences other attainments come distract from
this fundamentally Deep thing and if anything let let these other possib
abilities if they're important for you let them uh be the cream on the cake and the cake is this wonderful
thing this phenomenal thing the peace the well-being The Joy the happiness that can come when uh we're free of
suffering and that's where the and knowing this is possible is a happiness producing
thing so many years ago when I was a news end student I knew a u an other's
end student who was a um uh stained
glass artist and that's not really important part of the story but she
um she had very bad knees and she was uh supposed to get
knee surgery I think knee Replacements and um but what she did was
she started paying very careful attention to her knees and the pain in
their knees and by tracking the pain the slightest little ache slightest
little something that felt off she started walking differently and and
slowly the pain and her challenge around her knees went away and she didn't have
surgery so so I'm not maybe that sounds like a miracle story but it's a story of someone who
paid really careful attention to pain really gave rather than trying to
avoid it or trying to fix it in some kind of medical way which sometimes necessary but but uh and I was really
struck by that that wow that that was the first time I met someone who used
pain as a teacher as a guide and that really you know you know taught me
something deep and as a result of this uh she decided to become a doctor and
applied for medical school and was accepted and I lost touch of her touch with her but
um um I thought this is fantastic that someone like this is a
doctor so um and then I have a friend who was many
years ago who was teaching mindfulness-based stress reduction a wonderful uh protocol that comes out of
this practice and out of Buddhism in America and was applied clinically to
people with first in hospital settings people with mostly acute pain and when uh when uh the medical
world couldn't really help them with their pain and and had adop adopted this kind of pra adapted this practice so
that it could address people's pain otherwise couldn't be helped and um they had a high Su success
rate partly because they screened people to be mo who were motivated but my friend was teaching it
here in small City most small town here in California and probably there was no screening for high
motivation and or something but uh there was this um he as
he described it this really um maybe it's not fair to describe it this way but Burly
Macho older police officer who had a lot of
back pain that was not helped by Medicine by doctors and uh so he came to he was
assigned by the doctor you should do take this 8we mindfulness base of course and uh so they came to the first
lesson and my friend was teaching it and then and gave the instructions uh pay uh
bring your attention to the pain and uh and the guy got
Furious I'm here to not experience the pain not to feel it and he left and he
never came back so one person that there you know the first person focused on the pain and
found a way out of it the other person ignored the pain and well certainly
wasn't helped that way maybe he found some other way then later here in
Buddhism we want to be wise about our pain and when the time is right it's
really important to be honest about it and to face it and to study it to be
present for it and I use the word pain purposefully because the the mean the
word Dua which is the poly word that's usually translated as suffering in our
circles literally means pain and it kind of has a little different feeling if you think of it as pain but it's used to
apply to the deepest existential sufferings we have and the deepest emotional sufferings and the slightest
little irritations we have the whole range everything you know things that are a
pain and um and I've certainly uh considered that my com my laptop is a
pain and uh and you know it's not literally a
physical pain uh and the laptop is not causing me anything for me to blame the
laptop for that pain is uh is to miss
what's you know my responsibility my role my frustration my attachments my desires my you know you know all kinds
of things going on in me so if I spend my whole day kind of
blaming my computer shaking it throwing it against the wall hoping to get you
know yelling at it you know whatever the computer is not going to care it's not going to listen to that and I might even
break it but if I don't want to stop suffering I have to stop blaming the computer I
have to take a good look at myself and I have to feel that pain feel that discomfort and really get to know it
really study it and find out what's going on and find out what I'm doing that's extra what's not needed what's my
responsibility what's my role in that what I call the computer is a pain that
would be the way so in Buddhism the four noble truths are a call for us to be
honest that there is suffering in this world there's suffering in ourselves
there suffering in others and some people get so happy when they hear that Buddhism teaches this because they grew
up in a situation in circumstances maybe family maybe communities where there was
a lot of avoiding of suffering a lot of uh pretending it wasn't
there uh and they were very confused they felt like there's all this suffering your suffering my family
suffering people are suffering but no one's admitting it everyone's putting on a smile everyone's being distracted all
the time and and you know this doesn't seem right to live in this kind of
sometimes that some people have reported to be a lie this avoidance of
it and then they come to Buddhism and they hear um this say yes there's
suffering categorically yes there's suffering there's no we don't want to avoid it we want to name it we want to
say it's here it's it's part and parcel of The Human Condition it's completely part of it and
so much so that one of the orientations that we have in Buddhism is to
understand that we don't have to take it so personally um it is personal in a way
that you know the the the pain of the computer is personal you know I'm I'm involved with that causing that pain but
it's just so human to have this frustration it's such a common phenomena that we're maybe built in certain ways
to have frustration and pain and suffering and grief and and these kinds
of things that there's a kind of way in which we can be honest about it and begin studying it but not identify it
too much closely not to Define ourselves by it this is who I am or this is this
is being done to me or something but rather what we do is we begin to look at
suffering and stop so that my bumper stiner if I had one was I stop for
suffering and um and theya okay let's take a look at this let's really be with it this emotional pain that we have with
and then what we're doing partly here in Buddha in Buddhist practice is learning how to do this in a wise way it's not
easy to be with our suffering it's not easy to be with um The Suffering that
you know conventionally and reasonably we say it's been caused by the world around us people grow up in war zones
and there war zones are a pain and uh and to say well you know you
got to look at yourself the bombs are going off and look at your frustration look at your fear you know uh that's uh
you know disrespectful it's harmful to do that so we want to be very careful
about the time and place but at some point sooner or later we have to turn
and look inside and for some people who have known uh there clearly was conventional
causes of it in the external world but at some point all that was left for them
to do do was to look at themselves that was the only way forward uh I known people who thought
they were dying and the conditions outside that were causing them to die were clearly outside of themselves but
at some point they just uh realized this is I'm I give up remember one man who told me this
many years ago was in the mountains and caught in an
avalanche and um under layers of snow or something and um and at some point he
realized I'm going to die here no one knows I'm here or something and um and
uh and when he let go when he admitted this and kind of really saw it um you know he wasn't blaming the
snow uh he he experienced this profound peace and then he says a strange thing
happened that um at some point my arm punched upwards and he broke through the
snow and then he was rescued but uh that was life-changing
for him to have this profound letting go that happened because he thought he was
dying so when we really when we finally ready to stop and look at our suffering
in a deep way is uh is a is something we need to consider well and one of the
purposes of medit meditation in Buddhism and mindfulness practice and love mean kindness practices and concentration
practice is to provide us with the inner resources the inner stamina the inner
skills the inner strengths so that we can really turn towards our suffering in
a useful and meaningful way we can turn towards it to find the freedom from it
and find our way through it and some people are ready for that right away some people are ready for that after a
while of practice but this this idea yes there is suffering
here and then a very special thing happens and that is uh that at some
point when we don't take the suffering personally in some kind of attached way
when we don't uh stop blaming the world outside of us when we stop complaining
when we stop to really take a good look at some point the way that we look
becomes the secret becomes the treasure to be able to see and recognize
suffering without attachments without identification without resistance to
have a a Clarity of seeing where in the seeing there's kind of a freedom in the
seeing there's a kind of the Delight maybe can exist sometimes on a clear day
Blue Sky day and the windshield reir got
completely clean you think you can put your hand through it it's so clear and so nice maybe after a long time of
having smudge and so to have your ability to oh
this is this is suffering this is my suffering with that kind of clarity with
that kind of ease and lack of clinging this provides a very different reference
point for how to go forward in life how where the where the freedom is found
that freedom is possible it's possible not to be defined by the suffering it's
possible not to have the challenges and difficulties of our life which can be huge it's possible to have them not be a
burden we carry they have things we have to address but they don't have to be
addressed as a burden as a drag as a wind drag so the four noble truths
are suffering which we want to turn toward and know and understand
deeply there's the literal word of the second Noble Truth is the arising of suffering is really to be present for
the appearance of it but often it's called the cause of
suffering and uh and then the third Noble Truth is the
cessation of the suffering cessation of the cause and then the fourth Noble Truth is
the practi is sometimes called the path of practice the practices which lead to
that so um and and and are a result of
that so the three levels first is the mind the mind is a little more the
cognitive level and that's where we can uh study the cause of suffering and this
is a brilliant thing to do that uh to understand that suffering is not just
Without a Cause to understand that suffering is not just something that we have to live with because it's inherent
in human existence and there's no no possibility of changing it but the sufferings we have when we're able to
see the particularity of it we'll see that it always has a
cause and uh and sometimes the cause is external and sometimes we can address the external cause if it's appropriate
sometimes we can't address the external cause but what we're trying to do in Buddhist practice is to take
responsibility for our contribution to our emotional
pain and uh chances are uh often there's
a contribution you make even if 90% of it comes externally from external cause
the 10% that you contribute that's what the contri that's the part of it that you probably have the most ability to
change sometimes it's it's hard to change the external world and make it you know behave
properly and uh but maybe you can do something about yourself and that's
where kind of the you know the the work of Buddhism kind of really is is uh at
at its heart so one of those things is to look what are the cause and one of
the fascinating uh ways of understanding their suffering and the cause of
suffering is to switch it around by by realizing that in Buddhism the cause is
always SE to be a certain kind of thirsting for something and they use the
word thirst in the ancient language so it's kind of a metaphor the C it's a metaphor to
describe the cause and so it's for you to fill out the metaphor what does it apply but usually people who want to be
more lit more kind of not so metaphorical will uh translate it as
craving sometimes as clinging the there's some kind of
compulsion of thirsting a compulsion of craving that goes on so sometimes I like
to translate as compulsion because it has a life of its own you can't drop it E le like it's sometimes that compulsion
craving thirsting has taken over and now we're addicted now we're driven now
we're kind of no wonder we can't end our suffering because there's this powerful drive that keeps it going so the cause
is to look at that drive to look at that cause so to turn these uh first and
second Noble Truths around I like to say if you
cling you will suffer or to another way if you want the
bumper sticker um uh clinging is
suffering craving is suffering compulsion addiction is
suffering and so to look so the to to looking at the cause then is to look on
where is my compulsion where is my drivenness where's my what am I attached to here because as soon as I get
attached then we're fragile as soon as we're attached we're stuck as soon as
we're attached we're contracted and and and we start contributing stress to our
whole psychophysical system I think I would probably suggest
I've never done the statistics but I would say that probably
90% of human stress has its Genesis in
in uh this clinging thirsting compulsion of the mind and um and you know maybe I'm wrong
about the exact percentage um maybe more of it is maybe less of it is but it's a it's a I think
a very significant statement to make that 90% is has a birth in are
clinging because uh then if when you feel stress don't blame the world take a look
at yourself what can be done and people who meditate a lot will find often that
meditation is one of those things that can quiet calm relax the mind and as the
mind gets relaxed the physical stresses we carry begin to settle away
and you after a while it becomes a very clear connection what goes on in the mind causes physical stress causes the
headache that I'm having detention headaches and
um so to look at the cause is what the mind can do the mind is bright sometimes
it's clear uh the your mind only has to be as intelligent as it actually is you
don't have to have any more because whatever ever intelligence you have um
that's the intelligence uh that uh brought you your
suffering and so that's enough intelligence to find your freedom from it so just be happy you know it's not
like it's you know you can do it and once we see our suffering is born
from clinging it isn't that we can let go of it easily which is a third Noble truth but there's practices we can do
that support rep us prepare us for the day it can something can be released and
let go and so these are ethical practices living in ethical life is Central to this there are practices that
where we begin paying attention to our mind and begin training our mind to be able to be focused and mindful and clear
and see what's going on and there are practices of intentionality of purpose and there's
practices of of focusing choosing to focus F us on the perspective to be oriented
towards uh suffering and the end of it so the second uh level so this is
more the Mind level which is very helpful is to drop down deeper into the
heart and for the heart to register your
suffering and one of the surprises for me in doing Buddhist practice was I in
the beginning of practice I suffered a lot lot every meditation session was a
session of suffering but I I kind of was I was given with the practice I was
taught in Zen was a practice of just sit with your experience don't do anything about it and that worked out really well
for me because I I didn't complicate it with analysis I didn't complicate it
with fixing and what happened slowly that as I relaxed and settled into my
suffering my heart awoke up it was kind of like I had uh the
meditation was the like meat tenderizer for my heart I had this crust hard crust around
it and it began to soften and soften and at some point what awoke in me was
compassion and I was able to meet my suffering with compassion to meet it with love and care
and to soften and meet it and the capacity to to be open to suffering and
allow it to to meet it with compassion with care not with anger not with
resistance not with fear but with this beautiful quality of the heart
compassion so the second phase of noble of the four of the Four Noble Truths is
um again you have to turn towards it and allow yourself to not just study it and
feel it and analyze it maybe even you want to stop that because that gets in the way at some point from allowing
yourself to feel what's going on in some deeper way feel below the reactivity you have
or maybe you have to feel the reactivity as part of the complex of suffering to really make room for you to allow
yourself to be how you are warts and
all suffering at all and just learn to breathe with it and make space for it
and not try to fix it not try to make it go away just be patient with it and and
and this beautiful thing can happen where the heart can meat it maybe you
can't it's too hard for you to do but your heart has the capacity this
emotional Center that I call the heart it's a wise part of us it's part of our
deeper I would say subconscious just operating M milon kind of there's always
mamillion um functions that we share with other mammals of care for their
young and care for others and these beautiful stories of animals will come
to the rescue of humans I'm particularly fond of the dolphin ones when people are
kind of drowning at Sea and the dolphin will come and carry them and um and I like the stories of
you know Predators taking care of their prey sometimes if occasionally you hear the stories like you a lion is helping a
deer or something but at least they take care of their young usually and so this
mamillion so it's something more than just kind of just the what we think we are but something deeper and built into
our genes almost maybe and so this capacity to feel suffering and let the
heart respond and you'll be surprised how much the heart knows how to process this and be with it and the benefits
will come and then we have the third level and then we and I like thinking of these
you're going deeper and deeper to yourself and I call it the belly in Buddhism it's sometimes called the
source the literal uh meaning the word in P is Yoni and sometimes that's
translated as womb but it doesn't quite mean womb it means like the The Source where something is born so like the the
egg is the Yi for the chicken they don't you know they don't have wombs I suppose
they have the eggs and then there are things that are water born in Buddhism and so that's their Yoni so the
source and um so to drop down to some deep place where there's something
that's operating within us a knowing a way of thinking a way of perceiving a way of
feeling a a a creativity an intelligence that's has more an emergent
quality where it's something that's emerging from deep inside as opposed to something that's coming from the the
usual maybe uh thinking mind egotistical mind self-centered mind that's I have to
do something I'm happen to me that's a kind of eye that's usually caught up in
its own little drama kind of dissolves as we drop down and we're not trying to
make something happen but we're beginning to allow something to happen and the difference between making and
allowing and so they're dropping really deep down and what happens there was we
we have have an opportunity now to allow all experiences to just be there without
interfering with them and without overlaying our judgments and our
Concepts and our stories on top of our experience this is a phenomenal thing to
do to quiet the projections we have on life it's a very wonderful thing to do
for your friends to quiet your projections and be able to see others and you know
unfiltered by all the bias we might have or projections or preferences or
something but to do it for ourselves and and towards ourself and
then be there in the rawness of the present moment experience
the place where because we're allowing things to unfold things are appearing and
disappearing they're coming and going and this is where the meaning of the second double truth being arising the
word samoda means to the arising now we see the appearing the coming and going
of our suffering we see the rawness of it just like we see the uh Surfer sees
the coming and going of the waves and the surfer doesn't get attached to any one wave you know it's just that's just
the wave of the moment and um and so but and and in that is able to ride the wave
sometimes so to ride the experiences that are coming and going within us to be very close to see to feel to
experience that in the moment a moment experience the rawness of experience there's more than just suffering there's
also in the moments there's also the ending of suffering there's a coming and
going the appearing and disappearing nothing is static nothing is constant
nothing is stuck and that's the advantage of dropping down to this deep emerging
place is to find the way of being unstuck where everything is flowing and
Buddhism uses a lot has a lot of references to the the metaphor of a
river where everything is flowing and most people have been to the river with
a bucket or two or a thousand and they scooped up the water
in their buckets and they go around saying look I have the river and it's my
River you don't have the river anymore if you have a bucket full of water if we
cling we've lost the flow of the River of Life and so drop down to the place
where the River of Life is flowing and us the coming and going the rising and passing the
the the ups and downs of the waves of thoughts and feelings emotions
clinging and to experience there the gaps the gaps when we're not thinking
thoughts the gaps where we're not in our anger the gaps where we're
not in our craving and desires the gaps where we're not holding on or resisting
the gaps where we see oh there's a peace here there's a freedom
here there's a well-being here and to begin then seeing that and relaxing
seeing that and letting go seeing that and kind of allowing this emergent
possibility of peace to show itself at such a point where the theoda
the sensation of suffering is not a letting go we're not doing doing it but
the sensation of suffering the third Noble Truth is a profound
releasing that you can't take credit for it's a something deep releases
inside of something something deep and lets go and
then this belly this Source this imerg and quality within us begins to have a
greater life in for us and that this is part of the Great
potential that we have that Buddhist practice is supposed to bring us to it can bring us to is this point where the
release is strong enough that there begins to
emerge the eful path whereas the eful path is not so
much practice as we do anymore but rather a state of Life state of being
that we begin to make room for and live by more and more so if we're not practicing ethics we become ethical and
ethics doesn't become a choice but rather it's an expression of the freedom that we
have mindfulness is uh not no longer something we have to do but it feels
more like something we allow for it's like part and parcel of who we are in the Deep emergent way even concentration
can feel like it's not something we have to do and strain for but it's more a letting go and allowing of something to
settle and then um uh the other aspects of the eful path all that are these
emerging qualities and something begins to grow within us or we start to kind of really feel
like we're flowing in a river that's moving through us and going
through so Four Noble Truths
they're invaluable teachings they're more than
teachings they're a framework to explore our life it's an
orientation the perspective with which to step into to see ourselves in a new
way to not see ourselves through the usual Concepts that Society wants us to
live by but to see our eles through the through the framework of our
suffering the cause of it or more deeply where how it
arises to see the end of it the letting go of it the cessation of it and to understand that there are
practices to engage in practices and states to allow for that really allow
for this freedom and joy and happiness to become part of of our life this is
the four noble truths of the Buddha and
um and it's a happy thing so don't get so happy that you
don't don't get too happy so you don't look at the
suffering but maybe get happy enough that you're say okay I'm ready to take a
good look at this suffering now be honest be present for it
so thank you and um so in a few minutes we'll I
guess there has to be some setup still for the tea and so maybe if uh you're
planning to stay for the tea or not uh if you'd be willing to turn to a couple of people next to you and say hello and
welcome them to IMC and even if it's your first time welcome them and maybe there's something about
this talk that touched you you might share it with them or at least break the ice so you know somebody here be if you
want to stay for the team so thank you