so my friends I think that uh we
have
sound and we
um so you have sound and you have a
picture and yeah so that took
uh a long time to figure it out so we
had various problems here there was uh
the LA turned out out that the laptop oh
I'm
echoing
um yeah so the problems were that
somehow someone was here yesterday and
disconnected the
laptop and so all kinds of things were
disconnected and then somehow the all
the settings for the broadcast uh
platform we have Were Somehow scrambled
and so to understand the broadcast
system and uh a new
was uh you know I haven't gone that
deeply into it
before so um so here we
are and
uh U was trying to figure out what how
Gil got to choose an
osprey the Osprey is a
um is
a a bridge device
that connects the video camera from the
video camera to the
computer and um and
so
[Music]
so I don't think now in these next few
minutes I want to try to start up again
in the theme that I did last uh but I
think what I'll do is um finish this
five-part series on
Monday uh with the fourth Noble Truth
and then uh next week I was going to do
um the four the noble truths of
Happiness this is what we did this
week's the noble truths of
suffering and maybe that works really
well because then I don't won't won't do
an introductory uh Monday I would just
start on Tuesday with uh the
four noble truths of happiness which is
not a not a tech a um Buddhist concept I
just made it up but it's a building on
Buddhist teachings to offer the other
side of uh the four noble
truths because in fact as much as it's
important in Buddhism to study suffering
understand suffering enter through go
through suffering it's also it's equally
important to understand happiness
and to enter into happiness and even in
a certain way go through to the other
side of happiness and what would that be
the other side of Happiness it's not
suffering it's something even better
than suffering than than even happiness
so we'll do that next
week and uh and I'm very aware that uh
we
have
um the
international national and maybe local
challenges of all kinds and some of them
are very local to individual people of
you
all and um and uh in my own way I'm
trying
to uh address these things for all of us
offer support through these teachings
and it maybe not not uh in a direct way
but in an indirect
way and uh I'll continue to do that for
a while problem
so um thank you very much and I see that
there are you know I can read the chats
and you know maybe if there's a a single
question that someone wants to ask about
the the topic of this week or something
um I can try to uh say a few words for
you uh before we stop at
7:45 and
um so it was very nice to be with you in
this few minutes to finally get it
working and
um
so it's very nice to see your names
and I saw earlier I saw on the other
laptop I did see that the people were on
even though the camera wasn't working
and that's I was glad to see that the
YouTube channel at least was on and
um
so well what's the fourth the fourth
Noble Truth is the Noble Truth to the
end of suffering and it's a it's the U
it's the path of practice that uh has
this wonderful dual nature that it's
both the uh the path that uh that uh
leads to the end of suffering but it's
also the path that uh emerges with the
end of
suffering and so that this dual nature
is quite quite fascinating and uh so
I'll talk a little bit about that next
week and
uh some teachers say suffering is
unavoidable and sometimes they can be
ended are these two different types of
suffering that's a good question uh um
the
uh uh I think that in ordinary human
life um uh one way or the other people
are going to suffer and that it doesn't
mean non-stop but sooner or later we
have all kinds of things and the is the
the art of it or the the challenge of it
is uh to understand what is optional
suffering and what is the emotional pain
that just comes with being human being
that we can learn to not send any second
arrows
to that we can uh just uh see as um part
of human life that we have to accept um
sickness old age and death is inevitable
part of the world and it is a kind of
suffering uh perhaps or but um but it's
not uh the suffering that arises from
clinging and craving and so really the
formable truths is
addressing uh the optional Suffering The
Suffering that we contribute to the
second third fourth 100th arrows we add
to our
life and uh and so you have to always
kind of uh and and the idea that's this
word Dua suffering is uh means different
things in different contexts is uh goes
back to the time of the Buddha and uh so
we have to uh appreciate that that um
and they have that you know you know
which type of suffering are Dharma
teachers talking about when they say
that it's
unavoidable and which kind of suffering
are they talking about that is avoidable
that that can come to an end and um and
in the classic teachings and maybe I'll
talk about this next week uh in fact all
suffering can come to a phenomenal end
um uh with a uh um but that even that is
temporary because some of the
unavoidable sufferings of Being Human
will return later uh as our bodies get
older and creakier and
achier it's possible to go into these
deep states of meditation and have that
disappear and then returns when we come
out of those
States so but uh the emotional suffering
the emotional the optional emotional
pain that we are responsible for that
can come to a complete end and that
doesn't have to return um and so that's
why it's possible to go through life's
challenges with much more ease and peace
when our contributions to it don't cause
us to be
agitated uh so um thank you
for showing up today and for hopefully
being patient with the challenges here
and uh so I'll plan to pick this up on
Monday thank you very much