so hello everyone and
welcome so the what I'd like
to suggest today is that uh we focus the
meditation
on uh Faith meditation supported by
faith and Faith sometimes is seen as being extremely religious
uh phenomena emotion motivation and maybe it
is but rather than thinking of it it's something that we can't experience and know and something not relevant to
exactly here and now the faith I propose is the faith and the
practice and uh we call on faith to to practice here with a little bit of kind of
analysis we could or orientation we could think of many of us spend much of
the day having faith in the wrong things that whatever your mind is
preoccupied with that is something that you or your mind has faith in that it's
valuable to do so it's purposeful to do so it's and we put a lot of faith into
sometimes fantasy sometimes planning sometimes remembering and
reviewing and we have put Faith in desires for things we have faith in aversion in things and to put our faith
in those things uh sure changes us it limits
us and instead when we put Faith in the
practice we are making room and space for something within us something that's
unlimited something which is not defined by Me Myself and mind something that can
grow and expand and develop and be creative and uh and be
freeing and the simplest way of saying what the faith is when we practice is we
have faith in being awake and I use this word carefully
because instead of saying faith in being mindful faith of being aware um to be awake is a in in a in a
sense it doesn't refer to an activity that we do but a state that we are in we
can be sleeping at night then in the morning we wake up and we're awake then
it's just the quality of a characteristic of being somewhat maybe clear somewhat um maybe uh conscious
somewhat uh there's a present for our experience and but without putting any
restrictions on anything without uh having to focus on
something it just being awake in the midst of what this life of ours and to have faith in being awake
and reason why this is so significant is that
um an awareness an alertness a presence that um doesn't restrict anything
doesn't interfere with anything doesn't reinforce anything
uh doesn't reinforce the unhealthy activities of our mind and it makes room
for some profoundly deep healthy activities of the mind it makes room for
healing it makes room for settling makes room for uh
uniting unification of all we are it makes room for growth and development
that we can't engineer so to have faith in being
awake and as we sit uh for this sitting maybe
um you can just very gently gingerly tenderly use the word
awake maybe each time you
exhale or maybe at the beginning of the inhale but say the word with faith in
the value of being having a living
awareness living attention to this
moment as if you're making room for whatever is
there without reinforcing
anything without participating in thoughts and desires and
aversions where being awake is bigger wider than anything any involvement with
anything where there's room for what is healthy to grow and develop and do its
work awake so assuming a meditation
posture that may maybe has a little intentionality in
it that encourages a a
wakefulness if you're sitting upright maybe your spine
can be a little bit more alert if you're sitting in a chair
laying laying back into the back rest even so you
might readjust slightly so you're a little bit more
alert in your spine and if you're laying
down maybe there too you can adjust the shoulder blades so that they are a
little bit more maybe roll and kind of slide down the
back providing a stronger flatter surface for supporting your upper
back and maybe such a way that your chest maybe comes out a little
bit closing your eyes
relaxing on the
exhales relaxing in your body
relaxing in your mind
and then with some regular intervals maybe coordinated with the
breathing or maybe not gently almost as a whisper almost as
of a ever so light Breeze almost as if you're not saying
anything maybe it's a not even a
nonverbal knowing say or know the word
awake as if something in your whole mental and physical
systems knows what that is recognizes
that the word awake awakens being
awake a wakefulness in which your present moment
experience of body of
breathing of mind is known is revealed
without any restrictions or judgments or
participation with the word awake reminding yourself
of having faith deep Faith full
faith inner
attention that gives infinite room for all things to be in the present
without participating with any of
it
for
e
for for
remembering
to be
awake and being awake is similar to
making Infinite Space around
everything so that what needs to settle can settle
relax and what is healthy and good can grow or
expand independent of you making anything
happen except remembering to be
awake
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to tap into once more what Within
Comes Alive around the word word
awake to be
awake to wake
up to awaken a sense
of living attention in the present
moment an attention that maybe is connected to a sense of
Vitality even if we're sick or tired there is evidence of being alive
in every Sensation that we
have and to be awake is to make lots of room give breathing room to
everything deep faith that we don't have to fix
or do or make happen we can
allow something deeper to awaken as we stay
awake Awakening from our
depths and then to include and
in our wakefulness other people other living
beings where we give Infinite Space and room for them to be just as they
are easier to do if if we allowed ourselves to be that
way and we don't allow anything to diminish us ourselves
and in this field of relating this related
relatedness to others in the in being
awake may we spread our good will our compassion our
care may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you for
so hello everyone and welcome to this third talk as I
continue for the second week um conveying trying to convey some
of the core teachings that underly my orientation my perspective as
a Buddhist teacher and it's uh building on what I said last
week so it's part two of the same topics and
um so today it's uh the uh my my
teachings are based on a very strong naturalistic orientation and um and what I mean by
naturalistic is that um it's in the world of our direct experience things we
can know for ourselves we can experience for
ourselves that uh we don't have to uh explain things with things that we
can't really know or can't really discover uh so the supernatural World
which is such a big part of religion often and Buddhism as well um uh not to
dismiss that or say that it's wrong or not true it's just not the orientation of how I
teach it's almost like I put those that aside as if it's not something we have
to address or deal with for this path of Liberation path of practice for uh
living a life of compassion and love and
um so this naturalistic uh approach um
can be explained a little bit as uh as is pointing out that in the early Buddhist teaching it's it appears that
the Buddha when he taught without saying it in this kind of modern way uh uh uh presented the human being
as having two separate operating systems that uh are not really
comparable or not not equal or uh not
but they're operating it's almost like apples and oranges they being very different from each other so
the one of them the one that is uh so there's a wholesome one and the UNH
wholesome one and the uh UNH wholesome uh operating system is the one that is
founded on Greed hate and delusion and greed hate and delusion are I think of
as as deep as they might seem in a human being they're much more surface reactions to things and um and uh they
engage our surface muscles our surface thoughts our engagement and our uh often
they engage our uh ideas and Concepts and conceits of self Me Myself and mine
what I want what who I am um that is kind of an overlay on top of a broader
wider experience of what it is to be a human being so uh the uh this operating system
that's founded on Greed hate and delusion is uh also one that constructs
Engineers so it uh imagines and thinks about things and builds up stories it's
the world of um uh make belief making things up and most of us maybe don't
live in a world that we think of is make believe but um uh I remember reading d
this wonderful novel and um and the um
and you know UNC conventional way Don kyote was living in the world of delusion but it turned out by the end of
the book it would seem that um um everyone else was living in a socially
constructed world of all these rules and behavior and Concepts that people were
navigating that was more delusive than seem seemed normal but more delusive than Don coyote and he had these
fundamentally beautiful values that he was living by that uh raised the question what is what is delusion what
is not delusion and um so this constructed
world of that we live in that we inherit from our society and it has it teaches
us profound things about who we are who we think we are the constructed
self the other operating system of the Buddha is uh can be can be
simplistically called the holistic uh side of it of our life uh it's uh from a
deeper Source within and it's a source of uh of life within of source of
thoughts s source of emotions s source of motivation which is not made up it
doesn't involve a makeup made up World Concepts and constructs does not involve
greated hate and delusion but arises some deeper movements from deep
within and um and um the uh maybe that
they arise from the opposite of greet hi and delusion from um generosity love and
wisdom maybe they arise from uh an organic Source within uh meaning that uh it's something
that we don't construct but something we allow to grow that uh we uh we can build
and construct a house but we cannot build and construct a baby we can allow
the natural abilities of of of gestation
to allow the embryo to grow and develop over time and it's remarkable that this
something that's so much more complex than a house uh can um can become
somehow grow and evolve and develop uh and our uh the task of a mother is to
allow the best conditions for that life to unfold within develop
within so it's not a coincidence that I use this as as the example because one
of the sources of this deeper way of living that the Buddha talks about is he
talks about the yonis which can be the place where life begins and so for
humans that's sometimes considered to be the womb so there's a there's a place where life gestates uh the the uh the
emerges that it um um and uh and from
deep within and that's not constructed and so these two operating
systems have very different ways of relating to it one we we engage in and
fight with and fix and and adjust and and uh the other one we have to get out
of the way for and allow we have to recognize it make room and space and the wonderfulness about the
Dharma practice is that as we were mindful of things as we're awake and
present uh it has uh a different effects on these two systems operating systems
the operating system that is based on Greed hate and delusion is a system that's based on
tension and as we're aware of it and present for it that tends to help the
ention relaxed the system that is the operating system that's
gestational that's emergent um that something that grows
and develops um with the food and nourishment of attention the space of
attention it has more room to grow it is more develop to unfold and develop and
move so attachments tend to move towards
letting go and and uh the Deep wisdom of Awakening
the Deep compassion the Deep uh Faith the Deep equinity the Deep peace grows
and develops The Joy the happiness of practice grows and develops from this deeper
source and um and these two operating system I associate with um the
difference between uh fight and flight and approach and nurture
that um um the fight and flight engages the surface muscles it's a muscular
thing uh approach a nurture uh to nurture and support and tend something
like uh like a gardener tends a plants um that tending uh is something that um
uh is a deeper Instinct a deeper motivation it involves something deeper than our musculature that uh is operating exactly
what that biological source is maybe you know we can have all kinds of speculation but for the Buddha it was um
something that was not of the muscles not of the flesh that was somehow deeper
within so in saying my uh my orientation is naturalistic it's um appreciating
something that's very natural about the human being that is healthy and wonderful and capable of healing and
developing growth um where and one of the things it wants to grow into is a
freedom from the restrictions freedom from the limitations of um of what this uh greed
hate and delusion um operating system provides us that the tension holds Us in
check in some way so um so
um you might consider that uh uh we have you have these two different operating
systems and which of them do you have faith in which of them do you which of
them do you uh feed and support and strengthen over time by participating it
and engaging in it and part of Dharma practice is to have a deep faith in this
natural naturalistic source within us that arises and operates the more the
constructing mind the Conceited the kind of sense of self the Me Myself and mine
um quiets down and makes room for it and it's remarkable how much self-
preoccupation how much self criticism how much self um Concepts that we live under that
um uh we can put down we can have faith we don't have to continue that
way we can let go of the faith we have in me myself and
mine in terms of this preoccupation and and concerns and thinking over and over
again about me as the central character of my drama of my
life to something deeper inside that wants to be emerge that's
growing and um and uh to continue with this metaphor of of you know of U of
human being kind of growing as an embryo within um one of the one of the
wonderful things I experiences I had as a young parent when my kids were young
was just the kind of seemingly natural way in which um I became less important
my own concerns and and my own you know preoccupations with self
fell away for just caring for a young baby I mean sometimes it was quite tired
sometimes there was not a time to take a shower so occasionally I you know I was more I had to take care of the kid
rather than maybe even um you know eating when I was hungry staying up late
at night when the kid was sick um and knowing the next day I'd be tired for
teaching the Dharma um the usual way in which I maybe I've been involved in my
own con concerns kind of fell away and it felt so freeing so wonderful uh to do
that so uh to have faith in this natural operating system that we have
and not have Fai faith in what in this kind of way of talking is
unnatural uh the constructed the imaginary the the uh the um
the make believe that we often live in so thank you very much and
uh and um we'll continue this topic these themes
tomorrow also before we end I meant to do this at the beginning I want to um
just for a moment celebrate with you that this is juneth day and uh so
wonderful holiday because of um any holiday that celebrates Independence and
freedom is a Buddhist holiday and for us as Buddhists to focus on Liberation to
appreciate the the worldly Liberation that's such an important thing that people to have that uh uh that was long
coming for the slaves in America is um a wonderful thing to celebrate and if
you'd like to join us this uh evening at here in California at 6:00 p.m. uh we're
having a um juneth Day celebration by the wonderful uh teacher uh an Roy who
um uh some of you might know she's uh taught for mindfulness Circle for black
practitioners and she's also taught the happy hour so thank you