good evening can we have the volume up just a tiny bit here just so that uh I don't
have to project my voice as much um maybe a tiny tiny tiny bit
more so funny There we go thank
you so I wanted to talk a little bit about
uh this little encounter that the Buddha
describes about before he was awakened when he was just an ordinary person like
us and he encountered some people quarreling just in case you see anything
in the news about quarreling or something
so oh the scene is that um it's between the sakian people and the kelan people
and they had um these irrigation channels that were from the river that
uh formed the boundary between their two regions and one year there was very
little rain so they were quarreling about okay uh what are we going to do
that uh we want all the water no we want the water what are we going to do this is maybe not so
unfamiliar something like this and apparently they were insulting each other and it got so bad that the
different armies were on the two different sides of the river about ready to go to war and the person who was to
become the Buddha he's not the Buddha yet uh shows up and he wants to talk to
them and then uh he describes the impact that it had on them I'm just going to
share with you a little excerpt here it's not the complete um it's inv verse I should say
this is a short little passage that in verse and it goes uh like this just look
at people and their quarrels I will speak of my
dismay and the way that I was shaken seeing people thrashing about like fish
in little water seeing them in conflict with each other I became
afraid I felt discontent at seeing only conflict to the very end
then I saw an arrow here hard to see
embedded in the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash
about in all directions but when the arrows pulled out they don't run and
they don't sink so what is this about this whole
idea I've shared this verse a few times so teaching I I just love this it's very
um it's there's a there's a richness here there's lots of themes that I could pull out but I'm going to pull out this
one particular theme here just going to read these few lines again where the
person who's about to become the Buddha he's not the Buddha yet he says I felt
discontent at seeing only conflict to the very end so this idea of like wow I
don't see how this is going to end seems like there's just always going to be like there's no way forward I just can't
imagine how it's going to be and then um he continues then I saw
an arrow here hard to see embedded in the
heart so he's looking at them seeing nothing but
quarreling and then looks back at himself and sees that he has this arrow
in his heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash about in all
directions so whereas before he was thinking like okay you guys got to get it together and figure it out and
whatever this problem is here maybe I can help you like you know really kind uh this emphasis on what's happening
there but then when he saw this Arrow recognizing that people when they
have this Arrow Dash about in all directions that is maybe I like the word maybe thrash about in all directions
throwing blame throwing judgment throwing insults or you know all kinds
of things that happen with this arrow in the heart and so what is this arrow in the
heart we might say it's the married ways in which we say
no no no to this moment no to this experience I'm having no
to anything and everything in this kind of way this way that the small and
countless ways in which we are cultivating this discontent in which we are
resisting what's already here in our
experience I'm not talking about conceptual big things that are happening out there or experiences that aren't
immediate I'm only talking about this moment this moment this moment
in which we're saying No this is a little theme I've been talking about lately I've just
been this maybe just the climate these days and also noticing in myself the way
that I'm often saying no to things like no I don't want it to be this way and
then just seeing the impact that it has on me these subtle ways so resistance this way of saying no
no no I don't want it make it go away it should be different this like shows up
in so many different ways I'll talk about it this evening but uh it's just this natural response to
discomfort I mean right this is just a a normal thing that our predecessors our
ancestors of course they had this uh discomfort maybe was you know in
response to a threat and so they had to pay attention
or had to behave in a particular way but it's this way that this uh
response to discomfort is it's conditioned it's something that we
learned like if we didn't respond then we had a lot of discomfort a lot of pain and we didn't that's painful so we try
to you know uh create a way in which we can avoid it or maybe we just saw you
know our communities our families the way that okay there's certain uh
discomfort comts that are tolerable exercising restricting what we eat or
something like this but there's other ones that aren't tolerable emotional discomfort and we're not ever going to
talk about uh this uncomfortable thing for example or something so it's conditioned we learn it it's a natural
thing it's all of us have them I certainly have them I'm guessing that
you guys have them too so it's this whe when we encounter
something Pleasant whether it's a difficult emotion uncomfortable emotion or maybe
it's a challenging situation which then gives an uncomfortable emotion I might say or
maybe if it's just a minor inconvenience which then gives rise to an uncomfortable emotion of irritation or
impatience or discontent or something like that so it's this natural human
tendency to push it away or to avoid it or try to control it might it be
different and it takes many forms so what are some of these ways that uh that
I'm talking about here there's this way in which uh this
resistance this way subtly or maybe not so subtle sometimes saying no shows up
we might call this like mental resistance things are happening in the mind there's this where we creating
stories or narratives to to help us not feel the discomfort itself or to avoid
feeling whatever the emotion is so we can create these complicated stories or
narratives I'll give an example in a moment or we might try to
rationalize or minimize or intellectualize the
situation and uh this is one of my favorites I didn't recognize it so much
but uh it's not a mistake right that I spent years of my life uh training to be
a scientist and then being a scientist right scientists are ones that like to just go up into their head and uh
rationalize things intellectualize it and I did my fair share of that I come
from a family of scientists so you know it's not a mistake that I do that it's not a mistake that I became a scientist
myself or there might be this way in which we get caught in this Lo Loops of
judgment and blame and we're just kind of stuck going around and around and around and not feeling like there's any
way forward but there's this way just being in this Loop also helps us you
know not actually feel the emotion feel the difficulty instead we're just in
this loop again and again just with this stuckness I'll give it a example of this
or we might distract ourselves with busyness or planning lot of planning or
just being busy yeah I I like to do this too oh I
need to prepare for this and get ready for that and design this and I don't know it's seems like I can always cook
up things to do to be busy with so what are some of these
examples what if uh you imagine like you experienc a significant loss and but you
tell yourself you tell others oh no I'm fine I'm fine and actually I'm moving on
really quickly and there's this way in which it's it's not quite true and instead
it's this denial of your act what you're actually experiencing and it's a way that it's
preventing you from fully grieving from this loss you're telling yourself and everybody oh no I'm fine I'm
fine and then with not not being not fully grieving and processing this pain
of this loss whatever the loss might be right our lives are filled with so many loss of uh loved ones relationships
jobs uh capacities capabilities this is
this is The Human Experience so there's one way which we might be um um resisting feeling that by
saying to ourselves and to others I'm fine I got this it's going
well or maybe you have a disagreement with a friend and instead of
acknowledging the hurt feelings you spend hours just replaying the conversation in your mind and focusing
like oh I should have said this shoot why didn't I say this or maybe you're um
rehearsing in your mind all the reasons why your friend was wrong and they shouldn't have said that or they
shouldn't have said this or but there's this way in which kind of like going over and over what happened and what you
should have said or what they should have or should not have said just keeps you stuck in the story just going around
and around another form of resistance you're not feeling actual the
pain from this disagreement with a friend you know this like Schism that uh
God created and not feeling the hurt instead you're just stuck in the story
and in some kind of way you're perpetuating a certain type of hurt
maybe or maybe you're perpetuating this idea of like well the next time I see them I'm going to you know X Y and Z and
kind of like uh nurturing this sense of resentment and what I'm going to do next
or something like this but there's this way that this old also prevents you from
feeling and processing your underlying emotions keeps you stuck in the story or
maybe you just find yourself caught in a loop of just intrusive thoughts about a past
mistake like oh I can't believe I did that regret remorse or maybe you're this
future worry oh I hope this doesn't happen and saying this over and over
again and you try to suppress the thoughts but they just keep on returning with a
greater and greater intensity and there's this way in which
we're trying to control the thoughts which is actually just another form of resistance so we're using resistance to
deal with the resistance which of course is just
resistance and so there's this way that kind of like strengthens these thoughts right they uh just
get perpetuated because there isn't a way in which we can allow them to maybe
shift and change and Bloom into something else so those are different ways in
which the mind can um have some resistance against feeling uncomfortable
emotions whatever that emotion might be sadness
anger blame
regret but there's also a way in which we just might suppress or deny or numb
our feelings or maybe we're like projecting our emotions onto others or maybe we lash out in ways that
we have an inappropriate response to something and I was thinking about this
that um I just I spent some time trying with this like every time time that I
was um projecting like oh wow that person is angry or that person is sad I
found I just made it a practice like am I angry am I sad why am I projecting
this onto them and it's quite something to do this to discover oh yeah there's there was a
little bit of anger there this is more in my personal life I'm talking about
when I'm in the role of a Dharma teacher I meet people in a different way than
I'm just meeting them with uh like my friends and family and just uh in my
daily life and that's something for me to think about too like why is it why is it a little bit different when I'm in the
role of a teacher and when I'm just with my friends and family but just this idea
that sometimes we are just so concerned or we're like wow they're so angry
they should really work with their anger and not recognize that in fact we are the angry one but we don't want to
feel our anger so we're just projecting it all onto somebody else I mean this shows up maybe or
having this like inappropriate responses also could be maybe as
we um lash out at our partner over just a minor issue you know and our anger is
disproportion to the situation and maybe there's this way that this is masking a
a hurt or a resentment that we don't want to feel this is another way that
resistance shows up is just uh making a lashing out or
something like this or maybe we feel overwhelmed by a loss and so we find
ourselves watching way too many YouTube videos or or Doom scrolling
or so there's so many things that we can do right to numb the pain another form
of resistance and then lastly I'll talk about there's physical resistance where
we might try to excape through using substances addictive behaviors or
unhealthy relationships there's all these ways in which we are trying to you know just not feel the Heartbreak that
we might have not feel the discomfort of minor emotions or even the
big major ones and this can show up also just in
um carrying chronic tension in our shoulders our neck or our
jaw which is this expression of this uh
unexpressed anxiety or stress or
something so why do we have this resistance I said that it's because we don't want to feel discomfort
but there's this way that our brains are wired and to protect
us from perceived threats and this works when there are actual threats doesn't work so well when
the threats are just discomfort of emotions or something like
this so we resist we have this fear of discomfort but we also have this desire
for control we want to control things of course we do we want to feel like things
will be the way that we want them to be we want to feel like that we have the agency to make our life go in the
direction that we want and we have this idea well okay well I can just figure it
out and I can fix it and uh then everything is going to be fine and then
or I'll figure out a way to make this go away or something this sense of wanting to
control to feel like that uh we can just make everything be okay instead of
feeling oh it's not okay it's not okay
so we are busy trying to fix whatever we can whether it's a major
thing thing or a small thing fix ourselves fix other people fix objects
wri a nusty letters to whomever like it really shouldn't be this way it should
be however it should be you know or maybe there's a way in which um
we resist because we have attachment to our stories we have this stories that we
tell about ourselves or about them those people over there
and we are resisting what's actually happening because what's actually
happening doesn't go with the stories that we
have for example maybe you've been hurt by someone in the
past and you replay this event over in your mind or you
have there's this way that this uh has been built up into your mind and your
reliving the pain and the anger and all the associated emotions and then part of
this is you're telling your the story of how you were wronged this may be true you may be
wrong have been wronged but then there's this way in which you're holding on to the
resentment as a way to protect yourself from being hurt again and it's this
resentment that prevents you from forgiving or prevents you from letting
go and instead you're stuck and you're not moving forward instead you there's
this the resentment is a form of resistance of feeling actually the
Betrayal feeling the hurt feeling the pain of whatever or the anger of
whatever happened or maybe this idea of control
you have a family member or a loved one somebody you care about and they have the unhealthy habits and you're always
giving them advice you know you really should do this and uh you shouldn't do that and I don't know why you keep on
doing this and you try to persuade them to change and then you feel frustrated when they don't comply whatever this is
kids or Partners or parents this is kind of uh your desire
to control their behavior is just your resistance to feeling the discomfort of
actually you have anxiety about your well their well-being it's going to feel
terrible if their health really declines or there's some accident due to the
things that they're doing and so we're resisting accepting that we
can't force someone to change and and instead we're just going
to stay in there this so we're doing this because we
think it's going to make us feel better but this
resistance actually amplifies and prolongs the
discomfort we don't know this of course because we're so busy resisting we don't know what it's like to be when we're not
resisting but It ultimately really it definitely creates more
discomfort there's this way that um you know what we resist persists turns out
to be true there's this way in which when we're tangled up with something it's the whole activity of being Tangled
that uh keeps the difficulty present instead of allowing it to arise and to
be experienced and to pass away which is the nature of all experiences
but not only does it kind maybe amplify or prolong our uh discomfort but it
really limits our growth but getting stuck in
resistance means we're not uh learning like how to be with the discomfort in
other ways and and it kind of maybe it's uh we were missing some insights about
our some of the way that we are showing up in the world world and why people are responding to us the way they do perhaps
or something like this or maybe there's this way of resistance also is uh
creates some disconnection when we're having to resist we're no longer present
with what's actually happening this the anger the sadness the grief the
rage whatever it might be so how can we we work with us how can
we work with resistance how can we not resist the
resistance just notice it start by just
noticing notice all the ways in which the mind and the
body are how they react when you anticipate
you're going to experience discomfort or you are experiencing
discomfort do you tense up do you start thinking negative
thoughts oh this is going to be terrible I can't handle this this is
uh I this I don't I there's so many different thoughts here I'm not so good
at extemporaneously coming up with them or do you reach for distractions
this is what the I do a lot I reach for distractions and sometimes I don't even realize it's such a habit like oh yeah
I've already distracted myself and and might we've created
a society that's filled with nothing but distractions right we all carry around
these little gizmos in our pockets that are designed to be able to distract ourselves so one is just notice some of
the ways in which we are resisting any some anything that's
uncomfortable and just are will have a whole Myriad of ways but there might be some that are more common than others
for us and then once we've noticed it can we
just acknowledge their presence say oh I'm feeling resistance right
now resistance feels like this and then it might be right into
distraction again or it might be into the body being tense again just simply acknowledging it
might not be enough to disrupt this uh momentum but this is where it starts this is where it starts just acknowledge
it don't no need to judge yourself or push it away like Yep this is resistance
this is a natural thing humans don't like to feel discomfort and we do
different things to prevent us from feeling discomfort but these things that we're doing are kind of causing us to be
stuck and it's the opposite of having Freedom it's the opposite of having
peace and then acknowledge the resistance as best you can and then
shift from storyline to Sensations that is shift your attention
to the sensations in the body what's actually here tangible moving much
slower than the thoughts and something that it's easier to rest your attention
on than thoughts or something kind of like diffuse about this uh concept of a
resistance feeling uh tension in the shoulders is much more tangible and
palpable and then can you acknowledge the discomfort of the resistance the
tension in the shoulders and can you acknowledge the discomfort of whatever it is you're
resisting you don't have to necessarily jump right
into the grief jump right into the rage just be with a resistance to the
grief and the rage as best you
can as best you can this makes a huge difference so often like we don't even
know that with the grief and rage I'm just using these two as examples we don't even know that that we have
resistance to them but if we can be with the resistance then the grief may show
up the rage may show up it may not but it'll show up in a different way it'll
unfold in a more natural manner instead of being
Amplified and prolonged by resistance so it will rise and pass
away I can't tell you exactly this time frame but I promise it will arise and
pass away the more resistance we have maybe the higher it is and the longer
the duration so notice the signs of resistance just
get curious about yourself what what are the ways in which what do you do when you don't want to feel anything
uncomfortable two when you notice that oh yeah that's happening right now just acknowledge it maybe it can be helpful
just to say okay I'm feeling resistance right now three to bring attention to the
bodily experience this is so much easier to be with and so much more real actually it's
what's actually happening in the moment you might be having an uncomfortable emotion you might be having resistance
and you're having bodily Sensations so you're being here with the experience and then
four be kind and patient with yourself this is not something that gets untied
really quickly but this is the way to Peace and
Freedom it might seem like oh this is just some minor little thing we're supposed to do but it turns out freedom
is all about not having to resist anything not having to avoid things or
um not having to
not having to um pretend like things are different than they are freedom is to be able to
just meet whatever is arising so if we want freedom in our lives if we want peace in our lives if
we want to not have this arrow in our heart that the Buddha to be was talking
about then we look at our resistance patterns and then we have peace with whatever is
arising and then we can show up in a world bringing this peace and we can see
things differently feel things differently than others can then we can be a force that helps create peace in
the world instead of insisting that those people over there should uh behave
better instead we are the ones that have the peace like why not start here
so I mean resistance is a natural part of the human experience but it doesn't have to be something that
um we can learn how to use it to be a way that supports greater peace and ease
and freedom in our lives and by learning to recognize and
work with resistance there's this way in which it just will happen there'll just
be more ease in our lives and here's a poem I'd like to
close with this is by Dorothy
hunt and it's called peace is this moment without judgment peace is this moment without
judgment by Dorothy hunt
do you think peace requires an end to war or tigers eating only
vegetables does peace require an absence from your boss your spouse or yourself
do you think peace will come some other place than
here some other time than now in some
other heart than yours peace is this moment without
judgment that is all this moment in the heart space where
everything that is is welcome peace is this moment without
thinking that it should be some other way that you should feel some other
thing that your life should unfold according to your plans
peace is this moment without judgment this moment in the heart space
where everything that is is
welcome so resistance as the path working with resistance as the pathway
to peace thank you and I'll open it up for
some comments and questions thank
you sometimes to be a healthy adult don't we have to listen to our resistance I mean I remember when I was
19 I had this 21y old girlfriend who was really manipulative and I wish I would have listened to Mar sooner and said
okay I don't I think we we should not see each other anymore you I stay with her too long probably so don't we some
have to listen to our resistance from the heart I guess I wouldn't I'm using
resistance as a different uh way than you're using you're you're talking like maybe where the body in the heart is
saying no this isn't helpful for me that's different resistance is resistance would be um completely
denying your experience for example but you were you were hearing the no and
choosing not to follow it for some reason so I'm using resistance a little bit different I'm using
resistance as this uh present moment
experience as and to not uh want to be
with that experience does this make sense or yeah I'm just wondering if if to be a healthy
adult we have to listen to our no we have to be say no you know you know just is an important part of being healthy
you know saying no right yes yes yes yes but what I think what you're pointing to
of course right we have to have boundaries and we have to say no yes of course we do um
you're maybe I'll just leave it with there yes we have to have boundaries and be able to say no yes
yes thanks for the uh the talk it really resonated and I think just want to share
maybe a couple of comments or observations uh that I thought were
interesting um I think um One using the analogy or the
metaphor of like The Arrow it was interesting that recognizing the Arrow
by doing that you're you're basically pulling it out like in recognizing it you're pulling it out I was originally
thinking of it as like oh there's going to be steps but you know so I thought that was that was interesting
um and then the other thing that came to me during the talk was I was reminded of
one of the there's the five hindrances and one of them being doubt
and as I was thinking we we it's easy enough to talk about the
arrow right and in in one point of time like one Arrow at a time but then I sort
of started to have doubts when I was like well here's to a lifetime of arrows
or many at the same time and how do you know when you've pulled them all out and those types of
questions um but I think having faith in the process is part of removing them you
know you you're not going to find a discret point in time where they're all out but um I don't know that that was an
interesting one this kind of tests the the faith yeah yeah thank you this idea of
like oh my gosh how many how many arrows are there going to be non-stop arrows for the rest of my life that's just an
idea right and you use this word doubt right that's just an idea it turns out that once we start to get sensitive to
this it uh resistance just uh shows up so much less less and less and less yeah
yeah so thank you for highlighting this and when you talked about the five entrances I thought you were going to
talk about aversion because uh aversion is maybe in there too but uh yeah thank
you anybody else have a comment or
question okay so I'm wishing you well now with the time change am I the only
one that's like feeling like oh it's something's not quite right
so I'm wishing you uh I don't know what to say a happy healthy time change I
don't know I'm wishing you a wonderful evening thank you