[Applause] so one of
the well I just mentioned that for the last three weeks or almost four weeks I've been living Outdoors uh mostly in a
sleeping bag under the stars at night and um natural settings teaching mostly
teaching in that context and there's something quite marvelous about the immediacy of living
outdoors and the contact with the natural world and the Awakening of our
natural senses and uh this speaks to uh the topic for
today which I'll introduce uh for the meditation by saying that Buddhism
begins and ends Buddhist practice with being in the present moment a radical
clear seeing of present moment
experience and um in between the beginning and the end
it's seeing clearly that thoughts about the future thoughts about uh the past
are occurring in the present and uh to see them really as
present moment occurrences that everything we need to describe discover in the Dharma for the
purposes of the kind of deep liberation of heart that Buddhism
teaches is uh found by a simple
attention to present moment experience and it's fascinating to watch
how difficult it is for the mind sometimes to stay in the present how it travels off into the land of thoughts of
the past thoughts of the future thoughts of fantasy and
um so um this morning let's
see how to be here and now with a clear
seeing of present moment experience without wondering off and of
course you will wander off and then the task is always coming back to clear
seeeing no need to analyze judge no need to
criticize if you can return to the clarity of seeing Oh this is present
moment experience uh this is what's
immediate this is what is inviting me to see more deeply into reality the reality
as it unfolds in the present moment so to assume a meditation posture
whatever posture that is appropriate for you and in that posture that you take is
there ways of adjusting it so that the mind can be a little bit more
alert sometimes that's by adjusting the body in the posture so that there's a little bit
more intentionality in meditation
posture and then as almost as a ritual of entering into the present moment of
meditation to take a few long slow deep
breaths and as you deep as you breathe in
deeply to experience the Torso expand stretch
open and as you exhale to relax soften
settle maybe gently closing your eyes
and letting your breathing return to
normal for some people breathing is
the is the primary connection or tether to the present
moment if you know you're breathing you know what's happening in
the present breathing is always
now and if you're not able to stay with the
breathing can you see as present moment experience
what is taking you away don't get swept into the past or
swept into the future swept into
fantasy [Music] commentary but let there be a clear
relaxed settled settling
attention to this is thinking about the past
this is thinking about the future this is telling stories in the
mind commentary and after clear seeing of
that notice what the experience of breathing is like has it
changed has it tightened up for gotten more held
or or has it gotten softer and more
gentle whatever way it is is fine just notice how it
is moment after moment return to
seeing what the present moment experience is
a kind of Refuge in the
present
for
e
for for
yeah if mindfulness is to see what's happening in the
present to see it clearly what can you see clearly at this
moment what can you see without commentary judgment being for or against
so that you appreciate the act of seeing or
knowing it's Simple and Clean
spacious just this is
known just this is known with contentment or ease
for
e
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting perhaps you're a little calmer or more
your capacity for present moment
awareness almost as
if you're standing at the entrance of
a at the gate at the entrance of a new
territory and you're able to watch what comes through the
gate the gate being the present
moment and everything new has to come through that gate
and to relax and settle back and see it
clearly and find your freedom in that
Clarity in the Simplicity of knowing
and may our ability to see
clearly translate to our ability to see others clearly
without judgment and bias expectations
demands fears to see
clearly as an act of generosity Act of care and
kindness May our ability to be present for others be a means for us to offer
profound respect to each and every person we
encounter may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and can our ability to be present for
others contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello everyone and I'm glad to be back that I've been
gone for about a month and um and uh had a wonderful time um for about
three weeks being involved in a training program to train people to be Buddhist
teachers in the context of the natural world the Wilderness Wilderness Retreats
Wilderness back uh um uh you know periods of time of living
in the natural world and that's what I've been done for the last
month except for the last uh four days or so that I went backpacking with my
wife to add to the time uh living outdoors and camping and quite
wonderful so for this week's um teachings I'd like to go through the
five qualities of the Buddha's teachings the the way it's uh uh
described is it's the um it's the description of the wells spoken
teachings of the Buddha and
um and the word for teaching is dama which is a very rich word and and it
could also be uh mean reality the truth itself but for now I'll call the
teachings and it's the five characteristics of the teachings and the importance of these five is seen in the
fact that the monastic terad Community chants these
every day as part of their liturgy they're being reminded of these five qualities on a daily
basis and um
excuse and um
so um this is how it goes in English in
Translation the Dharma is well proclaimed well spoken by the blessed
one it is visible Here and Now immediate inviting to be seen for
oneself onward leading and personally realized by the wise
so these five qualities of what the Dharma is are also the instruction or
the pointing out instruction for how to practice where to look how what to where
our focus is for discovering what these teachings are they're not about finding
them in a book it's not by finding them in lists but rather it's pointing to a
direct experience that we can have ourselves and and
um so it's visible Here and Now is one
translation uh Sun Dio is the poly word
and um di here has the the meaning of um
to see or to view or to observe um sun with for oneself with
seeing and uh it's not to be contemplated it's not to be logically
figured out it's not to be learned externally there's something that we're
looking for to see that's directly visible here and now and so the question is what is that
and um and the times when the Buddha describes what this is uh we could in
Modern English call it uh seeing certain psychological States in particular
seeing uh in the simplest way he says it is uh to see
directly uh greed hatred and delusion as it's uh
present and when there is no greed hatred and
delusion when we see that the absence of this then we're seeing the Dharma so
this is not a teaching into states of Mind into meditation into uh metaphysics
into Phil philosophy it's about seeing the the psychological State psych state of mind
that is free of Affliction free of the stress free of the suffering that comes
with greed hatred and delusion if you see that you're seeing the Dharma that's visible here and
now and uh and the rest of it follows is what the Buddha says as well it's
immediate you see something that's here and now it's not of time it's not
something that um belongs to the world of time because it's a very present and
immediate and that um this teaching about this kind of seeing this teaching
is saying for you it's inviting you come and look for yourself discover this for yourself
don't have to believe it don't have to memorize it just come come to see for
yourself and see for yourself what the absence of greed hate and delusion is
like see for yourself how uh the absence of GRE
delusion is onward leading it provides a it's a guide It's a guidepost for
ourself it's a North star to have some experience of this kind of Freedom The
Joy the happiness the peace that can come from this kind of absence is
um is uh a guide for how to see it again
to find it to look for it to live by it and this is something that is not
supposed to be uh believed but something to be experienced by the wise and here
the word the wise is you that you are you are the wise person who is learning
how to see clearly learning how learning what to recognize what to
know and for today I just emphasize this absence of greed hate and
delusion uh this is kind of the umbrella term for all kinds of states of
Affliction excuse me
thank you as I clear my throat I bike down here to from I'm seeing the cold I
think that somehow trigger a little bit of um maybe some reaction to
something and um so
um so the um this ability so the emphasis is here
is a deep seeing into ourselves into the states of mind the qualities of mind the places of
attachment the places of clinging not to not so that we hang out there and see it and suffer because of
it but so we can look past it look Beyond it uh to see a mind that's free
of Affliction free of these particularly difficult States psychological States
and so I fond of saying that Buddhism is sometimes more psychological than it is philosophical
more psychological than it is religious because it's pointing to something directly to be experienced in our own
mind our own the way our own mind operates and works and that it's there
that we discover Freedom if we're spending time trying to solve the problems of the world
something that's very important to do uh it's important to know that that's not where we're we're going to find Freedom
we might rearrange the world to be perfect just the way we want it to be
and um it's not going to stay that way not for long and uh very quickly things will
change and not be perfect anymore uh but if we turn the attention to
ourselves that's where a certain kind of perfection can happen that's where we can learn how to find our freedom how to
find find our freedom in an imperfect world how to find our non-reactivity in
a world where people are reacting all the time where we can find our wisdom in
a world where there is no wisdom and the wisdom that we're building on is the
wisdom that arises from knowing for ourselves that it's possible to live
without greed hatred and delusion so um that's the direction what
practice is going toward this is what the Dharma is what the Buddha is pointing to this
possibility and um and it's something that's directly
visible that's immediately here and now this word stico can also sometimes
translated as it's here and now to be seen here and now and
um and um so much such a a healthy way of
living in the world can arise so much wisdom can arise when the reference
point for how to live in the world is to be free of afflictive
States now to be a free of greed hate and delusion in some permanent way is a
big task but I hope that each of you have moments through the day where you
find yourself maybe accidentally free of these afflictive states of stress of
greed of hatred and delusion and um and uh fle free of clinging free of
grasping free of pushing away free of anger free of fear and um and maybe it's accident
Dental maybe you go for a walk in your neighborhood and you see someone has a beautiful garden and or a beautiful tree
and something about seeing the tree or the garden um settle something or releases something for a few moments
just the appreciation the Delight The Joy right there are moments of
Freedom um you there right there we're seeing the Dharma that it is possible to be free of
afflictive States so uh look for those through the day uh appreciate the small ways which
they occur they are teaching you the Dharma and then from seeing those
clearly then you might begin understanding the afflictive states more fully when they appear later and you
might not be as waited to them so committed to them you might not want to invest so much time energy mental real
estate to uh being uh caught up in um obsessive
thinking caught up in clinging caught up in resistance caught up in uh anxiety there is another way of
being that uh we're free of it and if you can see it in small ways through the
day those can build those can grow those can um inform you how you can live don't
underestimate the value of seeing the small ways in which we are
free it's those that we build on to experience a greater greater freedom in
our life a freedom which um is visible Here and Now
immediate inviting us to come and check it out for ourselves onward Le leading and
personally realized by the wise so
um thank you and uh I'll go through the next four of these qualities over the
this week week and hope that um it helps you to uh understand Dharma and practice
in a in a intimate way thank you