okay so I think we'll get started so welcome welcome everybody Welcome to
IMC for those of you who don't know me I'm Diana clerk I uh teach here regularly on uh Monday
nights except sometimes I'm off teaching Retreats and I just got back yesterday
from a teaching a beautiful Retreat down at uh IRC it's our sister Center we have
a retreat center down in Santa Cruz and uh it's a beautiful thing to be able to
offer um it was a 7-Day silent residential Retreat maybe I'll just say
a few words about me
um I found meditation in a time in my life when I
felt like you know from the outside kind of like look at my life and you would think like oh it's you know
she has everything that she needs I felt like I had everything I needed but somehow I didn't feel
happy I felt like there's got to be something more as it happens I had a
certain amount of professional success I have a PhD in Biochemistry and I don't know I just had
achieved all these things and somehow felt like my life was missing something
and that I was like disconnected from my life in some way and disconnected from
the people that I was close to that were close to me I just felt like somehow I
had followed all the rules but yet my life I don't know just
wasn't turning out the way that I expected or wanted and it was just
uh I don't know it wasn't like I actually intended to become a meditator
it uh just something that grew out of a a yoga class and a casual comment by
somebody I knew in this yoga class so quite something and I hate to say this but I'm going to ask you to not sit
right there because you're underneath the camera there you go thank you Nicole
yeah so let's see if there's anything else I
need to say about me um I've done a lot of retreat practice I have spent
cumulatively a couple of years years on Retreat silently meditating all day
long and it's changed my life completely changed my life in such a beautiful way
and I'm very happy to be here to be sharing with you some of what I've discovered what
I've learned from others and provide an opportunity for you to practice a little and to ask some
questions so maybe I'll just say a little bit of about uh meditation so here we're we're doing mindfulness
meditation where the Insight Meditation Center Insight Meditation is often
associated with mindfulness meditation sometimes uh similar to what
mbsr John kittson who um started nbsr
actually trained at some of the same place I trained and uh Gil frall the founder of this Center trained so
there's you'll find a lot lot of overlap a little bit of difference of course and I do want to just say that so
this practice is comes out of Buddhism more specifically tervada Buddhism but
and I'm not going to talk about Buddhism here I have zero interest in converting anybody to Buddhism you're perfectly
welcome to follow whatever spiritual path you have and that's meaningful for you and I'll also say a little bit that
um tervada Buddhism and Insight Meditation mindfulness meditation I'm just going to
say it's distinct from Zen and Tibetan Buddhism and I'm not going to go
into the more like exactly how it is I mean I could give a whole Dharma talk on that but we're here to learn how to
meditate so just to bring some clarity like what is it that we're doing here so
just to say explicitly what it is and I would say maybe more generally
we're just taking this natural human
capacity to pay attention we all have this it's not
anything that uh is new and we're just directing it a certain way and
cultivating it so it's something that we're maybe
developing and there's a way in which um in this context that uh we teach it and
practice it here this cultivating this um ability this capacity to pay
attention not only does it lead in general to Greater understanding
understanding ourselves and in some ways I would say certainly from myself as I started to
understand myself more I started to see oh that's why everybody else does this
thing too you know so I just started to have greater understanding of everybody else the more I started to understand
myself I could recognize people's behaviors or things that they would say which I had just
kind of like explored or noticed like oh I feel like I understand The Human
Condition much better now but not only does it un create this
more um self- understanding but it also helps create the conditions just for
more stability without knowing it I'll say
before I was like pushed around around by my emotions a lot and just kind of like get the felt a little bit of the
mercy of you know if I had a bad day I just felt bad or if you know one of my co-workers said something I spent some
time in Corporate America in management uh positions and you know there's a lot
of stress I'm sure many of you know this maybe you have Corporate America jobs right now but I discovered um yeah that I
could just get pushed around a little bit by feeling bad or feeling good or
just feeling disconnected so this noticing practice is a way that helps us
have some stability and some uprightness no matter what is happening no matter
what is happening this turns out to be such a great gift it just uh makes one's life
unfold with so much more ease and openness and I would even say joy and
happiness so and maybe I could even enter that and say love and peace all this starts to
become more and more available as the body and the mind start to settle down
it's just we don't have to make love and peace arise that's just what arises when
settling down happens it's just a natural consequence that occurs and I invite you to discover
that for yourself you don't have to believe me about this
so this is a 4-week uh course um it has been taught as a
five-week course it has been taught as a six- week course but right now it's going to be four
weeks today I'm going to focus on teaching uh mindfulness of the breath
and a little bit about posture and it turns out like these are like foundational
fundamental meditation practices upon which all the others buil build upon so
this is like kind of the the basics which actually could be enough to just
take you wherever you wanted to go with meditation practice but it can be helpful to learn more so today will be
the breath next week will be the body third week will be about emotions and
the fourth week will be about thoughts and thinking and they are all build on
the preceding week so it's uh meant to be you know it's sequential
so it's a very intentional the order in which I'm teaching this it doesn't have
to be in this order it could be taught in other ways but uh I'm choosing to do
this uh in this way and in this time
frame maybe um something else that I'll say is that I'll be talking about you
know meditation usually like formal sitting meditation but so much about what we
learn in sitting meditation will apply to our daily life as well
meditating while waiting at the bank this afternoon as I did while I went from one person who told me I had to go
talk to a second person who then told me I had to go talk to a third person and the third person wasn't available and I
found like I'm just going to sit here and just rather than getting irritated by how long I'm having to wait at the
bank for something I thought was pretty straightforward I'm just going to sit here and calmly do standing
meditation what I I I could feel a little bit of irritation arising like oh I don't actually have to go there and
just kind of like get settled again you know life unfolds differently if you recognize you have that uh
capacity this capability so I'll say a few words about
I MC just uh maybe if you don't know everything
everything is offered freely here just offered freely IMC runs
on uh generosity and so the and people feel inspired and
feel appreciate what they discover here and they may choose to make a donation
it's not required it's all appreciated but not required there's a donation box near the
door and there's a little kiosk that's uh right around the corner here if you want to use your credit
card not required so like I could talk nonstop
for hours about meditation but that's you didn't come here to hear that let's just do a very quick little
meditation get in any posture this is just going to be for 5 minutes so get in any posture that feels comfortable
enough for you
and we'll
just feel feel into this moments
experience in particular feel the pressure of the chair or the
cushion against your
body feel the contact with the sitting surface
if you're sitting in a chair using the back rest maybe with the
back with the
buttocks the back side of the
legs the feet
we are here in this
location specifically your chair your
cushion and it's
now nothing in particular needs to be happening we're just noticing the
pressure against the body
and then we can open up the
meditation and hear
sounds letting go of the pressure in the body and now turning towards sounds
my voice the
fan that little rattling noise that shows up when the fan is
going the traffic
[Music]
so just a brief exercise of like intentionally
placing our attention on an
experience feeling the pressure against the body and then intentionally moving from
that experience and in some ways kind of like opening up to sounds and
just be able to receive whatever sounds are
there I'd love to hear from some of you how was that was that uh like yeah yeah
yeah I know how to do this or was it h seems too simple or have some just it
was this short thing was there anything that you noticed was it
easy was it uh turned out not to be so easy to keep the mind just on the pressure of the body or the sounds or
did you find yourself making comments anybody have something they'd like to share
yes Jim can we thank you Jim I should say thank you so much Jim he has been
meditating longer than I have and just out of the generosity of his Spirit he's uh helping me out tonight
he's hi there um my what observant I
found is that when you were talking about the body and the pressure on my like on my legs and my seat then when
you switch said give that up and go with the sounds I I kept finding that I was
back on on that all the time it was like it kept pulling me pulling me back so it was hard to move on to something else
and was that like this um was it Pleasant or was it unpleasant this both
the pressure against the body and the uh this would think like oh yeah I'm
supposed to be on the sounds but I'm here instead just that trying to be on the sounds
but really quickly jumping right back to the body every second so I just noticed that
great great this is a noticing practice you noticed I love it thank
you anybody else have a comment
okay I'm going to spend a little time about posture because when you're
uncomfortable in meditation right that's like the only thing that happens in meditation often is this you know when
is the Bell going to ring kind of
experience so I'll talk about um both with uh on the cushion and on the
chair and on a bench when I'm sitting I have one leg in
front of the other as often as the most comfortable as opposed to uh there you
could you could do quarter Lotus or half Lotus if you know that then go ahead and do that of course but it's this way that
um it feels very stable to have two knees and the buttocks right it's just like this tripod it's very stable
the first time I meditated I could do this maybe for 30
seconds and I remember going to a like a meditation center and just being amazed that people
could sit there for you know 30 minutes or 45 minutes I didn't even know it was humanly
possible it's you know so this is definitely something that uh most of us
will have to practice with if we choose to sit on the on the on a
cushion maybe I'll say a few things about this that um I'm sitting on the
very edge of the cushion like maybe the quarter the first I don't have a cushion
here to show you but um I'm like on the first quarter of it so 3/4 of the cushion is behind me and I'm just on the
edge of it and part of the reason is so that my
hips are are higher than knees this makes a big difference so
higher than are the same level as if the knees end up being higher than the hips
then there's this way that kind of like our femur kind of goes down into the hip joint it can be comfortable enough for a
few minutes but uh for extended times it's not so comfortable so it can be
really helpful to have your hips higher than your knees but then you might say but my knee
I'm not that flexible I can't do it and so often what we would do we have these
cushions so you can put maybe a cushion here because we don't want the knees to
be uh just dangling we want to have a sense of stability so if your flexibility only allows something like
this then I would get a second zuu the
round ones and then yeah would get up
higher and or do something like this under the under the knees so that you
really have this contact with the ground so we want to feel
stable maybe while I'm still on the not not in a chair I'll say also an
alternative is to sit in a bench I'm going to talk about the chair in a moment so sitting in a chair is
perfectly legitimate perfectly legitimate just cuz I'm not so tall actually chairs are not that comfortable
for me so I always sit like this when I'm teaching or meditating or this so
that's just you know this Anatomy uh prefers to sit on the floor but that's not true for everybody of
course um these uh benches can be a way if you
don't have the flexibility to do something like this you can do something like this put
this back here and you just put this behind you maybe I should go this
way oh is it
here and so my uh my knees aren't like this so my hips don't have to be as
flexible and the spine is can be straight up just as it can elsewhere
this can be really comfortable and when I was first beginning I would uh alternate between the cushion and this
and a chair like all three sometimes if the um yeah maybe
I'll just keep this this simple so there's these benches a whole slew of benches
underneath the stage there right at the end of the stage there and then I'll say a few things
about the chair and if you're like you're welcome to go get some cushions but first I want to say a few things about the chair
same principle holds with the chair about hips higher than knees or the same
level as knees so if you have really long legs this mean you want to put a cushion on
the chair and sit on the cushion that's on the chair if you're like me and your legs are not very long then uh you put your
feet uh you put a cushion underneath your feet so as it would kind of like bring the ground up want to have both
feet uh firmly on the ground the body and the mind are so
connected much more than we might realize so when there's a sense of stability in the body it really helps
having a sense of H stability in the mind
too what you do with your hands you can do whatever you like um
but we recommend that you like be uh have some symmetry so whatever is happening on one hand is the same with
the other I tend to put my hands here because I like to have a neutral wrist
but some people will put it on like put their hands here a little bit of a Bend
here the only thing to notice is whether your hands are a little bit here and there's a little bit of pulling on the
shoulders because then there's this rounding of the shoulders and instead what we want is this straight spine and
the arms just hang from it and then they can be however they
want to think about having the ears over the shoulders so maybe the chin goes
back just a little bit just a tiny bit to make sure that there's this uh that
we're not leaning forward these days with computers right so or cellones
right there's this way in which the head is not um over the shoulders very often
if some of you would like to get up and go get some uh cushions you're welcome to or a bench you're welcome to do that
no requirement of course and uh we'll do a a meditation another meditation here in a few minutes
maybe I'll sit on this I'm a little bit
taller maybe there's one one more thing I could say about hands
is that sometimes it's helpful to have something like this in your hands
because it takes the pressure off of the shoulder which takes the pressure off of the spine so it can be helpful to just
have a cushion here a lot of people practice this
way again there's absolutely no requirement to um be on the floor I I
once taught a retreat there was five of us meditation teachers six of us
meditation teachers and I was the only one on the cushion and five of them were uh in a chair so it's perfectly fine to
be in a chair but unless you grew up kind of like sitting on the floor it will be
uncomfortable at the beginning it's not uncomfortable for me now right so it's
just something that um the more you do it the easier it gets just like everything else right
I'm looking at my notes to see if I've forgot
anything this is not as stable as I would like it on this uh so I'm going
to use a cushion here
does anybody have any uh questions about
posture can I make a few comments about what I see you might want to move up so
move a little bit forward on your off yeah just so that your knees are on the ground a little bit little bit more yeah
there you go that's a little bit easier y Le like
[Laughter] beautiful Yan Le is she'll be giving instructions soon and same with Lydia
who's sitting next to her so great
great okay I don't I see how do you want to
put a cushion under your knees here's some cushions here if you want to just up here
and can we can you maybe you can hand these back to him or then we can like do a a group
a that might be a little high the red one there and you can fold you can fold
these right you can fold this in half to make
it there we
go so as I
mentioned so mindfulness practice is a noticing
practice and if we set up this idea that um actually this meditation practice is
to get rid of our thoughts or to Bliss
out [Music] or discover the truth of some
question we have that's a different goal than
noticing doesn't mean those things don't happen but we really are orienting
towards we just want to notice what's
happening and so it doesn't require that we're in complete Comfort or that the
mind is completely settled or something like that we're just noticing what happens and if
you notice that your mind wanders then you're you're practicing in the
right way because so often in our days our mind is just wandering and we have no idea it's wandering it's just uh
doing what Minds do so it's pretty common that with the
meditation if we set a an object I'll guide us in a moment with
the breath it's kind of like if you come
to and this happened to me not so long ago where you're let's say you're out
hiking and there's this uh this some water and you're not sure like is this
just a swampy area or is this like a very slow moving Creek
maybe it's not clear so uh you take a stick and you put the stick in the water
and then you could see oh there's this very little wake next to the stick like oh yeah okay this is a creek it's is
moving and it's going this direction in the same way in the exact
same way we choose to put our mind on one thing and then we notice how much it's
not on that one thing and that's part of what this practice is
we start to notice what takes us away what are our patterns of mind what are
habits what ises the mind like to do we would never notice that unless we were trying to put it here on the
object and then of course the more we do it more we keep it on the object the
anchor the breath I'm going to lead us in the breath then it becomes easier and
easier but in the beginning we're like here on the breath and then the Mind goes and then gee I have to remember to
stop at the grocery store when I get home what time does that place close and it's so nice that the light is blah blah
blah blah blah blah right oh right I'm supposed to do that meditation thing and then come
back and then off you'll go I can't believe my boss said that to me today
what should I have to you know these are just the things that happen and then you'll wake up at of it and just come
back so when you find yourself like you wake up you realize I'm using the word wake up to like when you notice oh yeah
I'm supposed to be medita I was off planning
worrying fantasizing remembering doing all these
things we don't have to make it be a problem in the sense that we don't have
to create a narrative such as my mind wandered I noticed I'm a
terrible meditator I can't do it everybody else can do it look at them they're sitting still and you know we
often will like build this little story on top of when we realize that the we're
no longer on the breath you just notice oh yeah the mind was thinking and come
back to the breath we don't have to say we don't have to make a a value judgment out of
this cuz it's very often that people will have this goal or they think that
there should be no thinking or that they should be completely
relaxed this does happen but it doesn't happen um and you know at the very
beginning of a meditation practice we're just
noticing we're going to like choose an anchor and then when you have an anchor
then as we go in these further weeks we'll turn towards things that are compelling things that are like really
drawing our attention it turns out sooner or later
everything in your life will show up is being compelling you don't have to go find it
you don't have to chase it everything will just Bubble Up When It's the time for it to Bubble
Up so we'll just stay here with the anchor and when we discover that we've
been lost in thought we're like oh lost in thought and come back so I'm using the word anchor an object as synonyms
and as these weeks go we're going to change what they are but for this guided meditation we're going to use the breath
and I would say that's the foundational practice for the
breath okay so let's take a
posture have some upright brightness in the posture that expresses your
intention to meditate so has this maybe a sense of
uh the word that comes to mind maybe a little bit of [Music]
nobility as this uprightness and some
ease and this might take take a little time to get the hang of how to have this
uprightness and
ease we'll start the same way we started the other
meditation just feeling the pressure against the
body feeling the contact with the sitting
surface again it might be the back if you're in a
chair the buttocks
the back of the
legs the feet feeling what the feet are
touching feeling grounded connected we're here
maybe you can just scan your body see if there's some obvious places of tension
or holding common places are around the
eyes or around the
jaw the shoulders letting the shoulder blades
slide down the back away from the ears
and then rest the attention on the
experience of breathing that might be the belly moving
in and out might be the chest or rib cage
expanding Contracting or it might be the feeling of air going
in and out of the nose whichever one of those three areas
feels the most comfortable most accessible just rest your attention
there
feeling from the inside so to speak what does it feel like to have an
in breath feeling the stretch or the movement
feeling this stretch I'm sorry feeling the experience
of an exhale how does that feel
and when the mind wanders as it's apt to do we just very simply gently begin again
with the sensations of breathing
nothing in particular needs to be happening we're just noticing this
sensations of
breathing it doesn't need to be any words or just
feeling but if there were words there would be more like
adjectives e
there's nothing to figure out we're just noticing the sensations
of breathing
doesn't matter how many times you have to begin again
just when we wake up out of thinking just very simply begin again
with the sensations of
breathing
for for
can you give yourself over to the sensations of
breathing letting the thoughts go they can take care of
themselves for
if you find yourself really tired wanted dozing off you can straighten up your
posture that often can make a
difference for
just tuning into being sensitive to the experience of
breathing feeling the
Rhythm
e for
if you notice that you're thinking can you choose to be with the
sensations of breathing letting the thinking just be
in the background of the experience of breathing in the
foreground
for for
maybe you can run a little experiment here and just see if you can notice what
is happening whatever is happening in a
nonjudgmental a very ordinary way just notice what's happening in your
experience
what's it like to have non-judgmental noticing oh it's like this right
now it's just like this we don't have to add anything extra
[Music]
when I was first learning to meditate I would be like ring the bell ring the bell ring the bell when are you going to ring the
bell maybe some of you had that experience
too so in that meditation I started by directing you to feel the pressure
against the body I like to do this as a way to start because it's a way to feel
really connected with this uh with the location of where I am present
moment and then maybe to do a little bit just a general body scan just to see if there are some areas of the body which
are really tense and that it can be that bringing awareness to them bringing attention to them allows a certain
amount of softening not always but
sometimes and then to rest the attention on the sensations of
breathing sometimes we can think about breathing and think that we're meditating on the breath so that's
partly why I suggested like just to feel how an inhale is like to break up the
breath into more than you know into its parts and just notice the inhales and
then the exhales and then when you notice that you're
lost in thought just begin again on the breath that it can be that simple it's
very simple I'm not saying this is super easy and you can get it right away this
is definitely a practice but it doesn't have to be complicated and part of its power and I
would say its transformative power is the Simplicity of it the things that we
kind let go of in that shed when we kind of like stay with the Simplicity of the
experience just enables us to be in the Simplicity of other experiences instead
of filling our minds with a you know kind like getting disconnected from our
experience and planning or not listening to what somebody's telling us instead we're
trying to plan what we're going to tell them or something like this so I'd love to hear some comments
or questions how was that was that easy peasy or was it like oh my gosh I can
wait for you to ring the bell or was it uh feel like really Diana aren't we
going to do something more complicated or I don't know anything you'd like to
add or ask yeah I noticed that as soon as I put my attention on my
breathing my breathing went from automatic to manual so it was sort of
like as soon as I paid attention to it I was like how do I
breathe am I breathing too big like I kind of you know it's not really
observing it was more like I was doing it intentionally but kind of forgetting how I normally breathe yeah yeah um can
you turn down the volume just a little bit I think we're getting some feedback that little feedback thank
you is that what's supposed to happen or it's so common it's very very common
that we feel like oh actually I'm going to control the breath a little bit it's part of noticing and controlling go
together it's perfectly okay it's something that uh will just work itself out it'll just uh eventually you won't
feel like so much you have to control but then I will say that sometimes we feel like we need to control the
controlling and then we have the control the control of the controlling right and then we just get wrapped up so it can be
helpful if you feel like in some ways you're kind of like getting wrapped up in this uh not wanting to control the
breath and you didn't say this I'm just maybe offering this for anybody else as well then it can be helpful sometimes to
open up to sounds and then come back to the breath kind of like you know interrupt the
momentum of the that we might get into a little tessle with that trying to control the breath or
something was that was that helpful yes thank you anybody else uh have a comment
we'd like you to use the microphone just so everybody can hear okay thank
you just uh two questions if you're in the chair should you not rest on the
back you should be actually forward yeah so thank you for asking that the
question you know should we use the back rest if you can if your back allows you it's much turns out to be much easier to
not use the back rest but a lot of people do and often what happens if
you're just a beginner meditator you don't have the strength to like sit without a back rest and so uh sometimes
we'll people will start without a back rest and then maybe uh lean back for a little bit and then come forward but to
do it in an easy Gentle Way and it can be really worthwhile to work up those uh
muscles to be able to sit without a back rest and the second question is um when
you're exhaling should you open your mouth like you you know should you ex like deeply open your mouth and
no we're not doing any the question was with the exhale should you uh open your mouth and deeply exhale no we're keeping
the breath completely natural for this practice we're not doing anything intentional with it okay thank
you hello um I'm just wondering it was really hard for me to not focus on my
body and how that my knees were feeling um so any tips for especially when your
foot's falling asleep how do we focus on the breath when our knees are killing us yeah I I I
was waiting for somebody to ask this question because of course this happens in the beginning or something like this
and I'm assuming that it was uh uncomfortable the sensation in your knee is that right yeah
yeah next week we'll talk a lot about the body and how to be with the body I'll say a few things here to uh talk
about some of the discomfort um one is that you can zoom
in in one kind of way so what I mean by this is to bring some curiosity to it to
like okay this is uncomfortable but is it a stabing or a tingling or a
throbbing and so we're just resting our attention and you know bringing some cous osity to it and then we can ask so
not only the particulars about the sensation and then we can also ask about the location is it very specific or is
it broad is it moving or is it in one place the point is not to find the
answer so much as it's to shift our relationship to it because we're
probably like dang it I wish this wouldn't be happening there's often like this aversion and sometimes I can turn
into anger and you know all these types of things but you know the truth is right there's a lot of discomfort in
this Human Experience so there's something about uh being able to build our capacity to be with discomfort and
one way is to shift our relationship away from aversion towards
curiosity so that's one way is to maybe like to dive in and to just bring some
curiosity there a second way is maybe to as best you can go to something neutral
so it might not be easy to do right if it's really calling your you know if it's really painful then uh you might
not be able to do that but if it's just like an itch which maybe isn't painful but it's calling your attention you
didn't say this but I'm just saying this in general for everybody um you can go
to a neutral experience pressure against the body something like this just like
bring the Mind back and back and back this practice is all about just bringing
the Mind back back back and then maybe a third thing that
I'll offer also when there's an un maybe there's two more things third thing is um we can instead of zooming in Zoom way
out so um as if you're like the birds ey View
and maybe like how that uh plays out is yes this comfortable sensation is in my
knee and I feel the pressure in my body and I feel the breath oh discomfort in
the knee pressure in the body discomfort in the knee pressure in the body discomfort in the knee sound something
like this but there's this way when something's uncomfortable we tend to kind of collapse into it and it becomes
our whole experience and we just get in this wrestling match and you know I used
to get like so angry when I was like uncomfortable and I would start blaming I would blame anybody and anything like
this is wrong this has to be different so that's the Third Way zooming in
neutral zoom out the fourth way is to shift your posture but shift your
posture while being mindful it's like oh this knee is really
uncomfortable my foot is falling asleep I'm going to die if this batt doesn't
ring I'm going to move my left leg and we would like say this like in kind of
in your mind okay I'm going to move my left leg and then we move the leg feel
it feel how it is in this new posture and then go back to the breath so it's
not like we stop meditating shift and then come back to meditating we just fold the shifting of the posture into
the meditation that it was a long answer but was that helpful yeah thank you you're
welcome I'll talk more about this tomorrow or next week
anybody else have a comment or
question how many of you usually meditate using an
app and so this uh sometimes comes up with a question it's like well what
about music like is it okay to have you know like some relaxing music there's
nothing wrong with that but what we're doing here is we're learning some
selfreliance you might say we're increasing our capacity in so many
different ways capacity to um recognize what the mind is doing to notice to come
back to gain some self- understanding and so with that
it's often better to not have music so it's I mean if you're meditating only to relax that's
something different and that you know you can do whatever you like with that too of course right relaxing and stuff but here
we're um building as part of a practice to really honestly can transform Our
Lives make us having this stability and peace and ease that definitely 100%
translates off of the cushion into your life I mean relaxed is helpful too of
course often people ask but I'm falling
asleep what can I do there maybe I'll say for some people it
might be better to sleep than to meditate honestly because we are such a
kind of you know we have this go go go culture and why don't need to you know wake up early early staying up late up
early this type of thing and if you're just physically tired you won't be able
to meditate right your body needs to sleep so for some of you maybe you know need to have a a sleeping practice
rather than a meditation practice that's okay right of course there are some things if you find
yourself really sleepy I mentioned like you know just have some uprightness in the
posture I'll say that um if I'm going to fall asleep um it'll while meditating
it's only if I'm sitting in a chair leaning with a back rest it's there's something about that that uh you know
it's easier to sleep but you know just holding the body up takes just a little
bit more energy and that helps keep one awake also there can be a helpful to
open one's eyes but to keep the Gaze kind of like just down here so not
looking at anything but having light come in because usually when we sleep
right we don't have our eyes open of course right so and just notice if the eyes are falling asleep and or closing
and then just open them back
up if you really want to meditate and you're really sleepy
then people often will do standing meditation you can you know just stand
in one place and meditate and that can be way usually you won't fall asleep if you're standing too
so are there any more comments or
questions um what about the the time of day like should you do it first thing in the morning then you be
sleepy or away yep thank you she was asking like what time of day should we do this and that's where I was going
next is um it can be really helpful to have a regular meditation practice of
course this is just just like playing the piano or learning to ride a bike learning to drive any of these things
right the more you do it the easier it gets right this of course so to meditate
regularly and it can be really helpful to actually experiment in the beginning
when is it the best for you to meditate for some people it's uh best first thing
in the morning because the we haven't yeah it's just the mind isn't cluttered
with all the other things that they uh that the Mind happens to do so some people I'll have a cup of coffee first
and then uh you know have a cup of um then meditate I find myself uh meditating
midm morning but you know my uh schedule allows that to happen I like to do go
outside go for a walk or something like this first thing in the morning and then um a little bit later I'll uh meditate
some people meditate at the end of the day it just find a way it's just kind of helps
to um unwind from the end of the day but it can be really helpful to just explore
okay what is it like what's the difference between the end of the day oh I know some people who meditate at lunch
actually somebody who go sits in their car from their job and just sits in their car for 10 minutes and meditates
right so you know whatever your life allows and I think it's worthwhile
experimenting what's it like in the evening what is it like in the morning what is it like at lunch time or
something like this so and then the question often shows up is uh well how
long as long as you well so you know I'm kind of like I think you should meditate
for 2 hours no I'm just kidding I think 20 minutes fantastic if
you can do 10 minutes that's great if you can do five minutes that's okay too if you do nothing but just get into the
meditation posture take three breaths that can be okay
too because often what happens is we have this sense like oh I should meditate but I don't have time I'll do
it later and then you know it just doesn't happen or oh I want to meditate but it's painful in my knee so I'm not
going to do it or something but there's something about if nothing else just like taking the meditation posture and
three breaths just kind of like reminds ourself that oh yeah it doesn't have to
be a giant Endeavor it doesn't have to be um something that we have to
rearrange our entire life for initially right and then we'll do three breaths and then you know five breaths and then
five minutes and you know something like that but start where you are I I if you
can I would say 20 minutes but you if that just feels like way too much 10 minutes and then a question often arises
about a timer maybe it doesn't arise because there's so many timers on phones now
these days
I would say some people um ask about well I have my clock like right in front
my phone that's counting down like right in front of me and I'm sometimes I just find myself watching it waiting for this
it can be helpful to have the phone out of you and just give yourself over that
uh you'll get up when the when the bell rings
and then I'd say if you don't meditate at all if you like maybe set the
intention okay I'm going to meditate every day and you find yourself just not meditating even once notice why not like
notice like what is it that's uh like uh getting in the way that this is a noticing practice
right so just notice if you're not doing that what's getting in the way that can be really supportive for one's life too
and then I'll offer something else about um practicing at home is of course you
know I'm sitting here in a meditation posture I'm giving instructions for a meditation posture but meditation
doesn't have to happen in a meditation posture so something that can be really helpful is to
choose an activity that you do every day that takes a short amount of time and
just notice all the sensations ass associated with that a common one is
brushing one's teeth just like okay I'm just going to how does the toothbrush feel in my hand what's the weight of it
what does toothpaste really taste like and uh if you have an electric one you know feeling the the vibration or you
know and just feel your feet on the ground feel the water in the mouth as you rinse you just be there completely
with that experience and as you find the Mind watering just come back to the brushing the teeth and so that can be a
real support to just choose something like this to uh bring some mindfulness for yes can we bring that microphone
back there thank you
Jim uh do you encounter people who sometimes avoid meditation because you
are just afraid to be by yourself and encounter where confront yourself your
thoughts yes okay so what's the solution for that so I would say now that we're going
to just come back to the breath just come back to the breath so with
thoughts well we're going to do a whole week on thoughts um but I think it's
tremendous let's see so your question is do people avoid because of the thoughts that arise is that is that you no it's
like almost like being afraid of by being afraid of being by yourself
because now you're going to encounter or confront your your all the random thoughts that come into your
mind so some are good and some are maybe not so good so yeah then maybe just be
in a meditation posture do three breaths and then do three breaths when you're waiting at a stoplight do three breaths
when you're wait waiting for the other person on the phone to pick up you know these
types of things just sprinkle it throughout the day and it starts to become easier and easier but this is not uncommon right
that people don't want to be with their thoughts there's a lot of scary stuff that's happening in here yeah
yeah oh so you mentioned not leaning back on
the chair so much I mean is there like an energetic thing that's happening by not being supported
by a chair or it just turns out that um there's something when the spine when
all the vertebrae are stacked like one on the other and the arms are just able
to hang then you can sit like this for a very long time probably you don't notice
this but when you're sitting in a chair lean back you're adjusting your posture subtly all the time so
frequently and so uh it's just a little more stable and steady to just be
upright like this so that's one an energetic I don't know this is something
you can explore and just feel see how it is okay thank you you're
welcome okay so we're at the end of our time together so thank you for coming
and you're welcome to come up and ask me some questions afterwards if you have thank you thank you