well good morning
welcome it seems that overnight uh the year changed Happy New
Year I feel uh I feel very very happy to be joining you for the the first session
of these 7 A.M sittings in 2024 May our practice this year be
fruitful I'm joining you now from Insight Retreat Center so I'm on the west coast
and the the dawn is just starting to break I'm starting to see the Grays and
blues over the Treetops wishing you all an eful
morning so we will start this year as um
I understand is the custom at IMC by returning to one of the central
Frameworks in the buddh teaching returning to the root we might
say and the teaching we will look at for this week is the four noble
truths let's spend some time setting up the meditation then we'll we'll enter
into silence together so for this med this
meditation to welcome ourselves into it you can
first imagine that you're walking in
forest and say this Forest has grown dense thick with
leaves thick with trees and brush and shrubs and grasses
and the density increases to the point that you you're
not sure how to proceed you don't know where to take the next
step so the best thing is to be
still still with senses open still and
attentive and somehow in that Stillness oh a Way Forward
emerges you could say we're rediscovering the path a path that's been there all
along now that we've seen the path we can walk confidently
on so I'm imagining some of us perhaps in 2023
became full of concerns and preoccupations maybe the the trees and
shrubs of Our Lives became dense maybe to the extent that we could
benefit from a Paws Stillness and
observation so that we can sense our way forward and ReDiscover what path it is
we're
walking so to to hold two Reflections in our mind during this Retreat one or this
sitting one is now that we've turned over a new
year what is asking to be released
relaxed or even let
go and then later in the sitting from that space of Stillness not from the
head but from the senses and the Heart sensing sensing our way into what's next for us
let's start there so let's find our way into the
sitting
posture
settling our weight on our
support spine growing
long
we so aligning that maybe the shoulders roll
back and welcoming some deep
breaths
already what is asking to be
released perhaps there's some extra muscle
tension but the scale of the
forehead backs of the
hands
here with
Simplicity present for this moment of an
experience what is asking to be released
here the body
breathing what it is asking to be released
and then as it fades as it is
released what's the quality of the
absence left
behind
release and
absense what is the co quality of this
absence a space where something new May
emerge in its own
time no hurry
and in the last minutes of this
sitting what is asking to be released
relaxed let go
opening the hand that
grips and then
sensing the quality of the
absence the quality of the absence and what has become
possible
than
you
so welcome again seems to be the first day of
2024 wishing you a joyful and dharmic New
Year and uh as I mentioned it's the custom at IMC uh I've seen Gil give uh the first I
think Sunday Talk of the year is on the four noble truths so
inspired by that we'll take up that same topic this week in the context of the the teaching
lineages of Buddhist mindfulness the formable truths of course hold a central
place um the tradition holds that the the formable truths were the content of the Buddha's first teaching after his
Awakening um one helpful thing for us is that the
for Noble Truths can be a sort of summary of so much of the teaching or
they can serve as a framework that con connects so many parts of the teaching so there's that really big
scope and then there's also um I find that the for Noble Truths have this
impressive degree of application they can be applied uh as an
understanding that's so helpful in a wide variety of um the circumstances of
our
life so maybe with the four noble truths in the background um one of Gill's
slogans is that if you want to be free study where you get
stuck so that means we will have to study where we get stuck and that's that's exactly what the for noble truths
are asking of us [Music] um so to start understanding the fornal
truths one helpful thing to know is that the um the Buddha the Buddha was one of
his names one of his um one of the ways he was referred to as the great
physician and the formable truths are set up uh seemingly to follow in that
medical model of his time so four parts you've got the ailment
you have the second which is the basis or the condition or the cause the third is the
prognosis and the fourth is the treatment medical model so let's
correlate these with the four noal truths the first the first the ailment Dua
suffering uh stress we're going to get to Know This Much More
Today second Nal Truth uh correlates with the basis the C
cause the sometimes the cause the condition this is the arising of Dua and in uh in the dharmic terms we
say it's the craving that leads to further becoming and we'll unpack that somewh
tomorrow third Noble Truth correlates with the prognosis and that is this
wonderful fact that the cessation of suffering is possible the cessation of
that same craving that leads to further coming it can end that's
amazing and then the fourth Noble Truth correlates to the the course of
treatment so the path of practice that leads to the cessation of suffering so
you can pretty easily see the the correlation with the the ancient medical model
here something that's very interesting and makes the formable truths not just not just an AB abstract set of ideas but
locates them in our lives is this fact that each of the four noble
truths has an Associated task or a Duty
or a practice and uh as we go throughout the
week uh we'll talk each day about one of the truths and its Associated task and
today we're looking at the first Noble Truth and its Associated task is to understand or to comprehend suffering
so let's zoom in a bit on this first Noble Truth so the task of the first Noble
Truth being to understand Dua suffering and
stress uh it Bears mentioning here that that it is it's a it's the nature of the
path that our understanding will be partial all the way along until full
Awakening it said that if we fully understand in its depths Dua to its
bottom then uh that that is um that precipitates
Awakening so I mention this now that our understanding will be partial as
actually a bit of encouragement that let's not be too hard on hard on ourselves for having a
partial understanding we're all doing our best with the understanding we
have so to talk about how we might develop in in terms of understanding Dua I want to borrow an
analogy and that is uh the Appalachian Trail and I'm going to use this to uh to
point to three different modes of developing an understanding so say say you wanted to
hike the Appalachian Trail first uh first layer would be
um of course it would be great to read about it number one uh you might find
out that the Appalachian Trail is X X miles or kilometers long or that it has these certain
features the second second mode of developing an understanding would be
reflection reflection on what you learn uh you could reflect on the features of
the trail you might reflect on your own capacities as a hiker uh and see that this Trail is
appropriate for you for right now in your level of skill and this this does something
really important which is uh gives us the confidence that yes I
can do this so that it's this reflection that really gets to know what you've learned
and then gives you some confidence and then the third mode of developing understanding is to walk the
path for yourself and this is the sort of cultivated wisdom that only comes by uh
let's say getting your boots dirty so similarly in developing an
understanding of the Dharma and for today developing an understanding of the first noral truth you can start in this first mode
by reading or in this case listening to the teachings um in such a way that begin to
understand oh this is what this is what the Buddha meant when he talked about suffering and stress this is what all of
these centuries of teachers have been talking about this is it then the second mode would would look
like a certain reflection on what you learn in terms of your own
experience uh one of the one of the things that this opens up this mode of
reflection is this realization that oh the Dharma is right here the Dharma is
right here in my life not somewhere else this is where I can learn reflect and practice it's this actual suffering it's
not some suffering in the abstract and then that opens the way for
the third mode of developing understanding that is to practice directly walk the
path for ourselves the one teacher put this concisely and beautifully that uh it's
our problems actually that are our meditation Hall it's our problems actually that are
our meditation H so let's go just a little bit further
into each of these three this first mode of understanding in terms of the first
Noble Truth is to uh hear and learn the teaching so this is a moment when I'll I'll pull
straight from the texts one of the definitions of duka suffering and stress this is from uh for those who
like the Sut references middle length discourses 141 the Buddha says what uh now what is
the Noble Truth of stress birth is stressful aging is stressful death is
stressful sorrow lamentation pain distress and despair are stressful
ful not getting what is wanted is stressful in short the five Aggregates
the five clinging Aggregates are stressful for today I'm really interested in highlighting one of these
and that is not getting what one wants is stressful this is a this is a sort of
first Noble truth that it so visible applicable now who of us cannot relate
to not getting what we want from time to time and here again we see this
characteristic of the Buddhist teaching that it's this it's this duka that's evident and applicable and visible and
understandable just right right here in our lives in in my understanding to broaden
this teaching a bit by duka suffering and stress the Buddha means the entire array of suffering and stress from very
obvious physical pain or emotional distress all the way to existential fear
to death itself and to very subtle perhaps
pervasive disease it's this whole spectrum of
experiences this might sound this might sound like a pessimistic start to a very
important teaching but uh let's remember that um it's right here in our problems
that the Dharma unfolds and the Buddha didn't didn't teach suffering just suffering but
taught a a path and a an assurance that
its ending is
possible so this second mode of understanding reflection I want to highlight especially not getting what
one wants and tell you just a brief story um and as I get into the story
um yeah maybe a moment just to reflect for yourself if there's been a recent time that um you didn't in fact get what
you wanted and then how that went how was that how was that for you my story went something like this
and it was about two weeks ago I I traveled to my home state to visit family for the
holiday I had all kinds of expectations this these uh Visions visions of days in
the kitchen with my my uh family and visits with my siblings and there
spouses um it wasn't long after I got there that expectation met
reality and they didn't match but presumably on the plane despite um
despite my care um uh I got sick a few
days after after the arrival I found I was quite sick and had to spend most of the holiday um without my
family uh not what I expected expectation met reality and they did not
match it meant that I I couldn't be in the same home as my vulnerable parents
in all of this vision and expectation these things that I'd been looking forward to they became
impossible I wasn't getting what I wanted now right here right here if we
really want to pile dooka upon duka this is our opportunity to compound our
Misfortune uh so we um uh we could we could
um sort of double down on our expectations and make our make our uh
desires into demands maybe this is a place where we can see any underlying underlying Tendencies of aversion not
getting not getting what we want and just like trying to assert uh that aversion will will annihilate this
reality that I'm experiencing or maybe the underlying tendency is to ignore these are all possibilities but
right here right here where we're not getting what we want this is so precious
because it can reveal to us oh what's happening underneath the surface and because of the power of our
mindfulness practice we know that that bringing a balanced open wise
attention to all of the circumstances of life helps to grow the
beautiful interestingly what um what's expected
and what arises when they don't match actually there doesn't have to be suffering there that's an amazing power
of mindfulness that can grow our confidence and this is exactly how we go from the second mode of understanding to
the third mode of understanding by stud studying our suffering right here in the specifics of
our life right here
and we can learn from we can learn from the Dua itself the suffering and stress
itself we can learn when the Dua actually doesn't arise when we expected it to arise or we can uh we can learn
from that process of being with Duca understanding it seeing it
observing it reflecting on it and then watching it fade and let go it won't be
here with us forever
so uh to conclude briefly the task of the first Noble Truth is to understand
Dua and we can practice it in these three modes hearing and learning reflecting and cultivating and
developing this is the beginning of an ennobling path of the four noble truths
and we'll talk more as we carry on tomorrow with a second Noble
Truth take care wishing you a happy New
Year