okay so today I would like to talk about Buddhist
pilgrimage and the Catalyst for that was I just finished doing a Buddhist
pilgrimage so it's very fresh in my mind and and very much a part of my heart and
so I'd like to just speak what's what's up for me the simplest definition maybe of a
pilgrimage um that I kind of like is that um a pilgrimage is where a outer
journey and an inner Journey um intersect and support each other and so
but conventionally pilgrimages are often relate uh associated with going to a
sacred site and so they're spiritual nature not everyone well some people
think that uh our life itself is a pilgrimage some people will call pilgrimage
something which is not necessarily spiritual but that's often the association and um I've been on I've
walked four pilgrimage routes in my life two of them
were not a pilgrimage for me there was other people's pilgrimage
routes so they were people of other religions would enter into it in a deep way because it was deeply connected to
their faith and I went along those partly because they were spiritual I felt to that was
an important part of why I was there but I didn't share the same spirituality as
them and so the Resonance of that part wasn't that strong for me and I've been on two which were
Buddhist pilgrimages and they were actually part of my faith part of my spirituality and
really felt be important parts of it and um one of them just ended two days ago
so so um that was quite lovely the
um uh so um so pilgrimages involved kind of
an inner and an outer aspect and uh and the outer one is one
that uh is connected to the places we go to the out outwardly one of the kind of
simple definitions of a added definition to a pilgrimage is uh walking to a
sacred site to a sacred Temple sacred place and then maybe walking back is
also part of the pilgrimage a pilgrimage is a time when you're we're separating ourselves from life as
usual and uh work and home and all these kinds of things that we leave behind so
we enter into kind of a different way of being in the world and it's little it's has a lot of
overlaps with going on a retreat where there're also the that we leave our home
behind we leave our work behind life as usual in order to be able to experience
life experience ourselves uh independent from the how those influence us or
condition us or or weigh us down or something and it takes a while both on a
pilgrimage and on a retreat to let ordinary life settle away to pass away and not be so pressing on us and then
something else can start happening the um
uh and so the pilgrimage that I just finished uh did have a kind of a sacred
site there was going to but it was both uh this pilgrimage began at a sacred
site and kind of ended at one and um and so we were walking between these two
places and on land that some people considered to be sacred land and um I'm
happy to call it that when I walked on it so um the sacred land was um Mount
Tamal payas in Moren County and um one of the people on the
pilgrimage with us uh was following in the foot in other times had done a lot
of following in the footsteps of a kind of a sacred pilgrimage that was started
by the beatniks that um Gary Snyder and different people in the 1960s started a
pilgrimage around uh Mount Tam circumambulating Mount Tam and that's
been going on for years and now I think it's kind of uh an abyss but but but
some of the one of the people I've been involved in has done that now a number of time and there's a book about it and she follows the route of the
book so she was on the right on the pilgrimage it was there was 10 10 of us doing it
together and um so and going from we went from from kind of over mount mount
alayas from Spirit Rock Meditation Center to green gold Center both
Buddhist centers where I've taught where I've practiced important places for me personally and and U I would consider
them sacred sites and uh and uh it was a wonderful
in both places uh we were uh offered Hospitality one of the characteristics
often of pilgrims pilgrimages the pilgrims are guests of everybody and
they're kind of uh received by the people who get along as and receive
Hospitality it's not always that way but but that's often uh one characteristic of it and so the the pilgrims usually go
with certain kind of humbleness um as a as you would guest into someone's house you don't go in
there and demand that they you know that instead of serving you um spinach salad
that should have been some other you know you know SP kind of the wrong kind of salad dressing you're using for me
here I demand you know like a restaurant you might go in and demand like it's you know something but you know you're a
guest someone's home there's a humility or humbleness and receptivity of being a guest so to be that kind of guest
walking through the lands and uh putting aside your status
for example with your work and your place and just being a kind of a humble person the word pilgrim comes from a
kind of a Latin word that kind of suggests being more like a servant
and um and so a certain kind of way of walking with Simplicity usually uh uh pilgrims don't go with a
lot and um so it was very nice because that's we received the hospitality from
Green Gulch first from Spirit Rock and uh we slept in the meditation Hall they
have you know nice residence halls but they were they didn't offer us that and U it was lovely then to sleep
the meditation Hall and and then uh when we came to Green Gulch Zen Center uh we also slept in
meditation Hall there and um and U the difference was at Spirit Rock um no one
was using meditation Hall the next morning at Green they wake up Bell starts in the meditation Hall at at
quter to 5: and it's we had to be out of there by then so we had to get up early
which was part of the charm of it all and then we slept two nights on Mount
Tam because we took our time with the walk and it's exquisitely beautiful and um so it was um uh so that
was that was the our our pilgrimage and
um and in the process to that the land played a very important role uh for us
certainly for me uh the land the trees we had a Bist along who told us little
bit about the plants as we went along and I learned that uh the redwood trees which are a big part of that area um are
Apparently one of the oldest continuously present species of living
beings on the planet and that uh the redwood trees as a Genus goes back to
the jurass uh Jurassic times so 200 million years ago and the species we
have go back to the crustacean time which could be about 100 million years ago and and coincidentally I learned
that a very big redb tree has a 100 million leaves it's kind of astounding to me and
uh the scale of time the scale of kind of complexity and the these redber trees
are so beautiful and so so so tall some of them that we saw and so the
pilgrimage in the scale of time that we're part of the scale of um and then
also to to see as we went along and botanist pointed it out so it stood out kind of
wonderfully that um um uh how the
plants uh are shaped by the environment they're in the way they were evolved and
you can clearly see that because all the understory plants they all you know they
have a problem with getting enough light so they're all flat going directly up to the sky and you can see how they were
all shap created in shapes that helped them find light and but because the larger trees were kind of it didn't
leave other choices for them to evolve and so this way that we're and so humans
as well we've evolved uh as as a species um conditioned by the land the
environment the natural world in which we've lived in and been in and so I as I
was walking along the pilgrimage I thought of uh one of American one of the
anthems of the United States for some people uh Woody Guthrie's uh song that
uh and but I had to CH I wanted to change the last the the refrain to
um this land uh made you and
me this is a land that made you and me if you've been here in the United States for more than seven
years probably to some degree or other you've been made by
this and uh it's very nice sound and
um so
um so the idea of going someplace and then walking and there's something about
walking the movement of walking the sematic experience of walking that
loosen us loosens us up it creates a kind of different different way of being on the land than driving a car is a
different way of Being Alive walking outdoors in beautiful natural
environment then um and then then being um where the real estate is a computer
screen you know that's a very small piece of real estate to spend the time with everything focused on which some
people work that way and spend hours each day doing focusing on this little screen the little piece of real estate
that calls on so little of our phys ology a little of our body and our senses and experience of life and uh and
who we are in relationship to that screen is very different than how most people feel who they are in relationship
to a natural world the forest the ocean the the rivers the the trees the
mountains that we all went through these last days and uh for one thing I reflect on
is that when I came back I did go on my laptop and I looked at my screen and wonder how am I different here and I
could feel how uh how I was bigger than whatever the screen is I'm like a big
thing the screen is only I don't know a square foot or something at the most and uh and it's um you know I'm big and
substantial and and I'm alone there's something about the Solitude of being in
relationship to a screen even though my wife was in the house there was something about those very different
compared in contrast to being Out outdoors where all the senses are open
and there's this huge receptivity that develops over time the walking is a lubricant or is a massage is a it kind
of uh opens things up step after step after step and just you always have to
take into account what's around you and uh many times the trail was not
completely even so there's a constant call your whole body is being sh how it
moves through space is constantly being adjusted and changed on all these little micr muscle ways you know little
adjustments with the ankles and the where the foot comes down the knees and which muscles are activated and which uh
what what an environment you're tuning into are you tuning into things through the ears are you tuning in through the eyes and what are you tuning to the
ground the trees the sky the birds the ocean and it's a constant shifting of
all kinds of things and the whole body is involved completely in a way that I'm sure your
body is completely involved uh in your
laptop but it's not it's probably not as fluid and and open and flowing and it's
probably getting more and more tense sometimes and you know kind if you if you spend a lot a lot of time on doing
the same thing with your body things begin to stiffen up so this wonderful kind of way in which a pilgrimage is
built into it is is walking walking walking and hours of
walking and uh uh we uh walked in silence before lunch so to walk with a
group of people together there's something of bonding that happens when we spend time together in silence you
get to know each other differently there's a kind of feeling of of way of
tuning into people when you don't have to be figuring out what to say or or how
what how to respond to what they're saying there's a kind of sense of camaraderie and commonality and
something very I think for me very touching about that kind of experience not so many people are
willing to spend a hours you know six hours or something in the morning or maybe not that way probably four hours
that we spent um in silence as we walked we did talk occasionally like learning
how old the redwood trees are and um and we had a little rituals
we did very little simple rituals we did uh as we went along that involved some
speech and um the um and so the because of the
outer silence it affects the inner silence and it was like being on a
retreat or meditating where the inner landscape became highlighted and uh became much more
aware of my thoughts much more aware of my feelings my Sensations and there became an inner silence an
inner Stillness started to develop being in this out this having this silence as we walked being in touch with an
environment that uh I don't know if you would say was a silent environment but
it was so spacious and so uh supportive that it kind of
contributed to kind of a inner receptivity and inner silence and that was a very important part of this
pilgrimage an outer silence that supports an inner silence an inner silence that supports an outer
silence and as I went along the little slogan I had for myself
that became very rich to reflect on kind of a or practice
phrase was um um love teaches us to say
yes to everything wisdom teaches us
what to say yes to in every situation so we're not saying yes to
everything just automatically there's things we shouldn't say yes to but even so even in those situations there's
still something we can say yes to and so what is it we can say yes to even in
challenging situations even in situations where you don't agree with someone and one one of the things was
was um uh yes I'll I'll listen to
you you know this isn't exactly the conversation I want to have but yes I
don't know if I agree but but yes I'll listen as we walked along yes I'll
listen why not the bird I listen to the birds I listen to the ocean I listen to The Creeks yes and so there's a very
different orientation to have this yes knowing that I disagree knowing in
certain ways you know that I would say no or something but yes you know to live with a yes that I
felt that was kind of like how do I say yes here where is the yes that I can live
with as opposed to the for some of us uh sometimes the automatic policy is no you
know you know no no no but yes to live a life of yes I felt to me it was a
wonderful piece of aill pilgrimage to do this pilgrimage route and then we had uh a Buddhist
teacher at at Spirit Rock gave a little short Dharma talk to us to begin the
journey and uh and that was an kushman who has spent uh years studying
pilgrimages and done Buddhist pilgrimages in India and so she was you know familiar with us and then we were
um uh at um Greeno one of the senior teachers there met us
and gave us a short talk and both places we meditate a little bit with the teachers and then we we met and um they
gave a short talk and so it's kind of like bookended the whole thing with this wonderful um you know receiving
teachings as we went along and the zen teacher gave this beautiful teaching
that is from a kind of a co- and uh the Japanese Buddhist tradition of um it's kind of a fable I
think but you decide uh the Buddha himself was out for
a walk with his students maybe he was in a pilgrimage and um and he stopped at some
location and he pointed to the ground and he said this is the place to build a
sanctuary a sacred site apparently the the phrase can also mean uh the way it's
translated in English is sanctuary apparently the Japanese words can also mean um a place for enlightenment place
for Liberation this is the place and so the Indra who is the was was I don't
know if he still is uh the one of the most powerful gods in the Indian
Pantheon um heard this and and was coming following along I guess on the walk and you know somehow came down from
his Celestial domain and and uh and plucked a a blade of grass out from
somewhere and planted that blade of grass into the spot the Buddha had pointed to and said the sanctuary is
built and the Buddha smiled that's the story and so uh and the and the teacher
talked about the Z teacher talked about um uh how Indra being the most powerful
God in the Indian Pantheon could have just you know snapped his finger and created a huge Palace a cathedral you
know real building as the sanctuary but he just took some some of the most most
humble simple ordinary thing that is right there I suppose a piece blade of
grass and put it in the spot and I made the sanctuary and so one interpretation of
this for pilgrims is that every step is the sacred site it's not about going to a
sacred site it's not about leaving a sacred site it's about finding the sacred site in every step every
step is uh is something very uh precious and valuable to be present just for that
and so part of the task of a pilgrim is maybe a Buddhist Pilgrim that maybe a
Zen Buddhist Pilgrim but is to find what does it mean how do we discover the
tremendous value you the power the spirituality the
sacredness of one step of the place we're standing the place where our foot comes down this particular moment here
and now and it certainly requires a certain kind of humility humbleness it
requires certain receptivity it requires a certain uh
quietness in the mind where we're not caught up in our thoughts and concerns
so much that we miss the missed the moment we missed the footstep we're not here for
it and um and it uh certainly requires some kind of feeling of the value the
specialness of really being here in the place we're at and uh part of that specialness for
Buddhists is to appreciate the possibility of Liberation freedom from attachments from clinging
from self preoccupation self building up the self um defending the self
um preoccupied with the future preoccupied by the past finding some Liberation from all that which is not an
easy thing to do I think one of the characteristics of many people's lives
is preoccupation with some aspect of these things but to find it with every
step and there's something about walking all day along through the natural world
that um that contributes to that contributes to that contributes to
that uh somehow the scale of our life and what's important changes in that
world so we W part of what we walked along was um the Marine Headland Cliffs
and you amazing we had good weather it's amazing view of the ocean uh you know
going far far out we had him uh you know the other thing that I loved about the
pilgrimages was how much how friendly people were to us as we went along they
were people we encountered and even if they didn't know we were doing a pilgrimage people were just friendly out
there and um some of them were were uh County employees who were doing their
different work that they had to do and they were just so happy to be there and meet us and walk with talk with us or
answer our questions about what they were do what they were doing and um and then also uh what was
nice was that we were a pilgrim group and as we walked we and through
the days we started bonding together and uh becoming more and more it felt like
now we're not just a group of people doing the same thing we're a group of people sharing a certain sensitivity a
certain mutuality a certain sacredness a certain kind of like we've come together
some of the some some of us we never met before never met each other before and
um and uh but you know and the the um
the the kind of peak time for that really felt like a gel was um there were
um uh there were two nights we slept out um on Mount Tam and sleeping bags and
Tents and um and the second night there was a picnic table we had our dinner we'
finished everything the evening was coming to a close and we all just sat around the picnic table and there was a
feeling as it was getting darker that we were it was a full moon uh and uh we
were all kind of like we were now jelled into kind of a single kind of a single
body there was you might say for a group of people kind of like we were all now on the same page sharing the same thing
same same kind of sensibility and feeling very connected to each other and um
so and probably partly because we had walked so much together we were sharing
the sacredness of this land and this purpose that we're doing and because of
the of um you know that the the strong
connection we had to this to the practice that we all had everyone was a
practitioner so we spend time meditating together sometimes during the day we'd come to these spots that just seem like
the right place to meditate and we'd sit there and meditate there's a place called I don't know if you know some of
you might know it Cataract Falls it's one of the great hikes in the Bay Area so we walked up Cataract Falls and
halfway up there's a great waterfall and we we sat there on the hillside
meditating and so these things can
happen right here in the Bay Area and what made it a pilgrimage in a
sacred pilgrimage was uh the intention the purpose and the kind of context in
which it was created and um it was created last year this is the second
year we've done it and um before that this pilgrimage didn't
exist all Buddhist countries have uh uh pilgrimage routes as far as I know in
Asia most religions like maybe all major religions have pilgrimage routes and I
don't think there's been too much of this or any much of this I don't know any of this in United States yet so it
was high time that we have one here in in California and so now we have
one and uh the idea is to make it longer and so this year last year we did uh
Spirit Rock to green gold the Zen Center and this year we actually walked a little bit further to Rodeo
Beach and ended there and then uh the idea is to make slowly make it the is to
try to spend as many nights in meditation halls or Buddhist temples as we make our way down the coast and maybe
eventually make to um our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz or or or further make it
all the way to tahara T Sahara is deep in the Los padris National Wilderness tasara Zen
Center and uh so I don't know how long that would take but but it's um a lot shorter than the
El Camino that people know in in Spain so maybe will get away with
it so um that was what I did for my vacation kind of my for my
pilgrimage so hopefully that was nice for you to hear and um if you have any
questions you want to ask about it um be happy to try to
respond good morning Gil um mine is less of a question but more of a comment on
your uh your talk today it if uh I couldn't help but draw the analogy that
uh if the sacred sight equal Enlightenment and each medit um each step was the
sight uh revered a sight it would be each meditation would be the step and
even more each moment of our lives would be a step and how also you said how
difficult that would be yes I I completely agree with you I think that's the all you know that's definitely the
conclusion of this practice is to realize that every every meditation you're sitting in the place of Awakening
it's a sanctuary every step every every thing you do and um uh so that's the
goal some of us need some help and uh and pilgrimage is one of the
ways to get that help because it's not just going on retreat but it's you're you're living kind of a life in the
world walking and encoun ing things and and so there it's really palpable that
this is what you're doing and then hopefully we learn from that we imprint that becomes imprinted in us so that
when we go back home that we bring that with us through appreciate that every
sip of water is a pilgrimage
and you're welcome to ask anything else too it doesn't have to be a pilgrimage
Gil has been a long time but I've done the Cataract Trail a couple of times and it's it's a
very wonderful place I was glad to hear that you've done
it
sure let's see if this yeah this is better uh and the waterfall there counts
as a body of water you could say um and you saw a view of the ocean I think you said as well I saw in the news yesterday
I just saw the headline um about what makes bodies of water so
peaceful for us to um be next to I didn't read the article just saw the
headline uh and I I resonated with that cuz I I myself find bodies of water to
be very peaceful I just loveed to be to be there but I don't know why any thoughts on
that why are bodies of water peaceful the
um maybe I want answer the question directly the way he asked but uh this
last year there's been a few times where I've been in situations where people had to kind of introduce
themselves with a little bit about their background where they come from and there story of their life and I've told
my life story or you know short version of it or so many times that I'm not that
interested in it anymore so it's not like my so so I was so I I I I was I had
time to reflect before I was going to do this introduction to myself and uh and
um and other people were doing theirs first so it was kind of interesting to hear other people's introductions and
then have that reflect back to understand myself in a different way based on what they said and by the time
it was my my turn I didn't want to tell any stories or any conventional ways it just didn't wasn't really relevant for
me but what was most relevant what I felt most was um at that the last I
guess six months where this has been an issue is um
um how how have I been shaped by places in
nature uh and uh one of those ways that I feel when I was doing this reflection
is bodies of water you know they I spent a lot of my life on water and it's been
a really big theme throughout my life you I was born on the coast coastal town in Norway and um there's a lot of time
on water and Fs and this there some of these FS can be so peaceful so calm when
there's no wind and so the the calm bodies of water I feel like have shaped
me there's something that lives in me in a way that that um the spaciousness the
openness the expansiveness of of peace or calm that uh seems to kind of kind of
um impact something in my chest where the chest becomes similar something in
my chest gets peaceful and quiet and peaceful um why that is I don't know but
uh so you're asking why but um the uh certainly has had a big impact
so certainly water I know that was an odd question thank that's a great answer thanks so something some of you might
want to reflect on is how would you tell your life story uh from the point of
view of the places you lived as opposed to you know what you
did and um right thanks to you
hi this is Ashwin uh we just recently completed uh Everest Base Cam
tracking and I wish we had thought of some of the ideas that you mentioned
such as walking in silence for half day and stopping at different spots and
doing the meditation and have purposeful
conversations uh so I I I think it's a wonderful thing uh looks like and uh
maybe IMC will organize some such either hikes or pilgrims that uh non-teachers
maybe or others can participate in it and explore this further great thank you yeah there's a there is some people who
have uh organized hikes and U and um
Kristen uh Benson has offered a couple this last year she was trained to be an
e chaplain and so she's offered hikes that that have brought together some of these things
and I don't know if she's planning to she does it on the soul St or Equinox time so I don't know if she's planning
to do it in um you know the summer solstice but keep keep keep an eye on the newsletter to see but it's a it is
do more of it and and um and then um you know maybe with
uh with um if this pilgrimage route gets developed all the way down to
you know south of here some point it has to go through the peninsula and U so either either you'll
have to wait till it gets that far and then you can join or maybe we'll do it develop it in
sections and uh don't know if that we can just try finding sections on the peninsula to make and then we can later
connect it to create a peninsula P
pilgrimage I have a quick question um I just came back from a sacred Place Salt
Lake City and um was um IMC came to mind
in Buddhist practices because I really was challenged in different ways in terms of what I witnessed and I tried to
have um a curiosity should I move um and
an openness and I continued to have my challenges so I'm just curious any
thoughts um in terms of my struggles with that experience of mine Al so I
don't quite understand but I think what you're saying is that uh you came out of maybe maybe a religious situation that
has it had problems um no I'm not I don't practice
I I just went on vacation to Salt Lake City and um I I struggle with aspects of
that faith I don't practice it right but just the history and the unfolding and
um the hierarchy and treatment of women and um so you're um commenting on
um kind of an openness a having a more of a curiosity versus a a
judgmental is kind of how I interpret it um so yeah so you so again I think I I
appreciate very much what's behind your question sounds like you're asking a very important question not sure my
answer will respond and we can talk more later but the um um
um I have I have Mormon friends and number so I know some of the you know
who grew up that way and and so I know some of the challenges that they have
with their own religion and or some of them have left their religion and but those challenges are not that maybe the
maybe the nuances the details are a little different but almost every religion probably every religion has
some of the same problems and you don't have to you don't have to you you don't have to kind of look very for long or
very far to see problems with Buddhism as a religion as well Buddhism is not free of this as well um but I've uh I've
in terms of this idea of you know saying yes to everything um so yes there's problems in
religions and uh there's a lot of goodness in people as well so I I was i'
I've noticed that there's a a lot of uh generosity a lot of
friendship a lot of Ethics in among Mormons that I've met that have inspired
me and I know some of the difficulties as well but I really like to orient
myself around that which resonates with me and that which inspires me in it because that's that's a way of
supporting more of that than the world uh to only Orient ourselves towards it to the problems is uh is kind
of limits the ourselves because then we're resonating with what the problem
is and the distress that causes us and I don't know if we grow from that as much
as we do resonating what's good but what's what's very important is not to be polanish you know and just ignore the
problems I think there's a real tremendous importance to see it clearly
and then but not to be limited by it or or or in any kind of way but to actually
find where where is the spiritual growth happening and um and one of the ways to
be inspired that's not the right word but one motivation that I have from when I
see things that are terrible in the world is that uh it inspires me to do
better and it reminds me that that the world I want to live in is the world
that needs to begin with me so if so so that you know rather than waiting for
someone else to fix the world at least we try to fix our own world the world that born is born out of us and so if um
if other people are being unethical I would like to live in a world that's ethical and so that then I have to look
at myself has it come for me in the world with at War I want to live at peace at War where there's conflict I
want to live with Concord so how do I live and promote Concord coming out of
me rather than participating in the conflicts in the world so is does this
little bit answer your question oh no it it very much answers very inspiring thank you okay
great great so thank you so it's now the official time to
stop he I'm happy to stay up here if you have some more comments or questions but uh I hope to see some of you at the at
the picnic and um thank you for being here