morning I say good morning it's morning for me but I recognize it's not morning
for everybody and as you can see by the title that uh for this week these five
days I want to talk about the inner critic and I'll start by just doing a
definition of the inner critic and maybe I'll start by saying not everybody has
this inner critic so many people do but not everybody does so I don't want to
you know universalize it and feel like oh if you don't really know what I'm talking about then uh you're not uh
somehow with the program or something like this no no no just some people have it and some people don't and it's kind of like a um maybe
we might even say like a sub personality inside of us if I could use that type of
a language this way which it's constantly putting us down and belittling us and this voice of negativ
that's blaming ourselves and nagging at us and has this uh maybe a pervasive
sense of Shame Shame for what we are how we are who we are or maybe there's also
a uh climate or an attitude of harshness kind of creates this environment this
internal environment where we're really harsh with ourselves and when this inoc is up and
running there's a feeling of in advocacy like somehow I'm just whoever who I am
is not enough or how I am is not enough or somehow I'm not worthy or in some
kind of way this feeling of inadequacy that can result from this uh inner
critic and wow there's so much pain so much Dua associated with this structure
that uh this constellation this Dynamic that uh many people
have and so today I want to start with um a guided meditation that's uh
designed to kind of like disarm the inner critic and part of how we're going
to do this is maybe with a meditation that's not the usual
meditation partly because uh the usual meditation probably the inner critic if
there is one has already co-opted it and is already like oh you can't do this right or it's your it's hard for you and
it's easy for everybody else or you're not doing it good enough or it's
something like this there's a way in which uh this might even be so familiar to us we don't even recognize
it so I want to introduce uh an meditation practice that uh can be
incredibly powerful and transformative and not in the way that we're expecting
it and maybe part of its power is because we're not expecting
it so I learned this uh meditation practice from Sharon solsburg and she said that she learned
it from a 94 year-old Sri Lankan monk 94 years old who had an incredible amount
of energy and was enormously happy this sounds fantastic right somebody who's 94
years old with lots of energy and happiness this is what we all want for our lives
right and this person did this meditation which um i' like to share
with you and I want to say maybe before we launch into this maybe you're a
little bit curious like okay well what is this Diana but um before we launch
into it I want to say that it's
um an opportunity where we can put the maybe this logical or this reasoning
or this thinking mind it can allow it to observe and be present but maybe I kind
like maybe diminish or dampen some of the way it protests and
criticizes and um so allow the thinking mind maybe to relax or soften here
because if you were to think about it too much you would think like what this is such a weird meditation why are we
doing this but don't you know that's okay if that feeling comes up but um
we'll just uh engage in this anyway and why not just run a little
experiment discover for yourself come and see how is it for yourself uh to do
this so I feel like I have to before I launch into this I have to like put some
um I don't know what's the word uh I I can't think of what the word is but uh
like this really long preface before really just jumping into this meditation
so with all those uh caveats uh before Let's uh let's start we'll meditate
so so taking a meditation posture a posture that
has some uprightness and some
ease and this uprightness can be literally or
figuratively I'm just taking a moment to feel into the bodily experience at
this moment
does it feel to be in this body at this
time just in
general and we allow however the body is to be how it is
because it is how it
is and I'm going to guide us some meditation and you
can repeat silently after
me as I lead us in a type of body
scan a body scan that incorporates some well-wishing some
warmth May the head be
happy May the hge be
peaceful may my eyes be
happy may my eyes be
peaceful May the shoulders be
happy May the shoulders be
peaceful May the arms be
happy May the arms be
peaceful May the hands be
happy May the hands be peaceful
May the upper back be
happy May the upper back be
peaceful
May the lower back be
happy May the lower back be
peaceful I'm using this expression May the body
part as an [Music] invitation maybe less a supplication and
more an invitation for that body part to be
happy without thinking about this too
much may the chest be
happy
May the chest be
peaceful May the belly be
happy May the Bell be
peaceful so it's a little bit less thinking and more well-wishing
warm-heartedness May the hips be
happy May the hips be
peaceful May the legs be
happy May the legs be peaceful
May the feet be
happy May the feet be
peaceful working our way back up May the legs be
happy May the legs be
peaceful May the hips be
happy May the hips be
peaceful May the belly be
happy May the belly be
peaceful May the chest be
happy May the chest be peaceful
May the lower back be
happy May the lower back be
peaceful May the upper back be
happy May the upper back be
peaceful May the hands be happy
May the hands be
peaceful May the arms be
happy May the arms be peaceful
May the eyes be
happy May the eyes be
peaceful May the head be
happy May the head be
peaceful and then is there any area of the
body I could use some care some good will some
warm-heartedness
e
and then to continue at your own
pace maybe modifying the words if you'd like but keeping it very
simple to do a gentle body [Music]
scan up and down the body
with well wishing warm-heartedness towards different parts of the
body
e
[Music]
for [Music]
good morning good
morning today we'll start this um Journey on looking
at the uh inner critic and in this guided meditation I
used a way in which we can maybe like a subvert uh the critic because maybe it's
such a integral part of our meditation practice like oh you're you're no longer
on the object you're lost in thought or you know there could be this way in which these little pervasive thoughts
just show up in our regular meditation so I thought it'd be helpful to do a little bit of a different meditation
that keeps the mind busy gives it something to do so this uh inner critic
isn't busily uh chattering and not only that can provide a sense of spaciousness
and warmth which is what's needed if we're going to work with this inner
critic so again I'll describe this inner critic a little bit as maybe it's
something like a sub personality inside of us this way in which it's like
constantly putting us down and belittling us it's a voice of negativity
that's blaming ourselves and nagging at us and maybe it has a sense of
Shame Shame for what we are or how we are or who we are or maybe there isn't n
a sense of Shame with it maybe it's just a bunch of criticizing but one thing that this
inner critic has is a sense of harshness like it's not warm and
friendly it's a sense of uh you know you're not good enough you have to do
more there's this feeling of a inadequacy of I'm not enough who I am is
not enough or I'm not worthy and maybe those words aren't so explicit but it's
this attitude that's often like Just Happening kind of like as this running
narrative in the back of the mind or accompanying our daily life what
whatever it is that we're doing and wow G be so much duka
associated with this and and for some people it's so prevalent and such an
ongoing part of their inner world that it's even hard to imagine that it can't be there or it's even hard to imagine
that it can diminish or maybe there's a way in which they have a certain loyalty
to it and their real hesitation to even put it down or to look at it and we can
honor this and respect that we're not trying to critique the critic we're not
trying to say like oh I shouldn't be there right that's just more of the same but today I want to emphasize that
it's understandable that people have have this this inner critic this
self-critic I think uh I wouldn't be remiss in saying that it's a cultural
phenomena something that we've learned that we've conditioned from our family
from our education from society from culture and I think it's can be
enormously helpful to not blame oneself that we have this inner Dynamic that we have this type of a tone in what's our
inner life and to be sure some people feel like it's just them that they are
the only ones that have this inner critic and when I just started um to
train to be a retreat teacher and to be a meditation teacher and I was sitting
in on practice discussions that other teachers were doing this was quite a big uh Revelation
for me was to recognize oh this is such a common theme when people come to talk
about uh their practice with teachers they're under they don't use this language necessarily explicitly but
underneath is this sense of like I'm not doing it right there's something wrong
with me everybody else seems to have it okay but there's something that's uh
inadequate with me I have a problem this is so prevalent and we have this idea
that we're unusual we have this we think that we're the only ones that were unusual to have this persuasive inner
critic and we mistakenly believe that we're the only ones that have this naging negative
stories but it's not true it turns out that so many of us are
walking around trying to convince everybody like okay I got it together I know what I'm doing I'm not really
messed up as sometimes I think that I am not everybody has that I a but there's often this sense of like okay I got it
together when inside we don't feel like we have it together and in fact one of
the most healing outcomes is When people's realize oh they're not the only
ones with this inner critic in fact it's so common I don't
want to say everybody has it because not everybody has it but uh it's so common
it is so common and I think as part of the pandemic we started to have more
group practice discussions on these uh online Retreats and um I Heard and saw
either explicit or kind of like you know implicit people recognizing like oh
other people have these thoughts too and they start to hear what other people were saying in these practice
discussions and there's a certain amount of healing that happened like oh I'm not the only one and I can say it's
important to know that we're not the only one because right there's this way there can be the critic of the
critic this inner critic kind of co-ops even looking at the inner critic and
there's the inner critic of the inner critic and then right there's the inner critic of the inner critic of the inner critic and off it
goes but today I'd like to just mention or point to that we can let ourselves
off the hook for the conditioning we received for the conditioning we
received or the cultural conditioning societal biological familial like all the
different forces that were present from when we were born until an adult but
certainly in our early years like we didn't ask for this particular body
shape color size we didn't request this particular mind that has these habits
that are unhelpful these UNH helpful patterns or we didn't select from a catalog okay I like this
emotional style and this way of thinking and this certain appearance and these
challenges in our lives none of us did that we didn't ask for all these things
that uh had such a giant impact on the way that we are as adults now it's kind
of this uh cultural conditions just the things that uh for formed and shaped who
we are so we don't have to blame ourselves for all these unhelpful
patterns and idiosyncrasies and ways that we show up in the world we don't
have to blame ourselves it's due to conditioning with uh Buddhist teachings
we know that everything's due to conditioning but so often there's a way in which we kind of not intentionally
but think like oh yeah there's all this conditioned stuff but somehow I'm responsible for the way that I am that's
not conditioned it's my fault no we have this conditioning and
it doesn't mean we don't have responsibility we have
responsibility for working with the cards that we were dealt we didn't deal them to ourselves but that's the hand
that we got and it's our responsibility to work with them and this is part of where this uh meditation practice and
Buddhist practice can help with is help us to take responsibility and to
recognize that change is possible of course it is like otherwise
we wouldn't have a meditation practice if we didn't think that it would be of any benefit and that anything could ever
change of course we can so we don't need to believe these
thoughts of the inner critic we don't need to give them the attention they're demanding we don't need to hold them in
a really high by Authority and think that there the truth and all other um
data or experiences that we have somehow don't count because we have this inner critic we think that must be the
absolute truth instead we can offer kindness to
ourselves we can offer warmth to ourselves we can offer care to
ourselves and for some this will be a radical idea and for some it will be a journey
it's not something that we're going to just you know have this inner critic go away but it starts with recognizing that
it's here in a lawful way because there is this conditioning and in fact we could just
notice how often there is this subtle message that comes from outside of us
comes from our environment saying that oh we should be different somehow and
I'm not saying that we're absolutely perfect we shouldn't change anything but it can be enormously helpful to just
notice how prevalent this message is how many books are there trying to
help us improve something how many podcasts are there
soing that you should improve something how many
conversations do we have in which one person is putting themselves
down how many movies are there how many television programs how many fictional
stories include somebody who's putting themselves down who thinks that they're
not worthy or isn't good enough in some kind of way it's so
common this idea this oh let alone talk about the whole advertising industry
that's its whole intention is to you know some give you a sense of inadequacy
so that you feel like you need more more more and of course whatever it is that they're trying to sell so part of you
know their whole message is the sense of inadequacy and lack so I want to say there's nothing
wrong with wanting to change there's nothing wrong with wanting to improve
there's nothing wrong with saying yeah you know I have some unhelpful patterns I have some unhelpful h habits which
causes harm to myself and causes harm to others and I'd like them to be different that's healthy and perfectly
normal but what a difference it would be if we have this wanting to change that
comes out of care and comes out of warmth I care
about myself I care about others therefore I strive or I Endeavor or I
have a wish to modify something some of my behaviors because I care out of
respect for myself and respect for others as opposed to this loam I loathe
myself therefore I better be different oh so painful it's so
exhausting so I don't want to say that we're absolutely perfect but can we do do this um way of
um try of encouraging ourselves to modify ourselves a little bit or change
out of care and out of warmth and not giving into the inner critic that wants
to convince us that uh all kinds of terrible things it wants to convince us
but one is that somehow we're inadequate and have to change so two things I'd like to suggest
for today one just notice how prevalent this message is I'm not good enough that
comes from outside that we just hear from you know our society in whatever
ways or family members or books or movies or you know any media that uh we are consuming just notice like oh yeah
wow it's all over the place and maybe we hadn't noticed it before because it's so
normalized so that's one and the second thing that i' encourage that you might
like to explore and play around with today is when you not notice the inner critic inside like really ramping up and
getting really loud that you can hear it maybe you can just say I'm doing the
best I can right now I'm doing the best I can right
now I'm doing the best I can right now it's doesn't mean that in the next
moment you can do something different and it doesn't mean in the previous moment you did something different at
this moment right now this precise moment we're doing the best we can and there's a way in which that can
kind of like soften the inner critic and and as these days go long as this weeks
go on I'll work I'll explore and um share some different ideas that we can do but maybe we'll start with this today
otherwise we'll really activate the critic of the critic and that's not the direction we want to go so this moment
I'm doing the best I can right now and just notice how many messages there are are about you should be better H it's
awful so I'll end there and wishing you all a wonderful rest of the day or if
it's evening for you or what however what portion of the day Still Remains for you and tomorrow and I'll be back
here tomorrow and we'll talk about more about this inner critic thank
you
it's nice to see the comments thank you thank you well thank you well it's so
nice I wish I had an April Fool's Day joke or something to think about but I
didn't so this not an April Fool's Day message
here yes I'm doing the best I can right
now thank you all it's so lovely to practice together it's quite something
right that's you know after all these years this song that comes together it's a
great thing I think it's a great
thing thank you thank you all