so hello everyone hello and welcome to harier it's lovely to be with you ah SAA
Community how nice to be with community so the guided meditation I
want to invite us to engage with um is going to ha have to do with the theme of
community and shared um shared kindness shared
friendliness shared Goodwill that is shared it's reflected it's it's mirrored
um it's supported it's supported we don't do this practice alone if we if we're the only person doing this
practice of cultivation it would be hard but we're not alone We're Never Alone
even if we Imagine That We're Alone we're never ever ever alone we are
deeply deeply interconnected with with
other humans other beings this deep web of interconnection that we impact we we
have impact on we um impact how others feel and behave
and we can have a positive impact or negative impact and others have NE have impact on us too so so to really value
to really appreciate um that we are supported that we support
others um and that we matter we matter our actions
matter and especially um what's with what is
happening in the world our world um I I
saw this quote actually paraphrased quote from ramas that whether today is the first
day way of an apocalypse or or Utopia
well our task is still the same we still act as best as we can with Integrity
with kindness with Good Will in the world so um trusting that we impact
others and others support us other like like-minded like-hearted people so
coming together here in happy hour um it's a reminder um of the support so
that's the theme that's the theme our practice so with that let's
let's land let's arrive in our posture in our meditation
posture if you need to shift and move and maybe if you're sitting shift left and right front and back your shoulders
roll them back maybe your arms just to feel ah
your body and maybe move your ankles a little bit your feet your legs
befriending your body getting back in your body very important for
practice for us to embody inhabit our body and then when
you're ready come to Stillness feeling your feet if you're
sitting on a chair feeling your feet stable on the
earth a white stance feeling your hands touching one another or your
lap feeling your bottom on the cushion or the
chair sense of stability uprightness of the
body stable upright and relaxed Let the Body soften
starting with a few breaths receiving relaxing and receiving just a
few breaths to settle in the body embodiment first and foremost
St e
and if thoughts are arising with friendliness and the
smile say thank you not now we come back to you later giving my whole heart to this
practice of settling and cultivation right now
and connecting with the breath allowing it to be known and
received fully fully as fully as possible breath fully in the body
completely expanding with the breath in breath Contracting with the out breath
the body the abdomen
as if your life dependent on it which by the way it
does not dismissive or ignoring what your life depends on fully attending to the breath
the fullness of the breath however it shows
up
e
e e
now I'd like to invite you to consider as you are receiving the
breath feeling the breath in the body so that we stay embodied during this
reflection we don't go into our head become he and just involved with
thoughts but an embodied reflection drop this reflection in your
body feeling not thinking feeling that you
are connected you are connected deeply
intertwined connected in this web with other
beings bring a few beings perhaps your family and friends colleagues
to your heart space to your
mind not thinking again feeling as you were sitting with them in space
breathing with them in breath out
breath perhaps imagining this rbra of
your breath as actions that impact them your moods your words your
thoughts impact them and they too impact you support you vice
versa how we hold each other how we hold each other in this invisible web
how we are held by one another and again feeling the breath in
the body Let It Be
sensed and you don't have to think of action or words make it detailed but
just a sense of
interconnection co-creating our reality together our
world together feeling the breath in the body
even if you haven't interacted or talked or
written this web of people still you're deeply interconnected let yourself be
nourished by the goodness of it yes there are always ways we impact one another negatively but for now I'd like
to invite you to lean into the good or hearts and Minds have a tendency to go
for the negative and the mistakes and uh not right now not right now not
skillful stay with the wholehearted whole wholesome ways
we support care for love appreciate are grateful for one
another the way we inspire one
another and feel into it feel not so much think but
feel if it ever gets heavy drop it all just come back to the breath and the
body
you know what to
do again if your mind goes towards the negative drop it for now
please intentionally turn towards the skillful
ways you have been supported elevated
inspired the way you do that for
others
e
e e
too many stories and thoughts arise gently lovingly let them go come back to the
breath and the feeling of
interconnection
e e
and perhaps in your heart's mind you can imagine an embodied
game where you receive you catch a ball of goodness from
someone support care a phone call a
smile if there throwing you a golden ball of
care you receive it appreciate it then you transform this ball of care
Golden Ball of care kindness Goodwill
regard positive impact and you share it with someone
else you keep reive these balls and passing them on to
others perhaps imagine oh yeah lots of balls lots of balls are sent your way or
flowers if you prefer that imagery lots of golden flowers your
feet that so many have sent your way with their care
and you send flowers to others as
well of care goodness
e
e e
and as we turn to in this sitting
period I invite you to bring to your heart or it space the members of this
community happy hour Community are showing up either on Zoom or on YouTube or
listen later on the
web all of us supporting one another in this path connected to one
another through our Goodwill our
practice an invisible web of kindness goodness support
offering each other flowers of care through our
presence seen or unseen seen or
unseen and maybe in your heart saying thank you to those those in this community and
also your own network
dedicating the goodness trusting there's goodness here in our practice and dedicating sharing the goodness of this
practice with all beings to whom we are invisibly connected may all beings
everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be free including
[Music]
ourselves thanks everyone thank you for your
practice so today's invitation was
to practice with the support that we
receive the support that we give to others seen and unseen these gifts that
we have we have received from so many beings we continue to receive the gifts
we've given to so many beings and we continue to do that and I invited you in
this practice especially uh because the mind can sometimes go to all the mistakes we've
made the ways we have not been supported the ways we haven't supported others yes yes yes and and yet we know that our
minds as humans um have a tendency toward negativity much more than
positivity so just try to balance that a little bit with tonight's practice not
to say that it's not wholesome to perhaps have remorse or there challenges
or or forgiveness all those practices are good in their own right this is a different practice tonight I invited you
specifically to stay with the goodness really feeling the goodness of the
support and giving goodness and and earning our minds intentionally towards
that and this is part of the four wise efforts one of the wise four wise
efforts is uh bringing up wholesome States if they haven't Arisen
intentionally intending to bring them up to cultivate them to to nourish them so
that's what we were doing here so also feeling the goodness of
this community the connections we have here here we support one another in this
practice and see how your heart felt bringing a
sense of being supported by others and supporting others for me as I was practicing there's just goodness this
this feeling of oh yeah this person and that person wow there's a sense of
goodness that has supported me and of course not everything there's been so much support in my life and continues to
be like everyone one of your lives um you know all the inventions for
example Zoom has been inv invented and we can meet through it I consider that to be a support by person who invented
it and I'm invisibly connected to that to those groups of people actually not a person huge groups of people over time
who worked so hard to make this possible wow thank you so either directly or
family or friends loved ones um or indirectly just so many human beings we
benefit um from from their work from their Goodwill from their effort from
their intention from their hard work and the same for us so really appreciating
that um helps us feel less alone if we are feeling alone and again loneliness
is one of the number one issues in the US and and the world actually especially
the since the pandemic but anyway so now I like to invite us to engage in small
groups with um with one another as a way to bring our practice the rubber meeting
the road and the invitation is to practice
meta mea in small groups and um I will put that in chat
the guidelines so the invitation is to um
stay with um there we go uh M standing for mind
well meta of course and then M also standing for mindfully listening and speaking really considering the practice
of small groups as a continuation of the meditation embracing compassion if
internal resistance comes up or any reactions or discomfort both for yourself and for others so can you be
non-reactive and hold it with kindness whatever is coming up and staying on topic and the topic I
like to give you tonight is how what happened when you brought up
intentionally brought up um feeling supported by others and supporting
others was there particular imagery that worked for you or staying with the body what can support you in this practice
and again be brief take turns brief offer just one nugget um let others
offer nuggets or you can also hold silence just say a little bit and hold silence uh and maybe just showing up in
the group is a part of your Community Practice feeling the support of others maybe you start by saying thank you for
being here and practicing with me I feel your support right now um so it can be either in real time practice of holding
each other with support and care or reporting about what happened in your practice in your guided meditation in
the meditation that you sat and avoiding cross talk not giving
advice not commenting on other people's um experience so that we keep it really
safe for one another so so always practicing kindness good will taking
care of um each other taking care of Al ourselves and each other so I'm going to
create the rooms right now and let me check the
rooms um yeah let me hold on need to fix something
here be patient with me okay all right see if this is going to work I might
need to move some of you so I'm sorry if this is going to be Rocky I'll try to do it at the very beginning all right here
we go I'm going to open the rooms take care take care of yourself take care of one
another hey welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back and we
have some time for um Reflections and questions and you can
either raise your Zoom hand or you can also type in chat I'm going to open chat
now so Barbara uh your hand shut up what's
up oh I was just saying to my group something that I thought of it the last
second and I didn't have a chance to say it so I'll just say it to the whole group and that I so the the dental the
dental hygienist yesterday and he is uh
from Mexico and he said he's so sweet he said well how are you going are do you
have any plans for the holidays and I I said yeah how about you for are you
going to celebrate Thanksgiving he said no I'm from Mexico we don't celebrate
Thanksgiving and I said you don't what about
gracias and he goes his eyes got big and he said you're right that's Thanksgiving
said yeah go for it that's great that's
beautiful thank you Bara I I love I love how uh this this this friendliness I
mean basic first thing I'm just going to comment on what's the Unseen but in in
the frame is just this exchange this friendly exchange of of reflecting goodness back like oh yeah here you
already have that you already have this it's like oh yeah is reflecting the goodness of others and that's what you
were doing um yeah for for one another which is so lovely so lovely oh yeah
thanks for sharing this it uplifts my heart gracias alava exactly and which by
the way reminds me there isn't that there is a famous yes song by by
Mercedes Sosa uh uhuh yeah do you know that Barbara no
okay it's it's has given me so much that's it that's it
that's it that's what I was thinking that's the song It's a in fact I might ask um there's a particular version of
it which just it's oh it's so beautiful um I'll send it to okay uh I'll send it
to Neil Neil remind me if I don't um send it to you so they can send it to the Google Groups it's the B version it
just stops it's so beautiful yeah his point to me was just formulaic do you have any
you know plans but then I thought you know you too we all can give thanks
right and when he got it immediately he was like you're sweet yay thanks Barra
thanks for sharing this is so sweet gracious Elita lovely thank you very
sweet ah other Reflections Amy or Aloha
Amy Aloha that word itself is such a
interconnecting word here um I was to drop in with it I was like
picturing moments of like laughter or eye contact or
hugs um and that was really helpful uh
um historically I've uh like written down people's names
and then kind of went through and thought of things that I'm like grateful for moments I'm grateful for connections
I'm grateful for um or like even thinking through the Love Languages like oh this person I feel like met by like
words of service or you know Act of service or like you know those types of things and and I kind of like to I used
to do it for like a bunch of like the people I could think of in my life and that was really supportive so that might be something I try
TR again um I think laughter is the way we connect and it each
other gosh thank you thanks for sharing the practice that you used to do and and
I also appreciate you your inspiration to oh yeah I used to do this I was
really sweet and heartful and yeah that was supportive and yes why not let's do
it again because especially I'm going to say at this time in this time we we need
to uplift our heart and feel the support of one another um so important so that
we go we don't go towards the darkness too much of course not ignoring it but
so that we are more resourced through each other's um support that we can we
can take wholesome actions in the world so thank you Amy that's lovely and this
too right the darkness and this through this you know Beautiful Moments with our
Dharma Community here and you and everything so thank you thank you thanks
Amy aloha aloha is both hello and goodbye
right love it
Claire I just wanted to add sort of spin off what Amy was talking about at least
five years ago I was trying to to Mentor somebody and I noticed that she wasn't
very appreciative of the good things going on in her life anyway I got the bright idea of staring a gratitude list
via email and she and I and one other gal now have been circulating this list
for five years every day okay and what was really funny was that the first time
I did it I couldn't think of a thing that I was grateful for it was all I was
the one who needed it I thought I was giving it to them oh I love it oh my goodness that's that's that's great CL
it's been such a gift to me uh to get my mind to think in terms of what's working
and not well and what's not working and I so I want to pass it along as a tip to
others because it's been great for me so so sweet Claire I I just love it um
especially you know this this recognition that that also this this goodness if you wanted to do something
for someone else like oh yeah yeah I want to support this person like wow you're actually receiving more than you're giving in some ways right like I
need this like why so and it's often like that isn't it it's you know we give
we we receive in the giving it's not more than or less than it's it's we we
receive gift yeah giving is the gift it's yeah and that's how I feel about
happy hour you know it is it is a giving of my time and sharing the Dharma and yet I receive so much for being with the
community and practicing together and learning from you and being inspired so it's just makes my heart really happy um
every time I I come so thank you I want to thank you for all of you for your
practice and showing up and supporting one another yeah what what a beautiful Community what a beautiful beautiful
community and we've been going on for a while you know you mentioned Claire five years you've been doing the
the uh gratitude list which yay I'm inspired and that's so lovely and you
know we've been on online together uh for four and a half years now and and um
I think maybe seven years ago or seven and a half years ago something like that eight years I'm losing track I'm not
good with dates we started Happ hour um in person at at
U at IMC and four and a half years online so going going strong here we
are so dear ones I don't see any other hands I don't see any other Reflections
in chat so how about we uh yeah we dedicate them here unless maybe I'll
just keep maybe hold one pause give give a beat or any last minute if somebody's
like oh oh oh but I didn't want to say this to Feel Complete I usually don't talk but I do want to say this
going once going
twice okay all right so we can close with with appreciation and um yeah
gratitude appreciation gratitude feeling the support supporting others
being supported by others giving receiving giving is receiving receiving
is giving um yeah oh how sweet how beautiful may all beings
everywhere be happy be free including
ourselves thanks everyone appreciate you all thank you I am going to stop