so hello everyone and welcome and happy to be here with you
and so the topic this week is
gratitude and gratitude uh can be considered a
feeling first and foremost ideally there's a feeling a sense an
inner emotional quality of inspiration of a certain
kind that uh is the Awakening of gratitude within us it's possible to
calculate to understand that someone is doing something for us and to thank
them and uh and offer the words and it can be sincerely offered
but for some reason what the per person has done has not really enter deeply
into our body into our hearts uh to uh
evoke an emotion of gratitude an emotion of appreciation an em an emotion of uh
inspiration that would like to acknowledge what's happened with the words thank you or a bow that's of in
often can be an expression of gratitude and
um they um and so to feel
grateful and I don't think it's something that we want to make ourselves
feel but we create the conditions for it the conditions for for gratitude to
arise when something what beneficial for us
arises and in meditation uh the Ben benefits can arise
that are from the meditation itself we can feel calmer we can
feel more peaceful we could feel more settled we could feel more connected to
ourselves we more at home there's all these kinds of uh benefits that can come
and many others we I could list and and but they kind of arise they emerge they
slowly kind of settle in and it can feel like a gift and I think of meditation as we
practice it that it gives a rise to lots of gifts the gifts of a of uh a quieter
mind the gift of concentration the gift of clarity the
gift of understanding the gift of uh of loving
kindness or compassion all these things can arise and then when they arise and we feel
that benefit what are the conditions that allow us to feel grateful and one of those conditions is
feeling safe feeling that we're not contending with some threat feeling like
we're not feeling safe enough to allow something to relax the sense of caution
the sense of being on the defense the sense of uh IM imminent
danger maybe anxiety relaxes maybe fear
settles so to sit in a field of safety
is one of the functions of meditation and so today perhaps you can
call on that there might be dangers beyond the walls of your home or
place where you are there might be dangers lurking in the future and today where you're going
to go but to live with your
body caught in that danger is to
limit the intelligence the warmth the freedom the peacefulness to limit our
capacity to tap into deeper support for moving through our
day and so to sit appreciating whatever degree of
safety that's here and now at this very moment in this very place in the real
estate that you're sitting on that's all and if there is fear in
you there might also be over easily overlooked small places
within where it feels safe maybe your little finger feel safe
there's no threats to your little finger maybe your
earlobes maybe the back of your elbow maybe some part of breathing
and so to begin Gathering Together how you're safe in this
moment so that when the gifts
come something inside responds with
gratitude with acknowledgement that's deep enough that
something emotional is touched Within so to assume a meditation
posture and close the
eyes and even if you're feeling anxious even if you're feeling
tense to search through your body your mind your
heart for the little places the little moments of
safety the absence of fear the absence of feeling a
threat and if there are small Pockets here and there throughout your body
your
mind taking a few deeper breaths that connects all those
places almost as if breathing in deeply allows something inside to
touch all the places of safety
and as you exhale a settling
relaxing if it helps you can even say gently the word
safe for
breathing normally and seeing if any part of the
cycle of breathing has a feeling of safety in
it or touches some place of safety Within
and as if breathing is a needle sewing safety
together so peace safety as you
breathe
for
e
for for
perhaps saying safe as you
exhale and in the wake of safe the wake of
exhale open up to feel more deeply the depths of
yourself open up to allow
the deeper feelings Sensations to have
time
e
for
for for
the thinking mind will quickly go on to the next
issue the next preoccupation and not allow you time to
pause to feel and sense deeply into your
body maybe following the sensations of breathing deep in your
torso to feel and sense
maybe even an emotional Source
Within
for for
and feeling sensing inside
how you have benefited from this meditation the
goodness the pleasure of the meditation however
small are you a little more settled little more
relaxed calm
something eased up in
you do you feel more connected to
yourself allow yourself to feel these as gifts
gifts for the depths of your
being appreciating acknowledging those gifts
and if that appreciation comes out of the source of
your emotions might there be gratitude as
well
for for
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to make room for gratitude make room in your
heart make room in your torso your
chest in your
mind in the very at ude of
awareness aware in a grateful way grateful to be
aware a gratitude that has a quality of tenderness in
it gratitude that maybe has a desire to say thanks
gratitude that might contain seeds of of Love
kindness and to end this meditation with an this expression of gratitude
I thank all that supports my life the animate and inanimate support
for how I live I thank the generations of
ancestors and Elders whose labor and Care made my life
possible I am thankful I give thanks for the safety and resources I have in a
world where many people don't have
this I am grateful for the goodness which has fed my
heart I am grateful for whatever health I
have I am grateful for the people in my
life and may I find gratitude in the ordinary events of the
day may it be that simple gratitude sprinkled
through the day gratitude at the ordinary events of life
leads us to a greater appreciation and care for the people we will
encounter may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
[Music] thank
you
e e
so hello and welcome to this second talk on gratitude
thankfulness and uh today I want to talk
about gratefulness as a emotion or a feeling
that we have inside that uh it's certainly possible
to be grateful uh on principle or on an intellectual understanding that someone
has done us a favor it could be that's a habit that someone does a small favor
does something nice that we say thank you uh someone opens the door thank you
and um someone hands us something thank you uh someone helps us in a store thank
you and um it's an acknowledgement and of what they've done it's kind of like
saying hello and acknowledging that someone is there they're seeing and um acknowled you know it's
kind of a clear acknowledgement but there's a difference
between doing it as a habit or doing it as intellectual acknowledgement of something and just and the feelings that
can arise to be really touched some people are moved to tears in in
gratefulness so moved by uh benefits someone has provided
I sometimes I've been deeply moved almost as tears uh watching or seeing or
knowing what someone has done for someone else and uh and it's so so
moving for me and it's not exactly that I have get gratitude but it touches that
space inside where gratitude is born and so gratefulness to be a feeling a sense
something goes deeper than just the mind it's not a calculation it's not a habit it's not merely an acknowledgement
and um maybe it's not even a acknowledgement it does appreciate what goes on but it's allowing the experience
we've had the gift we've been given to be
absorbed some people will very quickly uh try to respond to something has done for us
in a way that kind of little bit stops it from really sinking in maybe out of
embarrassment maybe out of out of um feeling of obligation or feeling even to
avoid a sense of obligation or something and one version of that is uh is to say
uh you know someone opens a door and say sorry sorry that I had to you had to open the door for me um and that uh that
sorry is taking in a very different feeling inside a very different sense of
who we are and how we are and what we deserve or something then I
thank you a Sor is not quite a gift a Sor is a
somehow a diminishing of ourselves lessening of ourselves so as not to bother someone else but um uh but uh to
say thank you thank you for opening the door thank you for what you've done uh
not sorry for the trouble that I caused you the um um because a sorry does
not um um create a it does not ignite something
good in the person it's a little bit like a praise it's a little bit like acknowledgement you've done something
good and that's you you know it's a wonderful thing you've done it's almost like taking the gift that someone has
done and building on it and letting it have a have a the goodness of it have an
honor ongoing life when we say sorry we it it stops there it blocks it
it the cycles of uh giving and receiving the cycles of how goodness can travel
and move back and forth through our society kind of comes to a screeching halt in ourselves with the
Sor and um and the gift stops there and so gratitude is a way for the
gift to keep giving and so we but we have to first be able to take it in the
goodness feel it in our in the chest in the heart in the belly wherever it is we
feel same place we feel love we can feel grateful and but that requires something
of us and uh and to live a life of gratitude is is to be concerned and
caring about the preparation the for it for gratitude or
being in a good state for gratitude um and it turns out that
preparing ourselves being ready being uh open to gratitude is the same state that
needs that's needed for mindfulness for awareness for love for a lot of different things so it's almost like
very state of pausing being receptive allowing ourselves take time to feel
what's happening wow so not not rushing to thank you but
like almost like wow and take it in and then thank
you if you do that the thank you has more power it's more embodied it's
Fuller the person can sense that you have really taken it in you understand
you've been changed wow thank you for that as opposed to thank you being a
habit just a custom that we do so to take in to feel to allow it to be here
and one of the qualities I think it's worth mentioning that supports allowing
ourselves to feel and take in the goodness of the gifts whether it's from a person or from the meditation or from
just the air we breathe life itself one of those things that gives us a chance
to take it in is if we can live in safety live in
Beauty and and um and uh some people don't have much
safety in their lives and so it's very hard and I've met known people who have
come to a Buddhist Retreat and said it was the first time in their life they ever felt safe they grew up in fear grew
up in with danger and it kind of can kind of settled in really deep wherever they go they they never felt they
belonged or never felt that they were not under threat so it's quite deep that this was on but it's possible also to
shift this and be heal this or settle that fear and to begin to feel safe in a
significant way but one way that uh I'd like to suggest that I was very moved some years
ago when um I was part of a workshop and the guest presenter
came and asked everyone to I think maybe to write down on a piece of paper uh
what they needed to feel safe in the group and people immediately got many
people got very busy and some people kind of wrote a lot of things on their on their sheet of paper the things they
needed to feel safe and um and it was kind of fun to watch how absorb people were some people sincere they seem to be
and really taking that homework that little assignment um to heart and writing What it Took what how they would
might feel safe what the conditions were and and so uh then we stopped and uh the
facilitator kind of appreciated people's work and what they had done and said yes safety is very
important and then she said and this is I think was the what surprised everyone
and jolted everyone there she said um for all those things you wrote that you
need to be safe you bring it with you so I think the expectation was if we
had became clear about what we needed to be safe we'd be telling it to the group and the group make group agreements and
the whole group would help support everyone to support everyone else to be safe by how they behaved and spoke and
uh the facilitator then turned it around and said you bring it you show up
carrying that with you so you feel safe you bring your safety with you and um now this is not this doesn't
always work of course but um uh in the situation that we were in was a very
safe place people who were very well-meaning and had a lot of practice
had a lot of sincerity and integrity in them and it kind of turned the table
turned some hearts inside out when they heard that they said oh I'm responsible
for this rather than expecting it from others I have to find how to hold safety
here for myself and this is the profound thing about Dharma practice is that we learn
how to create safety here in a sense from
ourselves from how we take in what other people say how we take in what happens
to us so that it doesn't really get picked up it doesn't really get react to
it it doesn't touch places inside that um that uh uh uh you know we keep safe
by how open we are how relaxed we are how uh unthreatening we are to
ourselves non-reactivity so safety is needed for
gratitude safety is needed for love safety is needed for deep
relaxation can you evoke that sense of safety can you
evoke a safety where you're protected from someone who then insult you because
it doesn't touch anything it doesn't reach anything inside you don't pick it up you don't push it away you just let
it kind of float and disappear in the air where all words
disappear as opposed to taking it on and and uh reacting to it or thinking about
it or just letting it
go and maybe this is one way that you can allow yourself to kind of feel more
grateful some people like to write gratitude list at the end of the day
maybe three things you've been grateful for so you might try that as well but to
um but not just to write it feel it take it in what's the emotional
feeling of gratitude for you and you might begin also the end of
that little exercise write down uh the best you can of what gratitude feels
like for you and do that over a few days because it might take a while to pick up
all the nuances of how it actually feels in the body and the heart and the mind
um how it feels physically how it feels emotionally how it feels mentally how it
feels uh motivationally how it feels
um uh how it comes what other emotions it comes along
with so to be safe take time to pause take time to be safe for a few
moments so that the gifts of Life can touch something deep inside and you can
feel the Gratitude and wait to say thank
you wait before you bow until until you've received the
gift thanks works much better if you first
receive and then give back so may
today's Reflections and Explorations you do on gratitude support you and the
people around you may we continue the cycles of giving
and generosity in this world through the generosity of saying thank you thank you