so hello and welcome to this Monday meditation
session and uh it's very nice to have all of you
along and all of you who are doing greetings thank you and I know so many
of your names either from other occasions or from seeing them here on
YouTube chat and for all of you who are not chatting welcome wholeheartedly
and uh I probably if I was in attending this kinds of session I probably would
not be chatting and saying hello just sometimes I tend to be a little
bit believe it or not maybe a little bit shy or
something so um one of the interesting
very interesting phenomenas about human life
is the way that uh or say it differently that there are two words that I like a
lot for meditation little AIDS supports for meditation and they are the words
yes and no and a very interesting aspect of human life is the way that functionally
there are times when how we behave what we do might be exactly the same whether
we say yes or we say no if uh you find that your hands are
dirty as mine were yesterday working in the garden um I might say no to keeping my
hands dirty before I go into the house to make dinner and uh or I might say yes to
having the the hands clean so I can make dinner but the no and the yes both have
the same function I clean my hands if
um um my mind is caught in obsessions of
some kind I could say no to those obsessions or I could say yes to the
awareness or the mind that's free of obsessions and sometimes it seems really
good and for me to say just say yes I like that a lot and uh yes to being
aware yes to being aware of this it brings me a smile sometimes when I just
say yes to being aware of obsessions aware of thinking because in the yes
awareness is stepping away is becoming free and then I have to have something
to be aware of it just Delights me that I can be aware of something which is maybe difficult or ways I'm caught up
while I'm be becoming free or I could say no to the
obsessions I can say no don't want to do that no thank you in
a way that leaves me being aware so uh for today I would I like to
suggest in the most loving way that you can most generous
kind supportive way you can maybe introduce the word no there's something
very strong in self kind of claiming our Our Place claiming our independence
claiming ourselves here free of being caught in Things That No
indicates so no just gently no to keep
thinking about this no to keep pushing something away no to wanting something
expecting something no it's not a no that pushes anything
away not a no that rejects anything it's a very particular no that says no to
being involved with it to picking it up no to perpetuating it no to being
involved being caught so it's not a rejecting of anything it's not a pushing
anything away it's just like no I'm not going to do this I'm not going to continue doing this
the mind the heart might have their own ideas and things continue but you just gently say no stepping away no or it's
kind of like releasing from your hands uh something that's very
unpleasant to hold no no and see if that loving no can help
you stay aware stay connected to the present moment say the no so that you're
more here with this whatever it is
here so
to assume a meditation
posture and to gently lower your gaze or close your
eyes
and without doing anything else appreciating what it's like for you
at this moment to be aware are you sleepy are you
eager is there Clarity is there dullness is your awareness being pulled
into your thoughts and preoccupations what is it like to be aware
and if you are aware to take a few moments to be aware
of how you are consciously
intentionally feeling noticing recognizing how you are in your
meditation posture as if you have permission to be
this way but rather than being lost in it
you're knowing it recognizing
it and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths as you exhale relaxing softening in the body
maybe on the deeper inhale feeling this different parts of your body that you can relax as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal and for a little while the same
exercise with a more or less normal breath to feel some part of your body on
the inhale where there might be tension or holding
and then soften relax that holding that
tightness as you exhale
and then as you inhale to feel the thinking mind any tension or
pressure contraction and as you
exhale soften in the thinking mind maybe
relaxing micro muscles maybe in the area of your brain
your head your forehead your face that somehow are
connected to thinking
and then settling
in to the body's experience of
breathing perhaps centering yourself on the body sensation of breathing
and if you find yourself involved in thinking
gently say no to being
involved if the thoughts are in the background and you're not particularly involved in them let them be in the
background but if there's a more involvement you're lost in them
or reacting to them picking them up
participating a gentle no to doing all those
things and know to step away into being more aware of what's
Happening
and if there are ways that you're concerned about things almost
nonverbally that you find your attention is locked into some feeling emotion
sensation in the body not to say no to any of the
feelings or Sensations but to in a kind way no say
no to being in involved with it reacting to
it where the know is so gentle and
light that it itself is part of being free
and if you're not caught in anything with a light
touch ride the inhales and
exhales
e
for
e for
when you find yourself caught in thoughts or
feelings saying no to being caught saying no to being invested
or holding on
participating say gently no and you you might need to say it a few
times thinking that it's an experiment in learning how to say
no so there's a wonderful feeling of freeing stepping
away making room breathing
room for awareness
for
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to take a few
moments to recognize feel how you are right
now how are you now compared to how you were at the beginning of the
meditation and how is it to be aware how how is it to be
mindful is there an appreciation for awareness
itself appreciation for attention and to the present
moment appreciation for mindfulness Maybe it
Simplicity as you sit here still in the meditation posture
and might there be a healthy wonderful supportive way of
saying no lovingly no to
yourself when greed arises
no makes room maybe for generosity when hostility or resentment
arises no making room for respect and care and
love no to when all kinds of crazy thinking
delusive thinking spins around
no so there's a better chance for what wisdom Clarity awareness
is there a way of saying no to being shut off or pulled away or
being aggressive in relationship to other
people the know that allows you to be there all of you all of you present
attentive to others and in with and with that full
ention to have Good Will May the people you encounter today
benefit from your ability to be awake present
attentive aware without clinging without
preoccupation May that awareness be the vehicle for your your Good Will May all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of us in any any way we can however
small contribute to the well-being of this
[Music]
world thank
you e
hello and welcome to this Monday when we start a new five-part
series and um for this week I'd like to um introduce you some of the main themes
of ancient Buddhist teaching that I translated uh for about 20 years or so I
studied a particular Buddhist text that uh became kind of foundational
for my orientation or supporting my orientation in Buddhist practice some of you know that some
months ago I talked about core Buddhist teachings for how I teach and that it's
a kind of a naturalistic form of Buddhism and um and a lot of this comes
from or supported by or inspired by a particular text that um then I
translated and published as a book called the Buddha before Buddhism and uh and the idea of calling
it the Buddha before Buddhism is um uh uh it's more something
like the Buddha's teaching before Buddhism uh or the Buddha's teaching
before it became Buddhist so with the idea that over time
maybe even his own lifetime but over time the teachings got more organized
more systematized more developed more expanded and and the core Simplicity of
them sometimes got lost and um and uh the um but the the earliest
version of these teachings were really radical in many ways in going back just
to the central core of practice so uh the name of the text that I translated
the literal meaning in in English is the book of eights which is a very
uninspiring title and so I titled the my translation and commentary on this
ancient text um the Buddha before Buddhism so people would ask a question
for themselves what might have been the earliest teachings of the Buddha before it became a
religion and um and there Scholars who uh believe that uh this text is a uh
maybe the earliest oldest um Buddhist teachings that we have that maybe they
were given you know in the first years of the Buddhist teaching or well before
the the layers that got added to it those teachings in the in the generations right after the
Buddha and um so I would like to read um um couple of paragraph or short
paragraph or two from the introduction what may be perplexing to
many is that the book of eights does not espouse a religious doctrine that exists
in opposition to other doctrines nor does it put forth a teaching that is
meant to be seen as Superior to other teachings in a manner that challenges
the religious beliefs of many people including many Buddhists the text explicitly denies the
role of ultimate religious truths and religious knowledge in
attaining personal peace instead the text points to a
direct and simple approach for attaining peace without requiring an an adherence
to any specific ideology the possibility of this piece
is what God the teachings and practices in the text the value of these teachings
is not the profundity of their philosophy or their Authority as
scripture rather they are valuable for the results they bring to those who live
by them instead of doctrines to be believed the book of eight describes means or
practices for realizing peace so it's almost as if it's pulling
the rug from underneath many of the usual ways in which people relate to religious teachings they people often
involved in religion want to have their religion be ultimate be the most amazing
the most wonderful the most true and we have this big orientation towards having
truth and sometimes that gets in the way sometimes that leads to um religious
wars that I have the truth and you don't and um and and rather than kind of
lobbing onto the truth and knowing the certainty and this assurance that you have what's the most real the most true
uh the whole orientation of this early text was to look in a different
direction to be concerned not with truth and ultimate truth but be concerned with
um Peace and um so here the the goal put
forth in the book of eights is describe both in terms of states of mind to be attained and the mental activities to be
abandoned peace and equinity are the most common descriptions of what is
attained and clinging craving being entrenched and quarreling are activities
most frequently said to be abandoned there is a clear relationship between the states to be attained and the
activities to let go in that to experience peace for oneself when most
release one's
clingingsmith poems that make up this text and
um and uh some of these poems have um
eight verses and that's maybe why it's called the book of eights having
views about what is Ultimate a person makes these the best in the world and
and calls other views inferior as such they have not gone
beyond quaring seeing benefit in things seen heard and
thought or in precepts and religious practices and then grasping at this a
person then sees all else as inferior what one relies on in order to
see all else as inferior is an entanglement say those who are
skilled one should therefore not depend on things seen heard or thought out or
on virtue and religious observances pretty ra
radical nor should one they nor should they make up views of the World by means
of knowledge precepts and religious observances nor would they think of
themselves inferior or Superior to others and they shouldn't uh take
themselves as equal so neither better or worse than others and also not equal um
um so you know what's left what's left is letting go of what
is taken up the person free of grasping does not depend on knowledge or take
sides with factions when take sides when factions disagree or or fall back on any kind of
view one not inclined to either side to becoming or non- becoming to
hear here or the next World there exists nothing to get entrenched in when
considering the doctrines others grasp here one does not conceive
of here one does not conceive the slightest Concept in regard to what is
seen heard or thought how in this world could one Recon recognize a Brahman who does not
take hold of views one does not consider struct prefer to take up any
Doctrine a a Brahman a kind of a wise person not led by precepts and religious
practices who has gone beyond does not fall back on
belief that person is one who is thus this wonderful expression that um rather
than being better than others worse than others inferior Superior rather than having ultimate teachings and seeing
other teachings as being poor or bad One lets go of all clinging including to all
stories and ideas of who one is and in
this wonderful expression one who does thus is one who is
thus and I think it's a wonderfully generous thing to say thus who are you thus without
definition thus that includes all of who we are no part left out but it doesn't
need need to be named it doesn't need to be constricted or Limited in any way and
the most unlimited way of saying who are you is saying I am thus like this and
open our arms and just say whatever you see whatever is here with this why do I
have to Define it any more than that and um so um it's a um very radical
text and um over next four days I'll go through four of the major themes in the text and uh and hopefully you'll
appreciate uh a text that's been very important for me and inspiring for me
and um and maybe you'll find this useful I'll end with one more um part of a poem
from it this is one of the most touching poems in the book I feel maybe in all the Buddhism because the Buddha is is
talking about himself in a very touching way about how he was before he was
enlightened the process of coming to become enlightened and he talks about his own kind of
Anguish he he says violence gives birth to fear just look at people and their
quarrels I will speak of my dismay and the way that I was shaken we
often don't hear the Buddha talking about himself that way this is before he was
enlightened seeing people thrashing about like fish in little water and
seeing them feuding with each other I became
afraid many people are afraid these days the world is completely without a
core everywhere things are changing wanting a place of my own I saw
nothing not already taken I felt discontent on seeing only conflict to
the very end then I saw an arrow
here hard to see embedded in the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash
about in all directions when the arrows pulled out people do not run and they do not
sing so pulling out the arrow is the core
teachings of this text that pulling out does not require
ideology does not require Buddhist abstract teachings and
philosophies it's a very simple direct message in that Buddhism began with this
message and then there were maybe layers and layers of complications that got added over time and I find it very
refreshing to go back to the Simplicity of this text and reminded of the
Simplicity of uh the path the way to a profound form of
Peace so that's the task for the next uh four days and to go through this little
more and I hope you do find it interesting thank you