all right nice to see everyone as we settle in I'll mention
that our wholesome quality for today's meditation is meta Goodwill or loving
kindness um but we'll explore it from a few different angles so I hope you'll
just follow along if you'd like so settling in
sensing the body and whatever posture you're in allowing the attention to come
inward closing the
eyes maybe taking a long slow deep breath in
[Music] softening on the out breath
and offering the invitation of ease to the
body so could there be an easeful way to
rest against the surface that you're resting on so softening into your seat what
you're lying on
not having any pushing against that surface but just a softening or even a
melting into
it and then also feeling a comfortable straightness and alertness that's actually more more
easeful than collect s so soft and
present allowing the shoulders to
relax soften down maybe Imagining the shoulder blades
sliding down the back
softening the eyes in the eye
sockets inviting some ease through the Torso area
through the chest and heart area down into the
abdomen not any kind of a demand but just a an invitation
and softening the arms and legs so they're in kind of a natural
natural
position so a sense in the body of having arrived
to the degree it's available right
now and if there are any parts of the body that
are uncomfortable today in some
way that's fine we feel that
that's okay for the body right now we just offer our caring attention to those
parts without dramatizing
them and you're welcome to continue on with
the meditation more on the breath or the body if that's um what feels right for
you the invitation is also to bring the attention into the area of
the heart to point the Mind towards
some good will just having a sense of softening in
the heart area and how is it there it might already be warm or soft
or it might feel a little bit tight or hard or
achy or [Music] numb and so for so we just see what's
there
some of the feelings may be physical and some extend more into the energetic aspect of the body a little
more
subtle so again using the mental function of the Mind in a skillful
way we can bring in the image or felt sense of a being for whom it's easy to
feel friendliness it might be yourself that's a totally Fine Place to
Start very classical place to start if that's not as easy you can
often people like to use an animal like a pet it should be some some simple
being not someone with whom you have a complex relationship so usually we
wouldn't choose our partner for example some easy being or it's just
simple to wish well but rather than focusing entirely
on [Music] them we just use their image or sense on
our heart as a way of evoking the feeling of care the focus is on the feeling in
US Good Will of an easy kind of loving
kindness friendliness we just want this being to
be happy and feeling that feeling in the
heart of wanting that caring about
that I'm sensing that feeling connecting it to our
breath so as the breath comes in it's like a Bellows shining on a
beginning of a fire and when we bump the Bellows the Fire gets bigger it's being
fed so as we breathe in The Meta
grows getting warmer and brighter and as we breathe out we notice
The Shining of that Flame or hot
coal Radiance of it breathing in
again this sense of this being The Meta grows flowing on
fire breathing out we notice the radiance
as you get a sense of that you can let the sense of the being go actually and
just notice the
meta growing and radiating
now the thing about a fire is that it radiates in all directions
equally whereas we tend to be focused on the front where our Cent orans
are so we can deliberately imagine that the radiance is shining forward start
where it's
clear as if we've drawn a curtain aside and it's shining freely out to the
front and then drawing that curtain around to the
right Radiance shines out to the
right the back little messy easy
maybe keeping the feeling of matter of it feeling it extending out of
our [Music]
B and to the left
side and also AOW
and below so we removed all the curtains and
the heart is shining freely turning back into that feeling of
meta can you even feel it physically sense of warmth or
ease in the mind perhaps it's a pleasant feeling feeling of
friendliness openness subtle
Joy it may be that this feeling is not so accessible at this moment that
happens and if that's the case then just stay with the intention
and whatever feelings are present that are somewhat
useful letting the meta permeate the body as it shines
outward it doesn't need to go very far and a light doesn't push its energy out
so you just let it shine maybe it's pretty small
candle or maybe it's bigger doesn't
matter it's just The Shining
if you want to imagine that this meta is nourishing for the
body that's fine notice how it shines through your
body before it goes out into the world we we are always the first
recipient of our
meta we may bring in a sense of how any being in any
direction would be touched by this field of meta
and it's quality one quality that to focus on is
its non-c
contention meta has no conflict in
it it's just it self it's just
friendliness joh home
you're welcome to continue if you would like but there's also an invitation to
now soften that deliberate use of the mind
and relax back to an open awareness of the flow of experience
but retaining this quality of non-c [Music]
contention allowing each thing in the body and
mind to have its life in the field of our
awareness without a sense that we need to decide if it should or shouldn't be
there what it's about because the awareness is just
itself just simple knowing without any conflict with what's
coming and going but we stay present nonentangled
and seeing if you can rest like this for a
bit
e
e e
so let's bring in now another aspect of
Mata it's been implicit in this sit but I want to make
it explicit that is to consider
that we don't actually know what will arise next in experience
do we so even in our own mind just sitting
quietly here you're basically just with
yourself but you don't know what's going to [Music] come you don't know absolutely
everything about your mind and so there's this certain kind of
courage and faith in just offering this good will non-c contention I don't know
what's going to come next but the intention is to meet it with meta with a
non-conflicting way of
being it's kind of beautiful to have that in the face of
the unknowability of the flow of experience and similarly as we
will soon come out of meditation and soon go out into life interacting with
others going somewhere consider that in
others you don't fully know them they are always going to be deeper
and wider than you can see maybe even than they can
see and yet can we have this intention that we would
meet that with friendliness or kindness or Goodwill whatever dimension of meta
is appropriate in that moment and what a courageous heart it
would be to go out into this vast unfathomable world but still wish inside that we can
meet it with kindness and care and well wishing
even in the face of that ultimate unknowability in a sense why not why not offer
Goodwill so may it be that we retain some of that momentum heading out into
the wider World meeing it in this good
way certainly doesn't guarantee that everything goes well or that others like
us or any of those smaller considerations
but it's a good place to start and what's the alternative
really so may we continue with our open
heart may we have the courage to let that be what we're about
finding a way to meet life with this care and kindness so That
Others May to the degree that they're receptive sense
that and benefit from one kindness in many ways seen and
unseen may all beings receive kindness and find in
themselves happiness and and peace
so we'll continue with the 10 epithets of the Buddha and we'll finish up
today um one that we haven't covered uh out of these nine that we're
mostly talking about the extra one is tat which is technically the first um not
included in the traditional practice and this means uh thus come or thus gone
depending how you read it or maybe it means both maybe the word being slightly vague is meant to convey both of those
it's a little unclear you know if you just give that literal translation what it is I like uh Gil's rendering of it as
the one who is thus the one who is thus it's kind of just the thusness the it's just what it is
kind of way of being that the Buddha had and I mention it today on last day
because we've reached kind of the culminating qualities of the Buddha which have an air of unfathomable ility
about them so with that introduction we'll we'll move into the last two um
that we haven't talked about yet the first of these is
budo uh which simply means awake I mean it's the general form of the word Buddha
that we often use to address the the Buddha um but what's interesting is that
if you remember back from the sequence I know you may not but on the very first
day we talked about this quality Sama  which I translated has fully self
awakened so why do we now get to just buddo instead of s s budo a simpler
version now late in the list you know we've seen over the week that this list
is pretty sequential it has a a directionality to it where it starts
more internally just the Buddha's awakened mind himself then the way he acts eventually his ability to see um
everything from which he teaches so we see it's going kind of outward if you
will so why do we get to buddo now just awake the usual understanding of this
which makes sense to me from having done the practice myself is that this is meant to be a direct simple powerful
awakeness that the Buddha has about him um such that but those who are attuned
to the teachings can feel the presence of Freedom uh when they're in his
presence so the Buddha's awakeness was so deep and so unshakable that it was
something that could be resonated with uh by others if they were you know of a
mind doesn't mean everybody could feel that um but this awake
quality can um influence us directly in a in a at a subtle level so buddo has to
do with the Buddha's ability to connect so directly with the heart that a person
actually could awaken if their mind was properly trained we have to do the
training ourselves this isn't like a magical transmission where he just can
touch anybody and wake them up it's not that there there isn't that kind of magic in this understanding but if the
mind is trained and if the person is participating then yes actually we can
gain that influence from the Buddha the sutas name 10 instances of people
becoming fully awakened simply from hearing a Dharma talk from the Buddha it
was more than 10 people sometimes there were a lot of them um but if you really
analyze the sutas you can find this on Lee braisington has done this analysis uh there were 10 cases where
the one or more people became fully awakened just from hearing a Dharma talk
and presumably their minds had been prepared in some way so
um so that's you know those are in the early teachings these suggestions that
this is possible but um we can see you know in our own experience how does this
relate for us since we don't have a living Buddha um it can that even
translations of the Buddha's teachings you know even passed down and translated into another language there can be a
direct impact on the mind if the mind is ready I'll give as an example um I've
had experience with this I read the sutas quite a bit and um and other and
you know teachings from other Buddhist Traditions also and I had an experience one time of reading a verse translated
from a certain B teaching it was what it was in English and it was like there was
a shift in my mind I was somehow just ready at that moment and my mind shifted
into kind of a meditative State and I noticed it you just from reading this verse and I thought it was so
interesting I actually put it down and you did some meditation and you know went on after
that and at some point I mentioned this to a friend and it actually had the same effect on her mind so can happen Joseph
Goldstein also mentions um he's talked about in Dharma talks that he had an
Insight actually from something that he read I don't know what it was but he
read some kind of a wisdom teaching and he had an insight into not self so um
these things are possible even now but again it depends on the conditions we've
put into our mind through meditative practice and training and developing ethics and
wholesomeness so how much more so right now going back to this quality of budo
how much more so if someone is literally in Buddha's presence right so there's
this idea that awakeness is a is a thing and we can explore that you know
in our own practice the degree to which that's meaningful for
us and then the final quality attribute epithet of the Buddha
is bwa bwa and that is um that's often used in the sutas it's usually
translated as the blessed one the blessed one said this Etc and or simply
blessed if it's as a an adjective this one though um I mean
that's a translation and it's meant to you know blessed has a kind of a religious
quality to it and it's you know it's meant to try to capture or something but I think it's hard to put into simple
words I mean what is a blessing in a in a religion that has such a thing so I
think it's best encountered if we understand this last quality of
bagawa in doing the formal recol recollection practice itself and seeing
what it evokes for us but I'll I'll offer some words um see how they resonate for you so this
is from bod talking about his interpretation of these nine epithets
and he says the blessed one the fortunate one who practiced and fulfilled all
meritorious qualities and extends his waves of blessing out to the
world that's his definition of of bwa how we should recollect that so that's
interesting right what does that mean now centuries after the Buddha's physical death I don't think it's meant
to be pinned down rationally so not something that we should think about and
analyze and um really get our get our mind around it I think it's the point is
more to rest in the opening that comes from this term um you know we kind of
land on bwa at the end the blessed one blessings maybe still happening I found
this quote in the sutas a realized one is freed from Reckoning in terms of form
they are deep immeasurable and hard to Fathom like the ocean and that talks about form and it
goes on for the other Aggregates feeling perception mental formations
Consciousness we can't really reckon them in terms of those things we can't
pin them down and say exactly what this is for that person they're deep
immeasurable hard to Fathom in the end we don't really know the Buddha's mind we don't really know
who who was the Buddha what is the Buddha it's for us to to feel in
ourselves so we find that at the end of contemplating all of these attributes of
the Buddha we're left with can't know it all just have to rest in something open
so my sense from this is that what happened under the bod tree whatever that was is still echoing in the
world and perhaps in a practical sense there's a
way that our life could be lived such that that
reverberation keeps going at least don't dampen it through the way that you live
let that keep resonating through your body and mind not deadening it not
taking energy from it so that it continues on after after you're
here in fact doing this recollection practice I would say is part of keeping
that reverberation going so just let it echo through your
body as if you choose to do this practice this B it just just
Echoes so as a recap we have the
tagata is we don't really contemplate tagata but that's the first of the 10
the tagata is Aram fully wholesome free of greed
hatred and delusion worthy of offerings that's what our literally
means s fully self-awakened didn't see just his own
Liberation from his particular set of defilements but he saw the whole picture
all the way down to the depths such that his teachings are still relevant today VI Char
Sano accomplished in knowledge and conduct able to manifest that understanding in his very
actions with his body and his knowledge of how not to get caught in anything and
so he is sugat happy gone to a happy place that can't
be thrown by anything that happens in the world speaking of the world he is Loca
viu knower of the world able to see and
understand how suffering Rises and how it can end in all situations he sees how
the mind works how the sense system works all the Realms of being that we can be in and how they flow
lawfully based on wholesome and UNH wholesome actions and how to escape from
that he is ano pad STI the unsurpassed
trainer of beings To Be Tamed so he can tame even the wildest mind because he
always knows how to calm it he is
sat not just a trainer but a teacher for deavas and human beings explaining to us
the process how it works so that we can be empowered to also walk this path
ourselves and become free become independent in the DH and become our own
teacher and perhaps teach others use budo so awake that it
communicates to us just in his presence the awakeness can enliven and awaken us
if we are receptive to that and
Bava it continues on sending blessings through the
world so these teachings encourage us to reflect upon the awakened mind and the
awakened life not as a way of diminishing ourselves but just the opposite as a way
of inspiring us aligning our practice showing us the way that we can
contribute to the continuing reverberation of goodness that came from Buddha's
Awakening and the sutas say specifically that this kind of recollection leads on
to a series of beautiful qualities gladness Joy Tranquility happiness and
somani there's a way way that the mind can unify and gather through this kind
of recollection so I encourage you to find some way that these Reflections are
meaningful for you if that's of Interest see how this week lands and
continues on and for those who will uh who can be in the area tomorrow I will
teach a day long that includes the formal recollection of the Buddha practice if you want to try it out I
think it'll be recorded also so thank you very much for this week may your life be an ongoing
Resonance of what happened under the buy tree in the specific and unique and
individual way it can be for you thank you