so I want to talk tonight about our affective responses to
experience okay so as life flows along from morning to evening from day to day
we're impacted right we feel things and other people do too I hope hope I'm not
saying anything radically new with a statement like that but I also want to
suggest that we carry at least some
identification and maybe a lot with our particular
emotions and we can see this in the way that we say things like the sunrise
makes me happy or I always cry during romantic movies and we some consciously think
that part of who we are is our emotional landscape which is relatively constant
relatively fixed right this is how I am so let's explore a little bit in this
realm and see how it relates to Dharma practice and to what Buddhism says about
training our minds so I hope we'll start off in ter teritory that's pretty
familiar and you might be saying yeah okay I get it and then let's let's
wander forward with that and see what some of the implications are and how
that emerges in our practice so first of all let's
consider how uniform are people's responses to a given
event I'm remembering back to the time uh long ago when I was
working and the company I was working for the founder of that company was
getting ready to retire and he sent out you know an email
to all of his colleagues and business associates just to let them know that
you know at a certain time in the future you know five or six months from now he would be retiring so he just wanted to
uh let them know and say something about how nice it was to work with them Etc and he got back a lot of responses
you know from the people who knew him well and he noticed that his American
friends tended to write back and say congratulations fantastic you know what
are you going to be doing next something like that and um this was an
international company and almost all the responses he got got from his Japanese colleagues said I'm so
sorry you know because um at least at that time a while ago the understanding
was that you know if you were retiring you would lose your connections many of your meaningful Life Connections to the
Working World and so they said well I'm I'm sorry you need to be doing that I
hope it's going to be okay for you so clearly in some cases there can be quite a wide variation by culture and
we can imagine um many other circumstances that would affect someone's response of
course so the event itself does not determine how we feel about it and
that's even true in more extreme cases as we'll see later but what about the person you know
does a given person tend to respond in a predictable way to certain kinds of
experience well people do have what's called temperaments this is even
recognized in the Buddhist commentaries it talks about different temperaments that people have and we say the same
kind of thing we don't always use that word but you know we know that certain people are generally warm or anxious or
hot-tempered or hesitant you know and this is real we do see some stability in
fact that stability is exactly why we can identify with our emotional habits
that relative stability allows us to think I am like this or that person is
like that but for the
Buddha these habits are all just that they're conditioned habits some of them
are very deeply conditioned and may not change in the course of our life and
some of them are less so and it's expected though that d
training will shift our emotional responses over
time right it has to because we're moving in the direction of less
suffering right so that means that as we practice we will less often experience a
re a reaction that comes from greed or hatred or
delusion so this all might sound pretty clear yeah I get that theoretically but
what does that imply well it means that we're going to have to give up our subconscious idea that we are
always angry or anxious or envious in certain
situations and sometimes that is a real barrier on our path is getting past our
own expectations of how we should
feel so to be clear we do have whatever emotional
response that we have that is a lawful arising so I'm not talking about
experience needing to be a certain way or certain responses not being the right
response I just want to say that really clearly because emotional realm can be
an area of a lot of suffering um not just for the emotions themselves but we
have ideas about that oh I have too many emotions I have too few emotions I have
the wrong emotion so we add extra judgment onto our emotions and I'm not I'm not making any
judgments like that what arises is what arises but I am saying that over time we
do expect shifts aan cha a Thai teacher from the
last century said that one measure of our practice is that as we move along
the path fewer and fewer things cause us to suffer and more and more things bring
us happiness and that's a very broad brush statement but doesn't that make sense if we're moving away from
suffering there would generally be that Trend it's kind of an average Trend
don't think it sort of goes linearly because it doesn't but it's an average
Trend and I think the reason for that is clear greed hatred and delusion are UNH
wholesome or unskillful so they're sort of ethically detrimental things whereas
skillful or wholesome qualities like patience or care compassion meta
honesty these things actually bring happiness ethical conduct is the root of
a deeper kind of happiness and we uncover more and more of that on our
path so now let's let's go a little farther along this
idea sometimes this development of how we respond in an AFF
effective way can go in surprising directions so I want to relate a story
that I heard recently from a teacher this teacher is someone who used to have
a lot of anger so he was an angry person earlier in his life he would have
characterized himself that way um before he had done much practice and he's
addressed it a lot of different ways you know sometimes just with mindfulness sometimes with actively practicing meta
things like that but he says that um he's practiced for a long time now he
says now he goes walking and he likes to pick up bottles and trash that he finds
along the walkway and sometimes when he's walking with someone the other person will Express anger that people
have been littering you know people have not been taking care of the
environment but he says that he feels nothing but happiness because it's a chance to pick up trash
and bottles and make this face look more beautiful than when he than before he
got there and he noted also a little bit to the side
that sometimes the person who's expressing anger is not picking up any
bottles they're just expressing the anger about
littering so do we always need to have the conventional emotional
response no no who who's happy about finding
bottles along the road this guy who's practiced for a long time is great we can be genuinely happy about
trash sometimes so this path goes against the stream that might be a
phrase you've heard and this is actually noted in the
sutas so I'm not just making this up this is from the SU nepata
what others speak of as happiness that the noble ones speak of as suffering
what others speak of as suffering that the noble ones have known as
happiness don't take it too literally you know you could read that and say come on what about war or disease of
course that's not what it's talking about we can give Buddhism a little bit more credit than
that so I think it's some saying something a little bit more subtle what others speak of is happiness
that the noble ones meaning longtime practitioners who have some understanding that they speak of as
suffering what others speak of as suffering that the noble ones have known as
happiness I understand this to mean that the more commonly accepted ideas of
Happiness such as material possessions or you know world success of
some kind tend to become less appealing to people who have done a lot of Dharma
practice those people maybe find a different and more satisfying kind of
happiness in things like Simplicity or living a Dharma oriented
life so like we mentioned you know a few minutes ago the person who is happy
about seeing trash that they get to pick up make the world more beautiful
there's a way that wholesome qualities provide the foundation for a deeper kind
of Happiness might even be that you know
what others speak of is suffering having to wait having to you
know be with people who are in distress maybe that's a form of Happiness if your
heart is very compassionate that's a wonderful opportunity to connect to
serve this same text that I quoted from a little bit later says that some of the
insights that one has along the path of letting go run counter to the entire
world this was written not written down but it was said 2500 years ago so the
Buddhist world was similar even then people who were doing longtime practice started to feel different in a certain
way started to see things differently to the point where they felt like maybe they had different
values so we see this you don't even have to be a longtime practitioner to start running into this as a
teacher I hear fairly often from people who have started to practice
regularly that they aren't as interested in hanging out with with some of their
friends now that they're meditating so the activities that they
do with those friends just don't seem as interesting or as enjoyable now this is okay this is
normal natural uh I I don't tell people to go out and get rid of those friends
immediately I tend to say just add some Dharma friends you know just add add a
few extra people add some people that also meditate or that will understand
something about what you're getting into now and and just let things evolve and
as they do so we started out with very obvious
statements about our affective response our emotions and we kind of followed
that into how is this changing along the path have we wandered into kind of surprising
territory oh wait a minute yeah things do change such that I'm not quite as in
alignment with the usual suffering of the world that's cu the usual conventional way in the world is a path
with a lot of suffering we're trying to do something different here and yet we still live in
the world how does that work so one implication of all of this I
would suggest is that we need to develop a certain kind of
confidence maybe the confidence to have the actual response that we do and not
require it to be what is expected by Society by other people even by
ourselves can we acknowledge that our emotional responses are changing and of
course they are this is the path that transforms us transforms our way of seeing the
world we have to allow ourselves to change though if we're going to walk this path we have to allow ourselves to
change in Zen there's a process called uh
tario where a practitioner has to wait outside of the monastery gates for
anywhere from hours to days uh before they're being led inside to join the
monastery in practice and it's supposed to demonstrate your dedication maybe and
also it's a chance to watch your mind when it's under some stress pretty much just put in a room and said you sit here
and we'll come get you you don't know how long that's going to be I mean they they give you food and they let you go
to the bathroom but other than that it's pretty much it and so Gil actually went
through this process when he was doing his Zen training he did a a period of tario and when it was finally over after
a couple of days his response was not actually relief or Joy or maybe there
were some of those things but what was most prominent was that he cried because he thought that he
would never be that intimate with himself again that was his response after being
locked in a room for a couple of days I think he was surprised that that
was what he felt that was maybe different than what he would have expected so can we allow
ourselves this kind of freedom of response
I think practice moves us toward a kind of deep inner
honesty where we really open up to how things feel in a complete way in
ourselves rather than in a conventional way or in a habitual way we accept that part of us might
feel happy at a funeral or saddened at a
wedding we all allow ourselves the full range of feelings to flow and to change
as the path changes us now we wouldn't Express or act on
just any of our inner experiences we can still have discernment about what would
be appropriate you know for the people that we with of course we might not say or do anything
with the feelings that we have arising if they're quite unconventional or
unexpected from the usual but part of this training that we're doing is not to
suppress our inner response and instead to be clearly mindful of
it and to have the confidence that if we keep seeing honestly our inner world
will harmonize and will move toward more like that response that Anan cha
mentioned more and more things bring some measure of inner Joy To Us
isn't that nice you could have inner joy and not have to express it if it's
not expected in that situation and yet there you are not suffering on the
inside so it's a reasonable question to ask how do we do that so let's turn now
to practice how can we practice with including more inner emotions and
responses so the first way I'll mention is something that I do in my own practice sometimes um which is to create
an atmosphere of safety for various inner
responses sometimes I'll note to myself at the beginning of a sit I actually say
this in my own mind it's okay for anything to arise and it's okay for
anything to cease and sometimes I also um add that I won't dismiss any responses that come I
won't laugh at them and I won't make them into anything that they're
not so you might try it if that sounds appealing it's interesting because we
can be our own barrier in terms of feeling our inner response you know what I what am I supposed to be feeling now
what am I supposed to be thinking what's the way that I've always felt about this for the last 25 times I've thought about
it but sometimes we can ask is there anything else here something I haven't
acknowledged or admitted it's useful so I find that when I do this
like when I say it's okay for anything to arise or cease Something in My Heart
relaxes and I'm more likely to be able to sense a wider field of my emotional
landscape of course it's also important to have the capacity of mindfulness to be able to handle anything that comes up
so so make sure that you're developing that muscle as much as possible um
throughout the day on and off the cushion and if anything comes up after you've invited you know it's okay for
anything to arise or cease if anything comes up that feels like it's getting overwhelming it's fine to back off you
don't have to have to stay with anything that's arising we just want to make sure we're
not limiting ourselves so it's also the case that the
Buddha gave some specific recommendations for How to Train our perception and how to relate to
experiences such that we uh don't get caught up in just habitual responses and
I'll name just a few of them tonight probably the most important is
to notice the quality of anicha of inconstancy or impermanence that's the
poly word anicha and particularly we can notice that in the realm of uh feeling tone
wether experi experiences Pleasant unpleasant or neither Pleasant nor unpleasant and also mind states which
our emotional responses go into that realm if we start watching we see that they change all the time Pleasant
unpleasant Pleasant neither unpleasant neither Pleasant if you try to track
feeling tone it's always constantly shifting and as we respond to that
emotionally uh we can start to feel that there is a lot going on
and also you know maybe more subtly when we allow ourselves to see change with
some continuity for a long time the heart begins to understand at a at a
deeper level than our thinking mind starts to understand that clinging doesn't really make sense things just
keep changing right so um when we're clinging less getting
stuck less often then the Mind naturally becomes more flexible more
responsive which we could call Freer right more flexible more
responsive so Dharma practice like the realm of noticing anicha noticing
feeling tone tracking our emotions you know that is a a practice it's a way of
corralling the mind to you know pay attention in a certain way but if we pay
attention in that certain way in a wise way it will eventually open up and
become more flexible does that make sense so if we wisely contain the mind
in certain ways we're stopping it from dissipating its own energy and sapping it away through clinging so then it gets
freed up to be more creative more reflex more more flexible more able to
respond so the fruit of practice where we're open we allow ourselves to be more
and more emotionally responsive even in surprising ways is that we become Freer
a Freer response these trainings open and release the mind so it's less stuck in
conventional ways of seeing things it's subtle we're slowly learning to free the
Mind from various deadening or limiting responses we are our greatest limitation
actually and then another crucial understanding that comes from this is that we begin to let other
people have their responses also whatever they are there comes to be less judgment less
policing of other people's ways of being ways of seeing
things this comes about naturally as we learn to loosen our own way of seeing
things and so this is a way to reduce conflict so much conflict comes because of
rigidity in how things are seen we can help by increasing our own
freedom of response so to be clear we don't become
you know more LAX in areas like ethical conduct because we learn that you know
reducing harm leads to deeper happiness but in all the ways where where we're
unnecessary holding on to fixed ways of seeing things or habits or old ideas or
conventions all of those begin to soften so I think this is the secret of
why quite a few longtime meditation practitioners particularly monastics you
can see this but many longtime practitioners seem to get jollier and
more peaceful right as they practice and also more surprising
in their responses so I want to end by reading a
story from the monastery within this is Gil's book from a little while
ago and try to listen to it in light of what we've talked about tonight it's a few
pages I hope you'll indulge me for it's four pages um I hope you'll indulge me
in reading the whole thing because it takes us kind of on a journey of a change an emotional response an opening
up a freeing and then a maybe surprise surprising by the
end so read it listen to it in in light of what we've talked about tonight of allowing our emotional landscape to
change so the abis of the monastery was a most exceptional person she seemed to
always have a smile in her eyes when she looked at you it seemed as if she knew you better than you knew yourself she
once told the following story of how she first came to the monastery when I was 13 my family would
send me up to the mountains around the monastery to collect edible plants for our evening meal these foraging trips
were the only work I enjoyed doing otherwise I tried every trick I could to avoid work on my family's Farm I was
still in school but school had no interest for me my anger was a welcome barrier to learning anything the teacher
was teaching on one of my foraging trips I would pass by the monastery while the monks and
nuns were out sweeping the leaves from the pathways the first time I saw them working I was mesmerized watching them
go about their work for many months after I would often stop a while to watch them sweep they worked silently
and with an efficiency that seemed effortless then one day a monk walked up
to me and asked what I was doing in the mountains the question frightened me and I became defensive I resented anyone who
tried to get to know me so instead of answering the question I countered by asking what he was doing and the monk
smiled and answered that he had been told to sweep and that he was just killing time until he could return to his room for a
nap as I walked home later that day I thought about his answer and was glad that he did not seem any different from
me when I was required to do anything my heart was never in it and my attitude was that I was just passing time until I
could be excused taking a nap was certainly preferable the next time I passed by the
monastery on one of my foraging trips a nun stopped her sweeping and also asked
what I was doing again I resented the question it felt like an intrusion
however this time I did not feel as scared again I deflected the question by
asking what she was doing she answered that she was doing extra work in Hope of
being assigned to the kitchen which was warm in the winter and always seemed to have one or two extra sweet rice cakes
in the cupboard to nibble on without saying anything I nodded and left to continue my foraging the nuns answer
resonated with me since I too liked to be warm and eating Sweet Cakes was one of my favorite activities second only to
sleeping the next time I passed the monastery another Monk asked me the same question this time I was surprised I was
not defensive or resentful of being asked however again I deflected the question back to him he explained that
he was sweeping as a spiritual discipline to help him overcome his anger later as I walked the mount and
trail with my bag of plants I felt a kinship with this monk like me he had anger but I was perplexed that he would
want to overcome it for me my anger protected me a week later I was again outside the
monastery watching the monastic sweep yet another Monk came up to me when he
asked what I was doing I mumbled something about collecting plants I doubt he could hear me my voice was so
faint but I did muster up enough strength to ask him what he was doing he
replied that he was beautifying the monastery so that others Could Be Inspired in their work of spiritual
transformation before I left him I glanced down the well swept paths and
realized that part of the reason I was compelled to watch the monks sweep was that they seemed to be transforming the
paths into something that made me feel peaceful the next time I stood outside
the monastery watching the monastics I was drawn to walk over to yet another nun and before she could ask me what I
was doing I asked her she looked at me with kind eyes and after what seemed
like a long but soft silence she explained that she was sweeping to be of service to all who used the monastery
and in practicing this way she hoped to find Ultimate peace as I left the mon Monastery that
day I thought her answer strange as I didn't know what she meant by service and by peace I certainly couldn't see
how these had much value for me the next time I visited the monastery
was the last time I had an unfamiliar feeling as I walked up into the
mountains it was a warm glow of gladness in anticipation of what I would
find when I arrived at the monastery I walked up to an old monk who seemed to be absorbed in his
sweeping I inquired what he was doing as he answered each of his words
washed over me like cleansing water me I am not doing anything my
self-consciousness was Swept Away long ago there is no eye that does
anything before I could respond he handed me the broom and walked
away I have been here ever since
so why are you sweeping your
path so with that we'll shift to if you have any any
questions and we have a microphone so that others canar here and we can record
it yeah Jim behind
you thank you for your talk seemed very
instructive I'm wondering if I understood understood it correctly or
you seem to be pointing at if we sort of impose some constraints on our
thinking and and specifically probably trying to diminish hatred greed and
delusion or we obtain Freedom or it leads us to Freedom
through these constraints in a sense is that yeah you look puzzled as you say
that is that the part that you're trying to clarify well it seems pleasantly
surprising but but also it sort of makes sense but I'm just wondering if it if that's a
reasonable uh summary well I don't know if it's a summary of the whole thing but it's a um
certainly a thread that was in there is that um uh channeling our attention in
certain specific ways it feels like it might be a constraint um but uh the if
we do it in the particular way that's prescribed through these practices it
has the effect of opening the mind making it for more flexible and free and yeah I think that's can be
somewhat intuitive and yet you know we do wonder about it but it's clear enough
right that if we um at least everybody who's made it to the room I think is
that if we keep living life as just kind of following the whims of our mind we
begin to get a feel like it feeling like it may not be going anywhere in particular or at least not where we were hoping it would and so the question is
if we can put in some kind of you know is there a way that we can um tweak it
that's a technical term uh such that it um we actually reduce the constraints in
the long run so that was what I got to at the end is how we practice and that's what's represented by the monastery and
you know taking on the the path of of sweeping the path so we're you know
we're doing less we're doing we're channeling our attention in certain ways noticing body feeling mind mind and mind
States right the four foundations of mindfulness but as we do that um there's
a way in which we discover uh all the ways in which we're
limiting our own mind Mind through just habit conventional responses we
understand how things work we understand how we're bringing about a lot of the suffering that we experience in our mind
and as we let go of the the ways in which we're limiting ourselves we become
both happier and more flexible so I'm hoping that you know
by saying that in sort of a broad way way we can think of maybe examples in our own life where that's been the case
where actually um doing the practice has brought about some kind of shift such
that we felt looser more open and I Wonder has there been anything like that in your
practice it's a work in progress It's always a work in progress for sure um
but even something as simple as um in the Physical Realm often people find
when they start practicing that they relax you know something in the body
actually feels a little bit more relaxed why how can that be just from sitting still but if we were sitting watching TV
this wouldn't happen but if we sit and pay attention to the breath over time maybe we soften a bit that's a certain
kind of release a certain kind of opening so even
that yeah thank you
yeah over
here thank you for your talk um two things that came to my mind um it's um
nonjudge being non-judgmental yeah and um unconditional
positive regard um trying to have a that kind of
running in the background um you know I'm a teacher so um and I
believe I work in a system that is fraught with
um um inefficiency so I say what what kind of a teacher are you uh special
education special education and today I I was judgmental two times and I acted
unskillfully both times and uh um your talk helped me kind of reflect
on that um and how you know I try to use my practice as
um you know as a life tool um um a relation a
relationship tool yeah um as much as an inner um Journey definitely yeah so um
thank you for reminding me to uh attempt to stay non-judgmental
and retain positive uh unconditional positive
regard is there a term in Buddhism or is there a concept that would match that unconditional positive regard um I
suppose that's an aspect of meta okay of generally having a mind of Goodwill
toward whoever we're interacting with okay thank you yeah I think we don't
need to constrain ourselves to um I don't know unconditional positive
regard yeah let's just call it part of meta that's good
enough anything else yeah here's one
thank you so much for the talk and and the the closing uh story so I was sort
of struck by how um as the the monks and nuns
progressed right it started from a very I'm sweeping to kill time before I
go to sleep right a very yeah you know self-oriented self-oriented right then
I'm you know I want to be warm then I want to help others s you know on the path and and you know make it more
beautiful for others and becomes outward looking and you know just struck by how
you at least me right you don't come into this saying I want to be of service to others right you're like no I need to
find some way to calm my mind because I'm suffering and you know I just need
to be able to you know deal with myself right but then once that calms you can
begin to think about others and you know to your point I'm a I was a professor I've been an investor
I've run companies and like every time it starts you start it's about me it's about me it's about me but at its best
it's about service to others and helping others and that's the only thing that ultimately you know when you talk to
people who've been successful or have reached you know some piece in what they do it's always outwardly looking nobody
says yeah I know at the end it was all about me right that never ends up being the the end of the story so anyway I
found that really an interesting aspect of of how the whole thing unfolded yeah certainly there's a shift to including a
bigger perspective what did you make of the last fellow who says uh you know there's
no one who does any sweeping anyway transcendental right yeah so this particular path I think
goes all the way all the way back yeah yeah thank you
if anyone has typed anything into the chat we could have one from online
you're invited online if you want to type anything in someone is watching it's just nice to include
everyone
it can be helpful at times on our path to um just reflect
internally why is it that I'm practicing or still practicing I don't Rec recomend
doing this like every sit or even you know every week that's that would be too
much but like maybe every year something like that um and the
reason for that is that it refines over time remember the story that I read um
and so we have to uh kind of renew that in a sense and maybe we'll discover that
something new has emerged we have to keep you know tracking this and kind kind of when the space opens in your
practice if there's been some kind of a release there's a way in which we have to step into that space and occupy it in
order to then take the next step so I just offer that as a piece of
advice if you haven't for a while reflected on what you're doing sit down and have a session where you just allow
things to come up about why you're practicing and see if anything's different and if it is that's okay too
and if it is move into the space all right that'll be it for
tonight have a wonderful rest of the day