so hello from Insight Meditation Center here in Redwood
City and um welcome you to our
meditation and this week the emphasis is on mindfulness of
breathing um as a and the different foundational approaches or attitudes for
mindfulness practice and one of them is um the idea
that um there's a wonderful idea I think that
uh mindfulness of breathing works even when it fails and maybe even the language of
fails shouldn't be used but it's kind of a little bit of a kind of evocative way of saying that
uh if they uh we kind of offer at the beginning our attention to breathing
but when that doesn't work uh then the task of mindfulness is
not necessarily to go back to the breathing but rather to know to
recognize um what is happening to notice what has taken us
away and if we notice that and see that then uh we're mindful so even when we're
not successful at staying with the breathing the breathing is that reference point
for noticing when the mind is drifted off and the more stronger the tendency
to drift off in thought be preoccupied uh with anything at all the
chances are something in our mind or body has some tension in
it uh tension is uh often the
fuel for preoccupation uh tension
clinging strong sense of pressure about wanting something or not wanting something and part of
mindfulness important part of it is to see that and to see it to know it know
that's happening without participating in the pressure in the
tensing in the desires or the aversions and the Art of it is that just
in the knowing just know it clearly or feel it clearly in such a way that's
kind of like stepping back and and observing rather than being in whatever
is going on participating fueling it engaging in it uh identifying with it
identifying with the good cause of the desire or the aversion or the the the
preoccupation so uh in that way and don't worry about how successful you are
with staying with the breath uh just do it just practice focus on mindfulness of breathing just enough that it helps you
to see better what is the currence of preoccupation the energy the momentum of
your mind and heart in a clearer and clearer way and learning how to relax
around what's happening as there's more sense of ease or relaxation with the present moment it
might be possible to uh remain longer with the body's
experience of breathing and and this idea of lingering
or hanging out with a breath um cruising on the breath floating on the experience
of breathing um surfing on the waves of
breathing in and breathing out uh when my son was quite young I
would put him to sleep by imagining that he was an otter floating on top of a the
ocean in a nice comfortable bed of kelp and that the gentle waves would lift him
up and down and that the gentle waves was the movements of his breathing and he would just kind of lay in bed kind of
feeling those movements of breathing in and breathing out until he fell asleep
and um so uh so you kind of just stay with
the breathing and there's a number of ways that we can linger with a
breath and uh one is to rest in it one
is it to um uh different people find different things are useful but one is to rest in
it the other is just to gaze upon it like you're gazing upon waves coming up
and down on the ocean shore perhaps just watching um something that becomes more important
as the practice of mindfulness matures is uh some combination sometimes
one sometimes the other sometimes both and some combination is to feel the experience of
breathing the sensations of breathing the physicality of breathing to really
feel it and to know those Sensations to know movement is movement pressure is
pressure release of pressure contraction is contraction to know warmth is warmth
coolness is coolness to know a smooth movement versus a choppy movement not
without judgment just oh this is what it is and the art is to do all this not So
Much from the control tower not at all from the control tower in the head but to have an intimacy or to be almost as
if if you're in the experience the physical experience of breathing feeling
it and gently quietly simply uh knowing
it and sometimes the feeling of the breath is enough to linger and stay and
if we kind of rest and surf on those the sensations of breathing and sometimes we
um it's really helpful to have some clarity oh this is movement this is
pressure this is contraction and um and to know it but to know it not
forcefully or to know it not as a checklist that's like okay know it and then on to the next thing but uh the
knowing which is kind of like to know and then almost like The Knowing opens
the Vista opens the Mind opens awareness to feel and experience the breathing
more fully it's almost like the each Act of knowing movement for
example there's movement there's a almost like um okay now let's receive
welcome that experience of movement more fully so uh those are a lot of words to
explain this and now we we'll guide you with this a little bit more so to take a
medit assume a meditation posture
and either lower your gaze or close your
eyes and so it's less from the control tower and the head directing what's
happening let it be almost at the direction of the body
itself Direction Guided by what's comfortable and nice to do from from the
body's point of view Let the Body allow the
body to take some deeper inhales and deeper
exhales and with a deeper exhales relax the body
soften with a deeper exhales maybe you can allow the thinking
mind to relax and soften as well
on the exhale allowing the center of gravity of your sense of
being to settle into your torso into your
body the deeper inhales begin in your
torso and end in your
torso how does your torso experience
breathing and then to let your breathing return to
normal take a few moments here to scan through your body and see where
else you can relax in your body
soften
e as you
exhale maybe calming the thinking
mind if there's any sense of contraction or narrowing of the
thinking mind on the exhale let that spread
out
widen and if there's any sense that you are your
thinking you are your con concerns on the
exhale relax and settle yourself your sense of
self let it come to a rest deeper in the Torso maybe even all the way to the
belly
and as you breathe notice the rhythm of breathing
in and breathing
out and which is clear for you breathing in or breathing out
The Body Sensations as you inhale or the Body Sensations as you
exhale
and other Body Sensations of breathing which are
Pleasant and if there is is whenever they
appear feel them in
intimately the pleasant sensations of breathing are an invitation for
you to linger to remain
resting on the body's experience of
breathing and if there are
Sensations connected to breathing which are unpleasant or simp or
neutral see if you can allow for a kind of pleasant
lingering resting in all the sensations of
breathing
and an important part of mindfulness is feeling the sensations connected to
breathing not up in the control tower watching it or thinking about
them but allowing the body to
feel to sense the
sensations to sense the sensation
in the place where sensing and Sensations occur
together
with every exhale relaxing and letting go of
thinking that Creeps in and as you let go of
thinking let go into the sensations of the body
breathing
for
e
and as you feel your breathing the sensations of the body
breathing let there be a very simple knowing of what those Sensations
are knowing the breathing
and simple means
allowing recognition to occur almost from within the sensations
themselves instead of straining to understand or to figure
out no strain content with whatever
way this deeper quieter knowing can
[Music] occur that's deeper than the usual place we
think the knowing that arises out of
Silence pressure
movement inhale exhale pause the end of the exhale
sensations of begin that associated with beginning and ending of the
inhale gently calmly let there be as you feel the
breathing get to know it
better the knowing that allows for a deeper familiarity
he
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this s
relax even more can you settle
calm and take a few moments to re familiarize yourself with
how the breathing is now maybe noticing how it's different
now than it was at beginning of the
meditation
and then without changing necessarily how you
breathe with your imagination or imagine you welcome
others to come in
close so that they can be comforted or
[Music] reassured with your calm
breathing as you breathe
calmly it's a
reassuring presence for others nothing you need to say or
do reassuring others that it's okay for a
few minutes just to be without needing to do much of
anything that others for a few moments are allowed to be as they
are and then imagine
how coming back to your breathing and
relaxing can be beneficial for yourself and for others
as you go about your day and may it be that our capacity
to relax with the breathing check in with the
breathing may it be for the benefit of others as
well may we be reassuring for others may we be a
peaceful presence for others may we be a
friendly presence for Others May this meditation support us
to have good will for all beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank [Music]
you
so welcome again to this introduction to mindfulness meditation and this fourth
talk and this first uh five talks uh centering on breathing mindfulness of
breathing and breathing uh is a kind of an unusual maybe exceptional piece of
our psychophysical existence in a way breathing sits at the
Nexus at the crossroads of so many different parts of our life so much of
our cognitive emotional uh e
um physical world come to play as we breathe so much of what happens in the
world around us and our intentions what we want to do or our emotions in regards to what's happening around us will
affect our breathing uh breathing speeds up it goes deeper it goes
shallower um we breathe differently if we're trying to be physically exertive
than we are if we're just very calm and relaxed not doing much we breathe
differently if we're afraid than if we feel deeply reassured and safe we Fe we
breathe differently if we have fantasies that are frightening or filled with
desire and then if we do if we imagine ourselves in situations where it's very
comforting and easeful for us so our thought World our physical world what
happens around us affects our breathing and
um and so as we learn to pay attention to breathing as we become more sensitive
to it take time to get to know it um we're kind of sitting there at the
crossroads of so much of what's happening in our life and we don't necessarily have to understand
everything that's happening but we can begin appreciating how um the breathing
shifts and changes and how certain ways of breathing maybe are more tense or
more part of reactivity or um and that there's other ways of breathing which
are more calm and settled and soothing and
settling and so um and simply to know that to experience the breathing make
time to feel it introduces into the breath a new element it introduces to
breathing a kind of sense of um space or time um an element of giving room for
breathing to relax to soften that is not going to happen there happen if we do
not notice the breath but stay preoccupied with our irritations frustrations
our um desires our fears and U we to spinning out with our
thoughts then there's no room for breathing to by itself to begin
relaxing um but if we sit down quietly and there no longer doing the things
that agitate or contract ra or you know affecting the breathing uh and then if
we learn to relax a thinking mind and and learn to relax the body the
breathing starts to shift and change and the shifting changing nature
of breathing and starting to know get a sense of an easeful breath and be familiar with that is one of those
reference points that are so valuable in mindfulness meditation a reference point
that helps us see better more clearly when the Brea brething is not easeful
when we're tensing up when the breathing gets tighter or contracted or speeds up or moves from the belly relaxed and
moving to the chest being kind of the where the force of breathing begins
happening and um and uh and a big part of uh this
practice of mindfulness is developing a heightened sensitivity and familiarity
with all the different ways that breathing happens all the different ways which the mind is caught in its thoughts
and feelings and the heart and and as we know it not necessarily having to fix it
maybe in mindfulness practice not necessarily having to fix anything but a certain kind of allowance
and making room to know it trust the knowing and the knowing makes space The
Knowing creates a kind of atmosphere uh that um allows the things
which are tense uh to relax any tension that we carry any
force and agitation of strong energy we having is in a sense a um a working
against the pool of gravity it's working against the natural way in which muscles
want to relax if if they're given a chance and um but we keep them tense we
keep them by by our activity or thinking our fears our emotions our desires and so just to know and feel and
make room for everything it lets things return return to a kind of
equilibrium homeostasis a kind of peace and so one of the ingredients of
this in mindfulness meditation is uh giving time to what's
happening to feel it feel the sensations of it and let there be a quiet
knowing recognition oh this is what it is and um and we're both the feeling and
they recognizing are themselves uh peaceful or calm or
settled uh if people hear the instructions to to know to recognize
what's happening some people take that to be work they have to strain and lean into it and contract to try to do a
better job but the way of mindfulness is the opposite there is a knowing uh recognition but a
recognition that comes from that soft relaxed place a recognition that is
itself kind of relaxing um it's kind of like if like we're having we're tense but we don't
even know it we're so CAU up in our concerns and a friend comes over and gently puts their hand on her shoulder
and says so kindly it seems that you're tense today and only then do you
recognize that you're tense but having that someone recognize that something goes ah
relaxes and um and uh and the opposite could happen as well as if someone
recognizes that uh you seem so uh happy today and um and there's something about
being recognized that something kind of lightens up and oh yeah I am I didn't kind of I wasn't really taking it in but
I am it's true true so that uh this gentle recognition that kind of ah yes
I'm I'm tense that's the case as opposed to oh no I'm tense what a terrible
meditator I am this simple simple recognition and and so as we practice
meditation with uh breathing uh it's important to remember the first steps that uh I've talked about this week that
we don't have to stay with a breath you know stay there and hold on to it and without wandering
away um we just want to start seeing more clearly what's going on here as we sit to meditate and learn how to
relax uh some modum of relaxation but at some point as we get more settled then
there is a a u almost a natural tendency or a wonderful dedication to then uh
Stay Stay surfing on the breath lingering with a breath hanging in there with and just kind of be aware of the
more breaths over time and that does a few things one thing is that then the
mental energy is not being channeled all of it into thinking and
preoccupation um less energy is available for preoccupation because now the mental energy is going into uh
staying with a breath and so the energy that goes into preup ation that creates
more tension agitation is not being not creating it and it allows the mind the
heart to settle and quiet down and so just lingering and staying but not
without without Force without holding on and without the idea that you're failing if you can't do
it uh it's actually important if you use the word fail it's important to have
that because that indicates there something you want to recognize about the Mind One wering off the mind being
agitated it's all just something to know and recognize in a calm
way but then as you are able to stay with the breathing of sensing and
knowing it knowing it and sensing it uh staying close and intimate to the
experience um uh uh floating on the breath rising and passing rising and
settling with each inhale and exhale and allowing that breath to inform
you so um this is something that uh you can do throughout the day and I'd like
to offer you one practice for daily life that um can be invaluable and very
simple to do it doesn't take much time and that is to uh take the three breath
journey and that is whatever circumstance you're in uh uh you don't have to close your
eyes people don't have to know you're doing this but um maybe close your eyes
and but then just kind of give yourself over to really experience three breaths
experience how you are what's happening with you as you breathe just stay with those three breaths and maybe count one
two three to really as much as you can give yourself over to just those
breathing those three and familiarize yourself for the breathing and you might find that if you
do that through the day throughout the day in small ways traffic lights or standing in line or waiting for
something to happen or um May sometimes even um doing that before answering an
email or even might even be time to do it when someone calls and let it ring
for a while and you take your three breaths um you'll probably find that
just taking those that little three breath break shift something inside of
you it also will help highlight for you how you were how you are and how there
can be a shift to a different way of being and how breathing is different after three
breaths and um so this mindfulness of breathing is not only something to do in
meditation but something to do in daily life as well and for those of you who
maybe uh in meditation uh it seems really hard to stay lingering or surfing on breathing
the forces of distraction are quite strong uh it might be useful to uh not
try to stay with breathing for a long time um but rather in meditation too
just do a three breath journey and when that journey is over when you're ready do it again not any more uh ambiti I
about staying with your breath than just that so
um uh I hope in the process of all this you
come have a greater appreciation of the body breathing um breathing is not just
bringing oxygen into your system it's h connected to so much of who we are and
um that's it's why some people some religions really put breathing as a
synonymous with life so thank you very much and um we'll
have one more day on mindfulness of breathing and then we'll go on to mindfulness of the body thank
you