okay so nice to see all of you we're starting
a fresh week together so just as a brief introduction
I'll say more after the sit um I'll tell a little story one of the early influential
teachers of the teachers who founded the Insight movement in the US was an Indian
woman whose name was deep and she had had a very difficult life
with a lot of loss and then a powerful Awakening that made her really an
embodiment of love and wisdom and she was teaching a retreat at IMS in
Massachusetts and somebody asked her what's in your mind it's an interesting question right
and she answered very straightforwardly she said there is meta there is
concentration and there is peace that's a nice mind so this week uh
we're going to be looking at a list that says something about the Buddha's mind
uh it's considered a very it's actually considered skillful in this tradition to
open ourselves to reflecting on the qualities and abilities of w awakened
people and even then on our own wholesome qualities it's meant to reflect back into us so there's a list
that's called the epithets of the Buddha or sometimes it's called the attributes of the Buddha that we'll be exploring
this week in the talks um there's also a way of formally
meditating on these qualities but it's not quite the right format for us to do that during the meditations so in the
meditations will be touching on our own wholesome qualities in various ways but
if any of you are in this area and you want to learn the formal practice I'm going to teach it at a day long this
Saturday October 12 so that's called the recollection of the Buddha
practice um but for today uh we'll we'll be meditating um on various on a certain
wholesome quality of mind so let's get started on that please find a posture
where you can meditate well it's fine if you're sitting or lying
down or standing could even be walking gently back and forth if that works for
you and check in with your posture
so finding a way to be upright or at least to have a straight
spine and also relaxed
softening to the so we want to be alert and present but not tight so easy to be
a little bit overly tight as we're
present so softening in closing the eyes if that feels comfortable for
you maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths
in and then softening on the out
breath letting your breath fill the body to the degree that you can so that you
really feel the energy of it flow into not only your chest and belly but your
arms and legs and
head letting the attention spread over the the wholeness of the
body and then to kind of greet the body by touching in with the attention to
various parts so the softening the muscles of the face the eyes and the eye
sockets jaw
bringing the attention down the neck throat to the shoulder area that too to
soften letting the shoulders drop a bit I like to imagine the shoulder
blades sliding down the back
down the arms to the
hands and into the chest
area sensing the heart space and also the physical rib gauge
the front the back the sides
releasing the [Music] diaphragm letting it just move on its
own and softening down into the whole belly area just
inviting
ease I find it helpful to simultaneously soften the abdominal muscles and the low
back muscles so the tightness of the in the spine
Falls away on both sides of the
spine and softening the hip joints sensing if you're sitting the
contact point with the seat relaxing into that letting yourself be
supported then releasing any tension in the legs all the way down to the
[Music]
feet and inviting mindfulness in the mind inviting
presence of already been cultivating it with this simple connection to the
body so softening that gaze and letting the mind take in the whole of the
body and know that you know that and be at ease with how the body is
it's fine as it is
and allowing anything else that's present if you're in a certain mood or there are certain emotions or
thoughts lingering in the mind spying to acknowledge
those and for just uh the beginning part of this sit I'd like to invite the use
of the cognitive mind to bring in a reflection on your
aspiration and it's up to you to decide if you want to have an aspiration just
for this sit or if your mind is happening to be
opening to a wider aspiration about practice
aspiration is not goal you know we're not setting some requirement for
ourselves in the future self-improvement project an aspiration is an uplift in
the heart that we feel when we sense what is good or
beneficial about this practice that we know
so maybe there's a sense
of ease we know that there's an openness a
softness in the heart it comes from practice and we open
to that to whatever degree it's is present we know ah yes this
this is good or it could be a broader
reflection like knowing that over time our tendency to react has been
decreasing feeling Joy at the ease and relationships we've noticed from
that then having a sense of yeah this could keep going
or for some there's a sense of walking in the footsteps of the Buddha the
Buddha also did Sitting meditation it led to his Liberation from
suffering and here we are partaking of the same action how
amazing so whatever it is I'll be silent for a couple minutes
while you touch into that preferably as a bodily feeling yes it's in the mind but can you
feel it also in the
body e
and then allowing the cognitive mind to relax or release if it hasn't
already and just settle into the sensations of the breath
and if there's a lingering sense of goodness or even some kind of Joy or peace from
the aspiration maybe consider if the breath
can distribute that through the body just inviting that
possibility noticing the
effect and then even allowing that intention to
soften so this is a skillful way it's okay to use thinking
mind or the directed purposes and now settling into our usual
mindfulness of the breath or body
just noticing as you continue to sit normally if there's an effect from
having brought in the [Music] aspiration
e
e e
if you find that the mind has drifted away which is very
normal you could touch back in briefly to the
aspiration that you had evoked as a simple way of re-inspired
uplifting the mind as it starts again in the present
moment
e
e e
as we continue to sit you're welcome to just continue on
with the breath or the body or your regular
practice or if you like you can invite a deepening of the
embodiment sense of this aspiration or
wholesome wish for your practice wholesome
motivation really feeling the goodness of it in your
cells in your tissues even in the
bones not creating anything but letting the mind's
Beauty Infuse into or resonate with what's
already open or free in the body so we have a sense of Mind and Body
together breathing through our
goodness the goodness of our practice it's not
selfish it's not UNH wholesome in fact it's very
wholesome to really
feel what it is that we are doing in this practice and the goodness of it so
resting with that breathing with that daring to feel it all the way to our
core
having confidence in our good intentions
e
e e
and as we come toward the end of this
sitting sensing into how there may be some
momentum generated from this kind of practice or
this way that we directed The Mind in our practice
today and that we can carry that out into to our
life our mind will become occupied with other things of our
day but there is some momentum that we carry from touching into this
goodness it travels within us in some way and there's a bit of protection that
comes from that know maybe that moment and will
make it less likely that we can get knocked off balance by reading something or hearing
something that is disturbing or even thinking something one of our old
habitual thoughts maybe like when the bicycle's going a little faster it just doesn't
get knocked off so easily and so we might be a bit less
reactive we might be be a bit more open to others more open to
ourselves and there's some protection some degree of Refuge in
that so our practice once again is benefiting not
just us but those around us those we encounter and it serves as direct
protection in our normal daily activities what a beautiful
thing that can [Music] come just from paying attention
for period of time
so the theme this week is called uh Buddha's mind which might be a little
grandiose because the mind of the Buddha is actually unfathomable but it's meant to capture
the idea that it is skillful in our practice to touch into in various ways
from time to time what it means to live in an awakened way and the Buddha was
the Exemplar of the awakened life does that mean wearing monastic
robes and living in Ancient India no um instead we can uh we can look toward a
list that is traditionally called the epithets or the attributes of the
Buddha and in the main list that's used in the tadan tradition which is chanted
every day in monasteries actually uh there are nine of these
attributes according to Scholars the official list has 10 and it's actually
used in every major Buddhist tradition so it's something that's common across all of Buddhism from the earliest texts
up to Modern practice that's happening right now so it's very appropriate that we take that up this
week um but I want to say a little bit about about this so you know why why
reflect on attributes of the Buddha at a base level it's meant to be
inspiring or uplifting and within that of course there's some mental training around how
we handle ideals within our mind I'm going to talk about these qualities not
as impossible ideals that we're not measuring up to yet but instead as
beautiful qualities that we already have some measure of so just
I was reflecting around this process and I remembered that when I was a kid I was
a trumpet player for a while and um there came a point where I had the
opportunity to meet a trumpet player named Claude Gordon who was uh quite a
master of the 20th century and in particular he um it's funny I didn't
know this at the time but he taught a method that included training in in breathing he he made his students do
breath exercises and he also devised some of the most detailed practice methods for trumpet that are probably
similar to practice methods for meditation you they're sort of a step-by-step process he was a very kind
and precise teacher and I had a chance to meet him and there was you know there was I'm certainly not was not on the
track to being a professional player at all I just was doing it as a as a kid so
there was never any consideration that I could be like Claude Gordon but I felt a
lot of respect for him and it was really wonderful to meet him and I also had a sense that I wanted to bring forth
similar qualities in myself that I saw in him so we could say there was kind of
wise admiration going on there um uplifting motivating for my for my
music and in the collection of the Buddha practice we bring to mind these nine specific attributes or epithets of
the Buddha and we turn them over in our mind letting them sink in so it's kind
of parallel to this wise admiration if you will and I'll acknowledge actually
that you know for some people uh the recollection of the Buddha practice is genuinely uh devotional and is a pure
art practice um but uh there's also different aspects of it
so um this week we're not going to be doing the formal practice but we are going to reflect on these nine in the
talks with three aims one is to inspire and uplift the heart uh the second is to
see aspects of these in ourselves because we actually have some of these
qualities to some degree and to feel that and to recognize and acknowledge
that and then third uh to see in them ways that we can use them in our daily life practice ways
that we can use them practically in the moment to support how we're doing our practice so
um that's the idea so there are nine of these and we'll cover the first two of
them today and I will offer interpretations of them based on my own
practice and the commentaries of earlier traditions for your teachers um so this
whole list I should say also is Progressive the order is not arbitrary let's say it that way so if you hang on
throughout the week they get um more and more interesting and um move toward uh
really something quite amazing at the end so the first of the qualities is
simply called Aran it says the Buddha is aratham and that's the poly and um arant
is the goal of practice so it's um a mind that's free of greed hatred and
delusion so I like to think of this as you know kind of in modern terms perfect
mental health and so we would turn over in our mind wow you know what would it
be like to have a mind with no gried no hatred to no delusion wow you know that
would really um that would really be meaningful and amazing um we know uh from our own
mindfulness practice we are aware of greed hatred and delusion in our own
heart it's one of the things that mindfulness reveals and we have to take that on if we start a mindfulness
practice but I think it's very inspiring to think of uh the possibility of not
having those it's like why [Music] not to say oh no I'm not there I could
never get there but to just reflect on what that would be like and so then um
it reminds us in a practical sense to be aware not only of the moments where we
are falling into various habits or where we just did and have now returned to
mindfulness but also to be mindful of moments where greed hatred and delusion
are not there right now after all these qualities are not
with us 247 they really aren't so for
example I'm going to do an exercise that was taught uh by the Burmese Master
tangu sad contemporary of mahasi
sadon and he would say look into your mind right now because usually while
we're listening listening to the Dharma we are not terribly caught up
in re hatred and delusion so look probably there isn't very much greed in
your mind right now you're not obsessed with getting something with the next thing you're
going to have probably the mind is pretty free of
grasping how does that
feel and and probably at this time your mind is not horribly wrapped up in
hatred in Rage or in detesting something you're
just sitting listening how is the mind without
hatred and probably your mind is not having a terribly distorted view of
reality right now I we all still have ignorance probably um but this moment you're
probably not grossly caught up in a a self a grandiose self view or um some
kind of very distorted understanding you're listening to the
Dharma how is it to have a mind relatively free of delusion
this is not too far from a taste of nibana of
I want to be careful about being too grandiose about that but there are moments of Freedom throughout our day
and can you bring a recognition of this kind of mind how this is for you into
your day more often we're not so far off when the mind
is relatively calm peaceful so Aram the possibility
of having mental health having balance in the mind some degree of ease that's
not dependent on conditions in the world being a certain
way and then the second of the bud gut as they're called in P is Sama s buo
s s buo which means something like fully
self-awakened It's usually the translation and I like to see this as
the Buddha saw all the way to the root of what's going on in the mind he saw
the the underlying process so in a sense he saw all the paths to Freedom not just
his own you know he had his own from based on his many lifetimes various
conditioning that he freed himself from but he saw so deeply that he didn't just
free himself he saw all the paths that are possible and so um the way we see
that in the modern world is that the teachings that we we read or hear about
are still so relevant I mean the Buddha lived in an ancient Indian culture 2600
years ago across the world across the world for most of us um and here we are in a totally
different time in culture and yet when we hear the teachings we think yeah that
feels there's something right about that or we read it we think wow my mind works
that way too I'm Amazed by this and it's I think because of the Buddha seeing
down so deeply that he could teach in a way that touches human Minds in general
no matter where and when they live so there's a lot of gratitude arises in me
from that and then I feel a connection to the long line of practitioners who has uh kept these teachings alive for so
long after the Buddha saw so deeply so I like to think that these
verse two emphasize that the Buddha's mind was fully
whome and our mind too has many whome some moments many moments where we see
into the reality of Human Experience We Touch in our own hearts and
Minds this is how it is and we're aware of that and we do our best to meet it
without greed hatred and delusion so this is um quite amazing
that this process is still unfolding there's a suta that says that um the Buddha said
I'm paraphrasing what the Buddha said but he essentially said a person whose mind has not so much greed hatred in
delusion is close to me regardless of their distance whereas someone who is
even following right behind me holding my robe is far away from me if their
mind is filled with GRE hatred and delusion so there are ways in which we
reflect these wholesome qualities um and it's important to
notice that and to reflect on that and to bring it into our hearts because as
we all know greed hatred and delusion are the roots that bring about
wars various other problems in the world like uh the challenges that the media
offers us of the delusion of various kinds spreading of um agitation harmful
views uh all the kinds of greed that unfold in the world all of these come
from these roots when they're unrecognized and are allowed to just grow out of control each time we bring
in our wholesomeness our aspirations our practice our mindfulness and we
recognize that in our own heart we contribute to the reduction of those
forces in the world so how beautiful is that and we've all
done it together this morning together and I hope you'll keep that in mind as
the day unfolds it's so simple each of our moments of wholesomeness but they
add up to quite a Rushing River of all of us doing this
together so this is our first and really the simplest
um understanding of these attributes of the Buddha and they'll continue to
unfold day by day and we'll go through nine of them by the end of the week hope
you'll continue so thank you for your practice and for your good heart and
your good aspirations and may they benefit many people today be well