so good morning everyone and hope you can hear me out there in the hall okay
thank you so um last
week um I gave a talk on the sense of self and the stronger the sense of self
is I believe or I suggest that um the less we're in our
senses and that one of the switches that happen when we meditate is We Begin
becoming embodied more and more in our senses our physical senses the sense of
being in a body embodied in a body connected in the body and to the degree to which the
sense of self is related to thinking ideas stories memories and all that
kinds of stuff it's very easy for people to identify this self as connected to
thinking and we we have this famous expression comes from French of I think therefore I am the French philosopher
came up with and um and uh the um the Buddhist if they
buddist were going to use the same three words they probably say uh I am therefore I
think and um the um the uh you know the amness comes
first and thinking is just kind of like an appendage or addition on top of it
and that thinking world can be an support for us it augments the the
Fuller way of we being in the world but it doesn't take predominance and for some of us there
are times in our lives probably some of you where the um
thinking uh is takes the lead living in the thinking moving forward and the
momentum the pressure to think the forward directionality the addiction to thinking the magnetism of thinking and G
engaging in thoughts um becomes a little bit like having the cart in front of the
horse has a little bit like having um the thoughts are ahead and the body is
following along the body is the appendage appendage to thinking and there's so much thinking going on and
jumping around from one to the thought to the other to what our plans are we have to do figuring everything out and
um and I know that I'm quite capable of uh beginning to just uh have a feel like there's a lot to do and my mind is just
jumping around between them and the more I do that the less I'm in touch with my
body the less that I'm here and that things like sitting down to meditate is
uh begins to put the horse in front of the cart sitting down to meditate uh places
the C the the central sense of being alive here in this body being connected
here more than the sense of aliveness somehow inhabiting the world of thinking
the drive to think and one of the interesting questions to ask any of us
uh is where do you live and not your address but um you
know and and there's plenty of people who live in their thinking that's the world that they
inhabit and in Buddhist practice we're trying to live in our bodies more than
in our minds to be embodied here and so the experience of being in the
body belongs to the realm of Senses the sense the sense capacities we have and
the world of Sensations and what is uh really uh Rich
really valuable in the teaching of the Buddha is that he distinguishes between two different areas of
sensing so there's those Sensations that we experience that come from having uh
our senses s stimulated by the outer
world so if it's cold outside then this
our temperature nerves senses the cold cold and that has a whole effect on our
system and the whole physiology begins to change and shift the more cold we
feel as a way of taking care of ourselves and it's a rich Dynamic inner world that gets
activated if uh our senses pick up warmth it isn't just simply there's
warmth on our on our skin but that is tied to a whole dynamic system inside of
temperature regulation and your Poe and sweat and who knows all the things that
go on lots of things go on and um so this world of Senses is a
rich world of regulation of finding our way understanding our way in this
world so uh uh if uh we have pain pain
is an extremely valuable thing to have and um and so generally it gives us a
signal that something is off that we should respond to just as I say that I remember the time
when I was staying in a little Hut in Thailand and I think I was taking a nap
or maybe I was sleeping but I was sleeping and uh and I had a
dream and in the dream I was walking barefoot up a grassy null and when I
came to the top of the null I stepped down and there was a steak in the grass
and my toe went into that mistake and it hurt but it was a dream so it's
okay but it it really hurt but I knew I was dreaming it's just a dream but it
really hurt so I opened my eyes to look and
there was this big ant biting my my uh my
toe and you know I was getting a signal danger signal but in this dream state it the
the message was coming through these images that I initially
misinterpreted it's just a dream and um so you again there's this
Dynamic Rich system inside that gets activated by something like pain that
who knows all the things physiologically psychologically mentally uh that are
triggered by it but in that situation it was that Dynamic inner World of Pain
played itself out in a dream how did it get from the toe to the Dream It's a rich CH dnamic world it's not just pain
it's not just pleasure it's not just these simple things the sense the senses
we experience is are richly connected and what happens as we start
meditating uh I think in an ideal world it's not easy is that we've become more
whole where all our apparatus all our capacity to be
the signal of danger came in without the my ordinary conscious
mind which is busy probably thinking about things um too busy to notice but
something is noticing something is taking in the danger and it's being expressed someplace
within so the body is an antenna the body picks up things and it's part of that bigger apparatus of experiencing
that's so valuable and so the more we can be connected to body then more we feel sometimes oh something's off here
what's going on something is right here what's going on here or if I go this
direction it just feels like that feels like a rightness a goodness to it wholesome it's this is wholesome this
direction is UNH wholesome this direction this activity is nourishing this activity is not
nourishing and one of the great Joys that I've had from doing this practice is really getting a sense of this inner
nourishment that's possible that's and the the feeling and sense of nourishment of being nourished
by the activities I do and feeling what it's like to do something which is Den
nourishing that's the opposite and then in Buddhist practice uh generally the
guide for what we do is to choose what's nourishing what's wholesome what feel
feel has a certain not just feels right but it actually feels like it it uh it
um fills us with a sense of rightness and goodness and warmth and kind of
makes us kind of better people and avoid the stuff does the opposite so as we
tune in to the body we make this switch from having the cart in front of the
horse to the horse I don't know if it's behind uh the the the the horse in front or I like to
think of it is no cart involved um uh it's uh rather than us being
behind the horse pushing it um we're on the
horse or being in front of the horse pulling it I don't know what the analogy is but but but the the point being we
get to sit on the horse and the horse is our whole being the wholeness of it all and it's
phenomenal that we have this apparatus the body that can support us has this intelligence in it has this has this uh
antenna that gives us so much information and so to drop into this
body and um I love this pyramid that we have on the they used to have it do we have it
anymore do we even have money anymore this pyramid with the eye on the
top of the pyramid um I sometimes I think of the human being as um a
pyramid where the the um the body is the big wide
Foundation then there's maybe the emotions in the middle and then there's thoughts on the top and if you tip the
the the uh the pyramid over on its head it's very unstable but if you have it all in the
right position then it's stable and so U and so the pride of
place because it's so insecure is we're given to thinking
it gets to be up there where that little eye is and um and maybe it has a good
overview sometimes but uh but it's just a small part of who we
are a huge part of what we are is the body not the hunk of flesh but this Rich
Dynamic world of the senses that come alive through the body the processing in the
body so that was all leading up to the Buddha distinguish distinguishes between
two kinds of sense experiences we can have in the
body and um and so the ordinary one is when the senses are stimulated by the
outside world so uh we hear a sound and that also can has this ripple
effect within us that can be quite Dynamic more than we often realize the the what we see through the
eyes we see certain things and that's maybe a little bit easier but sounds sometimes too can be very soothing very satisfying
very inspiring to hear music of certain kinds voices of certain types um some voices and music is
jarring and um we can see things same thing some sites are actually nourishing
and supportive it shift the Inner Light landscape dramatically and uh I love
water and so um uh I when I drive around the Bay Area it's rather unfortunate I
have to usually be the driver because going across the cemeter
bridge or just at a little place on 101 going to San Francisco just past just before you get to Candlestick Park or
whatever it is I just love to look out across the water and I can't do enough
of it if I'm driving but just it to look out on flat
quiet calm water is for me is so something settles deep in me I grew up
around water so maybe that's why so so so we can things come in
through the eyes tongue smell the body oddly enough you have to kind of Go
Hopefully go along with me in the psychology of Buddhism the mind is a sense organ as
well it's a six sense organ so our ability to have a thought and know we're thinking
is um is the the Mind sense that's seeing it knowing it
somehow oddly enough this is the odd part even more
odd uh those thing those thoughts are sometimes considered to be external
stimuli on that sense door but that seems strange because most of us are our thinking I mean what can
be more personal and now you're saying it's outside one more thing's outside that's coming
and um and so but it makes more sense if you begin understanding that the Buddha
had a whole other area of sensing that was not the senses being
stimulated by something outside and he he he made this this
distinction he made is between uh sensations of the flesh the flesh are
somehow stimulated and Sensations not of the flesh you usually the translators
don't know don't want to do translated that way into English so one way they translated is uh
uh worldly Sensations worldly feelings and non-world feelings so that's just to
me is confusing non worldly and um the um and uh so uh the
um but what's the it's the non the sensation is not of the flesh the
things that uh arise in the sense field but not because some particular thing
stimulated the senses so for
example um when
um um I've been around little children and and uh like I used to go to my kids
nursery school and there was lots of stimulation
there but something deep inside of me kind of just got really
sweet really kind of feel oh this is kind of sweet quiet
warm kind of loving especially all nurser kids were taking a
nap I mean I mean that that is a that's like one of the Great sites go
the to sit there with all these kids so peaceful and quiet napping
oh who would want to wake them my son
actually I think both kids but my young older son he he got he
got expelled from school the first chance I mean he
started he started early with this because he went to pre nursery school
and he would wake up the other kids during the nap and the that and the teacher just
didn't have any then wouldn't have it so that's his that was his beginning of his school
career so we found a better place for but um but the sweetness this you know
that's that would be considered not of the flesh even though we feel it in the flesh we feel it in the body but it's
not a particular thing is being stimulated some some and maybe the way I
felt that way was tied was related to all kinds of things it part of the rich part of the inner landscape that was
coming alive I felt very nourished and supported by that sitting in
meditation the uh which is the Buddhism the classic reference point for this not of the flesh sitting in meditation
minding your own business and having nothing good coming from the outside but
starting to feel settled and calm and warm and connected and and at ease
feeling safe feeling somehow involved in a nice way with the
meditation and then there starts being this this suffusion of feeling of calm feeling of
pleasure feeling of goodness feeling of ah I'm home that you can't really pinpoint to a
particular thing having been stimulated it's not like you know someone went in there and tickled you in a particular
place in your heart or something but it's it's it's something that's much more suffused diffuse through the
body and you can't you know you can have maybe have tension in your shoulder and that's a very particular spot that you
can bring your feel maybe to feel that tightness or the hardness or the pain or
the belly when I'm afraid I can feel the tightness in my belly very clear space
but there's not of the flesh thing is doesn't have that specificity it's something a little bit
broader and wider so the mind the thinking mind that likes to have things likes to want
something wants to Define Itself by something and by and hold on to it
there's not actually something to hold on to there because it's so diffuse but it's some of the most
valuable feelings we can have as a human being these feel is not of the flesh
that's where love love that is wholesome and
nourishing comes out that way through us the Love sometimes what's confused
with love is intense desire there's a lot of things that get
confused for this wholesome not of the flesh Love sometimes uh uh some people
what they think of as love is the tremendous Delight they have that
someone else loves them they don't love they don't actually love the other person they just really thrive on being
loved and so they say I love you but it's really because how good they make me feel like you know I'm important here
I don't know if that's the same kind of deep satisfying way of feeling something that we have in
Buddhism that's partly based on on attachment uh or sometimes love is
confused with secur which is such an important thing to have for our very sense of being alive and
well-being and sometimes the person that provides us with security is that which we kind of think we love but it maybe
it's a kind of love but there's a different kind of love that's deep that's effusive that arises with this
kind of warmth or or or Delight or deep
sense of appreciation and that's almost like there's no desire in it it might
give birth to certain kinds of motivations Inspirations aspirations
Expressions but it's not caught in any attachment any clinging any need to have something
happen so this not of the flesh it's Sensations but it's a very different uh
species of Sensations than the the species that come from a particular
sense door being stimulated including being stimulated by by particular
thought I've been minding my own business in meditation feeling quite content and happy
maybe and then somehow my mind brings up a thought of someone who 15 years ago uh
offended me that's all it
takes you know and suddenly you know I'm like captured by that particular thought
and stimulated by it and you know my calm just dissipated now I'm tense that
didn't like 0 to 60 in half a second it's quite something what's possible in
there and uh but then it's very particular things have gotten tight things have gotten you know kind of
agitated by the stimulation from those thoughts but what happens when the
thoughts get quiet and peaceful and the and our thoughts are not stimulating
I've also been stimulated by thoughts of uh pleasure I w't tell you the
details but uh you know and it feel feel kind of delightful and pleasure suffusing my body but it hasn't been
nourishing to confuse pleasure with nourishment is one of the things that we
can distinguish or the ability to distinguish pleasure from what's from
nourishing pleasure or Den nourishing pleasure from nourishing pleasure is one of the things that comes with this
heightened sensitivity to our body and what's going on here and some Pleasures
are Pleasant in the moment but are harmful for us in the long term some uh some things that are uh
actually feel unpleasant in the moment can lead to a sense of profound feeling
of well-being in this non this not of the flesh world that's part of who we
are and again but you know taking care of young children um I've had to do some pretty
unpleasant things conventionally and my favorite one to tell you hopefully it's
okay maybe I should warn you what's coming stay on your seat no but it was
uh was this amazing thing that when my my baby was you know pretty
young and um was sleeping next to us in bed next to us and got sick and suddenly
we had to deal with this sick baby and and uh it was clear that uh he was going
to throw up I didn't know people could do this it was very unpleasant on one hand but it was also at the same time so
it was unpleasant conventionally but I was filled with a feeling of compassion love generosity
goodness I took my hands cup them together to receive the
bomet can you believe it it never once had ever occurred to me
that that was a possibility and that I would have these good amazingly like of course I'm going
to do this for my child wow like what is you know wow you know so it was
unpleasant in some ways but boy the the sense of it was really Pleasant in this
inner landscape that has come alive for me through this
practice so so uh as we go through our life we have we understand it we're
Guided by a very different sensibility when we're in touch with
this world not of the senses if it's all about the senses it's
all about the ideas all about the thoughts we really limit ourselves and
uh and we're not you know uh not availing ourselves of the full richness of what it's like to be a human
being so this switch from being in thoughts to being
embodied is huge and um and I would I propose that
you know this kind of simple idea that's frequent now I think that human beings
evolved Plains of Africa a long time ago to
um use all their senses all their senses uh are
[Music]
negotiation I'll do X and you do y for me um it's the it just it's more of a of
a well it's a it's a Wellspring it's a fountain that emerges from below it's a
generative world that flows upwards and outwards as opposed to an impoverished
world where we're taking in taking in and trying to fill ourselves and fill
ourselves and um and it's really easy when the Carters in front of the horse
when we are in our thoughts to to this this complicated inner world that we
live in and complicated this Rich Dynamic world that's kind of we don't we
don't under the surface of what we see that if we're always in our thoughts
thinking and Desiring and wanting and Afraid and anxious and planning there's a tremendous feeling of
emptiness or lack that we feel because we're not paying attention to a big part of who we are and something feels that
lack and one of the responses to that is then think more want more look outside
search outside more and it's sometimes it's a perpetuating self-perpetuating
movement of being more and more disconnected and therefore feeling more lack and then trying to fill it outside
and and it goes on and on and some people don't know any other way because they've never been trained never looked
to never told about this deep Wellspring that's available inside and so to find this
generative Fountain of goodness that's within
us is one of the reasons we sit to meditate and why we learn the art of
doing a switch from being concerned with thoughts you still might think isn't
that thinking is a problem if there's a problem it's being addicted to thinking
the problem is thinking the solution is in the thinking chasing the thoughts
participating in thoughts living in the thoughts we think it what's really great
is that if we can make that switch
here into the body and which puts us in the present
moment because this Rich world of the body that were or the heart if you
prefer um it's always here this can't be anywhere
else to find it to a switch and get grounded and centered
here you'll still think and you'll think a lot
better but it puts the thoughts in its right place on the top of the
pyramid and your thinking will feel respected because you keep it up there on the very top so it's not going to be
insecure it's actually and it's feels it's more capable to participate in the
whole participate in the way this very Dynamic and Rich and fascinating inner
World operates that we can't even see usually it's so
complicated but to feel like we're part of this Rich generative
Dynamic world of of the senses of the F of sensations of the
Flesh and if not of the flesh to feel the interplay and the connectivity and
the wholeness gives birth to a whole different way of being in the world that
um that for some people will say there's much more going
much more interesting stuff going on here than me there's something inside of me which
is not me which is really valuable really significant that's a source
of what animates our life in a wonderful way and in Buddhism that's often
associated with Liberation and freedom to be liberated from self
to be liberated from desires to be liberated from hatred and fear is a way
of stepping back from The Limited world of preoccupation in opening and allowing
for this richer World generative world to move through us and uh I'll end with this wonderful
idea at least for me that um that rich inner generative
World it doesn't make any sense to appropriate
it as yourself it doesn't make any sense to claim it as self it doesn't make any
sense to use it for your selfish
purposes it that it it doesn't belong to that world of self- preoccupation
self-definition it's put it takes you beyond the sense of self to a sense of
being alive to a sense of compassion care love joy peace
warmth friendliness all kinds of beautiful things that we're capable
of so from sense of self to the
senses that's the path so thank
you so we have about 10 minutes and or so before they we will'll stop um so if
some of you would like to ask any questions or comments and yes please and
if you can use the mic that would be nice so if you want to say your name uh when you first speak uh you don't have
to but it's nice just to get a sense of community so my name is Bonnie I don't
have a question but I want to share what happened yesterday during um The Retreat
here uh I didn't come in the morning because um I need to swim uh so I had a
wonderful swim and I was looking forward to the afternoon and as you know I haven't been back here in a long time
and within 10 minutes I know I was doing some thinking about a relationship where there's a lot
of ambiguity uh I started getting this intense crushing heart pain and I
thought I was having a heart attack it then moved into my jaw and and my thinking then went to oh
my God what if I die right here and I just feeling shame and I don't want to
disrupt the s or should I leave the room should I go call you know what do I do with this and I decided to just be
really still and to lean into the pain and I just trusted the process I
didn't know what was going to happen uh and I sto stopped letting go of the um
the concern about the outcome and I've had this happen before so it wasn't like
the only unique experience but I think this was really a metaphor as I sit here
listening to you about where I am in my life right now um I don't want to go
into all the all of that but um thank you for this because it it definitely
helped but if I could share a contrasting situation where when I was back in Cambodia I went
back and January and I was uh to see the kids and I was sick 20 out of 23 days
and I could not have been happier it was the happiest time I've had in four years
you know so I was just coughing and wrenching you know every minute of those
23 days and the joy that I felt as you were talking about watching those kids
nap the joy I felt just in their presence watching them interact watching
them interact with me and you know so much happens in The Experience yeah
great thank you very much so first of all is song can you
hear me okay so first of all I'm Kathy C you might want to go see a doctor about
your chest pain because women do present differently with but anyway um now after
your talk thank you for your talk but um I'm going to sit here um and say don't
think don't think don't think because you know that um that's my
inclination is to stop trying to try not to
think so so there there there there might be there might be another
option it it might be more interesting to begin with to become friends with your
thoughts okay and how do you do that respect them listen to them allow
them to be there but uh but don't be in them the metaphor which I used yesterday
is is uh you know if you have a friend who's distressed and in trouble or something and and they ask you can you
can we meet in the park and go for a walk and then you accompany them listening to what they what they have to
say but if you get as as dressed as they are then uh you're probably not going to
be supportive you have to accompany them with a respectful listening caring way
uh maybe but calm it maybe equanimous that then they they really know you're hearing it and it's meaningful for you
that they're hearing you that that they know you're hearing them without being distressed and you don't pull out your
phone to look you know you know to check your emails while they're doing that
you're really there for them so the say to be friends with your thoughts is to do it maybe the same to your thinking uh
don't believe them don't be involved in them don't participate in them but um accompany
them and as you accompany them see if you can feel what more is going on under
the surface thoughts are really just kind of like a surface phenomena they're not usually they're not as important as
we think they are and if you're able to listen to your friend in this case you in a deeper way
but listen with calm with equinity don't look at your uh phone which means don't start thinking about something else just
really be there you might start noticing that uh your thoughts maybe are arising
out of some emotional Source it might be you're afraid or angry or anticipating
or um delighted or you you want or there's a desire or there's an aversion
you start seeing there thoughts are again tip of an iceberg tip of a
pyramid and so what is it that's if you if you're really a good listener good friend you start listening and feeling
what's deeper because that's what your friend wants they want to be met in that deeper
place
thank well hopefully my response was good enough for
everyone um my name is Sylvie
when uh when you were talking um that was very powerful and um I wanted to
maybe paraphrase in a different way to make sure that I understood because something that came for me was pretty
strong um so the feelings or the senses
that are uh of the stimulated by the outside right and then they are um
feeling or Sensations or phenomenas that are coming from the inside and is it
that when we remove kind of the sense of self and we and you know the self is
stimulated by what it it contact with in the external world and we deep go down
like what you are talking about I had a sense that
um then we reach kind of the elemental Bing
blocks of our beings in a way and um the re the reason why you were talking about
like compassion and love is to me what comes to is when we come down to that
Elemental sensient being kind of operating system then we are in
interconnected with both the planet and other beings and so but that is why this
love or compassion is coming there is no more I'm Sylvie yeah I'm I'm really part
of the Ecology of the universe very nice
I like this very much so but I like to respond a little bit to you um uh I
agree with you but I want to be a little bit few care careful with a couple of things one is we don't want to make the
sense of self too much of a problem because it's vague what we're talking about we say sense of self more Central
to the issue is attachment you know clinging to something um and uh so sense of self
often comes with attachment doesn't I mean doesn't have to and so if it's no
attachment maybe it's okay it's it's safe enough but it's the attachment and the reason why the attachment Narrows
the attention it uh it uh keeps us out of touch with a wider field of Who We Are
and it's through attachment then that uh we're not in touch with all the
different ways Rich ways in which a senses take in other people where we
have mirror neurons we have all these different ways in which we are attuned in a very deep way to other people that
we feel really connected in a very rich way that uh is that attachment is the
barrier for so that so that that's the little it's okay with you it's a little bit of a yeah I mean in a way you're
saying that the attachment is what comes on top of our Elemental Humanity it
covers it covers it right so we're not so we can't be in touch with it yes and so when when we are at that attached
level we cannot really be fully uh connected with the universe and other
people yes very nice sh thank you so
so okay I think that um so in a few minutes there's it'll
take a while to get the lunch ready and um everyone's welcome to the polu and
whether you're brought anything or not the most important thing to bring is yourself and uh and that uh because it's
a potluck it's a little bit social if you would be so willing to take a few minutes here to say hello to the people
around you and introduce yourself maybe to at least two people so no one's left alone in the middle of just look around
so everyone's get and if you want to share some ideas that came out of this talk for you that's important that would
be nice but um it's just nice to have make the connection here easily at begin
so thank you