so as I said earlier um I I'm a recent
graduate of the Eco chapy program and so this is a topic very dear
to my heart um so I've been on this long slow
Evolution towards being more connected with nature
um and this accelerated exponentially during the
pandemic so before the lockdown as people call it
um I would um I knew that I was always a little anxious in the mornings and I
would get up and get the kids off to school and go run errands and things like that um have my
meetings uh and I thought it was uh just this restlessness and anxiety was
just something that I just needed to get out into the world right and connect with people but then the pandemic came
and we couldn't go anywhere right we had to stay home and so I just went outside
my front door and sat on my patio and I
realized I just needed to be outside it was amazing how my nervous system
just powered down and so you know at first I just started
to uh meditate outside and then it became my
office um it was kind of funny the UPS man one time my husband was sitting out
in the front UPS was like where is Hillary why are you in her office um so before that I used to
meditate inside and just trying to let go of my
egocentric worries right but if only I had known how
effortless it was to realize anata or not self just by going
outside right my fra ego buffeted by these eight worldly Winds of praise and
blame gain and loss Pleasure and Pain success and
failure that all fell away as I became part of a much
bigger ecosystem grass and trees bushes and
flowers birds and squirrels Big Blue Sky the clouds the
sun sometimes the rain I was no longer separate
self but part of something much bigger and interdependent and I realized that it
wasn't just up to me to go do stuff make things happen that all of nature was
working with me to help create balance and
equinity so this new feeling of belonging began to arise in me I
realized that the elements in my body were from the earth and formed in the
stars and that my genes were just the latest uh incarnation of a long line of
ancestors who had been through countless traumatic events including natural
disasters plagues Wars to say nothing of childbirth and
illness without Mom modern medicine and the most amazing thing of
all is the realization and this is not only true for me it's true for every single one of
us that's on the planet right now alive is that every single one of our
progenitors lived long enough to birth and care for the Next
Generation back through our parents our grandparents great great great grand
grandparents all the way back to the first human and the first
mammal on land and then in the water in the oceans all the way back to the first
one celled organism four and a half billion years
ago every single one in our line from that beginning to where we are now live
lived through all kinds of of traumatic events and wonderful events for us to be
here like just take a moment and take that in what is the probability of
that it's it's it's got to be less than 1% it's got to be something infinitism
small and yet we are all here
so there has been a lot of there have been a lot of ups and downs in the world's history and there's a lot of
disequilibrium on the planet right now not only in the what's happening um
in terms of politics and Wars but the the um the whole climate crisis right
and some people say that we're at a Tipping Point and there's not much time left and so some of some people are just
in total denial right oh just can't go there um and then others are just shut
down in fear and paralysis and some just want to distract
like I just want to try to be happy before you know it all burns
up but in Buddhism we are incouraged not to
tell ourselves stories right just be with what is don't tell yourself a story
but we humans do tell stories and the story We Tell
matters so it's called wise view the first step on the eight-fold
path with what eyes do we see if we see through the eyes of
hopelessness we will passively let things happen without taking action action is
the fourth step on on the path fful path but with hope we move out of freeze
into flow I love this definition of hope I read in a book called rooted by lean
leanda ly H I'm not sure if that's the right pronunciation but she found this in a
Benedictine library in a book it says hope is that virtue by which which we
take responsibility for the future we are co-creators right of our future which is
empowering she says the hope I'm interested in is about broad
perspectives with specific possibilities ones that invite or demand
that we act it's also not a sunny everything is going to get better
narrative though it may be a counter to the everything is getting worse
narrative you could call it an account of complexities and uncertainties with
openings it's a recognition that we in fact do have the capability to turn
things around and if we have wise intention step two on the path combined
with wise speech action livelihood and effort which are steps 3 through six we can do
this but first we must all learn to love this
beautiful Earth we will save what we love what we
cherish but part of the problem is as leanda says in rooting in countless ways
modern culture and urban habits contrive to separate us from our
indwelling earn intelligence while we have while we have
more scientific knowledge of the universe than any people ever had it is
not the type of knowledge that leads to an intimate presence within a meaningful
Universe with the rise of the modern Sciences we began to think of the
universe as a collection of objects rather than a communion of
subjects we talk about the Earth in terms of
resources not as source source of Life of nourishment of
beauty so Robin wal Kimmer is a Native American um scientist a
biologist she says that we it what we don't understand when
we see a bird or butterfly or tree or Rock whose name we don't know we it
it I would never point to you and call you it it would steal your
personhood itting turns gifts into natural resources it gives us permission
to see the land as an inanimate object these beings are not it they are our
relatives instead considering using key I think that's how she would pronounce
it key for singular or kin for plural spelled
Ki this is kimmer's imitation be more respectful of the
natural world by using key and instead of it these are variants of the ashabi word
Aki meaning Earthly being and if you're concerned that this
amounts to appropriation of native ideas kimra says that to appropriate is to steal whereas adoption of key and kin
reclaims the grammar of animacy and is thus a
gift so living beings even the Rocks the soil and the
water infused with life
so we we have this tendency to separate ourselves from nature so
objectify um but we also talk about taking a walk
or going for the for a hike in nature right but the truth is we are
nature natur we are nature going to take a walk in
nature so how often do we do that really mindfully when we when we do our walking
meditation we do that very mindfully how often do we take a walk without taking our
phone without chatting with someone or listening to a podcast or listening to
music or or just snapping pictures all the time I I must have admit I do a lot
of that right we want to capture the moment um it's okay to do that a little bit but but do we just stop and look do
we just see sometimes so there are many people who live in urban areas right which is not a
bad thing it's not a bad idea for people to congregate kind of together and leaving wildness more wildness um more
Wilderness um Liam says that new psych
new work in Psychology reveals that simply the knowledge of flourishing
wild just knowing that there's Wilderness there's wildness positively
affects our psychology and creativity and it's this knowledge that
we are called to cultivate daily so Studies have shown that people
in hospitals when they can see out a window and see
Greenery their healing accelerates simply the fragrance of
certain trees invokes calm does anybody like if I just say pine pine tree does
anybody can you have a felt sense of that I I
do and it brings some calm and recorded nature sounds also do that for us even
gazing at a house plant so wherever we are even in a
high-rise apartment in the city gaze upon a house PL look out the
window step out onto the balcony or onto the rooftop connect with the skies the
clouds the Sun the rain the birds in a book called Church of the Wild by
Victoria lur she says we long to experience the sacred and in that
longing forget to look outside our window and engage in
conversation with a world that is already
sacred but better still but take a walk
outside right in Japan in the early 1980s um Health practitioners started to
realize the benefits of walking in nature um shinin Yoku Forest
bathing and um Healthcare practitioners would actually prescribe people to go do
Forest bathing and in 2016 Professor Miyazaki compiled all
these scientific studies and he said that all of our
psychophysiological functions are adapted to Natural outdoor
settings he his research showed how walks outside lower blood pressure decrease the heart rate reduce cortisol
production improve blood sugar levels improve immune
function and just overall physiological relaxation
just 15 minutes a day Forest Walkers had a 102%
increase in the parasympathetic calming
right so it's it's like when we take a deep breath a long slow out breath in
our meditation it activates that parasympathetic nervous system let's just do that right now together
breathing deeply in long slow out breath
how do you feel I feel instantly better I don't know about you it's so
easy um and being outside also helps to do that for our
nervous system it's a way of letting go of releasing daoka
suffering so one of the daily practices we were encouraged to do in Eco Chaplan C was to find a sit spot does anybody
have a set spot do you know about that no okay so choose a special place
outside where you can return to daily for me it's just going out and sitting on my patio out in front of my
house get to know the land that you're sitting on get to know
the rooted green beings and the for legged and winged
beings along with the changing light different times of year the changing
seasons so perhaps you've heard of the term kith and kin and we all know what
kin is and I was like what is kth does anybody know what kth
is um it actually means the land where you
are so with the exception of Native
Americans we are a nation of immigrants right whether or not our
ancestors or or we chose to come here in search of New
Opportunities or came against our will as slaves we are
transplants right just like plants from another place we are from somewhere else
and we can feel uprooted and not feeling a sense of
belonging where we are so finding a Sit spot is a way to
help us cultivate that feeling of belonging in um the book rooted leanda
refers to this as return and be claimed not only do we come to know this
place to SI spot but we feel a mutuality of being known to each
other in her book she writes that Linda Mapes who wrote a book called witness
tree spent a whole year visiting a single oak tree every
day and she told me she has no doubt that in time the tree recognized her
presence that they belong to each other so tick not Han engaged in hugging a
spiritual practice when he said when we hug our hearts connect and we know that we are not
separate beings breathing in I know my dear one
is in my arms alive breathing out so
precious to me if you do this the tree being hugged
will be nourished and Bloom like a flower so on an eapen SE um Richie we
were invited to connect with the tree first asking the tree's
permission right we want to be really respectful um and so when we feel that
permission is given perhaps we might simply gaze at the tree we might feel it
spk we might lean against the tree
we might wrap our arms around the tree and we might just listen for some
wisdom it might have for us so we were in beautiful Redwood
forest in the Santa Cruz mountains and there these just just straight up to the
sky 100 200 ft these redwood trees and so I was wandering outside trying to
find my tree that I was going to connect with and one just caught my
interest and I walked over and asked if it was okay if I could connect with
her and I felt it was a yes
and this tree was bent was curved over and then it went this way and that
way trying to find the light in this Forest of
Giants and I felt such a deep kinship a resonance like how I too in my
life right had to bend and twist and
turn trying to find nourishment and and and reach for the
light and for all the twists and turns and Bess and the crookedness of this
strong it stood up through the through the storms
right and so I thanked her for sharing the wisdom right and her strength and I
felt stronger inside of myself for connecting with this beautiful
tree so another practice we might engage in is called earthing I know this is
really popular I don't know decades ago maybe in the 70s where you take off your shoes and you put your feet on the on
the ground has anybody done
that so we speak of being grounded right for some
stability and in terms of electricity right we need that third prong that goes into the the outlet right in case
there's a surge of electricity it actually goes into the ground right
right the ground absorbs it so when we place our bare feet on the
earth anxiety and stress can flow from us into the
Earth I have done this myself and I've done this with uh people that I know who
have been really emotionally disregulated in the middle of a panic
attack and it has a very calming
effect walking with your feet your bare feet on the ground tick not
Han he's passed away but I I speak of him in the present tense because his
teachings live on tonan invites us through mindful walking to feel that
each footstep is kissing the
Earth so in in rooted leanda combines both practices hugging a tree with bare
feet she describes the experience with shoes shed we become closer to them the
trees as our mentors putting not just a cheek but an
ear directly upon a tree's bark allows deep listening the rhythmic movement of the
blood in our bodies the cranial I cranos sacral fluid of our spines and
skulls mirrors the movement of sap in the trees the breeze in a rustling hair is
the same as that in the leaves the branches the
clouds she also reads to the trees she likes to read Emily Dickinson in
particular in the book The Enchanted Life by Sharon Blacky she tells the
story of restoration ecologist suaa sh shashan I'm sorry if I'm
mispronouncing that from India who sings as she walks through the
jungle and she says partly because the animal sing so sweetly to me all the
time it's their generosity that I aspire to match but singing is also my direct
announcement to others in the forest I am here I walk alone I come in
peace I believe that singing transmits much more than presence it carries
information about the state of my body the state of my emotion and my
intention they can of course choose to stay or leave but usually they are not
alarmed and they know it's me the singing woman from the hill
so when I sit in meditation sometimes in the morning I'll do some chanting and I've noticed sometimes the
birds will get quiet as I chant and I feel somehow I'm singing to
them and then I stop and they start singing and I feel like they're singing
to me so we sing to each other or when the Raven cause actually
this happened just before I came here I was sitting outside and there was a raven I think connecting with another
one in another tree but I tried to answer [Applause]
back although I'm afraid I do not know what I said I'm hoping it wasn't
anything bad because I would love to know Raven language but I
don't so there are many ways to connect with our kith and kin and the children
program um the Dharma Sprouts we sing this um Betsy R song that's called
breathing in breathing out and we actually meditate also um we the the
words go I am blooming as a flower and as we breathe in we open our
flowers fresh as the Dew I am solid as the mountain and the kids put their
hands up over their head heads like a mountain firm as the Earth I'm feeling
the Earth firm beneath us I am water reflecting what is real
what is true and I feel there space deep
inside of me and I'm free so in Buddhist terms to be
equanimous is to be centered and grounded to feel grounded on the earth
we sit in meditation we're sitting cross-legged like a mountain right we are in the
shape of a mountain wide at the base right smaller at the
top feeling at stability and when we sit up
right their backbones straight we're like the trunk of a
tree and our breath is like that
reflection the Blue Sky reflection right reflecting what
is accepting without resistance and we make space inside and
around us cultivating peace so there were two very pivotable
pivotal experiences of the Buddha on his journey to
Enlightenment and he began with um one of them is remembering a time when he
was six and he was sitting under a rose apple tree and he could hear the adults in the
distance they were doing a ritual tilling of the ground and it said that he sat in
seclusion from sensual desire feeling an utter sense of contentment and happiness
that came from within himself it wasn't dependent on something outside of himself and yet I cannot help but
feel that it was through the five senses that he felt he felt his way into a deep sense
of Peace into samade I imagine this shade of an overarching
tree this Rose apple tree keeping him a little cooler as the warmth from the Sun lulled
him and the apple blossom so beautifully blooming I can imagine
looking through the branches of the tree up to the blue sky and the smell of the apple
blossoms hearing the hum of the insects and the chirping of
birds feeling the firm ground beneath his
body another pivotal moment was sitting under the bod tree and he committed to staying there
until he achieved Enlightenment so Mara sends all kinds of
things enticements and fears armies of demons and terrible
storms and finally the final Challenge on this path to Enlightenment
with self-doubt who do you think you are to become
enlightened right the Buddha did not answer with
words he simply reached down and touched the
Earth and the Earth affirmed his worthiness as each one of us is equally
worthy to become enlightened so nature teaches us so many
things one of the most important is non-judgmental awareness right that is like the basic definition of
mindfulness it is an unselfconscious
beingness right nature teaches us that right no matter how we come in into
nature nature that we are going out into nature no matter how well-dressed or
bare skinned we are right whether we are sad or we're
anxious we are um bathed or we don't smell good
right we are not shamed or shunned we're just part of nature just another
animal if we are respectful we are welcome we are not separate
right and in our connections with Mother Nature we begin to feel this
appreciation this gratitude love in braiding sweet grass Robin wal
Kimmer writes knowing that you love the Earth changes you activates you to
defend and protect and celebrate but when you feel that the
Earth loves you you in return that feeling transforms a
relationship from a one-way Street into a sacred Bond the land loves us back she loves us
with beans and tomatoes with roasting ears of corn and blackberries and bird
songs by a shower of gifts and a heavy rain of lessons she provides for us and
teaches us to provide for ourselves that's what good mothers
do so in reclaiming the wild Soul by Mary Reynolds Thompson she says if we
don't reclaim and come to love our inner wildness how much more of the Earth's
wild places will we be willing to destroy let the great rewilding of our
world begin with you with me with all of us whoever we
are wherever we live no matter our ethnicity our sex our religion political
affiliation nationality we are all children of this
Earth and when we climb up to a mountain or we fly up in an airplane we look down
upon the Land There are no map lines right
and if we are able to escape Earth's gravity we will find ourselves in the
Blackness of outer space looking back at the
Earth only astronauts have had this perspective and they have brought back
pictures when a particular Earth rise I'm sure everybody's seen that beautiful
picture of the Earth from the Moon and they' brought back accounts
personal accounts of how this moved them so deeply and in the words of one astronaut
Edgar Mitchell suddenly from behind the rim of
the Moon in long slow motion moments of
immense Majesty there emerges a sparkling blue
and white Jewel a light delicate sky High blue
sphere laced with slowly swirling veils of white Rising gradually like a small
Pearl in a thick sea of black mystery it takes more than a moment to
fully realize this is Earth
home so may we all know ourselves as one
family with a deep deep love and appreciation for kith and
Ken knowing that only do we Earth love the Earth but the Earth loves us
back and may we save the Earth save what we
love so thank you for your attention and now we have um
some time for questions and for Reflections and
for connecting with each other about how this may have landed for you and what
comes up for you
so do anybody have anything they want to share or any
questions or how how this might feel in your body and your
heart and I also want to invite people to um one thing that I like to do
sometimes is to invite people into small groups of three or so if you want to
really feel a deeper connection with sa and Community if that feels something
that you'd like to do maybe you could gather into groups of three and then just share you know how was this for you
and then we can come back together and see what came up for you so feel free to do that say hi introduce yourself and
we'll come back in about 10 minutes if you want to come back to our
larger Circle I I'd love to hear you know a few shares uh about what came up
for
you all like as well Jim here works for NASA so
perhaps I can help you I'm too claustrophobic frankly to go
up knowing me and $5 will get you a cup of
coffee it used to be 25 sense but
oh I actually have I got it for one of my kids um who loves astronauts and
things that are base oriented and I have a poster of earthrise that is signed by
Edgar Mitchell there's something is very special about I don't know I kind of put
my hand on the signature it's like wow this person has actually been you know in space looking back at
Earth whoa
special yeah oh do you want the microphone
yeah yeah
online testing oh yeah I think one of the things we talked about and or I
certainly shared a lot about um this word alienation and the
example I think it comes up for a lot of us but just how disconnected we are
from uh nature is one of them but like it could be from each other things that we do and so I thought
of the kind of Supermarket I'm going there later but just how many things we take for granted
that like we don't know where the source is necessarily or you know of the food
the process food anything I mean when so we partition things we're like oh this is water this is bottled and it's here
and you buy it like we create these extra things and um so a lot of the
exercises and just thinking about and connecting Back To Nature makes you kind of realize like
kind of how roundabout it is that we we do all these things to like repurpose it
or sell it back to each other things like that so it was
a you can never overthink that I think yeah and I love the way um when we
do um a blessing on food when we think about the
interconnectedness like when we're actually taking in nourishment
like how many how much there is that we are taking in Tak on H and I loved how
he's with this with his interbeing um teachings you know talks
about with every bite of food we're taking in the soil the food grew in and
the Sun and the clouds and the rain and all of and the farmers and the Farm
Workers and the people the truck drivers and the store people at the store and pretty soon it's like oh my gosh who
wasn't involved with this right we're so interdependent it's amazing um and the
thing that I love too about um really focusing on on putting our
attention on food is that and I used to think about this Earth as being kind of
like a nightmare of everything trying to eat everything else you know whether it's plants or animals I mean it's like
we're eating each other it's like oh that's awful and then I thought no wait a minute it
it's like it's a Sacrament it is a a gifting of life to each other like when
I eat the strawberry it's like it was a seed and it grew and it got plump and
red and juicy and then it got picked and
then I take it in right and it's a strawberry that's gifted its life to me
and I am now taking it in and it becomes part of me to nourish myself it's like
wow you know I me some people talk about sacralizing you know making sacred you
know everyday life and when we really stop to think about it
um it's hard not to right thank you for that share any
anything else one one one share maybe or
or not if but I I do want to finish with I I've got this poem that um is called
No Matter What by Kai sidenberg from a a book of poems poems of Earth and
spirit no matter how hard they try they cannot keep us apart they can pour
concrete over the rich dark Earth put us in a plastic chair inside a sheetrock
box hook us up to electronic devices and tell us we have to stay there all day
and still we will be breathing the breath of towering Pines growing on
rugged Mountain slopes and Tiny green Plankton floating in dis
seas and even though the water we drink travels through many miles of pipe is doused with chlorine and maybe contain
in plastic bottles still we will be drinking water
that has tumbled over Granite Boulders hibernated in frozen lakes and reflected
The Morning Sun from a spider's web and even though the salad weed may
be grown hundreds of miles away harvested and washed by hands we will never sea and packaged in a plastic
box still we will be eating leaves from plants whose Roots embrace the Fertile
Earth as their tender green bodies reach toward the light and no matter how
relentlessly we have been trained to sit still to hold our tongues to follow the
rules even when they make no sense still we are animals of Flesh and Blood kin to
Deer bear and whale with deep wisdom in our bones and Untamed passions in our
hearts still there's a wild one inside us running Barefoot through the forest Gathering sweet berries dancing around
the fire singing To The Moon so I hope that we will
be more mindfully bodily
connected to the Earth to the
cosmos and that we will really love this Earth and do all we can
to save the planet from more desecration and um with
hopefulness right with hopefulness we can do it we just need
the to come together right and um so thank you so much for your
coming this evening for your practice and take good care
and hope to see you soon