welcome uh welcome folks good to be with
you yeah welcome to you all okay we'll uh we'll sit
so finding uh getting situated and finding
uh finding your posture
relaxing whatever can be relaxed
allowing any tension that remains to
remain and we relax in order to feel
more we relax in order
to give our nervous system a little
break we relax because
clinging always carries a kind of burden of tension
we relax because it feels
good and because it conveys to life our confidence that we can meet
it e
what would it be like if we were deeply
unafraid of our inner
life for
what would it be like if we just assumed our safety for these 30
minutes that it was okay to
deeply relinquish our vigilance
rather than Patrol
phenomena we surrender to
them
e
e e
um breath might be an anchor sound might be an
anchor the hands or feet or some pleasantness in your body might be an
anchor the anchor might be everywhere
but even as we incline our minds
towards surrender relinquishment non vigilance
we're nurturing uh the
clarity of the attention high
resolution not foggy not mediated by dense
story
e e
our attention snags on phenomena like a hang
nail on
fabric we momentarily forget a
nature impermanence
and then we let
go knowing experience Moment by moment
but not holding it
still
e
e e
you're too busy
knowing to feel like you have a vantage
point too busy
knowing to keep tabs on who you are how you're
doing too busy
knowing to keep track of
the million things right and the million that are wrong in this
moment
e
e e
you get caught up not even not even the slightest problem
just forgive
yourself and SE that
ground and get busy
knowing
for
e
e e
too busy knowing to have even the faintest
clue about who you are
about your strengths and
limitations
e
e e
it's good to uh good to sit with
you so over the 12 years or so that I've been
teaching full-time um I've received a lot of of feedback
and uh I used to be featured in a kind of
video course that you know maybe 5 10,000 people would
take uh each year and uh to complete the
course the learning management system required people to give detailed
feedback so they could not get course credit unless yes they gave detailed
feedback on the trainers of which I was
one and this this is uh if you if you
think you truly understand anata read the feedback from 10,000
strangers you know so even still I've
always I've always kind of valued it uh even if sometimes
it's jangly or something but I valued it because it it illuminates you know it
the response to feedback illuminates the architecture of self
view the kind of sacred cows of self and we usually think like okay I'll
take in the feedback that's right and I'll refuse the feedback that's off base
and that's fair enough but I think from a Buddhist perspective
it's like regardless of whether the feedback is right or wrong if it highlights
defensiveness it's a value it's a value because wherever there's
defensiveness there's clinging and clinging can always lead us to to
harming self and other
so I say all of that as a kind of introduction to a little piece of
feedback that's been lodged deep deep in my brain maybe like medulla oblongata
deep kind of like the part that regulates breathing
you're rooting for me you're rooting for me you're hoping it's not that bad
you're hoping I'm going to be okay just just stop rooting stop rooting
it's about to get real so this person this guy turned out
to like me this is in La um but when he walked into the Dharma
Hall and saw me sitting up on the de his first thought was um who is this
middle manager of Kinkos about to give us all a Dharma
talk rip Kinkos you know
but yeah okay now maybe I laugh about that so
that I don't cry or I laugh to diffuse some kind of shame or something like
that but honestly when I heard that and when I say it it brings a lot of
delight it brings a lot of delight I I think because there's
something true about it there's something true about it and
this is not like my self-hatred talking this is not that W my my sense of self was not a
casualty in that moment at all but I do think that maybe I read a
little bit like a junior manager of
Kingo and I think I I think I read I think I read like that because there
are of course certain aspects of practice that are under
developed and so the dharma's a thousand beautiful qualities and if we cultivate
even a few we're fortunate right so I was talking with a a Dharma
friend and uh she also took the liberty of giving me some feedback you know just
just open open season on the esteemed leader of certain
Wednesdays okay so more feedback and um and she said you know
sometimes she uses a very simple map of capacities head heart
belly head referring to Clarity
discernment you know the kind of pristine kind of view conceptual
understanding coherence allows us to cut through the static and illuminate what
matters and uh in heart referring to uh kind of affective sensitivity and
empathic connection and love and Attunement and compassion this
realm and then belly
belly referring to
groundedness groundedness presence
earthiness the kind of weight the force of a person's
presence involves the belly involves a certain kind of deep
embodiment and this friend who I trust totally said you know Matthew kind of
have developed two of the three you can guess maybe which
underdeveloped belly belly kind
of the weightiness of uh the yeah the
the weightiness of presence so why why am am why am I
telling you all this am I using you as like a therapeutic mirror or something to you know to get whatever to
no no not at all telling you this
because a teacher cannot only share their wisdom
but uh also their delusion right we share wisdom and delusion because I
can't tell the difference between the two and so sometimes it feels reasonable just to kind of come clean oh okay I see
clearly their aspects of the path that uh are I want to keep
developing n said one one um one repays
a teacher badly if one always remains nothing but a
pupil and so I'm telling you this because the student is expected to
exceed the teacher I'm telling you this because
it's um it's
fascinating how the Dharma kind of yeah or the Dharma grows and it's
somehow kind of can grow and accommodate our own Neurosis in a graceful way sort
of but it's like we can practice in such a way that there are certain aspects of
the path that we really don't notice and that image that I I I've
mentioned before of like you know when like a tree branch that has grown like
entangled with a power wire up on a telephone pole you know
and the electrical crew just deems like okay we're just going to have to cut
both sides of the branch and then there's that chunk of wood that's just
suspended by The Thin Line you know and I kind of I don't know
there's something about that image that makes me think of the ways in which
kind of like you know just the gnarled pieces of us just grow around something
uh sort of um force it to accommodate our our pain or
something and this is all fine it's like yeah generally it's good
to develop our strengths but then we got to double back to what comes less
naturally you know I'm telling you this because uh
because the Dharma is so wild it's so wild it has so many surprises in store
for us I don't I don't know that those stop
you know but the unwillingness to be startled you
know is uh is maybe a sign there's something deadening in
us and so so
we yeah growth is always a little startling it's a little
startling we get kind of comfortable in one mode of practice and then the rug
gets pulled out from us we get we sort of like at some cruising altitude and
then some there's some turbulence something changes and the encouragement is just
like yeah to be open to being startled to be open to having some vision of who who we
are kind of like cracked open you
know we we practice
um yeah we cease to predict you know predict cease
predicting ourselves in the next week or day or
moment you can maybe sense the kind of openness of
that and so yeah growth is kind of startling sometimes you
know but we do not shy away from it you know that's kind of like the Dharma
attitude I feel do not shy away from it we're here for too little time we
all are here for too little time die too
soon and so we trust that there's there's nothing nothing nothing you can
discover about yourself that will be a reason to love yourself less and you
know that in your bones then the self-exploration becomes
Reckless and
uh yeah becomes just
all all it's all dhama all
love so offer this for your consideration and uh we'll be uh back
next week okay folks