good evening welcome nice to see you all in this
windy rainy day makes us happy I think that it rains
after having gone through that drought makes me
happy so I don't know if we need to turn on the recording or if
that's thank you Jim so I'm going to continue on this series
of talks talking about like efforting or making something happen or determination
resolve you know these types of things and uh I'm touching into some of the
lists and stories that aren't so commonly spoken about they're definitely in there in the suit as I'm pulling them
out of there but uh not as often spoken about and in some subsequent talks I'll
talk about some of the dangers of what I'm talking about but I'm not there yet so right now we're just going to talking
about uh you know just this movement towards an aspiration we have or we have
an inspiration and then how do we carry through and what are the things that get in the way and how can we find our way
through to what's important to us what's meaningful to us so I'll say very briefly that um I
started this series talking about the five factors of endeavoring
and those five factors are confidence Vitality Integrity energy and
wisdom and then I talked about uh the next week I did a talk on setting an
aspiration and then having this resolve to go pursue that
aspiration and I did that with the story of Prince bod who didn't want to make
any effort towards uh doing something that was important to him and said he was hoping that the Buddha would make
all the effort and uh that didn't work out so well for Prince
B and then uh last week I talked about well why don't we do these things that
we set out to do we really want to our heart toci set on them set on them it's meaningful for us and why don't do we
and I pointed out another quality that the Buddha talked about Ki which can be
translated both as tolerance and as patience because the reason why we don't
do things it's hard and it takes time it's not a secret come to find out
we're I think we're all kind of secretly opening right that there'll be hoping that there'll be some secret teaching
that'll make a difference but even just this idea of County tolerance and
patience just to cultivate it in really small mundane everyday settings this is
exactly how how it gets cultivated we don't wait until the really hard stuff arrives instead we start where it's easy
we always start where it's easy like why not that's the best way to go
forward so tonight I'm going to start with um a little story a brief story and
this is with h bad waja who the farmer Cassi Brad
waa and this was the first day of of the um of the planting season this was the
time of year when they were going to plant and Casi Brad waja is a Brahman
he's a priest in this brahmanical tradition and was doing a big like festival and ritual and all these things
to for to start the season of planting makes sense right if you're the
kind of the whole Community depends on the crops surviving it's not like they
can import easily from other places where they didn't have this Logistics that we have today so a
lot of importance on having the crops work so there of course there were these
uh festivals at the first day and so here's a description of the
festival that comes like 800 years after the time of the Buddha and they're like
filling in the details but I I kind of like this uh so there's this Festival there was
3,000 oxen were present this is a lot we don't have to take the numbers
literally in uh in the sutas and uh certainly in Polly there's not as much
emphasis on Precision there's more emphasis on just big bigger biggest you
know and so 3,000 is a big number so 3,000 oxen and all their horns were kept
with gold and their Hooves were kept with silver and they were adorned with
fragrant garlands so they put the decorations on the o and I like this it
brings a nice uh image to mind you know for this festival and then there were
500 people and all of them were wearing clean white clothes and they also were
wearing garlands and were garnished with had some flowers and Kasi bradan he was
the head uh priest and he was going to lead the festival so he took a bath it's
so funny that this is in the details right he took a bath trimmed his beard and anointed himself with fragrant
scents so I got all dressed up I'm I'm sure this is before right they
have all that stuff but um he had two rings on each finger so he had 20 rings
and he was wearing earrings he had had a turban on his head a Garland around his neck I'm not sure I think these garlands
are made out of flowers but they also might be made out of wooden beads I'm not sure and then um he does this ritual
with uh milk and rice and then he offers this milk and rice to the 500 people
that are about to take the 3,000 oxen and start the season so a lot of people
a lot of animals this is a big and you can imagine how much effort it went into
to prepare for something like this I don't know if they literally had gold and silver and but clearly just time to
decorate or you know the animals and oneself so as it happens that the Buddha
was nearby and he had this sense that uh
maybe this Cassy bradaa he could find some more freedom
so he approaches and as if he's on Ms so
here's this person who just did this big ritual and this festival and he's feeding all these people sees the Buddha
he's just wearing robes and has a bowl right and is looking for a
meal and um Cas bread W is a little bit uh irked about the Buddha and he
says I plow and sew you know sew seeds to plant I plow and sew aesthetic so
he's just calling the Buddha aesthetic like just this generic word you're somebody who is just like a
Wanderer I plow in so athetic and having plowed and sewn I eat you too must plow
and sew and having plowed and S you can eat saying like there is no free ticket
here that uh you have to do the work and it's we reap the benefits of the work
that we've done so just like Brad Wan he thinks the Buddha should do the same and
the Buddha replies I too Brahman plow and SE and
having plowed and sewn I eat and then uh the Brahman says but we
don't see your Yol your plow your oxen like where's if you're really a farmer
where's why aren't you participating in this festival and where's all your implements and animals and things like
this so then um Brad waja he uh decides okay I'm going to speak in verse and
this happens a lot in the suas when there's like an important conversation happening it often shows up in verse so
whether they actually spoken verse or whether this event actually ever happened of course I don't know but so
here's a W what he says to the Buddha you claim to be a farmer but we
do not see your plowing tell us about your plowing so that we can understand
your farming okay how do you farm without plowing and then the Buddha he gives a
number of different descriptions of how he does it I'm not going to talk about all of those maybe at a future time I
will I want to focus on this one stanza where the Buddha
says maybe I should say that um he the Buddha says that he plows with wisdom so
his blade is wisdom that like cuts through things and I'll unpack that a little bit more in a minute here but
Buddha says energy or effort is my Beast of Burden carrying one towards security
from bondage it goes ahead without turning back to where one does not
sorrow so he's saying energy is my Beast of
birden so of course a beast of burden that's like an oxen something that's like pulling something that's heavy or
carrying something that's heavy so the Buddha he's like saying just as the
Brahman paraja just as he is using an oxen and he has this blade that's like
breaking up the Earth like tilling the earth I guess and then this blade when it goes
through it uh like severs these the networks of the all the roots of the
weeds or whatever is growing there so the way that he's tilling it and so the Buddha is saying in the same way he has
this plow of wisdom so the blade is wisdom but rather than having oxen
carrying the blade blade it's effort energy or effort that's allowing
this blade to go through and rather than severing all the roots of the of the
weeds it's severing the defilements these are roots of unskillful behavior
unskillful things in the mind and then the so energy is my beast
of burden and I try not to think of the rolling stone song when I hear this
right do you guys think of [Laughter] this and then the second line is a
carrying one toward security from bondage and so we could say that nabana
Awakening is the security from bondage like what are those things that hold us back what are the things that we get
tied up with or that uh push us around
you know that kind of this idea of bondage is like something that's preventing you from doing what you want to do so you have security from Bond so
nothing standing in the way can do whatever you
want so this no longer being pushed around by our incessant desires or these
uh things that trying to get away from something or or the concerns that we
have we want to look good or we want to feel comfortable all the time no longer being pushed around by all
that and the third line is it goes ahead without turning back so the Buddha is
describing his plow goes ahead without turning back and this is in contrast to
of course like the Brahman right reaches the end of the field it has to turn around it has to turn around and goes
back and forth and then of course next season has to do it all over again however many growing Seasons there are
in a year but it has to be done repeatedly but this uh this plow of
wisdom something that I appreciate very much the Buddha saying it only goes
forward it's not like you regress with our practice we're going
forward it's true we have some insights we have some new understandings which we totally forget later and then we learn
them again but that's different than going
backwards there are times in which uh we don't have access to our greatest wisdom
or maybe we um are under a lot of stress or illness or something and we don't
have our full capacities but this path goes
forward it never goes backwards I don't know I this is like
such an obvious thing but for me it feels um I know meaningful that each whatever
we're doing for practice whether it's just one moment of mindfulness or listening to a Dharma talk or um
behaving ethically or having some Compassion or kindness for others it's
always supporting this movement towards greater Freedom always always it's
always going forward and it's always talk and what's also being spoken about here is this
irreversibility of some experiences that we've had or even
some attainments that we've had specifically the Buddha here is talking about you know some degrees of Awakening
or insights like once that happens you can't go back and the way
that I think about this is kind of like once you've learned to read you can't unlearn how to read unless you know
there's some Dementia or something like this that's happening so the same
way and then the last line to where to where one does not
sorrow in some ways this is all what we what we all want right to not have
sorrow and again this is pointing to nabana
Awakening so this idea that wisdom is the blade and energy is what is helping
this blade go forward so rather than oxen it's energy or effort
one thing I'll say is that um oxen often
not always are like there's two or four or six there's a number of them and
something that I appreciate about this is that the same way energy sometimes we're with others and maybe our energy
is low and theirs is high and we can borrow some of their energy or maybe there's a way just like in the same way
that we practice here together being with others Maybe you sit a little longer than you would if you were at
home or pay more attention or do something differently when you're with
others so there's a way that doing things with others can be a tremendous support it's not always a support
sometimes we have to do things on our own also but there can be a way when we talk about energy or effort there can be
this real sense of like I have to do this I must do this but I don't think we
should ever underestimate the power of practicing with others what a big
support it is for whatever it is we're doing with our practice or wherever we are in our practice or however we feel a
practice so this idea of energy moving forward Viria is the word sometimes
translated as effort how do we keep this energy
going how do I keep this effort going we might have some initial inspiration
something or aspiration that really motivates us but what can continue to
motivate us and especially after like it's gotten
difficult or it's gotten tedious or it's gotten boring or you know just so many
reasons or maybe something else turned out to be more interesting and just kind of our enthusiasm has petered
out so I'd like to talk about another list of course right there's no shortage
of a list that uh gets interpreted so many
different ways um partly because um it's one of those it's amazing the word this
word is really really long I tried to memorize it before I
came over here let's see if I got it it's Chanda Samar padana Sankara Sam G
that's one word has like 40 some odd letters in it
right it's it's a so what it is it's a number of words that are stuck together but so
because it's such a long word and which has all these different parts and it's not clear how these different parts are
related to one another that there's a lot of different interpretations on what
does this really mean and it's never explained anywhere in the suit do it's just this
so I uh recently heard a talk by a dma teacher James Barz maybe some of you
know him he teaches in Berkeley wonderful teacher and he uh interpreted
this in a way that I think is really fun and interesting and helpful and relevant
to what we're talking about here so this word that uh I I gave one
of them is uh it's a collection of these four qualities I'll call them
qualities and um The Collection itself is called the idiotas there's lots of different ways
this word idipa gets translated roads to
success bases of power foundations of potency you know
you can ity and pot these two words get together
and some people some teachers some Scholars related specifically to uh the
cultivation of somebody some collectedness but others don't and James
Barz he applies it to motivation what is
it that motivates us what is it that uh keeps us going when we really don't feel
like going and what he did which I think is really interesting he says that these four idas we could
maybe understand them as four temperaments there's four different
things that can motivate people and some people tend to be motivated this way and
some tend to be motivated that way with this recognition that if we understand
this about ourselves then we can really protect and
cultivate this little flame of motivation what what supports this motivation in
ourselves and I appreciate that Maria papova she's a
writer she wrote We are each born with a Wilderness of possibility within us who
we become depends on how we tend to our inner Garden so James BRZ is poting to Let's
tend to our inner garden and part of the way we do that is to recognize for ourselves which one of these
iipas is the way that uh our motivation shows
up so the first one is Chanda so it's Chanda Samar padana
Sankar Chanda this can be translated as Zeal or
enthusiasm so somebody who has this is kind of a wave their orientation or their temperament has this Spirit of
Adventure like okay let's just go for it let's just do it let's jump in you know
they kind of have this uh feeling like all right let's just go they're like
inspired or on fire with like yeah okay whatever we're gonna just do it maybe
maybe that Nike uh logo let's do it and some people maybe they feel this way
about teams some of their sport teams like their you know this tremendous fans and they just have all this enthusiasm
and go yay and are really supporting the team or learn everything about the team
or whatever it might be so this is Chanda or maybe for some people this
they have this enthusiasm for being outside going for walks hanging out in
nature or maybe they have Chanda for a particular cause maybe they have some activism they do or there's a cause at
something that's really important for them and I know for me I had I certainly
had this Chanda this Zeal or enthusiasm at the beginning when I first discovered
this practice I felt like wow it really spoke to me some kind of way and I had
this like voracious appetite to learn about it and to practice and explore and
maybe some of you had the same too when you first encountered these teachings or this
practice so Chanda Zeal or enthusiasm and we could
all of us we could just have this query where do we have that in our life do we
have this enthusiasm or Zeal is there a way that we can nurture it whether it's
for our spiritual life or our um Dharma practice for anything in our life if
it's worthwhile to really acknowledge and honor that this kind of this uplift
Vitality these different words we could use for Zeal
enthusiasm the second idip is Viria
energy this word Viria shows up in so many lists and in so many ways it's a
little bit different so in this way
there's this uh way that we might sometimes ver gets translated as perseverance and that's kind of the
slant I'm going to take here so maybe there's a way in which there's like some
determination or this uh resolve like it's not through enthusiasm but it's
like okay I started and I'm going to finish even though this I don't maybe
I've lost uh enthusiasm for it but you know I started it so I'm going to finish
so there's this coming from this maybe this inner strength of or this sense of
it's important to finish things that we start this way of being undet
undeterred and there's this way I could say for me the way that this uh shows up
is when I'm on Long Retreats I've done Retreats that have been months long I've quite a few Retreats that are months
long it's just natural after been there for you know quite some time you're like
really am I still here there's just like oh my gosh I
can't believe it there's still two more months or you know something like this this just arises of course it
does but there's this sense okay no I started this I'm going to finish I'll
find my way through this and even though right now I'm feeling completely unmotivated doesn't mean I will always
be unmotivated and I'm just going to go to the next it or you know whatever is
needed maybe sometimes what's needed is to go for a walk in nature and feel
booed and nourished that way so is there a way that there can be
like a commitment maybe commitment to practice or just this sense of okay I
started I'm going to finish this uh resolve or determination so that's the second for
for some people that's the way that they're built I know somebody who's very much like this and it's really
impressive they just have this kind of like this doggedness like nope I'm going
I'm no matter what and I can be that about certain things there's a way of kind of like just putting my head down
and going you know just getting it done and it's not always the wisest thing to
do but is there a way that we can think about ourselves when do we have that s
sense of determination can we honor that respect that and maybe even cultivate it allow
that little flame of determination to Glow brightly flame Bri flame
brightly the third idipa is chitta and many of you know that this
word can be pronoun uh translated either mind or heart they didn't make a distinction between mind and heart in uh
the time of the Buddha and I like that James Barz for this he's done this when you've been
touched by the Dharma like you've fallen in love with the Dharma like it's touched something inside of you there's
like something resonating with it where this um maybe and it
um can like fuel this intense desire for like freedom for more or like this it
often happens after you've had a flicker or a glimmer or a glimpse of
something some more ease some more peace some more quiet some more freedom that
you didn't know existed until you started practicing and that certainly has been
the case for me this is reason why I went on these long Retreats is because there was something that I just felt
like like U I don't know I had like touched into I had like a little glimpse of something
and I couldn't even necessarily articulated clearly but this uh this wish to okay I
I want to go this direction not even quite sure exactly
what it was and I would say in my role as a Drama teacher and a retreat teacher
now I see this a lot in students that go on retreat because they have touched
into something and they want to find their way towards that and of course
this can get in our way too if we're trying to recreate an experience we had earlier so instead of this wish to
recreate exactly what we had before maybe to focus in instead on the desire
the the the
wish for to touch that again so instead of focusing on that
thing out there again it's about focusing on oh this this uh energy here
this desire for it and then you might say but wait aren't aren't the Buddhists
supposed to be down on desire are they not supposed to like desire and um somebody did ask Anand
this exact question wait is there to be desire but uh you talk about uh the
Freedom From Desire as nabana and then Anand said in response venerable sir is it true that
you had this desire to go to the park but then when you got to the park
that desire no longer was there and the person said yes and he said it's the
same with this with all these ity poas did you have enthusiasm to go go to the park and
when you arrived there the enthusiasm is no longer there and same With chitta This Heart
felt uh wish to go this desire to go so these are things
that help us along our path but as we're finding more and more freedom they just they're not there they're not needed
anymore and they just naturally fall away they're not an impediment well they can be an impediment but they don't have
to be de facto and then the fourth one this
four via which is we could uh translate as
investigation or curiosity like this way of like wow I
had no idea that this was all going on in my mind before until I started meditating right I think this is the
first Insight that everybody has as soon as you start a meditation practice you start to see like oh my gosh I tried to
stay on the breath but my mind was going everywhere it turned out not to be so easy and there can be this way of like
well what else is happening in there what's going on and can be this
curiosity or this wish to explore or investigate one's inner life the mental
inner life and the emotional inter life in this sense of wow this is
fascinating maybe like in a way that uh you go to a museum natural history
museum for example like wow I had no idea look at this so it's not so much that we have to
figure it out and we're trying to solve a big problem it's just like going to
the museum it's like it's uh interesting and
fun to be sure the things that we discover in our inner life some of them are not all fun some of them are rather
dis disappointing really I don't want to be like that right we discover our
impatience we discover our ill will we discover our how our mind is going to
all these different places that's okay we practice with that
we practice wherever you are whatever is going on practice meets us exactly where we
are and maybe I'll say for me this uh studying the sutas and learning poly has
been for me it's been a big part of that I just enjoy it it's just fun and it's
uh you about practice and it makes me think about my own practice differently and it makes me think like okay how can
I support others differently and gives me some new ideas and I don't know for me it's fun I'm I'm one of those one of
those types of people so these ity poas these four OTAs Chanda Zeal or
enthusiasm the second one is Viria energy effort
perseverance third one is chitta which uh I'm emphasizing here a like being uh
the heart being touched and having this heartfelt wish or desire and the fourth
one is vmsa investigation or
curiosity and it might be easy to think like okay pot is I don't haven't heard about this very much it must not be very
important but it's one of the group of it's there's seven sets so there's this
uh 37 Wings to Awakening eight factors Eightfold Path
seven factors Awakening five faculties five powers for foundations of
mindfulness for great efforts I'll talk about these in a later talk and four
iipas all of these are required for awakening according to the Buddhist
teaching so it's there in this list of things that are to help us support this
movement towards nibana towards greater and greater
freedom idas and with that I'll end and open it
up to see if there's some questions or comments
hi uh could you discuss the third ity po somehow that is kind of eluding me
what yeah I'm trying to do a little slide of hand with it and hoping that you're not noticing but you did notice
so CH this so mind or heart gets translated
I'm putting towards heart and so just a something that uh like the heart's
desire you know something that um let's see like this way you just fall
in love with the Dharma or falling in love with
practice or something like that and this is something that can provide energy
like can help us like continue or go
forward is not
helpful it's better than nothing so yeah so it it did gives a gives me a
little thing to hang on to there okay so I'll offer you another what as I said
before this these words right are so long and so many different people have interpreted them in so many different
ways I'll give you another interpretation let you can try this one on chitt this which uh can be mind or
heart and if it's mind then some people focus on awareness like just knowing
what's happening there's a way in which we just to be aware of what's Happening be present for our lives is provides
energy and a way to go forward it's a way to feel like oh I'm living my life fully I'm have awareness I'm here I'm
not uh off in uh the past or the future
but I have this awareness that's here so that's another interpretation of this third
idipa would it be fair maybe that to think of that as sort of a you've started a virtuous circle or yeah yeah
yeah absolutely I would say all of these are like virtuous
circles and maybe there's a little bit of enthusiasm a little bit of effort a
little bit of love and a little bit of curiosity maybe mix them all together
make a super in a cauldron and then that's what helps us uh go forward maybe
sometimes we need a little bit of this maybe sometimes a little bit of that I think we all have these inside of
us but what James Barz was poting to is that there's also ones that are more
accessible to us and that show up in other areas of our lives and he was
talking about like you know cherish these like really take care of these
temperaments is what supports us making effort and to notice them for
ourselves so maybe chitt for you isn't one maybe there's another one that is uh
feels more more
accessible thank you uh so this is my first time here welcome welcome thank
you um yeah I really appreciated your talk and I've never heard of the what
what are they again the itas yes what what suta is that referenced in so
there's a whole chapter in the semaya that's called the it pot chapter so it's
I don't know do you know the the I'm I'm actually in the process of um doing the
majima study that you and Gil um uh I guess have published in the Sati yeah
Center so I'm just starting into like a more in-depth study of the sutas but um
anyway but I guess I have both a comment and a question one is that
Veria shows up in all all of the lists it seems right and so you know you were
talking about all of these different um factors or all these different kinds of
qualities but it's just interesting to me that ver as I recall is in virtually
all of them and so just it's curious to me why there's this um duplication um of
that and then also I guess for me when I think about chonda and what provides
that motivation or that prompt to just continue down the path um it occurs to me
that in my experience there's this intensely just like it's such a pleasant
experience it's like that that pleasure that's not of the senses right and once
you get a taste of that that it's that to me is what really is so
compelling um and so you know that wasn't really mentioned in your talk but
I think it's sort of noteworthy at least in my experience to know that there's so much pleasure that one can attain
through this practice as well and that that's a big part of I guess what keeps me motivated so anyway so I just just
wanted to make that comment and also just see if you can speak to why vir is so often uh duplicated in so many of
these lists yeah so I'll say maybe we could have imagine that you're maybe the
pleasure is the maybe we could even say it's the chitt kind of like this desire for more you've had a taste of something
and uh fallen in love with it and going after it so I guess I'm the one with the
CH your something and then the reason why viia
shows up everywhere so remember this is like of course thousands of years ago and there was a lot of philosophy and
religion happening then right the conversations and some some of it was like well do the are there gods that do
everything and we're just ponds so we don't have to do anything it's all
predetermined and so the budha was emphasizing no you have to put effort you have to the gods aren't just moving
us around like ponds we have to do effort so that's why it shows up in all these lists just to recognize there not
there's no passivity just complete passivity right well and there's also this element of
like uh it's work you know yeah um but
there does seem to be sort of like a pay off at every Point as you're progressing
yeah yeah and and you it is work right because also kind of with the Buddha's not kind of what the Buddhas he is
pointing to undoing some of our patterns right and to undo a pattern
takes work right okay thank you you're welcome you're
welcome hopefully uh brief but I was trying to
understand so question and then maybe follow up but uh what was the 37 was it wings or a list of yeah so often I get
translated 37 wings of Awakening or Wings towards aw B
Pia something so it's a uh aids to Enlightenment is how it it literally
gets translated okay of which the OTAs are part of MH okay what I'm trying
to I guess understand the motivation for understanding the idas like in
particular is um yeah I'm trying to understand maybe
the role that they play in particular out of 37 Wings let's say but the thing
I can come up with is it sounds like they're very particular ways to
realize impermanence you know but yeah yeah I guess I'm trying to what
in particular to the OTAs or may they you know guide us to this is a great
question and it depends on who you ask because how it gets uh interpreted there
is a a legitimate way in which you can um interpret these to be about samadi
and so it could be like effort and Sami because like the Chanda
Sam well what I'm not going to go through that um it's so it could be like
just to allow the mind to get really collected or something like that and
maybe it's a concentrated effort maybe is how some people might think of the ity poas but it's fascinating how
they're never explained anywhere yet they're part of these 37 and lots of different Dharma teachers have different
ideas and most Dharma teachers don't talk about them because it's yeah it's a little not
quite sure what to do with them starts here starts here
yes hi I'm not sure if this is I understand what you were saying more or less but I'm having a problem with
procrastination big problem with procrastination so any tips you
have I'd gladly
accept yeah I had something there was something just recently that I learned
about procrastination
lack of motivation yeah you know it's not it's not arising in my mind right now but I'm
going to I'll I'll look into this and I'll talk about this because right I think we all do this at some extent you
know in some settings all of us do some procrastination I think so yeah this is
a good question it's a good question but back on Monday next
Monday and I'm trying to think like um but even like something like this uh
could help too like well what is it that gives us energy and can we tap into that to just notice what types of
things motivate us is there anything that motivates us you know anything in
our life and is there a way what can we learn from that and can we borrow some
of the energy from whatever else um motivates us but this is a legitimate
question procrastination the Buddha didn't talk about this in particular well he did talk about
practicing with urgency with a sense of urgency but I'm sorry I don't have
anything right off the top of my head that's specific about it thank you okay so we're at the end of our time
together so you're welcome to come up and talk to me if you have some more questions otherwise I wish you safe
travels home and enjoy the rain than
you