welcome welcome everybody nice to see you
all so tonight I'd like to start with a small verse that comes from the early
Buddhist literature talking about this idea of inner
peace something I think uh all of us are interested in having some peace and ease
and spaciousness well-being Freedom all these types of words having this
experience having it be a part of our life so the verse goes like
this internally one can find peace not
through another for one who is at peace with themselves there there is no picking up
when putting down this is pointing to how so often we
are looking for things to be peaceful outside externally right so that then we
can settle down and to be sure there is value in
doing something like going on a retreat at a retreat center where things are
pretty peaceful for those of you who've been on Retreat you know that uh after a few
days it just gets really quiet everybody kind of moves a little bit slower and uh it's it can be really
lovely it can also be aggravating if you're feeling really restless and everything's so
quiet but the truth is that whatever is outside of us is of
course it's outside of our control not that we get to control everything
that goes on inside either but especially things that are outside whether it's other people or whether
it's the situation the weather the news the temperature whatever it is these
types of things we all know this and in Buddhist teachings there's
this emphasis on letting go like not really clinging and holding on this
recognition that uh difficulties and tension non peace the UNP
peacefulness the agitation arises from like really holding on to
views um Concepts uh um ideas about
ourself ideas about how we think things should be or or having some aversion
really not wanting something and just getting tangled up with it in a way that
uh have a certain hostility and then that leads towards some some
agitation but what this little verse is pointing to that if there's this inner
peace then not only is it easier to let go and we all have this experience of
you know having woken up on the right side of the bed feeling well
rested and maybe looking looking forward to something that's going to happen that day something fun or
celebratory and then we're just so much more tolerant right we're not uh cranky
we're able to not get tingled up with things so letting go is much
easier and we don't pick up as much we don't pick up like hearing somebody say
something and feel like that we have to give them a piece of our mind letting them know how they're
wrong or we're not picking up like trying to solve something that uh maybe
it could just unfold on itself I'm not saying that we shouldn't solve problems
of course we should of course we should but maybe some things are not as big of
problems as we think they are so often this is the case
right I'll read this verse again internally one can find peace not
through another for one who is at peace with themselves there is no picking up
when putting down I like this word when we don't use this so often in American English but like why would there there's
no need for putting down because we haven't put up there's no need for letting go because we haven't picked it
up so with this verse the Buddha is pointing to this possibility of inner
peace this inner sense of
wellbeing sense of Freedom or ease he pointing to that we don't have
to live with this inner turmoil this often this inner conflict or sometimes
there's fear or maybe there's like a little aggression or hostility that's feels really uncomfortable towards
others towards ourselves just towards the whatever is happening
but instead we can touch into this peacefulness that is available to all of
us it's not something that we have to create from scratch it's already
there and part of practice is creating the conditions in which we can touch into it which we can hang out
there and for some that'll be with a meditation practice which were able to
like settle the body and settle the mind but if this idea of peace is to
become something other than just an idea if it's supposed to become something other just than just this abstraction or
concept then we have to live our lives in a way that supports
peacefulness it's not like we're going to live our lives one way and then Shazam there's
peace instead like the goal and the means are really tied together of course
they are this is how you know things naturally are that okay we'll have little moments of peace or we'll learn a
little bit more about what doesn't bring peace which is just as important and it's just through this
accumulation of learning to live peacefully having these moments of peace
more and more in our life that peace becomes more prevalent and more readily
accessible so there's this way in which we can live in a manner which nourishes
and supports peace and one way that we can do this
well there's a number of ways but one way that uh we can
recognize how to have a little bit more peace in our life is to notice what
takes us away from any sense of calm that we
have a classic way to think about this is with a meditation practice and with
some meditation if there's a certain amount of settledness sometimes there isn't right
sometimes just with meditation we feel Restless a lot but sometimes there is
time which there's some a little bit of ease and like feels good maybe to just sit
and then when the timer has gone off when the bell has gone off for example you
feel in like there's a sense of Peace some calm some
ease and then pay attention when does that piece go
away is it as soon as the bell ends like okay bam you I'm off running and I got to take care of this I got to do that
and I got to you know this way that we often can do but to make it a little bit of
practice just to notice like okay what is it that we think is more
important than being calm what are we willing to sacrifice our calm our peace
for what is it that we is um causing agitation or that we're getting agitated
about because it doesn't have to be this either or that I'm either meditating and
I'm calm or I'm taking care of my life and going to work and my household and
people I love and care for you know it doesn't have to be that way right we can
bring whatever calm we're discovering in a meditation practice with
us with whatever we're doing so it can be really helpful to
notice well what is it that uh causes this to end to go
away and there's is there a way that uh we can just look like honestly at the
cause of the agitation that we're feeling but maybe as I said there's
restlessness or maybe with meditation there isn't even really a deep sense of
Peace maybe things are a little bit more calm but there isn't a real sense of ease and
freedom and one reason why this might be and in my role as a dhad teacher and
I have practiced discussions with individuals and it's not uncommon for
people to talk about what what I'm calling the inner critic this maybe like you know we could
use this expression uh just colloquially as like this subpersonality that's
inside of us this uh Voice or something that's constantly putting us down and
belittling us you're not doing do it right um whatever you're doing it's
clearly not the correct thing or this sense of um this
negativity or this judgment or this uh blaming ourselves or nagging at
ourselves oh this inner critic can be so cruel and incessant and
mean not everybody has this and it's not there all the time but when it is there
it has such a big impact it causes this agitation because this inner critic has
this uh tenor this uh attitude this mood of
harshness and it helps like engender this feeling of inadequacy or
insufficiency like whatever I'm doing it's not enough
or I'm not enough somehow I have to be better somehow I have to be more and
this can be so uh debilitating and there's a way
it just takes uh so much of our life energy in some kind of way just kind of like saps it out of us in addition to
the agitation and for some people it's so
prevalent and such a common part of their inner experience they may not even
notice it it's just so familiar like oh of of course I'm always beating myself
up how else am I going to get better of course I'm already being a
little bit mean to myself I have to otherwise I would never get out of bed in the mornings I would just lounge
around and doom scroll in from bed or something like this
right so and and some people also feel like maybe it's just them that like
everybody else seems like they have it together and I'm the only one who feels like I I
don't want to say it's understandable that some people have this or at certain
times or more very often whenever there's this way that maybe our
from family or education or certainly our society kind of really supports this
idea you should be more therefore buy this product so that you can be more or
you know do this thing so you can do more or read this book you know self-help books or something like
that there countless reasons why we might have this sense of not
being okay somehow being
insufficient so I think it's important not to blame ourselves if we discover that there's this Dynamic this
constellation inside of us that's uh putting us down not something that we
willfully created and the last thing we want to do is like well to criticize
ourselves for having the inner critic right because then we would criticize
the criticizer and then we criticize the criticizer who's criticizing the criticizer and off we go right this like
this uh incessant Circle
so I just want to just describe a little bit more like one thing that happens
with this inner critic is there's this um strong sense of like
should I should do this I should not be doing that there's this way in which
there's a sense of should kind of like puts this pressure on us and sometimes we feel it like literally like this
ug you know kind like it's weigh heavy on our shoulders and even if you come to a
meditation center like this maybe you're thinking I should meditate
more or you know I should go on a retreat or you know something like
this I know I certainly I've had those thoughts certainly when I first started
my meditation practice it it was a little bit of a struggle to be uh consistent and to have a regular I was
like oh I should meditate more I was hoping nobody body would notice that I wasn't meditating at
home but this uh this sense this sense of should that creates a pressure kind
of like constricts us kind of like constricts the heart and constricts the mind causes agitation so it's anything
but peace peaceful or calm as peace has this uh sense of space
and uh openness this inner I just kind of like
shuts that down and kind of squeezes it so to support working with inner
peace we can work with this inner critic I want to offer a few ideas for
this one is as I was saying like you know
criticizing the criticizer this inner criticizer and then you know it just
goes on and on and on how many criticizers there can be how many iterations there can be of
that but when we notice that we're caught in kind of this Loop of the aversion to aversion or judging the
judging whatever it might be when we notice and we feel that we're
really stuck in it something we can do that can really change the direction and interrupt the
momentum and really change the mood so to
speak is to just ask ourselves how am I right
now how am I right now how am I right
now and we're asking this not because we have to find the answer we're asking because this is like
a big shift this is like a reorientation towards asking or
inquiring or being present for like what's what's our experience at that
moment with some care with some warmth how am I right
now is a way in which there's this such a different uh mood instead of like you
should do this you shouldn't do that and now you have an inner critic and now you have to take care of this inner critic instead of just well how are
you is this way is it such a different um
attitude maybe it'll be obvious I'm miserable cuz I'm beating myself
up but even that just this uh recognition of what's happening is a way
that undermines the authority of this inner critic instead it brings in this
attitude of being present for what's there this kind of respect and care for oneself
and maybe there's this way that how am I right now maybe we can like feel into
the body kind of like undermine some of what the mind is doing right this inner
critic often even though its effects can be felt in the body it often is this uh
going around and around in the mind so how am I right now I have this
lump in my throat and my gut doesn't my belly just doesn't feel good and I'm
really agitated now that's something that we can be with and work with instead of the
stories we can still work with like oh yeah I have this lump in my
throat and just feel into that what is the lump in the throat
like and now we have a completely different way of going forward to be
with our experience in the present moment and this is the
practice and not only that it's been with the experience in the present moment with a sense of
care which might be a radical thing in the midst of the inner critic to you know have some warmth and care for
oneself so that's one thing we can do with this inner critic something that's kind of like stealing our peace is to
change change the direction by just asking how am I right now something else that we can do is
with our meditation practice just to bring this same attitude of kindness and
warmth to meditation it's not uncommon and I
certainly did my share fair share of this when meditating you know I'm supposed to be like meditating on the
breath and then you know lost in some thought about what I'm going to pick up at the grocery store on the way home and
don't forget to get this you know whatever and then realize oh wait I'm
supposed to be meditating and then there would be this very little quiet dang it Diana when are
you going to get it together and I wouldn't even notice and then I would like come back to the
breath it took me quite some time to notice that there was like this you know this beat after kind of like waking up
after being lost in thought that was a little bit mean and then I would kind of like yank the Mind back to that
breath instead can there be like yep that's what Minds
do let's let's pay attention to the breath again it's such a different way such a
different attitude so this can be such a fruitful place to practice is to notice the
moment right after you realize that you've been lost in thought when you've been and intending to meditate and just
notice the flavor the mood the attitude and I know some people I think
it was um I think I first heard this from Sylvia borin if I remember correctly and uh she
would say something like oh sweetheart oh sweetie you're lost in
thought again just come back to the breath so she would throw in a little term of endearment for herself you know
just as a way to just really uh um counteract any harshness that might be
showing up there's something that I think is kind of sweet about that so maybe we all have our we can use a term
of endearment for ourselves that doesn't make us feel squeamish but instead makes us feel has
a some warmth to it and then maybe there's this way in
which we can just recognize the inner critic and just
say oh there's the inner critic and this wave like okay yep I
guess you're going to be hanging out with me for a while come along you know instead of this idea that
we have to get rid of it and it's a problem and I'm going to fix it and I have this agenda first I'll do step one
and then step two and you know to make but instead like oh yep here it is I
know quite a few people that have given their inner critic like a a name
I heard uh one person this name you know I don't actually I shouldn't say it because what if some of somebody who's
listening that is their name but uh somebody who had shared a a different
name and just Ed this as a character that would somehow accompany them during a
meditation so as a way to you know like maybe in um instead of turning it into a
problem just like giving it space space okay the inner critic is here
doesn't mean we have to believe it doesn't mean we have to give it Authority but it also doesn't mean that
we have to like repress or pretend that it's not there just recognize oh okay
here it is here is this inner critic and so this whole idea of working
with an inner critic I think uh Rosemary traumer um expresses really well in a
poem that uh she published yesterday and I was just happened to be uh looking at
and I thought oh I'm going to add this to the talk this a she I should say
she's a Buddhist practitioner and uh she writes a poem and publishes a poem every day she a beautiful practice a beautiful
practice she's uh I think she's an amazing poet so here's Rosemary trummer at the
end I'll give the um the title of this poem I don't yeah I'll give the title of the
poem and uh this is how this poem goes on a day when I am at war with myself
when I battle my own humanness and a longing to be good to be better than
good to be perfect when I point to myself with a snarl and a sneer as if I am my own
enemy then I know notice how my whole body contracts and I'm a crumpled up map
a gray lump in the throat a stone in the gut a crumpled Wing in the chest and
it's hard to breathe and it's hard to move that is when I'm grateful to have a
body grateful for the way it helps me remember I have a choice to meet this
moment with kindness it's as if mid comat I'm
delivered a postcard with a forever stamp sent from my wisest self
saying dear woman who thinks she is not good enough I see
you it's okay to feel this way and what looked like a battlefield a
blink ago now looks more like a vast Green
Meadow filled with low golden and light where all parts of me are
welcome the one who makes mistakes the one who judges the one who longs to be good the
one who thinks she shouldn't have to learn the same lesson
again there is no part of me then that is not welcome that cannot be loved and
my body expands like a great Alpine Basin unfurls like an unending White
Flag how easy it is then to stand with all of in that field and know what it means
to be home if I like this way that Rose Mar trauma she's describing this battle
inside and then she says that it's as if mid combat I'm delivered
a post card with a forever stamp sent from my wisest self this way that sometimes like our
practice can be a support for us like our meditation practice our loving
kindness practice compassion practice this is a way that can just some like show up and interrupt in the same way
that when we're meditating and we're lost in thought and then we don't know why then Bo all a sudden we wake up and
realize oh yeah I'm supposed to be meditating there can be a way with practice with this uh inner critic like
oh yeah I don't have to do this there's a different way I can ask how am I right now I can
give it space I can have a see if there's a way I can be with an attitude noticing my
inner experience in particular with warmth and
kindness so that's these are some ways to work with this inner critic as a way
to support some inner peace then I'm just want to mention a
little bit briefly another way to support with inner
peace because I there was a time I for some reason this like seared in my mind
I was on a long retreat and some things that I had done earlier in my life that
were very harmful came up in my memory oh my gosh that was
so painful day after day these memories coming up and like haunting me and I'm
like wow and I was like wishing there was anything I could do right I'm in a retreat center very quiet very still
nothing to distract oneself and here I am with these memories like again and again and again like oh it was so
painful just like you we can't to undo the past right however much we wish that
we could instead we deal with the consequences of some
things that we whatever we've done right this is part of what it means to be
human and so this kind of like sense of regret or remorse is often a way in
which we feel agitated not the only way of course but that's a way in which we
our peace gets second riced or you know it gets in the way of feeling this inner
calm and peacefulness and of course every great
spiritual tradition talks about the benefit of ethical Behavior like
behaving in a way that uh doesn't cause harm to others doesn't cause harm to
oneself instead there's this uh emphasis on recognizing that
we all of us have this capacity within us to maybe appreciate and take joy in
Integrity honesty this uprightness or this ethical conduct or you know warmth
of heart or openness of heart and the way that we show up in the world so that
we're not causing harm to others or to ourselves it's important right for both
of these so this ethical having behaving ethically is such a foundational part of
how we are in the world because there's no end but
literally there is no end as long as we're alive we'll be interacting with others or interacting with ourselves in
some kind of way and there's always a way in which we can perhaps be like a little bit more skillful a little bit
more tuned into what is a way that can provide
most benefit and least harm to others self and both self and
others often that's not so straightforward it's not so easy in order to do that often takes that we
aren't always just doing the path of least resistance but instead we're having difficult
conversations instead we're going out of our way to avoid a topic or and but
letting others know that what the harm that's being done in a way that is skillful and supportive in a way that
people can hear not in a way that makes them shut down or get
defensive but in a way that they want to listen to what you're saying this takes
work it's not easy to consistently striving to cause
the least amount of harm in this world so ethical Behavior as best we can
is something else that can really support this sense of Peace so that we don't have regret we don't have remorse
or we don't have fear like there's a thing that I did to that person and now they might retaliate or if they don't
retaliate maybe they'll be rude to me or now we feel like we have to avoid them because we feel bad that we did said
that thing to them that time or sent that email or whatever it was whatever
it was so I don't know some sometimes when we hear this expression ethical Behavior
it feels like ug it sounds a little bit oppressive but I'm pointing to just
showing up in the world with a commitment to not causing harm to oneself or to
others in the Buddhist tradition this is like the what we call CA ethical
Behavior so the Buddha's teaching and he's really pointing to this possibility
this this radical transformation that's available to have this have a pervading
sense of peace and to be able to touch into the
sense of peace that all of us have even if there there's a big part of us that's feeling restless and
unsettled there's a way that can support more and more peace more and more ease more and more
well-being and more and more freedom in one way is working with the
inner critic the Buddha doesn't talk about the inner critic in particular but
I wanted to bring this in just because I often have seen this and with practice discussions and I've experienced it
myself and also this uh importance of the way we show up in the world and not
causing harm maybe I'll end with reading
Rosemary traumer poem again the title is called
self-compassion so Rosemary traumer poem self-compassion it goes whoops it would
help if I had the right Pages next to one
another sorry about this here we go
Rosemary trummer's poem self-compassion on a day when I am at
war with myself when I battle my own humanness in aing to be good to be
better than good to be perfect when I point to myself with a snarl and a sneer as if I am my own
enemy then I notice how my whole body contracts and I'm crumpled up map I'm
I'm a crumpled up map a gray lump in the throat a stone in the gut a crumpled
Wing in the chest and it's hard to breathe and it's hard to
move that is when I'm grateful to have a body grateful for the way it helps me
remember I have a choice to meet this moment with
kindness it's as if mid combat I'm delivered a postcard with a forever
stamp sent from my wisest self saying dear woman who thinks she is not good
enough I see you it's okay to feel this
way and what looked like a battlefield a blink ago now looks more like a vast
Green Meadow fil filled with low Golden Light where all parts of me are well
welcome the one who makes mistakes the one who judges the one who longs to be
good the one who thinks she shouldn't have to learn the same lesson
again there is no part of me then that is not welcome that cannot be loved and
my body expands like a great Alpine Basin unfurls like an unending white
flag how easy it is then to stand with all of in that field and know what it
means to be home very nice I think I'll end there
and I'll open it up if there's some questions or comments thank
you anybody have a question or comment or something they'd like to say
ask is it on yeah um your question about um when
did you lose peace most recently or I forget the context
exactly I was thinking of a Sunday when I did lose peace and I'm think trying to
think what happened and the light bulb went off thought distortion
that carry this in my wallet you know personalization catastrophizing All or Nothing thinking
you know I've got about 10 of them here nice so uh that's what takes me out of
out of Peace it's not an event but it's a thought Distortion
around could be something totally fictional or made up very nice so but
thank you for the question yeah yeah yeah that was awesome yeah thank you
yeah thought distortions very nice anybody else have a comment or
question maybe Scott in the back there
just a straightforward question about the poem I I think there's a line in there it say
something like what was a b a battlefield and is the word weak or Bleak ago blink like the eyes blink go
okay it's a hard word to say blink blink battle field the blinko yeah it's kind
of hard to say blinko also works yeah yeah yeah it does thank you it does work a bleak
ago okay well if there's no comments or uh questions we can end here and I wish
you all a wonderful rest of your evening thank you thank you