welcome welcome good evening hello and happy Memorial Day here we are
on a holiday
wishing I for all those families who have lost loved ones
and in Wars wishing the best for
them and honoring those people have died
in so many different
ways sometimes for a memorial day we didn't do it this year but in years past
my mom and I we would get some um this like some plastic flowers and we would
bring them to Graves of you know of our family people have died and then I just
love to bring tons and just put them on other people's Gra you know I don't know who these people are but uh just this
idea of honoring other people and Imagining the Delight of a
family member were to come and like oh look somebody uh left some flowers for this our family member
here so just holding in our hearts those families and who have lost
loved ones and so today I'd like to talk about um
something um maybe I'll like weave together a tapestry in some kind of
way but using a different elements different um I use this word elements to point
towards something and this whole idea of journeying or this idea of being on a
path maybe a road trip in some kind of
way and I'm going to start with the passage that's um from the majam
Manaya and uh this is ganaka molana who was talking to the
Buddha and um and he had asked the uh Buddha like is do you have like a
training program like all the other per professionals have training programs the
accountants he's an accountant guka means accountant so he's mulana the
accountant uh that people who do archery have training programs there people who
uh work with elephants have training programs in ganaka mulana asks the Buddha do you guys have a training
program also and the Buddha says yes and he describes this training program which
is the gradual training I'm not going to go into the details of that right now but then after
the Buddha gives that a long explanation uh to galana k m Kaka molana asks so when your
followers are instructed and in and advised by you do all of them achieve
the goal this is a legitimate question you have a training program but does it
work does anybody become awaken do they reach nabana I appreciate that kind of you
know he's G molana is just asking them do all of them achieve it or do some of
them fail and the Buddha response some succeed While others
fail and then the natural next question is
why why do some of them fail why though nibana exists the path leading to nibana
exists and you are present to encourage those who wish to find nibana why do
some succeed and others fail this is a good
question and then the Buddha he answers this question by asking a question
back well I'll ask you about this in in
return and you can answer as you like do you know how to get to rajagaha the
Buddha asks gak molana do you know how to get to this other city that's a far
away yes I do so what do you think suppose a person
were to come along who wanted to go to rajagaha this person would approach you and say I wish to go to rajagaha and
please point the way and then you would say to this person this wrote goes to rajagaha go
along it for a while and then you'll see a certain Village then continue and Go a
little bit further and then you'll see a certain Town continue and go a little further and there you'll see Raja
gaha in my mind this maybe goes like go to this Village and then hang a left or
something like this and then go to a town and hang a right or you know something like this but it's just like
you know here's some different uh landmarks that you'll see and here's how
you get to rajagaha and then the Buddha asks him
um or says to him to the ghak mulana so
instructed like this by you they might still take the wrong
road but a second person might come along and ask you how to get to rajagaha and they may make it there to rajagaha
and then the Buddha asks him why is that why even though you gave them clear instructions on how to get there some of
them make it and some of it don't and guka molana says I don't know
I gave them instructions it's up to them to follow the instructions and the Buddha says well
it's the same for me too the Buddha shows the way but all of
us have to walk it ourselves can't do it for us of course not
so then I'd like to share this other little uh excerpt where the budha gives a little bit more details about this uh
path this road to nibana and this time he's talking to
somebody named Tisa and he says to
Tissa Suppose there were two people one who did not know the path and one who
did know the path I could say like knew the road KN knew the directions or who
didn't and the person who didn't know the path would ask the person who did
know the path about how about the path and then
the person who knew about the path would say come this is the path and would show
them then this would be the part of the description so go a little way and then
you'll see a fork in the road avoid the left hand branch and take
the right hand Branch then go a little bit further and you'll see a dense Thicket go a little bit further and
you'll see a vast marshy swamp and then go a little bit further
and then you'll see a steep precipice then go a little further and then you'll see a delightful expanse of
Parkland so he's describing you know these like literal landmarks that you'll see this um Fork in the road and this
Thicket a swamp steep precipice and then you'll get at this park like and then
the Buddha says this is a simile and I've made up this simile to describe the path of practice and these things stand
for certain things these uh these what we what you would might find in
nature and he says and the person who doesn't know the path this is for a regular practitioner
a follower but someone who is not awakened but someone who does know the path is somebody who's
awakened and then the fork in the road is a designation for
doubt we can think about doubt is often how it gets described as a hindrance as
this hesitation this velation like should I go here should I do this should
I do loving kindness practice or should I do mindfulness practice should I do open awareness practice or mindfulness
of the breath or you know this kind of way in which we might not not it might not be clear on what practice we should
do that's a way some way that often a doubt shows up but often doubt shows up
too is like well I'm not sure about this whole mindfulness or Insight tradition
or maybe I'm not so sure about the teachers or maybe I'm not so sure about the Buddha or maybe I'm not even so sure
that I can do it maybe it's a fine path but it doesn't seem like it's the one for me so doubt can show up in all these
different ways and so I love that he's describing as the fork and the road because often what happens when we have
doubt we just get to this place and we stop and we're not sure like how to go
forward and we end up kind of like stuck there with this uh
doubt and then the budha goes on to explain and he says well the left hand path is the wrong Eightfold Path and the
right hand path is the right eight-fold path I think many of you have heard this
before that right we might translate this as wise or helpful I think may be
helpful so it's the unhelpful path and the helpful path I'm not going to go into details
about this but many of you are probably familiar with this wise view wise
intention wise speech wise action wise livelihood wise energy wise mindfulness
and wise concentration these are like eight different elements that really um
support our movement towards greater and greater freedom but there's a way in which we can have you know unwise action
and unwise livelihood and which were causing harm and that would be like you know going down the left
fork and then he uh talks about then you would go to this dense
Thicket where you know it's you can't see your way through it's not clear how to go forward and when you're in the
midst of it you're just like uh kind uh stuck in it and the Buddha says this is a
metaphor for um ignorance like just not knowing that's often how it is like we
can't see like we don't know and there's a we have to use like a different
um different faculties to know how to go forward like we can't use the visual faculty in the way that we are
accustomed to so when we're in the middle of a Thicket maybe there's a way in which somebody
shows us the way or maybe we follow Intuition or maybe we follow just a
trial and error it's just not clear we don't we
just don't know the way forward and then after this dense
Thicket is this marshy swamp and the Buddha describes this
marshy swamp uh was getting stuck in sensual Pleasures there's a way we can do it's
like chasing one pleasure after the next after the next after the next you know
psychologists call this the hedonic treadmill right even though we might have one thing that's pleasurable well
okay then that starts we starts to get accustomed to that and then we want something even more and then we get
accustomed to that then we want even more and we can spend our whole life just chasing pleasures and I kind of
like how this is a swamp it can't feel like you kind of get quick sand like maybe sunk down in there and it's not
easy to get out especially because uh there's so much of our society that's
really promoting this sense of entertainment you know find something titillating even the news often is given
in a way just to you know poke you a little bit like oh I better pay attention you know it's given in a way
to you know entertain you in some way even though it's uncom able off in the news but it's also meant to grab your
attention and keep it in the way that entertainment does so then after this uh marshy swamp
is this deep precipice and again this is like all on
the path to nabana so I don't know I just love this he's not saying okay look it's neat and tidy just go here hang a
left and you'll be there it's like no there's these swamps and there's this dense Thicket like a forest and you're
upt to get lost in there and there's going to be this steep precipice which
he describes is anger and agitation and I kind of like this as
being a precipice because anger like can be helpful indicate to us like when
boundaries are being crossed or when things are inappropriate are being done but there's also a way in which anger
can tip us over into the off of a precipice and when it's uh mixed with
hostility when it's uh mixed with this maybe it's a subtle sense but of wanting
to cause harm in some kind of way and then agitation right we just
often don't have access to the best version of ourself when we're agitated so this deep precipice of you know
agitation maybe a having to watch each step and be careful on the way to Nana
so that's one of the ways that the Buddha describes this
path Guk molana described it as oh you see this Village you see this town and
you'll get there and the Buddha say well here's some specifics in a different sua he's saying here are some
specifics and then the Buddha uh ends this by saying you should be be happy
Tisa for I am here to advise I'm here to support you and I here to instruct so
he's saying you know look there are these uh difficulties along the way but
I can help I appreciate that it's it's not it's uh you know saying it's not
pretending like everything's easy peasy or something like this because sometimes
it's not uncommon for people to feel like oh this is really hard or I'm getting lost or I'm confused and somehow
we feel like oh I don't understand it there's something wrong with me or something like that but
instead I mean here the Buddha he's just pointing out that's part of the path is this
way is that there will be confusion there will be uncertainty there will be
difficulties and just to make like to normalize that instead of this idea that we have to know everything and have to
should be comfortable all the time so then we might say well why are
some reasons why people don't go on this path the Buddha was saying some people
don't reach it and it might be that maybe they don't
really start maybe they they have a maybe an inkling that okay there is a different
direction that's possible but they don't really want to like they maybe like dip their toes toe
in which is okay that's certainly how I started and I think that's how a lot of people start with just maybe dipping a
toe in but also there can be this hesitation
to begin maybe it's doubt or maybe it's just a uncertainty or about what to do
or how to do it or maybe they realize oh this is going to be hard there's going to be swamps and
thickets and and and steep precipices
Cliffs and they feel like it's feels dangerous it feels
scary and it's not uncommon for people in their meditation practice when they reach like some different meditative
experiences that they haven't reached before some people are like oh cool check it out never experienced this
before and some people are like whoa what was that and it's okay whatever
experience we have is the one we have so there can also be some hesitation based
on you know just uh tasting something that's different and not quite sure what
it is and how to hold it or how to be with
it or maybe there's uh people don't kind like finish on this path or maybe they
just start a little bit because they get distracted and part of the reason why
they get distracted is because maybe their life is better they've started a meditation practice maybe they have a
little bit more ease in their life maybe they have a little bit more uh ease in their bodies a little bit more
relaxation and they feel like okay that's that's enough you know my life is
better than before but I'm don't really want to look in some of the corners of my
mind and the corners of my life I'm not I'm not quite ready to do that I might
have to make some difficult decisions if I do that I might have to do things radically different and
maybe they don't want to do that it's perfectly fine all of us get to choose our own way our
own pace our own path certainly there's no requirement to do
any of this it's kind of like an if then statement if you're interested in more
and more freedom and peace and well-being then here are some things to
do it's completely you know up to us of
course but now I'd like to point to uh rather than reaching back you know
thousands of years ago somebody who's talking about this path that goes to
Awakening and freedom to use a modern voice from a poem was published in the
early 1960s but I think it does a good job of describing part of what it might be like
to maybe endeavor on this path partly on the beginning of this
path the poet is Mary Oliver many of you have are familiar with this uh poet she
I think she won the Pitzer prize but I regret that I don't know which year she
did so she's a recognized poet and this uh the name of the poem is
called The Journey so again again that's a Mary
Oliver's poem The Journey one day you finally knew what
you had to do and began though the voices around you kept
shouting their bad advice though the whole house began to tremble and you felt the old tug at your
ankles Mend My Life each voice cried but you didn't stop
you knew what you had to do though the wind pried with its stiff fingers at the
very foundations though their Melancholy was
terrible it was already late enough and a wild night and the Road full of Fallen
branches and stones but little by little as you left
their voice behind the Stars began to burn through the sheets of clouds
and there was a new voice which you slowly recognized as your
own that kept you company as you stroe deeper and deeper into the
world determined to do the only thing you could do determined to save the only
life that you could
save and it ends there it's part of this poem that I just
love about this poem there's a lot of beautiful elements here but I love this
uh ending like determined to do the only thing you could do determined to save
the only life that you could save and then I think many of us in our
minds are going oh yeah save my life or save your life like we're completing the poem in some kind of
way or as the you know the poet she's uh leaving it to us to kind like make that
next step she's leaving it blank I'll read this one more time and
then uh I'll point out a few things again this is Mary Oliver The
Journey one day you finally knew what you had to do and
began though the voices around you kept shouting their bad
advice though the whole house began to tremble and you felt the old tug at your
ankles Mend My Life each voice cried but you didn't
stop you knew what you had to do but the wind Pride with its stiff fingers at the
very foundations though their Melancholy was
terrible it was already late enough in a wild night and the Road full of Fallen
branches and stones but little by little as you left their voice
behind the Stars began to burn through the sheets of
clouds and there was a new voice which you slowly recognized as
your own that kept you company as you stroe deeper and deeper into the
world determined to do the only thing you could do determined to to save the
only life that you could
save so this poem begins with one day you finally knew what you had to
do in Buddhism they sometimes point to this as this feeling of urgency this
feeling like oh I this uh I need to find a way to Greater
freedom and sometimes this arises because we have a lot of suffering or sometimes it AR is we you know receive a
terrible diagnosis or a loved one has a terrible diagnosis or maybe it's just an
intuitive hit I worked in Corporate America for
quite some time and I had this fantastic job I had a great job and I felt like I just don't quite
feel happy in the way that I expected to having this great job I got I have my
professional success that I wanted and like what am I going to do
now and at that time I worked for a company that yeah was it was a great job I'll just say
this and then um I was thinking like oh should I leave this job but it's not
going to get better anywhere else I'm not going to get find a better job I think and it took me quite some time
thinking that should I do this feeling like you know like no I can't oh yes I
should and then for some reason one morning I woke up and it was just so clear to
me I will always think that I should work more I should you know get higher
in the corporate letter earn more money you know all these things I will always
think that there's like that's not going to go away but somehow I don't know why
I can't explain I just had this intuitive hit I need to leave this job
and this story I told myself I'm just going to leave for one year and my life
situation allowed me to do that certainly that's not available for most people and then I'm going to come back I
just need one year to figure out what to do next I was working so hard I busy all the time but I couldn't figure out what
to do next I thought okay I just need a little space to figure out what to do
next I can't believe that was uh so many years ago now that what I
said I'd be gone for one year and I guess it's been 18 years now so didn't find my way back instead I
found the Dharma and this is where I've been ever since but it was just like I
just had some clarity this doesn't hit so often but sometimes it does where we
have the sense of like y this is going to be hard or it's not clear I can't figure it out but you know what I'm
going to do it anyway there's something inside of us I'm going to do it anyway
and the story that I told right my life situation allowed me to do that maybe making a radical change isn't available
to people because they have a responsibilities and other people that they care for but my point is that
sometimes there is a a god feeling that we have not always but sometimes there
is or maybe not it's not a gut in in gut
feeling or an Insight but maybe it's a just an
understanding sometimes with a meditation practice we start to see things differently we start to see
ourself differently we start to understand like oh I'm like
that because of these conditions it doesn't mean I'm a bad person it just
means because I'm always hungry at 3:00 and that's why I'm yelling at the person that does something or other you know
I'm just making this up on the spot but when we start to realize oh yeah all these things are
connected and we as individuals are not like unique that we're not connected to
everything we are connected to our conditions everything around us of course we are so the things that we do
we sometimes like take credit for them but we also like blame ourselves for them and not
recognizing oh yeah well the person that we were speaking to was uh
really angry because their partner didn't take out the garbage like they
said they were going to and uh they come into work and they're irritated because they had to take up the garbage or you
know whatever it is things that we have no idea about impact us and affects us so maybe
that's this type of understanding we start to see oh it's not that I'm always
this way it's that that there are conditions in my life which
uh creates the conditions for me to be that way support that way and there's something we can have a
little bit more sense of Freedom a sense of possibility oh yeah maybe if I spend
less time um watching things on social media
that is mean and hurtful and demeaning and disrespectful to other people you
know of course it impacts us whether it's uh geared towards us or not just to
know that humans can do this and to know that that kind of Venom is exists there in the
world so maybe there's a way in which you can listen to sometimes these quiet
voices that are saying yeah something else is possible and maybe we don't even know
what that something else is and maybe the change that we make is
something small very small it doesn't have to be some radical thing about going down a whole different
path it's like well maybe I'll meditate
more maybe I'll spend time in nature more maybe I'll do something creative
more you just allow something for our hearts and Minds to Blossom and have
have some Breathing Room often our lives are kind like feeling cramped and and
we're feeling like we're pushed around so there's so many ways that this
one day you finally knew what you had to do well maybe we can interpret it as the
poet here saying you knew what you had to do and maybe all you know is that you have to do something
different and maybe it's not even clear what it is just this feeling like oh yeah maybe even something different is
possible and then just this willingness to be curious about well what what would be different what would be helpful for
my life because the next line in this poem says though the voices around you kept
shouting their bad advice the people that are uh in our
orbit so to speak you you know often especially if we've um had relationships
with them for a long time there's a way in which we kind of set up this dance like okay you do this and then I do that
in response and then I do this and then you do that in response you know I'm looking at the really really big picture
I get angry and then uh you get quiet and then I'm mad that you're quiet so
then I go call my friend you know or whatever it is you know these uh dynamics that uh get developed in all
relationships and sometimes this shouting their bad
advice is like no don't change even though you can see that it would be helpful for you to maybe let go of some
patterns of behavior letting go of staying up late and not getting enough sleep because
you're on social media I don't want to beat up on social media but there is a
lot of bad things on there right we all know this right there's some helpful things there too but there's a lot of
very helpful things so there might be a way in which
they uh want us to stay the same in some kind of way or maybe these voices that
keep shouting their bad advice maybe it's part of the inner critic that's you know these are voices inside of
us and so this uh poem is pointing to like knowing that there's something to
do even though there is pressure to not do things differently
but instead to go on this journey and then the next line is though
the whole house began to tremble like things start excuse me
start to feel a little bit more shaky right when we decide okay I'm going to do things a little bit
differently doesn't feel as solid doesn't feel as
steady but that's what it feels like to grow that's what it feels like to to
stretch our capacities that's what it feels like to touch something new experience
something new Go a different direction a little bit like the house began to tremble it's not the same and
also maybe if we start taking a few steps on the this
journey maybe we look back at the house and we see oh maybe it was trembling all
along and we just didn't notice it cuz we were in it and we were shaking along with it maybe we take a few steps and
notice like oh yeah it's a little
shaky and then I'll skip forward to this uh other line in the poem it says it was
already late enough and a wild night and the Road full of Fallen branches and
Stones so this is describing when they're like going out onto this journey
I love this it was already late enough we could
interpret that a number of different ways it was nighttime maybe but late
enough this could be like later in our life it's maybe often when we are
younger that we make these decisions and then it's not until later in real life
you know this is not uncommon for people to feel like hm I think I want to make some changes and go a different
direction so she's uh the poet is pointing to maybe the late in life too
we don't this isn't just something that uh young people do as they go off to start their
lives and then it was a wild night with the Road full of Fallen branches and
Stones it wasn't perfect setting it wasn't neat and tidy and clear and
pretty but there was going to be these obstacles on the way here they're getting described as uh
Fallen branches and Stones the Buddha he was describing it
as uh swamps and thickets and cliffs this a recognition that uh
journeying going to or Awakening going towards greater Freedom going towards
greater peace and ease in our lives going towards the best version of
ourselves is going to encounter some difficulties that's part of the path it
doesn't mean you're doing it wrong and there's others that can
help there's teachings that can help there's friends that can help there are teachers that can
help this is some place maybe where social media can help too there are communities
online that can be a support as for this uh Journey
and then lastly I'll end with this uh line from the poem that says there was a
new voice which you slowly recognized as your
own so pointing to transformation pointing to like this new voice this new way of seeing things the
new way of thinking about things or speaking about things any
realized oh yeah this is some of my wisdom that I've earned on this journey
of life that's uh supporting
me so the path of practice of going towards greater
freedom and the Buddha talked about it and described it
as you know having difficulties not necessarily being neat
and tidy sometimes when we hear like the eight-fold path it's just you know here's these eight things and do them
and you'll be fine it would be great if it were that easy and
straightforward but it's not always easy and straightforward and I kind of I want to normalize that that this path is has
beautiful parts and it has difficult Parts because that's what it means when we like transformation of course isn't
going to be completely um simple and straightforward and
painless it's uh there's going to be some stretching and growing and we're going to realize oh yeah this cloak that
I used to wear doesn't really fit anymore but it's my favorite one and I really like it something like
this to this idea of the journey the
journey and I'll end there and open it up to see if anybody has any questions
or comments
just talking to it okay yeah well is a simple straightforward I get these little messages and I ignore
them it's terrible that you said something about little messages earlier and it's exactly
that perfect I hear them I mean I I don't really hear them but they come to
me and I it's like I say oh no that's not for me that's not me it's ter you
have to listen to those little messages well that's why take on it but yeah and part of this skill is is
learning like well which ones do we listen to all of them do we listen to some of them and how do we know which
ones right that's part of the I think part of uh maybe maturing in this path
but uh uh here's here's a Something That I Used To Guide Me On whether to listen to these messages or not is that and
often this is very subtle so I has to be uh I have to pay attention If the
message says do this and then very quietly it says in order to get this
whatever this is usually those are the ones that aren't so helpful if the one that says
do this because it's the right thing to do those are the ones that tend to be
more helpful but the ones that are are trying to like to are means so that you can get something I mean maybe it helps
you get that thing but uh I'm just this is what I'm using for myself as a guideline of which one of those little
voices to pay attention to when it says that well because it's the right thing to do and then how do
you know what right thing to do is maybe I'll say something because there's a certain sense of ease or spaciousness in
the body like yeah okay that's the right thing to
do you're not in your heads you recognize this even though it might feel difficult or
not what you want to do or something like that yeah thank you does anybody
else have a comment or a question or something they'd like to
share it would have be nice if all those obstacles were visuals that as you described yeah that's true that's a very
good but uh unfortunately uh I see it as more kind of a mindfield where you're kind of walking
along things are going well and then boom something just comes out of
nowhere and uh that could be challenging yeah yeah do you have the
feeling that they come out of nowhere I'm just asking maybe some um sometimes yeah yeah um just a interpersonal um uh
relationship ship or a um well for me re recently it was uh I
came home and my roommates like um I'm not redoing my lease and um you know
this is your 30-day notice you know and I'm like oh darn you know yeah uh things
like that yeah yeah or I'm a teacher so in schools too it's you never know
what's going to what you might step on you know yeah so that
kind of the way I look at it great thank you this idea of mindfields that just sounds brutal or
gory know you know there goes you a limb
or something great thank
you does anybody else have a comment or something they'd like to
say I should have voices instead of what I said I think you said Little Voices
did you I said messages oh little messages oh
[Music]
okay I'm so happy I came today
because you you were talking to me at this point of my
life and uh I need to make some changes and I'm so comfortable with with
what it what it is and and then this point this just T to me that don't and
in my meditation and in my God says do it no matter how difficult it is and my
God the whole talk tonight is all about you know it could be difficult
but it's the path is to freedom of what's been not comfortable
all along so I'd like to thank you for that you're welcome yeah yeah I just
like to share this with you MH thank you thank
you happy to hear that
okay so I think we'll end the evening wishing you all a wonderful rest of the evening thank
you and if you'd like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me