ah good morning good hello and uh
greetings sometimes I enjoy a little bit of fun
by reclassifying human beings rather than calling them Homo
sapiens um I call them consider them to be homo
stor uh that we tell stories one of the
distinctive qual distinctive characteristics of humans is their ability tell
stories uh other animals
know they can understand a lot but uh I don't know how much other animals tell
stories the way we do and we tell stories we make
plans we
um pass judgment we bring things experiences people into the court of our
mind and where we are the judge and we will be judging things we fantasize we
imagine we tell stories of all kinds and certainly part of the richness
of human beings that sitting around a campfire and telling stories and it's
and sometimes it's the way we understand ourselves understand our people our history and and uh make sense of the
world so stories are a very important part of being a human being
and so is um you know other things eating is
important but if all we did was eat all the time that would be a
problem and sometimes when we meditate the story making mind is
clearly a form of agitation formly a way a way of being spinning out or being
preoccupy being being in a certain kind of way disconnected from ourselves in the
present moment and it can be lovely in meditation
when uh that storytelling mind planning mind
stops reviewing mind stops uh it I think it maybe belittles
that moment to associate it with or compare it to the hum of the
refrigerator going off and there's a Ah that's good we didn't even know there was a
some little bit bit of tension with the hum until it
stops and or we don't know that the our windshield of the car has gotten dirty
slowly on a long road trip until someone cleans it and wow now I see
clearly so to let the story telling mine take a break or
rest you don't have to eat all the time you don't have to tell stories all the time you don't have to make plans all
the time you don't have to review the past all the time you don't have to be
at court all the time judging and evaluating you don't have to be a
scientist or an engineer constantly probing to understand and to figure out
or to build or to create ah all those
efforts of the mind that the thinking mind which is
complicated active can go to
rest there might be other forms of thinking maybe species of thinking
the that continue without that particular species of thinking known as story making or
that that this part of the mind that constructs
spins fabricates there might be very simple
thoughts that say oh that's nice for things to be quiet
ah I'm home I was up in my head all the time
and disconnected from anything below my neck ah they went quiet that part of
thinking so another voice says Ah this is good I'm here I'm
home I've arrived for these minutes it's good to
be here just like if you go to take a rest
with a little nap you don't bring your device with you
to continue doing emails you put that aside and
ah I can put that aside for now so here we are going to meditate
putting aside not abandoning but putting aside the story making mind the
constructing mind the mind that has abstract thought about things
so we can have the pleasure and the
challenge the important challenge of just being here with what's deeper and
more intimate more connected than the story making
mind
to know without a story to know without
imposing knowing just know simply the most simple
way without any conclusions and judgments
predictions here so assuming a meditation
posture and considering have you
been are you activated have you been activated with a abstract mind of
thinking thinking of abstract thoughts of plans and memories and
stories and it has its place in our life to do that but not
now now is the time to connect to a deeper Source
Within
closing the
eyes taking a moment to imagine that you're dropping
your attention down into your body to what for you feels like the
deepest place you can touch the deepest place that awareness
can rest in
maybe it's in the heart area generally General heart area maybe it's in
the diaphragm area or deeper down into the
belly whatever it feels like the quietest comest deep place
within let your inhale begin from
there spreading
outwards
and let the exhale return to
there and if that's at the
center the calm still place
within let the mind of stories and ideas
and Fantasies and abstractions let that be on the far
edges almost like it's occurring in a be just
beyond the range of your
hearing center yourself in the calm still place
within where there might be very simple
thoughts and the simplest thought you can use maybe is the word here h e r
e here at The Quiet Center
the of all things
relaxing into that
Center breathing from that
Center allowing the thinking mind the story
mind to relax fade
away the tensions of the story making mind melts
away centered
here
maybe it either at the inhale or the exhale saying the thought to
yourself here but saying that
thought from that from a place deep
within
on
for
e
e gently turning off the thinking mind the
story making
mind relaxing the tension or effort to
be perpetuating ongoing flow of thoughts
that have nothing to do with Here and Now
finding relief in being
here here with the whole
body gently lovingly repeating being the simple
thought
here
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to take a few moments to
appreciate the potential potentials available to us when we are
truly here when we're
present in a relaxed rooted
way without the momentum of stories from the [Music]
past desires about what's to
come and now this is the way we can be with someone who
needs our support needs to experience the basic
human
companionship someone who needs to feel that someone is present for them without
any filters just
here that in the Simplicity and the
clarity here without stories there's a Clear
Channel for our respect and love and care for
others may we
offer our our friendship our friendliness to
others through the medium of a Simplicity of heess being able to be here in a
clear and simple way not wanting anything particularly
from others without aversion to others just here with friendship friendliness
meta May our good will spread to others out
into the [Music] world may our friendliness spread from
us to others and out into the world may our simple respect for others
spread out to them and to others may it be that this practice and
its goodness spreads wide and far
may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free
thank
you
e
so hello to this fourth uh talk
on grasping or clinging and how we create not just a
single grasping and clinging but we create bundles of clinging
we some of us specialize in clinging and grasping and holding on and attachment
to many things and it's almost like we go through the day collecting things to
be attached to we start the day not even knowing
what we're going to new thing we're going to be attached to today today and sure enough we something comes
along and something maybe we never even thought about maybe we have a
smartphone and there's suddenly there appears a new operating system or a new
new app that does something we never dreamed of before and uh and now we
really have to have it and we've collected a new attachment a new clinging and so we can
go through the day and acquire more and more um we see something beautiful and
we want it we see something ugly and we want to push it away and it's a kind of
a clinging and attachment for it to go away and um and it's fascinating to
watch how this the the the the appearance new attachments new clinging
the mind watching on the mind fixating on one way or the other either for or
against things the mind is fixated now and um it sometimes people have
amazing capacity for one-pointed attention uh when it's for something
they're attached to they're clinging to wanting something really hard
including not wanting it to go wanting to go away wanting to get away from
it so um so the Buddha uh put a tremendous
emphasis on understanding clinging and what we cling to and and
how what clinging feels like and so uh he has he lists four five
different bundles five different categories that we bundle up into forms
of clinging attachment the first one we talked about I talked about on Monday is appearances
physical appearances the second is feelings of pleasant and
unpleasantness the third is our perceptions our recognitions of things
and today it's um the constructions of the Mind the poly words sunara can
literally etymologically be translated its constructions um and um uh Tanis biku
monk who's a translator into English he calls this Fabrications and I like to use the word
constructions and uh some translators do mental formations but mental formations is a
little bit weak and uh it's or abstract Fabrications imply something which is
made up that we make constructions means kind of the same
thing and it's not any any con any activities of the mind it's not all
mental activities it's a particular kind of mental activities which has to do
with um uh constructing stories judgments
identities uh constructing um ideas that are about the
future and the past um building up and an edifice of self by all the different
kind of ideas of what self is who myself is what I'm supposed to be doing who I
and we create these edifices these complicated worlds of constructions and some
people you know maybe you know 50% 90% you know if it's close to 100% uh uh
sometimes we're considered to has to be somehow mentally ill the more we live in
these constructions these fantasies these delusions delusion that the mind
can create uh the more disconnected we are from reality and U most of us are
not go so far that others are worried about us um but uh it still we're going kind
of where there's a range from having no stories no no constructions about things
and being very innocent and simple and and maybe naive about what's right here
to to being completely disconnected from what's here just have spinning out in
stories but in between there there's a range and in that range uh there are
times we get attached to these stories constructions um uh built up identities
that we have so uh we're making things up in the mind we're building things up
in the mind and we get attached to them and um and that can be as simple as
um you know maybe i' I've never been on a that's true I've never been on a on a
electric scooter that they have now around town so maybe today I try one and
uh it turns out that I have aptitude for doing it easily and simply and zipping around town and between pedestrians and
between cars and and after a few hours of zipping around on this scooter um I
conclude that I am the best scooter driver in
Redwood City no one's as good as me look at me I'm just my my my role in this
town is to show people uh what a good scooter scooter scootering I'm doing and
um so here you know before I woke up today I had no identity no story about
myself and on a scooter but then I it gets constructed right in front of my
own eyes or behind my own eyes um as I do this and I have this whole sense of
Pride and status and you know Wonderful delusions of grandeur and probably I'll
be interviewed by Oprah and different things because I'm so good and I'm drifting off into this world of story
making the Buddha said that that this world of constructs is one of the
bundles things that people get attached to cling to and um and uh to become free
the kind of spiritual Liberation the Buddha was emphasizing all grasping has to come to
a stop all the ways in which we're tightened up and fisted up in the heart and the mind wants to be released so we
release the mind that holds on to stories the mind that has attachment
that's the fuel to for building and making the stories and uh we can feel that
sometimes we can feel it sometimes as um tension in the mind
pressure we can feel it as a the the effort is operating effort is can be
tiring can be forceful we can feel it as a limitation where our world has narrow
down into this this little world of story making little world of
in the head from the neck up and we're just kind of going and spinning around and around and around making these
things and sometimes one makes the next so I make him have an identity around
around being a good scooter driver and then um that gives birth to ideas that
well certainly there's a nice scooter outfit that I should be wearing and um
and this is really important and to appear right so they get attached to my appearance and then I want to have um
gloves for my scooter driving that's are really comfortable and and uh get attached to the comfort of what I'm
going to wear and and then it goes on and on the uh the these bundles I start
collecting more and more bundles of attachments in relationship to something that when I woke up this morning I had
no attachment to and I create maybe a Universe around this thing and by end of the day nothing else is important in my
life except everything to do with um my scooter and what it means and the
different aspect of it so um so some of
us will live in these kinds of uh mental constructs AB abstractions
Fabrications and not know that they are that um it's just a part and parcel of
kind of how the mind oper op Ates that we think that it's true and this is how it is and it's
accurate but if we sit and meditate and get quiet enough we can feel the tension
of that kind of thinking the tiredness of that kind of thinking we can start feeling how it keeps us limited from the
whole and um uh and so to um learn how
to to quiet that down enough to begin re
bringing our attention here in a Simplicity of being a radical
Simplicity of being that the story making mind will criticize as being
simplistic and not important not fun not where life really is the where it really
is is building and succeeding and making something fantastic and wonderful that
uh uh requires that kind of thinking that kind of story making that kind of
ambition and uh and to be resting in a Simplicity of being is um is um a
betrayal even or is a not as much fun or it's not going to get us ahead in the world and important
ways but to let go of our grasping opens up a door opens up a capacity to be
present for ourselves and the world in an fantastic
way it gives us depth it gives us fullness it gives access to the all the
working of this intelligence of this body and mind that we have if we're just
in the neck up in the stories and we're disconnected from The Amazing capacity
that this body mind heart art has for knowing here and now our whole system body and mind has
been designed to be
intimately attentive int
intimately processing intimately responding intimately
interacting with present moment reality and so much over the fullness of
of who we are comes out when we turn off
the story making mind and can come from this [Music] deeper uh operating system that we
have that uh is so much richer than what anything the story making mind can do for
itself and what's fun about that is that when we're more connected and settled
and not attached to the story making mind the we can still tell
stories and that but we know their stories we're not grasping at them but
they can arrive arise out of this deeper C uh place of creativity within that can
be have its own fun its own wonderfulness its own wisdom that uh cannot operate if we're
from the neck up so you might go through
today looking and seeing what are the stories about the
future you're living in actively like reflecting on thinking
about what are the stories and ideas of the past what are the stories you're making up about self who you are and who
you are in the eyes of others a lot of the story making is has to do with Me Myself and
mine and and then see if you can notice the contrast between the stories you live
in and the Simplicity of
being that you can live in may you live in the fullness of your life
without having the story making mind
obscure be an obstacle to the fullness of your
being thank
you