so hello and welcome welcome to this Friday
meditation and I'd like to this meditation build on
or continue with the momentum or
the the background of these first days or these last two weeks of
meditation last two weeks of teachings to offer something rather
Radical Something That is a maybe would turn things around quite
TR atically for a few of you having to do with where you Center your
life and um it it has to do with
happiness that the deepest fullest
happiness that can come from Dharma practice and a certain kind of way
doesn't come from a cause doesn't come with reasons doesn't happen come with
anything changing in the outer World often we're looking to be happy by
having things go well for us in the world and we're unhappy when they're
not but to have an inner uh our inner life be independent
of what happens around us independent of success and failures independent of
praise and blame independent of being liked or not liked
being there's a there's a happiness inside that is not
dependent on what's happening in the world it's not dependent
on all kinds of things that or ordinarily we think we need to change in order to
be happy and so a happiness without cause a
happiness without reason a happiness that
comes when we are letting go of searching getting get letting go
of wanting letting go of the stories that we tell ourselves stories that might have some
truth to what's happening around us or in the world but still we might be
telling ourselves stories about it remembering it thinking about
it making commentary letting go of
stories letting go of searching of wanting letting go of
resistance letting go of Doubt letting go of all the extra ways
in which we stir ourselves up all the ways which we live in a reaction active
mode or all the ways in which we live in an activated
mode just to be here without all those
things and here turns out being here in a full
way being here without all those other things is where we can find
happiness that has no reason you could say it's there because
we're not stirring ourselves up so that's may be a reason but it's
the reasons those kinds of reasons are talking about what's
absent nothing has to be present nothing has to be
happening let go enough and happiness
comes let go enough into mindfulness into
awareness and there's a yes in our whole system a yes to be here yes to be
attentive there can be a yes to physical pain and emotional pain oddly enough
there can be joy and happiness together with physical or
emotional pain if we've let go
enough so to meditate to assume a
posture that supports you to let go
deeply is there a posture for you where you can be present not fall
fall asleep but also let
go into this
moment gently closing the
eyes and immediately letting go whatever you
can and in the letting go let go into the body
breathing if anything is activated let go relax
settle into the body
breathing in order to gently
brush aside your stories your
preoccupations gently take deeper breaths and deeper
longer exhales as if it's
sweeping whatever is extra away blowing it
away and settling into your body here as you exhale
long exhale quieting the mind as you do so
letting the breathing return to
normal and taking a few moments to
definitively feel sense that you are here in this body at this time
and in this definitive feeling of being here when as you
exhale settle into it as you let your thinking Drift Away
and things like wanting and not wanting searching expecting trying to
fix searching for answers being caught in
stories all those come with a certain degree of tension pressure
stress
agitation maybe you can't have them stop
but as you exhale let there be a quieting of
them and a shifting of your life center from the
stories from the
wanting to this body breathing here
for
e
e for
rather than wanting something or trying to make something
happen rather than doing meditation
shift your way of being to
allowing allowing something to
arise if you feel calm allow that
to [Music] grow if you feel
content or happy allow that to
surface allow it to be there the feelings of
it and if there's any way that's somehow inside
you have a yes to being present
aware here now allow that
yes
hello the present moment
to flow into your
being maybe like an underwater spring that flows water into the lake
from the lake Bottom
allow whatever goodness whatever
wholesomeness that can Surface once you let
go
for
e
e for
any sense of goodness well-being that you might be
feeling that is not there for a reason it just is because there's space
and room and quiet for the humming of the body to show
itself for the humming of a subtle
attentive aware body and
mind allow that humming allow that
well-being to spread through your body to spread through your
heart to spread through your
mind
e
for
e e
and then as we come to the end of this meditation whatever benefits that you
receive from meditation whatever way that you are calmer
happier more at ease
don't leave it just for something to do in
meditation it can grow for you if you consider how you can you how you can
bring it with you or have it as a reference point for how you interact with people
today if there was a very non-threatening way to meet someone
in the current state that you are
in what do we like to be
with talk with someone that you'll see
today if you were the way you are at the end of meditation
is there some way that it's beneficial for you to be this
way in the conversation in the encounter is there's something you can
offer the other person offer them a calm
space offer them greater Goodwill gaze upon them with whatever
well-being that's
present and in this way we begin bringing the benefits of practice into
the world while at the same time those benefits can grow for us benefit
us may it be that whatever happiness we
experience may we we wish happiness for others may it be that whatever safety
that we feel that we support the safety of
others whatever peace that we experience let that be a gift we give
others and whatever Freedom letting go we have of attachments and claim
let's appreciate meeting others without those attachments without our
clinging may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
thank
you
e e
it seems I have to push a button over at the control station I'll be right
back e
so hello and welcome to this fourth of four talks
on the truths of happiness and maybe it's a bit bold to put those two words
together the four truths of happiness but uh I
hopefully allowed to do it uh as a continuation or building on the central
Buddhist teaching on the four noble truths of suffering suffering the cause of
suffering the end of suffering and the path of practice leading to end of suffering
and so the path of path leading to end of suffering doesn't just lead us to an end
a dead end a you know it just uh it leads us to
happiness and U the Buddha was said to be the happy one the people who practice
with him were uh noted for being happy and
smiling and um and happiness and peace is probably the most common emotional
characteristic of someone who's attained Awakening in this early this Buddhist
tradition and so what can we say about happiness and so I've offer these things
that as a compliment to the four noble truths uh of suffering and as a four I
don't want to call it Noble but the four truths of of happiness and um and uh
so there there is happiness that we can Avail ourselves of the first truth the
second is there are the conditions for the arising of it uh we don't cause it but we allow
certain conditions to bring it about and uh there's a truth that's
second and the third is maintain it the truth of maintaining it it's not the
truth of the end of happiness but the truth of sustaining it keeping it going
the Buddha emphasized uh in very kind of uh emphatic
statements of maintaining sustaining increasing developing
growing um wholesome qualities and wholesome qualities and well-being
happiness are closely connected and then the fourth is
um uh there is just like there's a a path of practice to the end of
suffering there's a letting go that uh
leads to the practices of happiness or say it differently there is
a letting go that surfaces that gives
birth to the ways of being that promote happiness and what I mean by this is
that both in both these the fourth of the Four Noble Truths the fourth of these four
happinesses are explained as the Eightfold Path Right View right resolve
right speech right action right lifestyle right effort right mindfulness
right concentration and um and in the ancient text there are two ways that these are
discussed one is as practices that lead to the end of suffering but the other
way they T they presented is that these are way not I don't know if we still
want to call them practices but these are ways of being that arise for us um
as we let go of clinging as we let go of our craving rather than something we
intentionally do it uh the ancient description is they become us we become
endowed with them we become filled with them they become who we are rather than
what we do so we we are we see the way we see is
we see we don't have to practice seeing this particular way we
see uh Right View we see in that way they just a natural outcome just like if
you um if you
I don't know if you someone tells you thatone points out to you that um
something that you haven't noticed yet about anything then after you've not after that pointed out you can never not
see it so it's now it's built into who you are that of course you'll see it that you'll see
it so um there is right uh
resolve of course you're not going to be cruel of course you're not going to be unkind
of course you'll be kind and compassionate that just arises out of his deep state of letting go so you
become compassion you that you don't practice compassion you become free of Cruelty you don't practice being free of
Cru being without cruelty right speech becomes a
description of who you are not a prescription it isn't that you have to this now I have to do this this
describes what how you speak so all of these then become descriptive rather than
prescriptive and so there is a letting so the the and um and this is the
welling up the rising of
well-being and um
so uh there is this deep letting go there is this Freedom that allows something that's deep within us to
manifest as a different kind of happiness than ordinary happiness in daily
life ordinary happiness is dependent is conditioned things have to come together
in the right way we have to win the lottery we have to have the right date the right experience we have to uh get
something that brings us a lot of pleasure we have to get praise or we have to feel that we're doing something
good in the world it's always there's a reason for it and some of those forms of
Happiness nothing nothing inherently wrong with them some of them involve craving and can produce a lot of
suffering but there's a whole other way of being happy that comes with a very
deep Letting Go letting go that doesn't leave us with
nothing a deep letting go of craving of clinging that doesn't leave us to be a
blank slate a big blank but a makes room for
this big yes this warmth this hum of yes
this hum of goodness of well-being that is portable we can take
it with us it lives within us as who we are and maybe we don't always feel it
for sure but it's available if we stop it's available if we slow down it's
available if we let go it's available if we just turn our attention to it here
there is a yes there's a delight there's a a pleasure of Simply being here
present alive to be alive without any hindrances
to be alive without any clinging to be alive without any resistance allows for
a kind of natural harmonious functioning of all the functions of our
life all the the the inner faculties that we
have and there's something remarkable that can arise when everything is in
Harmony from all the Letting Go all the ways we limit ourselves shut ourselves
down resist ourselves uh get caught in something to not be caught and let the homeostasis
let the heal the natural healing occur the natur natural opening occurring when
everything is in in us has a c not everything but when there's a certain kind of Inner Harmony inner allowance of
this goodness to flow from deep within then there is a
happiness which doesn't depend on anything in the world then there's a well-being and a
peace that's a parad that's a paradigm shift it's a revolution AR change it's a
radical different way of living our lives than the way that most people live
and what Society tells us to live and how it wants us to live it we then
become um uh centered um oriented around a different
way of being in the world than what advertisers want us to do politicians wants us to do that uh we
become the um settled peaceful and
something beautiful flows out of us
a furnace
that's warm and producing heat does not
need a little space heater next to it to make it
warm when you're firm Fess of Love fness Of Happiness well-being of peace is
strong enough in you you don't need small space heers of praise and
blame success and failure pleasures and avoiding
displeasures you don't need the world to provide
you because you're radiating something
beautiful so I hope that uh this has given you something to
consider something maybe to challenge you with but more important than that
something that you will experiment with something that you'll now go into the world live your day with this question
with this exploration this kind of feeling centering on yourself where is that happiness
where does it arise from what are the conditions that allow it to
arise if um I let
go if I Center myself on it where's the happiness that's not
dependent on the world and can I trust
it and live my life from
that live a good life so thank you very much and um I'll
be here again on next week and I guess I'll be here for right through the whole
Thanksgiving uh week Thursday morning as well and um so for those of you who come
this next week I look forward to our time together and um the rest of you I
wish you well and for what might be happening next and maybe as you go into
this week in whatever circumstance you have maybe you'll be really well
supported staying close to a happiness that's not dependent on anything that's
what we can be thankful for thank you