so so hello and welcome to this uh fourth guided meditation on
mindfulness of emotions and what I'd like to uh start with
today is uh using a kind of a
analogy we can say uh in English uh uh we use the distinction between the
words listening and hearing someone might direct you to listen to something
and and then intentionally you turn your attention to listening to and um or you can you can hear
something without the intention to to hear and uh these two words overlap but
hearing is more likely used for something which is more receptive and maybe
unintentional we hear a sound and then we're interested what is going on and so we listen carefully and the listening is
the more the effort to be engaged the same thing with um seeing
and looking uh someone doesn't say uh someone might say see here but um if
you're more the usual instructions is to look um and so in the way I'm talking
about today trying to highlight the difference between two different ways of
uh using our eyes is to see one there's more a natural receptivity where we see
what's happening without um trying to see and the other
is seeing by trying to see intentionally to look and so when we practice
meditation uh both are activated and both are fine but there is a kind of a
orientation or a leaning towards the part that is more receptive more um not trying to make
something happen so if we're sensing the body breathing if we're
sensing The Body Sensations the idea is to not be so much in the control tower trying to sense or
making making kind of a kind of extra mental effort to really feel well what's
going on but rather to put ourselves in a situation where we can really sense
receive uh in an open way the sensations and
um so um on this topic this week of
emotions uh in that in this way we want to uh receive the
sensations and and and nice mode for being with our emotions is to listen to
them the the way we would listen not the way we would um the way we would uh um
no we would hear we would uh hear them we allow they
come we wouldn't direct ourselves to kind of strain there's no strain
involved uh it's just kind of allowing ourselves the this the emotions to be heard to hear deeply what's there so I
don't know if this distinction makes so much sense to all of you but um the idea of
receptively uh being open and to hear to listen to the emotions as if there's
something profound to hear there for some people that gets their their um
self-consciousness out of the way their efforts to try to fix or make something happen out of the way it's a way of
allowing the emotion to be there uh giving a permission to be there
uh while also being available to hear to
feel to find out what's going on here and more deeply so it'd be akin to sitting on a
sitting with a friend and who just wants to be heard and you just are an active
listener you're present hearing allowing it to come but you're not involved in
trying to fix or or um question question or interfere with your friend you might
indicate that you're listening well and Nod and say yes or I hear you or maybe
sometimes repeat back what you hear but you're just a a really good listener and that's all they
need and so with emotions mindfulness of emotions we're trying to shift the
orientation from any tendency we might have to be judging them to be preferring
one over the other to be uh resistant to them to kind of approach them as if
they're a problem and I have to fix them and if I just bring mindfulness to it this difficult emotion will go away the
idea is to approach it more um with the capacity to allow it to be there and I
use that word capacity very carefully we're trying to increase our
capacity to sense feel hear
see uh whatever is happening in uh um without interfering with it and and by
doing so to be able to see it deeply to hear it deeply to feel it deeply to see
you know so that it reveals something deeper about itself and one of the simplest things it
reveals is that it's some way or other is always changing and to see a
change uh makes it easier not to be kind of stuck around it and and a fixed view
or reaction to it it's easier than maybe to allow it just to change to unfold
give it room to do what it wants so to increase
capacity so we'll begin this uh this uh meditation with a small Act of
imagination and then uh we'll go into this a little bit more deeply so assume a meditation
posture and gently close your
eyes and before doing anything else before taking some deep breaths and
relaxing spend a few moments feeling or
listening deeply what is here for you how are
you and one way to increase the capacity to hold and be with whatever is here for
you is to imagine that you're in a very very large
space big Cathedral like room or a vast
landscape and whatever way you're feeling is clearly a one part of a
vastness all
around maybe looking into the night sky and you still feel just the way
you're feeling but the vastness of the night
sky it both highlights how you're feeling and it's it's like there's a vast room for it to be just the way you
are do you be quiet and still spacious with how you
are as if a awareness is the vast
Sky within which how you are is
known in the vast Sky nothing is a
problem it's just a piece of the
whole and then in the middle of it all breathing
in and breathing
out and as you exhale to relax soften the
body
and then centering yourself on your
breathing the center of all things is breathing in and out within a vast
landscape of a spacious awareness of
space maybe almost as if there's vast space in your own
body and the movements and sensations of
breathing maybe are like a g Al wind coming and
going as you exhale to relax relax the thinking
muscle relax around thinking calming the thinking
mind
more often than not there's a thinking mind which contracts
us Narrows our identity who we are what's
important the more we're preoccupied and caught in our
thoughts the the smaller the capacity
is to be open and aware non
reactively
for
and as we continue meditating for a little while longer
Center yourself on the breathing but with your peripheral
awareness with a very light touch not trying too hard peripheral awareness around Beyond
the focus on breathing be aware
of your body maybe the weight of your
body the substantiality of your
body without focusing on the body or thinking about it much let it be a
companion on the edges of Bri full
awareness the edges of
breathing where peripheral
awareness provides more room for breathing to come and go
inhales and
exhales
for
and now take a few moments to recognize how
how you're feeling what's your emotional state
mood the state of your inner
being how more globally do you
feel and let there be lots of
space for how you're feeling or maybe
your central attention is being with your emotions your mood your
state maybe breathing with it but the peripheral
awareness creates a
vastness a spaciousness where it's easier just to
allow the emotions to be there without reacting or doing anything
about them judging them or making
commentary
we're like a good friend you're just listening or feeling or
seeing the emotion for what it is giving it permission to be
there
finding an ability to give lots of space and
room to how you feel without thinking about it or
analyzing it or reacting to it the task is to increase your
capacity to Simply allow how you are to be
there and you listening or sensing
feeling how it is how the emotion
is as if you're a friend for
it
where you're present for the sensations of breathing of of the
emotion how the emotion is expressed in the
body and and for that you make lots of
room
for
if it's helpful for staying present with the emotion breathe with the emotion breathe
through it let breathing be in the middle of the
emotion and on the edges vast space
openness that allows your emotion to be there as it
is
for
checking in how are
you checking in without trying to disturb anything
just to see and feel as if everything is allowed to be
just the way it is undisturbed but you seeing it knowing
it as gently as the breathing might be a Brea as as gentle as a gentle
breeze of breathing
making room for how you feel and feeling it in the body the
sensations of your emotions it's okay let it be for these
few moments
breathing
there is freedom to be found not by changing what's happening
but by changing a relationship to what's
happening and one of the ways that change can take is to know and be aware of what's
happening in a spacious Way open
way listening deeply listening with respect to all
things
while not disturbing
anything
and then as we come to the end of this
meditation without disturbing anything or thinking we have to do anything
directly to anything open your awareness wide
broad vast like the
sky and become aware of the people of your
life those you know the neighbors you don't know people on the streets and places
of Commerce
work and for a few moments to hold it
spaciously allowing without a mind that disturbs
anyone with our judgments or commentary our
preferences just a A
Ware an awareness within which people are safe from us safe from our judgments
safe from our fixing and condemning and pushing
away or holding on an awareness that helps people feel
safe and in that safety in that capacity to hold people in our hearts in our
awareness to wish them well may you be
happy may you be
peaceful may you be safe
may you be free and may we live
together so in such a way that we all can be
happy we all can feel
safe we all can be peaceful we all can be
[Music]
free thank you
so good morning good day everyone and welcome to this fourth talk
on mindfulness of emotions and um one of the great skills
to develop in relationship to our emotions and how we're feeling is to expand our capacity to
feel and partly that means uh in a very powerful thing that can mean is expand
our capacity to be
uncomfortable many of much of our reactivity in life challenges we have is
because something or other is making us feel uncomfortable and and so then we don't
like it we want to fix it we want to blame someone we get caught up in the trying to do something about being
uncomfortable and that discomfort might be physical it might also be emotional and there's a lot of things
which are emotionally uncomfortable and to be be to become
wise and skillful with situations that where we feel
emotionally uncomfortable one of the ways to find our way with that is to be able to allow
ourselves to feel what we're feeling without reacting to it without being
pushed around by it or feel trapped by it or feel somehow like we have to do
something because of it and all of which uh is subsumed under
the idea of of uh increasing our capacity to feel how our emotional
life and without reactivity this allows us then to be
more reflective of what we do to consider what's the wise thing to do in this situation if we feel that uh we want to
um swear at someone because we feel bent up anger or frustration um if we increase our
capacity to feel frustration then it doesn't have to be an automatic
trigger to swear at someone we just kind of oh we rest we open to what's
happening for us and then we can reflect what would be the skillful thing to do what would be the wise thing or the
compassionate thing to do uh with this phenomena with this P
what's happening here and um and there might be chances are there are better
things to do than to swear at someone or we might might shut down we
might collapse or pull in and or or or kind of shrink away if something is
uncomfortable and it's certainly understandable we can feel threatened and challenged and want to do that but
there are also uh capacities to the ability to kind of stay open and feel
afraid but without being influenced by it just it's there and we kind of are bigger than the fear we have more space
for it and again we can then be wiser about how we respond to the fear rather
than shrinking maybe we take three 10 steps back and and um without having to
diminish ourselves or Shrink or collapse in some way or perhaps uh we can assess
the danger more carefully and and uh have a wise response while standing our
ground with it um so these are all just kind
of examples that maybe you can fill in but the idea is whatever is happening it
doesn't have to just be discomfort some things feel really good and uh and
sometimes uh it can be quite stressful to be overjoyed or feel delighted and
and uh feel happy and or it's easy to kind of get swept away in it and we lose
ourselves in it uh and lose our mindfulness lose our
presence because we're so kind of Swept Away in the in the excitement of the moment and there's it might be nothing
wrong with that but uh it's easy T to make mistakes to say the wrong things to
uh do some things which later we regret we did in the excitement of the moment and um and it's a wonderful thing
to open up to a capacity to feel our joy not to diminish it but to allow it to
kind of live in us in a very different way than if we allow it to uh um take
over and and uh get us act activated around
it and there are times when it's the best thing we can do is to just hold the
good feelings in this broad open way because there might be a deeper
Wellspring of responsivity that has a chance to surface if we don't act from the surface
joy and the excitement of it all but we open and relax and feel oh maybe there's
love here maybe there's generosity maybe there's um you know um being more
inclusive of the other people involved rather than caught up in our own excitement and joy and somehow lose
track of the people around us so the principle of increasing our
capacity to feel our emotions without being reactive that's kind of like one
of the North Stars that we're working with when we're practicing with mindfulness of
emotions so one way to do that is to uh find
something a different way to be with emotions than the way we are when we get
activated or reactivated by it very often what uh what activates us
around it is the story or the way we relate to it the attitude we have
towards it and so to increase the capacity to hold an emotion it helps to
kind of sit quietly like in meditation breathe gently be present uh feel the
emotions in the body and then take a look and see what is your relationship to the emotion
being there is there is your relationship the way you're relating to it the way you're
reacting to it is it making the space smaller you're getting narrower contracted or you're getting kind of
caught up in it or are you able to relate to it more spaciously and openly
and for these few moments at least allow it to be there so there's an expansive
quality of the heart of the body of the mind of awareness so that oh it's like
this and so to part of the task of mindfulness of
emotions is to notice what is our relationship to the emotion and this is not meant to be
analysis it's not meant to be spend a lot of time thinking about it it's just kind of asking yourself the question and
if nothing jumps out as being obvious uh don't go looking for it just but
sometimes you say oh of course I don't like it I'm trying to push it away or I'm trying to fix it or I'm um you know
I'm trying to justify why I feel this way with the story so so if it's obvious is then see
if you can expand and say oh it's just a story it's just a way of relating to it there's the
emotion and the relationship to it and then maybe it's easier to kind of
drop in and feel the emotion by itself and you can just make room for the emotion and feel it and allow it to be
there another way of talking about expanding our capacity to feel emotions is expanding our developing
ability to stay uh quiet and still with the emotion to cap develop a
capacity not to automatically act or automatically think to what's happening
but find a place of stability and quiet and Stillness inside in meditation in
that Stillness or that stability recognizes the
emotion some people find that there's a kind of stab ility or a kind of U
Stillness in the peripheral awareness that uh so it's kind of like
the this is an analogy is that of a site we have central vision and we have peripheral vision and when we look at
something we're engaging central vision and um but uh when we're um but
peripheral vision is kind of always there and we can kind of tune into
peripheral vision almost by not trying um we can't kind of turn our
central vision to look at peripheral vision we have to kind of relax and open and and kind of just sense and feel
without a central Focus being predominant same way when we sit in
mindfulness and just with our eyes closed and we're aware there is a kind of peripheral
awareness that is more kind of like peripheral vision where when we're not
caught in it we're not fixating on something we're kind of have spacious around it we kind of allow it to be
there and um and in a kind of Stillness of peripheral vision or non-reactivity
of peripheral awareness and so it's another way of then developing this capacity to be
with emotions in some emotions it turns out
that some of the wonderful emotions can become more wonderful when there's that space for it and we don't get
involved tinkering with it and some of the difficult emotions when there's space and this kind of awareness tend to
get be to be deflated tend to relax because they tend to be there because of
tension and the very thing of not being involved takes away the in the tension
that comes from involvement so to increase the capacity to feel and be is one of the great uh
skills we're trying to develop here in mindfulness and it doesn't require getting rid of anything it just requires
a quiet way peaceful way of staying present with this it's a skill that we develop over
time so don't be in a hurry but uh I hope that this teaching
today about increasing your capacity uh is something now that is of
interest for you and you have a sense oh yeah maybe I could do it a little bit at a time and let me experiment with
this and so for example as you go through your day there might be times
through the day that you're emotionally uncomfortable or maybe emotionally
excited in some good way and you might uh spend maybe three breaths maybe a
minute see what would it mean now to expand my capacity just allow this to be
here with a spacious peripheral awareness as if there's lots of room for
me to be this way if there's if I have the ability to stay still and
non-reactive kind of inner Stillness or stability just to be with it and to feel
it and what happens if you do that for a minute um and maybe you want to start
with emotions that are not um really strong maybe there's medium emotions
that you can experiment with this capacity to expand this ability to expand your
capacity and in the end maybe what you learn is how to be comfortable with
being uncomfortable and that is a superpower uh all kinds of things are
available if you can do that that are not available if you're reactive to be
being uncomfortable so
um I hope hope that you have plenty of opportunities today
to explore for a minute or two how to expand your ability Your Capacity to be
present for your emotions non reactively where you kind of become bigger and more expansive as you allow
the emotion to be there and um and maybe you do this incrementally so don't don't
have a high standard for what this look looks like but it's a skill that gets developed over
time so um thank you and we have one more talk tomorrow on this
topic