okay welcome uh welcome folks good to uh good to be with
you um I realize I think I need to
meditate which is maybe fortunate timing maybe not but uh here here we go so uh
settle in find uh get
cozy cozy alert
just try as best you can
to recall all the moments of
willingness all the moments which you've offered your heart
up to the Dharma all the moments of uh
sitting or lying down meditation or walking or Retreat or listening to
talks or being with Dharma
friends I realized yesterday I've been practicing for
exactly half my
life so just as we
begin gather up uh all the goodness
from your practice just bring it right in front of
you feel it let it seed your
mind
e e
now all those moments of practice
all the moments of [Music] pain of uh greed and hate wisdom
love and it's all come to this
and so in attending to this moment we actually honor bless all of that
gently tending to your life
e
e e
the question how might it have been
otherwise becomes uh
meaningless just this breath
body our life as it constellates in this moment
gentle
nonviolent with
uh all
experience
e
e e
we plot out our
pleasure budget our pleasure as a way
of taking the edge off the intensity of The Human
Condition devise way is out
of anicha uncertainty
game out the contingencies
is try to soothe ourselves into
safety we reash the
past trying to think our way through it so as
to digest it learn its
lessons such innocent movements of mind
who could blame
us but there's a deeper refuge on offer
go for
Refuge
e
e e
just letting the Winds of Change blow right through
you trusting they won't harm
you
e
for e
okay um so uh good to sit with you
um so I read um Rachel kushner's uh recent novel
creation Lake um last week and
um there's a line that that um struck
me uh she she writes one of her characters says um Charisma Charisma
does not originate inside the person called charismatic it comes from the need of
others to believe that special people
exist kind of heart leapt up at that line and
uh and it um invites the question in in my mind like what is what is my need to
believe in special people
is idealization making of special people is idealization
just a facet of the human mind and there are certainly people who
Express particular gifts certain we could say parames you
know uh but special people special people that gets us into the realm of
projection and idealization and comparison
special people uh turns a quality into a person
turns a a verb into a noun so what what is it what is it about
our need to believe that special people exists where does that
come from and and what what are the
pleasures and also the ca of
idealization and for each of us to consider you know like what what is
your default assumption about yourself your power your relative place
amongst the special people whever they
are and how do you position yourself in relation to
specialness some people identify with the special ones I
want to be on that team some people want to own the special
ones some people are sexually titilated by specialness some people get
competitive and want to tear something down specialness evokes jealousy and
some self death doubt in others arrogance in yet
others and in reflecting on it struck me like maybe part of the belief in special
people comes out of the Dynamics of of childhood you know
where our lives depend on the power of
others you know and we so want a a parent or caretaker
to be omnipotent to control you know like our our
safety is contingent on their power our safety increases with their
power and the disillusionment and uh or fear
engendered by the realization that uh this parent this person this
caretaker this whatever not special very human this parent very
human this person doesn't exert much control over the world at
all and then we grow up but as Adam Phillips um once
commented um adulthood is not a cure for
childhood and we're kind of left in a way with an
unresolved relationship to
specialness and maybe there's some transitional role for
idealization uh seeing someone as special but that can't be the last word
and part of Dharma practice is about untangling
specialness and goodness maybe we say specialness um
requires a self and goodness does
not sometimes uh teachers uh start to think that they are the
goodness or that they own it or something like that but it's it's just
nature refracted through a particular body you
know and by the way if you like have some theory that I'm like massively
shading Gil and Andrea or something that's not it this not this not this is
just r AEL Kushner got me started you know it wasn't like I saw something horrible or you know
right so okay we start to notice the the
uh the childlike longings that that lead us you
know to put special ones on pedestals to make
them special and um and it's not like we have to
we're disparage a person we look up to but we notice the movements of our mind
in relation to specialness and we do this in part
because we know specialness can never be
sustained there's always [Music] disillusionment and part of spiritual me
maturation is opening to some measure of ambivalence that is the kind of Hallmark
of the human realm loving even amidst
ambivalence a love that's a little less
naive less and less specialness but there is reverence you
know the reverence is not
um it's it's not really for a person it's it's it's for goodness
itself and that still you know seeing
goodness that makes me want to get on my knees but I'm not bowing to special
to touch into goodness to actually feel it let it reverberate with our own
hearts that doesn't bolster or threaten selfworth at
all that doesn't make me feel less than as I look
up and that doesn't evoke the urge to possess or to be on that team it's just
a kind of Deep honoring I know goodness when I see it
you know I don't need to deify it into some form of specialness I don't need to
turn into a
noun but there's something in in that kind of you know and and this can be goodness
of of a million different varieties but in that kind of full
full recognition of uh of goodness we we
partake in it you know we partake in it it's it's like two two Bells
resonating at the same
frequency and uh nothing is owned no selves are needed comparison
that the whole grammar of comparison is a million miles away so beside the
point yeah maybe say this like mudita some way sympathetic
Joy our aspiration um becomes more and more
about being ordinary than becoming
special you know special is just the the charade the egoic
charade but the the parame me is they feel so ordinary from the
inside they only look special from the
outside and so there's this Progressive sense of like yeah
more more and more U ordinary goodness is so
ordinary even if extraordinarily
beautiful so um nor Norman fiser from training and
compassion says um just talking about M mind training
um says um although we can enjoy the Applause that we will probably receive
for practicing it practice mind training not for the Applause but because we know
it's right we know it's necessary in anyway there is no
choice when people applaud us for our wonderful achievements really what they
applauding is not us and not those achievements they are applauding life
they're applauding goodness they are applauding their own lives they are
applauding the human capacity to appreciate something
wonderful so it's good when they applaud
let them applaud and we will graciously accept it
knowing what their Applause really means
so I offer this for consideration and uh please pick up
whatever is useful leave the rest behind
okay all right
folks so uh good to yeah good to be with you I'll be here I'll be yeah we'll be
back certain Wednesdays has encountered a period of regularity uh and and doing gills group
actually next week it's a lot of Bren silver it's too much in my professional
opinion too much Bren silver
but feel free okay folks see you uh see you next
time