good evening welcome welcome and you know what Jim I I said
that we might have to turn the volume up I had to I moved the microphone a little bit can we just increase the volume just
a tiny bit I have to talk so we can thank you thank you there we
go hope you guys are all doing well with the rain mixed feelings about the
[Laughter] rain we I we need it I appreciate it but you
know discovered that blue skies are kind of nice too but
nevertheless so I want to start with this poem that is written by somebody
who read some of the poems of the terata and the terata some of you might
know is the oldest literature attributed to women in the
history of the humans so this literature that's written by women attributed to
women and we partly we know it's written by women because it has a lot of feminine aspects it talks a lot about
motherhood and husbands and you know stuff like this thousands of years
old it's in the Buddhist Cannon and uh there's a poet who read
some of these poems I should say this literature is poems they are Awakening poems it's the like poems that uh it's
part of the tradition that after you have an Awakening experience or sometime you would have a little poem to describe
it so I'm not going to talk about the Awakening poems precisely maybe I will
on another night and they have been spoken about a number of times here at IMC if you're interested you can find
them on aiio Dara but a poet who read these poems and
wrote his own poem inspired by what he had written these Awakening
poems so the uh the title of the poems are about the woman the woman's name and
this so this one the woman's name is Vaya we can translate that as Victor you
know somebody who like wins you know has Victory something like
that and uh these poems are written in a um contemporary style and in a way that
you know a modern practitioner could relate to them unlike the ones that are thousands of years ago sometimes they're
a little bit uh you know they're they read like they're thousands of years
old okay so uh this is vayia and the poet is Maddie
weest and the poem goes like this when everyone else was
meditating I'd be outside circling the
hall finally I went to confess I'm
hopeless I said the Elder none smiled just keep
going she said nothing stays in orbit
forever if this circling is all you have why not make this circling your home
I did as she told me and went on circling the hall if you find yourself partly in and
partly out if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing
away I can assure you you're in good company just keep
going sometimes the most direct path isn't a straight line
I'll read this again I I kind I like this poem very much just there's so much in here and um
I'll unpack it a little bit but when everyone else was
meditating I'd be outside circling the hall finally I went to
confess I'm hopeless I said the Elder none
smiled just keep going she said nothing stays in orbit
forever if this circling is all you have why not make this circling your
home I did as she told me and went on circling the
hall if you find yourself partly in and partly out if you find yourself drawn to
this path and also drawing away I can assure you you're in good
company just keep going sometimes the most direct path
isn't a straight line so this is describing a
practitioner somebody who had this hesitation about the practice and U some
she was convinced that she was hopeless and that she had to do
something different like okay I'm just circling outside I need to do something
else and but something that's beautiful about this uh poem and about this practice is this practice isn't asking
us to be somebody that we're not we don't have to like completely reinvent
ourselves and if you find yourself circling circling the hole circling the
practice or maybe sometimes for me I feel circling is like well this like uh
vassel olation or hesitation or just kind of like feeling a feeling of stuckness just going around and
around so the teacher gives her this instruction well just keep
circling nothing stays in orbit forever because I think what the teacher
is pointing to here is so often when we have this feeling like I'm
hopeless then we just abandon the practice and go do something else we just stop if we feel like okay I
maybe other people can do this I can't do this there's this way in which
sometimes we have this feeling like you know what this I I can't do it I don't even know what they're talking about what's being pointed to maybe I used to
be able to meditate but now I don't or maybe like everybody else seems to know how to meditate in the whole and but I'm
not I can't or whatever it might be we might have some of these ideas about how
it should be and we have we're noticing how our experience is and it's not matching up the ideas of how we think it
should be and then then that gets expanded to just because my experience
doesn't match my expectations it means somehow that I'm failing I'm hopeless she says in here
this and all of really that's happening is you had expectations and you're having experiences and they don't match
that's all that's happening but we've really just turned it into a big thing this commentary about our worthiness as
practitioners or maybe even goes beyond to um our the practice as a whole or
something like this or some other ideas that we might
have for me I feel a little bit um
sensitive to this idea that in this poem it says finally I went to confess this word confess I feel like it doesn't feel
like such a good word instead maybe it could be like I just went to talk to somebody about it or I mentioned this to
somebody or you know I shared it with myself instead of hiding it in shame
like oh I'm actually really a terrible meditator everybody else is okay but I
have this shameful feeling about a way that I am that's not what we want the
truth is meditation is not always easy it takes practice
sometimes if we had a really busy day and our minds are really busy or if we have some emotional stuff that is coming
up and our life is filled with emotional stuff that comes up this is what it means to be a
human then you know maybe our our mind just doesn't settle and can that be okay instead of
making these Grand uh conclusions I'm
hopeless so there's something else that I'd like to talk to that this poem is pointing to in one interpretation
there's lots of interpretations we could do here there's I don't want to say there's only one but here's one this
whole idea of circling and this feeling like I'm not going anywhere I'm just going around and
around points to this hindrance of Doubt skeptical doubt some of you might be
familiar with this idea that uh there's these five classical
things that get in the way of meditation things that are like barriers or
obstacles or hindrances hindrances to getting settled hindrances to feeling
connected to ourselves hindrances to feeling connected to other people and to our
life and one of these five is doubt and this is something that uh for
me I take comfort in thousands of years ago they were talking about this humans had troubles meditating back then too so
D is one of them I'll just mention the other ones I'm not going to talk about them desire this really wanting
something and I Noti I do this with my body because it kind of feels like this like we're leaning forward I got to get something other is aversion like oh get
this away from me I don't want it the third uh third is restlessness
this just feeling like just Twitchy and you want to jump out of your skin kind of feeling the fourth is sloth and
torper which is just this real tiredness like falling asleep sometimes literally falling asleep and the fifth one is
doubt so I want to talk a little bit about doubt and uh how to work with it
and I would say of these five hindrances doubt is the one that has the biggest
impact on us and it's the one that gets maybe seen is the most difficult to see
and can't have um as I said maybe earlier just give us to abandon this
whole idea of practicing so there's this idea
of Doubt is there's a number of ways we can talk about it and one is this
feeling like I can't do it like it seems like
other people can or the teacher talks about it or the drama book talks about it or I heard my friends talk about this
and but I don't know I I just just I don't know what they're talking about because it doesn't match what experience
I'm having or something like this so it's not
uncommon for I would say in the modern West and for this phenomenon to rise and
in particular we can see it in something like this with meditation and that is
the in inner critic gets activated this this inner critic this
feeling like whatever I'm doing is not quite right it's not enough or it's not
good enough or it's somehow is inadequate and then that kind of like
bleeds into I'm inadequate and I can't do
it and right in here in the poem she's saying I'm hopeless there's this little voice that's like
and it's we believe it right it's not only that it's a little voice that's showing up that somehow we think it's
the truth it's not the truth I'm telling you it's not the truth but doesn't
matter what I say you have to have this own experience just hearing me say that is not going to be necessarily helpful
but there's this way in which we uh we can undermine our capacity or our
capability or our what we're able to do our ideas about ourselves by this uh
voice that shows up we might call it some people call like a subpersonality
maybe like this a companion that shows up on occasion saying you'll never make
it this terrible uh voice and that we
believe so I'll just I've um done a number of talks on the inner critic it occurs to me I haven't done one maybe
two recently so maybe that's I should put as an idea to do one but um there's
this way in which this uh has like a harsh tone this
voice that's telling us that uh we were not doing it right and whatever our
experience is it's not the right experience and then I'll just say
briefly here if you find that you're like swimming in this inner critic that's really like putting you
down I me one thing you could if you can remember this is to just ask how am I
right now because we don't need to be critical of the critic right that just
perpetuates it we don't we don't have to try to get rid of it we don't have to make it wrong we don't have to turn it
into a problem to get solved instead just ask yourself how am I right now how
am I right now and that kind of like turns into your experience at this
moment and that's this movement towards how you're feeling that could be like your bodily
experience or your emotional experience that movement that orientation towards asking that question
how am I right now is a way that uh is more like a movement of care it's a
movement of some wisdom too and that really can undermine the inner critic so
I can uh like I said I can give a whole talk on this but that's a short version
this feeling of like oh I can't do it and just like well how am I right now
you might say well actually I'm agitated and then you could say well how does that feel in the body agitation feels
like restlessness like my legs want to move for example like I want to get up and do something or I want to distract
myself and and then as best you can can you then feel the distractedness and then here you are
right in the middle of practice this is what practice is it's just being present for our experience even if that
experience is not what we want even if it's
unpleasant so doubt can have this show up as this experience of the inner
critic putting ourselves down it can also Al uh show up as doubt in the
teachings like well I don't know those Buddhists they seem like they are
austere or they don't seem like they have enough fun or they're just sitting quiet what good is that I don't know we
can have all these stories about uh just this practice and it's uh whether it's going
to support us and help us have a life that we want a life that has more joy and freedom and peace and
ease or of course we can start to have a doubt about the
teachings uh maybe the practices the teachings and the teachers like does she
really know what she's talking about this is a legitimate question right I think if somebody's going to sit up here
you're allowed to wonder well I don't know what does she know what she's talking about does anybody know what
they're talking about you know those Dharma books and whatever the Dharma talks that you hear so doubt shows up in
these different ways oneself the teachings the practice the teachers and
one kind of like way that you can know it's doubt is there's this feeling of like this hesitation or vacillation or
I'm doing this with my hands going around and around in circles because there's this uh way in which we feel
like we're not really going anywhere we're just feeling kind of stuck and we're just
maybe moving around with a trying to like in Lost in our thoughts
and figure things out and thinking about them and and one of the consequence of
this of this well I don't know is should I do this is this the right practice or
maybe it shows up in some particular way when you're um sitting down for meditation you like oh gee yeah I'm kind
of agitated may maybe I'll um just count my breaths to really get uh settled and
then you realize oh gee I can only get to number two well maybe I'll do some loving kindness practice and then you do
loving kindness for a few minutes and then you think okay well I don't want to do Ling kindness I'm just going to open it up and do open awareness and oh that
sound oh that dog I can't believe that dog is barking again I'm going to write a nasty note to the neighbor maybe I'll
go do that now no I'm not going to okay I'm going to go back to meta practice so we spend our whole time really just going from one practice to another to
another to another and never really settle down so that could be a way in which this doubt shows up too is like
not really knowing which practice to do and instead we're just doing trying to put out uh perceived
fires so doubt is I would say it's rarely recognized as doubt initially
it's just seen as agitation or some kind of way or this uh or maybe agitation or
hesitation maybe there's a holding back or
a way in which we're not really engaged with what's happening this is one of the
consequences of Doubt is we're no longer really present with what's happening
instead we're lost in thoughts in fact we could say that doubt is a loose
collection of a family of thoughts that they're not onward leading instead
they're just uh we're just kind of like stuck when going round and
round so here how can we work with it how can we work with doubt whatever kind of doubt that it is one if you can
recognize what's happening just like oh I'm I'm uh kind
of feeling stuck here I'm or hesitant or vacillating or something like
this maybe there's this feeling of going in circles or hesitation or maybe there's some confusion or or maybe
there's a way in which doubt can get activated as a consequence of maybe just
touching into something that's uncomfortable like maybe there's just a
tiny bit of like a little bit of loneliness sadness
Despair and then this a lot of anger rather than feeling the despair loneliness will jump over into doubt
it's like oh this practice I'm not sure what to do and it turns out often we use this type of Doubt to distract us from
something else that's really uncomfortable this is what humans do
right we don't like to feel uncomfortable so we avoid and part of the avoidance is distraction right we
have Untold ways to distract ourselves and then when we distract ourselves with doubt we start to feel like no I'm doing
important spiritual work here when in fact we're just just going around and around in circles and not being with uh
whatever is uncomfortable so one thing to do is just
recognize what's happening recognize either the velation or recognize oh yeah
there is that flicker of something that I really don't want to see or experience you can be just recognize
either whichever is uh available to you at that moment chances are it'll be most likely the doubt if you don't want to
feel this difficult uncomfortable experience that's happening and then can you just allow it
to be there can you just allow it to be there I'm talking about this vacillation
that's happening what if we don't make it be a problem I'm talking it as a hindrance
but what if we just say oh yeah there's this feeling like I'm don't really know
what to do I'm not even sure if I can practice and just allow it to be there
and how we can allow it to be there is to feel it in the body feel it in the body all these types
of thoughts they have sematic signatures they have a physical correlates they may
be subtle they may be obvious there this way that can we get out of the abstract
thinking and philosophizing and trying to figure something out and instead just
feel it in the body feel the maybe it's restlessness or
uncomfortableness or this sense of not really knowing I noticed like I'm like foring my brow like I'm not sure what to
do maybe we feel there's some tension in the face maybe we feel like that um
often there can be tightness in the mouth or the jaw that we can be doing when we're like
trying to figure something out or make it be a little bit different or maybe
there's a sense of heaviness maybe like the shoulders feel kind of heavy and we feel like
H really am I going to do this you know there's or something like this to allow
it to be there and one way we can do that is to feel it in the body maybe there's a jitteriness this restlessness
really wanting something different to happen this feeling like oh I I want to get up off the
cushion and if you feel like I I can't I'm not quite sure what you're talking about or I just can't be with the bodily
experience there's a reason why I'm in the head is because I don't want to be with my bodily
experience then we can say well is there a way that you can relax the
body just notice the way that you're sitting maybe your shoulders are up near
your ears or is there a way that you can relax the body and then maybe take a big
inhale and then with the exhale there's a way maybe just follow the breath into
the bodily experience and just feel the breath and
you'll feel like maybe the shoulders the chest and the belly and it turns out this is where
most of our emotions or our experiences you know in the Torso and the face in
the front of the body the face throat chest belly and often that's where the
breath is too so if we're feeling really disconnected and we can't feel the sensations in the body you just take a
breath and follow the breath into the body and that can be a way that can help
uh bring the awareness into the bodily
experience so it doesn't matter this bodily experience where it is it doesn't
matter what it is it doesn't matter why it's there it doesn't matter whether it's a
identifiable emotion or something like that but instead it's this movement
towards actually just being with our experience whatever that experience is
and this is the practice and then the second thing to do
I'm saying just to allow it to be there so first to feel it in the body and then the second is to remind yourself or that
thoughts are just thoughts they're just thoughts how many thoughts a day do we
have how many of them do we remember how many of them just arise and uh they just
pass away I heard uh written uh in a
book uh this I think the book was published some time ago and I just stumbled upon this and it was uh
somebody talking about uh they were like doing their all their thoughts out loud
were on paper it was hilarious because they were uh driving and they were
trying to decide you know what to have for dinner and they were like should I have this I don't know do I like that
and I don't know the last time I had it was terrible and then you would hear them say get out of the way buddy where
didd you learn how to drive you know and then it was just funny to look at we
think that we have like clear thoughts but we have so many thoughts about all kinds of stuff all the time so working
with doubt allowing them to be there feel them in the body and remind ourselves
thoughts are just thoughts we don't have to believe them they're insubstantial of course
they are like what are they they there's there're don't have any inherent existence and they're not uh
something that we can uh grab onto and hold or something like
this but some of the thoughts that we have we might not be recognizing them as
thoughts there might be some of these subtle thoughts of like it shouldn't be this
way it should be different that's just a thought or why is this happening to me
that's just a thought can we can just let him go or or I don't deserve this
you know maybe we have this idea that it should be better because uh we've been meditating for so long or because of
whatever reason we feel like we should have better experiences or maybe like I can't handle
this maybe we're bored we feel like oh we can't handle boredom or maybe we're feeling restless and something like this
these are just thoughts you'll have other thoughts you know the next moment
maybe some of them get stuck on repeat for a little bit but there's just there'll be other thoughts or maybe if
not those thoughts that I said maybe there would be um the maybe they're like these thoughts
from a childhood when you've had some difficulty and maybe there's a flash of something that feels like oh yeah I've
had this thought my whole life that doesn't make it more substantial it
makes it more familiar but we want to give it Authority we don't have to give it
Authority there's a way in which you know we can tend to get identified with our thoughts but we don't need to be
there's this way in which thoughts can actually uh be a type of a prison a type
of a way in which they really trap us into a certain identity about who we are
or who the world is and how things should be I'm not saying we shouldn't have those thoughts but not allow them
to uh get stuck to get stuck there just to arise that all allow them to arise
and then pass away and then as soon as you recognize
that they are thoughts then there's an opportunity to turn back against to the physical experience you might be having
a similar physical experience that you had before maybe something
different and so this way of like undermining the authority of the
thoughts by turning towards your physical experience interrupting the momentum of
thinking chances are you will not want to do this chances are there will be
some resistance to go towards the bodily experience instead there might be these
types of thoughts of like oh I I have to figure this out I have to think about it in some
kind of way to make it better or I have to solve this problem this is often this
thought is often not so clearly articulated this way but it's a belief it's a view that we have that's fueling
these types of thoughts or maybe we have this thought like I have to find a way to make this stop and we think we're
going to be able to think our way into having different thoughts but it doesn't
work that way instead just be with the physical
experience the thoughts won't stop right away but they'll just start running out
of momentum they'll just start running out of authority they'll just start
becoming less interesting and instead we can just be with our bodily
experience and then once you're with those bodily experience nothing needs to be
done nothing needs to be done chances are there'll be resistance to this idea
also because we have to figure it out we want to make something happen and but
this whole idea of like no just be with what's
happening maybe it's a lump in the throat because you I don't even know why
because for me sometimes when I'm like tuning into the bodily experience I often have a some tightness in the
throat this or sometimes I mentioned earlier the heaviness in the shoulders
or the shoulders are up near the ears or there's a sense of heaviness and can we just bring some
kindhearted curiosity to that experience and then here we are are in
the heart of practice in the heart of practice we're just being with our
experience without um having to like gone is this feeling like okay I have to
fix it instead it's like oh it's like this right now there's a lump in the
throat and now there's a this feeling of
tightness in the shoulders and pressure against the body where I'm sitting and know just being with the
felt experience so working with doubt and I
would say such a big part about practice whether it's about doubt or anything else is just really learning to
distinguish between thoughts and physical
Sensations so often we're lost in thought and disconnected from our bodies disconnected from our physical
experience but just dropping into Sensations is always valuable always
valuable because that's what's happening that's actually the truth of the
moment and then as we learn to drop into our physical Sensations and tune into
the truth of the moment there's this way that the thinking will just naturally
start to quiet down it'll just happen naturally and then there can be a way in
which there's maybe this feeling of the senses being cleansed in some kind of way like
we can hear a little bit more clearly see a little bit more clearly feel a
little bit more clearly when the thinking starts to quiet down then the experiences of the
senses become more clear and then we can start to see
things as they are not so much what we're projecting onto them the sense of
whether I like it or I don't like it whether this is mine or not or whether this is going to help me or not or all
these subtle things that we're projecting onto all the objects out there including
people as the quiet as we start to pay attention to the body the thinking
quiets down there's a brightness that comes to our experience start to see things closer to
how they are and we start to notice Beauty in a way that wasn't possible
before when we're just busy with what's happening kind like some of the radiance
of the beauty of just ordinary things starts to
arise and we start to see oh yeah things are changing that sound arose of the born
and now it's gone I that sensation of the pressure
against the body that wasn't I'm was didn't notice it and now I notice it
again then as we start to notice things are changing then there's no longer a
feeling of stuckness but not only that there's a
feeling of oh I I kind of feel like myself as this
stable consistent thing that's constant but then we just start
to notice oh yeah there's just all these experiences happening and that starts to loosen up
this idea of a fixed self to which all experience is happening and when that
happens there starts to be much more freedom much more ease and freedom so in this way having
doubt this feeling of like I don't know can be really The Way
Forward just this way of like well can we recognize that it's happening and
just allow it to be there allow it to be the physical
Sensations and to notice some of the thoughts that are there and remember
that okay thoughts are just thoughts we don't have to ascribe a truth to them we
don't have to ascribe nontruth to them can we just let them do what thoughts do they just come and go come and go come
and go we'll want to grab on to them as best you can can you be with
your bodily experience instead and then you're right in there with
practice starting to see things as they really are not without all the stories
without all the I'll just use that word stories we start to see the beauty we start to see
how things are changing and this is practice and this is where we find
Freedom this is where we find Freedom and so I talked I said about how
this poem v v not exactly sure how to
pronounce it is um that Maddie weast wrote was inspired
by these Awakening poems from these nuns these women and in the original
Awakening poem that inspired mad West here she does become awakened the poem
ends with her becoming awakened it starts with in general with
her having difficulties in going to a nun and the nun giving her instructions and then she becomes awakened in M Wanga
poem we don't see the Awakening but uh for me I feel touched that uh in the
original poem that's there so here's Med one guasp
again when everyone else was meditating I'd be outside circling the
hall finally I went to confess I am hopeless I said the Elder
nun smiled just keep going she said nothing stays in orbit
forever if this circling is all you have why not make this circling your
home I did as she told me and went on circling the hall if you find yourself partly in and
partly out if you find yourself drawn to this path and also drawing away I can
assure you you're in good company just keep going sometimes the most direct path
isn't a straight line and I'll stop there there and open
it up to see if there's some questions or comments thank
you this idea of
circling and doubt and turning what can be a hindrance into the way that leads to
Freedom peace Awakening that's the importance of paying
attention to our bodily experience even though that's often what we don't want to do and certainly we have a culture
that uh like fetishizes the body and and but the mind is uh you know held up in
high highly of course it is right it helps solve problems create beautiful
things I mean the mind is a beautiful thing but there's this way we can get trapped thinking that it's the only way
forward
yes all right uh is it on yeah um I guess my doubt mostly shows up
in the form of um feeling that maybe other people can have these experiences
that I've heard of but uh I don't seem to be able to get there kind of thing
that um or that maybe people are having having these experiences
because they somehow believe in in these experiences and and
uh um and maybe I'm I'm just not capable of
of doing that of that that kind of belief you know you hear of these things of meditative states of you know deep
calm and and that kind of thing and uh yeah I guess I guess my doubt is
more along the lines of not believing that I can achieve what other people can
achieve um I wonder if you can speak to that well I'll say a few things about
some of these meditative states that um it just seems and I've I talked to a number of Dharma teachers about this and
certainly in my role as a Dharma teacher I've seen this too that some people have
uh little bit their minds work in such a way that they can get settled a little
bit easier and some people they can't and often this has to do not always but
sometimes like with how we spend our time if you're like uh an office manager
or a preschool teacher or running a household with a lot of things happening
then you're having to take care of this and so many things all at once and your mind is really good at going like this to one thing to the next thing as
opposed to if you're a mathematician or a theoretical physicist who sits and
thinks and focuses so just you know how we've trained our brains with our livelihoods
or how our families are has shows up and the Beautiful part is that we don't have
to have particular meditative States we don't have to have them for the for
certainly for the uh first stage of Awakening you don't it's you don't have to have you know some of these really
concentrated States so I'll just say that some people's minds you know just
have different uh capacities whether they're born that way I have no idea but
it can be um just how they spend their
time and then the second is I'll just say this for myself that uh my
meditation really took a shift uh where I could settle more when two things
happened one Retreat practice but it wasn't Retreat practice alone it had to
be Retreat practice that included walking meditation there was I I thought
like walking meditation that's recess you know I don't know that's just a break but it was something when I
started to really uh be attentive to
walking meditation and kind like being really embodied that way I don't know
then it really carried over into my sitting practice and and allowed me to
be more embodied for the sitting practice um concentration turns out to
be a lot about uh being embodied and not only that it allows a person to like to
do a Sit walk sit right or or you know all day long with uh some mindfulness I
don't know is is this helpful uh some of these things yes thank you you're welcome
yeah so maybe we'll end with the here
s thanks for the talk I think it um gave me a lot to think about um I think at some point you had
mentioned um between thoughts and emotions they have something called like
somatic signature or something that phrase um is it do you find it or I'm trying to
think about it as like um an object to meditate on like trying
to um whether it's a emotion a feeling like
how is it interacting with my body during a meditation I wonder if like that's
helpful being able to like parse out these sematic signatures or is the idea
that you know even that's kind of too far we should just feel our body and not
not try and name these and map the signatures but I was trying to
understand how to I guess meditate on that but yeah yeah this is a great question thank you I would say uh it
doesn't have to be so complicated I would just feel what there is to feel and we don't necessarily have to use
words because sometimes if we use words and trying to when I say sematic signature maybe that or map it to that
does feel like a cogni activity so maybe that's I should use different language but it's just like just feel and maybe
you don't have exact words sometimes I know in the beginning I used words to kind of help me stay there like feels
tight contracted feels uh congealed you know
just to help me stay there but as I got more accustomed to just hanging out with
Sensations than the words kind of uh kind of went away but uh in the
beginning sometimes it's useful to use adjectives or yeah Des
scriptures as opposed as just a way to kind of like help the Mind
stay is that helpful very helpful thank you you're welcome you're
welcome okay so thank you all for your kind attention and I wish you all a
wonderful evening thank you