oh hello everyone so lovely to be with you I've missed you I've missed you I've been
teaching a uh Retreat a 10day retreat um at Spirit Rock and uh it was sweet it's
always sweet to to sit with
practitioners really giving their heart to a um period of of retreat dedic this
sense of dedication offering our heart up and I was thinking of you I I um was
actually sharing this morning in the closing Circle in the um know closing
ceremony um sharing about happy hour and and how really delighted and happy this
s makes me and uh whether or not folks who come to to happy are as we know as
you have been coming consistently for a long time the the Transformations that practicing in this
way in this daily way this doesn't have to be a dedicated Retreat as beautiful
as that is and and as wonderful as that form is this is another form this is a way to really integrate um these heart
practices beautiful heart practices into our daily lives perhaps you come with a
heavy heart or a mind that's really reeling from what happened today
interpersonally or the news of the world and really the the work that we do the practice that we
do day by day by day by day it's um it's so heartwarming and astounding um the
the Transformations that it has brought about for for each and every one of us
so I'm very grateful to the S so with that in mind I want to um lead
a guided meditation tonight for good good will
for for Community Goodwill gratitude for Community as a resource as a resource we
don't do this practice alone if you were just you know doing this practice alone
on your own it would be very different not as supported not as supportive
as um coming together either on Zoom or on YouTube knowing others are practicing
with you or perhaps if you listen later on on the recording just trusting having
the sense that oh there are other practitioners who are practicing with you the sa this community that that um
is committed to cultivating a Kinder gentler more compassionate world one
heart at a time to transform our own Hearts so so that's the invitation and also the last
thing to say we know that when we wish well when we have good will for others
um that makes us happy it's it's it's a happy making process it's the more we
give the more we give of Our Kind kindness the more we have the more
goodwi and and joy we have so that's the that's the theme it's good willll and
meta for the s for others for the community which includes by the way us
because we're part of it we're doing this practice so so with that I want to invite you to settle in your meditation
posture whatever it might be landing
arriving feeling your feet on the
earth Sensations feeling settled as if you were a well-rooted tree
feeling connected to the Earth connected upright feeling your sit
Bones on the chair and the
cushion inviting the body to relax to offer its
weight to the chair to the cushion via the bones to the Earth whilea the
feet the legs as we invite the body to relax also
inviting the body to be upright sense
of sitting like a mountain relaxed spacious stable
and feel for yourself what what it's like to sit like a mountain [Music]
stable tall and yet
relaxed we don't associate agitation with mountains what do you associate
with the
mountains can you embody
one can you be a mountain part of a mountain range
and feeling the breath relaxing feeling the breath in the
abdomen breathing in and breathing out
and receiving the breath just taking some minutes to receive the breath and to
settle
e
e e
feeling feeling ourselves in our seat taking our
seat taking our seat feeling our bodies in our seat on this
Earth taking our seat on this Earth feeling our breath
move through this
body
e e
and now see yourself feel
yourself it's a part of this interconnected network of practitioners
even if you're just starting this practice the first time you sat down and hearing this guidance
you're still a practitioner and you're part of this network of of human beings
who practice to cultivate a Kinder
calmer more beautiful heart and mind you're part of this network you're a
mountain part of the mountain range feeling feeling yourself
interconnected you're not separate you are not separate absolutely
not feel the sense of inter inter connection other
practitioners those you know those you don't know this web this large web of humanity
interconnected some you know perhaps some you don't feel feel you taking your place in
this interconnected web
see what comes up in your
heart madees a sense of appreciation of being in this network
whether or not I acknowledge it usually but I am every one of us is
and wishing well wishing well for this for this web of humanity for all these
humans we all these beings may all of us
practitioners this community of people supporting one
another in seen and unseen ways may all of us
feel safe and
protected may all of us be
happy have joy in our hearts as much as possible be joyful may we be
joyful may we practice joyfully happily
may we be healthy in our bodies have as much health as possible
may we be strong and may all of us have Ease on
this path of wholesome cultivation of
goodness you can use all the phrases of met if you like or just use one or two
phrases simple phrases may all of us have ease may all
of us be happy may all of us be
well knowing that you are part of this network
people who are dedicated to goodness to peace to
ease those who sit meditation retreats in silence those who don't past present
future may all of us be
well may all of us practice happily cultivate well-being with ease
see which phrases of Goodwill work for you to open and expand your heart in
your own way
and for those those of you on Zoom who have a sense of the gallery view you all
these fellow practitioners from around the world you bring a mental image of that
to your mind to your heart for a
moment and let your heart be
brightened may all of us be well may all of us have EAS may all of us be
happy practice well practice happily e
maybe individual members of the community come up in your heart wish them
well if that's the case or just the community this web invisible web of
connection
e e
if you want to stay with the web of practitioners you're
part of that's fine and if your heart feels like expanding it to all beings
may all of us beings may all of us be well have goodness in our
lives however we're trying to do our best in the world even if our best looks
like a mess still may all of us have ease and
wellbeing and goodness sharing your good
will unconditionally may all beings be
well may all beings whatever their
circumstance of happiness health e
safety seeing that human life life is tough for
everyone may all of us have ease as much as
possible and if that feels too Grand then come back come back to just the
community wherever it feels easiest not complicated wherever it feels
easiest maybe it's easiest to be with yourself or just a
friend perhaps a practitioner friend or just a supportive friend that's okay too
where whatever it's
easiest
e
e e
and as we approach the end of this meditation
period feel in your heart the moment of connection
joy gladness happiness any goodness any moment of goodness that might might have Arisen
during this period even if it was just one moment of gladness reconnect with
that reconnect with this planting seeds of goodness
appreciation gratitude Goodwill whatever the flavor might
be and trusting that we're planting seeds that will flower in their own
time seeds of goodness together in this vast Garden of
humanity and dedicating the goodness of our co-creator of of our practice
together this co-created goodness the benefit of all beings
everywhere whether or not they're practitioners doesn't matter to all beings everywhere unconditional Goodwill
may all things be happy may all things be free including ourselves
[Music]
thank you everyone a sweet very
sweet yeah so um yeah we have some time
now maybe I'll I'll share reflection first so uh it's quite quite sweet to
for me to to feel into this invisible web that I usually don't think about and
consider and just wishing well wishing goodness for all these beings we're
cultivating and and for my mind and my practice support tonight is you know for me it started with with our sa here um
tonight and just the sense of us being together I I have picture of many of you
on Zoom you know the the Zoom Square it's like oh yeah here's this community coming together and this Goodwill and
for for me to be included and then all the people on The Retreat that I just had with all my fellow uh co-teachers
and then it just kepts expanding all the people I've ever taught or or practiced
with over the years and it just it just kept expanding wow wow so much goodness
so much support and then beyond all of humanity was very sweet
feeling into that the goodness of that for me the appreciation and and work the
Good Will of all these practitioners all of us doing this practice for the
benefit of not just ourselves but all beings it's really moving really
moving so I want to invite us to um engage with with sharing um a few words
perhaps how was this practice for us uh was there moment oh yeah so so the question I want to give you and I'll do
my own practice report on that is I asked you if there was a moment of gratitude joy happiness as you
practicing or Goodwill and for me there were many and and one in particular was
considering all the it just occurred to me all the people that I've taught uh or
connected I think I've taught more than a 100 retreats in person so so many people that I've met in person over
thousands of people uh by now so it just I was struck by wow this so lovely all
of us so many people over time um yeah it was a moment of wow this is quite a
vast Network that that this being is in interconnected with in this practice
just really brought a lot of joy for me so so I want to invite you to connect
with one another because now you're going to be in small groups in small
small SAS in in small you know four people three four people uh communities
of at first when you enter the the zoom room uh to just start with a moment of
maybe maybe a a few moments of silence and just wishing each other well just seeing all the zoom or if somebody's on
the phone the phone number like oh yeah wishing each other well wishing each other well um so starting by maybe just
a 30 seconds of wishing each other well um how sweet is that and maybe greeting
each other by well wishing wishing you well may you have ease just literally may you have ease may you have happiness
so and so just um and then if you like you can share what um there was a moment
of Joy or aha or or gratitude or or something that that came up for you if
you want to share and if you're distracted if you fell asleep that's perfect perly fine too that's a
perfectly fine fine uh practice report and I put in mea that we practice with
and just to always reiterate especially for new folks that our um small group
practice is continuation of our our um sitting
practice mindfully speaking listening embracing compassion kindness if any re
reactivity or reactions come up internally externally stay on the topic
that I gave you so first greeting each other uh first first silence just for a few seconds doing silent metaphor one
another and then greeting each other with Goodwill and kindness and then if you want to share if you want to go in
alphabetical order uh first name sharing just one thing that came up uh if
something and if not it's okay you can say pass no problem um and then taking
turns briefly saying one thing briefly making sure everybody has a chance to say something and not giving it advice
not interrupting staying with the order and yeah that's basically it and
enjoying each other really enjoying um the small groups tonight especially as
as an aspect of community these are your fellow practitioners this is what I was talking about it's it's exactly this
these fellow practitioners so I am going to uh
open the rooms and take care of yourself take
care of each other here we go hello everyone welcome back the rooms
are closed and we have a few minutes for
Reflections questions comments um yeah the floor is open any thoughts how was
this practice what what came up as you silently did meta in small groups for
each other and then um G each other perhaps with kindness Goodwill and
then shared or heard each other's practice discussions a practice uh just
got practice reports I'm still on Retreat mode practice reports what
happened oh and I'm going to open chat too if you want to put it in chat you're
welcome to can also raise your hand
and if in chat if you write it to me privately I will read your reflection not your name and if you uh write it
publicly I'll read both your name and your reflection any practice reports you like
to share for the benefit of the
community and May you're so chilled you don't feel like talking
Barbara well I just uh that I really appreciated this
particular meditation tonight because it was uh thanks to my Sana friend where I
was like ah I'm here helping uh uh you
know uh a medical emergency and all this and I'm stressed and he said Nick's in
five minutes and I was like oh boy I'm so
there so there you go a oh that's sweet
thanks for sharing this I I didn't quite um catch earlier that you share that you're visiting family in an emergency
situ situation yeah to to help out with with care ah oh holding you dear Barbara
with care and your family and and so glad you're here yeah thank goodness for
for support for community support for for practitioners and you know all of us
we're walking each other home we're just walking each other home all of us yeah
thank you Nikki yeah thank you Barra glad you're here you can join us and
hope this meditation this being with community supports you so that you can
support uh your family beautiful yeah holding you holding you in our hearts
yeah thank you yeah thank
yeah and [Music]
Diana um I had this weird possibly negative um
thing going on um in terms I was feeling connected when you
talked about taking our part or taking our place that's what it was uh but I
tended to not feel a a group I couldn't I somehow it
came to me that there's this group almost like a professional group or something and I and where that came from
so I decided to uh just be with people because I always think of this group as people I
see all the various people up there and I see them as individuals and uh feel very close that
way so because somehow in my head there was some sort of a group label thing
going on and so I decided to approach it more individually and then also uh
offered meta for my small group in my in my hometown here as well for myself
because I wasn't I wasn't feeling my group is a group or something
I don't know TR how to put it yeah what I'm appreciating in what you're
describing Diana is you know how mind was creating some blocks and and you
just worked with it okay that that feels funny okay fine I'll try this okay that works that's sweet cool so this is great
that's exactly right that's what happen that's that's what it is it's our minds finding ways to make the practice work
even though part of the mind like nope not that not that that doesn't work I so
beautiful thanks for sharing this this is great love it thank you um I see one
reflection sent to me anonymously Unfortunately today my mind and heart was filled with sadness for for lack of
love I'm feeling where I am now with family then I realized I need to appreciate what I have but still heart
is heavy one of those days I guess yeah thank you for for sharing that and and
what I appreciate in your in your uh practice report is you know it is what
it is right the the the the way that you're holding it is well it is one of those days right it's not like it's the
end of the world it's just one of those days there are some days like this and it's okay it's all right it's like this
so meeting it meeting the heaviness of the heart heart with honesty with vulnerability and and also
with equinity it's one of those days and also with with um realizing that yeah
there is goodness maybe there's some challenges in the family Dynamics family
situation and there is heaviness and being underneath that heaviness is the
need to connect is the need to have more love so that's beautiful so appreciate that and um also appreciating that there
there is goodness it's not all difficulty and challenge all the time um even though that might seem predominant
so I'm appreciating how you're working with it and and um it's um yeah bringing
more equinity and appreciation to what is uh and also meeting uh inviting you
to meet the heaviness of the heart with compassion oh sweetheart this is hard
yeah it's hard to have challenges conflict um difficulty lack
of care or in a family Dynamic it's okay honey may may I have ease may all of us
family family members who are entangled with one another in this way may all of
us have ease all of us are doing our best and our best looks like this mess and it's okay it's all right honey this
is hard this is hard it's okay so meeting it with compassion is what I
invite um you to practice with you are welcome said thank you the
person who wrote that you're welcome
so any other Reflections questions practice
reports going once going
twice okay great so let's let's close if there are
no other Reflections questions um yeah and this time the holiday especially
with with uh Christmas in the US next week There's A Time families coming
together and sometimes it's joyous and sometimes it's challenging and it's part
of Being Human so so yeah appreciating appreciating
ourselves for showing up for doing our best to cultivate to plant seeds of
kindness Goodwill for ourselves and for others in this in this world may all of
us have ease may all of us be free may all of us have goodness as much goodness
as possible in our lives thank you for your practice everyone may may all of us
be well
thank you so much