welcome welcome everybody happy Eclipse day right this a
amazing thing that happened over there in another part of the United
States it's kind of a such an unusual thing it makes me wonder you know
thousands of years ago the how they explained something like this like how
could they like how would you explain something like this if you didn't un know all the astrology
astronomy I don't think knowing astrology would help you much
but so today I wanted to talk a little bit about this idea of coming home to
ourselves coming home to ourselves this idea that uh this home
inside of us a place that has a sense of ease sense of maybe some safety and
that's a home that no one can take away from us it's always there and yet we are often not there
this place inside of us that um is
welcoming and has a sense of belonging and there's a way that no
matter what is happening around us that this is you know always available and it's always
there but we're not always connected to it we're not always
home if we want to use this language kind of like home this maybe um I don't know about
all of you but when I'm home I'm relaxed and I tend to be you know doing what I
want to do and wearing clothes that I only wear at home
you know it's just being comfy so there's this way of you know just this feeling like being who we really are
being authentic and not trying to impress anybody else or you know just uh
being ourselves for some people when they get home there's a sense of I know that uh when I worked in
Corporate America this would be like this thing that when I would come home from work with like okay I've changed my
clothes out of my professional clothes and into whatever I was going to wear to lounge around in the
evening and there was this sense of you know changing of the clothes was like oh okay now I can be a little bit more
relaxed can be who I am in some kind of way but when there's this uh sense of
being home there's a sense of there's nowhere that we need to go there's nowhere else that we need to be going to
or there's nothing else that we need to be then we can just be here we can just
be here in this moment so coming home to ourselves is
related to mindfulness being present for what's actually
happening as opposed to being lost in thought or you know in fantasies or
planning and so what are some of the ways in which we kind like abandon or like leave this abandon ourselves or
leave this home I'm using home just as a you know a nice way to point to a place
that feels comfortable and familiar inside of us even if it's not as
comfortable and familiar as we would like it to be maybe it's as comfortable and familiar as it might be is than
other places than when we're out in public for
example so what are some of the ways in which we abandon ourselves using this kind of as a maybe strong language to AB
AB in ourselves but what is this some of the ways in which we really start to orient outside of ourselves instead of
like staying here with what our experience is and part of that is just
very simply because we're experiencing difficulties whatever those difficulties
might be something minor like okay I can't figure out how to fix the
dishwasher that's uh not doing what it's supposed to do or or they're having some
really emotional difficulties like feeling really sad or
angry or having difficulty in our personal intimate relationships and so there's this way
and when there's often when there's difficulties there's the Mind kicks in and says oh I have to figure it out and
it starts to like go outside and it starts to um engage with things and want
to find a solution look up a YouTube video on instructions
on how to do fix that dishwasher or whatever it might be but that's not the only thing that
happens when we start to look outside ourself we start to look for answers but often we start to blame
to there's these difficulties and it's something outside of there it's that's
fault that person that entity that
situation as a way and then we kind of like get disconnected from ourselves because then all the energy goes out
there there's a maybe a strong sense of self-righteousness I'm right be but that
thing over there is wrong but that's not really a
comfortable feeling maybe it feels energizing this self-righteousness for a
bit but there's a way and also it feels um kind of like alienating or it's like
you're hiding behind this uh shield and getting all puffed up and it just takes
so much energy and to maintain this uh
self-righteousness is uh not a comfortable way to live one's life it's not a good way it's for goes
forward so maybe that's one reason why we kind of abandon ourselves why we're no longer home is because we're having
difficulties and we're either looking for Solutions outside of oursel or we're blaming something outside of of ourselves but either way we're kind of
like disconnected from ourselves or maybe it's nothing like difficulties maybe it's just uh We've um
gained this habit that our culture our society our family our education so
often likes to promote and that is like oh let's go chase the next shiny
thing let's uh have attainments or let's have accomplish ments or let's go get
whatever the advertisers want to convince us that we need or whatever our phones tell us that we should do or
something like that so it can just be a habit to always be like striving and
looking trying to get something or it can just maybe it's like
just literally buy something but any in either way it's also again this way in
which we are oriented outside of ourselves kind of being disconnected from this
home this uh place of spaciousness and stability
inside and then another reason why we might be a little bit like disconnected
from ourselves is maybe being
present for the moment and for ourselves is a let down maybe it's kind
of disappointing nothing nothing exciting here I'm just sitting here and we're so used
to right you know having this like something entertaining or interesting or
engaging in some kind of way and so on the surface to just be with our
experience maybe it feels boring
oh it's just like this but there's this way in which we
are when we can gain um maybe having some deeper attention some deeper
connection to ourselves that's when it starts to become so rich and
so um rewarding and delightful but it's often not that way
at the beginning in fact if when we start like with a mindfulness practice and we start turning towards ourselves
in the beginning it's really disappointing we start to see all this stuff about oursel that
we wish we didn't see all our bad habits we can't really
ignore them anymore or all the ways maybe that we have um
unskillfully harmed ourselves or harmed others we start to see that more
clearly and so then maybe we just want to like oh that's really uncomfortable and so we like jump out and distract
ourselves with uh what's on a screen or something like this
because there can be a way in which this inner critic can be really vicious and
mean when we start to see and I know for me that was uh when I started my
practice I you know I thought I was a pretty good person but I just started to see all these ways in which I wasn't
really showing up for my friends the ways that I was you know
telling Little White Lies and these ways that I was was always thinking like oh
yeah I'll I'll try more later like not quite engaging with
things with my life or something and no wonder I felt kind of like dis
uh I didn't have contentment with my life discontent was because I was kind of
like oh yeah later all engag but right now I don't know I don't even know what
I was doing actually but just wasn't Eng engaged with my
life and then when we start a mindfulness practice when we start showing up for ourselves it can be a
wakeup call I think I it might have been Gil
fronal I'm not sure who said something along the lines of like
um all self all self- understanding is not necessarily good
news so that could be another reason why we don't often are connected to ourselves because especially if our like
as I said is our inner critic is kind of vicious but there's this way in which
connecting to coming home to and making friends with ourselves is so important
it's so important but in contrast many of us believe that uh self-criticism is
this is an appropriate strategy for success and you know it works until it
doesn't it works you know a certain amount we can beat ourselves up be mean
to ourselves for a certain while but then it comes at a
price and a lifelong of this self-criticism the price can get
high the price can be that makes us anxious and makes us a not want to try
new things or take any risks because if we have this inner critic that's really
harsh we know that if we fail or we don't do it perfectly we'll just beat up ourselves up we'll berate ourselves for
quite some time so we don't try new things we don't take risks we don't
learn new things and then our life gets smaller and smaller and smaller just
only staying with those things in which we feel like we have some expertise in or feel familiar and
comfortable so the inner critic makes us anxious and our life turns and become smaller but it also has us be kind of
like U dissatisfied with our life this way in which not being connected and feeling like nothing's quite
right always something is wrong it also can contribute to a sense
of um being disconnected from others cuz if we are beating ourselves up so much and we think that we're so bad we don't
want anybody else to know how bad we are so we're hiding hiding behind a armor or
a shield or
something but so many of us feel like okay well we need this inner critic to
motivate ourselves I've talked about this a number of times a number of different
talks and a number of different contexts we have this kind of like convoluted
sense of self-care like okay I have to be mean to myself beat myself
up say mean names to myself so that I can do things in an
appropriate way or do do
well and so there's this way in which um
we might with this self-criticism we start to um have this this expression
this a lowgrade fever of self-doubt and then we start to feel
like not only we disconnected from ourselves but disconnected from
everything really feel like well maybe I don't belong here this famous impostor
syndrome or If people really knew me maybe they wouldn't be
okay so often what happens is we try to engage in this game of trying to
convince ourselves that actually we're okay we're okay and it's astounding like
how this is like such a common strategy that uh many of us have in fact you might say this is a lot of what humans
do is they going around kind of like I'm okay I'm okay and everybody's like
projecting they're okay they're okay they're okay but inside everybody's like you know what I'm kind of struggling a
little bit here whether it's they struggling a lot or just a little
bit so we engage in this game of trying to convince ourselves otherwise we try
to say the right things or look the right way or do the right things or be
at the right place or be with the right people or something like this is a way to reassure ourselves with this because
we have this lowgrade fever of self-doubt and then other people they have this low-grade fever or self-doubt
and they're doing the same thing too and it kind of gets normalized this uh way
of showing up in the
world so maybe we have this idea is like well people like me so I must be
okay but that really Rel on what's happening out there not on what's
happening in here in our hearts and in our
minds or maybe we have this uh you know I have a lot of professional success I'm
a good student uh my house is uh beautiful the grass is green or the
house is neat and tidy or beautiful or whatever it is I have all these things so I must be okay and we try to convince
ourselves of this and it doesn't last for very long
or there's always something right it's so it's never like okay now that I got my house perfect I oh I still
kind of feel the same I have a certain amount of professional success oh I feel kind of the same I need I need more
professional success that's a little bit of my story that when I was in Corporate America I
had a fantastic job I had a great job and I felt like um oh I'm still not
so happy I I thought that's what was needed you know to have this uh have a good job
or something like this and uh I thought well my professional life is not going to get any better than
this or not much better than this so there has to be something else has to be
something else and I left Corporate America not really knowing what I was going to do and I was
all these years ago and found myself
here so instead is there's this way that we can this journey it might be a
journey of like coming home and connecting to ourselves and
then here's the sometimes the tricky part in a friendly
way in a warm-hearted way in an open spacious
way sometimes they're like well like we we connect but it's with ourselves but it's with like a sense of we have to
whip ourselves into shape somehow or that we have
to it's this big self-improvement project and okay here's everything that's wrong I guess I'll start over
here and work on it or something like that but this journey
to kind of like coming home connecting to ourselves in a friendly way and for
some of us it might be a radical idea for me it certainly was this radical
idea of like oh to be to take care of honor and respect
myself my inner life it's really
important and so this journey it goes beyond just like feeling good about
yourself because it's not based on convincing yourself of anything it's not based on convincing yourself that you're
an okay person or and it doesn't rely on acquiring more more um success more
Badges of Honor more objects material objects or whatever it might be it's not
about um accumulating more even though that's definitely the
message we get sent in uh everyday life in this society that we've created it's
definitely this promotion of more and more and more and so and this journey is so it's
not exactly the same as like increasing our self-esteem because we might say that
self-esteem is a way you kind of like judge yourself like okay I'm good I'm I'm good
enough instead it's more more about uh
having this um recognizing okay I have
difficulties and how can I meet them with
care with warmth with openness so this journey to Greater
Freedom this journey to coming home to ourselves is not pretending that
everything is fine and not comparing ourselves to others or even comparing ourselves to how we think we should be
comparing ourselves to ourselves or our younger selves or our ideal future selves but instead it's something really
different it's saying oh yeah some of this is
hard but how can I respond to this
difficulty with kindness how can I acknowledge honor and
respect this difficulty this struggle that I have with uh
understanding with care with
concern how can we meet ourselves how can we like come home with kind of often
like this idea of home is a place where it's relaxed and safe and
warm figuratively or literally
and so there's this way in which this uh this journey of coming home might begin
with a meditation practice and one is
mindfulness kind of the emphasis here at IMC and I guess here I I um don't give a
lot of mindfulness instructions I have this basic assumption that people um
know mindfulness or familiar with mindfulness practice but briefly all say it's just
know being present for what's happening as best we
can but with an attitude of warmth or care or openness or
spaciousness feels like this is Diana's of confessions here I say like for me with a mindfulness at the beginning
somehow I had this feeling cuz I so really wanted to be mindful I didn't didn't uh appreciate that I was kind of
like using like a sledgehammer kind of like on the like the breath like just I'm here you know just somehow and it
turns out all it needs to be is like NOP I'm here it's more like a feather than a sledgehammer because the
sledgehammer well maybe I'll just say this you can an indicator of like how you're practicing
mindfulness can be like how you feel when the bell rings if there's a sense
of oh thank goodness then that that could be like you're doing a little too hard this
little straining too much but if there's a sense of like oh Belle wow listen to
how it's like wavering there's the second Bell
wow and then you know opening your eyes when you're ready or maybe know some of us are
like are they ever going to ring the bell oh my goodness we've been here for 2 hours already I'm sure of
it but this journey of coming home this journey of connecting to ourselves might
begin with this meditation practice so not only mindfulness or mindfulness
where we're meeting our present moment experience and we often talk about it as
we have an anchor mindfulness practice which is often the breath and we just
you know stay on the breath the mind wanders that's what Minds do and then when we notice that it's wandering we
just simply come back to the Anchor the breath and then when it wanders again we
just keep on coming back doesn't matter how many times you have to do this it absolutely doesn't
matter and then if there's something in the body that's like really compelling or
uncomfortable some difficulty let go of the breath and just
turn towards the bodily sensation oh the knee the knee and we often we'll
look at for adjectives it's throbbing it's stabbing it's hot it's pulsing
whatever whatever is the uncomfortable sensation is and then when the mind has
either slipped off or it's no longer compelling we just come back to the
breath so mindfulness is just showing up for we have an anchor and then move to W
what's compelling so that we're never in a struggle we're never like oh with a wrestling match trying to just stay on
the breath when something else is really calling our attention and this is a way in which we
just meet whatever is arising with the some care and just being present for
it this way that we can be open to whatever arises I gave the the example
of being with the body but it could be with sounds if that's compelling the dogs barking or there's a traffic sounds
outside can be emotions it can even be
thoughts thoughts are a little bit more tricky but but is there this way that
um when we start to do this when we start to do some mindfulness and we're
being with whatever is arising there's this way that uh we discover that oh
we've been compartmentalizing ourselves like okay I'm going to try to
ignore this part of myself that I don't like and just pay attention to this part
here and then this part here that we don't like we're kind of like excise it or hoping that it'll go away if we
ignore it long enough it'll wither away or something like this but if we're just
practicing with mindfulness whatever we're trying to ignore sooner or later will become compelling it'll show up in
some kind of way and then we're trying to shove it away this won't work and
then we realize oh okay so mindfulness practice is about allowing all aspects
of ourselves even those ones that are so uh
well hidden and that might only come up when the mind is really quiet and the
body is settled and there's a way that we might
have been disconnected from some of the more subtle difficulties that we're
having and so we invite them in too this is part of way that we're coming home to
ourselves is we're inviting in all these different parts and let letting them in let
letting them come home and sit in front of the Hearth and get warm and
cozy but there's also a way in which this meditation practice is we can bring some uh what we might say some
compassion for ourselves so this is maybe I'll can use
this word care is to just this warm-hearted like oh this is what's happening for me and
it's not easy but to meet it with some openness
some warmth and some care some of you might know that loving kindness one way that we could um I'm
sorry compassion one way we can talk about compassion is that it's when loving kindness meets
difficulties so this well-wishing when it meets difficulties turns into May
these difficulties go away May these difficulties May the difficulties uh
diminish or no longer be as no longer be difficult
so this journey home this journey to connecting with ourselves may may
involve some meditation practice mindfulness but also with some compassion too because we will meet some
difficulties in ourselves that's part of how we come home as we meet all these
different places but there's something beautiful that happens with this process not only
do we come home also but helps us connect with
others connecting with ourselves helps us connect with
others when earlier I said that it's not uncommon that people are trying to
project okay I'm fine everything's fine I got it together even though inside
there might be a lot of discomfort or confusion or some difficulties or suffering but then when you start to
connect with yourself and you say oh yeah when I used to have a lot of
self-righteousness or I used to brag a lot or something like that that's because I was actually feeling kind of
awful inside is did the microwave is the microphone still okay yes it is okay
something happened just my ear maybe it's different so
the so we might recognize somebody's doing a behavior that we used to do and we did
it when we felt uncomfortable so then when we see somebody's doing a lot of
boasting we might think oh yeah they just might not be feeling good about
themselves right now they might just uh be having some difficulties and then
we're more up to connect with them we recognize okay they're just like us in
this kind of way and then of of course there's this
way in which connecting with ourselves is helps us
to there when some of us kind of like withdraw into ourselves when we are
having difficulties but when we recognize that no this is just what it means
to be a human this is part of The Human Experience then we're less likely to
with draw and try to hide and isolate and can connect with others and of
course connecting with others makes our life richer and often we learn more about
ourselves by what's getting reflected back to us by those that we spend time
around and then we might say that there's no particular endpoint to this
process of making friends with ourselves it's kind of like this there's
it's not like oh okay I'm finally done I never have to treat
myself with care again it just it's the way that we show up in the
world it's just the way that's kind of like we express
ourselves and so there's this way in which the process unfolds naturally it's just this uh this
uh unfolding that happens this way that like okay we care about
ourselves so then we have like a little more interest like what's what's because
I care like those people we care about we care about what's happening in their lives how they are what's happening and
so we start to care about ourselves and like okay what's going on here why are
you feeling agitated we might say that to somebody else but we might say to ourselves oh yeah I'm feeling agitated
what what's going on maybe there's something vague that we're not even clear
about so this process is this unfolds
naturally that leads to some greater understanding from some understanding comes some acceptance and from
acceptance Comes This Love Love for
ourself love for others and maybe just love this warmth
that shows up in so many different ways so this coming home to
ourselves is a way in which it's can be a journey and it can be this radical a
move movement this radical shift from trying to this self-improvement project
or maybe disowning parts of ourselves to this really different movement
of oh what's happening there's difficulties here how can I meet
this with kindness how can I meet this with warmth how can I meet this with care and myself instead of the usual
beating up that so many of us do not everybody not everybody does this but so many of us
do and then to help that kind of like radical shift can be the mindfulness practice as
we start to see more and more subtle difficulties as well as some heart practices maybe some some things maybe
have a formal loving kindness practice or or compassion practice and if not
just this intention to meet with warmth the difficulties that we're
experiencing so that we can be at home in front of the fire with hot cocoa and
slippers little blanket or I don't know whatever it is whatever you know for you
whatever home nice cozy home would be so this idea of coming home to
ourselves and how meditation practice can be a
support so with that I think I'll open it up to see if there's some questions
or comments uh about we were what I was speaking about something does somebody
have something they'd like to
say
well I'll start I saw a movie yesterday and it had somebody that I I
think is an early Mentor for me on self-acceptance oh it was a comedian
named Red Skelton and he some of you may have seen he was on television for about 20 years
and he was very self effacing kind of goofy guy but
just always had that sense of love and acceptance at least that was my take on
it so he was he was an important um role model Al I didn't realize it at the time
I thought he was just funny but going back and seeing a movie that he made from the early 50s reminded me of that h
that's I'm not I've heard the name but I can't bring to mind you know how he is and I'm so great to hear this that a
comedian was com mean has some self-acceptance because usually they're kind of or these days they're kind of jabbing or you know something like this
so do you want to give any example Jim about uh something like he would do or
would say or uh well it's hard for me to to
exactly remember but there there was something about how
he never jabbed like that I mean you know like he would he he would speak uh
honestly but also kindly and kind of make fun of himself
so I think that kind of making fun of oneself in a healthy and useful way I is
is important I think being able to laugh at yourself and yeah thank you for
saying that that's so important right this uh I should have spoke about that
this sense of play too right like okay we can play around or experiment and see
like okay what how I am or just playfulness in general or something like this yeah that's a good idea thank you
thank you Jim anybody else have a comment or
something they'd like to say
or hi um when you were talking about the inner
critic and I was thinking of kind of the opposite I don't know if this will make
sense anyway um I was thinking about fueling the inner critic you know
getting in habits of talking meanly which thankfully I don't do much um and
then the opposite which I've been thinking about lately when I'm in the present moment and I'm um the word that
comes up lately is satisfying so I notice like I was just
this morning looking at the light on the telephone pole you know something very mundane as the sun was coming up and it
kind of soaking in that satisfying feeling nice and um thinking of it as
like the fuel you know to notice ah this feels good and and kind of um I don't know
using that fuel and not being and and there is the thing of of not striving to
have that feeling right you know oh I want to be I want to be present you know
yeah um but when I notice that I am and it feels good or satisfying is the word
that that comes up lately I I'm kind of that's the state I'm in
lately perfect and this is so great that you're talking about because often you know we do have those moments but we're
often dismissive of them like going out trying to find you know something to solve or be entertaining or something
like this but I love this just the light on the light post or the telephone pole
or I don't know whatever it was fantastic not the same as the eclipse but but
uh thank you thank you there's somebody back there that
has my name is uh my name is Kurt and I wanted to share uh what one thing that
came up for me um Robert Duval I I really love movies and good acting and
Robert Duval to me is a terrific actor and he was you know um The Godfather all
sorts of great movies anyway he was being interviewed um on TV
by I think it might have been um oh doesn't matter but he was being
interviewed and the guy was who was interviewing him said you know um Robert
when you did this in this one particular movie you were so brilliant and you just got so
emotionally um you you were portraying this very emotional uh person and what
he said and I'll never forget what he said was and so the guy said how do you do that
and he said well for me what I do is I never go
beyond who I am I mean I can like you know when I was first acting he said you
know I would try to I'd try to go over the top and really you know act in a in
a very convincing way but it was but I was going Beyond Myself it wasn't really true to who I am and so he said this
very articulately but but it struck me because um you know I've I've done a lot
of that trying to be a certain way present a certain Persona or something
and he was kind of addressing that for me that he never goes
beyond who he is so he can go get very emotional anyway you get what I'm saying
would you say that he was trying to say that something about authenticity like he was trying to like be like the I
don't know I don't yeah well I I yeah I I think it was I think it's more than
just being authentic I I think it was also it's hard for me to describe this but it really struck me but I think it's
more than being authentic I think it was I am I'm supposed to the role here I'm
supposed to do is very dramatic but I'm not going to overplay that I have to
stay within my own range uh that's what he said I have to stay within my own range cuz if I try to go beyond my range
it doesn't come across as authentic yeah there we go great great thank you thank
you very nice very nice anybody else have uh something
they'd like to say or question or
comment over here in the hi I'm
Katherine um you spoke about let's see that the tendency is to
contain or compartmentalize our emotions or our
experience and that the goal is to
meet life and experience as it is is there also um kind of the downfall
of overindulging in experience or emotions
that we should be aware of because there's the suppressing the
compartmentalizing there's the meaning and is there an
overindulgent aspect that can be detrimental just curious yeah yeah can you say a little bit like how would one
know they're overindulging like let's say meeting
difficulty in life and and
um maybe not meeting it as
effectively in and I don't even know what effectively looks like or is um I'm just
curious if there's an aspect
of just overdoing the um the feeling of
of difficulties I see so you mean like being with difficulties in such a way
that it perpetuates the difficulties and you just kind of get stuck in this kind of uh loop kind of like this yeah does
that h i mean is there something on that end that we should be aware of curious yeah and so with mindfulness practice
there's this way in which you could uh you could start to see if this is a pattern that one has and this becomes
then very something very difficult I'll just uh make this up like let's say um
when there's a difficulty with one's uh Intimate Relationships there's a way in which there might be just be this
collapsing and say oh no it's fine it's fine and you're like not talking or not engaging with one's partner or something
and then with mindfulness you start to see oh yeah okay here I am I have this this I'm this collapsed feeling again
and it might just notice it because with the body being like this somehow or something but then uh this awkward time
is like oh I see that I have this pattern I see that it's not helpful and
I'm doing it again and I'm doing it again right so this is how it starts is
that you start to see or understand or be more familiar with some ways of
showing up in the world and then you can't just stop because I now that you see it and it's uncomfortable but it
does unwind it does unwind but it starts with having to see
it and then and then again you have to bring this kind of this warm heartedness
I talked about like okay I'm watching myself do what I know is not helpful but
I'm doing it again and then just to kind of this recognition that okay I know
it's not helpful but I'm doing it again that kind of like starts the ball
rolling to stop doing it is that helpful I think it is like it's like
it's the principle of it but it's like the fine details of the of the doing of
it is like to do it with Precision um and knowing this um is
challenging yes yes that's right it's not easy this is not
easy well so here's a little hint that I'll say here's a little hint that can be helpful it can be enormously helpful
to uh Orient towards adjectives rather than nouns I know this
sounds weird but instead of saying um I'm sad I'm just making this up I'm sad
say like oh there's real heaviness in the body there's pressure behind the
eyes the thoughts are really slow um I feel like I'm can't I'm not
going anywhere so to do a descriptor instead of like I'm sad because I'm sad
is kind of just you know then we start having a relationship with this word like sad means oh I've always been sad
I'm going to be sad again and I don't want other people to know I'm sad but if we start to say oh I have this heaviness
in my body pressure behind the eyes then we're engaged with what's actually
happening we're Mindful and this is the Precision here so and this then things can I keep on
using this word but they can unfold differently if we can stay with the adjectives with the actual experience
any adjective is fine you know describe it in any way but instead of just slapping a a label on it so to avoid
judgment on it and to give it space with just neutrality of description exactly okay
so like a naturalist would do with a uh with a uh you know you're looking at
some creature in the woods or something like oh it does this and then oh look it's doing that you know so same thing
this yeah okay so thank you all and I'm
wishing you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you