okay so welcome welcome to our third day on talking about our working with the
inner critic and today I'm going to start I just want to talk a little bit about
thoughts and in the guided meditation we're going to turn towards thoughts we're going to work with thoughts and uh
and I'll talk about it some more in the daret afterwards and there's this way in
which if we um turn towards thoughts instead of just thinking like oh this
thing is annoying get out of here I'm trying to meditate which let's face it sometimes that is our attitude we have
this like oh shoot why are you here you know there's this tone of um them not
being welcome but when we are willing to like turn towards thoughts acknowledge them
and I'm like okay come on in you might as well be part of the mindfulness practice because you're here anyway if
we have that kind of like you know turning towards them and inviting them in there's this way in which that we are
honoring thoughts we are respecting thoughts we are being inclusive by when
we bring awareness to this common everyday experience of
thoughts and we all know it's such a big part of our experience but there's this way in which
we are honoring its nature or somehow dignifying their presence because they
are here and it becomes a gateway to our
immediate experience there's just another thing we can become aware of and in that way you
can just uh highlight the present moment experience and no longer be um lost by
them no longer be pushed around by them so so there's this way in which we
can just invite in our our awareness or maybe I should say the word uh receive
the thoughts because they are already there we don't have to try to um make
our experience be different than how it is and there's this way in just shifting
our attitude towards thoughts is enormously powerful just
shifting our attitude from please get a go away to
like oh hello there you are come on in right it's very uh different so there's
lots of uh instructions that we often give um on meditation Retreats or here at 7 a or you know if we're going to do
some teaching of the introduction to mindfulness but maybe right here I'll
say there's um two different ways in which we can think about thoughts and one is the experience of thinking
so like what does it feel like to have a thought is it constrictive or do we feel like we're getting um just lost and
carried away by them but they experience the felt sense
and then the second way is to notice the there's a
theme is there planning fantasizing
remembering ruminating then of course
judging so one just the experience and two just to notice the theme we don't
have to get concerned with the exact content but just noticing if there's a
theme and that's what we'll start with uh in this guided
meditation [Music] so to begin with our meditation this
morning just tuning into the bodily experience
as it is right
now how does the body [Music]
feel we can begin with a global assessment does it
feel energized or is it low energy
is there a sense of okayness or even well-being is there or is there a sense
of General kind of discomfort or
disease however it might be can we just tune in and acknowledge and maybe even
bow to it like yep it's like this right
now the bodily experience is like this right
now and then noticing that the body is breathing
the body breathes itself of course it does you don't have to do anything
intentionally so tuning into becoming sensitive to the experience of
breathing that is the bodily experience of breathing like how does it feel to
breathe
and then for just a few breaths not all of them just a
few we're going to extend the exhale just a little
bit the exhale often is associated with some relaxation
or releasing some tension it's just a physiological way
the body works so we can take advantage of that
and just in a relaxed easy way intentionally
extending the exhale just a tiny
bit maybe it's associated with a side maybe
[Music]
not then allowing the breathing to to return to normal not changing it in any
way just resting attention on the sensations of
breathing the experience of breathing the embodiment of
breathing
and tuning into any sense of okayness any sense of
well-being maybe it's delightful to connect with others this longer in chat
maybe it's delightful to know that you're doing this wholesome thing for
your yourself this helpful thing for
yourself and then from this slight or maybe obvious or maybe
very subtle sense of yeah this is it's okay
it's okay bring your attention to a lovable
being a being that when you bring this being to mind just makes you smile
whether it's a exter internal smile or an internal
smile and just rest your attention
there with the loveliness of The Lovable
being in whatever way feels comfortable easy accessible for
you of course this includes lovable beings that are puppies or kittens or
maybe maybe you saw this really cute kitten video recently and I'm chuckling because I did see a kitten video
recently that was so Charming this little kitten that reached
out and hugged a duck I think this was going around the internet maybe some of you saw
this apparently they I'm assuming they must have grown up together these two creatures es it was sweet silly and
sweet can we allow ourselves to feel the silliness sweetness Beauty lovability
whatever it might be allowing the heart and the body to have this little bit of
uplift
e
allowing yourself to just feel
experience that maybe there's a slight sentense of delight or an okay sense of
okayness I'm smiling it's makes me smile to think about these
things
and then can we use this sense of delight
loveliness warm-heartedness can we use that to
Source our experience to fuel our
experience and I want to normalize if it's not there you don't have access to it that's
perfectly fine too last thing we want is the tyranny of
a guided meditation telling you you should be one way when it's just not happening that's
perfectly okay whatever you're experiencing is can it be
okay
and then just to tune into the experience of
breathing I'm bringing this attitude of warmth or
Delight into noticing the experience of
breathing
noticing the inhales and the
exhales
e
and for now when you find yourself lost in thought just very simply gently maybe
with this attitude of warmth begin again with the sensations
of
breathing
e
and now when you wake up or realize oh I've
been [Music] thinking you just recognize it as such
just this very simple word thinking and then return to the
sensations of breathing so recognize that thinking was
happening in a relaxed easy way very simple oh yeah okay I was
thinking I'm going to return to the breath
no need to make it complicated add stories to the stories just oh yeah
thinking and then rest attention on the sensations of
breathing
you find that you're just left in thought just not really being
mindfulness that much on if breathing that's okay can you just maybe tune into
the exhale and notice oh yeah thinking is like this then I have an inhale
and with the exhale oh yep thinking is like
this
what I'd like to point to here is the Simplicity just noticing yep that was a
lot of thinking okay and come back to the experience of
breathing and without having
to add an attitude of somehow it should be
different this is what Minds do they think we're just
noticing thinking happens and then begin again with the
sensations of breathing thinking is Perfectly
Natural don't have to disparage it
e
when we recognize that we've been thinking just meet it with a
warm-hearted attitude
thinking doesn't have to be any more complicated than
that and then simply begin
again with the sensations of
breathing
e
e [Music]
[Music]
okay so this idea of noticing our thinking in
a relaxed simple way without having to add
anything extra to it so this is our third day of working
on uh with the inner critic and I've been describing the inner critic is this
interior you know I'm using this word said personality but you know I'm not a psychologist I'm just using that in the
you know just not in a technical way uh by any means but it's this way in which
there's this uh voice that's like a constantly putting us down or belittling
us and this voice of negativity that's blaming us and nagging us and the strong
sense of like you should do this or you should not do that or sometimes it's associated with this
real sense of Shame Shame for just being who we are or existing and it's really
has this quality of harshness and creates this attitude this
interior experience of a harshness and so going to link this to
thoughts that often this inner critic shows up as thoughts and they might be like quiet
thoughts that uh maybe U we don't see so much but it's just of the nature of
thoughts that for the most part most thoughts are self-referential that there are these
thoughts about me you know whatever you know there's just thoughts about um who
like there's this implicit sense of that there's this me at the center that needs to take care of something or do
something or everything is relation to me or however it might be but there
maybe two things to notice about this that these thoughts about me are always
distorted in some kind of way we don't think they are we think they're accurate
and true and and precise but they're distorted and it's not until often that
we um can get away from being lost in thought all the time that we can start
to see how distorted our thoughts are and so in one way that they're distorted
is this idea of you know always judging ourselves and putting ourselves down
disparaging ourselves this inner critic that shows up and for many of us it just
feels like normal well of course there was this inner critic putting us down that's just the way it is in fact we
might not even notice that they're NE netive or that they're critical it just might be so familiar it just feels like
okay this is what the interior landscape is like and I also want to normalize this isn't true for
everybody for um this is 100% anecdotally but those individuals that I
recognize that grew up in the United States they often have this inner critic maybe less so if you grw up outside of
the United States this is just Diana's observations no scientific evaluation about that just my simple observations
but and so it can be enormously powerful to notice that we are having not only
thoughts but that they are judging us and that not in a positive way judging
us in a way that is unhelpful and there's this way in which the less we are aware of our judging
thoughts the more likely we're uh allowing them to kind like chip
away at our sense of self-worth or our sense of wellbeing there's this way that
just a little bit by a little bit it kind of like diminishes any sense of
okayness or contentment or satisfaction that we might have so these thoughts that are
disparaging towards ourselves really take a toll they're really texing
and so it can be enormously helpful to just notice them and then not only to
notice them but to kind of like take the rug out from underneath them from away from the authority that they seem to
have the way that they like to masquerade around is they're the truth and accurate and it's not the truth and
it's not accurate it's there's a way in which it's distorted they're of course
they're based on things that actually have happened in reality for the most part not always so I don't want us to
say that you know we have to completely um ignore them but uh so often
they're um twisting what's uh actually happening so with mindfulness practice
little bit what we did in the guided meditation just noticing thinking that um activity to just notice
like oh okay I'm I was lost thought but in a way that brings some
warm-heartedness or some warmth to it as opposed to like oh gee Austin thoughts
again you know we can sometimes have that attitude but if we can bring just a
simple awareness of thoughts then that helps us to
discern what's helpful what's not helpful what's healthy what's not what's
not healthy because there's this way in which the inner critic if we don't notice it just
uh drones on and on and on and sometimes if we do notice then we're just critical
of the critic and that's just another way of droning on and on right it's just like maintaining this attitude of being
critical and disparaging and judging in a unhelpful
way so when we notice that the thoughts are are
disparaging they're pejorative they are unhelpful towards
us we can isolate those types of thoughts are
unhelpful from other types of thoughts that are helpful we need thoughts of
course we do to plan to communicate to maybe our livelihood depends on thinking
and we need to solve problems in our daily life how are we going to get that
big bowl in the dishwasher you know whatever uh whatever the uh problems
that are meeting us in the day so first is to notice
thoughts and then to second can we isolate can we separate those thoughts
that are judging I use this word critical disparaging from the other
ones and so this is a skill that often requires that we bring
mindfulness to our thoughts and sometimes we're just so lost in thought that we can't do that but is there a way
in which we can separate we can isolate we can discern helpful solving problems
communicating planning not helpful beating ourselves up making us feel like
we're unworthy or shame or something like that to practice is to separate
from the helpful from the unhelpful so what's one way that we can recognize the
unhelpful I mean the obvious ones are if the if the particular thoughts are
obvious to you like you know if we hear these words like you're worthless oh you're hopeless you know if
we hear those types of thoughts okay that's obvious that's not it's really not helpful
but there's another way in which we can notice is the tone of the thoughts
helpful thoughts often just have a neutral tone but the unhelpful ones have
this way of a maybe this feeling like they're barking at you you know the tone
is maybe sharp and loud and harsh something like that or maybe that we
notice that it it's not about a particular thing um maybe the thought
has as I spoke about yesterday has taken a specific event and just globalized it
like okay you were lost in thought during meditation and then the inner critic
takes that one piece of data and says you're a terrible meditator you're a
terrible person like why are you even bothering you know oh gosh it's just so hard it's it's hard for me to even say
these things out loud right it's painful but there's so many ways in which the Mind likes to do this the
inner critic likes to do this take one little data point and then use a broad
paintbrush to make something about our innate value our innate
worth so that's another way if we can notice if um the inner critic is arising
these thoughts as if it's challenging your innate value in some globalized way and
then Third Way which we might notice the tone of these unhelpful thoughts if
you're starting to feel weighed down there's like and you kind like the posture like
oh my gosh you know this just feels too much and this we can start to feel like
the energy just really dropping and feeling
um hopeless feeling uh overwhelmed like oh it's just too
much those are thoughts that are not helpful not helpful so how can we work
with this first as I said we can like separate helpful thoughts solving
problems communicating planning unhelpful inner critic disparaging
ourselves making Global assessments about our value and then just label it
judging is like this judgement is like
this and then just tune into the experience yeah it feels heavy feels
crappy doesn't feel good and there's a way in which just the
actual judging helps us to get a little bit disentangled from it we're noticing
it but there's something about like um turning into the experience of judging
which is you know mindfulness being aware of and the mindfulness has a
little bit of uplift with it the judging itself might be
uncomfortable but to be mindful of uncomfortable brings a little bit of space and
uplift so this just saying judgment is like this helps us to crystallize this
understanding that we're judging it helps this judgment to stand out to separate from the other thoughts that
are helpful and then but just to be careful here there's no need to judge the
judging judgment is like this and I'm judging the judging and then we can like
judge the judging of the judging and then off we go right so if you notice that just say judgment is like this just
kind of stop with that and um it's like judgment is like
this and then we can just see it as just a bunch of thoughts it's just a bunch of
thoughts and what are thoughts what are they they're like you know they're
intangible there's like you know we could just blow them away right
there's like how many thoughts a day do you have how many bazillion guilan made
it feels like that so many you'll have other thoughts later
so notice that you're thinking separate the helpful from the unhelpful when you
notice that there's judging just label it say judgment is like this judgment is like this it feels like
this and that's a way that creates some space then you can like tune in if
you're meditating tune into the sensations of breathing or just continue doing whatever it is you're
doing so I'd like to add this to some of the instructions that I gave earlier in
the week because you know whatever's available right when we're in the midst of the inner critic we work with
whatever is available so on Monday we had this expression I'm doing the best I can
right now maybe that comes after like judgment is like this and I'm doing the best I
can right now and on Tuesday yesterday I gave the instructions to like tune in like how am
I right now like just to tune into the felt experience as a way maybe to interrupt the inner critic maybe you
could add today's uh instructions like judgment is like this and how am I right
now or maybe it's just like judgment is like this it's like this it's just a bunch of
thoughts and our thoughts they like to push us around they can feel authoritative they
can feel weighty but they're just thoughts you'll have other thoughts you
were having other thoughts just a moment ago we don't have to believe them or get
as invested in them as often as we do or as much as we do so today like not
disparaging the disparaging instead just to say disparaging is like this judgment is
like this and help take the the sting out of it or the just make
it simple just make it simple so with that I hope you have a
day in which you can separate that unhelpful judging from the other types
of thoughts thank you thank you all I look forward to practicing together tomorrow
deep bows deep bows to all of you
hean be self meta rather than self-critic oh that's cute I like it I like
it yes thank you for all you it's a beautiful thing to practice
together
so nice too how you all support one another and
support me and this feeling of community even that we're all over it's beautiful
beautiful like what would the world be like if everybody had this experience to
be able to know be with other people who are warm-hearted and kind and
generous I think that we are like changing the world just by coming
together like why not have it start with
us is being openhearted towards one [Music]
another
it's spend for me to connect with you all reading your
chats
every rights we have grown together over the years right it's quite something that over the years know so many people
tune in it's a beautiful thing I think that uh
I don't know we shouldn't underestimate how powerful this is
tooy writes we Embrace new every new voice that appears in the chat
beautiful
GNA sign off now see you
tomorrow