so hello everyone and
welcome and I just uh feel kind of delighted to sit down here and
see uh your names for those of you who are chatting I think there's something
feeling very something very beautiful about names maybe the beauty I'm seeing in
them is their is what they represent they represent the beauty of each of
you or somehow the specialness or somehow a deep appreciation
of who's behind those names you I justed to feel very happy and contented to sit
here and see all the names and telling you a little bit because I'm
surprised by that's what comes up first sitting here so thank you for being
here
so today uh for the meditation I'd like the theme to be
Simplicity and the overall overarching theme of this week is um this the uh the
consequences of letting go con consequences of release of non- clinging
non- clinging which is at the heart of the goal of Buddhist practice is a quite
a profound involves quite a profound transformation or change and to only see it as non-
clinging the absence of clinging misses some of the ways in which you fills in
or expands out into a very rich sense of being alive and being here and being
creative in this world that we live in so learn to recognize some of the
consequences of this Letting Go non- clinging supports the richness of the
experience and so Simplicity is one of them
to cling is complicated especially if we're clinging to many
things to be distracted is complicated being undistracted is simple just being
with what's here to be
uh re reactively thinking and story making and having discursive thought in relationship to what's going on is
complicated to have a Simplicity of being and just being with things in the simplest way without clinging without
being for or against does not curtail does not limit
our intelligence or understanding but it adds a a through line through our life
through our experience where something inside of us maintains a Simplicity of
being so that we're less distracted
less conflicted less confused less scattered and less jumping around less
um uh involved in the complicated world of clinging clinging
inevitably not inevitably but more often than not um involves story and meaning making
and wider purposes and sometimes they involve conceit in the complicated world
of identity and who we are and who we want to how we want to present ourselves to people and prove ourselves clinging
is a complicated world something inside of us get becomes simple when we don't
cling something inside of us becomes quieter it doesn't mean that what we're
involved in is not complicated we still live in a complicated world
but we address that complicated World in a simpler way maybe without with less need with
less attachment so for this meditation let's uh have Simplicity as a
reference point and if you don't feel a Simplicity of being as we sit here even just the
idea of Simplicity can um just be like a highlighter that
highlights how actually what we're doing here is
complicated so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing your
eyes and Beginning by a simple
acknowledgement that you are where you're sitting are you're where you're
meditating this is the
place and generally when we sit down to
meditate we're entering into a world that is somewhat removed
somewhat free of needing to answer the phone cook foods go
shopping solve issues take care of our responsibilities for these
minutes we're allowing us ourselves the gift of a Simplicity of being here in
this place in this
body and taking the time to feel the
body the body can have a lot of different Sensations in it sometimes it's complicated our
relationship to the body is complicated but to sit
quietly with your body in your body
can allow the tensions of the body to begin to
soften allow the body's wish to be soft
relaxed settled to have a chance to
unfold it's rare that the body wants to be tense it's where the body wants to be
agitated it's almost like a deep wish in the body to release
relax the body likes to be simple there's a very strong movement in
the body towards homeostasis towards balance to wholeness
and within the body as part of the body becoming aware of the body
breathing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
can be a settling
Force like a massage from the inside
out as you sit here allow that rhythm of breathing to have an influence on your
body a connecting relaxing
influence take give time to feeling your body feeling your body
breathing so that you're moving towards a Simplicity of being here without a lot
of desires that things be different Simplicity of being with how
things
are
to offer a simplicity of attention to the thinking
mind the thinking mind itself can have a wish a deep
wish to
rest to unwind to soften its
tensions gently slowly on the
exhale begin a process of quieting the
mind letting the Mind relax and settle
for
and [Music] perhaps an ongoing
support for an ongoing Simplicity of being can be the rhythm of the body
breathing in and breathing
out yes Simplicity where not much needs to
happen except staying here
present where in the Simplicity you can find non-
clinging where in nonreactivity you can find
simplicity
e
for
are there ways you are more complicated now than you need to
be find your way back to a Simplicity of being
without the complexity of a lot of thinking a lot of wanting or not
wanting without trying to make something happen
content to be aware content with a simple
awareness of what is
e
for
so as we come to the end of this sitting
you might want to take a few moments to consider how being simple our Simplicity
of being how and when it might be a a great
gift to give yourself maybe there are times when it
can feel like a
relief maybe there are times it can feel like Freedom
itself and how your way of being
simple in Social circumstances can be a gift to
others and one way to understand that is that being
complicated is the opposite of a gift being complicated can
be confusing sometimes there's no room for other people in the complicated
mind if we're caught up in complications we can't see very
clearly we can't be with other others very
well maybe it's through a Simplicity of presence of
attention that we support people to be themselves to be respected as they
are to feel safe to be able to relax around us
may it be that what we learn through this practice helps us to support the
well-being and happiness of Others May our life
contribute to the welfare and happiness of
others and one way to do that is not
complicated but to offer a simple presence a simple attention a simple accompaniment of
Others May all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we discover how profound it
is to share with each other a mutual Simplicity of
being a mutual
contentment with being simple Here and
Now
[Music]
thank
you
e
so hello everyone and welcome to this
talk on the signs
symptoms um consequences of non-
clinging and um these are this non- clinging is a synonym for Liberation for
Freedom kind of a spiritual Freedom Buddhism talks about and
um the symptom or the indication of non-
clinging that I'd like to emphasize today is Simplicity clinging is complicated
clinging involves a whole background of conditioning of beliefs of desires of
wishes of uh relationship to other people of memory of projection into the
future clinging can involve a complicated world not non clinging is
simple it's the absence of clinging and in that absence an absence
of that immense complicated edifice that keeps clinging in
place so when we learn to not cling to when we learn to let go when we become
free of of clinging we can feel that Things become
simpler in ourselves the world around us might remain May remain
complicated and the and but to uh have a through line that runs
through how we engage in the world be an inner sense of
Simplicity and of course we have to deal with many things that are complicated but one way that helps that is to um
simply do one thing at a time it's compc at to multitask it's
complicated to do many things at once some of you maybe are quite capable
and proficient at multitasking but it comes as a at a cost
and the cost is we stay in a more complicated world and we keep spinning hold you know
um um juggling lots of balls in the air when we're
multitasking and so there's very little opportunity Unity to appreciate freedom
to appreciate Simplicity to appreciate non- clinging more likely where there's a
certain distractability in multitasking that we don't see what's
behind all the things that we do we don't see what the drives are what the fears are what the desires are what the
aversions are uh we don't see the conceits that are operating because we're so busy doing so much
that um that it obscures the kind of clarity that arises if we're just kind
of doing one thing at a time hearing listening to One thing or
doing one thing being with one person at a time listening
well and um and so when we do one thing at a time maybe we get more less things
done but we also maybe get things done better so we don't have to redo
them maybe there's uh when we're at ease and relaxed that we do things in a
better way I found that um sometimes when I feel like I've too much to do and not
enough time paradoxically I find that if I sit down to meditate for 10 minutes
somehow I have plenty of time afterwards that in the complexity of
having a lot to do there's a kind of tension that builds up in the mind a kind of pressure in the
mind that um uh that makes do doing
whatever I'm going to do more difficult not as and not as intelligently or not
as creatively or not as fully that gives contributes to the sense there's not
enough time so a Simplicity of being that's may
be con connected to a content M but these words like Simplicity and
contentment can be off-putting uh because our lives are
rich and wonderful and complicated ways and doing many things at once and many things and Rich things and complicated
things is enlivening and vitalizing maybe so but there's uh even
there there's a way of staying simple in the middle of the
many things we do I was once a fast order cook at a restaurant after being
for almost three years in the Zen Monastery and um there was a lot of
activity going on and U fast and quickly quick and tracking many different things
but I would say that uh in the middle of it all I was there in a very simple
way that I was not caught up in a lot of desires a lot of memories a lot of what
was happen happening tomorrow what happened yesterday I was fully completely there for this amazing dance
in the kitchen and uh I would leave the end of my shift feeling more settled more
peaceful more simple more concentrated than when I started my shift it was a delightful
feeling so there was a kind of Simplicity of being of just being doing
doing the just doing the complicated Act of f fast order cooking and um and
um so just because we have a lot to do doesn't mean that we can't find that
Simplicity through through line through this as well this as well if we're
distracted a lot if we're caught up in thoughts a lot that's a complicated
world if we're fretting over things and anxious about things I propose to say
that's a complicated world if we're living in our memories too much
and reviewing and thinking about things that's a complicated world uh if we're trying to figure
things out too much it can be too complicated of course we have to figure things out but um sometimes uh we figure
things out better if our minds are clear and open and sometimes I uh things that
are difficult to figure out sometimes I I don't figure them out sometimes I'm
reflecting on and thinking about them but then I'm doing something else the answer
comes um sometimes when I don't remember a word or someone's name um if I stop
searching for it then 30 seconds a minute later it comes up if I stayed in
that complicated mode of searching and wanting and concerned and worried about not remembering it keeps obscuring the
mind's capacity to find its way
so look for so when you are able to let go when you're able to find some modum
of non- clinging to things to appreciate it better look for what feels like
Simplicity Simplicity of being a Simplicity of perception a Simplicity of
thinking a Simplicity of care for the situation maybe even love for the
situation so this is the theme for this week is not that you have to be
simple but rather if you're able to stop clinging let go of the grasping you have
or the resistance you have appreciate some of these result
what results from that and for today appreciate the a feeling or sense of
Simplicity that comes from that Simplicity of being something becomes less
complicated and um so it's complicated to want to and expect and ask people to
be simple but I'd propose that it's simpler
to suggest notice the Simplicity that arises when you are no longer
clinging and then appreciate that take time with it be nourished by it let it
condition you let it recondition you in a way that maybe begins to heal from the
conditioning that comes from being overly busy there's a huge cost of being
complicated and doing too much and running around and juggling too many
balls um it can really wear a person down out it can really cause a lot of
stress and so as we begin appreciating the Simplicity of being that can come from non- clinging it's actually a
medicine for a a reconditioning medicine from the
unhealthy conditioning of living in a way too complicated inner world and sometimes in outer
world so
simplicity so as you go through today uh you might look for
opportunities to not cling maybe there simple moments
throughout the day that maybe you're taking a bus somewhere and you just sit
on a chair and in the bus and just don't look at your phone don't do anything but just be there and in in letting go of
the drive the desires is to always be doing something and see if you can find the blessing of
Simplicity standing in a line in a store waiting
[Music] for a computer to St start if you turn it
on don't fill that time with something else maybe waiting for the water to
boil maybe don't try to be efficient to do other things at the same time maybe there's a way of just
standing and looking out the window or sitting down for a few minutes and breathing and being
mindful that overcomes some of the clinging you go through and You Begin appreciating a Simplicity of being
allowing something else to I condition you through the day than always being on the
go so thank you very much and uh I wish
you the joys and blessing of certainly of non- clinging today but also the joys
and blessings of Simplicity thank
you