hello my friends and Welcome to our meditation
and I'm feeling pretty appreciative and delighted to be here and uh to be here
in a relatively healthy way after being having a short cold short maybe
flu and um and it feels kind of special to be sitting
here so the theme for today is well this
for the dmer talk will be um appreciative
joy and so to talk about appreciation and joy briefly we have this amazing capacity
for attention and awareness or attention is often comes along with our
preoccupations with our ruminations with our uh uh primary concerns with our
fear and when it does so awareness acts like a magnifying lass so if we bring
our attention to something which we're challenged by some we find is difficult or unfortunate all these extra stuff
that comes with awareness um U makes it bigger for us and it can Loom really big
big and but this uh and we then we miss out on the bigger picture of what's
happening and meditation is meant to settle the preoccupations the pre the
the the fears the biases the selectivity
by which the attention is used to help us see the bigger picture of the of the
moment and in doing that it's helpful to almost
counter the tendency the negativity bias that many people have to from time to
time take time to appreciate all the good that you have appreciate what is
right maybe just in this present moment even if much in your life is
difficult to be to be preoccupied with that for the
mind the heart to be caught in that all the time is not healthy for us it's good
to take a break it's good to step away to get a bigger picture to realize there's more to life than the challenges
we have and from time to time it's good to uh appreciate uh what is good in life
what's good the sunlight the warmth the the
um that we have food to eat that we have a roof over our head many people don't have these basic
simple things so now we're sitting here the goodness the appreciation for
the opportunity to meditate the opportunity to meditate in
community the opportunity to enter into your meditation
posture and um there's something very very invaluable something very powerful
for me to step into my meditation posture posture that I've assumed now
for 50 years and the associations the familiarity is quite wonderful and that
I have been able to have this posture uh that is so meaningful for me
brings me a lot of Joy it brings me a lot of joy that I have a practice of
mindfulness that frees me from suffering frees me from the preoccupation with it
frees me with the added fear added added um
rumination it frees me for that magnifying glass that tends to highlight
the difficulties so I live in them thinking they're most of what's Happening mostly what's happening in the
present moment for most of most of us uh it's good mostly what's happening for most of
us are things that are working uh May many of our biological
functions that Keep Us Alive if you're alive they're working even if some of
them are challenging challenged most of our mental functions
allows us to be aware and recognize what's happening as it's happening a lot
is working in the brain in the mind even if some things are a little bit
wonky and to know that there are these teachings
for finding our peace is phenomenal lucky to have
them so to sit with appreciation and not so much spending a
lot of time thinking about it but just enough thinking about
appreciation that something in you begins to smile maybe it's your mouth maybe it's
your heart maybe it's somewhere in your whole
torso maybe it's in your eyes to
appreciate the goodness that's here the Good Fortune that's brought us to this
moment these moments even if wider moments of the day are not so
fortunate and doing this appreciation can allow something to settle that's the hope some kind of attention we carry can
be put to rest for a few minutes so assuming a meditation
posture and maybe find a posture today that has a minimum amount of pain
or discomfort find one that is comfortable
for you so it's easier to appreciate being in a
body the body that becomes the home or the temple for
meditation gently closing your
eyes
and and as you breathe in you are particip ating in a
phenomenal Global process of the oxygen
Cycles we're doing our part to create carbon
dioxide that the trees and plants can use so they make oxygen so we may
live we can't just take and take take and
take we participate in this cycle of giving and
taking in so many ways our life is a process of giving and taking receiving
and giving and now as we breathe we're
participating in a wider process than just our own
life but which keep which keeps our life
going taking a few long deep
breaths relaxing on the
exhale and letting your breathing return inter
normal and see if you can
now listen quietly feel in a deep sensitive way
to a place inside where all things are
good is there a place deep inside below the level of
your thoughts and preoccupations past and future just here
now maybe in your breathing
maybe in your heart maybe in a back corner of the
heart maybe somewhere else in your torso maybe low down the base of your
spine the length of your
spine and if there is a place of goodness of peace or quiet or
calm breathe with it breathe with
appreciation breathe with gratitude
and maybe with a small smile on your lips breathe with
joy
e
for
for e
if you can give yourself over
fully to the rhythm of breathing breathing in and breathing
out it can become as if Joy is
what animates the
breathing a joy that comes when
we give ourselves fully to one
thing in a relaxed soft
way
e
for
e for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to reflect a little bit how easy it is to be self
centered how easy it is to see the
world as if field of opposition me versus
you you or me but coming out of meditation there's
no indic no orientation for this it's all in a certain
way a Cooperative field where we're all kin all working
together and think one of the advantages of coming out of a less centered
Place through meditation is to be able to appreciate
others not just care for them not just wish them
well but appreciate what's going well to celebrate with them when they're
celebrating to reflect back what's good when what they do is
good the ability to share in a delight in the success and well-being
and goodness of others is one of the great joys of
life and people appreciate being appreciated people appreciate being
recognized in a certain way we put promote the
Good by appreciating the good and may it be as we come out of
meditation today that we consider going into the
world of our family and friends neighbors strangers people in stores
places of work ready to appreciate them
maybe having spent some time reflecting about the people who do good
things are helpful
supportive who do a good job makes it easier for everyone else whatever it might
be may we
appreciate the happiness of others may we appreciate the way others care
for people may we appreciate the integrity and honesty with which people live that
helps others to feel comfortable with them may we appreciate how others help
people who are suffering and may that appreciation of
others bring us Delight May It Be inspiration for
us may it continue to awaken what is good in our own
Hearts may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for
so hello my friends and welcome to this fourth talk on the aspects of love I
feel pretty fortunate to be able to talk on this topic brings me
joy and uh the first day was ANUK which I translated as care and it's a care that is deeply
connected to respect for others I like to think of it as a respect where we see
everyone as kin that maybe we're not directly family
but we're kin we're related we're part of a global family and
um and that kinship then leads us to want to be friendly inclines us to be
friendly to however we meet why would anybody be an enemy why would anybody be someone who we would not be happy to see
just happy to see people maybe that's what friendliness is and um and offer some of our
happiness to them in our way we say hello or maybe that's all it is
I and then um and then when people
suffer uh to want to help to have be motivated to see their suffering end
they're kins of course we want it to end so if we can we may do something if we
can't we then we uh we are a witness we are we recognize we help people not feel
so alone we accompany and then today it's when
people are having success when people are doing good things when people are
happy themselves when things are going well for them we we don't want to end up
being envious or jealous but rather when we're kin this openness this respect that we're happy
to see people uh uh when people are having
success we feel Joy we feel happiness to feel that happiness to take time for
that to not Overlook it to not race Beyond it but but to
appreciate and in Buddhism there's a whole medit ation practice on appreciative
Joy where we just kind of focus on the well-being that other people have may
that well-being continue May that well-being fill
me with inspiration with joy may this well-being of others spread
out through the world so different ways of kind of highlighting but the idea is
to take the one way to do this is the words another way is to take the feeling of appreciation of joy and let it
radiate and that takes time you have to pause a little bit not just kind of Rush
on with the conversation to something else um someone tells you that they're really happy and you say oh that's I'm
so happy for that but you know I'm having I'm really challenged with my car my car is not behaving properly and and
you've kind of changed the subject to something it wasn't necessary to talk about or in a right away it was not
necessary but to stay and linger to appreciate make room for that
and sometimes people uh it's invaluable for people to really feel they were
heard really feel like you're there for them that you make space for them to make more come out tell me more this is
so good that you graduated from high school this must be really great that you accomplish this tell me
more and um but so this idea of appreciative joy joy in the joy of
others can be cultivated and developed in the process of all these forms of
Love they can coexist with their kind of opposites where the things interfere with them and part of the value of
practicing them or bringing them up and reflecting on them and letting them be a guide through our day is that it
sometimes can highlight the opposite highlight the things that interfere with
these things so what inter what for you interferes with appreciative joy and the
joy of others so I mentioned U Envy or jealousy which uh can be quite strong
and quite a current strong current in some people's lives and so then we would
uh in mindfulness practice we wouldn't berate ourselves for that or criticize ourselves for that but we do something
more important and that is we would study it we would take a good look at that what's that about uh what are the
emotions that come along with jealousy and envy what's the sense of self what's
the belief system that's operating can we sit and just feel that for a while uh
accompany ourselves in those feelings because accompaniment is so powerful ACC
competent let's let allows something to settle or what is what else gets in the
way of appreciative Joy it might be um your own desires your own
preoccupations that uh you want to get what you want and uh you don't have time
to take it other people into account it could be fear it could be fear that if
you take in and appreciate others take in their joy that you make it makes you
susceptible to be taken advantage of or people want more from you or or uh you
know something might happen or maybe it uh highlights your own
unhappiness because if you really recognize happiness in others then you feel worse about your own and how your
life is difficult I'd like to propose the opposite that appreciating the joy in
others can be an inspiration for us food for us to be able to then practice with
our own difficulties so appreciative Joy is not meant to be a distraction from our own
suffering from our own difficulties but rather uh uh create the amb ambience in
which we easier to focus on our own to be present for our own to give a wider
context for it in some ways that appreciative joy to
others is probably not going to make you um panish because in Buddhist practice
um what comes up clearly uh is an emphasis on suffering but not to drown ourselves in
suffering but to find Freedom from suff suffering so in this emphasis on
suffering I don't think you have to worry about being poly Anish um if the others are suffering then you don't want
to paint it over with joy and make them kind of kind of show things on the
bright sh side for other people or even for yourself as a way of ignoring the
difficulties are going on but when things are going good when things are go
delightful for people that uh they're happy be share that happiness accompany
that happiness take time to take it in just take time to say wow that's
great uh in a way that brings a smile to your face in a way that brings you kind
of to light and uh it's phenomenal uh how great this
appreciative Joy can be in us and sometimes it can feel that you're the one who's benefiting from it more than
the other person uh maybe it sets free something inside a flow of joy of
delight of happiness because you've become an open channel for
um for for these wonderful feelings and uh it's sometimes uh people
who doing meditation on appreciative Joy will feel kind of shivering or shivering
right word but a wonderful uh vibrating feeling of joy
and Delight that courses through them uh when the appreciating Joy is so
strong and um so appreciative
joy and uh so people this during this holiday
time there's a lot of joy in seeing each other and being together with each
other share in that Joy Delight in that Joy celebrate that Joy toast that
joy and on the holidays also there's many people who suffer more that uh
people feel left out or lonely or something so that also should get our
care and our love appreciating them and not to uh rub it in for them by
emphasizing The Joy when they're not having it maybe then we emphasize calm
attention calm Lo loving compassionate
attention and so the care we have for others is something that's morphing and shifting and
changing sometimes it's compassion sometimes it's friendliness loving kindness sometimes it's uh appreciative
joy and one of the great joys one of the great aspects of this practice is the
fluidity by which we can shift and change move between them and there's a
way that to allow each of these to have their own time and maybe even become
strong uh allows us to uh Let It Fade Away as we move into a different
circumstance and the another one is needed we can be friendly with
someone you know for a while we go to another place and we're we have
compassion we shift we go someplace else to be with someone else and they're joyful and we
then kind of shift with it we morph we meet the circumstance not because
we're rejecting or being dis unloyal to the people who were suffering when we
feel Joy but rather we're just in a sense loyal or present for how it is
now and each time being appropriate for this circumstance not carrying past
circumstances with us and so this fluidity between these different states
care kindness compassion and appreciative
Joy uh the more we're fluid the more we're not stuck in any one of them the more these can live in our lives in a
wonderful way feeding us in a way that they're always available
and um much more available Than People Avail themselves for these are
Treasures the Buddha called the Brahma viharas a practitioner's wealth so if
you want to be wealthy these are these are the real wealth is to have these
wonderful qualities so then tomorrow we'll finish with uh equanimous love and um so may
you in the meantime look for opportunities today to either
privately in yourself so no one knows or out loud to
appreciate uh the goodness the joy the success of other people make that a
theme um see what happens if you accompany PE ACC company or open
recognize people for their joy and their happiness and may it bring you Joy may
you be Delight lighted by all the success and goodness
that there is in this world for all the all the terrible news we
get I suspect there's more goodness every day than uh than what is difficult
and and painful thank you very much