good morning everybody um had a little uh glitches this morning I tried like
six times to go live on YouTube and every time I got a message saying this
message is PRI this this broadcast is private so so Kevin had to had to open a
kind of a third- party way of of uh accessing the the stream so I'm very
happy to be with you and I'm sorry you had to wait um and let's uh let's just let's sit
together you each of us in our separate places
all around the world but uh but together in this sa in
this sa that has become meaningful to so many people over the
years do I assuming you can hear me
you and
uh and see me I think uh I can see in the chat that things are going
okay
so once again you can
uh just uh pay attention a little bit of attention to the posture that ear
in let there be ease and
alertness looking around the body
for areas of tension that can be eased up opened relaxed a little bit
softened
let there be ease and this morning I invite you to uh
to begin with with this hearing again with hearing sounds and sounds
that that are present in where you are and any sounds
that that arise from from your device related to my voice
or maybe there are some notification beeps or rings coming through
from other programs that are want your
attention and uh knowing you can just hear
them without effort if you're if your ears and your your sensory apparatus is
working they're audible you don't have to reach out in
any way in order to hear the sounds they come to
you so to welcome them
and then notice that they they go they pass
away they can be received in our awareness it
sounds I can hear the sound of the the fan of my
computer it's a very fing it's pretty
constant occasional sounds from
outside other appliances making their little thingss they come and they
go sometimes they persist and sometimes they're just momentary and all of them can just be
received just received
and the same is true for the sensations of breathing
often when we're meditating there there can be a sense that breathing is an
intentional action that we're causing it to happen
and and you know I think quite a few meditators have a a habit of controlling
the breath often even unconsciously when we when we meditate
but you know the breath will continue if we leave it alone when we leave it
alone it's not going to
stop we don't have to do anything in order for breathing to happen the
body breathes every minute of every day that we're alive
and we can just let it happen we can be receptive to the sensations knowing it's
happening without interfering just as we don't need to interfere with the sounds
that we hear
there's no need to reach out with a
mind just allow whatever is arising in you the sensations of
breathing any sounds that might be
arising any thoughts emotions whatever is arising within you
just let it be known as it arises and as it persists if it
does and then noticing as it goes
away each sensation each breath each sound that has its little
life and then it's gone
and if we can be receptive like this open to all that's arising
then all that's making up our life right now and just come to
us come to us in its fullness
all the experience that makes up our life and it can it can be known there as
a flow just a moving flow and we we can
come to know it very simply not interfering not trying to fix anything
just sitting and receiving all the things that make up our
life each moment can be fresh new and still very
simple
e
e e
and you might just uh just check your inner State the state of your mind
heart is there a leaning forward a a trying to
catch experience catch the breath or sounds or
whatever is arising you can let go if there's anything like that any kind
of um grasping
or trying to get hold of experience and just allow it to come to
you
your awareness can receive what arises can be known without any leaning
forward just
receiving
e
e e
[Music]
for e
oh I remembered to unmute after I had my sip of
tea um today is uh is is day four now of
our investigation of this list of six qualities of the
Dharma um this list uh you know it occurs in quite a number of sutas in uh
in several of the of the collections of the nikayas of the early
discourses it's not a it's not a teaching that only only occurs once or
twice so we've looked at four of these six qualities the first is that the
Dharma is well proclaimed it's a useful body of
teachings it's able to guide us from the beginning of our practice all the way to
full Awakening and the second uh quality is that it's visible here and now we see
it in our experience as it happens in the moment isn't theoretical it's not
found in books and Dharma talks but in our practice as we walk the
path and the third is that the Dharma is immediately
effective when we practice practice in a dhic way we can see that it works and
the fourth is that it's inviting inspections aaso we're invited to come to the Dharma
to practice it to see for ourselves whether it works how it works and to
keep looking keep exploring and then the fifth quality uh
the one I'll talk about today is uh opao on W
leading and uh I think this really follows uh logically from the previous
ones when we've come to see for ourselves how the Dharma works to see
its effective it's its Effectiveness in us you know here and now
immediately then we can then we see that we can uh we can trust the direction in
which it's leading us onward toward Freedom toward the end of greed and
hatred and delusion and when we see these qualities of the Dharma for ourselves see them
playing out in our own experience we know empirically that the path works and
I believe that uh as a result of that we practice it more
diligently we're inspired perhaps I know certainly I am
and uh to use the pebble in the shoe analogy that I once heard Gil use once
we've seen the effect of taking a pebble out of our shoe then we're likely uh
probably to to take it out more quickly the next time there's one in there um and after a while it kind of
becomes automatic you know we might even Shake our shoes out um if we've been walking around outside in fly areas
before we put them on again we might walk in a way that's less likely to
result in Pebbles getting into our shoes we might avoid pebbly areas not wear
sandals perhaps in pebbly areas there are a lot of ways to uh skillful ways to
avoid Pebbles and when we see that our Dharma practice is effective when our
inspection shows us that we we have more peace in our hearts and Minds that we
are Kinder wiser less reactive Ive we are LED onward we naturally begin to act
in ways that avoid putting uh Pebbles into our hearts and and
minds I think uh our understanding of the ways that
our mind works um uh deepens and we begin to have uh to
bring more discernment into uh decisions about how we we spend our time our free
time our work time even how where we spend our money how we interact with
with others the quality of our interactions we develop more wisdom
about avoiding activities like pebbles you know or people that lead us into uh
into more Dua our hearts get bigger they get more
welcoming more and more we make choices that are based on Discerning what is SK
skillful what's beneficial what's kind as opposed to what leads to harm both
harm for ourselves and harm for others we keep using the tools of the Dharma
mindfulness compassion Good Will ethical Behavior
generosity and we experience the results and that keeps us leading uh going
onward it's leading us onward ultimately ultimately to uh to
freedom and there's a slightly different translation of this Pow
opo with it and it's inward leading as opposed to onward leading and uh and I I
appreciate that I appreciate these the both of them my sense is that this inward movement points to the Dharma
being found within us you know there is something within us that recognizes and
responds responds to our practice and our study of the Dharma also by aligning with the Dharma in an
intuitive way there's something within us it is the Dharma I think our inner
life uh comes to express the Dharma more and more as we continue to practice the
Dharma has become visible to us we see it we see it we begin to see it
everywhere think you know sometimes we talk about us uh looking at life through a Dharma
lens um but my sense is that the Dharma lens is not something that we put on
like a pair of glasses it's the actual way we see the world Looking Through The Eyes of our
heart maybe our our our whole being through a mind that's developed Clarity
and discernment and care for others we're in the Dharma stream in the
D Dharma stream is in us and we see the world through
that and uh there's a capacity listed in in the essay that I've been referencing
about performative literacy and I'll put a link to um to uh where that essay can
be found on the web in the chat uh at some point because someone asked about it yesterday and there might be some of
you who are interested in it um I think this uh uh I think all these
are really they're really relevant uh to you know our Dharma practice and this one I think really um really uh goes
along with h with the uh aspect of the Dharma being onward leading and it is a
tolerance for ambiguity for Paradox for
uncertainty I love this suggestion because I think sometimes Dharma teachings are ambiguous
they are kind of paradoxical for example the middle way
you know the M often we talk about the middle way is being uh neither driven by
sense desires nor driven by aestheticism you know somewhere somewhere in the middle and that's one way of defining it
and it that's not ambiguous or paradoxical that's just balanced but the middle way can also refer to ideas and
concepts related to being you know to identifying with a self and as you're
probably aware the Buddha wouldn't answer when people asked him is there a
self he argued against those who were uh eternalists claiming a permanent
existence for self or for anything else that exists and those who were
annihilationist who claimed that nothing really exists the alternative to the these extremes that that everything
exists eternally or that and there's a self that exists eternally and that or
that nothing exists at all was said to be teaching by
the middle teaching by the middle things arise due to conditions and they cease
when those conditions no longer exist the Buddha said for those who see
arising there can't be a aism and for those who see passing there can't be
eternalism neither one nor the other does the self exist it depends the teaching the Buddha
teaches by the middle so you know being willing to not
come down on one side or the other we rest in a kind of uncertainty you know
it depends things depend when we solidly identify around a when we solidify kind
of around a a concept like the existence or non-existence of a self then we we
put a block in that natural flow of the Dharma the flow that is leading us
onward it's the flow of life you know we aren't seeing the onward leading nature of the Dharma when we're trying to pin
it down to fix it in place the quality of inviting inspection also plays its
part in this you know we come we come again and again we come and see for ourselves we don't need to come to a
conclusion we keep looking wisdom comes as a result of
keeping looking so this quality of mind being tolerant of uncertainty it allows us to
let go of a desire for final truths you know for some ultimate description of
reality or of the purpose of human existence and some definitive answer to
the question who am I and uh you know I think uh as far as
I've been able to tell um this the humans have always had a desire for firm
answers to questions like this like you know what is the purpose of life you
know what's uh what when did the universe begin you know
there if we can't hand questions like that I think it it's
um you know it leaves us in a state that where we want the answers but it's
really s it's really simple uh excuse me it's not simple it's really it's similar
it's really similar to um the the uh the
situation I brought up yesterday um talking about how um Sheridan Blau
actually was the other day a couple days ago there were shared and Blau said that students who aren't able to um uh
understand a te a difficult text the first time they read it they think that they're not Advanced enough to to know
the answer they think they they can't uh they can't read but actually it's it's
not because of that it's just because sometimes there aren't answers to uh to
these questions I'm times we think because we can't figure out what's the purpose of
life that it's because we're not philosophically sophisticated enough um
but the Buddha often refus to answer philosophical questions you know does
does does having an answer lead to the end of suffering you know is it practical to have an
answer what's useful is knowing the answers to the questions that lead to the end is
suffering sometimes things need to stay mysterious you know when the when the
Zen monk who was sweeping the courtyard um was asked uh who are
you he replied that he was sweeping sweeping humans like certainty
you know it makes us feel safe but the Dharma is pointing towards becoming comfortable with un uncertainty
comfortable with uh with Paradox with inconsistency with inconstancy with
change there's that fourth quality of the Dharma the one I talked about yesterday
aaso inviting inspection come and see for yourself keeping the door open
keeping looking and connected to this tolerance for ambiguity is a willingness to change
our minds to engage with different visions of the Dharma and to keep our
interest and uh and uh our curiosity fresh to not come to conclusions it's
really essential I think uh to be willing to change our minds as a result of what we're coming to see in our
practice to accept that we might be wrong about something and to see that
it's not really a problem it's just part of walking the path discovering more as
we go we uh we can engage with uh people who
have different views you know and come to appreciate those views come to see the logic and the usefulness of them
without necessarily even taking them on just keeping our minds open to other
possibilities in uh in his essay uh Blau mentions methodological believing and
doubting these are two ways of engaging with ideas that we come in contact with
we can try an idea on for size you know for many of us probably early early in
our practice we were just kind of giving it a chance seeing where it might lead having a kind of tentative Faith
practicing believing as an experiment and then on the other side
there's methodological doubting we can ask ourselves what if my views about
this are wrong being willing to question our own views and perceptions to ask what if I'm
wrong about this what are the implications of that just looking deeper
for me um I think of this in terms of rebirth you know at at present I don't
subscribe to the idea of rebirth I don't have direct experience of it for sure in
this lifetime and I sort of subscribe to the idea that you know it's probably just a
a hold over from views that that were prevalent in India during the Buddhist time it doesn't seem useful to me in the
context of ending suffering in this lifetime but you know many teachers who
I respect who I respect a lot they do subscribe to it you know and maybe I'm
wrong maybe I'm completely wrong maybe it's true and what would that mean to
investigate that what are ways that trying on that belief would be useful in
ending ending my suffering
an open mind a mind that is still curious and tolerant of not
knowing um maybe even uh really enjoying not knowing keeping ourselves ready to
learn something new from our lives as each day unfolds you know while
following the compass of our hearts and Minds that are more and more clearly uh
keeping us in the current of the Dharma there's that onward leading stream or
just moving into the stream that's how I want to practice that's how I want to live my life keeping beginners mind
don't know mind along with the faith in the Dharma that uh that grows as our
minds you know gradually incline more and more in the direction of actions and
mind States and attitudes that arise out of goodwi and wisdom opo onward
leading so I went a little over today and uh I thank you very much for
your attention and tomorrow we'll talk about the last of these qualities of the
Dharma and I hope uh I think I'll try to get on YouTube way early and
see hopefully it'll work uh without uh having to get Kevin to help me but I'm
very grateful for his help so thank oh I'm going to put the I'm going to put the uh the link in the chat right now
it's a let's see if I can copy and paste
it yes it went in so
hopefully you'll be able to use that it's a really I think it's a really useful essay so um blessings to all of
you and I'll see you tomorrow