so hello everyone and welcome to
imc's YouTube meditation session and for this morning I'd like to keep
the sitting mostly silent and invite you
to um put together what I've taught so far the first two days which is to
whatever happens for you during this meditation whether you're it's your breathing that you're able to hang out
with whether it's sensations of your body sounds in the area where you're at
emotions or thoughts that you would recognize what's happening you
would know it by stepping back not being completely uh entangled involved with it
or reating to it or judging it just know it really simply and then uh with that ability to
not be entangled or reactive just to know it simply then come and respect it
come together and decide the right distance for your awareness to respect it
properly um if it's a mountain line in the wilderness the respectful distance
is really far if it's um you know a young child that is injured and you're
putting on a Band-Aid the respectful distance is much closer so find the place and then linger
stay connected for at least three breaths to whatever is happening and
then maybe return to the breathing and then that would be the Rhythm where in the Silence of this meditation you are
meeting yourself you're learning you're experimenting with how to be have the simple presence recognition with
anything that happens there's a meeting happening and in a sense you're meeting yourself maybe meeting yourself in a
deep way and how you meet meet it how you meet your experience is what this
meditation is about meeting it with a combination of mindfulness and
concentration so um then we'll just start and uh with no other preliminary
if you'd like to use a preliminary way of relaxing and settling in like we usually do you're welcome to
do that and otherwise you're welcome to um just begin as you wish but we'll
keep this silence
today
for
e
for this meditation instead of being lost in
thought or caught up in thought
thinking meet your direct
experience one at a
time giving time for each
meeting meeting with mindfulness and
steadiness
for
e
as we near the end of this sitting for whatever is your
predominant experience of the moment the direct
experience step back from it a bit and know it with
respect almost as if you bring your hands together to
bow in respect to whatever is happening allowing it to be as it
is knowing it meeting
it with respect and
care
and then to turn your attention
outwards to the communities and people around you spreading
outwards in your neighborhoods or counties
provinces and the people that you will meet knowingly or you know about or you
don't know today that in the meeting with
others can you meet them with
respect where you are independent not in Tangled with
them but able to see them clearly
kindly with
respect
independent but always ready in your at least your heart to bow in respect to
whoever you meet
regardless and for the people who are challenging for
us maybe we can imagine that one reason that they're
challenging for you their behavior is because they have not
received enough respect and care for their basic
Humanity and perhaps without agreeing with to
them condoning what they
do being independent of them offer them
respect may all beings be
happy May may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful and may all beings everywhere be
free and may our ability to meet with
respect promote this
possibility
thank
you
so hello everyone and welcome to this cont continuation of
the introduction to meditation series and for this
um current series that we're coming to the last week in the last week of
it and two announce ments one is that um probably I'll I'll start a new
series on Monday maybe it's introduction to meditation part two or maybe we call
it the intermediate instructions but um I think it'd be nice to continue on this
and build on what we've done these weeks and the second is that um there
was a time we used to do some uh Community meetings on Zoom usually on
Fridays at day end of the week and I haven't had the chance to do that for a long time but I do have this Friday so
I'll post a zoom link uh on imc's what's
new and to um and then I will um uh also announce it again and
I'll post it in the chat on Friday and we'll go there right after this uh meeting uh on on YouTube and those of
you like to come together will will have some time for maybe me for give some
updates maybe for uh you to ask me some questions and maybe for some breakout
groups so some of you can meet each other and have a small conversations
so so as for today the um the con continuation of practice the
deepening of mindfulness practice is greatly helped by wisdom wisdom is the
quality of understanding that supports us from uh that kind of protects us from
getting entangled being caught with what our experience is or what's happening uh
we don't get reactive we don't get attached we don't get uh resentful we
don't uh hostile to but rather what supports us to meet things with a
profound respect with a profound respect for ourselves where we can uh kind of hold
our seat uh take our place in a clear
upright way and um and uh and uh be able to meet people
with uh respect with kindness and maybe with
wisdom because we've taken the time to really know what's happening here and
now so one of the advantages of developing some concentration with
mindfulness is that concentration tends to quiet the thinking mind and as we as
the thinking mind gets quieter then uh we see the thinking mind
better uh it begins when it does arise we start seeing it in highlight against
against the silence against the Stillness often in daily life we're so
busy thinking we don't even know we're thinking distracted from distractions by
distractions and um and the thing thoughts might be coming so fast that we
almost don't have time to really assess what's going on but as we sit and
meditate there's a tendency to get calmer not always but when it does and
then we can start seeing the thoughts as they arise see them in highlight and we can start seeing the nature of some of
these thoughts we can start seeing them for what they are and in doing that we
become um uh you know able to see with uh start seeing something with uh free
of the lens of the particular Concepts ideas Paradigm even by which we're
living and um and we can see with fresh eyes see in new ways
and so to as practice develops we develop more and more wisdom where we understand better what's happening and
the understanding makes it easier not to get caught in it so I want to uh do a little showand
tell uh around um uh this and uh first
I'm going to hold up a flower and
uh and this flower um just you know it's
a it's a little flower of sorts and um
and a little purple and green and uh if you hold up just a flower it's just a
flower and there's a famous story that's told kind of Mythic story that the
Buddha was in an assembly of people and he held up a single flower and didn't say anything but one disciple
smiled and uh the Buddha uh recognize this and then uh recognize somehow The
Awakening of that disciple and um gave him permission to be a teacher
himself and um this is a story is particularly told in the Zen tradition
and so Buddha just hold up the flower and one of the things about the flower is the suchness of the flower just the
flower is itself and many times we think flowers are beautiful and appreciate
them and and um in Japan they have an sometimes a custom of having a single flower in a
special place in a toono a special uh um
Al Cove in the wall and the and by having just one not a big bouquet of flower but a single flower that then
highlights the specialness of the flower the thusness the sness the flower in itself when we put a big bouquet it's
beautiful maybe with colors and everything but the uniqueness and specialness of each flower is lost in
the whole the whole bouquet so just holding up a flower and so maybe we appreciate that
but then um we can do something different is I can hold
up um a different flower and uh and this one is new one is
smaller I don't know if you can how well you can see it but um it's a smaller
flower and uh so now we can say something we couldn't say before we can
say that this flower is the large flower and this flower is the small flower this
flower is the you know and uh and you know that's pretty straightforward and
obvious and if someone um if I ask someone to go get the large flower of
two flowers if this is what they were looking for they would bring this one to me so it's very effective if I have
something in particular in mind to uh to call this the large and this and small
but now look what happens if I I'll do magic in front of your eyes and you'll
see how the hand trick works of the magic so remember this is the small flower and this is a large
flower and um so now um I bring this
flower and now the flower that was a small flower before the big flower
before the large is now the smaller flower with this white one is bigger and
um and so now what was small what was uh large is now small right in front of
your eyes and uh and so it turns out that
large and small is not inherent in the flower
large and small involves the mental capacity to compare one thing and
another and so the flower in and of itself is neither large nor small it
just is what it is humans with their Capac our capacity to compare and our capacity to
have desires preferences the desire to make things happen in the world find it
useful to compare uh the large flower and the small flower depending on the
context but comparisons don't exist inherently in nature it turns out that a
fair amount of human suffering is one way or the other born from comparative
thinking that uh uh many people suffer because of their what how their body
looks and that means they're comparing their body to other people's bodies their hair their nose their fingers
their belly whatever and um uh or they're comparing it to some ideal we
have about how it should be it turns out the body parts that we have can exist
happily in their suchness they many times they can just be our hair can just be our hair our
hair is content to be what it is uh whether we have a lot or little or
something and um but it's because of our comparisons our values our Fe years our
stories we have around that we begin to suffer the We
compare histories and biographies and compare people by what we've done and not done we compare ourselves with our
past to our present our present to what our imagined future is We
compare uh um values We compare uh you
know goes on and on um what we this comparison one to the other we have
thoughts and we think that's the most beatific wonderful thought anybody's ever had we have another thought and we
think that we're we have the most awful thought that anybody's ever have and because and that involves
comparison now some of these comparisons have some usefulness u in order to get things done
in the world and um but uh if um but
it's also the uh the ways in which tremendous amount of suffering happens
if we sit in meditation we will might compare our breathing uh yesterday I had a deep long
sweet breath and today the breath is shallow and tight and we're comparing it
and through that comparison we want yesterday's breath or we condemn today's breath the breathing is just like the
flower the isness of the of the breath is just what it is a shallow tight
breath is just a shallow shallow tight breath it it's uncomfortable but that's
just discomfort in and of itself with no comparison to how it could be or how it
used to be and so there's something very profound that can happen when we see oh
my reaction my way of getting tight here or resistant or of uh getting mentally
entangled is born from the mental capacity to be comparing
things that's an activity of my mind as we meditate and get quieter that
activity has a chance to quiet down and we can see that it's somewhat
optional we don't have to always have these thoughts sometimes they're useful
as I said but often times they're a source of unnecessary suffering and meditation is a time where
we can't we try to give ourselves the gift gift of letting ourselves just be
in our isness the suchness you know just we are the
flower we are the single flower that's allowed to exist without any
comparison to anything else where the beauty the uniqueness the specialness of
each of us as flowers is allowed to just be as it is
regardless of the characteristics of our body
regardless of our belief systems regardless of our past and the future
regardless of whether we're healthy or sick or have
some limitation or not limited in some ways that all those things are something
we can respect and care for at the right time but to live caught in those or
oppressed by all kinds of things um is as major source of human suffering and
to sit in meditation think of meditation as the place where we are
allowed to Just Breathe just exist as we are to be our the unique flower that we
are and for a few minutes put aside all the comparative
thinking so that just to be alive is wonderful just to be here and now free
of all these comparisons and of course that's easier said than done and part of mindfulness
practice is when the comparative thinking arises to recognize it as
such and uh step away from it so we're not entangled with it turn around and
look at it clearly oh that's comparative thinking and and then meet it carefully
study ourselves on that oh that's how it is um and U maybe three breaths Journey
with that's the mind that compares then maybe feeling the physical
sensations of what comparative thinking is like feel the underlying emotion each
of them is given their time each we're met with we respect taking our time and
um and uh and perhaps you'll discover
the gift of letting yourself be a flower letting yourself just be yourself
breathing meditating just being
yourself practicing with that um so this
is how wisdom can operate part of wisdom and uh as your practice goes along uh
there might be a day where this kind of uh wisdom becomes obvious and available
and it'll support the further development of the meditation so thank you very much and I
look forward to meeting
tomorrow