so hello everyone and
welcome and now we're continuing this week with mindfulness of
emotions when I practiced in Burma there was no explicit instructions
on emotions however there was a very strong
emphasis on staying in the body being mindful of the s
ations that were at play in the body as we were meditating and the consequence of that
was that when we had emotions coursing through us the focus was not the emotion per se
but on the sensations in the body the physical expression of the
emotion and the and then the consequence of that is that we learned not to judge
the emotions not to react to them not to make a story of them or par participate
in the story making which sometimes fuels this the emotions but rather in a
sense to kind of a radical leaving the emotions alone not interfering with them
not getting involved in them and just feeling how they were being experienced in the
body so that was what we were taught and now that we're teaching this
mindfulness practice in the modern West there seems to be tremendous value
in actually naming mindfulness of emotions to make it a subject for mindfulness there's no reason not to the
way I was taught in Burma was in principle was we learn to be mindful of anything and
everything it's just they never mentioned emotions there and so here we can learn to be
attentive to emotions and there's many ways wise ways of being with emotions you know you can
journal with it you can go for a walk and feel them you can talk with a friend about what's happening for you with
emotions there's uh many things you can do around emotions uh so that are wise
and useful but what we do here in mindfulness is also a very wise approach
which is used ful to learn and in some ways it will support other ways if that's what you want to do but it's also
very powerful for itself and so what it came to then is that to learn how to be
present for emotions without interfering with them to be present without judging them
without repressing them without celebrating them or getting involved in
them in any kind of way it's very simple and the consequence of that is a very
deep respect for some inner embodied wisdom or process by
which our emotional lives have a chance to unfold with in their way just like we
allow a cut to heal itself our emotions are
not fixed things they are processes in motion and when we're in a sense wounded
emotionally something deep inside knows how to care for that when there's wonderful things
happening to us there's a way in which trusting the depth of what knows how to be here that can't happen if we are
reacting involved uh participating in the emotion it's
nothing it's it's fine to do those things sometimes but to learn the the
phenomenal benefit of mindfulness we put aside all the ways we
get involved and judge and get entangled with emotions in order to trust some deeper process that is not in our own
making and so two things uh that I find very helpful is
that when we sit to meditate we are intentionally giving permission for an
emotion to be there but the way we allow it to be there the second thing is I the kind of
this metaphor the image that I love for this especially when there's difficult
emotions is that we're taking uh doing the equivalent with attention with
awareness as we would be take our two hands to and hands together cup our hands and gently hold
something um maybe there's a little you know animal a kitten that's been born
that and you have to maybe carry it someplace and so you gently hold it in your open hand and you feel the
tenderness the softness the fragility of that kitten and you just hold it
gently and um so to come up underneath anger come up underneath fear come up
underneath Joy come up underneath um confidence and just allow it to be there and just
hold it and the way to hold it that that works is to feel the emotion as it's
expressed in the body with its Sensations the sensations of the emotion the
embodied um uh what is what is activating the body when the emotion is
present finding that place and then imagining we're we're giving permission there and just holding that
place and and so it's very similar to the exercise we did in the week for mindfulness of the body uh exercise with
a hand so we'll start with that exercise and then we'll apply it to
emotions so assuming and um a um meditation
posture gently lowering your
gaze maybe closing your eyes and let there be
a let your inner
attention be gently directed to your
body
and take a few gently gentle but deeper
breaths gently deeper just so it feels good for
you in a longer exhale letting there be a gentling of
your body a
settling
for and letting your breathing return to
normal just for next few breaths on the exhale relaxing your
body maybe feeling holding patterns in your body tensions as you breathe
in and softening around those tensions on the exhale
for
and now gently bringing your attention into
your D minute
hand
and then feel the sensations of your
hand and the idea here is to Center yourself on the
sensations without centering yourselves on the judgments the ideas of
hand with not centering your yourself on your opinion about doing this exercise
or being for or against what's happening without
analyzing allow the sensations of the hand to be there as they
are and it isn't so much that you're feeling them as it is you're attuned
you're you you know notice you see how the hand experiences
itself tingling
pulsing vibration warmth and
coolness maybe there's something unpleasant maybe there's something pleasant
contact of the hand against some other surface pressure
weight and allow the hand allow the
attention to gently roam around
feeling different parts of your hand in some random relaxed flowing
way without the attention being fixated
or zeroing in on any one place but just gently slowly taking
everything in in a gentle Journey around the sensations of
the
hand if it helps you to stay present you can imagine your
breathing your breathing is accompanying the hand or your breathing in and out
through the
hand
and now
notice how you're feeling in terms of your mood your emotional state
mind State the general state of being that
you have it might be very subtle it might be
strong it might be something not normally called an emotion
maybe might be a feeling of being settled or
agitated there might be subtle sense of worry or
fear or a subtle contentment
confidence there might be a sense of inner ease or
well-being it might be an inner sense of
unease we not feeling so well
in whatever way whatever mood emotion that's present for
you how is it experienced in the body what part of your body is
activated what Sensations are present related to that emotion
that mood that your
state it might be very broad
feeling maybe it's mostly in the Torso or above the
waist maybe it's throughout the body maybe it's mostly the front of the
body or the front front of the chest maybe it's very
specific in the belly pit of the
belly the chest around the heart in the face around the
eyes and once you local localize the sensations connected to the emotion
then in that that physical Place see if you can have the same kind of attention
as you had for your hand give permission for the sensations
to be
there and let your attention gently roam around that little that
location sensing feeling what's happening
physically in relationship to the
emotion if your state or emotion Fades away see what replaces
it if it gets stronger allow it to do so
whatever is happening to it give your emotion
permission to be present and permission to change in
whatever way that it it wants to
change maybe with a sense of awareness that is like two soft hands
coming below the emotion below the sensations to hold
them to allow them to be held and felt as they
are independent of your stories reactions
beliefs independent of
any story about them just allowing them to be there in their own
right and as you hold the emotion that way what
happens
and just gently allow your attention to move around the area of where the
sensations are so it mitigates any tendency to get
fixated caught reactive to your emotional
state for these few minutes trust the body trust the
mindfulness of emotions in this very simple sensory
way
centering yourself in the physical Sensations not centering yourselves in
the thoughts and attitudes feeling judgments stories predictions
and if it proves difficult to do this maybe there's a secondary
emotion that has to do with your relationship to the primary
one and maybe that secondary emotion needs the same kind of
attention
for sometimes it's easier to stay out of the
head and out of thoughts if you have your breathing
breathing with or breathing through the sensations of the
emotion
e
for
and then to begin ending this
Meditation Center yourself on your
breathing Center yourself on the body's experience of
breathing and gently take some little Fuller deeper
breaths longer exhale as you relax and let go and settle in
more feeling your body more fully more broadly wide panoramic sensations of
your body on the inhale and a saddling or grounding on
the exhale grounding in your weight in the surface that holds
up your body chair cushion
bed as you exhale is there anything it would be
useful to let go of any
thoughts
ideas letting go of whatever is
useful
and then in whatever the way that you feel more settled or open
or more tender or more connected to
yourself caring of
yourself can you turn that outward into the
world that allows for some
simple nonassertive [Music] non intrusive
way of feeling a connection or feeling a care or feeling
a tenderness to the world of people in
your life life in your communities and out across
the world privately that no one needs to
know wishing them
well wishing that your capacity for awareness and
attention is clear and clean so it can be a conduent of your
good will your well-wishing may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and if you feel a little
more tender vulnerable from this meditation this morning you might
repeat out loud or silently to yourself these phrases that I'll repeat
of good will may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may I be centered in respectful of
myself so in my my way I can contribute to the welfare of
others [Music]
thank
you
so so with this talk today becomes the third talk on mindfulness of emotions in
this 25 part series on introduction to
mindfulness and um one of
the challenges of developing mindfulness meditation
is the degree to which we identify with our experience and what identify means that
is we Define ourselves by it in some way or we uh are relating to emotions or
whatever is happening uh as if um uh we
are what's happening so if we have an emotion we must be that emotion it
defines who we are it it represents Us in some kind of important way so that
who we are as a person can now be judged based on what's
Happening and uh and with emotions this gets very tricky and partly because emotions are
so changeable and uh so conditioned and dependent on so many factors outside of
our own lives and um some of the emotions we experience are
conditioned by our society that we don't even realize how much we've internalized values of our
society and that these internalized values then become the basis by which we judge ourselves by which we feel
frustrated feel we U we want think things we like certain things we don't
like other things and in the wake of liking and not liking wanting and not walking wanting there can be joy and
happiness getting what we want there can be anger frustration not getting what we want there can be fear and worry about
how we'll be judged if we don't live up to certain societal societal
standards is a phenomenal amount of our emotions are not unique to ourselves but
are strongly conditioned by the the society the family the the friendships
the ideas of people around us and um and it's not necessarily wrong
for this to happen but uh to be caught in the net in the web of these societal
values in such a way that we are uh um debilitatingly uh caught in our emotions
our reactions our identifications around what's going on is one of the things that mindfulness is
trying to free us from and and to do this in relationship to emotions is phenomenally useful it's
not to dismiss anything but by but by being able to not be identified with our
emotions then we can start seeing much more clearly what is actually happening
it gives us a phenomenal insight into the cultural way that emotions are have
a are conditioned and the the values and beliefs from which they
come uh and we begin questioning not necessarily the emotions but we could connection we can start uh questioning
some of the underlying assumptions beliefs values that we don't even know
we're carrying that are the seedbed for some of the emotions we have and this is
especially true for the difficult emotions I mean certainly there's can be very strong grief that grief is to be
deeply respected and has a very important place in the heart and some something to really learn how to hold
carefully lovingly and grief can be entangled with
identity and how we should be and shouldn't be and and deeper assumptions
about who we are and what the good life is and all things that can add to suff
to grief so that there's unnecessary suffering connected to it so one of the ways that we then uh
practicing mindfulness is looking how to practice mindfulness without the extra layer of
identification the extra layer of telling a story about the emotion
perpetuating a story and instead not to not to again dismiss identification
dismiss storytelling but to put it aside for a while so we have something more
important to do with the emotion and that is to feel it and know it so we can
really know it in a deeper way there's there's a depth inside of us that is not
accessible uh easily if we stay in the storytelling mind if we stay in that
part of the mind that's uh preoccupied about what this means about me and who I
am and what I should do and what other people will think about me uh we have tremendous reservoirs of
wisdom of compassion of Love available uh deep inside if we can
drop below the the uh the kind of place we're
involved in navigating negotiating identity in relationship to the emotions
we have and so one of the powerful ways of doing that is radically simple and
it's not the way not the only way to be with emotions there's a lot of other valuable ways to be with emotions I love
the idea that we just go for a walk with a friend and have a chance to talk about what's going on and talk about how we're
feeling and uh that can be tremendously useful it can be useful to journal it
can be useful to dance the emotions it can be useful to express it in art
there's a many ways to work with emotions and as and one of those ways is
mindfulness and mindfulness has its own approach that uh is can be phenomenally
useful but it's not the one that's always always useful that you know it's not the be all and end all of how to be
with emotions so knowing that maybe it's easier to give oneself over to
mindfulness of emotions because we're not trying to make it the only solution
or the solution or the the but it's one way and to know that it's one way maybe
we can give ourselves okay for these minutes I'll do it I'm going to do it the mindful way and one of the mindful
ways is to um is is meant to be very simple and that
is to Simply find the physical manifestation of the emotion in the
body and as we feel it the physical Sensations then um give permission for
the emotion to be there if we give permission for the emotion to be there and we're caught up in the stories and
our reactivity then we're just you know perpetuating this endless cycle of of
feeding the story feeding the identity issues and that we have that can actually make it go on for a lifetime
but if we could drop below that and just feel the physical Sensations physical
Sensations are not just physical uh they are deeply connected to
the heart to deeper psychology of who we are that there's something profound that
can begin unfolding and working and showing itself when we drop down into
the sensation level of the emotion and it's there that we can give permission
for the emotion to be we make room for it by making room for the physical
Sensations and this image that I love is to take two cup hands and let the
awareness be like two cup hands that comes underneath a difficult emotion and
just holds it in it they're there it's okay I'm just going to be here with you I'll hold you
I'll be with you I'll feel you however long you need you have permission to be here forever it's okay that radical kind
of permission and then stay present and make room and allow for whatever needs
to happen with the sensations let them move and shift and and um and become
stronger become weaker just be with them as we do this we be we come to a
vantage point where we can now begin better seeing our relationship to the
emotion that in fact we hate it in in fact we love it and we're trying to hold
on to it in fact that we're the relationship is when we're not just letting the emotion be there we're
telling stories about it we're judging ourselves judging it judging other people we're seeing the the world
through the lens of that emotion if we're angry Everything is aversive Everything is wrong so we begin seeing
that is not just the emotion but it's also how we're relating to it or how we're caught in it or the stories we
make about it and um and so we're starting to see
as we settle down into just being breathing with the sensations breathing with the emotion at some point what
begins standing out in highlight is that we can't do that there's is in fact a
layer of reactivity a layer of judgment a layer of identif medication that goes
on and rather than seeing that's wrong or bad or reacting or being upset
because that's there if anything in mindfulness meditation it's more like we relax and say oh I see that's how it is
that's what's happening for me and um and so we see it and having
seen it and known it then you have the choice to say okay let me put that aside
and just stay more simply with the emotion now without that
reactivity or and we're still trying to be simple or we see well this reactivity
this judgment this identification there's a different emotion that seems to be the basis for
that let me kind of now do that simple mindfulness of emotion with the fear or
the anxiety that seems to be fueling the ID identity the way I want to identify
or disidentify with what's happening or maybe there's uh it seems to be that I
have a strong feeling of aversion that seems connected to um the
um the the way in which I'm aversive to my my don't like my
emotion maybe that aversion needs the same kind of careful feeling at the
sensation level make room for it to be there and um always kind of stepping
away from the story stepping away from the interpretation stepping away from from the the ident identification we
might have with it and this is a way of me lots of room lots of
Simplicity and to do that in the meditation posture where we're not going
to you know punch someone out or grab someone or run away or
just kind of just feel it with a guideline keep it simple keep it simple
as simple as you can what is a simple way of holding the emotion what's
happening trusting it's okay if I feel it in the body I can maybe just allow it
to go the exception to this is sometimes some emotions like
fear sometimes if we feel it um uh it actually can then reinforce more fear
and sometimes there's a loop that we we feel it and every time we feel it we get more afraid we feel it again we get more
afraid and and it can get out of hand a little bit so you have to kind of uh
same thing with anger same thing with despair or grief you have to have watch yourself monitor yourself to see and if
you feel like it's somehow uh there's a loop and it's getting stronger and stronger then you want to find some way
to uh switch what you're doing maybe um just go back to your breathing and not
focus on the emotion directly maybe it's to do love and kindness meditation maybe
it's to open your eyes so that that breaks the loop cycle and we kind of
look around and and just do mindfulness of seeing or mindfulness of hearing that
kind of helps us to dis get disentangled from this looping that goes on that can
uh make the things go get out of out of control so um but uh if it's not looping
and getting too intense um the possibility
exists of uh learning a radical Simplicity around emotions that's deeply
respectful of them allows them to do their own thing allows them to be there
without interference without analysis without fixing without
making it go away just allowing this the the wisdom depth within us to show us
away with emotions so uh for this day if you want
to explore your emotions further um uh periodically through the
day check in with yourself see what emotions you have and see how you feel
it in your body this with the idea a that just the physicality is a simple direct embodied experience and as you do
that um see if that helps you see more clearly what relationship you have with
the emotion are you for it or against it are you judging yourself because of it are
you telling a story like a prediction of the future or is it are your storytelling and that's what's fueling
it just see what the relationship is and once you've seen it relax come back into
your body a little bit and then continue with your day so thank you very
much