good evening can we have the volume up just a little bit
Jim so that um I don't have to feel like I have to yell how's this is is the volume okay
back there
okay so tonight I'd like to start off with a story that uh we find in the
sutas that is like the early Buddhist literature and it's about the day that
the Buddha dies it's not about the Buddha so much but that's the occasion
in which this uh happens and it's it's quite something
the Buddha has is talking to Ananda many of you know Ananda is his attendant was
his cousin but also somebody who helped take care of whatever need to be taken
care of at that time and he tells his attendant I'm going to
die today I don't know what his mood was but you know just kind of matter factly I'm
going to die he he knew he was dying and asks Ananda to prepare the
place where he's going to die so Ananda it's between these two Sal trees and he
bring pulls together stuff a soft place for the Buddha to lie
down and then uh it said that the Buddha laid down on his right
side and then did some meditation things
and then died but before that happens Anand says to abuda no no no no no don't
die here in this place he says um this is uh Maurice
Walsh's uh translation which I just love it's kind of fun he says so Ananda is speaking to the Buddha and he's saying
May the blessed one not die in this miserable little town of waddle and do
right in the jungle in the back of Beyond so he feels like the Buddha should die in a place where there's uh
people that can sub uh help put on a funeral or take care of what's Happening
he didn't want him to just die in some kind of uh I don't know just the back
Waters or something like this you know what Jim can we put the volume up just a
tiny bit just so it's a a little bit easier for me and in the bag there too
so I think this there we go maybe that's even a little
too too loud no I think it's okay thank you Jim I'll say a few words and then
I'll say no can you put it down and then no no can you put it up just
right don't say said it there yeah so Ananda is saying you know don't
die here in this place and that uh Ananda says well why
don't you die in all these other places and he lists a whole bunch of other cities and he says well there's more
wealth there there's like these more affluent communities and there are supporters of the Buddha and then we can
take care of the funeral and treat your death in the way that it's worthwhile
for somebody of your stature to take care of the death and then the Buddha says no NOP
NOP I'm going to die here and he tells the story how this
place it's at the time of the Buddha is called kusara and then he tells Ananda
it used to be called uh kavati and there at that time there was
this righteous King who was the ruler there and and kavati as a city was one
of the really uh robust prosperous cities and the King
mahasa was a righteous King and then the Buddha goes into this long story about
mahasa about the king who used to live at the place where the Buddha was
dying and then I'll tell you like the punchline of the end of the story uh the
Buddha says that he was that King in a former life so well hold that however
you like so um this King mahadasa the story is and this is a
story right this is very much a story he said that
um he saw a sign and he described it kind of like a
wheel like something that was up in the heavens he saw a sign maybe a star a
planet I don't know and when he saw it he took it as a
sign that he should go that direction so the King goes the direction of uh where
this wheel in the sky is and when he goes he's bringing his whole army with
him so his his uh elephants his horses and the uh attendants so they go
marching off in the direction of where this wheel in the sky
is and then when he he would get to this place where he felt like he was right
underneath it and he stopped and the people who were in that
location would go up to the king and says oh welcome Your
Majesty we are your subjects please rule
us so you know there was like no Army there's nobody taking over anything there's no Wars or anything like this
he's just getting invited in and said oh great okay you can be our new king you can be our new
Sovereign and the um King replied he gave them some
instructions his instructions are do not take life do not take what is not
given do not commit sexual misconduct do not speak falsehoods do
not take intoxicants and then this those many of you will recognize those five or the
five precepts and then the sixth one slips in there is and be moderate in
eating and so the people did and continued to be a prosperous place and
then this whatever it is in the sky that the king is saying is in a different place so then the King goes to that
direction same thing plays out the people are happy he's there he gives them instructions and they are a happy
Community you know this goes like all four directions all four cardal
directions so then he finally returns back to the capital and uh he's feeling
I guess particularly happy and generous and like this was quite something now
his kingdom is really large and there's people who are his subjects who are
happy to be his subjects and he says suppose I were to construct Lotus
ponds for the people and he did so and these Lotus ponds were lined with
these four colored tiles this gold silver barrel and Crystal Barrel I had
to look this up is a crystal like an aquamarine colored
crystal and there's in the there's these descriptions of these Lotus ponds they're very beautiful and and then the
king thought well what if I put flowers lotus flowers in these Lotus ponds and
blue yellow red and white flowers and he does and then he said well suppose I
were to place attendance on the banks of these ponds to help those who come
here and he does suppose I were to place charitable
posts on the banks so those people who wanted food or drink clothes transport
or sleeping place or money that they could go and get what they needed so
here's a king who's been very generous he's R he's giving them some guidelines
okay we're going to follow the pre precepts we're going to behave ethically but he's really taking care of
everybody there's a certain uh amount of a good will and a good feeling in this
uh Kingdom and so some of the wealthier members of the Kingdom said um let us um
make this great donation for you this King we're happy to have you as our King and he says no no I don't need
that um but then he says so they they
say okay we we'll just build you a palace and they build him a
palace and then the um the king becomes even more generous you can see where this story is
going right it's like this uh this idea where this king is just Bec enormously
generous and um and then he decides that he also wants to take care of all the
spiritual Seekers of the time you know like the the Buddhists at this time were mendicant such that they were have going
Ms every day right they didn't have any of their own food they had to go to Ms to get food from everybody so the king
helped uh support the Buddhist well the Buddhist didn't exist at that time in
this story but you know all the people that would go in um Ms rounds and then he decides to go to this
Palace that uh the wealthy members of his community had given to
him and he decides to and he go to do some uh to meditate
and to do some spiritual practice and then he he does something what I think is kind of
remarkable he decides he has this thought he has this question this
reflection of what action is it the fruit and result that I
am now so mighty and powerful he's asking how did I get here
why are things turning out so well why are people generous to me and
willingly becoming my subjects how did this happen and so often when things are
going our way we don't ask this question we just think like that's just the
natural order of the universe of course things are supposed to be go well for me and supposed to be easy in the way that
I want right we tend to think that and whenever it doesn't go that way then something's terribly
wrong but I appreciate this king is like how did I get here why is it this
way and so he um
he says this um why am I now so mighty and powerful and this expression that
gets translated as mighty and Powerful is also how the uh Buddha describes
himself and his students so that we can maybe draw some
parallels of how uh this king is is with how the Buddha was with this kind of generosity and supporting people giving
them some guidelines on behavior and yet um being very generous
but then the king he has this reflection well how did I get here and he comes up with some
answers and the first one he says is it's that there's three actions one was
uh generosity I started by being generous he took care of his
responsibilities like to the town's people and to the spiritual Seekers and
he had this where he thought about other people's welfare not just about you know acre more and more wealth or gaining
more and more power but instead was being generous to
others and we Al also can recognize how this so many good things come out of
generosity hopefully we've all been recipients of generosity when people have other people have helped us out or
like with the shared their resources whether it's time or money or expertise
with us and we know that uh what a big boom
that can be to be able to receive that but also how it's a good feeling in the
heart to be able to support other people in whatever way that's appropriate for us and what station we are in our life
at that time or whatever we feel that we can um offer this movement of
generosity because there's this way that that uh generosity like supports relationships there's a kind a little of
a knitting together of a relationship if uh somebody helps you or you help
someone and relationships are so important right we can't walk this path
this life this path all alone I mean we can but there's a a certain point in
which we also need to be aware of our connections with others and take care of our relationships
so the king reflects okay so part of his uh generosity is part of why he has this um
all these good outcomes from his life the second is this word that we don't
hear so much in the in the teachings is this idea of this uh inner
taming so I kind of like this word taming in some kind of way because uh
often not everybody but some people when they think about their youth when they were young they can can think about like
the wildness of their of their youth you know like maybe we did some things that were some irresponsible or a little bit
crazy and I remember uh you know I wasn't
certainly younger than I am now but uh there was a kind time when I uh lived on the east coast and um on Friday
afternoon we'd say you know we should go to Florida it doesn't matter that it's a
12-hour drive but you know for the weekend we should just drive down there
you know like some of this craz things that uh we would do just get in the car and drive and drive and drive and drive
and sleep I don't know it's just you know quite something just for the weekend to go down
there you know all of us have done things I imagine that's what we consider a little bit of a wildness in uh one way
or other and so we might consider this idea of inner taming the poly word is
dhama it sounds like so many other words but it's spelled differently than the
word that we sometimes say is Dharma and different than Danna
dhama and it's um this dama kind of is related to like
domesticate or so it's like the way to we domesticate ourselves it's this uh
inner taming and this way maybe we could say like coming home to ourselves
also and something that I appreciate so much about this is the it's not that we
have to like turn into something else turn into somebody else we don't have to
be like completely transformed into be somebody that we're not we get to be who we
are of course of course and the same way like you know
just what I imagine like if we were to tame a lion we're not asking the lion to
become an elephant of course not just to be a lion that um doesn't
eat the caretakers or something like this so if we're Lions we get to be Lions if we're
elephants we get to be elephants but there's this way kind of this inner taming this Taming of
the wildness which often just Happ happens naturally right as we mature
this is something that uh sometimes just as we get older we I don't learn more or
maybe run out of energy we don't want to do some of the crazy things we did uh when we were
young but I think importantly we can also we can tame our Tendencies to be
harsh with ourselves some of this wildness maybe is this way which we beat
ourselves up thinking that we're inadequate or insufficient oh you fool
you idiot why did you do that you shouldn't have done that or some of the things that we tell ourselves so The
Taming is part of like okay let's let that soften let's let that kind of like
uh drift away and not have so much Authority if that's a habit to berate
oneself it's not something that's going to go away quickly but we can take some of that power the energy away from
it there's also a way which you can taming is like to tame this uh our
tendency to want to distract ourselves all the time or feel like we have to be entertained or um not be experiencing
anything unpleasant and I know that sometimes I
do this that uh when I'm feeling a little bit agitated or or like I I I don't know just a little bit out of
sorts and sometimes I find myself you like jumping into a little project and
maybe the project doesn't have the highest priority but it's kind of a way to distract myself or do
something instead of just being with the feeling out of sorts or
uncomfortableness and just letting that kind of letting uncomfortableness be there
and letting it unfold instead of like turning away and getting absorbed in a
project or something like this so that was the second thing that
the king recognized of one was the generosity the second was this uh inner
taming D that he realized was supporting him having this good life and the third
is this uh Sam samyama also a word that's not so common
and we could think of it as kind of like restraint or some self-mastery
or self-control something like that but I'm
hesitant to use these kinds of words because then it feels like that we have to clamp down really hard on ourselves
and you know only be one way the
time but instead it's like to like
understand and regulate our responses like how we show up for whatever life is
bringing us so not just to be
uh just respond or we um yeah the word just slipped my mind
but not to when something arises not to just do whatever is comes first to mind
and is the easiest and the fastest and we don't care if it's going to harm anybody just do whatever we want instead
to uh recognize yeah you know in the bigger picture I think if I respond this
way it's going to be the most helpful for everybody myself others and both myself
and others but this um idea of like maybe self-mastery
first I want to reiterate we are not machines so we are not going to be
perfect like all the time of course not but this idea of kind of like
Mastery kind of like and I wish there were a softer word I'm not maybe some self- proficiency
or something like this it's this way in which there's this
uh encouragement for us to cultivate the talents and skills that we
have you know to become the best versions of ourselves as I said we don't have to be somebody else or something
else but to be the best versions of oursel and for everything I don't think
there are any exceptions for everything to have a certain amount of Mastery
requires practice requires practice I think many of you know that
um Malcolm Gladwell who had that book now I don't remember the title of the book but
uh Tipping Point maybe I'm not sure that one where he said you know 10,000 hours
right to do something in which you have some uh Mastery so practice right just to do something
repeatedly so but in order to do something repeatedly requires that we set the intention and that we value it
and and we're willing to put in some diligence and some effort and some
patience so these three things that the King when he did this reflection
generosity entertaining and self-mastery
but something I want to build on this so maybe I mean like what I'm saying isn't
a surprise like okay we can imagine that and we have this expression what goes
around comes around so if we're generous it's not surprising that people are generous to us as
well and if we practice on our skills and becoming the best versions of our s
our life unfolds in the best way it can but I also want to point out what I
started to talk about a little bit earlier this whole idea of reflecting how did I get
here when things are going well reflect that because so often we don't do this
at least I don't do this as much as I think I ought to or should or could or
one of those words right somehow when things are going well I'm just kind of going along with what's going
well it's when the difficulties arise is when we often are thinking like wait what how did I get here and how can I
remedy this so I want to just say here's a
short another little story that as it points to something similar and this is the Buddha this time
is talking to his son rahula and he's
uh in the middle of admonishing his son who had told a
lie and this is um you know not a good thing at all and I can imagine that the Buddha is
really disappointed but uh this is a little exerpt from this conversation that they're having and uh the Buddha
says to his son right here's a father and a son and the father is having this conversation with his
son and he says um rahula what is the purpose of a
mirror and rahula answers the purpose of the mirror is to
reflect venerable sir and then the Buddha says that's
right before doing acts of body speech or mind you should
reflect during acts of body speech or mind you should
reflect after actions of body speech and mind you should
reflect you should reflect did this act lead to harming
myself did it lead to harming others did it lead to harming both self
and others was it unskillful with the suffering as its
outcome and result or if while reflecting you know in fact
this act was wholesome and had Pleasant consequences and pleasant results then
the Buddha says then you should be happy and glad and practice in these with these
wholesome States so to unpack this a little bit that Buddha is saying okay reflect before
during and after acts of body speech and mind that's pretty much everything we do
right it's one of these things and so often in the teaching is
like okay well before you do it consider the consequences and while you do it you
know consider like okay does this seem right is this I mean the way I was thinking but so often afterwards we're
not necessarily reflecting did that turn out the way that I was imagining was there any harm
caused and if not in fact if there was this increase and helpful wholesome
skillful states can we be happy about that can we
have some Joy about this can we have some gladness about that as a support for our practice and
as a recognition that okay we're finding our way I kind of want to highlight that
this you know this joy and gladness is like an integral part of the practice it's not like we always have to
be you know buried down and like oh got to do
this and chastise ourselves when we don't meet up with the measurements we
have for ourselves but instead to notice like oh okay that was a good thing but I
did I didn't know nobody got harmed and there's a little bit more peace or ease
or freedom in the
world so there's this thing about like to evaluate the results of our actions
is kind of what the Buddha is pointing to in these are two different
stories it takes it takes some real honesty and it takes some
maturity it takes some honesty that um because so often we want to think of
ourselves as somebody as being a good person that's not harming anybody or not
uh doing things that are UNH wholesome unskillful
unhelpful so it can be hard to see like oh yeah that
yeah that actually wasn't a good idea there's some obvious things that we
do where it's very clear that people were harmed but maybe there's some subtle things that we do that aren't so
helpful and can we recognize that and learn from it without beating ourselves
up sometimes is the tricky part sometimes we can fall into this tra
like oh I can't do it I've I'll never be able to get it everybody else can do it
but I can't you know there's some version of that but there's a certain honesty of
saying you know actually I see that I had mixed motivations why I did
that and I was only when I was thinking of doing I was only thinking of this one
motivation that made me look good and made me feel good but now now I can see I
also wanted people to notice me or I wanted
to undermine that person over there that uh I don't get along with in that other
department or the neighbor or whomever it might be or maybe there's this way in which
we will feel like that uh maybe the motive is maybe we just wanted more
attention or we wanted more
anything really and we don't often want to admit that to
ourselves so to evaluate the results of our actions requires a certain amount of
honesty that rather than trying to just preserve our self-image or and our
self-image may be a negative one so rather than like oh yeah of course I didn't do it right or it might be one
that's like Oh I'm a good person I do everything right but just to see no actually it was mixed here and what can
I learn from that and it also takes some
maturity is being able to recognize oh yeah okay this is some of my motives
actually aren't so skillful and um even though I really want to I'm not going to do this even
though I think it's going to make me look good I'm not going to do it because
it can cause harm or maybe there's this way that
um the maturity is maybe just even to recognize that the the this Minds have
kind like a committee inside with these different motives and these different um
pressures to behave in a particular way or to be seen a particular way and it
takes some maturity to say oh yeah it's not black and white I'm not black and
white I have a mixture of stuff going on inside just like everybody
else and so is there a way that we can learn to say you know what I'm going to say no to those things that aren't
helpful but not know in a way that's like we're going to repress are those uh
motivations that we might have that aren't so skillful or wholesome
so much of this practice is uh becoming whole like inviting in all aspects of
ourselves and so the majority to recognize oh yeah okay I have this I
really dislike my neighbor's dog who is barking all the time and I often have
ill will towards this dog for example and then just to recognize that
recognize that this when you are filled with ill will kind of like the tightness
uh there's a collapsing it say your life isn't getting better and maybe you're not harming with your actions or your
speech but there's this way in which in the mind this kind of like a this ill will can kind of
fester and can really undermine a sense of well-being that we might have
and so there's this way that maturity maybe I would say also is about
recognizing that our sense our self-esteem our sense of being an okay
person it's really fragile if it's dependent on always getting things
right because we're not always going to get things
right it's we're humans and we're not perfect we not completely
awakened I suspect if any of you were completely awakened you wouldn't be here on a Monday night You' be out there
doing whatever completely awakened people do so there's this way in that uh to
recognize there's nothing demeaning by re by saying you know what I made a mistake I did that action it didn't turn
out the way that I thought or maybe it did turn on the way that I thought and now I realize that that was my I had
some unskillful ideas there's a way in which we can
recognize that like our dignity lies in just being able to recognize our
mistakes our dignity lies in just making a resolve
like okay I learned something there what can I do so that I don't do that again
or to have this uh to remind ourselves that
oh yeah I've learned this before when I've I've been uh encountered a dilemma
on whether my coworker who irritates me no end but yet uh wants my help am I
going to help them or am I going to turn them into the boss or am I going to put them down I don't know there's so many
different things here that we could say or
do so this idea of reflecting after our
actions and the story of the King was kind of like this long story but uh the
Buddha wanted to point out kind of like the power of just recognizing oh
yeah how did I get here and then to finish this story of
King mahasa he was so generous with the Lotus ponds and the all these things that he was
given to this people he went uh into Retreat decided to practice and this is
the before the time of the Buddha so Buddhism holds that you can't didn't
couldn't become completely awakened but you became as awakened as a possible
without a Buddha so he had this like the best possible outcome for his life after
this so to reflect after we do things and then to have some of the honesty and
maturity to just recognize yeah that wasn't so great and to have some the
words p and Poma have some joy and some gladness when we recognize oh yeah that
was good that was uh that was helpful for others from myself or both
self and others that was that was the right direction to
go so I'll end there and I'll open it up and see if there's any questions or
comments this idea of reflecting maybe I'll just say I kind of
like that uh here we are you know thousands of years ago there's a little bit of a word play that still um works
today like what's the purpose of a mirror to reflect and we still have that in the mind you know to reflect in the
mind so something that worked thousands of years ago is still working today
so um my question is cuz of the three things um you the second was this the
the tame oneself and then the third was self-mastery what what would be the
difference this is a perfectly reasonable question so I would say that uh
entertaining is more about um I kind of I was using this word of
wildness so some of the patterns that we do that are not so helpful to diminish
the amount we do those patterns and so so that's more about to not do things that are unhelpful and then Mastery we
could say maybe to do things that are helpful so there you know really do we
need to make a distinction maybe not but uh in this list there was there thank
you anybody else have a comment or
question and I appreciate this idea of rejoicing uh when we have realized we've
done something well just like how the world would be different if people were happy when they did things well instead
of always beating themselves up yes Peggy hey um I don't I don't think I
have a question but um you said reflecting after you do something and um
and I've had a really good week um I've been in a better mood than usual I usually lean a little towards being
depressed and um just kind of happy this week and um and a few encounters that is
sort of my work that um it was helpful to people and and I'm just feel grateful for that but the odd thing is when I
think like how did I get here I haven't meditated in a week well here I am and
this morning but um so I thought that was odd and my classes I have a couple classes that are part of practice and I
haven't been attending to them either so it was like that's kind of weird but
maybe I don't know I thought maybe I was putting too much pressure with too many things on myself possibly and um I think
you sort of said I gave myself more of a break because I was busy with other things so maybe that helped I don't yeah
there is a way in which having a regular meditation practice can be like this oppressive thing that we feel like oh I
have to do this and I don't know if the course is the case for you but there can be some benefit to like backing off a
little bit and you know being able to see things a little bit differently I don't know Peggy if that was yeah I was
thinking that maybe like finding the balance somewhere yeah thank you it's
hard to fit everything in in life it is it's hard to fit everything
in hi um I really appreciated what you
mentioned about um how um if we sort of
Base our sense of self on whether we succeed or fail at something it's sort of a fragile sense of self um and I also
thought it was interesting and really useful that you talked about how um our
Dignity should come from the fact that um we sort of have the ability to
reflect on our actions and um make better
decisions following that yeah thank you yeah great great thank you
okay so thank you thank you all for your practice and I'm wishing you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you