okay let's go ahead and get started for those that I don't know my name is May
Elliot and this week we'll be exploring the Buddha's five daily
Recollections sometimes called the five remembrances or five Reflections and uh these are a series of
Reflections that the Buddha recommended that we we actively bring to mind daily
and when I learned that there was a practice that the Buddha actually recommended daily it really caught my
attention I was like oh well this must be important um however when I learned
what they were I realized they really weren't easy Reflections but I could see
how tremendously beneficial they could be um and when I actually practiced them
that's what I found so hopefully you'll think so as well so here are the five um
and to and we'll start with the first one today so the first is I am subject
to aging I have not gone beyond aging the second I am subject to illness
I've not gone beyond illness I am subject to death I've not gone beyond
death the fourth is I must be parted and separated from everyone and everything
dear and agreeable to me and the fourth I am the owner of my deeds and heir to
my Deeds Deeds are my womb my my relative my refuge I shall be the heir
of whatever Deeds I do whether good or bad so these are the five we'll do one
each day um and uh during the meditation period we'll actually practice with the
remembrances so today I'll provide a slightly longer uh premeditation intro
just to share about how we'll actually practice with them so we'll begin with just some quiet breath meditation so
that your minds can settle a bit become a little more calm and then I'll offer two ways to practice
with the recollection we'll start with um uh just dropping the phrase into the
meditation kind of like dropping a pebble into a pond uh without conceptualizing a response just seeing
what naturally ripples through the mind and heart uh so that's the first method and
then after that and maybe I should say that could be complete in and of itself that can be a complete practice but just
to offer you a variety of ways to practice with these teachings um we we'll do a second method and during the
second method we'll actually do an Engaged contemplation so a word on contemplation
um uh in these sorts of uh meditations we're actually we're we're intentionally
inviting thinking to occur um around a specific theme um but given that the
mind can be very discursive and one thought can easily lead to another and another and another um we're going to
keep a short leash on the thinking so so that um keep that in mind as we do the
contemplation and I'll remind you of that during the meditation um so that might sound like a lot um but
we'll keep it very simple just these two different practices um so uh returning to our
phrases um again today I am subject to aging I have not gone beyond aging and
while we all know this the purpose of this reflection is to help it sink more deeply into the heart to help us realize
it more fully so so let's see what happens during the meditation so go
ahead and find your meditation posture a position that allows you to be
both alert and
relaxed maybe Beginning by taking a few deep breaths
connecting with your meditation anchor that might be the breath maybe listening to the
soundscape may be a global sense of the body sitting or lying down in whatever
posture you're
in inviting the mind to rest
to settle on your
inchor so we'll have some time in silence now just to to
land to connect with the here and [Music] now to
settle
e
e e
you notice that the mind is wandering gently and kindly bring your
attention back you might slide your attention back to the
Anchor especially if you're noticing that you're jerking the Mind back or tugging the Mind back to the present
just a smooth non-reactive slide back to the
now
e
e e
shift now to introduce our
contemplation just like dropping a pebble in a pond we'll drop in our
reflection just allowing the words to move through the mind and heart and body
and seeing what ripples out no effort to make anything happen or to squint to look too
hard here's the phrase dropping this in I am subject to aging
I have not gone beyond
aging just seeing what happens maybe nothing maybe
something I am subject to aging I have not gone beyond aging
or sometimes translated old age I am subject to old age I have not gone
beyond old
age taking a minute or two to play with this on your own at your own pace
maybe there's Sensations in the body maybe certain thoughts come to mind
and if they do you can include them you don't need to push them away you can see what sorts of images or
words arise in the mind it's part of the Ripple
and when you're ready letting go of the phrase and coming back to your anchor
allowing the mind to collect and settle once
again e
introduce our second form of
contemplation that'll include a little more
thinking this is our engaged contemplation we'll offer the phrase
again and this time with some questions to allow you to think about the
phrase see what comes up for you and I'll offer several several questions and
you don't need to reflect on each one uh just pick up whatever stands out to
you I am subject to aging have not gone beyond
aging so How Deeply do you know this do you know it conceptually only or
do you know it in your
core when you visually see that aging is happening how is it for
you maybe wrinkling skin sunspot graying
hair maybe a change in ability [Music]
levels how is that for
you it might be thinking that arises out of these of course but don't forget to
include the body so there may be some thoughts and there maybe physical Sensations emotions that arise so we're
including it all
when you feel Aging in the body how is that for you maybe less strength less
functionality i' had mentioned less ability
maybe memories come to mind a tenderness in the heart just
holding all of this with gentleness and kindness
when you consider old age is there fear if so what are you afraid of
what are you looking forward to what are you looking forward to as
you AG some of you of course May identify already being in deep old
age we we're all getting older we're
lucky so as you get even
older is there anything you're afraid of or looking forward
to e
imagine yourself in your ideal old age what does that look like what does
that feel like reflecting on this what does it feel like in the
body your ideal old age
coming back to the breath the body letting go of the
inquiry settling back into silence
if there's any tenderness in the heart whatever may be reverberating from the
contemplations including those including nose in these moments of Silence
together making space for them holding them with kindness and
compassion
gentleness
e
e e
knowing that all beings are subject to
aging may all beings be joyful and
happy may all beings be strong and healthy
be may they be safe and protected and may they live peaceful and
at ease
thank you for your
meditation welcome
back so for those who are just arriving welcome to you my name is May
Elliot and I'd like to start with a poem po by K Ryan it's called the Niagara
River as though the river were a floor we position our table and chairs
upon it eat and have conversation as it moves along we
notice as calmly as though dining room paintings were being replaced the
changing scenes along the Shore we do know we do know this is the Niagara
River but it is hard to remember what that
means so here we are all floating down the Niagara
River we're all on this boat calmly rearranging the furniture watching the
passing scenery and as K Ryan it we do know that we're all on the Niagara River
but it's hard to remember what that means so it's hard for us to remember
that as we live our lives we're all making our way to Niagara Falls we all
have an expiration date in other words we just don't know what it is yet so it's it's not news to any of you
that there's aging sickness and death and yet we don't often live with this
understanding so the Buddha provided us with a teaching so we could remember you
could remember what's hard to remember and what he offered us are these these five phrases five daily
Recollections um for daily reflection and for those just tuning in
I'll share them again I am subject to aging have not gone beyond aging
I am subject to illness have not gone beyond illness I am subject to death have not
gone beyond death I must be parted and separated
from everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me and lastly I am the owner of my Deeds
which sometimes translated as actions I'm the owner of my deeds and heir to my
Deeds Deeds are my womb my relative and my Refuge I shall be the heir of
whatever Deeds I do whether good or bad so these are the five and
clearly they're not easy they're uh they're not easy Reflections so we'll be
talking about that over the next couple days um and these come from um from the
angut nikaya 557 upana Su and they appear elsewhere
in the sutas as well so this this first phrase today I am subject to aging have
not gone beyond aging so we're all growing older and yet
we forget or actively deny aging um and you know this is common trying to look
young forever with products and surgery and all number of things I had an an
elderly Aunt who was very into making herself look young and she went to Great Lengths and great expense to do so and
um she wasn't married and she was she was dating well into her 80s and so here
she is she's in her 80s and when she'd go on a date and a man would ask her how old she was she would say I'm closer to
60 than 50 but she'd say this when she was in her 80s and technically it was true she
was closer to 60 than 50 but it was also a little misleading so people do all
sorts of crazy things to keep aging away and it makes sense because Western culture Rejects aging you know that
further amplifies our tendency to forget uh but something I find
intriguing is that this uh this tendency isn't just a present moment phenomenon
2600 years ago during the time of the Buddha people were also forgetting forgetting that aging sickness and death
are coming um that I am of the nature to grow old to get sick to
die uh so the Buddha must have realized that for most people these truths had not fully penetrated the psyche that the
the conceptual mind knows this but the heart doesn't so these these uh these
phrases they function to move move this truth these truths from the head to the
heart so through Daily Reflection uh we uh we can learn to live more in harmony
with aging not go to war with aging with these different experiences of life so
in a lot of ways we might say this is uh an acceptance practice we're coming to
terms with the way things are um because so much of our suffering
actually comes from being in contention with the way things are with the way things have come to be and part of learning to accept the
truth of Aging sickness death loss um is really it's a shift in our expectations
such that we're no longer surprised when they come for us so that's part of the way this functions the shift in expect
expectations um the former abis at Green Gulch F shider used to
say when firemen get to a fire they don't scream oh my God it's a
fire no they've expected that's where they're going of course there's a fire
there no surprise so one way we suffer with aging sickness and death is that somehow we're
surprised by it it's like oh no what's happen happening something has gone terribly wrong
Frank ostaseski the co-founder of Zen hospice um he tells a story about a very
elderly woman on her deathbed and I don't recall exactly um she could have
been in her late 90s 100 something like that and from her
deathbed she whispered why me why
me so how can we shift our expect patients such that we don't take aging
and death as a personal affront on the contrary when we age it's
actually things are going right this is actually how it's supposed to happen and will happen and has been happening since
humans existed so one way these Recollections function is in in remembering them daily
is we become much less surprised um and and with it less fearful Charlotte Bronte quote to see
and know the worst is to take from Fear her main
advantage to see and know the worst is to take from Fear her main
advantage so when we've come to terms with the worst case scenario I am going
to get old I am going to get sick I'm going to die I'm going to lose everything I
love when we've come to terms with this here has lost its power over us in a lot
of ways and with it of course aversion has a whole lot less power over us because
this practice invites acceptance so uh at one point I was
exploring this practice um more rigorously and I
discovered an app a phone app called Aging booth and so you put a photo in you
press a button and it will age you by about 40 years or so so depending on how
old you are um some of you are already in your elderly Years and may not feel like you need any help visualizing what
you'll look like in old age um but for those who don't look so old yet Um this
can be a striking experience and to to face the reality of what's to
come and remember there's only one thing that can prevent aging and that's death
um so with this in mind maybe we should be delighted to
age and of course that's not the typical response so so by realizing these
truths um aging sickness death loss um the effect one of the effects is that we
actually can learn to live differently you know how does remembering these things affect what you
prioritize how does it affect uh what you allow yourself to become entangled
in or uh get upset over does it bring
perspective how would you spend your time if you really knew that death could happen at any moment that you won't um
have your faculties Forever how does it impact your
relationships your willingness to forgive
so this is one of the fruits of this practice is that it um it changes our
priorities and it changes how we engage in the present moment so another function of this
practice um each of these these these phrases has a different function so the
the Buddha named a different function for each phrase so um so I am of the nature to age has the function of quote
overcoming the conceit of Youth overcoming the conceit of Youth so in
other words the the sense of immortality the sense um that this energy this
Vitality will be here forever um and instead uh realizing that Vitality is a
temporary resource can we appreciate any Vitality that we currently have any Vitality that
remains so as I mentioned earlier um as we do this practice it can be
difficult and I'm I'm not sure these phrases can be treated lightly on the contract contrary um and especially as
they progress they seem to get a little hard one through the first through the fourth and to get a little harder and a little harder as as they go for people
not for everyone but um with this in mind um please be be gentle with
yourself uh with when engaging in this practice I am of the natured age may may
not push any buttons for you um but some of the next ones
might so um yeah so please be gentle with yourselves titrate this practice um
little by little in small ways we really don't want to weaponize these phrases um
and use them in a way that that takes us out of our bandwidth of tolerance or that provokes grief in any way that
overwhelms our capacity to be mindful and if difficult emotions do
arise can just practice by recognizing them allowing them and remembering that
that these feelings are the same that move through all human hearts this
is this is uh the natural purification process um that humans experience when
they come to terms with these truths now not my grief but the great grief that
belongs to no one and visits visits us
all uh so if if it's uh supportive as you do these practices um you might you
might close with some meta or self self-compassion practice you something to sooe the heart if it's become
agitated um so let's close together in that way may all beings be happy may all
beings be healthy may all beings be safe and may
all beings be at ease thank you so much for your kind
attention today it's so nice to be back with you and I look forward to seeing
you tomorrow take care everyone