so good morning everyone and welcome to IMC I'm delighted that you're here and we get to
be together and um one of the purposes of Dharma talks
is to teach about the practice of mindfulness practice of the Dharma
practice and so we might talk about meditation we might talk about mindfulness in daily life we might talk
about the practices of Ethics all kinds of things and and one of the principles of
mindfulness is everything is practice so one of the very important practices in Buddhism that is the
practice of listening to a Dharma talk which is what we'll talk about
today and uh and so one of the interesting things about talking about
Dharma talks the practice of listening to a talk is that all of you for the
most part are going to be listening to this Dharma talk and so it's about you and you're
listening so I want to um uh read this little story from this book The
Monastery within a monastery within a young woman from another
country moved with her family to live for one year in a town near the
monastery when in the course of the year she discovered the monastery she would
periodically visit to have discussions with the abis the abis introduced her to
meditation which became very meaningful for the young woman when the family's one yearlong
stay was drawing to an end the young woman said ask the
abis in my country there is no Buddhism and no one has even heard about about
meditation how can I continue to learn and deepen the practice you have started me
on the abis said when you return home ask far and
wide for who among the wise people is
recognized as having the greatest ability to listen ask that person to instruct you
in the art of listening what your learn about listening from such a person will teach
you how to further your meditation practice the art of listening those
people who were the direct Disciples of the Buddha were called in the ancient
language the listeners the Savas those who listened and in the ancient world
listening was a primary way of getting information from others there was no
nothing written really at back then and there was no you know Twitter
or to get all kinds of things uh it was all through the voice and people if they
wanted there's no libraries so if you wanted to uh remember what was being taught you
you really had to pay attention closely so it went in and stayed there so you can remember it afterwards it's a very
different way to listen if you're taking something in in order to retain it for the future
requires a higher attentiveness a higher receptivity a higher sense of presence
less distraction less scattered of the mind and um it turns out that those
qualities are really important for the Dharma
practice and in fact when the Buddha when he gave Dharma talks uh he gave
particularly profound teachings when he understood that the
audience the mind of the audience people in the audience was ready
receptive free from hindrances um uh uh
elated and bright the word bright sometimes translated as confident
trusting so there was a a recognition that a certain State of Mind can receive
teachings in a very different way then uh if you're scattered and spinning
and preoccupied with all kinds of things if you're if you have an attitude of resistance and you you know you don't
like this you don't want to be part of this or something um how we are how we show up is actually very important part
of the listen the practice of listening to a Dharma talk and it's so so significant that
um um there's if you're listening Ling to a
Dharma talk for the Dharma you'll find it the Dharma in the
listening so it's not in the words necessarily it's not out there in the
speaker but you turn the attention backward on itself what you're looking for is in the
attention what you're looking for is in the looking what you're hearing for is in
the hearing it's a quality of attention that we're really focusing on here and then
with a a certain quality of attention we have then we are can listen and be
receptive in a way that's uh touches something really deep inside so there's many ways of
practicing with the Dharma talk and uh when you listen to them and and what
strikes me as I give this talk is how how much listening to Dharma talks is going on in this world in a way that I
don't think has ever gone on the history of humanity I mean among some people I mean there's still a majority of people
in the planet don't listen to Dhat talks but uh but those in people in our
scene it's phenomenal how much people listen I mean when I was uh growing up
in the Dharma I was lucky if I had listen to One Dharma talk a week sometimes might
be a month before there was an opportunity to be with the teacher like it was in the monastery we didn't have D Dharma talks that often and the Abbot
didn't come through that often and sometimes we'd have two or three in a row two days and three days in a row but then he wasn't around and and so to this
idea of listening to a Dharma talk was kind of unusual and uh in um in the you know in
histo in historical times not so many decades ago in Thailand there are stories of uh people who are really
serious about the practice who would walk for weeks because you know you couldn't get
in a plane you couldn't go in a train they'd walk for weeks searching from for a teacher who was going to give them
teaching so imagine you know the preparation that takes and imagine
showing up to hear those teachings after all that searching for that person walking through the jungles of Thailand
and you know and contending with tigers and wild elephants and finally you find that person and said well I don't really
feel like it today and um so uh so you know it
brought a certain kind of seriousness attentiveness and there is a lot of seriousness about listening to Dharma
talks but they're so readily available uh through technology now and there are people now who listen to
Dharma talks every day and some people I know who do more and sometimes you know
it's been a tremendous support and help for people uh listening to talks and
sometimes it's a lot better than the alternative that's available to them with their own mind and activity and whatever's going on and this regular
listening to it and people listen have discovered all kinds of ways to listen that didn't exist in the old world I
know people told me they listen together with friends it used to be when they I guess before Bluetooth they would have a
wireless you know wired mic with two you know for one for each year but the friends would walk along with one in
each other their ears walks they go for walks and just listen together that way
or people go for runs people listen to Dharma talks going to work and
um and so there's something something that about Dharma talks and now now it's just not budism even it's podcast people
listen to there's something about the oral word that people aren't reading as
much as they used to dharm used to be that Dharma books was the thing to do and uh and kind I grew up in Buddhism
was mostly in the books and I had whole art to how to read Dharma books that really when I was in
the monastery to really to the reading itself the way I read was the
Dharma and um and but now we're going to the oral which is historically what
always happened and there's kind of different richness in the oral uh spoken
word it conveys much more than just sometimes the words do you get some kind
of the tone the speed the Cadence uh sometimes you're lucky or the teacher's
lucky uh something of the teacher's practice comes at through and how they speak and and so it um you know that it
conveys more than just the content in the words and so how to listen one of
the things is to listen to more than just the words to listen to what else is being
conveyed there's a some people talk about there's a transmission sometimes in a Dharma talk I've listened to talks
from teachers who just transmitted kindness and it just it was so wonderful just to feel the kindness they didn't
understand their talks but the kindness really touched me or the
compassion sometimes it was Clarity and sometimes some people were so clear on how they spoke the Dharma that I could
have certainly understand them but there was something really brilliant that it did to me to hear the clarity in which
it was presented like wow made my mind somehow clear and
listening there's uh some people um when they give talks uh uh their confidence
in the Dharma is what's contagious and the words are fine but what really changes the people who
listen is the wow this person feels has a lot of confidence inspiration around it I'm inspired Now by this person's
confidence I bu you know something so there's all kinds of other things that we can take in besides the word
there's also um what we're listening for and I think that over time listening
to Dharma talks changes what people listen for uh I think when people are new it's
pretty common to listen for the content the words the meaning some people are and it's really meaningful and really
powerful sometimes to hear some of these teachings for the first time and
um and I've been told by people like the first talk they ever heard just blew them away or the first talk they heard
something shifted inside of them and um and for most of it's later
but you still it can happen but we're listening for information we're listening for practice we're listening for something that makes sense out of
life and often it's a content of the words that were what's being said as people start doing the practice
and maybe they've listened to a lot of talks the content is still important at times but there might be other things
that are going on that are important and um when I was in the
monastery um um I I listen we always would sit in
meditation during the talks so meaning even our eyes would be you know either
closed or in Zen you look your eyes down in the in Zen there was a very formal
meditation posture to be in so we would be in the meditation posture listening to talk with the eyes down there was no
nodding you know oh that's good which is nice because then this then the Dharma teachers gets feeds back
and you know and you know sees what's going on the energetically and stuff but we were just there sometimes and I I had
this wonderful wonderful uh there's a Zen upside down smile which I'm I'm very
capable of sitting there it probably looked a little intense but you know came from some some
things do with concentration or the ier and um but I would sit there and
listening to the abbit very attentively but what I what my mind I was in my meditation State and what my mind was
drawn into was the The Voice what's being
spoken and I would get more concentrated listening to the talk than I did in my own
meditation and that's not uncommon for some people to have something about a certain kinds of Dharma talk people get
absorbed into the words so they don't necess the words become more less and less important as they just kind of
right there not mind is unwavering not moving at all just absorbed in it and I
would leave The Talk completely still completely open relaxed I'd walk outside
and just be in awe of the sparkle of everything and the peace that I
felt other times I would be meditating with the talk and you know kind of
didn't hear much it kind of went washed right through me and that's a whole other art to do is to allow the talk to
wash through to stay present for it but don't hang on to the words don't repeat
them don't question them and don't apply them oh you know this is interesting and
you know and you know and now think about other ways I can I can listen to the Dharma I'm sure I now I have this
device in my kitchen that talks to me and I can talk to it and I can just call up all kinds of Dharma and you've lost
touch of my talk because you're already applying it and um the other thing is just is
just let it stay in it but let it wash over you wash through you with a principle that if what's
important for you to hear if there's something important for you to hear um
it'll stick it'll touch something so you don't have to be looking and trying and
straining to kind of find something and get something as if you know you're trying to grab hold on tight for
something important you want to just be very receptive and see what Finds Its
way to your heart or find ous way to some depth inside of you and I've had that happen to me where I was just
following along following along just letting it wash through and then I was but in this receptive state that I'm
in I hear a sentence hear a word boom you know something happens and I've
known people who it was just a word someone said and boom that just kind of
made shift at things or organized their mind their thinking or the puzzle of their life kind of came together and fit
together wow okay and um and uh a common thing that people
will say uh to Dharma teachers is you know I've listened to a lot of your talks and I think you've said this a lot
of lot of times before but I could never understand it when you said it today it just changed me oh boy it really made a
difference today because we weren't receptive the Mind wasn't prepared the life conditions hadn't come together so
that it made sense or could land in some deep way so uh one of the things that we want
to be careful for in listening to the Dharma talk is not to be listening in a
way that hinders benefiting from the talk and one of the ways that hinders it
is to begin doubting it begin Su
suspicious you know you know you know you know and I've seen people kind of come to IMC here and like
they're like looking out of the dark glasses and you know it's like you can feel like
they're like not having buying any of this and you know you know and um and um
leally looks that way and um the um but I know I know some
people many of us maybe I've certainly have this tendency to sometimes um uh
have a bias towards what we don't believe or we don't like or what doesn't sound right to us not my preference and
there's some wisdom to that I mean you're not supposed to just agree to a Dhat because it's being taught being
taught um you shouldn't have blind you know trust in a Dharma teacher just
because they're Dharma teacher but um but there is something about the art of
taking in something that's challenging to uh and so one of the
things I've learned is um it's easy not to like something it's easy to see that
something is maybe wrong that's relatively easy and if that's the
case for you then it's wrong for you you're not getting any benefit of except maybe more
confidence in your opinionated mind you know that you're or your sense of I'm right and that you're wrong or
something so I don't want to dismiss people's your wisdom that you actually
just discern what's useful and not useful what's right what's wrong maybe that's a important thing to do however
even if someone says something which you don't like even you say something which you think is wrong it's probably not
100% wrong and so the the interesting question is to say to yourself well I
don't quite agree with that but let me see is there some pointer of
in some situation in my life where this thing will be useful so for example if they it's been
said that an unpopular Dharma uh theme for talks is
renunciation and so you know so as soon as the renunciation Dharma talk comes out sit back with the sunglasses on and
hat down and you know okay I'm not going to listen to this renunciation these
Buddhists they're just Party Poopers and um and so uh but instead if the
person asks themselves well I mostly disagree with this this renunciation is overdone the way Buddhists talk about it
which could be that's a fine opinion to have but let me think is there any you
think in this you know in this life of mine that I've lived or that I'm going to live is there any place maybe where
it'd be useful to learn a little bit more about renunciation so that's the right thing to
do and this person says sure enough uh there comes a time that pronunciation is
helpful the thing you've been looking forward to for months is watching the Super
Bowl and you just hardly listen to the drama talk because you're already you know thinking ahead to this afternoon
you know and where you going to be and what you're going to do and how great it's going to be with the chips or something
and uh and so you know and and so you don't even listen to talk on
pronunciation but you know that was a topic and then you come home and it's about time for
the Super Bowl it's so exciting your neighbor calls and
says I have appendicitis can you take me to the
hospital no
and your neighbor says but aren't you Buddhist into pronunciation
no I have my priorities and I I want something I want
it and I don't want to have to do you know not want you know tough luck on you or in that
circumstance I think maybe you'd understand renunciation might be a good thing
renouncing the Super Bowl to get your friend to the hospital before the pentis
gets to a massive system you know infection throughout their body and they
die I hope that that would be warrant some
renunciation so so but the principle here I'm saying is rather than
disagreeing you if you disagree you might not benefit at all if you do the
exercise in what circumstance is this teaching useful is it beneficial then you find
some benefit and this uh this is part of the principle here also is you have to do
some work with the Dharma there is certainly a time to
listen to the Dharma just the words going through and wash through and not engage with thinking about it and
there's a time to reflect and to think and and um and consider some people do
it during the Dharma talk some people do it after and uh and to never spend time
reflecting on it and questioning it both questioning it in you know how it works
what doesn't work all these things and try to get to try to get from it whatever is
beneficial then you won't benefit as much so which is okay but if you want to
benefit from the Dharma then do some work have friends you talk to some people
listen to Dharma talks and afterwards they talk with to friends about it to maybe listen to it as well and they kind
of go back and forth and find out you know what what struck them and what
questions they have and and it's a way of kind of finding more value from the Dharma
talk some people like I see someone right now maybe are are are
writing uh down some of the things being said in the Dharma talk some people find that very beneficial to listen and to
write and there are times I do that uh because uh I listen
better and I sometimes like I'm some the most common place I do it is when I teach with someone else and I feel like
I really need to stay on top of what they're teaching so that I can be in harmony with them or understand it so
then I I'll be kind of writing down what they say and I find I'm much more bright my mind is more attentive and more
present and I need sometimes I need that extra help because my mind might drift
off partly because I've heard so many Dharma talks and you so oh you know here we go
you know my mind yourself so so so but having the practice of writing I'm more
deeply engaged and I it isn't just that I'm more present and actually processing
the material better by that so that's a nice thing to do some people will Journal after the DH talk and write down
what came up for them or how it was um so the principle here one of the
principles I'm trying to convey to you is to be a active
listener in the same way that meditation is an activity that you give yourself
over to even though a lot of it's receptive a lot of it's It's like a not
doing it's also don't be a passive recipient of
Dhat that doesn't mean that you're straining or trying hard or you know uh
it means that you're maybe balanced upright receptive ready
available you're really here to be present for it maybe present in your
posture take a posture that really Expresses in people look at you oh that person's ready that person is really
here they're present here and now in their posture you can feel it in some people and you can feel when they're not
they're here yes but you know they're I know i' I've been some
sometimes in my life such a couch potato slouch that my shoulders were basically
in the bottom you know kind of where the bottom of the sofa and the side back
went up just like so you so um you know that's not ready
receptive so um and then and then I'll kind of bring it back to important point
I made at the beginning is that
um in in a very important way what you're listening
for is found in the listening the quality of the listening
the some characteristic of listening what we're trying to be mindful
of what we're trying to have mindfulness do for us is found in the quality of the
mindfulness itself what we're being aware of what we're trying to what awareness practice
is trying to do for us is found in the qualities of awareness itself so if
we're too focused on what's outside of us the object of attention what we're
listening to the what's then we're not paying attention enough to how we are
how we listen how we are aware how we speak how we
are the Dharma is found in the how not in the what so to sit in such a way that your
how you are is ready receptive free from hindrances free from
distractions um this is the maybe the harder one
elated inspired and then bright a bright mind a
bright attention and uh sometimes Dharma talks
can help that at least the Buddha did that it said it said in the ancient text that he would give talks that would
Inspire encourage brighten and Delight the people who listen
and then he would give his deepest teachings isn't that
nice so the practice of Dharma talks It's a Wonderful practice and um
I'm sure many of you who listened to talks have benefited from it otherwise you wouldn't keep coming back and maybe
this talk will just kind of give you a little bit more inspiration to notice how how you show
up to be listening to Dharma talk and I hope that over time you develop a
repertoire a range of ways to be with Dhat talk that depending on the
circumstance what's going on and how you are and you understand the different ways so you can choose the different
ones at different times as it serves you so those are my thoughts and uh
maybe some of you even practice this today as as I was giving the talk or that's for later
maybe today you just got the ideas so we have about 15 minutes and so
I thought maybe we can take about five minutes uh to um if you have any questions or comments about this and uh
or so and then few minutes where you can talk with each other about this little bit if you'd like and then uh we'll get
ready for the tea and and today I have to leave relatively or quick uh to go down and do more teaching um in s Cruz
so I won't be staying around so any questions any comments anyone like to
make it's lovely if you would say your name when you hi I'm Alex um I have a little
embarrassing question about listening actually so um I've been doing this
thing that uh you have taught called U on breathing in you connect on breathing
out you relax and it works for me phenomenally but then I was telling somebody about it and they asked me
connect to what and I realized I don't know actually that was a little embarrassing
and so the question actually is not whether what is it connected to the
question is should I find out from you what it is connecting to because it's working for me already right it's
actually not a joke yeah yeah so should I or should I just leave it as it is
well you just said that it it's working for you already so if something is working you want to be careful and maybe
not mess with it too much exactly yeah but at some point maybe whatever you're
doing when you connect you'll understand and when it's when the time comes you'll understand what you're doing what's
happening there but maybe you're not ready even to understand that you're just just go for the benefits and not
not now but it might be interesting to hear from you how you're benefiting because if you come back to
me and oh yeah that's really been helpful because it's been giving me really good lottery tickets I I connect
to Lottery T ticket numbers and then I'll say well that's not what I had in
mind but so it might you might have something you know better than lottery ticket numbers but you might um you know
hear from you that might be interesting and then maybe we can adjust something if it's
useful um so I think I I'd prefer to leave it like that uh some I mean in a
if you asked the question differently I would have been happy to have explained what I mean by that but right now I
don't want to mess with you
thank excuse me hi I'm Betsy and I was just just
reflecting that is this a way of of um
really practicing living and being in the present
and kind of getting an experience of being in the present I'm I'm kind of I I don't
totally have that Concept in my head but that it's a great it's a great question I think it's a reasonable question
because we focus so much on meditation in our in our tradition here but um medit ation is just the the training
ground where we're like going to the gym so that we learn how to develop uh
mindfulness attention how we learn to develop certain degree of able to focus being non-distracted certain degree of
wisdom certain degree of compassion and care so that we learn it here in the gym
so that we that we that can become strong so then we bring it into our life
and in some ways that's you know uh at least as important as what happens
in meditation and the go the goal in a sense for our practice is not to have a
sharp line between the mind and the Heart in meditation and the mind and
heart in regular life and so that you have bring bringing some of these qualities of mindfulness attention into our life is definitely what we try to do
and then what's wonderful is that these are uh reciprocal beneficial for each other what we learn in meditation we can
then apply apply it to Life as we apply it to life we learn things about ourselves that then we helps our
meditation deepen and so they two go back and forth and our
partners uh hi I'm Bruno and K quickly today you mentioned
something uh about a time when you were reading books about the Dharma and you
said that the Dharma is in the reading and today you're talking about how the Dharma is in the
listening uh is this is this related to the
concept of zazen and Zen or can you just
tell a little bit more about it I feel like the word Dharma is used in so many
different ways and I think today is the first time I I heard of this
great great very nice yeah so the Dharma is used many ways sometimes it means the teachings of the Buddha and then you can
go to a book for that maybe but uh uh
the book and uh the writing that way and just the words the concepts being given
in a talk that like today um uh if you spend too much time with that that's like spending all your
time in the restaurant trying to eat the menu as some point you have to order the
food and eat the food so uh the Dharma is not found in the menu the meal is not
found in the menu the the Dharma is only found in
you other it just otherwise it's just a uh and a uh you know Concepts and
ideas sometimes we can feel or sense the Dharma in other people their maturity how they've changed their freedom their
their compassion we can feel it so so you can get a sense oh that person's really matured in the Dharma you feel
this maturity or development that they've had and that could be inspiring
but um it's still don't get too mesmerized by other
people be inspired by them but for you it'll only the Dharma will only be found
in you thank you right behind you there you have hi
uh I'm Jake um I was kind of curious like the other side of this of maybe the art of preparing a talk or
like you know giving a talk yeah and you've given thousands by now um do you
have any sort of rubric or like checklist or did maybe did you have it
in the past where you're like I need to try and capture these things in this talk or is it you know more free form
than that or do you start with think it's a good idea then you you get stuck on it and abandon things or I'm just
curious great great question my relationship to giving talks has changed over the
years and um and uh you know so partly because I've given so many and
and it's become a lot of what I do is become second nature and sometimes when I try to sometimes when I'm in when I'm
teaching people to become teachers or teacher training I'll explain to people what I do in a Dharma talk I I don't I I
think it's useful to teach them that but I feel very uncomfortable it because it sounds like
I'm being so self-conscious and so like you know fabricated something but but
it's all second nature and there's all these elements that go on things I'm paying attention to that's kind of in the background that's going on but from
having done it now for you know over 30 years and U I'm a slow learner that's maybe why I keep giving a lot of
talks uh but when I was a new teacher the first 10 years years I often wrote
uh uh wrote out talks very begin First Years the the first two talks I gave U
is in Zen and in Zen you're not supposed to have notes so I wrote everything out
and then I spent uh hours memorizing it and so I didn't use the notes
but you know it was all there memorized and uh and so then uh I had
notes and part of uh sometimes it was really great to prepare a Dharma talk by
um taking notes and outline or different things if I was in the flow sometimes
I'd settle into the topic or into the Dharma I would sit first meditate and then it felt like was continuation of my
meditation practice you know and I love the creativity that came out that way
and uh so that wasn't a good good day and sometimes I would go sometimes
go and read a few little different books and uh pick up a paragraph here or there and see and in a good day I would feel
like it would Savor that those teachings and take them in and contribute to the not just the ideas of what I was going
to teach but also the atmosphere of the teaching the sense or the quality of it
and then at some point after about 10 years uh two things happened um I didn't
have I still had kids young kids at home I didn't have time to prepare anymore uh so that and then I thought my
talks got worse but people like them
more and then uh but the other thing that happened soon thereafter was that uh uh my relationship to Preparing
changed and I would sit down with a piece of paper to write notes and I'd literally feel a repulsive
force from that it was like I can't do that it's just like you know I mean was like quite something to feel this no way
that was going the wrong direction and so go for a walk instead or go sit meditate instead and uh and then there a
whole different process um and uh sometimes now these days when
I give her T dma talk I have some basic idea in my mind I've kind of formed an outline just on my own thinking you know
or maybe three points or what direction I'm going to start with and then as I give the talk um the the uh the the path
opens up in front of me and I just follow follow the trail you know I'm following something and sometimes it
takes me away from where I thought I was going to go and um and if
um and then also uh when I give a talk these days I'm also I'm still trying to
understand what I'm teaching that's my preferred stance to be in and so may maybe people who listen
to me think like I know a lot you know well get knows a lot or something I don't I don't have that internal sense I
mean I know I know a lot about Buddhism mean so that's true but my my inner feeling for myself is that I'm actually
on the edge of what I don't understand and I that's where I like to be so I don't know if that comes across
when I teach but I kind of that's I you know I'm exploring it with you kind of to some degree or trying
to and the other thing I've learned in these years of teaching and that's very important and
I'm and also trying I'm also trying to stay uh in touch with the feeling inside of whatever I'm
teaching there's a feeling tone there's a quality sentiment Sensations inside
that go along with it so I'm trying to feel my way into something too not just talk about it and uh so much so that uh
occasionally uh it was much more before but uh just occasionally happens
nowadays too I get into what I call for myself my explanatory mode
my wife will ask how' it go today and I said oh I fell into my explanatory
mode and when it's explanatory I'm just explaining something and my heart is not
in it it just ideas it's very dry it's like it feels like cardboard for me like
and sometimes there have been there's times where I I don't know I recognize it and I don't know how to get out of it
and okay I just have to put up with this today and this is how it is and U and um
so yeah I should apologize for those days because I don't like explaining
things even though I do explain things but there's much something much more important going on does that get kind
does that answer your question well enough satisfy your question but why did you
ask oh I like I've done a few myself over the years I'm sure people have like
probably in this room have thought about have done it or have thought about it so I was just curious to hear like your
process or your approach to it great yeah great thank you okay so uh thank
you all