hello and welcome to our meditation session
and and this week we're focusing
on what hinders our ability to be mindful present steady in our
practice and today the topic is the second hindrance uh which is a verion
it's usually translated into English and are are kind of Buddhist scene as
aversion though the poly word uh more accurately means ill will so it contains
a certain degree of hostility in it so it's more than simply not wanting
something but rather it's uh pushing something away or pulling away in a way
that is is uh hostile or uh has animosity in it towards
whatever is going on and uh and to understand this
better uh we can distinguish uh two kinds of
averting two ways of saying no one is with love and the other is
with hatred and uh one is with um Goodwill or kindness or
well-wishing and the other is with uh wishing uh ill for something or someone
another is with hostility uh with uh some some degree of
animosity and the difference between these is huge and how it can feel inside us is
different that when there's a feeling of of uh
free free free Loving Feeling a love that's
doesn't contain clinging as part of it doesn't uh there's no compulsion in the
love it's just a generosity love which is generous it can be a strong no to
something and uh when it's uh when the know is hostile it comes with tension
with strain with a closing down with tightening of the fist in the heart or
the mind let alone the physical hand and uh and to be able to feel the
difference one is nurturing nourishing one is uh might be energizing but it's
energy which is draining energy which is uh uh contains uh irritation or
suffering as part of it and so for this meditation I would like to suggest that
um uh you learn to say no during the meditation
lovingly and learn how you say no in a way that is the opposite of
love the opposite of well-wishing or care kindness
generosity so uh a loving way of saying no is to see that your mind begins going
into certain trains of thought which you know you've done before maybe it's resentment about
someone and you've done this many many times before uh same kinds of thoughts and you
see that they are don't serve you at all maybe even they're harmful for you and
you lovingly say no not going to have those
thoughts you are involved in certain preoccupations that involves
hostility and you say lovingly no this is not the time for that I'm not going
to do that and um uh on the other hand there might
be some thoughts you have or some experiences you have maybe your knee
hurts maybe your your breathing is not quite what it wanted to be your uncomfortable in some way and you have a
kind of a a stressful strain full aversion to it there's a some modum of
ill will or or hostility or animosity or um irritation
annoyance that's contained in the no not another uh you know aching knee no you
know let's get rid of it this is terrible and and there's kind of a sense of anger in it in that ill will that
know and so see if you can see that difference and if you
can um lovingly say no to the hostility
meaning don't give into it don't pick it up don't participate in it even if it
keeps moving through you step away and see it clearly for what it is and to
make this distinction between a healthy no appropriate no
that's loving and you kind of enjoy doing it even though you know just enjoy
it because it comes from love it comes from knowing what's best and uh and
distinguishing distinguishing that with that which is not healthy that's harmful even and um and keep choosing the
healthy no and apply it to your meditation watch your mind watch what you're involved in
and if it's not a healthy engagement with waking up being present in a mindful clear clean
way maybe you say no but lovingly
kindly in a way that maybe even inspires you to say no like oh this is caring for
me this is knowing what's best this is moving in a good direction and if your whole mental
physical system says no with hostility See Clearly that's the
case and especially if it involves trains of
thought so may this support you to be
present saying lovingly no to whatever takes you away from being present here
and now awake clear steady in the
moment so gently closing your
eyes feeling your body your body breathing
breathing and perhaps
saying a friendly kind warmhearted
yes yes to being here and present in this body in this
experience yes to being mindful being aware here
and now and lovingly without
demands without hostility no not
now for thoughts that take you
away and so we'll sit quietly
me
e
for
lovingly saying no not
now to thinking thinking wondering off being reactive just
know I kind of know that almost simultaneously is a
yes to here [Music]
now almost as if you're putting on a very comfortable
clothes yes as you step into your
body being
here
for
e
being here and now here in your
body is there something within you
that welcomes you with a yes yes be
here in the breathing in the body in the
awareness and whatever takes you
away from what is good in the body mind heart right now gently
lovingly say no not
now
and as we come to the end of this
sitting letting go gently
lovingly for everything that takes you away from being here in your
body aware open
receptive here with some whatever degree of calm or
stability that might have
developed and is there something
here that's appropriate to say yes to a
yes to awareness being here this
way
and is there now a clear sense
of a Kind no that lets you that lets go or steps
away from participating in things which are not
healthy or useful for you
and in this way your orientation can
be towards not making things
worse and instead to make things
better and as we come to the end of the sitting to
imagine being in the world of people and
activities with this
orientation don't make the situation
worse if you can make it
better and at least with your Good Will and your
kindness at least with the wisdom that knows to say
no to making it
worse may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you
e
so hello on this second uh day five days of doing discussing the
hindrances and this is building on the introduction to meditation series that
just just finished with the idea that once you have the basic practice
basic instructions for mindfulness practice that one of the really important next steps is to understand
what interferes or hinders your mindfulness practice and
that uh and that does two things it helps to settle the things that
interfere so it's easier to be present and and wonderfully what it does you
learn the art of making what uh hinders uh our mindfulness our
steadiness our calm to whatever that is to make it the object of awareness the
object of mindfulness and anything that can be made the object of mindfulness can be um uh can be related
to peacefully can be related to without clinging or
hostility and the Beautiful and inspiring thing at least for me of this mindfulness practice that whatever you
can be mindful of there's a the possibility of finding freedom in
relationship to it and to find be able to find Freedom anything that in the
world of experience means that freedom can be all-encompassing 360°
freedom and uh it's not an aloofness it's not a
disconnection it's in some sense it's the opposite it's it's uh it's learning
how to not to be entangled so that we can be connected with warmth with
kindness with love with Good Will to ourselves and to the world around
us so but that's an ideal that's maybe the direction we're going and so one of
the things we need to learn is how to turn the attention mindfulness to uh the
ways that we are aversive and um the ways in which we have ill will or irritation hostility
annoyance uh towards uh ourselves towards our experience towards other
people towards the world itself and um and generally in English
the word of verion um represents some form of
hostility or anger or um some degree or other and um like you want to get rid of
something in a in a um hostile way
and and um and some people uh will walk through the world with an attitude of
that kind of hostility of ill will they're looking to find they're looking for what is wrong they're looking for
what is uh what to be critical of and angry about they're looking they're
they're it's almost like a atmosphere of aversion they walking through with walking in the world with and some
people it's something that comes up periodically maybe periodically good part of the day but it's not an
overarching attitude by which we're living and um and it can be quite strong
certain events can give arise to anger in such that way that we're really um
feeling you a lot of animosity towards someone else or some situation and
um and it could be uh some of us sometimes have C certain degree of
animosity or ill will or I don't know if that's exactly the right word but uh
there's certainly stress and strain and anger and um eyes that have darts in
them towards uh our our our computers when they're not or the technology or
what we're trying to do there we can't figure it out and um so it doesn't it's not it's sometimes in adate objects too
that we have this with assigning blame criticism elsewhere
so these things exist for human beings and the radical art that we're doing here in mindfulness is to fold this into
our mindfulness meaning this too we're going to be aware of but not aware of it
to anticipate but to be aware as if we're stepping back away from it one
step turning around and looking it at it and saying I see you this is aversion
this is hostility this is uh uh um you
know um the darts of the eyes that are going out to uh to kind of stare at
something and indicate you know you are you know I'm angry with you this is how
it is this is how the tension in the body builds up but we look at it and we look at it
with kindness we look at it with freedom with non-reactivity with without being
caught in its grip and aversion wanting to get rid of something or wanting to
get away from it because it's so terrible um can be uh a um a tremendous
stress and strain it can be a kind of um causing harm even to ourselves and it
might not seem that way because what's happening might be like this is this is
really uncomfortable for me that I'm being hardened by it but sometimes that's true but sometimes it's our
reactivity our values our fear our um Pride that is being made
uncomfortable that makes us want to or our desires are not being met and and so
somehow so sometimes we have attached to desires desires aren't being fulfilled something THS it and so now we're angry
at what thoughts or desires all present an entanglement there is a healthy form of
aversion there is a healthy way of saying no that arises out of love and if
the word love is too sweet too Grand then uh arises out of Good Will arises
out of a friendliness a generosity of spirit arises out of wanting the best for
everyone concerned and um arises out of a goodness or uh or Rises out of wisdom
that of you say no uh I'm not going to be involved with the version that way I'm not going to be
involved in those thoughts or at least no I don't condone this I'm not
I don't want to invest myself in this might be a I might might might not be able to stop having those thoughts but I
don't have to be those thoughts I don't have to fall into them and believe them or um you know and so but that's can be
down with love when there's something that needs to be say we say no in the world like say no to some other person
for what they're doing uh can that be done with love as opposed to with hostility and aversion what are we
trying to accomplish when we are aversive what are we trying to accomplish when we have
hostility and animosity is it simply to protect ourselves and to push the other person
away is it to uh retribution to somehow
cause them to feel uncomfortable for them to get the message and to to cower
or feel hurt or to um uh be a little more submissive or what is it that we're
trying to to do in the aversive and is it necessary is there a
better way is there a better way to say no is
there a way of saying no that doesn't break the connection doesn't fracture
relationships doesn't um uh diminish other people or see them only through
the lens of how they are wrong to us but rather see them
as valuable people as people that it's possible to have a warm kind friendly
relationship to if they would allow it but we say no with
confidence but know that keeps the door open and know that clearly shows that
we're willing to be in relationship if they um if they um
change if they are different different but they feel that the no is not angry
it's not hostile and um so this is not necessar this is not
easy to do but uh the Dharma practice is a
Dharma of saying yes to whatever
supports freedom in US say yes to whatever helps the nourish the yes
qualities of who we are to come forth in the world and sometimes that
yes requires us to say no to certain things and um no I'm not going to be
hostile no I'm not going to um uh scare
this person with my anger I'm not going no I'm not going to shut my the person down um with anger in such a way that um
diminishes them or shut T them up yes I'd like to be present yes I'd like to
say no in a way that um respects
them where I get care for myself appropriately but it also haven't shut
this person out of my heart it's easier said than
done but it can be learned and it can be learned by
anybody uh in way that we can take care of
ourselves Dharma practice is a practice of taking care of ourselves and so in the process of doing
it we learn how to say no to making things
worse and if we get our way by being angry hostile to
somebody or something uh chances are in the bigger picture of things we're making the the whole thing
worse how do we take care of ourselves and others how do we take care
of things uh uh so they're better this is the art of Dharma practice and so the
simplest formulation of this that you little slogan you can take with you is
don't make it worse if what you're going to say is going to make the situation worse don't
do it and rather make it
better and over time with dmer practice we learn become wiser and
wiser what the nature of worse is the full implications of what we do
and how it comes back at us and and affects us and and uh in our
relationships and over time we also learn what makes it better and uh and to learn to say no to
making it worse can be an acto of love not an act of hostility to
say yes to making it better does not have to be greed does not have to be
clinging um but it in the in the bigger picture
this yes to what that makes it better is a yes that leaves us more free and
protected in a certain way in a good way so um
so may you today uh explore your
relationship to this General category that fit what what fits under this
General category that I'm calling no when you have no attitude to
anything can that can you avoid making it worse can you avoid that hostility in
that no and if it's necessary to say no can you explore
how do you do it with love with Good Will and uh and if this is the way you
learn to become wise about the second hindrance the hindrance of
aversion uh it'll be time really well spent thank
you