hi folks welcome [Music] um yeah nice to see your names there are
a couple Rogue live streams that were happening
that were set somehow I couldn't control it but set to private so you could maybe
see the video but um there wasn't a chat
and if you and I know we need our chat we need our emojis and our good morning
in the S and it makes YouTube actually pretty great I love uh
seeing all of that so if you're on a stream that doesn't have a chat just um
refresh or go back to the the the U IMC YouTube page and um should uh should be
able to get it um okay so uh so welcome welcome
all
okay so uh it's our Friday here and um sit in
a moment
um sometimes it's it's occurred to me that um excuse me it's occurred to me that
that um all all thinking is coping coping is maybe has a pajora of
kind of tone but it's like yeah we think to cope in one way or
another and very powerful that we can do that as
animals and and so it gets reinforced at such a
deep level and the Dharma is about doing something
a little new and uh
to actually release our coping strategies our kind of Moment by moment
coping strategies we uh need something like
faith and the faith we need is a faith in in
silence that it's safe to let go a faith in letting go a faith
in in love and uh a faith that it's it's okay
safe enough to uh stop reading the signals of our
body the kind of affective stimulation the emotional activation the state of
arousal Valance to to cease reading that
as indicative of threat or
opportunity and to in a
sense all the feeling that we feel means the same
thing to uh to let go so well uh we'll practice and
um explore so finding a a posture that
feels uh
sustainable
e
just bringing some some soothing to your body
mind
e everything looks different from the the
perspective of
Tranquility so maybe take some Fuller
breaths relax the jaw you're around the eyes
temples relax our
belly
soft
e
some reassurance that uh
it's not neglectful to put down comple
complications the Loose Ends of our life the problems that need to be solved it's not can feel like neglect not to chew on
those at all moments it's
okay okay to put them down not
neglect
e
in the end our thinking cannot protect us from
life but our heart
training canot do so
much so we
nurture kind of faith in
silence
e
the present moment doesn't wish to hurt
you
let him go doesn't wish to cost
e
it is our deep Habit to
overread all phenomena
to make them mean too
much it's maybe uh today maybe just for
a moment
we
stop
e
the the movements of our mind so uh so
innocent so innocent that we scramble and
cope
but uh if all we do is scramble and cope fa takes the
heart the silence doesn't care even a tiny bit
who we think we
are we come
to listen to The Silence take our cues from it trust
it keep letting go into
okay so
um was reading reading a book about um William
William James and um who is
yeah uh got the the potency of uh the
Dharma and um and this is uh from uh from his his
his dad actually kind of intense quote I saw so um James's dad says um
every every person who has reached even their intellectual teens begins to
suspect that life is no force that it is not Gentile
comedy that it flowers and fructifies on
the contrary out of the profoundest tragic depths of the essential
Dar in which its subject's roots are
plunged the natural inheritance of everyone who is capable of spiritual
life is in an unsubdued Forest where the wolf
howls and the obscene bird of night
Chatters it's a little Grim maybe but uh speaks to
something important life is no
farce it's no force great as uh the Zen folks say
great is the matter of life and death and
so uh what are we doing here what are we
doing here what what is actually on offer in this path what what
um what is the Buddha's uh promise
and to to meet the the kind of existential intensity of The Human
Condition with some modum of dignity to meet it with some modum of dignity that
takes training training not thinking but
training and it's easy for it to happen this way but we're not not here to graft the
Dharma into the infrastructure of our neurosis we're we're actually doing
something that is new like something that is different and new and takes
courage because it's unfamiliar to the kind of habit energies that that
run our lives so this is um
aaka she says on the spiritual path uh we have
to uh try TR something new in fact spiritual path takes quite a lot of
Courage because it means chucking out the old without knowing what the new one
is actually like if we don't have that courage we can't go on such a
path and so this path of relinquishment surrender
Letting Go all of that relinquishment
surrender silence Letting Go all of that feels
like Risk feels like Risk a certain kind of sense of the the extra vulnerability we
encounter that's what I was alluding to when I said it feels like neglect almost
to put our thought down to put the knots of our life down to put our problems
down not to try to solve them in every moment feels like neglecting a loved one
or something it it feels like risk it leaves us feeling especially
vulnerable and so we hold on in our lives we hold on in
our meditation we hang on to what's uh what's familiar and we just keep pinging
to all the familiar reference points but
there are uh many Dharma places to which we cannot
bring our knowing many Dharma places to which we
cannot bring our preferences many Dharma places to which
uh we cannot continue to hum the song of
self we're doing something new and to even get a taste of the
newness we have to relinquish something of what we've
always done
z um said the search for uh the search for reality is the most dangerous
undertaking for it it uh will destroy the world in which you
live search for reality is dangerous it destroys the world in which you live
we've sort of acclimatized to our own world of personal meetings over reading the
signals over reading our feeling and
thought over reading
and Dharma practice is uh relaxing all of that that energy of over reading
this um is hard it's hard to um it's hard to trust that we
[Music] actually find our power by opening
deeply to helplessness it's like very
counterintuitive for our system that we actually find our power our dignity
in opening to helplessness and maybe that that's the
kind of Faith required to let go that we we trust like yeah a trust in the
silence finding our our power entails like consciously
experiencing uh helplessness the helplessness of Dua of the first Noble
truth that there is suffering the helplessness of the the the dir into
which the the roots are plunged as James
said and so we uh we find our power in
this way we find our peace when we don't insist on it when we don't insist on it we find
ourselves by relinquishing ourselves so Letting Go U moves us
towards freedom but often hurts some often hurts
some and to trust that the suffering we encounter in practice is effective
suffering it's not the suffering that compounds suffering that leads to more suffering to trust that this is
effective suffering to trust that this hurts is not harming that takes some
faith and so we hold on to uh something we we
trust even though it um we're not sure it'll support us feels
like a a thin strand as U Ain Ain
suito says um Awakening is based on the process of Letting Go letting go is about carefully
revealing assumptions biases life messages and releasing
them you can liken the process to a gradual disent out of the tumult and
gridlock of your personal world into the free space of the
uncondition it's rather like lowering oneself down a rope to know how to do
that it's a matter of holding on to something you trust even though it seems like a thin
strand then Letting Go little by little trusting the downward
pull this is the trajectory of non engagement and
abandonment The Descent out of the gridlock of your person person Al
world we make that descent with uh with faith actually
Faith many of the kind of gateways that we get to thresholds in our Dharma
practice adore where we're letting go more
deeply understanding something in a fresh way when we get to that gate what what um what what opens that
door is not our willfulness but our faith our faith that whatever is on the
other side of that gate will not harm us so we trust that downward pull the
kind of uh this this kind of gravity maybe we say is
safe and into that
um that that kind of wondrous dark
open space of relinquishment yeah there are fewer and
fewer signpost fewer and fewer you know like we in some ways we
our life is just lived we keep like orienting orienting to this this this
this what happens when there are fewer and fewer signposts the signpost of preferences
the signpost of the story of self signpost of self
other past future it's like all the kind of
Accutron of self we just relax and trust that
downward pull and
to uh to care more about awareness than our
life more about this moment than my problems even if that's just for a
moment that that takes faith
and even if it's just for a moment that moment detonates something in the heart
and uh we um begin to inherit the
Dharma share it and uh be grateful for
it so I offer this uh uh for
consideration well uh we'll pause here thanks for having me for this week I know I am a sub and
um yeah I uh will in April on on Wednesday evenings I'll start a weekly
group on this channel uh Wednesday at 730 p.m. I'm actually awake then and uh
um so and I'll be this format you know a 30 minute H and then a short talk so we
we'll get that posted on imc's website and
um and one one more announcement I IRC in collaboration with Big Bear Retreat
Center we're going to do a Donna based Retreat uh at Big Bear couple hours
outside of La gorgeous Center love being there and um that'll be in July July 9th
through 13th so it' be great to uh see see some of you we'll get that posted uh
soon and um so keep keep your eyes open for that I love that uh have Donna based
Retreats at other places too so um that is uh that's it and um I
uh wish you uh wish you all well thanks for having me
e