so I'll start again with a welcome to everyone and on this Thanksgiving Day in
the United States and i' for myself I'd like to emphasize the uh giving part of
Thanksgiving that it's an act of generosity and
uh two wonderful things gratitude offering thanks giving generosity come
together in Thanksgiving and meditation that we're
about to do is one way of understanding it is to set create the conditions within
us so that we can be much more attentive
receptive to appreciating others
appreciating the world and uh because without
appreciation there's not really any deep forms of gratitude or
Thanksgiving and I'll talk more about it during a Dharma talk this act of deep appreciation and how important it is for
Thanksgiving but for the meditation I'd like to emphasize that meditation creates the
conditions for appreciation
we relax we step out of the preoccupations of our
mind the bias and the orientations we have to how we see people how we look at
them and how we're caught up in our own concerns how we see the world through
the filters of our emotions and moods and to somehow settle deeper below
that to a quieter place where the eyes become clear
where there's less filter and dust over the eyes of thoughts
and memories associations biases hurts
desires to quiet enough to settle enough to relax enough to see in a fresh
way and one means for doing this one
support is to find a contentment Within
that for minutes of meditation to feel content a deep contentment not about all
things for sure but for now to be
content to sit here to meditate content to be
breathing to be alive to be content
with the benefits that we have that allow us to sit down and quiet to
meditate and do this spiritual practice it's a remarkable thing it's a
remarkable uh honor and gift that we receive that we can do this many people
don't have the ability to take time off to sit and quiet and
meditate and for today to have a sense that we do this
practice and we find a place of deep rest deep
contentment so that we can enter the world with a giving heart enter the
world with eyes that can appreciate deeply so for
now assume a posture a posture that for you
you can be content that this is your meditation
posture that you can be comfortable in that you can
be awake
in and to gently close your
eyes and to Gentle a gentling of your
insights maybe with every exhale a
calming gentling of whatever is
agitated tense
feeling the body's experience of breathing from the inside
out especially in the Torso the rib cage the
diaphragm the belly
the back rib
cage and gently just enough so it's comfortable nice maybe even bring some
pleasure take take some longer breaths longer
inhale maybe especially a longer
exhale feeling the body from the inside the stretching the opening with
the in breath expansion this settling relaxing with
the exhale
with a longer exhale than usual settling in at the end of the out
breath to whatever sense of inner stability
there is there at the end of the out breath maybe in your
belly maybe all the way down to the your pelvic
cavity or the area of the
diaphragm or where your sitting bones touch a surface that hold you
up letting your breathing become
normal but continue on the exhale to relax into an inner
stability or in inner
Stillness
e
for e
and as you're meditating here can you find a feeling a
sense of inner
contentment that's very
simple not dismissing that there are things to be discontent
about but to not Overlook that there can be some way of
being content at this moment content with this
moment as it is as you
breathe not needing things to be
different or if you do contentment with engaging in a
practice that puts you on a path to freedom and love
breathe with contentment breathe
in breathe
out let go into a feeling of contentment
here
e
e e
to see if you can breathe content be
content enough so you can feel
an opening in your heart so there's
space to take in what is good here your own
goodness the goodness of your life that you receive that hold your
life
contentment that allows the
heart to be generous to be
appreciative to allow there to be an opening
of your emotional tenderness warmth
care so that every moment of
contentment appreciation
thankfulness opens the emotional Center
so you feel even more of the
same
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to turn the attention the heart
out into the world with appreciation for all the benefits
goodness that we
receive may we offer thanks may we have the sense of
generosity that can give thanks for the food we
eat and all the [Music] people resources and plants and animals
that make it possible for us to have this food we'll have
today may we offer thanks to the all the resources that we
have that allows us to stay in touch with each other and connected right here and now with the
technology and that we have
and all the web of communications that we have to connect and to know
people and all the people who support it and keep it
going may we be thankful for the so-called technology of the heart
that also creates a network a web of communication
and connections we have with others those who are close to us those
who strangers out into the world may we offer our thanks for this
web of social connections however small it might be
may we cherish the human capacity for
kindness generosity love
and appreciation we give
thanks for that part of the heart all our hearts that has goodness in it
that we've evolved to have an amazing amount of inner
goodness and we give thanks to all the goodness that comes
into this world maybe each drop filling an ocean
of goodness
and may we be content and appreciative and
thankful to Simply Be Alive in this
world so we can offer whatever goodness that we
have to where wherever it might be possible in whatever vehicle and means
it might be may we be thankful and
appreciative of ourselves and with
ourselves to be generous in this world to be caring and
kind contribute to a better world for everyone
and maybe begins as simply as offering
thanks the gift of thankfulness may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may our giving of thanks the way we do
that contribute to the well-being of the
[Music]
world thank you
for e
so hello and welcome to this fourth talk on
uh gratitude and coincidentally it's also
the gratitude today in the United States Thanksgiving and so I love the idea that
the word is Thanksgiving with the word giving in it and it touches into this
profound aspect of Buddha spirituality that involves
generosity and uh to give and one of the most profound things
we can give others is is our appreciation of
them and generosity gratitude I mean begins with
appreciation and I want to underscore this I've said it this week already but there are three steps three aspects of
generosity that makes it robust and full one is taking time to appreciate really
recognizing acknowledging what it is that's we benefited what received what
the goodnesses we've seen really take time to appreciate don't be in a hurry don't overlook
stop maybe the bumper sticker can say I stop for
appreciation and then take in that any of the goodness of that the thankfulness
of that as H receive it deeply inside of you so that it opens you in some way or
touches you in a deep way or moves you so that the emotionality the tenderness
the warmth of It kind of you allow it space to be in you take it in and receive it almost like take it in relax
with it don't don't take it in intense like now you have to do something and reply
and you have to immediately apologize or you have to immediately say thank you quickly but take time to really related
to register because it's one of the me
means to open the heart it's one of the means to feel a more heartfelt connection to others is to allow
ourselves to feel the thankfulness that we have to feel the generosity someone else has
offered and then and then there's more embodiment there's more fullness to this
Thanksgiving we can give then we want to express it in some way as I talked about
yesterday but today I want to offer something a little different that um uh the giving of
thanks uh can be done indirectly by how well and deeply we
appreciate others even people who are difficult for us is there a silver lining is there
something you can see that's wonderful in the person the goodness of inner beauty and integrity uh
authenticity a what can you appreciate in others and that this is a gift many
people in our world are not appreciated enough many people in our world some people don't have never really
appreciated um and to um to begin
appreciating to begin um to see take time and to acknowledge
what you see is good it could be as simple as oh it's so uh thank you you
know it's uh it's so helpful that you're helping with the dishes today or
um wow you came right away to help with that or to bring the food to the table
or or um you really stopped I saw you you really stopped and sat with that
person who looked like they were kind of being sad you don't have to necessarily tell them but really take time to
appreciate what you see um make it an art make it a practice to look for the
Silver Linings to look for what's good in people to uh almost like your heart's
going to say hello to it resonate with it uh feel it and um and maybe say that
you know may then then say some nice things about it maybe that's when you say thank you thank you for the kindness
back thank you for your helpfulness thank you for your care and your sympathy thank you for uh how honest you
were you know whatever it might be that you see um and maybe you don't say it
directly for people if it seems too personal or too awkward in the situation
but even that you can look and see people with appreciative eyes what is
good in people and part of that also then brings out what is good it reinforces it but it
also might open your heart maybe it resonates with the same goodness in you
for you to recognize it in someone else means something in you knows that and maybe that inspires you it
opens you and um and so um then and then after taking time
and to really appreciate someone then to offer
thanks or and to offer thanks in such a way that it opens you even more a thanks
that's not quick it's not to shut people out or out or but it's really almost
like the beginning of our relationships thank you thank you thank you for helping the
dishes it was nice doing it with you almost looks like you're not expecting
anything but uh you're just open to the moment to
what follows so you're opening and so there's this wonderful
cycle of gratitude and generosity gratitude
appreciation um that we receive goodness and benefits from the
world even when it's not specifically to us we benefit seeing the goodness in
others and to receive that but don't let it stop in
us don't say well that person's so wonderful but I'm not and feel inadequate if you feel and
sense someone else's goodness you have it in you somewhere and let the Cycles
continue let you let you open up and appreciate more open up and feel the
goodness of the others more the goodness of the situation goodness of this life
and then let your response your generosity that you would offer
something in return offer thanks offer
gratitude offer generosity offer to do the dishes offer
to help with a table offer to sit with someone offer offer to make a difference
in the world in some way so you keep the Cycles flowing you keep keep the
unfolding and don't let it stop with you and even if it stops with someone else
keep it flowing it's invaluable part of our
life this our process of appreciating the world the process
of feeling connected and tenderhearted and warm-hearted and brokenhearted in
profound ways and then offering a connection through
that it helps if you have a certain contentment don't be in a hurry don't
have filled with desires for things and activities
and for the conversations to go your way and for your opinions be content with
what's here happening here so there's room always creating room in your heart
room for others room for yourself room for appreciating what's here the
goodness that's here and then um support that to
grow your thanks is not an end of the story your thanks is how the proper
thanks the good thanks the embodied thanks it's really an appreciation heartfelt
appreciation we take time to do that is the food the fuel for more goodness
in this world more goodness in our families more goodness in our communities more
goodness that spreads be into with strangers we meet on the street or in stores or places of
work may it be that
we can can be mindful be present be attentive be content
enough to see the goodness even the sliver of goodness in
others and they are appreciating of that and taking that
in are being inspired by that encourage our own
generosity our own goodness to see but we can offer to this
world and don't underestimate the tremendous benefit of expressing
thanks in all the ways you can think of it so thank
you very very much for our time together today and this week and this year and
these years that we've been doing this on YouTube I feel very very fortunate that
that all of you are interested in this that you're coming regularly and and
this is important for you and uh and uh it's important for me I feel that I
benefit from that I inspired by that and I offer you my thanks and and
appreciation that we're doing this together thank you for today and may
this day be nurturing for you thank you