good evening can we turn up the volume just a little bit so let's see I have to talk
now to here how the volume goes yeah is this okay can you hear okay in the
back so good evening and tonight I want to talk a
little bit about something that often we don't think about neither in our uh daily life nor
in relationship to our meditation practice and that is the attitude that
we're bringing and in particular I'm going to talk about attitude that we bring to our
meditation practice but it's not only about that I mean of course the attitude
that we bring has an impact but often it's uh subtle and
often we're not even aware of the attitude that we're bringing and what impact it can have and we're not even
aware like is there an alternative is so than the way than the attitude that we're
bringing so I'm going to Define attitude as the way in which we are relating to
our experience you know like do you have an attitude you you have a like a chip
on your shoulder right is a kind of like an attitude and which people might show
up and interact with people with this kind of chip on their shoulder in which they are know just uh wri ready to be
offended and ready to defend themselves or defend uh something that's important
to them so the attitude we might be the way in which we feel about or think about or
respond to our experiences because like for example
another example might be and I'm sure all of us have this example it's uh funny that we have this expression you
know to wake up on the wrong side of the bed and I know I I sometimes use this
example because uh well sometimes if you don't sleep well I mean it's obvious like all of us have this experience of
not sleeping well for whatever reason right there's a numberless number of reasons countless
number of reasons why we might do this and then when we uh don't sleep
well there's a certain like Outlook that we have there's a certain way in which
we like see things I mean literally and figuratively if we're feeling cranky or
grumpy maybe I'll just say for me I'm one of those people that when I first wake up I'm usually in an okay mood but
I don't want to talk to anybody I don't want to say words I just don't want to interact with anybody at all I just kind
of want to do my own thing and then my own thing includes a
cup of coffee I just uh love coffee I have uh for such
a long time and uh you know then later after I've been awake have my cup of coffee
been doing my thing then um I'm okay then I'm happy to interact with others
but uh first thing in the morning wake up and then having to interact with others I'm often a little cranky I don't know that's just kind of
the way it is you know I don't have to be but uh you know I can say you no no
no I'm going to not be cranky and you know meet this moment uh with some
kindness but uh sometimes I'm just cranky first thing in the morning I'm
like that's okay that's just how it is and so there's this way in which this
kind of like this crankiness or grumpiness uh affects uh our Outlook
which I'm saying as the way that we see things so see things both uh literally
and figuratively that is we might just if we have this cranky attitude we literally will see oh shoot yeah the
floor needs mopping and wow look at the spiderwebs in that part of the bookcase
you know there's these things that we notice that are you know just a little bit
uh they're not the bright cheerful things right there's this sense of oh
here's a things that's wrong and oh yeah here's this other thing that's wrong or something like this we're not noticing
noticing that the birds are chirping outside we're not noticing that oh at
least the sink isn't filled with dirty dishes or you know whatever it is we're not there's a selection bias that
happens that's due to the attitude that we're
bringing and maybe that's not so bad you would say okay that's just the way it is
but this has such a bigger impact than just the things that we see
because the things that we see the like the what we're choosing to really place
our attention on what we're choosing not intentionally choosing but what we're
noticing influences our interpretations like for example just
building on this example of seeing how the floor needs to be momed and there's not dirty dishes but there's all this
mess that needs to be put away or something like this then there might be like an interpretation like geee the
people I live with they don't take care I have to do it all myself or maybe like
oh I'm not a very good person to take care of my living space or you know there's this interpretation we can make
this the selection bias and what we're viewing then we make it mean
something and what we're making it mean always has something to do with
us if even if this example that I gave about well the people that I live with they don't take care of this place and
then there's always like the next beat and they expect me to do it because they don't respect me or and uh they're not
sensitive to the condition of our living space and they're not sensitive to me
either and they don't know how important it is to me for it to be clean or something like
this so then when we make it mean something when we interpret it and it's
always about something to do about us always if you look at this if you investigate you'll see that's kind of
like by definition what happens but then that would maybe you
know that's bad enough but then it doesn't stop there because then our Behavior changes if we find ourselves
stuck in like well you know they don't respect me they're not sensitive to
what's important to me they're not sensitive at all look how they're insensitive in all these different areas
and they don't even notice that the floors need to be mopped or whatever it might be then that interpretation
affects our Behavior then maybe we're not uh going
to be generous as we could be or as uh warm when we are greeting them instead
we're cranky we meet them with a crankiness or grumpiness so our Behavior gets uh
influenced by the interp interpretation that we made by what we saw by What attitude we
had and then we might say well as if that weren't bad enough right it just
keeps on going then the behavior like well then maybe we're not uh as generous
generous in the giving them the benefit of the doubt or generous in doing
something like making a cup of tea for them or cup of coffee for them in the morning for example or doing something
nice for them that they you know to help them have a nice day and know that they're
appreciated instead then uh this our Behavior not
being generous kind of influences the experiences we have well if we're not generous to them then of course they
react to that and meet us and maybe in a way that increases our crankiness you
know maybe they're not warm and attentive to us are loving to us they
might be but they might not be too so this big whole Cascade of events
is just kind of like based on this attitude that we had but so often we
don't even notice attitude when it's you know extrem like crankiness first thing
in the morning and we know this is a pattern that we've had but so often
there are subtle attitudes that we have that are having a big impact on our life
and a big impact on our meditation practice and I want to talk a little bit about
that because I've been using this word uh outlook for attitude but there's a
way in which we might say we could summarize kind of like this part of this Cascade events I was talking about as
the lens through which we see everything or maybe we might even say the
prism that you know that through which we see things the way in which things are maybe being a little bit distorted
not maybe being a little bit distorted I would say all of us have our own ways
of distorting quote unquote what we see we know this right if you ask
eyewitnesses to what happened you'll get you know five different people you'll get five different little twists on what
happened like there's a way in which all of us are not seeing things exactly the
same so what are some of the ways what are
some attitudes that uh we could cultivate that can be a support for our
meditation practice which can be a support for having more ease and freedom in our
lives and first of all it's uh helpful to just notice like what are some ways
in which um yeah maybe I'll just resay this some attitudes we can bring to our practice
that can be a support because often we notice that we don't have these attitudes and then there's a
way in which of course it impacts our meditation practice which impacts the
this uh movement or this opening to greater and greater Peace and
Freedom so here's one attitude during mindfulness meditation
I'm going to particularly focus on mindfulness meditation during mindfulness meditation
which is what gets taught here at IMC and what we teach primarily at the
retreat center an attitude that is supportive is to recognize that it's
enough to clearly recognize what is
happening just clearly recognize what is happening my mindfulness meditation
that's all that is required is just to recognize what is
happening the sounds pretty straightforward but when we start to
look we start to notice how well actually we kind of want to have a
particular experiences so we're not just noticing what's happening we're trying
to be more relaxed or we're trying trying to have some more ease or we're trying to have some more happiness which
is all legitimate and valid and I'll talk about this Paradox in a moment but
for mindfulness meditation just this notion that it's the the activity the what's been
asked of us is maybe we might use this language is just to
receive the experience whatever the experience might be might be a sound might be the
pressure against the body what we're sitting on might be mental events it
might be the experience of breathing whatever the experience is it's
sufficient just to receive it and have clarity about it this is the pressure against the body
that the chair or the cushion is having this is the stretch that gets filled F
felt in the Torso when there's a an inhale or this is a sound we don't need
to know what particular sound we just need to know that it's a
sound so what's implicit in this during mind mindfulness meditation there's
nothing that needs to be changed or
fixed instead there's just this moment we don't have
to resist anything we don't have to prove something there's nothing that has to be
changed there's nothing that we have to resist that we have to uh you know push
away or something like this so with mindfulness meditating we're not trying to create something we're not to trying
to create a special experience that maybe we've heard about or read about or that we've had in the past we're not
trying to make those happen instead by just like receiving
experiences and having clarity about them there's a way in which we're creating the conditions in which uh more
ease and relaxation can happen but we're not like making relaxation happen we're
not making anything happen we're just aligning with
experience we're aligning with reality we're looking clearly at what's
happening and of course What's Happening Here is here in the present not you know
lost in some fantasy or not something in the future or the past or something like this so we're honoring what is already
happening it seems so simple it turns out not to be so
easy because even if we are noticing what's actually happening in the present
moment so often there's like yeah but it's not what I want I want more of this
and less of that and I want what I had before or you know something like this there's it's not so easy to just have
this clean receiving the experience and allowing it to be as it
is because well there's all kinds of reasons why but one of them is we don't
like to be uncomfortable of course we don't like to be uncomfortable
but if we really pay attention to our life we'll notice how often do we shift
our posture just in daily life let alone you know meditate meditating you'll just
notice that all day long we're shifting our posture little bit of discomfort all day long we're having to go pee we're
having to drink water we're having to eat right there's this little bit of discomfort turning down the volume
turning up the volume or you know these types of things in which there's just a little bit of discomfort all the
time and so there's so many things in which we can adjust and we do
adjust but what what would it be like just to receive
experiences and part of this attitude of you that it's enough to clearly
recognize what is happening is recognizing in that every moment in
which we are aware what's actually happening is an opportunity to learn
something we learn about ourselves we learn like yeah I yeah this is uncomfortable and I have this this
urge to change it I have this urge to make it different or to distract myself
and you know go off into a fantasy or something like that or maybe we start to
learn like oh yeah I have this pattern of uh meeting things that I really like
of uh having a little bit of fear that they're going to go away in this little contraction even though it's Pleasant
I'm sting like oh oh I wish it would always
stay or we might notice that we have this pattern of if something is a little
bit uncomfortable we have this pattern of like getting IR irritated
internally if somebody's this is one thing that I notice is that pattern of mine is that when I'm driving this
happened yesterday and I'm on a road in which uh there's just one lane going each way and
you can't pass or anything like this and the person in front of you is going way
below the speed limit and there's a huge tons of cars behind right and this
person you know there's nothing to be done you're just there and you're seeing the speed limit sign and you're looking
at your speedometer and going okay you know I'm noticing like there's some
irritation arising but what's fascinating is if we look at this
there's something inside of us that thinks if I have this internal
experience somehow it will change the external experience right there's some
crazy thinking that we're not even aware of that says something like my irritation is going to make my external
spe experience better I got irritated and the person in
front of me still dve drove exactly the same it doesn't work there's like this
getting irritated doesn't change anything except make ourselves irit
irritated and mean like often we don't even notice how we have this kind of crazy I'm using this word crazy
ideas because when we really think about it like that we start to say like wait is that is that right well why do we get
irritated what what's the function what's the purpose is it just a pattern it's just a pattern it's not
helpful so mindfulness is acknowledging and observing whatever happens but that
doesn't mean that we have to be passive in life
I would say mindfulness meditation is about receiving experience and there can be times in
which we want to do something with uh during meditation and especially if we're doing more like concentration
practice which we often do intentionally to kind like increase the stability and the
Stillness but there's this way in which maybe this is a a paradox or maybe it's
the pointing to the art of practice or some subtlety or Nuance to
practice is there a way that we [Music]
can be with our
experience and then maybe this flows into the next uh attitude or something
that we can bring and trust that wisdom
flows out of any sense of Stillness that's getting created if we can trust
what's the experiences if we can receive the experience even if it's exactly what we don't want in that
moment there's a certain amount of Stillness that gets created if we are putting down the pushing and pulling the
irritation I want more I want less if we're able to put that down then
there's a certain amount of non agitation there's a certain amount of Stillness
and out of that Stillness grows wisdom and we can trust that
wisdom we can trust that wisdom that flows out of this Stillness this non
agitation and then the nature of this wisdom that like arises out of that it
has this quality of clarity and certainty
it has if it's not clear then it's not wisdom it's a certain type of confusion
that you know maybe maybe Clarity maybe wisdom will arise maybe Clarity will
arise but if it's not Clarity it's not wisdom it's a certain amount of
confusion but when I'm saying Clarity it doesn't mean necessarily that we have a clear intellectual cognitive conceptual
understanding sometimes wisdom just shows up as a more of a felt experience
of maybe wisdom has a a bodily experience of nothing needs to
happen right now and it's just a sense of contentment
non- agitation non-resistance like yeah nothing needs to
happen maybe that's and it's just that feeling of steadiness of stability not
being pushed around or maybe wisdom has uh some real
conceptual cognitive idea maybe there's something that just bubbles up like oh I should uh ask for forgiveness
yeah I I I I uh did some harm there or something like this or I should uh
tell the truth about this I should tell the whole truth about something you know maybe wisdom just
bubbles up that way and you know even though it's exactly what you don't want to do you don't want to admit that you made a mistake or that you were
withholding the truth or something like that maybe sometimes it just bubbles up and you're like oh yeah I don't want to
it's but yeah I can it just becomes clear and then there's a certain amount
of certainty too there's a certain amount of uh certainty because it's not
it's uh the wisdom is not concerned about
outcomes it's not like this yeah I should uh tell the whole truth about
this so that dot dot dot it doesn't have the so that dot dot dot it has I should
tell the whole truth about this because it's the right thing to do because it's
it's the next thing to do if we have this so that dot dot dot
so that they will like me more so that I'll feel more comfortable around them
so that uh I can get a promotion this person won't be irritated with me so
that you know all this then that so that that may be a smart and thing to do but
it's a little bit different than the wisdom that I'm talking about or pointing to the wisdom that comes out of
this Stillness that comes out of this non
agitation but I'm saying it has this uh Clarity and certainty but maybe there
isn't Clarity you can have clarity about their
not being Clarity there's confusion right now and
you can be clear that there's confusion and in that way right that's
Clarity and I'm a person that doesn't like to be confused much better now but
in the beginning like I had to like understand everything and know everything and I spend so much of my energy trying to understand
everything and this was like a game changer for me if you know that you're
confused you're not confused you know that you're confused
and then so I would just say oh confusion is here and then somehow that would just feel better and I didn't feel
this certain like oh okay I got to figure it out feeling just you know that just like oh no no no this is just what
confusion feels like this feels like fogginess or uncertainty or hesitation
it feels like restlessness agitation however it
feels so if there's some Stillness you can trust the wisdom that comes out of
it the wisdom has Clarity and certainty if there isn't Clarity you can have
clarity about not having Clarity and that can be a certain part of
wisdom there's this way that we might say you know wisdom knows what needs to be
done instead of saying when I have wisdom I know what needs to be done
that's conventional language and we can use that and but there's a way if we were you know just to tweak the language
wisdom knows what's to be done kind of like take out the part of like I when I'm wise knows what to do or my wisdom
knows just like wisdom knows what's to be done there's a way there can be a
certain kind of relaxation of you know trying to prove something to ourselves
or to somebody else and kind of like know just taking the me taking the ey out of it
so also there's this way in which this Stillness that can happen when there's this non- agitation that can happen when
we are bringing um this attitude that the only thing that needs to be brought
to meditation practice is just to receive experiences with Clarity know
them understand them as best we can there's also this sense of equinity
that's essentially kind of what it means right to receive experiences instead of just immediately running away from them
or trying to grab on to them so equinity has this sense of stability this sense
of unshake ability a sense of balance or
we might even say ballast you know like this way of uh you know on a sailboat
you might go over to the side but with some ballast You Know It uh writes
itself I like this that uh Pabo uh writes that a mind that does not have
equinity we might say one that is not just receiving experiences is like uh being a drunk
driver he says uh PAB body writes it's like trying to drive down the middle of the lane but
no matter how hard the driver tries to go straight in inevitably they swerve right and left
sometimes they get to close to the car in the next lane or sometimes they get too close to the uh uh the edge of the
lane the edge of the road so there's this way in which uh we
can notice how when we don't have this stability the mind is kind of like doing this trying to find just the perfect uh
experience so this idea of like to bring this attitude that mindfulness meditation is about receiving
experiences with clarity as opposed to trying to have a particular
experience in some ways as I was pointing to earlier is really different than what we might have thought about
you know mindfulness meditation to be sure a lot of people
come to meditation either indirectly or directly through mbsr mindfulness based stress reduction we just want to feel
more relaxed we want to have more
ease and it turns out that a way to have more relaxation and more ease is as best
we can to soften the amount of pushing and
pulling we're having on our experience soften the reactivity that we're
having but it's so you know we live in a societ soety of course that's really
promoting you know pleasure and you have to feel good all the time and this idea
that if you're aren't feeling good all the time then you know something is terribly
wrong but there's this way in which um maybe here's a third attitude that we
can bring to our meditation practice is
that our wellbeing is important
and then you might ask but wait di you're talking about we shouldn't be uh chasing pleasure it's so important to
make this distinction between well-being and pleasure often they get
conflated and I know that sometimes uh and when I've have like uh practice
discussions with individuals I'm thinking of one time in particular I had uh you know given the
invitation or instruction or you know to pay attention to your well-being and you know be sensitive to when there's a
really high sense of wellbeing a good sense of wellbeing and then sometime later that
person came back to me and said well when you told me to do whatever makes me happy and to go after pleasure I should
do this no that's not actually what I said but you know of course we hear this
of course we hear it that way but there are times when our uh practice
when we're like meditating for example when there will be a sense of discomfort
either whether it's you know having the body be still or you know things are coming up that are
uncomfortable and I remember hearing a Gil say this a long time ago something
he said something about any spiritual practice worth its salt or will have
some time when you feel uncomfortable it's not just about you know having mean
pleasure all the time that's about Bliss that's probably involves intoxicants if
you want to be feeling pleasure all the time right but to notice if when you're
meditating if there's a certain amount of like you know feeling tired or like oh my gosh when is this going to end
type of feeling or like when the bell rings and there's a oh thank goodness
that kind of a Feeling then that can be an indicator that you're trying to have particular
experiences that you're Sly trying to push something away or sadly trying to
have something more and that undermines your sense
of well-being in the sense that wellbeing is this sense of uh maybe
a certain sense of stability a sense of okayness despite things being
uncomfortable despite things being you know really comfortable or something like this and this is a subtle thing
that I'm pointing to it turns out the greatest sense of
well-being is not chasing after experiences and not pushing them away
but instead to just be with what is
I've said this a number of times and I I like to say I'm going to say it again that often we have this sense of like oh
yeah but I want to be really uh um relaxed and happy and I want to not be
experiencing this thing that's agitating me or my life is a mess and falling apart and I want to have clarity about
that you know we want something that's not being experienced we want you know something out
there point B we're at Point a and whatever's
happening here isn't adequate we want you know this out there how do we get to this point B how
do we get to this place where what we want is going to be there when we when we're going to have
this sense of well-being and ease and Peace and Freedom and how do we get to
point B you get to point
B by being completely full fully at Point
a just being at Point a receiving the experience with with
Clarity that's how you get to point B and this is something that you can
hear somebody say this but it's not until you have experienced this you realize oh yeah
there's something about putting down the struggle there's something about putting down the um the
agitation and instead this incredible I'm using the word incredible
it is incredible but it's subtle this sense of wellbe that
arises even though we might be uncomfortable but we're no
longer just we're no longer wrestling with reality
it can be like yeah this sucks but it is
what it is and when we in those moments of non- agitation is when this wisdom can
arise so these are some attitudes that we can be to bring to
practice the attitude that you know mindfulness meditation is
about experiencing what is being AR what is happening as opposed to you
know having a particular experience that's one
attitude it's enough it's enough to just experience what's
happening a second attitude is you can trust the wisdom that flows out of that
Stillness and the third is your wellbeing is important pay attention to
the subtle sense of contentment ease Peace and Freedom these are
different than pleasure they're related to happiness they're in the neighborhood of Happiness
uh and happy yeah so if I but I maybe I want to
highlight is that it's different than pleasure so these three attitudes can make a real
big difference in your meditation experience as well as in your
life especially when we notice how often we don't have these attitudes that can
be really helpful too short little poem this poem is by Rosemary traumer of
course I love her poetry I'm often using her poems saying her poems so once a
really short it's called what took me so long I love her titles what took me so
long and here's this poem again it's by Rosemary traumer what took me so
long plain referee between the Sun and
clouds eventually I take off my stripes to be a spectator
instead how pleasant without all that
whistling plain referee between the Sun and
clouds eventually I take off my stripes to be a spectator
instead how pleasant without all that
whistling right the referees on the side are always whistling nope do this nope do that you know
and something that I love about this little poem she's playing referee between the Sun and
clouds sun and clouds this is nature they the clouds are
moving we don't control them just in the same way that uh there's so many things
that we don't control but we're trying to control but how helpful is it to see that oh yeah it's just the nature of
some experiences to be uncomfortable it's the nature that we don't get to control as many things as we think we
can or something like
this there's this way that when we stop being the referee stop whistling and you
know trying to make things go a certain way there's just kind of like a the
reactivity just uh settles down just through attrition or uh empath uh
entropy or there's this way in which the reactivity just starts to lose its
energy and and it's so much more pleasant so much more
well-being I think I'll end with that and I'll open it up to see if there are
some questions or comments we already have a question back here
it's been my experience that false beliefs can be really tricky and like I
have a lot of them about my spiritual practice it could be any number of things but how active do you have to be
in kind of like trying to see them and maybe say oh is that really
true yeah this is a great question so I was talking about like mindfulness
meditation in just terms of uh just like receiving experiences but there might be
a time in which you do a different type you know I'm maybe being technical here
uh during meditation it might be helpful to like stop doing being Mindful and
instead drop in a question and to say what is being believed
here and then you know just i' I've say this sometimes you like just
ask just asking the question and then something bubbles up so there's a way in
which we could be mindful mindful but we notice that we can't be mindful because there's this pressure to think or a lot
of uncomfortableness and we're just feeling stuck and we're just grinding our wheels or spinning our wheels or something like that then maybe it's
appropriate to put mindfulness aside and then to just drop in a question or something like
that thank you for that question
great yeah great talk thank you you're welcome um so the challenge I encounter
with respect to attitude or uh being uh the referee during my
practice is the apparent Paradox between accepting and allowing and
honoring and validating what is and wanting to cultivate compassion
find peace uh relax and I think the Paradox is very Salient in the example
of anger so when anger arises and I practice with it of course there's an
instinct to find compassion you know don't let the mind uh get lost in
thought come back to the breath there's you know an effort to uh not let the
anger consume me but on the other hand uh honoring and validating the
anger that it's okay to be angry it's reasonable to be angry given the situation uh it's not wrong or shameful
to be angry uh is a tricky uh balance I
find because if anger is allowed to have
free reign and it is perfectly fine the way it is uh I suspect that's
not going to lead to more peace and compassion so I wonder how you balance
this uh amount of effort especially in the example of difficult emotions yeah
yeah so I would say in mindfulness meditation well like in like a formal meditation period I'll say the anger can
just allow it to build up up up up rage oh my gosh murderous rage and you're still like sitting here and it's like oh
my gosh this like it's big and just experience expc in like oh yep heat in
the face the arms and want to like punch or something that the legs want to run
or in the body maybe there's lump in the throat you like there's just agitation in the body and you're still sitting and
maybe there's even sweat coming you're like and still sitting then it's the nature for it to come up and then pass
away but it's can we do that can we allow it to catch really big and what
often happens I'd say most often happens and this is a part of the difficulty is it arises and then we get lost in
thought oh I shouldn't be angry I I or or yeah I can't believe they did that
and that reminds me this other time they did that and the next time this happens I'm going to do this and you know and then we're completely lost in thought
and we're no longer just being with the experience so one way to just be with
the experience and allow it to rise and pass away and it will pass away of course it will is um to translate anger
into a bodily somatic experience I described it you know heat in the face
or want to move wanting to move or whatever it might be so to use
adjectives or descriptions about bodily experiences because anger all of our
emotions have different uh elements they have both thoughts and uh uh Sensations
in the body the sensations in the body are or what's happening in the present moment the thoughts aren't so let the thoughts
you don't have to get rid of them just let them be in the background and take care of themselves just like oh yeah
there's going to be all that story making there's going to be a lot of pressure and and then they're going to protest no no no this is really
important you have to think about this because other but as best you can just be with the bodily experience and then
that's then allow it whatever is going to arise next to arise yeah yeah very interesting so as I understand the
effort then is bringing the attention down and what I wonder then is what what
then arises with that effort is the resistance to
thought the resistance itself as an experience that recognizing that I am
lost in thought bringing the attention down being with what is here and
recognizing a strong resistance to new thoughts it's very interesting it's very
subtle resistance to those thoughts and the more that resistance builds and the more
I'm able to stay with the emotion of anger eventually that bottle is going to pop and the thoughts will come flooding
back even after long periods of Silence long periods of Stillness long periods
of being with the breath and the emotion the thoughts are not happy that I'm not giving them my
attention so can you be and shift the for example go away from anger and go towards
resistance oh yeah the experience of resistance is like this it's this feeling of whatever it is because that's
the next thing that's happening is the is resistance maybe that there's maybe
there's some residue of anger maybe some energy left or something but then to notice the resistance that's cool that's
perfect thank you you're welcome you're welcome okay so thank you all for your
kind attention and I'm wishing you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you