so it's not quite time to start but I was just happy to I was kind of looking forward to this
that we have haven't I haven't taught this intro class now since beginning of the pandemic and I was kind of delighted
and so I couldn't wait to start we're three minutes early and people are still coming so um we'll just kind of kind of
just say hello and are any of you like completely new to
meditation completely never meditated before so welcome it's very
nice and some the rest of you have had some meditation experience if any of you
have taken a meditation class before taken one here or somewhere else here with me okay great welcome
back it's uh I've been doing this intro to meditation class
for so it's 2024 probably for at least 30 years now as part of this community
and it's one of my favorite things to do and uh you know it's kind of I've done it so
many times it's a little bit second nature but I'm I'm part of part of my joy is I'm always waiting to learn
something new from the teacher for me I might say something new or say it in a
different way and and um and uh and there's something very very
significant about the kind of beginning instruction because it's not just beginning it's kind of like in some ways
the whole thing or represents something really really significant
about what we're doing here and in recent years I've liked to us to say
that um there are two kinds of meditators there are beginners and they
are experienced beginners so we're all beginners in some
way and some of us had a lot more experience being beginners but in some ways we're all beginners uh and that
makes it kind of fresh you know it's uh and it represents kind of a I think
something very honest about how life always brings us something new and something new to meet and be present for
and find our way with and so um so whether you've meditated before or
not welcome nice to have you so let's
um so welcome to this five-week course in introduction to mindfulness
meditation and there are people still coming in so maybe I'll uh one of the least important things to to say uh is a
little bit about me and um I've been the teacher for this community since
1990 and I came to study at Stanford and I'd been a a monk for 10 years
practicing here in this country practicing in Japan and Zen monasteries practicing in Southeast Asia in Thailand
and Burma and um and that was my life I was really
there was a time in my life to no longer be a monastic but I wasn't you know
leaving Buddhism or something so I I just somehow ended up at Stanford
studying of all things Buddhist studies so I didn't get that far away but then
when I came there the the people in I started teacher training with Jack
cornfield and um and Jack cornfield knew the facilitator for a small sitting
group in paloalto and they he tell told them well you can invite guil to be the teacher
and so I came there to start teaching in 19 August 1990 and um and then uh slowly over
those time that things grew and developed until it became uh active
enough for us to buy our own place and so and um in 2000 end of 2001 we bought
this place from the wonderful ministers we had this beautiful couple who they really wanted us to buy their church
because they were kind of mystical Christians and they sat in silence and
then we sit in silence so they really wanted us to have it and um so we had a
wonderful relationship with him a lot of love and a lot of kind of a mystical not
mystical but contemplative beautiful silence we had together and
um and so then we've been here now for 22 years it's a long time it's hard to
believe so um I have a lot of experience meditating that that mean I started
meditating when I was 19 and that was
oh when you do the math that was half a century ago it's kind of unbelievable so
so I've been doing this for a long time and uh I something I love doing and
um and uh something that has brought me a tremendous amount of benefit
tremendous healing tremendous uh wisdom tremendous Freedom
tremendous capacity for compassion and and um and it's brought me a lot of ease
in my life and uh so it's been a wonderful journey and um and so it's one of my
favorite things I said to teach this inter meditation class and for some of you maybe it's a beginning of a journey
and for some of you it just continues a journey because that's what I I think of from the point of view of Buddhism this
practice or meditation that's what life is it's one endless Journey that every step is so wonderful to do and now part
of the benefit of mindfulness meditation there's something that teaches us about the tremendous value of The Next Step
the next breath this moment here and so we find fulfillment in a certain way not
from the conventions of conventional ways of being fulfilled in life not by having jobs or finding partnership or
getting praise or getting wealthy or um I don't know
having wonderful recreational experiences and Vacations or there's a lot of things people
pursue um uh conventionally in order to be fulfilled to be happy that um are not
that are kind of that are kind of from a Buddhist point of view are kind of fragile they easily disappear and they
get challenged and many people it's not enough to have success and they want
more and the people there's lots of people in our Society who are poor lots of people who are struggling with
oppression and racism and different things and um and and there too to to be caught in
that world interactive world and and uh maybe not caught but kind of Trapped in
it because of how Society is meditation teaches that there's a kind of a side door to take that doesn't
really cure racism but creates a very different landscape that can again be healing can
be uh freeing can bring a Kind of Love kind of Peace that's not dependent on
what goes on around us and that provides people with a lot of Courage it provides
people a lot of confidence provides people with um a much more sense of um
sense the word of the day fulfillment that they can be fulfilled and happy
without the world around them changing
I have a book on mindfulness that's available for free on the on the counter you're welcome to take one if you're
when you leave there might be more of you than there are books on the counter but we have lots in the shelves so just
we can pull out more but the reason I'm mentioning it is it starts off with a story of um the Ancient Ancient World
where um they um there was a king who uh
they every back then walked around Barefoot and the king one day stubbed
his toe cut his foot or something so he ordered his people to carpet the Kingdom
so he wouldn't hurt himself again and someone said you know that's there's an easier way than carpeting the kingdom
just make shoes for everyone and then you can go anywhere and so in a sense to try to change the
world the whole world to make it just perfect for you so everything is good good um it's a lot of work and what's
much more realistic is figure out how to wear shoes and so wherever you step it
become safe for you and so mindfulness is a way to find maybe it's kind of
funny to call it shoes but uh to every every every Everything You Touch with
your senses everything you see and hear everything you think everything that
happens to you you have now have uh a u a safety net you have a you have a
capacity you have a means by which to know it and be with it that you're
protected you're safe in some deep inner way and uh and that's a lot better than
carpeting the world to make it all work for you and some people are very busy trying to change the world when it's
easier to change yourself so um I love teaching this
class and I hope to hope that this is nice for you you get a taste of uh This
Joy and kind of what's what's how mindfulness can be nice and
um um IMC our Center here is a Buddhist center it is a Buddhist Meditation I'm
teaching and though we're kind of Buddhist light here so we don't really
care whether you're a Buddhist or not doesn't that that's not really important you don't have to adopt Buddhist beliefs
ideas teachings in order to do this practice this practice uh does not me
the practice doesn't need Buddhism um Buddhism needs the
practice so um so if you come to do the practice and you hear me refer to
Buddhism and it's maybe it's weird or you know something just know that that's
the Buddhism part is take it or leave it it's all take it or leave it but just just just a little warning in case some
people some people get a little uncomfortable with the Buddhist
references and um the um so the way this course works is it's
five weeks and the instructions is Progressive so uh today we'll talk about
some basic ideas of meditation posture to kind of and then meditation on
breathing and with that as a foundation and then hopefully you'll practice a little bit at home and then next week
we'll build on that to do mindfulness of the body the body is phenomenally important um and so much so that it's
maybe unfortunate that we they translated into English the word Sati as
the ancient Indian word Sati as mindfulness uh it's probably I would have preferred they have chosen B chosen
body fullness because to really learn how to be embodied as part of mindfulness as part of where our
attention and awareness resides is uh is Central to this whole journey that we're
on and then the third week is mindfulness of emotions and um and
people have complicated relationships with their emotions but to be a human being is to have emotions some people
have them strong sometime people have them weak but they're still important part of life and so the idea is to fold
emotions into the practice not to push them away not to try to deny them or
have shame around them or feel like some are you shouldn't have some mindfulness is a is a amazing place when you do
mindful meditation that you can really open to the inner emotional life in a particular way that's very healthy and
healthy for that inner life of ours the fourth week we'll talk about mindfulness of thinking and for some
people who meditate there's a war between thinking and meditation because they think so much and they think they
shouldn't be thinking when we do mindfulness medit ation there's no divide like that that um certainly
sometimes the mind gets very quiet almost like it doesn't think at all and that's quite nice but there there we
don't we don't mindfulness practice we're not living in a divide between how things should be and how things actually
are we're always being present for how things are as they are and if we're thinking a lot then um
the idea is to learn how to bring mindfulness to that in a way that's beneficial for us how to bring attention
and awareness to it so we're not caught in the thoughts we're not being driven and pushed around by the thoughts or
troubled by our thoughts and so we learn how to be mindful of them and um but you
don't have to stop thinking so don't we don't want to set up this strong dichotomy strong
separation thinking is wrong and meditation is supposed to be silent so we'll talk about that on the
fourth week and it's a lot easier reason we wait wait for the fourth week to talk about thinking is that it's a lot easier
to have this uh useful attention to thinking if you're first have if you know how to be
mindful of breathing you know how to be present for your body and you know how to be present for emotions those three
then really are huge support for mindfulness of thinking and then the fifth week will be how to P pull all
these together so they work together as a whole not only in meditation but also
outside into our daily life and U and one of the one of the benefits of
learning mindfulness comes from not keeping the mindfulness to meditation but learning how to bring a higher
quality attention awareness uh into our daily activities in life and so the
benefits of meditation are carried with us into into our life in the way we live and then um from from a Buddhist point
of view then we learn how to live with much more freedom in our life than many
people experience when they're caught in their attachments caught in their fears caught in their Ambitions or
preoccupations so that's the kind of uh the path we'll take and um in the um so we'll do uh
I'll do some teaching we'll do probably most days we'll do one or two short
periods of meditation and then um and then uh
you'll be a chance for some questions and um and hopefully you'll feel well engaged
in all this so
um the other thing that I want to say as a as an introduction to this kind of mindfulness
meditation is that um it can be many people find it challenging many people find it
challenging to sit quietly and to um have their mind be quiet or sit still
and because they're Restless or they're something and um the
um um i' like to kind of encourage you
to consider that either it's impossible to fail when you do this
meditation or we simply don't bother with the orientation that you're doing
it right or wrong or you you're succeeding or not succeeding it's just a waste of time when you meditate to have
those thoughts um so you're kind of it's fine whatever happens to you when you
meditate the approach here is it's fine it's just one more thing to be
mindful of one more thing to be aware of to really recognize it this is a practice of recognizing what is as I
said earlier recognizing what is not recognizing what you think should be
and many people want things to happen they should happen I mean many people are suffering and challenged and in
their lives so of course we want to be happy but the path here in this mindfulness tradition is Define that by
learning how to be present for this experience now in a productive way in a useful way to really learn the art of
how do we show up for our life in the moment no matter what's happening to us
and um so that's that's why you can't fail because you just get to have be
where you are and then the Journey of discovering well how do I have a
productive how do I have a useful attention to this how do I hold this with care with compassion how do I hold
it with ease how can how can I be relaxed even with this even with this as
opposed to fighting it or justifying it or all kinds of complicated things that we
do so please come in you can come in anywhere to a chair and and
U you arrived at a good time because it's kind of like we're starting
now so I thought maybe a nice way of beginning is um to do something really
short to give you a little taste of what's possible that it doesn't have to be a long meditation to benefit from
this mindfulness practice and uh you can do it in the posture you're in you don't have to change your
posture because in this is can be done in daily life as well and it doesn't require you know anything more than just
a few seconds I call it the three breath journey and that is uh to close your
eyes and just hang out with three breaths you can count them one two three
and just with your eyes closed just stay there with three breaths
so why don't you try
that so maybe that was three breaths so what happened in three over
in the course of three breaths did anything change for you or is it nothing changed like why way did I do
that anybody want to
share yes please it's kind of nice and relax a little louder it's kind of nice
and relaxing kind of nice and relaxing in three breaths uhuh great someone
else oh I just noticed distractions you
noticed distraction well that's one of the primary things we're trying to do is notice what's happening for us and you
think it was useful to notice that yeah I I noticed it and was able to
refocus on breathing uhhuh and that was a nice thing to do it was great how
so just the sense that I don't have to be at the mercy of what's going on
around me or what I'm what thought comes into my head great lovely that's a great
lesson I felt a little bit like once I paid attention to my breath I wanted to
control it so and then it just took me a bit to try and relax and have it come at its
own uh Rhythm uhhuh I don't think I accomplished that in three breaths
though you know it u in the way that we do mindfulness uh it's enough just to
notice you're trying to control it you don't have to stop doing it the stopping will take care of itself
if you if you just if you see clearly what's happening that's all we're that's all we're doing in the main thing in
mindfulness practice and uh and then it's remarkable if you stay like that very simple and just say oh it's like
that it's like that um something begins happening without you having to fix it
and that's a real that's a real cool thing to see happen but I think I think it's
fantastic that you saw that you were trying to control it and I apologize if I'm completely miss you or something but
what I see is when people report right away when they sit sit down that they're trying to control the breathing it
represents a tendency that's playing out in their life in other ways as well and so so it's a good tendency to see this
is the good place to see it and kind of work with it and find another
way time slowed down for me time slowed down for you very nice so in three
breaths very nice so it didn't take long did it so some of you found it was nice
and so imagine if you did that you know I don't know once an hour through the
day it probably change your day quite a bit and it doesn't take the three breaths
doesn't take long and how many times in your daily life or you're just waiting for something to happen that where you
you could you could take the three breaths oh I don't have to wait I can just do three breaths and then see what
happens so mindfulness can be that easy we're going to meditate for longer but
uh but I think getting that message that can be that simple um and to do it repeatedly that three breath Journey
over over days of over the day here and there just whenever it seems like it's nice um you begin you start you start
building up a familiarity to all these little tricks of the Mind the body how
you are how you how things can shift you have you develop a capacity to let go of
whatever you're caught up in in the moment in some small degree and to have that kind of accumulation of those
lessons over time is really be very helpful in any life we
live so we practice meditation which is sitting quietly for some kind of extended period of time and um and the
classic idea of meditation is sit on the floor cross-legged it's not necessary to
do that those of you who are going to do your meditation in a chair you can be reassured or be inspired that the in
Buddhist lore and this the kind of Buddhist mythology the next Buddha will
be a chair sitter so um maybe you know maybe
you and U but uh there's something nice about sitting on the floor because it's
easier to have a kind of a the stability of a tripod uh your two knees and your bottom
creates a nice kind of foundation that uh in a low center of gravity that lets
kind of the upper torso kind of relax and settle and um many ago I read a study
that said that the two human postures that allow the human body to relax the
most is in yoga What's called the corpse posture when you're laying on your back and uh sitting in full Lotus like this
upright that's something about this alignment of these postures allow for a deeper relaxation over
time so it's nice to do this if you can and um the way we it's usually done is
you want to be elevated a bit and uh depending how open your hips are um it
will depend how high you want to sit if you're tight in your hips the higher you want to sit and if you're really loose
you can sit pretty low but you want to have enough height so that uh there is a teeny bit of curve in your lower part of
the back for most people it's kind of the natural curve that's retained but just a teeny bit not overarch but just a
little bit so there's a teeny bit of of uh uh movement in the spine that helps
push you the rest of your torso upright and alert
um and then there's also sitting on your knees like the gentleman here that's
that's uh's you're sitting on top of a cushion that way and some people find that works really well for them um and
the gentleman here is sitting on a bench we have it we have these benches in the back in the corner there and some people
love sitting in those benches and that's uh easier than cross-legged for some people and U but it gets you low center
of gravity if you're sitting in a chair the um um the classic instruction
is to have both feet uh flat on the ground in front of you and have the feet
parallel to each other legs and with with the the knees slightly lower than
the hips so that because if the knees are above the hips it tends to push out
the spine in the lower back it causes trouble over time and if it's um and if
you need to have extra help we have a variety of cushions here and if you're if you're short you can put
a a cushion underneath your your your feet if you're tall then you want to
maybe put a cushion underneath the the SE on the seat of your chair so that um you get the right kind of way in which
your your knees are just a little bit lower than the hips not a lot lower and not
higher um some people people like to have their legs out wide like in a triangle they feel stable that way but
the idea is to have a feeling of stability in the feet um that you're really here in a strong way so you're
rooted here with the feet firmly on the ground and then if possible to sit uh as
Alert in the chair as you can upright in the chair as you can some people find it
really nice not to use the back rest there's something that extra alertness that comes when you're not resting the
body against something but you're holding it up yourself and it supports being really present here sometimes when
people are using a backr too much it's kind of like you're being supported and some people are lulled into kind of
being a little bit complacent and not engaged fully in the practice but whatever you need to do so
you're comfortable um to do the practice um but the point is not to be
super comfortable don't don't like try to like because you're supposed to you think meditation is about all about relaxing and you're going to find
absolutely the most comfortable posture with you know that you can so that you can relax as much as you can that's not
the point of mindfulness relaxation is certainly a byproduct of this practice and it's really helpful up to a point
but if it's overemphasize and that's if that's the be all and end all of what you're trying to do when you're meditating you're you're Miss missing
out on the benefits that come from developing a calm but clear awareness
and so what we're looking for for is a balance between calmness and
alertness and if you overemphasize calmness then you lose the alertness if you over emphatize alertness then you
might lose the calmness it's a little bit stressful and so it is to find the balance and some of that is found
through the posture so the idea is to have a posture that supports both calmness and
alertness in our tradition we meditate with the eyes closed and and um but some
people prefer meditating with their eyes open which is fine to do um in our
tradition we emphasize in having your eyes kind of half open looking 45 degrees down to the floor with a very
loose Focus like you're looking at a mountain in the distance and the hands uh can be in many
many ways um these in the last decade or so I've been having my hands on my
thighs this way and um for decades before that I had my hands together like
this when I meditated and sometimes it goes back and forth still and um one of
the things you have to be look out where your hands are that your hands are not so far forward that they're pulling your
shoulders forward so because then it's very easy many of us you know in the computer all day or something and are
leaning forward already and so we want to kind of not be constantly kind of pulling over and so bringing bringing
the hands back so the elbows are right along the sides here of the body and if you're sitting with the
hands together Somehow Here rather than resting them on the ankle which
sometimes pulls you forward also is to get something that you
um you so there your hands are resting higher up and this kind of keeps the
chest a little bit more open and and and relaxed so that's kind of the basics
there's more I could say but that's I think for their purposes tonight so
let's uh uh try it I'll do a guided meditation on um beginning the
meditation which just getting started every meditation has a period of preparation getting getting warmed up
for it and then we'll switch over to do a few minutes of mindfulness of
breathing so uh so and if you need to get it we have lots of cushions there if
you want to try to get some more cushions and make yourself more comfortable you're welcome to do
that so assuming a posture that for you is a comfortable
posture that helps you sit
upright and gently closing your
eyes and the first task is to just relax the surface tension of the
day one way to do that is to take a few deeper breaths not too deep but deep enough to
be really feel your body stretch and expand your torso and then as you exhale
to relax your
body the deep
inhales are a way to feel connected to start making a connection to your
immediate experience of your
body and the exhale is a time to relax into your
body and then letting your breathing return to
normal but continue the process of relaxing on the
exhale starting with the muscles of your
face as you exhale softening the forehead and around the
eyes
as you exhale softening the
shoulders as you exhale relaxing the
belly
and maybe in the next few exhales softening your whole body
and there's one more place where it's nice to relax and that is any tension or
tightness or pressure that you might feel that connected to your
thinking maybe behind the forehead and middle of the
head maybe in the shoulders sometimes in the chest
wherever that there might be some tightness connected to thinking the thinking
muscle for the next three exhales relax that thinking
relax your thinking
muscle
and then
you notice now where in your
body is the experience of breathing most pronounced for
you where is it easiest to feel the movements in the body as you
breathe some people is the movements of the
chest some people the movements of the belly the
diaphragm some people enjoy feeling the movement of the air going in and out
through the
nostrils and some people like experiencing all those
together somehow the whole experience of breathing in the
body in a sense we're looking to notice how the body your body
experiences breathing
and whatever way you're breathing is completely
fine it's not about how you're breathing it's about how you stay connected to it
aware of
breathing instead of attention going to reinforce
thinking we use our attention to reinforce being present
here and now in our bodies as we
breathe
and sooner or later you'll notice your mind is distracted or pulled into a world of
thoughts you're not doing meditation wrong when that happens it's
okay what the meditation is what we do then is just recognize
clearly I'm thinking recognizing you're
thinking is not staying on the train of
thoughts stepping away and saying oh look at
that and then Begin Again with your
breathing
if the thinking mind is strong then you might start all over
again with the little exercises in relaxing the
body relaxing a thinking
mind
for
if you find yourself drifting off in thoughts often
strongly you can always do the three breath Journey
just to be content with three
breaths and then maybe do it
again
for
and then as we come come to the near the end of this
meditation you might pause briefly from being with your breathing
or trying to be with your breath and
instead see if you can recognize how you feel right now how are
you and see if in whatever way you are or you can let it be enough just to know
it just to recognize oh this is how I am without adding anything more to that
any judgments or commentary reactions to it oh this is
how it
is
and whatever way you are in the middle of it now return to
your breathing as if you're breathing into the middle of how you are
out of the middle allowing yourself yourself to be
the way you are but Cent h on your
breathing
and then to end the [Music] meditation again take take a few long
slow deep breaths and as you breathe in deeply
feel your body more fully reconnect more fully to your
body feel your body against your cushion the
chair the
floor and then when you're ready you can open
your
[Music]
eyes
so many years ago I was on a Meditation Retreat up in the Santa Cruz
mountains and there was a I had a break from the schedule and I was sitting at
the bank of a small Creek of very clear water and as I looked at the water it
was very shallow but very clear I looked at it and said I don't
think think the water is moving I think but it's a creek so it's probably moving
so I was kind of like looking at it so then I took a stick that was next to me and I put the stick into the water um
vertically and then a little wake little waves got formed on the edge of the of
the of the stick oh yes the water is moving and this is the direction it's
moving sometimes with our in our life we don't see see what's happening to us
very clearly we're caught up in our thoughts we're caught up in our activities our feelings what's going on
and we're so involved in it we don't quite know what's happening but it's useful to have a reference
point that from which we can see oh look at that so in meditation the breathing
is that reference point if you um sit down and try to follow a series
of breaths in a row and you very quickly realize you
can't my mind is out of control then now you and you didn't know
that until you started to be with your breathing then the meditation has been
successful not at following the breath but that's not necessarily the point the point is to see yourself more clearly oh
look at that my mind is out of control and we say in N tradition that
it's it's better if you have a mind that's out of control it's better to know it than not know
it and so having that reference point trying to be with the breath and not being able to because the mind is
spinning or preoccupied or or there's feelings and emotions which are bubbling up and all that if there's reactions
being bored like just making commentary about what's happening this is you know this is the best thing since peanut
butter you know this is great then uh all those things are taking Tak you away from the Simplicity
of just being here and so rather than being upset that it's taking you away from the Simplicity
of just being with your breathing it's actually the whole point is to be able to see yourself clearly look at
that I'm I'm thinking about peanut butter all the time when I meditate isn't that fascinating what's going on
with me I had no idea now that I think about it now that I realize it I'm thinking about peanut butter all day
it's probably peanut butter but some people that's what they do there's some equivalent and um so um so it's a way of
highlighting and seeing ourselves getting to know ourselves better so if you try to sit down to be
with the breathing and it doesn't work that's okay the meditation works if
you see what it is that's distracting you what's C oh that's what it is some
people get so frustrated because they can't stay present for the breathing um and that's unfortunate
because that's not the point the the main point is to see ourselves
clearly but as we but if you're able to stay with a breath the breath is a is classically a calming for most people
not everyone a calming uh influence on us and if you
can stay with the breathing breathe mindfully it tends to calm the the
nervous system some people find that just breathing a little bit exhaling a little
bit longer than usual helps that calming of the system down many people live
tense lives preoccupied lives so it's good to calm and so that calming effect
sometimes is contagious kind of like oh this is interesting I want to stay with this because it feels good and then
you're kind of in the world of breathing which can be nice and then but to stay with breathing sometimes you get calmer
quieter and some people you know really like meditation because things get quieter the mind gets quieter the
tensions in the body tend to fade away over time um mostly because we're not reinforcing them anymore but in the
daily life we go around thinking the same things having the same emotional responses and reactions and so the
tension is just being reinforced you know the Fe for fear all the time and every place we go we're afraid of
something you know show but before you know our shoulders up by the ears we don't even know it because that's just
normal and then we sit down to meditate and we're no longer living in that fear
World slowly the shoulders begin to relax because they're not being
reinforced as we stay with the breathing and just relax with it that supports
this this movement of no longer feeding our reactivity feeding our
preoccupations as we get calmer we start seeing deeper layers of
our reactivity deeper layers of the operating principles of what makes us run and what's driving us that is often
um happening uh out of sight from ordinary life we see some of the common
patterns of emotions that really are influence us or driving us or in you
know affecting us we see some of the beliefs and thoughts assumptions we have
that are kind of hidden because we're so much in the surface mind so bus and activated so there's a value of getting
quieter and quieter because it allows us to see what's happening with us clearer and
clearer I'm emphasizing this so you don't set up breath meditation as
something you can do and fail at there's no failing it's it's uh you do it the best
you can and then you learn from how you're not doing it then you're 100% doing meditation
accurately oh look at that that's what that's why I keep losing the breath
because I'm much more interested in peanut butter who would have guessed you know like wow I'm like a peanut butter
junkie and um boy I better stop eating peanut butter for breakfast lunch and dinner I that that's going to consume
all my waking hours so I'm being silly with that but it's not a silly phenomena
that people get preoccupied with all kinds of things um and um and um and
that's what they think about all the time or concerned with all the time sometimes it's kind of sad you know some
people there's a lot of people in our society we have a society that um that
uh feeds us fear Society social kind of constructs
that really reinforce fear and feeling of inadequacy of who we are and it's and
then people take it very personally a personal failure which really a society that's kind of teaching this to
us and we're some people are caught up in some level of anxiety all the
time to see that and be able to just see it and breathe with it and relax with it
is life-changing if it's an alternative to always being caught up in it and some
people come to meditation and discover that they I had no idea how that was pervasive I'm always anxious I didn't
know it's sad but it's really inspiring to
finally see it the principle in this practice here that it's much better if
you see what you're doing see what's driving you than not knowing it at
all once you see it the idea is to be really simple with
it don't there's no need in this meditation to judge yourself no need to to uh feel like
anything that you do when you're sitting quietly in this kind of meditation posture is wrong that it's just
something else to see it's something else to know and to hold kind of like you're your best
friend or you know maybe some of you I hope some of you have had the experience of either being someone's friend or
someone being your friend where one of the people is really Disturbed really upset about something and you sit on a
bench and one of the the friend just listens to you just is there accompany you it doesn't try to fix you it doesn't
try to solve anything they're really good listener and something in your system relaxes with that so they
meditation we're being our own friend we're just listening we're just being with how we are so that something in our
nervous system can relax so so the idea has to be simple be
that friend oh that's how it is oh that's how it is okay let's go back to breathing in the middle of it let's go
back because maybe there's more to discover let's go back and breathe breathe and then sometimes maybe you
breathe for not three breaths but 10 breaths maybe sometimes you start feeling there's a kind of little um um
at some point where uh you stay long enough with a series of breaths you kind of like Get In the Groove with
it and it just feels like you're starting getting concentrated and oh this is really good and it just feels
very sweet there's all this wonderful sweetness or actually kind of inner
beauty where the breath feels really beautiful you feel really beautiful on inside that comes from being absorbed or
being really kind of t uh kind of tuned into the breath over
time so that's one of the byproducts can happen don't try to make that
happen you know anytime you try to make something happen meditation then guess
what that's that's the opportunity to see look at that I'm trying to make something
happen turns out I'm I'm trying to do that all day long I do it all day long
trying to make something happen fix something adjust something improve something now I'm doing a medit of
course I'm doing it in meditation look at that now I can see it much more clearly I keep even here I'm doing it
wow I guess meditation is working I see it as opposed to oh no I can't meditate
I'm a terrible meditator because I'm always trying so that kind of attitude now I'm
not doing it right I'm a terrial meditator that's one of those odd things that's a self-fulfilling
prophecy if you have that belief it kind of becomes true but you don't have to
believe it don't don't go that way that's that the meditation is a radically different Paradigm of how to
be with oneself just to know this is how it is so now I'll take some questions or
about any of this we've done so far but before I do that I want to say I forgot to say at the beginning you know my
voice is kind of quiet so if you have trouble hearing me you can raise your hand and ask us to turn up the volume
but we also have a hearing system devices just outside there on the counter and you can uh go now if you
want them or anytime you come here those hearing system devices work well too to to augment the
sound so any questions about anything or concerns about anything that so
far hello um so I meditated for a few years now closer
here can you hear me now okay so meditated for a few years now and somebody once told me that when you eat
and then you meditate after it's it's not good because your concentration is doesn't it gets how you say it wouldn't
work you yeah yeah and so I never listen to it but I always meditate in the morning before itat and so today we ate
right before we came here and I realized that is that has some kind of Truth in
it or it's just I don't know just
thinking so it's very interesting what you say the idea in meditation in mindfulness meditation is
to learn to become your own teacher so you so the way you become
your own teacher is to experiment with that um uh um uh sometimes meditate
before you eat like before breakfast and see how that is sometimes do it afterwards and then see what works for
you some people find that it's easier to be present for meditation if their
stomach is not full other people find that only by uh eating a little bit
first do they have the energy and Clarity to be able to practice attention so different people are
different this way so rather than me telling you what it should be it's much better if you become the uh you discover
for yourself by trial and error different things is that okay yeah thank
you but there is a long tradition of meditators medit meditating first thing
in the morning um kind of before everyone else is awake and it's so it
can be so sweet you it's still very quiet there's not many cars on the road it's maybe dark it just feels like like
there's all this support for just being present and quiet and and calm and and
uh some people find the advantage of meditating as soon after they wake up is that um the momentum of daily concerns
hasn't built up and uh and so it's a really nice time some people find other people find that
it's terrible to meditate first thing in the morning and they're just so anxious and they can't wait for their cup of coffee
and you know so the idea is to learn how it works for you there was a long time
period in my life where I meditated um twice a day the when I was in college I
meditated the first thing in the morning and um the 40 40 minutes before I went
to bed in the in the evening and that was my rhythm and that was a great Rhythm for me there was another period
of time where I meditated first thing in the morning and then I meditated when I
came back from work in the in the 6:00 and that was really great to come back
from work and and just kind of clear out and a lot of the first half of the meditation was clearing out all the
momentum and stuff of the work day and the second half the of the meditation I had the benefit of then being cleared
out and now I was sitting there really clear and that was clear for the rest of the evening it was a real like I was
refreshed and clear and renewed for the evening so they he has to experiment and find out what's nice
and so there's a couple of can we he was he had his hand up before and
then um I was actually going to ask about meditating in the morning yeah and
trade-offs between you know there being I guess nothing to be worried about yet
yeah the day just started um but you you addressed it so thank you yeah and I
mean if if a person has lots of time and ability it's great to do it two times a day just because you different times a
day you different benefits in different ways but most people can't do it you
know lot people at work and they have responsibilities and and um so you know
once a day is plenty yeah so when I first heard that when I first started
that you can't fail at meditating um I remember I took that and interpreted
that as so whenever I sat down I would just do whatever let my mind go wherever
and I just go you know and so now I know a little better but would would you say
that that's I don't want to use fail but are you not really medit ating if you just kind of yeah yeah let your let your
mind go all over the place yes um it's possible to sit down and not
meditate you know sit sit there and just Daydream and you know I can't fail and
I'm thinking about going to Disneyland and buying more peanut butter and those are my first days yeah yeah you know and
and there's people who Wasted Years of their life because somehow they got their permission the idea that they're
allowed to think anything they want everything's okay in meditation and they're just drifting off in thought
and planning vacations and all that and I mean maybe it's nice to do but it's not meditating to meditate is to
recognize what's the core thing of mindfulness is to really recognize oh oh
I'm planning vacation oh this is what's happening now but it's not just recognizing it lightly
is to recognize it with such Clarity that it's the equivalent of
you're in a it happened happened to me when I was younger once where I was in a crowd of people who are arguing about
something and some reason I had to leave and when I came back a couple minutes
later they were still arguing but I was like 10 feet away and I just stood there looking at them and I was no longer in
the argument I was no longer invested I was no longer caught I just watching it from a distance wow that's quite
something they're they they're all kind of lost themselves in this argument and they're not listening to each other
other and but I was no longer caught in it so it's like taking a step back from
your life and really seeing it and it's not like a checklist approach you know
oh you know distracted and that you know let's continue talking thinking about
the distraction it's like oh taking the time oh look at that step back
oh I'm planning vacations oh this is what planning vacations are like and
what you'll see is what we as we go through these weeks then you can in order to see it more clearly you start
feeling the the sensations and physicality the body side what happens
you're thinking about vacations then you start recognizing the emotions that are driving it then you start recognizing
knowing how to mindful the thoughts that are driving it so the whole Ecology of what we're doing starts becoming open so
the active recognition is seeing kind the big picture of our life what's really all the details of what's
Happening and as you do that you're no longer caught in it you're starting to become
free and in that freedom the whole system will begin to relax and become
calmer and more clear does that make sense yes thank you so there is a there is a kind of purpose
and momentum and all this but um I mean if you really if you're like to fa if
you really like the idea of failing yes I mean if you're really just
sitting here daydreaming and just not you know paying any attention to what's going on then of course you failed
meditating but as soon as you are paying attention then you can't
fail thank
you hi um so uh I've been meditating hold Closer Closer okay so I've been
meditating for a while um but I wanted to um sort of contrast the experience of
mindfulness versus another technique so with what I've noticed with um you know
like the technique that you're teaching which is just keep coming back to the breath what I find is at least for a
while I'm wondering what is it about the breath there's no drama there's no nothing why should I keep going back so
there's a certain borom that starts coming in and then slowly I what I notice is the Dynamics that I start
settling down become calmer and then it can focus on the breath a lot better
does that make any sense or I think so there's there's many many ways of
meditating there are different kinds of meditation practice so and even Buddhism we have different meditation practice
people do some meditation practices are uh focusing much more on concentration
in rather than mindfulness in Buddhism there's just two major movements of
meditation there's the mindfulness movement and there's a concentration movement and some people do one or the
other some people combine them in a certain way and that's kind of what we do here at IMC is combine
them but some people uh begin with concentration concentration is much
easier to fail because you're either concentrated or you're not and the mind
wanders off and you failed you have to come back come back what's the advantage of the concentration approach just come
back and come back come back it's really simple you don't have to think about what you're doing you don't have to
recognize anything just start again start again come back something for some people something really begins to relax
when it's that simple and you're no longer feeding the distractions so some people it works
better to do concentration first and then mindfulness some people works better do mindfulness first than
concentration um some people um it's uh mindfulness turns out to be a
phenomenally useful meditation practice to learn to be able to do any other kind
of meditation practices people do or contemplative practices or prayer or spiritual practices people do and a lot
of people have come to who who following non- Buddhist religious tradition have
come to learn mindfulness so they can do their own religion better because they see clearly what the mind is doing they
see how they get caught they see how they uh can learn how to be more present for what they're doing so is this an
adequate answer for you or do you want to ask again no and uh I think that's okay okay
I have to kind of practice it some more to understand I tend to try and concentrate which is problem yeah so
that's what you did before was the the concentration approach yeah I've been doing trying to do mindfulness also but
I tend to start trying to con stay on the breath and then then it goes away
and then and then I wonder why am I just you know it's difficult to stay there
yeah so so what what I'm suggesting here is you know stay a little bit on the breath but is but when you find your
mind wandering off take the time to recognize oh that's what's
happening and then begin again at the breathing but always take your time oh
this is what's happening this is why I'm distracted this is what I'm caught up in and then Begin Again the breathing until
the next thing you and over time some of the reasons for being distracted will quiet down because you've seen it you're
no and maybe you're not so tempted anymore okay come back come back and
then maybe rather than being with two breaths you're four six eight and once
you can get into like maybe I mean without forcing it without trying too hard if you can stay with 20 or 30
breaths in a row at some point you might feel like something CL you get in like I said earlier you get in the groove the
sweetness of that there the human system that we have loves to be
absorbed have you ever read some of you maybe have read I don't people read novels anymore but now there's Netflix
but but um the uh uh some of you have
probably read a novel and it's just so enjoyable to read it or you do a craft or do play a musical instrument and you
kind of get absorbed in what you're doing and or cooking and you get absorbed in what you're doing and it's
just so nice to do it you kind of everything else kind of gets forgotten this idea of everything forgotten and
just really doing your one thing kind of being in the groove of that is really
good for this psychop physical system of ours there's a lot of it feels really nice and sweet to do it so the same
thing can happen with breathing that some point uh when we no longer get so
pulled away into all these things because we've recognized them we've learned to settle them we learn to relax
at some point you know 20 30 40 who knows how long it takes but the uh the
whole system begins to gather around the breathing and um it's usually called concentration you get concentrated on
the breath but gathered around and it's like believe it or not it's like better than reading a good
novel it doesn't mean un principle or just hearing that it seems ridiculous right the breath how can that be
interesting but uh what's interesting is not the breath what's interesting is the
way the mind's ability to get concentrated and focused and um not a
few meditators feel a lot of Joy there's something there's something that produces Joy a sense of well-being for
our system to be unified into an absorb State the unification of Earth most
people live fragmented lives and this meditation helps us to stop being fragmented and brings everything
together so it can be unified in Harmony and that's where the sweetness
comes yes
so um I find that when I'm trying to come back to the breathing so I get go
off in my little tangent in my mind I have this tendency to do this sort of
visualize this person who is doing this sort of motion in and out for the
breathing but I don't know if then that is using my mind to
like focus on the breathing but I actually I don't know it just sort of
happened where I just visualize this person who's just doing this motion I
don't know so the interesting that's great so the interesting to be able to answer your question I have to answer
your question I have to ask you a question um when you do visualize that
person doing this thing with the breathing uh what happens to you um well I relax and I I can do the
counting so I can do the counting the one so it helps you be present helps you relax helps you to be be there yeah so
then it's useful okay and uh and then but at some point you want to stop the
visualizing okay so use it when it's useful to get you going or get you centered and then once you're kind of
more there then stop doing it okay does that make sense yeah yeah you look a
little bit teeny bit per don't know that I can do that like think like
it's like I don't know if I can then what am I actually thinking about am I
thinking breath in breath out oh when there's no visualization yeah oh okay so
um yes so this is so this gets to another uh instruction that we give in
this tradition about mindfulness um that's optional but some people find it very helpful is uh as
whatever you're being aware of you make a very very quiet gentle tender relaxed
note naming it so if you're with your breathing you would gently say in as
you're breathing in out as you're breathing out and that might be enough for your mind to be
involved and in uh the way I was taught originally it was Rising because we were
told to follow the breath in the belly so breathe in the rising of the belly we say rising and then as you bre out
falling is the the belly fell so so there's this different words you can use
and then if you find yourself thinking about peanut butter you say thinking you don't even you don't have to even say
peanut butter you can just thinking or if you're finding yourself feeling kind of agitated agitated and
there's something and so we'll talk more about this but maybe for you this is the
you're looking for something that you can do so you're not too idle and so the visualization of this person doing the
breathing gets you involved right so so the other thing you might try is this
very simple mental noting in out and see if that keeps you on
track so yes so we have in the corner if you can wait for the mic and if if you
can turn it up a little bit the volumea so one thing that I noticed was I'm a
I'm I'm very new to meditation one thing that I noticed today as I was meditating was when I was concentrating
on the breath I felt that I have forgotten how to breathe I was just s s slow down but you know I don't have my
hearing a I lost them next week I'm supposed to have them back but um but so
yeah I was just saying that as I was concentrating on my bread I almost felt that I have forgotten how to breathe and
every action of breathe in breathe out did not feel natural like I was breathing in too hard breathing
out yeah like you know like it was more like a like what they tell you in yoga
like deep in very breathe when you are breathing in breathe in very deeply and
then breathe out very deeply so I was trying to do that because I was concentrating too much on the breath
right but I think that's unnatural but I also wanted to hear your thoughts about
yeah for people who who have come from a TR where you do a lot of um controlling
your breath where you breathe in particular ways it takes a while to switch gears and come here do this
practice where we don't try to do anything special with our breath we just leave our breath alone and let it
breathe it let the breath breathe itself just what we call it a natural breath but just don't try to make special don't
try to change it so but sometimes it goes for people some people it's goes on automatic that they start trying to
controlling their breath and doing the doing something their breath so there's two things you can do with that the
first to go along with what I said already today um now you get to be mindful aware of what it's like to have
a controlled breath it might be uncomfortable it might feel like you shouldn't be doing it but if you're
doing it uh just relax and keep doing it and be aware that you're doing it oh
look at that this is a controll breath you can use the mental note control this is what control is like and the magic of
this is that if you clearly see that this what you're doing at some point your inner system will begin to
relax but if you feel like you're controlling the breath and then you try to control it by controlling it
more it just you can you can spin out and end up in trouble so they just just
relax so control breath not control breath just know you're breathing the way it is and let it be really simple so
that's the that's the first thing I would suggest the other thing you can do is sometimes when we're caught up and
controlling the breath is just stop breathing for a little while and a little while means four seconds you know
just very short until you feel a natural pull to breathe in and just then allow
it to breathe in maybe at the top of the in breath pause until you feel the
natural pull to breathe out and sometimes that little pause breaks this
the controlling
okay do you have suggestions for creating uh the habit of a meditation
practice great great uh I think one of the one of the ways of developing a
habit of meditation practice is to do it every day and um and so that's kind of
like a catch 22 right so so first first what you should do is consider what's realistic if you
decide I'm going to sit meditate 45 minutes every day in the morning but your life is so busy and it's impossible
to do then you're just disappointed because you can never do it so you have to figure out how long and when in the
day is realistic for you that's some of the reason why some people find it really good to do it first thing in the
morning before we get caught by everything but you know it's possible
that you're that's not what your life is about and but it's possible if you do 10 minutes a
day that's long that you can realistically do anything more than that is not
realistic and um so I would start with something short and then build on that in fact
that's what I recommend from this intro meditation class is that for those of you who are starting your meditation
with this class start with 10 minutes each day uh for this next week and maybe
not even every day but um six of the next seven days um so you can you know and um and
so maybe Sunday's off or something but uh but um uh and then uh
and then next week add five minutes and so that's one way to develop
a habit doing something that's brief enough that you can actually do it and then once you after the week you might
enjoy it enough you might be in the groove a little bit more and so then adding five minutes is
manageable and then then the following week I'll suggest another 5 minutes another 5 minutes and um and once you
get up to you know 30 minutes maybe that's
enough Gil you um you have your morning sessions right at 7 7 o' yes um are
those also available like recorded yes people could do that even earlier that
7:00 time doesn't work right yeah what's being referred to is that every morning at weekday morning at 700 p.m. uh I'm on
YouTube with that camera up there and uh I do a 30 minute guided
meditation and uh and then I give a 15 minute talk and uh those are recorded
both on our YouTube channel that you can listen to it later and and um and also
we we recorded on the audio and we have a website called audio Dharma that you
can get to it's on the top of our we imc's website there's a link to it and
there is where you can uh listen to all the talks that are given here so like this talk today if you ever want to
listen to it again it'll be on the website and or if you miss next week's class but you want to hear it you can
listen to it on audio or you can go on the YouTube CH YouTube channel and and our Channel and and um because the
videos recorded as well so so so um but
what I'd recommend is so what's a little bit some of you might know this that I you know I've been doing now the whole
since the beginning of the pandemic these guided meditations for 30 minutes some people are kind of becoming
dependent on guided meditations and uh and uh so I'd
recommend that uh as you so you asked about a habit for starting that's another way people get the Habit is they
use guided meditations that keeps them engaged but it's sooner or later it's
really good to learn to meditate without any guidance and just be just be quiet and
not have any extra input and just because the idea is you're supposed to meet yourself and when you have a guided
meditation then you're a little bit you're not quite alone with your own mind and your own heart and that's where
the real benefit comes when you're really alone with yourself and meet yourself in some deep way um and the
people who have guided meditation sometimes get a little bit attached to how that the guided meditation helps
them get relaxed and then they get attached to that but that's not the point of this meditation the point of is
to see clearly the word for the the the ancient Buddhist word for insight you know we're
called the Insight Meditation Center the word is um the ancient word language
it's vasana which literally means clear seeeing this is the practice of clear
seeeing
so let's end with we're it's just about time to end let's end with a five six
minute
meditation so so beginning with a care for your
posture and gently closing your
eyes and again preparing for the meditation period taking some long slow
deep breaths relaxing on the
exhale then letting your breathing return to
normal relaxing the belly
at the end of the exhale pause for just a moment just long
enough to feel the impulse to want to breathe in and as soon as you feel that natural
impulse pulse in the chest in the belly allow let there be a feeling of
allowing allow the inhale to begin almost like you're making room for
it welcoming it ah
come
and then at the top of the inhale just before you exhale pause there as well just for a
moment just long enough to feel the body wanting to
Exhale and then [Music] relax so the body does
exhale release the
breath allowing the inhale releasing with the
exhale
for
allowing the inhale and as you release the
exhale release any concerns you
have let go of your
thoughts and ride the exhale all the way to the end of the
exhale
for
and then to end this meditation taking some deeper breaths to
feel your body more
fully feel your chair the floor the
cushion remember that you're in a room with a group of other
people and then when you're ready you can open your
eyes [Music]
so thank you for being here coming to this I hope this was not too many
words there's a tradition that I didn't follow which is when you want to teach
Med meditation you do it with as little words as possible so there's not so much to think
about um but I uh but I want to just say that as a way of
saying keep it simple try to keep it as simple as you can and if you don't remember everything
that I taught today it's probably better ju just enough to keep you doing it and
in a relaxed way and just kind of doing it a lot of the learning comes from doing it so so if you're able to over
this week to just meditate 10 minutes a day um you know and then you'll be more
prepared to come back and and hear the next set of instructions if you don't
meditate in the next week don't worry about it just come anyway if you want um
it's okay and the way I teach this course as we go along um I'm trying to
also teach some life skills with mindfulness and awareness it's applicable in your life independent of
meditating so I don't feel like if you're you know you're not a failure because you don't meditate so just you
know you might benefit from this anyway and um we some of the people who
showed up today to kind of help set up and prepare are longtime meditators here
so they're all people you can uh if you when we finish here you can you can you
can walk up to them and ask them questions about either meditation or about um
IMC if you want to learn more how it works at IMC or something so um like Tom who has a name tag there standing he's
been around for a long time he's taught this course before so he knows a lot of this and um and um Nancy who greeted
people at the table you can check in with her and the other Nancy up here has also been around done a lot of
meditation at our retreat center and she can talk a little bit of our Retreat Center as ketta here she's been at our
Retreat Center a lot from Retreats and um is there someone else
yes Nana of course and also name tag she's also been around here for a very long time and and uh she'd be delighted
to answer questions and and if any of you speak Spanish that you can do it in
Spanish which is some sometimes easier for some people so um thank you for being here
and um I hope this uh serves you
well and I'm here too so if you want to ask me a question come up here