to hopefully say something succinct and memorable that you can carry through the
talk maybe through your life um in the time of the Buddha he was
characterized as a teacher of action a teacher of
action and why would he be called that and what did he mean by action that he
would was known as a teacher of action so that's kind of the part of the topic
for today and um and in introducing this
topic uh I would say that um the Buddha was much more interested in what we do
than who we are and uh and in fact uh if we he was
going to Define who we are the Buddha would Define it by what we do a farmer
someone who Farms is a farmer someone who's a cook Cooks is a
cook and so someone who meditates is a meditator so it's what we do that the
Buddha was interested in how we got recognized and known and that goes a
little bit uh against some of the popular orientations we have maybe in
the west the modern West where I get a sense there's a lot of people who are looking for a message that somehow who
they are is perfect somehow who they are is
guilt-free someone who they are is okay something like that and somehow
inherently in who we are we're just fine to way we are somehow and um and I think that comes
from a culture that has really condition people to think the opposite for
themselves there's a lot of self criticism a lot of anxiety about me myself and mine in this culture there's
a touching story that wasn't there but I've been told of it many times by people who were
there that um the Dal Lama was uh doing some kind of teaching and someone was
asked him a question and he had a translator and the translator would translate the question and into Tibetan
and the the uh the person asked some question about how to work
with how to deal with self-hatred and
um and um so the the translator translated this with
diil and then he looked perplexed and so there was a long
conversation between the dalama and the translator no people didn't know Tibetan
didn't know what it was about but long at some point in that conversation maybe the Dilma understood the question and he
started to cry it was inconceivable to the somehow
maybe because of Tibetan culture maybe because I don't know who he who he is dama that there was a culture of people
who have self-hatred it was unbelievable to him and when he realized that he
started to cry maybe we all can cry what we have here in this
culture and so because of this there's often it's a it's a relief to get a
message that you're okay that you're loved the way you are you're you're fine the way you are and
so but that's kind of how you are and as a relief as a corre
correction maybe that's a a wonderful teaching but that's the Buddha had a lot more Buddha actually emphasized much
more than how we are what he emphasized in fact how we are was not that
important for him and certainly he didn't want to the Buddha was not oriented Ed towards a philosophy or
religious worldview or idea of ultimacy that there's some kind of core aspect of
who we are that's perfect the Buddha didn't have the notion of a soul for
example there is no essential kind of heart and that goes against the grain
for a lot of cultures where they have that kind of view so we have to kind of hold all this kind of lightly and maybe
do a kind of cultural translation to really see how it all fits
but for the Buddha in his own terms he emphasized action what we do and uh and that this is where we
could um um you know where we take
responsibility and in teaching about action he taught about action in body in
speech and in mind so there's a touching story I think is touching um of the
Buddha teaching his son so what most people don't know is that Buddha Buddha
was a father he had one child and uh
after uh the child was about six or seven years old the Buddha was the
primary parent and uh we don't have a lot of stories about what he was like as a
parent um but he was already a monk himself and so he would living the religious life and his son joined him in
that kind of religious life following along and uh as maybe it's not too
uncommon for children to stumble into this issue
that um one day uh his son was apparently caught telling a lie you know
maybe a seven-year-old you know and um and so um I remember when I was maybe
six or maybe seven or so my father saw that we were playing checkers and he saw
that I cheated I I guess I was losing so I kind of put cup cup my tecker pieces under my
hand and kind of slipped it on the on the
board and my father did a a a wonderful thing for me it was I thought it
was and you know it affected me for the rest of my life in certain way he didn't criticize me he didn't wasn't angry with
me or to me or something he just got up and
left and that's all I needed to know I didn't need someone yelling at me
or berating me or criticizing me just like okay if that's what you do this is
what I do action and so he didn't tell me you're a
terrible person and um so um so he his son was caught with a
lie and his son already was living a life of a novice monk Nas kind of
noviciate and uh which is which is not defined by what you are but how you live
your life it's in Action a way of living and the Buddha said if you if if uh you
tell a deliberate knowing lie then uh your life as a noviciate
uh is has as much kind of spirituality religiosity in
it as uh a bowl full of water that's been turned upside down so all the
water's gone out so you know I don't know if it's not criticizing the sun exactly but this is the action and this
is the consequence of the action in terms of what you're how you're supposed to be
living and then he went on to say he said that anybody who is willing could
tell a deliberate LIE there's there's no nothing Wicked they wouldn't do somehow
there's something about telling lies that sets a stage for a lot of other things that are cause
problems and then he went on and said to his his son what's the purpose of a
mirror and the son said well the purpose of a mirror is
reflection in the same way you need to reflect
your mirror is your actions if you want to see yourself
study yourself through your actions see yourself through what you're doing so
don't see yourself in some kind of essentialist way like but this is who I am but learn Who You Are by what you
do and this is how he's said to do it um
if you're going to do anything with your body any physical activity
before you do it reflect because you're looking at the mirror reflect um is uh is what I'm
going to do is it going to harm me is it going to harm others or is it
going to harm both so that was the first criteria does it cause harm not just to myself he
equally important was others and equally important was both which I like to think of is the community we in all
people and then he went out to said say you should also reflect is this
wholesome actually he said it this way you should reflect first does it cause harm to S others or both you should
reflect is it UNH wholesome leading to
pain is it UNH wholesome leading to pain if it's if it is causes harm if
it's UNH wholesome leading to pain then stop doing
it then he went on to say while you're doing something with your body you
should be reflecting that's the M look at the mirror look yourself through the in the mirror of your actions and see for
yourself is it causing harm is it UNH wholesome leading to pain
because some things don't cause harm in the moment but they cause harm in the
future so this thing you know it has ongoing effects and um and if you're doing it
and it's in the middle of doing it you should stop doing it and
um and then he said if you're after you've done something with your body you
should reflect have I caused harm was it unh ome leading to
pain and um and if you see that it was then you should could find a wise
person and just talk about it with someone so it doesn't say
confess but there's something about when you've done something that's been harmful UNH wholesome there's something
about the honesty speaking about it honestly getting it off not necessarily off your chest but getting it
acknowledged there's something about speaking that is a fuller acknowledgement and recognition of what
we done that helps the mind and the heart to dis disengage itself from it
from itself not be so identified with it and then it's a wise person who's kind
of now know what you're up to so it's a little bit more difficult in the future
to want to do the same thing because you know that wise person now is like really
you're doing that again and you don't want to your wise your wise friend to kind of have to say really you're doing
that again so it's a it's a way of supporting us to be more careful in the
future if as before you do something and you
reflect if it uh is beneficial to oneself beneficial to others beneficial
to uh both if it's wholesome leading
to pleasure leading to happiness just keep doing it or do it if
it's during then keep doing it if you reflect after then just rest content and
happy uh growing and cultivating wholesome States so if it's wholesome
what you're doing and you'd finish doing it and you recognize that this was a wholesome thing to do
then continue to develop wholesome States so wholesome states are developed
by what we do so then he went through the same thing uh with speech same
analysis then he did the same analysis and and it's wonderful I think this it's a speech because many of us find one of
the most difficult places in our life to be mindful let alone be wise and
wholesome in how we speak how we live is through speech and so here we're offered wonderful
criteria and how to reflect on ourselves and be careful how we speak and if we
kind of spend time just being pausing and looking and thinking about what we're going to say before we say it you
with these criteria we would live in a different world so what uh what I'm about to say
is this harmful for myself harmful for others or harmful to both
is what I'm about to say is it UNH wholesome leading to
pain if it is don't say it I mean what a great world would we live in if just
that was if that was followed I mean we would be like the world would
shine and uh and but if if what you're about to
say uh is beneficial for yourself and for someone else and and all all people
then please say it if what you're going to if uh uh if
it's uh is wholesome and going to bring benefits and happiness then please do it
so he goes through the same analysis so you know the So speaking so I recommend
that and and for me I don't know how it is for you this kind of this guideline that he
gives a son I'm actually more inspired by the speech part than I am by the
action part maybe because I'm less likely to harm people with my actions than I am with my
speech Just subtle things we do so subtle and and um and uh so having this little
criteria I find very helpful and then the um the third one
has to do with for some of us uh the speech we do in our head to
ourselves we track what we're thinking we track what's going on in the mind and and if what I'm about with the mental
activity the mental thinking I'm doing if that is harmful to oneself to others or to both
then don't do it and I think there it's particularly true that it affects us
ourselves I think we can harm ourselves tremendously the selft talk we do and uh how we harm other people if
it's all in the privacy of our own thoughts is not so obvious but I think
it oozes out by osmosis it oozes out by all kinds of kind of subtle ways of
communication to others and they pick it up and um and so we look at our own
thoughts and can we see is this wholesome what I'm doing wholesome what I'm thinking it does it lead to
happiness or unhappiness does it lead to pain or pleasure and uh so here again we look at
our own mind so this is our the three areas of
action the where the Buddha emphasizes to his son when the son was
young and we have three discourses where the Buddha was teaching his examples where the Buddha taught his
son and it's marvelous three discour teachings because one was when he was very young one when when he was a
teenager and one when he was just becoming an adult and for the little for when he was
the kid was small he was teaching him this kind of an ethical teaching we could say in
English uh when he was a teenager he he taught him um not to be caught up in
conceit some teenagers have little bit like that and uh but but his teaching
for how to deal with conceit was meditation to develop a sense of wellbeing and happiness through
meditation that the whole need for conceit begins to dissolve
and then when he was a young adult the Buddha taught him uh the insights the
pointed to the kind of way of seeing that is liberating so you have these three
phases of the young this but the first one which could be called ethical teachings is really foundational
teachings for all the Buddhism it's not just a teaching to a young kid this is
like all of Buddhism can fit underneath this criteria uh is it harmful or not harmful
is it harmful or beneficial is it wholesome or UNH wholesome does it lead to pain or does it lead to benefit to
happiness and uh uh and the deepest meditators people who are most skilled
in meditation going deep in states of meditation the same criteria are the
guide for how to go further and further in meditation all the way to Liberation
because we're getting more and more refined and to see subtly the subtlest
ways in which our mental activity causes
stress and causes freedom from stress causes tension and freedom from tension
and just that very little criteria seeing that is what is onward leading leads us we become our own teachers and
we find our way that way so this is not just the teachings to a young kid this is a teaching for all of us and uh
there's no no no metaphysical teachings there's no Supernatural teachings there's no um nothing you have to kind
of believe in in some kind of religious kind of belief kind of thing except you
have to believe that it makes a difference how you act and what you
do that can't be that hard that can't hurt that much to believe
that so then um but so especially so it's one of the most difficult places
for this is our inner life our mental life and for some people that's where we
tend to identify strongly with our thoughts identify strongly with our
feelings we Define ourselves by those and it's not and our society
sometimes helps us to do that and the analogy I'd like to offer for this sometime was sometimes like with being
caught in our thoughts and we we're so caught in the thoughts we think we are we thought our thoughts we think we have
no choice but to think thinking is kind of like obvious like this is true you
know whatever I'm thinking it's how it is because I'm living in my thoughts uh the analogy
is uh if you're if you're uh moving along a wheel burrow full of heavy
bricks it's heavy to push it along but then you're lucky you come to a little
place where that becomes it uh incline so you can you can roll it downhill a little bit just in the beginning it
feels good oh good it's not to push so much but the hill gets steeper and
steeper and steeper and at some point the wibur is in
charge you're just desperately holding on and running after trying not to run into all the people on the hill right
like you know and you're completely invested in CAU and you become the wheel bur almost because the wheels has the
momentum and you're just trying to hold on for their life so or thinking can be that way with
a wheelbarrow um it's best just to put it down gently so it stops
rolling if it uh or if you can't do that it might be better off just to let go of
it because a wheelbarrow is not going to keep rolling down the hill it's going to tip over as soon as you're not holding
it up and all the bricks are going to fall out so with our thinking we can be so
identified with them and sometimes that they can it's very a lot of negative
selft talk lot of thoughts there about the uh danger and anxiety and concern
for this and that and trying to figure things out and it's very hard to stop
that identification to believe Stop Believing in them because we're living in
them and so the Buddha his emphasis was action he was a teacher of action so how
does Action come to play well right now the action is one that's harming
yourself and so you know stopping it might not be so easy but what can you do and that's the
qu magic question what can you do as soon as you ask yourself that question
what can I do that's different you're already doing something
different just a question creates a little space just a question creates a little pause just a question means that
part of you is not so invested or caught or lost in the whole swirl of thoughts
so to have enough mindfulness to recognize oh boy am I caught what can I do here is that is the
is the beginning of what the Buddha wants us to be doing what can I do is that
question uh cause harm or benefit it's not so clear yet but it's
certainly not causing harm to ask that question but maybe it opens a door to figure out what to do is
beneficial and then so what can you do one of the things we can do is
relax because if we're whatever that whenever we're caught in thoughts there's going to be tension in the body
and in the mind in the thinking muscle and beginning to relax and soften
the thought the thinking the nature of
thinking is that if you're caught up in some big chain of swirl of
thoughts those thoughts are never going to on their own think that it's time to
relax it'll they'll never come up with kind of like maybe I shouldn't be doing this they're very convincing the
authority of our thoughts are powerful partly because we give them a lot of
authority but as soon as you ask what can I do that's different here you're breaking the authority of those thoughts
you may be not breaking how strong they are the wheel you're still holding on to the wheelbarrow but then begin to think
can I do something else with the wibur can I put it down so we can relax and so to become skilled and it it
takes skill it takes familiarity really learn how to do this learn how to relax
and it means becoming highly attuned to micr muscles around the temples the
forehead the jaw the shoulders where can you soften where can
you relax something that is the very thing that's feeding or keeping the the
thinking going obsessive thinking is reinforced by
tension if you you want to stop that reinforcement you have to look for where can I relax and
soften some of you probably wake up in the middle of the night
anxious caught up in thoughts there's something else you can do rather than just trying to go back to
sleep trying to go back to sleep relax start doing body scans just relax
look look at the microm muscles around the thinking relax
or I prefer the word release release the tension release because release to me is an opening it's
a kind of expanding so this idea you expand around something you you let go you open you
relax and expand okay and uh and so then
how are you doing that how are you relaxing are you relaxed that's a question always questioning reflecting
how am I doing this well is it am I heart am I relaxing in a way that harms me or benefits me boy
there I am again harming myself I'm there with a I'm there with a you know
yelling at myself and and U prodding myself with
sharp kind of me mental knives
relax come on you can do it oh you can't you're not managing it you're being you're doing it the wrong way and you
know everyone else knows how to relax but you don't know how to relax so there you are harming
again or are you doing it in a way that's beneficial what's the beneficial
way to relax so asking those questions those are actions those are mental
actions that can lead to benefit how do I relax can I relax in a soft way in a
easy way and can I relax without so being so focused on being successful
I just do the best I can and then um and so once we get the
same thing with emotions we're caught in emotions what can relax what can we soften how can we
open to this how can we be with it rather than the wheelbarrow of emotions
that we have they're caught in and
um so um so rather
than having the world do rather than being
concerned about the what the world does to
you be concerned of what you do in
return if you're concerned about the the world does to you too much you might be
forfeiting forfeiting taking a deep look at yourself and for the Buddha it's always
with your actions that he emphasizes how you become free how you don't become
caught by the world how you don't believe in the forces that come down upon you that tell you
otherwise you don't believe in the forces of Oppression so that you oppress yourself
or or limit yourself for the Buddha it's always what do you contribute how what
do you do how do you meet the
situation it's not what your emotions are doing to you that's important what's
important is what you do to the emotions it's not important what your
thinking does to you and exactly it's more important what you do
in return in response in Buddha being a teacher of
action is he's pointing to our role as actors
in our own life he's pointing to our own responsibility or our own ability to
respond our own capacity to find our own Freedom if we're looking for freedom to
be handed to us from the world it's never going to be handed to you we have to find our freedom from
within the deepest kind of Freedom what might be called spiritual fre
freedom and um the um and so there's a program that
I'm involed it at St Quinton State Prison and um and one of the things they
teach there what I think it's one of the one of the men who was incarcerated who
came up with this phrase um uh uh to be
become free while still in prison and the context of that is quite
for me it was quite powerful to think to be even in that kind of situation to find this freedom and not let the prison
guards Define who you are and what your inner life is like to take
responsibility this is kind of the most radical message of the Buddha and uh no one else is going to be
the caretaker for your inner life but
you don't what is it called in the in the business
world now Farm out what's the other another better expression what Outsource yeah don't
Outsource the quality of your inner life don't expect that there's some
person who's going to do it for you or thing or
event that least for the Buddha you have to insource it
and it's your actions your activity what you do and these criteria is the is that
that we offered here is it is it um cause harm or not harm the fact that
that sits at the heart of Buddhism it just makes me so happy given how much
harm exists in this world that really this is what's important and that is a
wholesome and beneficial wholesome and brings happiness what a fantastic thing if that
could be the primary message for a religious
life so um that's
uh started off that's what I was thinking
today and so I walked down here from home that was what I was my physical action was to come there and tell you
this and then I spoke and hopefully that's for my
benefit and for all of yours so thank you so we have a few
minutes if any of you would like to comment on this or would like to ask any
questions um can maybe take two or three
sure thank you hi Gil um first of all I've been
sitting with a slight smile on my face and immense gratitude for your presence
and talks I discovered your talks on a podcast maybe 12 13 years ago um on the
east coast and now it's funny I'm here with one of my best friends um in California living here a mom and so much
has changed in my life so um just very grateful for the presence
um the perspective and the peace that you have given to My Life um and I just
want to thank you first of all and um my heart is racing from excitement but um I
just want to ask you um today in the context of
relationships and raising um kids
um thinking about the emotion which is the feeling that comes
outward how do we communicate that in a um how do you
say um Wholesome Way during the times when it may not be necessarily a
wholesome message while we also
um keep ourselves free of expressing ourselves and do not let it ooze through
osmosis um so I guess that's Yeah question whooing out so when U my son
was small I thought I was doing a wise parenting thing so not not I wasn't
going to express anger to my son I was just going to name how how it was for
me and so I said to him if you continue doing what you're doing um I think I'll
become angry and uh he looked at me and said
dad you're already
angry so he knew before I knew so it oozes
out and um so I uh I I think one of the things to do is to practice mindfulness
out loud which mean you have to figure out exactly how to do it appropriately with children but to have the children
see that you can talk about how you're feeling without it being directed at anyone attacking anyone just say you
know that was a hard day today I I was really angry and and uh so I went for a
walk to calm down I went to meditate to come down and the kids see that there's a ways that parents get angry just like
they do but the parents not caught in it and they have a way of practicing with it or some way of dealing with it and
you might shared examples like today I was really angry or really afraid and so I talked to my
friend and that helped me a lot and so then the day might come when you're angry with them and then you might say
oh here I am you know I'm angry you know you know I've asked you many times not to walk across the kitchen floor with
Muddy shoes and I just cleaned the floor and you know could you know and so now
I'm getting angry um but I don't want to be angry I want to be able to talk to a friend about it can I talk to
you that's going to get their attention and anyway so you want to find ways of talking and one of the simplest ways I
think of being very careful is to try to make ey statements I mean there so much I could say but rather than you
statements and um the um
and then the other thing I learned being a young when I was had a parent of young kids was
um uh that kids
um at the young age will learn from the parents how to
be and so uh there was a period of time where a few time very rare but it was
sometimes where one of my kids was kind of difficult for
us and sometimes I would use my strong voice I thought to get his attention and
have him stop what he was doing but uh it was like no you have to stop with a strong voice and then one day I heard
him use the same voice to his younger brother and I said oh no what have I
done so I learned not to be really careful that what you pass on to next so
this I don't think I'm as answering your question adequately but maybe I offered little pieces that might is that okay
for
now uh so G we have a question from YouTube from an um she asked what about
when one takes too much responsibility for others feelings
well I think that uh one of the things to do always is to turn that the mirror
on yourself to to learn how to look more deeply and um and first rather than
analyzing or thinking about that you're taking too much responsibility but if you recognize you
are really look and feel what that's like to do that what it what's the
tension what's the pressure what's the heaviness what's the compulsion where does it feel like in the body physically
and to to start with the body begins breaking up the hegemony of the thoughts
the ideas the push of the responsibility and so um so and when you
start feeling it physically it's also a way beginning to create some distance
from these really strong compulsive attitudes we might have like including being responsible to other
people a as we kind of begin to relax around it and soften it gives the
opportunity to look at it more deeply what's going on and the next layer might
be to notice what emotions come along uh when you're taking responsibility for
others is it anxiety is it anger because you're trying to get everyone to shape up and be just like the way you think
they should be uh what what's what's emotionally is going on here and then learn to uh
understand them and once you understand kind see the emotions you're in a better place to take a deeper a look at what
are you believing what what's the what's the belief behind it what's the message you've learned about how to live a life
uh did you grow up with parents who took responsibility for everybody and then you've learned that's what you're
supposed to do and that's where the message came from or that's the belief or maybe the belief is that um you're
the all knowing one and uh everyone should just kind of you know behave
properly because you know and that's why you're responsible so I'm just making things up
but but uh but uh so to do a deep
inquiry in oneself and to to do it in a way with that mirror of mindfulness that
the way that we do the inquiry the way we study ourselves are present for ourselves with mindfulness and asking
ourselves good questions about what's happening we do it in a way that is um kind we do it in a way that's beneficial
that's wholesome uh we don't do it punitively we don't do it critically but say oh this is how it
is now let me take a deeper look so that's um what I think I'm looking at you
because you answer so thank you for the question on online so thank you all very much so uh
I can be up here a little bit if someone wants to talk to me but I have to also set up for that the meeting we'll have
here at 11:5 and uh you're all welcome to stay for it
and even if you're not you're welcome even if you're just curious what what happens in a community
meeting here at IMC and um and if you want in meantime if you you can there's maybe tea to be
had uh by the tea area and just hang out and we'll ring a bell maybe about 5 10
minutes before it starts and um and there'll be a little bit of setup in
here we're going to set up a big monitor there so because there's people on uh on Zoom going to participate and so we want
to have see them and so so you'll see it a little different set up differently in here thank you