good morning thank you Martha I'm as Martha said I'm Diana
Clark and for those of you who don't know me I uh teach her on Monday nights and occasionally substitute for
Gil here and there so this morning I want to talk a
little bit about what is it that motivates us to
practice what is it that motivates us to come here on a Sunday morning or to have
this uh daily meditation practice or listen to Dharma Talks on YouTube or
Audio Dharma or read Dorma books or you know whatever it might
be like what what is it that are aspirations that are related to
practice and it can be helpful to reflect on this on occasion taking some time to
think about well what is it that um what is our motivation or what is our
aspiration maybe as I'm speaking you can ask yourself this question what is maybe like the north
star that is guiding you or supporting you in
practice and there's a way in which when we align with our aspirations there's a
sense of maybe some openness or some ease or a sense of
well-being in contrast when we have like this goal that we got to get that that's
kind of associated more with a feeling of tightness or uh maybe um some
clinging or leaning forward maybe an aspiration is something
that's more of an uplift and a a sense of a I don't know some ease and
inspiration because there there is great power available when we are aligned with
our aspirations when the heart is connected with that which is important
to us when the heart is connected
to something bigger than just what we're doing at that
moment not that what we're doing at that moment isn't important but there can be a way in which um just I like this word
aligning or connecting because so often right just
the busyness of our lives really encourages us to be
disconnected from what's important to us and there's a way in which Our Lives can feel like one very long to-do
list every day this to-do list and sometimes we kind of maybe like
lose sight or that there's like something bigger that's possible
and maybe part of the gifts of having a meditation practice or even coming here
and sitting silently before a Dharma talk is a way in which there can maybe
Bubble Up what's important for us or maybe there can be some more space for the mind and the heart to touch
into what's important for us and it might be that our aspiration is for some
deep well-being and happiness peace
love freedom or maybe an aspiration is about
making this world a better place and having some service supporting others so
that they can bring their best selves forward and help make this world a
better place or maybe there's an aspiration about beauty wanting to bring things in
Beauty into the world or to share beauty or to express Beauty in some kind of
way all of us might have our own aspiration its own particular flavor
or expression but it can be helpful to
sometimes bring that to mind and connect with it and then there is this obvious this
question or maybe for me it's obvious because like well why am I not like
consistently going in that direction why am I finding myself distracted and doing
other things and partly because to consistently Orient towards our
aspirations is not easy if it were easy you would have all
be doing that and you'd be completely awakened or have Peace and Freedom Beauty all that kind of stuff
already so what is it that makes it difficult and can we address that can we
um work with that so that we can consistently move towards what's most important to
us one thing is that uh we've all kind of like created a society that likes and
promotes instant gratification
right we all like to you know have things right away how many inventions are about to make things
faster and right even like all these uh gizmos We Carry in our pockets that are
all about like making things even faster and better and you know you can learn
the answer to that quickly instapot you can instantly have
dinner ready I don't know something like this right so this idea that we kind of like
expect things to happen quickly or maybe there's this way we
aren't always connecting with our aspirations because we tend to
forget and again it's because this uh our community or Society is really
promotes this sense of distraction you know trying to like entertain ourselves or to always feel
better or you know not feel any discomfort so there we have to distract
ourselves because there's a lot of discomfort in life emotional discomfort physical
discomfort so sometimes we just forget because we have these Todo L this and
we're have a pattern of distracting
ourselves and maybe there's this way that just very simp our kind of like Society or the networks
of individuals that we interact with really aren't uh oriented
towards connecting with what's important to us instead we have these institutions or
um you know like the or industries that are designed to try to convince us to do
what they want us to do buy this do that believe this
right it's just you know what's happened where we find ourselves in
society we can be pushed around by these other forces it's easy enough to do and
certainly I have found myself going down the rabbit hole of uh YouTube videos and
watching the most bizarre things that I have no interest in it's quite
something it's these algorithms I guess right that are pretty
powerful so I'd like to talk a little bit about applying oneself to practice
applying oneself to a practice that can enable us to stay connected with what's important to
us and I'd like to use a story that we find in the sutas uh as a support for
this and this story is about Prince
bod uh some of you will know that this name this word bod means Awakening so
Prince Awakening and it's kind of a interesting thing that he's named
this so he Prince bod wanted to become awakened I don't blame him he must have
more Peace and Freedom but he didn't want to really work work at
it right I I mean who can blame him we all want things to be easier and have
the path of least resistance and instant gratification of course we do and for me
I find a little bit of comfort that thousands of years ago they were the same they wanted things to be as easy as
possible too so he wanted to become awakened but
he didn't want to work too hard about it at it and he had heard that it was going to be difficult and
painful so he wanted a shortcut so shortcuts that uh
specifically that he thought was okay if he donates a certain property to the
Buddha and his monastics where they could practice then this would bring him
something that would really support his Awakening so just this idea okay I'll um
give something to the monastics to the
SAA and he also had the idea that okay if he could have the Buddha do something
in particular for him something auspicious then maybe that's what it
would take is to have this awakened person do I don't know like some magic thing
and then Prince B could become awakened so Prince bod rather than
thinking that he himself had a role in his happiness that he himself had this
was responsible for connecting with what's important and going achieving or
having experiencing what was his deepest aspiration I'm assuming getting awakened
was his deepest aspiration maybe not but rather than thinking that he had
a role in his happiness he somehow was kind of like giving that over to the
Buddha or just thinking if he did a particular gesture donating property being a prince
this wasn't a hardship for
him so Prince B had this the pink Lotus long
house built I love this name Pink Lotus long house built with the intention to
uh donate it to the Buddha and his monastics as a place where they a
practice and he wanted to invite the Buddha to come
to have a meal and to come to the pink Lotus L house this is very common for uh
individuals to invite the Buddha and his monastics to a meal this was a very common way to support the SAA and to
show respect and care and to hear some teachings was common that after the meal
there would be some teachings so Prince bod invited the
Buddha and he had this delicious food prepared and they uh then he also asked
Prince buy asked in this pink Lotus long house for there to be a white cloth that
gets uh spread along the entire as the name suggests long house it's a like this long single room and then white
cloth to go down the stairs and onto the ground I'm thinking of it as like the
red carpet treatment right so he can walk on this when he comes
in so the Buddha goes and his monastics um they go
to Prince bod's house or Palace where he lives Prince bod is outside waiting for
them and he as greets he greets them pays homage to them
and invites them all to go to nearby to this pink Lotus L
house they all go there and they um and the Buddha stops right
before this white cloth before going up the steps to the pink Lotus long
house and Prince B had this idea if I can get the Buddha to step on this cloth
it'll be auspicious and that will help me so Prince Bodi sees the Buddha stopping
and he says Venable sir please step on the white
cloth please step on the white cloth so that it may be for my welfare and happiness for a long
time and the Buddha just stands there doesn't say anything doesn't move
he just stands there
so the Buddha had this he has this advice regarding shortcuts in general so
maybe he recognized what was happening here and I appreciate very much this
advice about shortcuts gets uh um captured in this short little simile
that's uh in a verse and this and the simile goes like
this this is the Buddha speaking he's not saying this to Prince
this is me doing an aside so the Buddha says as the Wagoner who left the highway
a road with an even surface and entered Upon A rugged path one Broods mournfully
with a broken axle so this idea that there's going on
a road with an even surface this is something of course there's no pavement thousands of years ago an even surface
mean that is been trampled upon a lot a lot of people have gone down this
road and so maybe there's this way that uh to like leave that behind and to go
Upon A rugged path like maybe to go where other people don't go and maybe in
my mind it's kind of like bushwhacking your way through this uh new territory
or something but then if you are taking your wagon Chariot something like this
then the EXO wheel breaks and for me I have certainly had
this right I'm on the traveling and then um my little app says oh there's traffic
up ahead like oh okay I'll take this exit and you it ends up right just
taking longer or I get lost or you know something like this right we often do this like literally go off the highway
and try to take a shortcut so getting back to the story
with uh Prince bodh so Prince bodh sees that the Buddha is just standing
there and he repeats himself venerable sir please step on the white cloth so
that it may be for my welfare and happiness for a long time the Buddha continues to just stand
there doesn't say anything he just stands there I can imagine that Prince bod is getting a little bit agitated he
says it a third time venerable sir please step on the white
cloth so that it may be for my welfare and happiness for a long
time and Buddha stands there and he looks over at
Ananda Ananda some of you may know is the Buddha's attendant and somebody who
really knew the Buddha well and had a lot of wisdom and I appreciate this so much Anda gets it he understands he
understands and Ananda says to Prince bod fold up the cloth Prince B the
Buddha will not step on the white cloth he has compassion for future
Generations so what's not being said here is that Ananda knew
recognized that if uh some If Prince bod if I'm sorry if the Buddha it were to
step on the white cloth then Prince bod would say oh I you know so auspicious
for me I'm going to become awaken now because the Buddha did this and the prince right he has a platform on which
he would be talking about telling everybody all you have to do is step on the white cloth or maybe the opposite
would happen maybe the Buddha did step on the white cloth and then a bunch of Calamity would happen to the prince bad
things would happen and then the prince would be saying oh that Buddha person don't believe them he he's kind he's not
helpful or maybe Prince bod would be talking about the importance of stepping on a wet cloth and that would encourage
people to like be looking for other auspicious actions you know something that they could do instead of taking
responsibility for their own welfare and
happiness so the Buddha didn't want people to always be looking for external
conditions some or to make somebody else do something in order for them to be
aligned with their aspirations in order for them to reach their
aspirations I think all of us know this but maybe there's a sometimes a piece of us that doesn't quite that want was
hoping that maybe it's not so true but this path of practice is one that we all
have to walk ourselves we have to find our own way
the Buddha points the way shows the way but we're the ones that actually have to do
it have to learn by direct experience have to overcome difficulties
ourselves so getting back to the story after the meal that the prince B
offered to the Buddha and his monastics um after he had folded up the cloth and
offered the meal and stuff then Prince bodh turns to the Buddha and says
pleasure is only gained through pain pleasure is only gained through
pain and the Buddha is assuming and interpreting that pleasure is like you know more ease more peace more freedom
maybe even Awakening and Prince bod has this idea okay you have to have a lot of pain
in order to achieve that and in some ways right the modern day equivalent of this is Nike no pain no gain right so
like thousands of years ago right they're talking about the same thing I love
it so this of course helps make sense you know why the the prince is motivated
to have the Buddha do something for him to rather than having to do it himself he doesn't want to feel pain we don't
want to feel pain none of us want to feel pain pain so maybe we can't blame him that he
was asking The Bu to step on a cloth and I have my own version of this
story this was uh early in my practice um after sitting a long
retreat that was hard it was difficult you know sometimes Retreats are fantastic and sometimes they're not
that's how it is and we don't get to control you know exactly how things unfold during a
retreat and this was a long retreat where I had a lot of difficulty a lot of tears and confusion and physical
pain all these types of things and I had figured like okay I paid my dues this is
enough I'm ready to just be awakened and I remember uh going to one
of the teachers and saying okay can you like zap me or give me the secret
teachings or you know something CU I feel like you know I've done enough now can't can't I just I I give this teacher
a lot of credit with a lot of warmth said it doesn't work that way [Laughter]
Diana but you know I just felt like okay you maybe I deserved it after all this
hard work of this Retreat or whatever it was I don't know what my thinking was but maybe just a sincere wish like
anything but this please so maybe there's a part of us that kind of is hoping that there's a
shortcut that somebody else can do something for
us so the prince has said what pleasure is only gained through pain and in
response the Buddha says he gives a little bit of his own
story as a way to as a teaching to the Buddha to the prince bodh he gives a little bit of his own story and the
Buddha says before my Awakening so while
he was still striving trying to get awakened the Buddha says when I was still una awakened but intent on
awakening I also thought that pleasure is only gained through
pain so some of you might know this story of the the Buddha's Awakening that
he lived in this had this opulent lifestyle lived in a palace he went uh
then he leaves the palace to strive towards Awakening he has some meets with some medit
teachers he learns um some exalted meditative techniques or reaches High
meditation States and realizes oh these meditation states are nice but they're
not Awakening so then he goes to the opposite extreme and practices
austerities thinking that pain must be the way to freedom and pleasure and uh he describes some of it
this way some of this austerity this way so this is the Buddha speaking describing his path of practice before
he was awakened seeking the state of supreme peace I set out to discover what is
skillful traveling I came to sanama and urua and there I saw a delightful Grove
a lovely piece of ground with a clear flowing river Pleasant smooth Banks and
nearby was a village for Ms so a comfortable place and he would be
supported I sat down and thought this would be a good place for
practicing and then he thought why don't I with teeth clenched
and tongue pressed against the roof of my mouth squeeze squash and Crush mind
with mind so this idea he's going to strive as hard as he can Crush mind with
mind like a strong person grabs a weaker person by the head and throat and squeezes squashes or crushed them that's
what I did until sweat poured from my armpits little graphic detail like just
to show like the amount of exertion here and the Buddha says my energy was
roused up and unflagging and my mindfulness was established and Lucid but my body was Disturbed and not
tranquil because I pushed too hard with that painful
striving so then still in this mode he tries breathing L meditation to hold his
breath he tries not eating so he tries all these austerities with this you know
real intensity and they don't lead to
Awakening and then so he's still talking to Prince
bod try to give this story about how all these different things all these different painful activities that he
tried didn't work and he kind of like sums it up by saying whatever spiritual adepts have
experienced these painful sharp severe acute feelings due to
overexertion no one has done more than me so just saying that like he's done
the the most painful
things and then he describes how he went to go sit underneath the booty
tree so we see that making no effort while he was in the palace or with
Prince bod didn't lead to Awakening or making tons of effort while he striving
and doing painful exertion doesn't lead to
Awakening so then he describes to the Buddha describes to Prince bod
how he did become awakened I won't go into the details about that
now and so Prince bod responds with well how long does it
take if you were my teacher how long would it take like I don't blame him right he
wants to know is this something that I have to do for a really long time or can
there be a shortcut because now that you've figured it out Mr Buddha then
maybe you can give me some hints and it'll be faster and
easier and then a Buddha replies with a question to The Prince and he asks the
prince are you skilled in the art of wielding a hooked go while riding an
elephant I don't know exactly what that is but uh a hooked go while riding an
elephant apparently this was something that uh required a skill to
do and the prince Bo says yes I
am and then the Buddha asks him suppose you were to train a person
and wielding a hooked hooked go while riding an
elephant could that if that person did not have any confidence could they
achieve what they could achieve if they had confidence
no if that person had no Vitality could they achieve what they could achieve if
they did have Vitality no if that person were dishonest and had
no no Integrity could they achieve what they could achieve if they were honest and had
Integrity no if that person had no energy could
they achieve what could be achieved if they did have energy
no if that person didn't have any wisdom could they achieve what could be achieved if they didn't have wisdom
no so then the Buddha says there's these five factors of
endeavoring confidence Vitality
Integrity energy and wisdom and with these five factors of
endeavoring the one can achieve what they want to
achieve and then the Buddha answers the prince bod's question about how long will it
take the Buddha says if you have these five factors of endeavoring someone could become
awakened in 7 years let alone 7 years 6
years let alone 6 years 5 years four years 3
years 2 years one year let alone one year 7
months 6 months five months you know how this is going to go right s weeks six
weeks five weeks 7 Days 6 days 5 days
let alone two days a person with these five factors of endeavoring can hear the
instructions in the morning and become awakened that evening it's beautiful right
inspiring and so I'll just unpack a little bit these five factors of endeavoring
first of all this I'll unpack this word of endeavoring maybe we'll say applying on
or working towards or seeking or pursuing with diligence or something
like
this and also I'll say that these five factors of endeavoring take into account all aspects of Our
Lives all aspects of who we are it's not just our um expertise with
meditation or it's not how much we know of the suas or the teachings or
something like that this confidence is the first one
this confidence that this is something that's worth
doing and confidence that it is possible that it is possible to have
greater peace and ease and that it's conf that you have some confidence that you can do that that you
can move in that direction and sometimes we think about
like okay this aspiration what would it look like when we achieve it and we think like I can't achieve
that that's like that's it's an aspiration it's so far in the future but sometimes what we forget is
that the version of ourselves that's going to take like the last step
is not the same version that we are today when we move a little bit in that
direction we're a little bit changed then we take the next step we're a little bit changed take the next step
we're a little bit changed so sometimes we like to project way into the future and say I can do
that but it's not the same you that's going to do that it's the you that has
made all the steps in that direction so you can have some confidence that you can do that all you need is the
confidence to take the next step just that's it just the next
step then so confidence that it's worthwhile that it's possible that
humans is possible for humans and that you can do it but you can do it all you
need is the next step that's all you need and then there's this next one about
this Vitality this Vitality all that's needed is sometimes
you might feel like oh my gosh I can't achieve that that's like so big it's going to take so much energy I don't
have that much energy all that's being pointed to is
maybe just the amount of Vitality that requires for example to listen to a
dormor that's all cuz this is about the heart and the
mind and sometimes when we listen to Dharma talks podcasts YouTube videos read a Dharma book there's a way in
which there can be a inspiration or there can be some
openness or some uplift that's all that's needed we don't
need tons of energy because the truth is that a lot of people come to Dharma practice because
they are ill or they have uh not they are have some sense of Despair and they
just don't have energy this practice is for you also it's not saying you have to have
perfect health it's not saying you have to have tons of energy just enough to
like Engage The mind or allow the heart to have some uplift
and then the sense of being having some integrity and
honesty the way this gets described in the sutas that honesty is about
sharing acknowledging what's really going on with
you if you have a teacher to really share what's going
on sometimes we want the teacher to like us or we want the teacher to think that we're good students
or it's teacher or whomever it is so maybe we're like skipping over those
parts of ourselves to where we're not doing so great that's okay but you're
short changing yourself some of this kind like honesty and integrity is to show up and to be
able to say this is where I'm struggling this is where I feel like I'm making some progress and I'm uh have
some Clarity but here's where I'm struggling to be able to share
both the struggles and the difficult the difficulties and the winds so this idea
of being authentic about how you're doing with your
practice and this idea of energy is just like related to the right effort in the
eight-fold path it's just amount of energy to recognize oh this is is
helpful this is not helpful this supports this movement
towards my aspiration this does not support this movement towards
aspiration that's the type of energy that's uh
required and then the last one is about
wisdom part of the wisdom is recognizing that things
change of course they change but to really see that in a really deep way
there aren't exceptions to this everything changes and just to have this type of
wisdom allows that things developments to happen things to shift so we don't have to try to cling
on to them or try to in insist that they be different instead they're going to change on their
own on a time frame that's appropriate for them
so these five factors of endeavoring that can support us in
reaching our aspirations being aligned with connecting with and moving towards
our aspirations confidence
Vitality Integrity energy and
wisdom we all have these if you're here you have them and if in the future
whomever is listening to this podcast you have them also if you have enough energy to listen to
this confidence Vitality Integrity energy and wisdom is these five factors
to support this movement towards meeting our
aspirations and I'd like to think that Prince bod took this uh under I mean
undertook this and became awakened did the sutas don't say whether he became awakened so maybe not maybe
being a prince he thought like oh no I'll go try some other spiritual teacher I don't know but may you all reach your
aspirations thank you