good morning warm greetings warm
greetings welcome everyone Global online s delighted delighted to be with you
again today happy to see all the greetings from all over the world in the
chat lots of familiar names and a special welcome to those of you who are
here for the first time happy to be with
you please let me know when you hear this that you are hearing me a sound
this is a sound check
okay so happy to be with you thank you for the feedback
appreciate it it's interesting for me we have like a two-minute lag or something like that
so so friends very good to see you and um see
your names and your greetings and we are going to take about
half an hour to sit in meditation lightly guided
meditation and then I will offer some teachings so the invitation when you're ready when
you've had a chance to greet each other is to begin to take your
attention inwards from the sense door of your
eyes in reading or responding into the
sensations of your body maybe if your eyes are still open
you might look around the room Orient yourself notice the
details of light or shadow of whatever time of day you're
[Music] in and then soften your
eyes as if the world is coming to you great Horizon in the
distance and then when you're ready closing [Music]
them noticing the sensations of warmth
or cool or moisture or dryness on your [Music] skin maybe clothing or a Shaw or a
blanket it in contact with your
body noticing the weight of this body on the chair or
cushion bed whatever supports
you and tuning into that sense of support
and then checking out the interoception the internal
sense all the different Sensations in this
body scanning through and noticing
areas of tension holding as well as areas of
lightness warmth and
relaxation it's all okay it's all
[Music] included noticing
especially the sensation of this body
breathing maybe movement at the abdomen or
belly chest and rib
cage or the subtle sensations of breath in and out
of the nostrils are playing over the top of your
lip the invitation is to include the whole body of the
breath from the beginning of the inhale all the way
through to the top of the inhale the
fullness and then that delicious moment of release of the
exhale noticing all of the little [Music] Sensations as the
breath transforms to air
perhaps after two or three more intentional slow
breaths allowing the breath to be natural however it is
today if you like tuning into the vibrancy
the energy throughout the whole body the
transpiration of every
cell which might be felt as a gentle sense of
energy aliveness vibrancy
settling in noticing a long breath as a long
breath a short breath with a short breath
inhale as
inhale exhale as
exhale making the
determination to have mindful awareness Presence at the
Forefront and allowing thoughts of there and then to fade to the
periphery the background
the instruction is that if a sound or
[Music] sensation something anything pulls the attention
away to turn with kindness completely
towards the arising of whatever that is in the moment bird
song moose [Music] munching [Music]
twinge memory as such and acknowledge
it then returning the attention back to this moment
whatever your primary anchor of attention is
laying in contact with the sensory
experience of
now noticing any Simple Pleasures that arise
with appreciation
savoring but not
clinging and noticing any challenges that arise with
love compassion not getting too involved
but allowing
receiving and returning to the sensory experience of the moment
you'll meditate mostly in silence for the next 20
minutes I'll add a few little nudges suggestions here and there
trust your
practice
e e
if a sensation or internal
experience begins to flood or become
[Music] overwhelming the suggestion
is to intentionally shift
Focus to one of your senses that is not troubling
you for example from the mind the
heart to hearing
experimenting [Music]
allowing the attention to shift temporarily when necessary
the hearing seeing [Music]
smelling and then if anything overwhelming is there
is subsided returning the [Music]
attention to your primary anchor staying standing
[Music] in whatever present moment s
experience connects you most
peacefully simply happily to the
moment
e
e e
from time to time refreshing
the mindful awareness presence of this
moment and if there was distraction rather
[Music] than self blame or feeling
badly the invitation is to appreciate the reemergence
of awareness invite it like a
friend welcoming present moment
experience
e
e e
then the last remaining moments of our meditation
together the invitation is to turn your mind your heart back over these
moments a formal practice with an appreciative
gaze noticing Gathering up
any moments of patience efforts towards
mindfulness emergence of awareness or
Clarity courage staying
with and appreciate them favor them take them in
and from that place of being nourished to include any
challenges experienced with an attitude of compassion
care nothing needs to be left out
and then turning that compassionate appreciative
gaze inner gaze outwards to the others in your
life you're making the determination may this practice
have a beneficial ripple effect on all people all
beings this life
touches May others as well as
ourselves be safe happy
healthy peaceful and free
[Music]
thank you for your
practice e
so thank you dear Global online sa it's just such a delight to be with
you I started sitting this sit the very first day it started after covid
Sheltering place and um have stayed in touch intermittently ever since and feel like
I know many of you from the chat and many of you I've met on Zoom or sometimes in
person so it's good to be
here so today I'm going to continue conversation the exploration I
started yesterday on the Buddha's teachings on
the senses the sense doorways bases fields
and as I mentioned yesterday this is a practice that's very accessible to you if you're totally a
beginner and it stretches all the way through to those Advanced beginners and
those who are deeply experienced and grounded in the Dharma in the Dharma
Stream So today we're going to look more deeply at how to work with the senses to support a
healthy emotional life and the Buddha's instructions on emotions and the senses as a way of
deepening Spiritual Development it's a lot to cover so this is kind of a
taster and I'll just mention that this exploration is actually a series I did a
couple of years ago this one talk is unpacked from um a much longer talk for
the Tuesday Morning Zoom it at IMC so you can look back I'll try to
remember to put the link in at the very end if you're interested in a deeper exploration of
this so first ways we can relate to our senses can support healthy emotional
life or they can make things much worse what do I mean well let's start
with how we make things worse overwhelm
sadness anxiety depression emotional flooding of all
kinds is strongly associated with getting stuck in preoccupied by stories
and thought Loops this also involves closing off the
senses all of the senses except for the Buddhist concept of the mind and heart
doorway Fe yeld being a sense door so when all of the other senses
shut down stories of suffering take over
and contemporary science actually confirms this neuroimaging and
scans and it also confirms that our capacity to switch attention to the
other five senses and be present increases a healthy dist from
and wisdom discernment about unhelpful thoughts
unhelpful emotions unhelpful thought patterns this stepping into the
senses increases resiliency satisfaction and a healthy
Simplicity a lifegiving alternative and it's available both in formal meditation
and walking around in the world extremely
portable this lifegiving alternative is something that has been core to the
Buddha's teachings for Millennia and perhaps it's part of why the Buddha and
his followers were known as the happy ones having nothing but robe bowl and a
few simple requisites to support them they were likened to Birds free
and their visages were glowing according to accounts from other religious Traditions back 2600 years
ago so I'm going to offer two practices
and these practices are both for the experiences of unhelpful emotion or
overwhelm and can be used to deepen development and present in
life the first I call taking a stand at the sense
doors and this involves intentionally placing your attention on one Sense
store not a troubling one but for example I used to teach in
pain clinics for many years and while the normal instruction in Vasa is um to
turn your attention to discomfort or pain as it is simply without adding anything and allow
it to pass or break down or dissolve and that's a good instruction however if
pain is overwhelming or tends to Cascade through the whole system the instruction
changes then it's to shift to a different area of attention often
sound or even seeing for emotional pain there are ways
that you can also switch attention those two switches to sound or seeing
work but others do as well for example one of my root teachers
sayia say means teacher U Tania mister
and then his Dharma name bringer of light holder of light he for many years
even though he was a serious meditator lived kind of a wild life and then was
burdened by many obligations and prone to depression and he discovered that
using a menthol stick like this would bring him back to the present
moment cut through dissatisfaction and keep him present so
scent intentionally used can also bring us back and cut through even very
difficult experiences one of my mentor teachers
Andrea fella uses a practice and then teaches a practice of what she calls
useless gazing I actually don't think it's useless at all the practice is to
look around you can do this if you want to at home at Junctions or Corners in a
room or if you're outside at where tree limbs meet and just do it for you know 30
seconds a minute and it will often begin to settle the system
settle the system down so those are
particular kind of little practices within the main one I'm offering here
which is to take a stand in a particular sense door that's not whatever is
troubling you second practice is if there's a persistent
ongoing story in the mind unhelpful unfolding in
our hearts to intentionally rotate through flip through the different sense
doors sight sound tasting smelling bodily
Sensations kind of methodically rotating through and that attentional shifting
tends to bring us more into the present moment and this does not have to be just for
overwhelm it can be for simple distraction or getting caught up in the
mind's default mode network instead that brings us to the
senses and then the opportunity for being present allows for
occasionally then checking the attitude or quality the mood of our heart and mind itself as one of the
six total senses movement can be helpful in
this there's a research study that was done some years ago I don't remember any
citations for it but they talked about the increased satisfaction and simple
presence of people I believe they were Dutch people who went for a walk every
day and there was something about the movement in and the act of appreciating
the walk together that increased a sense of
satisfaction and connection especially if they went with another person even if that other person's on the
phone so those are some kind of simple
practices that you can explore the Buddha also taught how to cultivate wisdom regarding emotions by
noticing them at each sense door there are three primary emotions he covered
Joy or happiness sadness or distress and
Equanimity and his instruction is to notice when any one of those comes up in
response to input at a sense store and
notice is it hooking the mind and making things worse or is this an onward
leading emotion a burst of Joy or satisfaction without
clinging that can be onward leading to development maturity deepening on the
path the word the Buddha used for hooked my word is
household and he means identified with lured in obsessing
over so there's nothing at all wrong with simple
happiness unhappiness even as long as we don't get lured and stalled
diverted spun out I'll give an example that kind of
encapsulates these in these last couple of minutes recently I was with a group of
friends and we were on this beautiful Ridge and this stunning view in One
Direction of a majestic Mountain we like 15 or 20 of us and
um some of the people there were dead set on seeing that view I mean it was a
spectacular view so that's Joy at the eye door I just a sense of happiness and
satisfaction and pleasure and um in their Rush interest in having the view
they actually kind of squeezed me out of my spot in order to see The View and so I
went and I sat somewhere else and there was a choice point there I could have
obsessed or grumpily kind of thought about oh look at what they did blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah like this means that about them and this means this about me and da d d da da or just dang
it I didn't get the view but instead I recognized oh pleasure at the sense door
of sight is driving this Behavior why don't I just let go let them have it be
generous and I went to a sort of side where I had a view of trees and a few friends and ended up having a wonderful
conversation and about an hour into this excursion I looked around and noticed that even the people that had been so
obsessed with having the spot with the view weren't looking at the view at all they were looking at each other
completely engag engaged in friendly conversation and the happiest people in
that group appeared to be those who had given up their spot for others practice
generosity letting go so the basic difference the Buddha is
talking about here is are we addressing relating to our senses like a clenched
fist grabbing on to what makes me feel good or even worse what what makes me
feel bad or is there an open hand
open-handed experience appreciation of what arises at the senses or allowing of the difficulties
that arise without getting entangled hanging
on or making things worse so thank you thank you for
listening to these teachings today I really appreciate I don't take it for granted that you all are here for your
own deepening of practice and development and community and if you want to hear more
on this topic it's a full 45 minute talk on aiod dharma.org and it is I believe
around October actually I can tell you if you look up my name and then go
to October 18th of 2022 you will find the full
talk thank you for your practice and see you tomorrow be well