so I was saying that mindfulness is a noticing practice and part of the premise of this
is that we can choose like you know that which we are noticing we can move our
attention and in some ways this means that anything absolutely
anything can be like the object of mindfulness sometimes like when we come
to a meditation center we see a teacher who sitting on a floor in a particular posture and we're going to instruct you
to do that there's this way we might think like oh well mindfulness has to be look a certain way or has to be done a
certain way but it doesn't have to be that way it's something that definitely
is portable that we can bring to our daily life to anything that we're doing but mindfulness of
the of the breath is often where we start and we often use this as the
primary anchor and what I mean by that by anchor is just you know some place where we're placing our attention so
just the breath and then of course like the Mind likes to wander and then we just very simply come back to the
breath some of the advantages of using the breath is that it's changing and
moving and there's something that's a little bit more interesting for the mind to be paying attention to something
that's moving there's more I can say about the breath
but I I'll stop there for now and also last time we talked about the
posture and how it can be really helpful to have an upright
posture in a way that you know expresses some uprightness but you know our
intention to meditate Our intention
to be specific with where we're placing the mind
and some have some alertness and this this is a a practice
in itself I would say to have this sense of uprightness and ease sometimes we
have this you know we feel like first we have to be stiff and if we come off of the back rest in a chair there's a
certain stiffness that can happen and it feels uh maybe stilted or forced in some kind of
way and I would say for uh actually I don't it's already I was going to say do
I know anybody yes I do know some people that from the beginning was no problem you know just to be in a meditation
posture but for many of us that's not the case like to be in a meditation posture is uh difficult or a little bit
uh uncomfortable and I just want to name that and I'll just say I think I said
this last time too but for me there is no way I could sit for more than like
you know 10 or 15 minutes it's not that I set out intentionally to try to be better at my
meditation posture it just happened I'm just meditating more and more it just got easier and easier so I'll just offer
that and so there are a few ways that we can teach
mindfulness so many different ways and here at IMC we tend to do it in a particular
way other ways are perfectly legitimate but uh this way is
if you can imagine a concentric circles that are like going out and in the
center is uh the breath and where the reason and it's the breath it's in the
center because it's often the most stable and maybe the most reliable and
accessible not always and not for everybody this is a generalization and then we would say
like one ring outside is uh the body mindfulness of the body is also has some
stability and in some ways you know we can even merge the breath and the body but for this one I'll say the breath and
the body and then emotions right we get pushed around by our emotions and often
there's some instability and lose our presence of mind so to speak with emotions so that's the outer ring and
then I would say even more so with thoughts that uh we just get lost in our
thoughts in our planning and in our fantasies our memories all these
different things so we tend to focus and really
um draw on and refer to what's more in the center so this is the breath and the
body and the ensuing weeks I'll talk about emotions and thoughts we can be mindful of them as well but it really
helps to have this stability of the breath and the body so this class we start breath and the body emotions and
thoughts kind of going to the starting with the most stable to the least stable so in this way there's a certain
progression so I could say like you know please don't have any emotions until next
week or don't think don't think and you know for two weeks or something like this until we talk about it but uh of
course that's not going to happen but I just want to put that in the mix that's what's uh coming
[Applause] up and so to talk a little bit about mindfulness of the body I mean of course
our bodies are such an integral part of what it means to be a human being right
to we have these bodies however it's so easy to be
completely disconnected from kind like the embodied
experience kind of society or culture that we've created just really supports
this idea of here let's uh get lost in this let us entertain you so you get
completely disconnected from your body or you have to think and make sure that
everybody knows how smart you are so make sure that uh you are always in your
mind prepared to you know have the right response or you it's so important to get the right grades like these are the
kinds of messages that uh we've been receiving or maybe we've even received
messages that some that uh there's something like impure with having a body or terribly wrong
either we receive that from others or even with ourselves we might be telling ourselves you know that there's
something terribly wrong with our body and it's best to just ignore it because it's uncomfortable to be with the bodily
experience or we might have had some traumatic experiences that are associated with the body and we don't
want to be with the body because It's associated with those terrible things that happened and it seems safer to uh
just not be part of it to you know kind of like move away from the
body and also I would say that uh kind of as a leadup to what we'll talk about
next week is that the emotions are actually a partly a bodily experience
and often we don't want to feel our emotions so we don't really want to be
embodied so I've just given a long list to kind of like normalize why it feels like wh it we you
know the want to be in our minds rather than feeling embodied in some kind of
way like really connected with uh what the bodily experience
is so it can be a training it certainly was for me I would say this I thought I
was embodied but turns out I wasn't so much
I remember hearing this Dharma teacher this was years and years ago saying that uh he experienced himself now I don't
remember exactly how he said it but this was the visual that I had in my mind it's like a lollipop like a stick with a
head on top and just like this head just kind of brings this stick around where
it goes right this the body had just been kind of you know just some stick that I dragg around with me or something
so to practice with this and those of
you who are on the retreat that I taught recently will recognize this just uh bring your attention to
your left hand and just like what is the
experience of having a hand
what does it feel like we're not thinking about it so much
feeling
handedness maybe there's some tingling some
throbbing maybe there's some pressure whatever that has is
touching and then bring your attention to your right
hand how does that hand feel like from the
inside the experience
do you feel this maybe we could even say the hand experiencing
itself so with no words just
experiencing throbbing tingling maybe a sense of Vitality or energy or something
vague like that and
then bring to mind like some ideas thoughts you have about the mind that's
the hand maybe it would be better if we had
longer fingers so that we could play the piano better or play the guitar
better or maybe your hands aren't very big or too
small or too big or maybe they have veins on them
or maybe they have spots on them what are some of the ideas about your hands
and maybe some of the judgments about your [Music] hands just noticing the thoughts we have
about the hands maybe the hands should be
different and then coming back to just the
experience of the hand
feeling the tingling or the pressure maybe there's some
throbbing so now I'd like to open it up I'm going to end this
little exercise and just to ask you what was that like could you tell the
difference or what did it feel like between like experiencing the hand
versus thinking about the hand and especially if we have judgments about our
hands what what was that like anybody like to
share thank you lizia I'm sorry you have to crawl all across the floor here
um it was interesting to me that my experience of just feeling my hands was
very different from thinking about them like so different and after starting
with feeling the hand then it was almost hard for me to get into thoughts about it because they seemed
very just like two entirely different worlds going on with the
really feeling the hand and then trying to think about it in an abstract way was seemed silly I don't know it
didn't it was interesting I hadn't experienced that before yeah do you want
to say which one was there a sense of which was more easeful like to to like feel oh yeah feeling that being in the
hand was definitely more I mean that just was nice my hands were warm they were relaxed it felt good and thinking
about it just seemed complicated yeah yeah it's a little more
busy and like trying to make something happen when you're thinking about the H instead of failing them great great
thank you Liz anybody else have a comment something they'd like to
say no okay thank
you so there's a few things to say first is maybe you know this already maybe
it's obvious already that we can be intentional we can go from the left hand to the right hand so we can you know
direct the attention especially you know um when we
are not lost in thought we can just move the attention to wherever we'd like for
it to go that's maybe the first thing the second thing is there are two
different ways to be with our experience one is to actually be feeling it and the
second is to be thinking about it but we think we're feeling it or maybe it's clear that we're thinking about it but
so these often can get conflated somehow like the thoughts about the experience
are really different than the experience and sometimes I like to emphasize that the experience doesn't
need words it's just you know you know I'm not going like we
would feel like oh it's kind of smooth or you know or um kind of like cool if
we were to use words those are like the types of words that we would use as opposed to often there's thoughts of um
oh was was my hand in the right position or should I move it over here or should I do something like this or I don't know
we have some ideas about what is happening as opposed to just being in
the experience and it turns out that uh
there this way that to intentionally like turn towards experience is a way
that we can like interrupt some of the um momentum that the Mind might have
about the experience because for example just make this up that uh with the hand for um I
took piano lessons when I was you know really I did last very long but uh I
remember sometimes when I think about my hands I think like oh yeah there was this thing that they I was trying to
reach different keys and they weren't uh quite long enough but notice how when I
tell that story that was how long ago that didn't that's just it's not here it's just a
it's just words completely imagination about something that
happened decades ago I'm still sitting here I'm still having the experience in
these hands but I'm kind of like thinking that I'm trying to stretch my fingers to get to wherever they were
supposed to go on the piano keyboard so there's a way in which our
thoughts can like pull us out of the
experience maybe that's obvious but what is sometimes not so obvious is that um
often the the thoughts that we have about particularly compelling EXP es
uncomfortable experiences often we don't notice them and then there's a way that it kind of
like compounds the compelling experience the difficult experience or the uncomfortable
experience so often there'll be like something uncomfortable and then boom this shouldn't be happening um my knee
is going to fall off if this uh stays like this or am I going to have to go to the doctors after this or will everybody
here if I change my posture you know something like this and then we're just
no longer with our experience and our life passes Us by why
we're lost in these thoughts so there's this way can we stay with the
Simplicity and the immediacy of this moment this
moment this moment and noticing When the Thought train has uh taken us
elsewhere 100% in our imagination right we don't go anywhere we stay right
here and then we start to just feel embodied and live with our live our life
in a particular way it does require a certain amount of
trust because we maybe for a lifelong have thought like I have to think about things I have to solve these problems
thinking is useful and valuable but we're doing meditation which is a
different activity so with that let's do a guided
meditation and if you want to stand up for a moment before we sit down you're
welcome to do that if you'd like to like shift your posture go from the chair to the floor or the floor to the chair or
something like that you're welcome to do that
okay so taking an alert
posture posture that has some uprightness
has some uprightness and some
ease just notice that we're here feeling the pressure against the
body from where you're sitting whether that's a chair or a
cushion just noticing how that
feels the back The Backs side the back of the
legs and the
feet contact with the
surface then we'll do a little bit of a body scan
checking in around the eyes sometimes there's tightness and
tension
there we don't have to do anything about the tension it might be that just simply
noticing allows there to be some softening [Applause]
noticing if there's any tension around the
jaw the shoulders allowing them to slide down the
back away from the
ears the upper
back lower back
the
chest the belly we just resting attention
and then wherever in the body that the breath is
felt whether that's the movement of the
belly the stretching around the chest or the feeling of air coming in
and out of the nose
just resting the attention on the sensations of
breathing feeling the experience of the breath
we're going to hang out here for a little bit with the breath
tuning into the experience of
breathing and when the mind is lost in thought we just very simply gently begin
again with the sensations of
breathing for
and now can you turn your attention to a
compelling bodily experience maybe something that's
uncomfortable pressure against the body maybe something that feels really
nice letting go with the breath and turning
towards this bodily experience
what does it feel like what is the experience what are the
sensations
and when it's no longer compelling or you find yourself lost in
thought come back to the breath in a relaxed easy manner
let's do that again to a compelling bodily
sensation something that draws or draws your attention
feeling into
it and this time notice if there's some thoughts
around it if there's a commentary around it sense of this shouldn't be there or I
hope this lasts I I don't know what she's talking
about whatever it might be we're just
noticing and then come back to the breath
then this way we can move back and forth between
compelling Sensations and the
breath nothing in particular needs to be
happening we're just noticing for
can you keep it simple just with the immediacy of the
experience and right now we're emphasizing the breath and the
body maybe going back and forth if need be
and being sensitive to any commentary about the experience
for this last bit here can you just hang in there with the sensations of breathing
[Music]
so it turns out that at every moment each
moment there most often there's two things happening one is an experience in the
body or whatever the experience might be and the second thing is the commentary
about that experience I like it I don't like it I'm confused about it kind of
maybe that's a maybe one way in a high level summary of what the the way is the
commentary that we have and there's this way in which we kind of like assume that the commentary
is just part of the commentary is often a judgment you know about whether it's good or bad desirable or not or it's uh
maybe leads then kind of like might lead into a story or a judgment about what's
happening and we tend to think that there this commentary is integral to the
situation it turns out it isn't that this commentary is
extra and I would say that this extra bit that gets added on which is just a
habitual thing that human Minds like to do is often where this if we're going to
have like the inner critic show up it's going to be something that's going to have a role in our life it's this it's
this commentary about our experience and sometimes it's so familiar that we don't
even notice it we just start to think well that's just the natural way of
things that you know I'm just making up these things that if uh you notice like
oh I've been lost in thought for quite some time and then there might be really quick like dang it I I'm I'm just not a
very good meditator everybody else can meditate I can't and will they notice if I slip out early you know or whatever it
is right these types of things and there's we can start to see how so often this uh shows up in our life but we're
not noticing it because we're as I said kind of like conflating the commentary with the experience especially if it's
an uncomfortable experience or a new experience or something like this and it turns out of course the body
and the mind mind are talking to each other they're integrated they are not separate of course they aren't and so
there's this way in which the aversion the the anger the maybe even the hatred
towards some uncomfortable experience like actually ends up turning
up the volume of the uncomfortableness of that
experience so our relationship to what's happening really has a big role in our
life and our actual experiences so our inner life our psychology about how we
think about ourselves how we think about others but also it impacts the magnitude
of our experiences right the physiologist and
neurologist will point to the same thing about how experiences especially like
bodily experiences or uncomfortable experiences they have uh more than one component you
know they're a complex of both what's happening in the mind the story that the
mind is making whether it's pushing against it or whether it's pulling towards it wants more of that experience
want more or less or maybe it's just feeling confused and just keeps on like uh just kick getting off of that
experience that relationship we have to experience uh has an impact
as I said to kind of like uh can increase the volume but it there's a way
that um the impact is also it takes us away
it kind of like dilutes the actual lived experience instead we're having a
relationship with our thoughts about the experience so we're like two decrees
separated from what's actually happening and as I said this takes a
little bit of a trust to think that it's actually worthwhile to be with our experiences because I I'll speak for
myself I certainly thought it was all about figuring things out like okay my life would just be
better if I could just figure it out and figuring it out happens here in the mind but it turns out that like always
like running towards the mind or getting lost in the mind or um privileging the
mental experiences it's a way that just we start more and
more to be disconnected from what's happening but mindfulness of the body
like really feeling the body feeling the experiences is a way that we can start to see how the mind likes to leave and
go and then we start to also notice like where it likes to go and we'll talk about that later in a few weeks
but so we that with talking a little bit about uh how there's experiences and
then there's our relationship to that experience and the relationship is often a mental
experience i' just like to open it up are there any comments about how that
meditation was either like being with the breath and then moving towards something
compelling and then coming back to the breath and then being with the breath moving towards something compelling and
then noticing what the mind is doing with it would anybody like to share like
how that was how that uh meditation was and you know what I'm sorry I don't have somebody to help me move
this thank you I don't have a manager
tonight oh can you turn there's a little button on the side to push
in it's really just fatigue and and immediately almost instantaneously
dreaming I just it's like actually staying alert as opposed
to uh so it's kind of that thing of like fighting the dreaming but then giving
into the dreaming but then realize I'm losing myself in the dream um and then kind of coming away for a little bit and
fing back into the dream so anyway yeah and is this a has this happened to you
like before other times when you meditate or is it different this time yeah sometimes particularly when I'm
well tired yes it definitely do that the dreaming is is yeah sure it's not the
first time so I have a few things to say that uh one is uh we can have this uh be
the object of our mindfulness it can be fascinating to you know just notice the mind you know getting tired and getting
like where the uh the hypnogogic images you know kind of this wavy thing and
then you fall asleep and then you wake up like oh yeah oh wait I'm supposed to be meditating but just to kind of like
bring mindfulness and sometimes that that investigation of the like heading
towards dream and then maybe you get lost in dream and then maybe there's coming out sometimes that investigation
can bring up the energy just a little bit so I'll just offer that another
thing is to uh pay attention to the posture like sometimes we have to just sit up a little bit straighter when
we're tired like putting a little bit more energy in that and then uh another one can be um
instead of just like the breath or a compelling sensation to give the Mind something to do that requires a little
bit more energy so sometimes it can be doing something like
um like maybe spending uh Sensations uh
the I'm trying to think about um the hands like how the hands
what the hands are touching and then pressure against the body probably like on the
buttocks and then maybe like the feet uh on the ground and then maybe uh the eyes
so if we go from the top to the bottom it's like around the eyes for maybe one second hands for one second pressure
against the buttocks for one second and then the feet for one second and just this kind of relaxed way going stepwise
through these different uh experiences can is just enough enough
energy it keeps the Mind alert but also has the same kind of calming and settling experience so that's an
alternative something to do and then maybe the last thing I'll
say is one can open their eyes too maybe that goes without say this and maybe you
knew all those things but I just offer them in case it's helpful anybody else have a comment or
anything they'd like to say I feel like I want to apologize if I've said some of these things um last week as it happened
I taught mindfulness just like intro intro in a number of different situations and it quite a few times last
few weeks just happened and I can't and I'm having a hard time keeping straight now did I say that to this group or that
group so apologies if you've heard a lot of this before anybody else have a comment when
how was it when I said well what are is there the thoughts about the compelling experience did anybody notice
that okay so maybe I'll move on a little bit
so this idea about uh the commentary is also you know some uh I
know recently there's been this idea of the growth mindset that is this idea of
um things are possible and you know one can grow and learn and as opposed
to I I forget now what that not growth mindset is but you know they just feel
like nope this is the way I am and this is the way I'm going to be for the rest of my life and kind of like this uh
certain stubbornness in terms of uh like not I'm saying stubbornness but it maybe
that's not the right word but this feeling like we have these beliefs about like nope this is just the way I am or
and that's just the way things are and this idea of a growth mindset
which turns out to have so beneficial in our lives kind of it uh Keeps Us engaged
with our lives this idea like oh yeah things can be different I can learn new
things this growth mindset also shows up in this relationship that we have to
uh our experience this commentary uh one way that I like to
think about it is um yesterday I uh visited my mother my
mom and uh we were watching some of the Olympic trials uh I love to do this sort of as
my mom and uh so we were watching these like these amazing uh women uh
gymnasts and I noticed uh like getting like you know really involved with what
was happening and like feeling emotions you know when a gymnast did what they were expected to or it didn't you know
was like wow it was like so thrilling and I was kind of like feeling in like well why why is there this uh all this
emotion because if you think about it these are just amazing athletes doing amazing things but part of it was the
commentary right with the commentators are saying they're getting all excited with their energy and okay if she makes
it now she'll be able to get to this but will she do it you know there's this kind of a thinking and then I just
notice like oh I have to pay attention so in the same way are we have this
internal commentator that's happening and it's uh influencing our experience
we may not even notice it but it's sometimes obvious you know if we one
were to like turn off the whatever some athletic event or something like that and uh turn off the commentators right
all of a sudden that event is really different and so that's just for
something to think about the role that uh this that this
uh recognizing what the commentator is doing or you know
uh some of you may know this movie Jaws right and it has that music
like right it's the same type of thing right just like setting a tone or something just with a this people who do
movies and stuff like this know that so there's also like this um
attitude that having a certain flavor of this commentary to our bodily
experiences not only does it take it away from the experience but colors it
maybe it makes it a a certain way that maybe it's helpful and maybe it's
not helpful and that we would have talked about this and maybe some of you are
familiar with this simile the simile of the two arrows so the Buddha asks uh the
people who are listening to him like is it painful to be shot with an arrow like
this is not a trick question yes it is painful and then he asks is it more
painful to be shot by a second Arrow like yes it's even two arrows is
worse than one arrow and so the Buddha is pointed out like the first arrow is what life brings
us these I mean difficult things happen in our lives it's like that's just the Human Experience there's no denying this
even doesn't matter how much we wish it were be otherwise the truth is hard things happen painful things happen the
second arrow is kind of like you know the one that we pick up and stab ourselves with and that often is the
commentary that's speeding us up comparing ourselves to others because
even if we are comparing and we think that we're so much better than everybody else then we have to make sure that they
see how much we're better and make sure that they don't see how we sometimes aren't better and we have to protect and
show off and it's exhausting trying to do that and if we feel like we aren't
better then H that's a terrible feeling too and if we feel like we're the same
then we always have to be comparing well I think I'm a same but are they are they getting ahead or oh am I getting ahead
you there's this way in which just comparing it doesn't matter what the
result of the comparing is comparing is extra and not helpful and
it turns out to always be painful and uncomfortable the painful and uncomfortable may be subtle at first we
might like oh look at me I'm the best but then then we always have to be
looking the best and we have to make sure that people don't see us so there's this way in which the commentary adds so
much to our experience that we're not noticing often and so mindfulness of the
body is a way that we can just be with whatever the experience is
is and then I'll talk more explicitly about like compelling experiences very
often like compelling bodily experiences especially in meditation there can be discomfort in the
body the knee can hurt the back can hurt you know what whatever it might
be and so there's a way in which as I've been saying we
can notice it's often the commentary is the loudest
with the most uh uncomfortable experiences and so is there a way that
we can soften the commentary around really uncomfortable
things just notice like oh yeah that's a lot of anger for some people they feel
like there's something wrong if they're uncomfortable and they want to blame
blame the institutions blame other people blame themselves it doesn't matter they just want to blame kind of
like deflect you know any responsibility for the uncomfortable situation CU they feel like they're
failing in some kind of way or maybe there's this kind of like hatred towards uh uncomfortable things
like dang it go away when are you going to go away and this feeling like it's going to be like this forever and I'm
going to never be free from this
so this way that we can be with difficult experiences uncomfortable bodily
experiences is to one way is to notice the story that we have around it but
also to notice is there a way that we can be
with it in a way that might to
expand our capacity like yes this is
uncomfortable yes this is not what I want to be happening and yes this is
actually what is happening right now this moment it feels
like this and if we can do this like turning towards the uncomfortable
experience that move movement from oh make it go away and um trying to like
separate ourselves from what's actually happening but instead to turn
towards that's a shift in our relationship and that shift in our
relationship to what's happening starts to create the conditions in which something else can
unfold that it can be that maybe there's if uh if you have some meditation
practice maybe you've already experienced this that something is really uncomfortable maybe you could start with something that an
itch I it's like oh my gosh I have to scratch I have to scratch this on my face I'm not going to scratch I'm not
going to scratch oh I need to scratch and then if you just uh be with this The Itchy itchiness itchiness and then maybe
it kind of like it comes up and then it just
resolves it turns out so much of our life experiences like this
but we don't notice we think it's like persistent and partly the way is because our relationship to what's happening
except we're pushing it or pulling and there's this way the act of pushing and
pulling hating blaming holding on to kind perpetuates
it fuels it but if we can allow it to be
there and it can just run its natural course and its natural course will not
be super the most extreme and it won't be the longest and again this takes some trust
and I would say that trust comes from experience maybe this willingness to like I think I'll try this for a little
bit I'm not asking you to believe things or you know something like this but en encourage to just investigate is this
true is this true can I like soften my relationship kind of like dampen the
anger that I'm having and one way that we can do that
dampen the anger cool the hatred towards like particularly uh I'm pointing to my
knee uh cuz my knee is a little uncomfortable to the uh uncomfortable
experiences is to actually feel either the uncomfortable
experiences itself or the anger the hatred and this is what we'll
talk about next week it's really hard to do that but just give you a preview
that our emotions have you know a bodily
experience and a mental experience the bodily experience is
moving so much slower right the mental experience is slippery and going anywhere and everywhere
so we could tune into either the pain the uncomfortable experience or
we can tune into the bodily experience of anger or whatever aversion whatever
it might be and that disrupts some of the momentum in the
mind does anybody have any comments or questions yes can can can we bring the
microphone back there thank
you um thank you for that you kind of mirrored what I'm
learning uh through coming here on Sundays and I was telling my friend I
had to do a oral presentation yesterday I do not
like can you move that mic just a little bit closer there I'm meditating here is
it on it's not on oh maybe it's not on there we go there we go um so since I've
been meditating here on Sundays and being with you last week I'm doing
exactly what you said and I named it today being UNC being
comfortable with wait being comfortable with the uncomfortableness yes and I
learned yesterday by doing that you're fine and you gain more confidence
because you overcame sweating now the anxiety the all the uncomfortable
feelings are still there and you're bringing it you're bringing yourself and it's absolutely beautiful yeah so thank
you so much and thank you to Insight Meditation for helping me that thank you
yeah that's it exactly so the same experience is there but some of the problem kind of drains out it's less of
a problem it's just it's what's being experienced yeah less reactivity less
reactivity and just presence and more humanness right because I'm showing up
with the anxiety and uncomfortableness and it's so human it's
so human it's so human and thank you for mirroring that yeah you're
welcome and maybe I'll build on what you said that it's so human because it connects us with other humans too we
notice like oh yeah this is other people maybe they are having these experiences too we can maybe notice that they are
don't want to be uncomfortable and see how they react or something like that so yeah and it's Brave to speak with your
voice quivering or whatever it is cuz you showed up yeah
yeah thank you thank you that's beautiful thank you anybody else have a comment or
something they'd like to say
um can be heard is it is it is it I think I think we have
to how about now here we go okay um just extending on that a little bit
um in terms of being comfortable with discomfort um there's the other side and
I know you used to do yoga I remember and then you know and I was curious just in your historical
uh situation what made you move I don't know if you still do yoga
and I'm curious or you moved fully over to Vasa the reason I'm asking the context is I do yoga as well and there
you move the energy you know it's a different framework and it's got its own validity as well right so I'm wondering
how you hold those two if you do yoga still I don't know yeah I should say I do yoga but it's more to support my
sitting practice wait is that true uh it's primarily but sometimes I use it
just to like move the body you know as exercise or something like that but that's the way that kind of I use it so
not so much like intentionally to I don't know I'm just like doing ASA
practice I would say not like all of yoga is does that make sense
yeah but what made you like switch over completely oh what made me switch over
um it's hard for me to remember exactly I think that
um it's funny that I don't remember what made me switch over I think they're both
beautiful practices in complimentary um that I don't I don't
know I don't I'm sorry I don't remember exactly what why that happened yeah yeah
I you know I batt because I got I got a z place I here so I got
back wondering like does evolve to a point where a path opens up and
where I see so I don't I don't think your microphone was on so you were saying that you've done you do a number
of different practices and you're asking does the path open up and and it becomes clear is that was
that what you're yeah you know evolve over time where eventually like okay oh no this is the way I should go that sort
of clears up I see I see curious yeah because I'm not mentally able to like fully commit to any practice you know
and each one has its benefits you know yeah yeah yeah maybe I'll say that uh
Retreat practice for me was a GameChanger it really made it was a big
difference like to spend days in silence meditating there just the heart and the mind open and settle in a way that I
didn't even know was possible and many of the meditation centers like have yoga rooms where
people are like go to practice yoga uh as a way to complement their sitting meditation but uh yeah I would say maybe
it was Retreat practice that was the having that
experience does anybody else have a comment or question
it's a little mundane but um mundane is good mundane is good yeah I I have I ate
dinner and I food stuck in my teeth and I just can't wait to go home and brush
my teeth and like so I had that commentary really loud this entire night
was I can't wait to go home and brush my teeth and floss you know and it just to kind of calm it down and sit with the
discomfort of having you know food stuck in my teeth was just like you know
that's what's my practice this evening and was it uh what was like the tone of
this idea like oh I want to go I I added that up I don't know if you did but is it like okay soon as I'm done here I'm
going to go home and brush my teeth like my gosh I can't wait to get home and yeah yeah I was like there's a lot of tension within me and
um I yeah it wasn't a very calm okay well this will be over soon and then
we'll calmly go home and you know brush our teeth and no it's like I'm like kind
of restless in a way yeah mhm and do you have a sense of like if you this kind of
like wish to like want to go home and brush your teeth how did that feel in the body that wish to go go home what
was that experience like the wish to go home
was I don't know I I guess the most I can comment on that is just like I felt
like getting up like urge to get up and yeah not necessarily leave I think I had
enough like you know I guess um self-possession to kind
of like still sit down but you know that did feel a little bit of a wanting to just get up and just you know let's
maybe there's something in the bathroom there you know in the in the meditation
Hall so yeah excellent I love it I love that when I asked you this question you knew and so this turns you know earlier
I said that we could just you know notice anything and so if what's happening it's like I can't wait to get
out of here we can just notice that and often this kind of restlessness does
show up as uh in our arms or in our legs and there's a sense of like I want to I want
to move and we can feel it in the body it's fantastic that when I asked you you had that sense tuned into that thank you
thank you anybody else have a comment or
question sure yeah can we can we bring the microphone over
here when the green with the green button is on it's working it's working there you go well this ISS a little bit
off topic but I too watch the Olympic trials
fabulous those girls they're just they're just amazing anyway fabulous but I was watching them and you they were
totally concentrating what on what they were doing they didn't care about the commentary that was going on I don't
even know if they could hear the commentary but they were just really concentrating on just
doing that bar routine or that you know doing it correctly and I love that yeah
they didn't hear they they couldn't have heard the commentary maybe that was for us as Spectators I mean as television
Watchers I don't know but but then they just they didn't I
don't know it just stuck Accord with yeah you know and I would say this is
partly why we like to watch athletic or dance or performance is because we can
tell when somebody is really like in the zone so to speak right and there's
something about watching other humans do that that uh I don't know is Pleasant or
is uh I I don't know what it is exactly but I think what you're you're pointing to is something that's like integral to
be a worldclass athlete I would say and and also part of what makes it un
enjoyable to watch and so there's this do you did you have
a question about this or I was okay yeah okay go ahead
we can we'll put the little blue can you put that like blue thing back on top of that there we go yep there we
go I just had a um something I noticed which I don't know if it's significant or not but um I noticed I speaking in
the plural sometimes when I had my my commentary like let's get back to our
breath as almost there two different entities and I just wasn't sure if that's common or significant any way as
opposed to being somehow integrated well I'll just ask you so was
plural was there a sense of more than one person or sometimes there's kind of like the Royal we right like you know uh
an individual will use the plural as a more kind like a formal or elevated way
speech I'm I'm not really sure actually something I noticed and it
wasn't yeah yeah and was it uh what was the tone was it like uh come on
sweetheart let's get back to our breath I was like get back to the breath or more not quite the whipping but in that
direction yeah yeah so it's just I you know I
um I don't know if I've had this this plural thing but you know all of us are
so different kind of like how our minds are I certainly wouldn't be concerned about it or um or worried about it or
something like that so yeah just have some curiosity about
it okay so next week we'll talk about emotions and like you know how to bring
up mindfulness to them and I mean they're an integral important part of the human experience but there's also
something that can kind of like hijack us and we feel like at the mercy of them
so next week we'll talk about how can we bring some stability to our emotional
life while also honoring and respecting our emotions so we don't want to repress them we don't want to pretend that
they're not there but how can we experience them without getting overwhelmed by
them so thank you all for coming and I'll see you next week and if you'd like
you're welcome to come up here and ask me some questions thank you thank you