so good morning from the morning of California at dreadwood city and hello
to those of you in other time
zones and we are here for the beginning of our new series for this
week and as a followup on the hindrances the topic will be the five
faculties and the reason to follow up is that the five faculties line up with the
five hindrances in a nice way and our supports to do the very opposite that
the hindrances do whereas the hindrances uh obscure and hinder
awareness and Present Moment attention kind of IM immersing ourselves
in our present moment experience the the the What's called the
faculties um support awareness promote awareness support us in bringing forth
our capacity to really be immersed in this present moment experience that
we're uh that meditation is about
mindfulness so first of these faculties is usually
considered to be uh translated as faith in English I'll talk more about it later
and it probably might not be the best translation for everyone but it what uh gives support
and strength to whatever the effort is that's needed
for meditation some people like to call it confidence um so it's not about
believing in something except for believing in the value of a
particular kind of action and for this morning that action
is a very unique thing that's sometimes not associated with action which is
meditation maybe it's an activity that we engage in and even that activity means the
ending and stopping of a lot of our doing physical verbal and even mental
doing it's still we're involved in an activity of calming of settling of quieting of becoming
still we're in the evolved activity of seeing clearly what's here seeing
clearly enough so that we're not in conflict with what's here we're not struggling with it and we're not for it
either we're not holding on and trying to make something happen and that this is part of a
invaluable path to bring suffering to the end
invaluable path to reduce our suffering and live in a way that's the heart is
set free and to have confidence this is what we're
doing this is what and to remember that at the beginning of a sitting so that we
can lovingly kindly relaxingly
give ourselves over to the practice whole wholehearted
practice whole being practice so to assume a meditation
posture and closing the
eyes and the whole wholeheartedness of practice for some people can be
initiated by the posture that we set ourselves in to
meditate that we're putting ourselves into an intentional
posture maybe it's a posture that you're familiar with you found for yourself long ago but still you're
intentionally finding a a posture that you think allows you to be most present most
wholeheartedly present without any
strain so it is a bit of an intentional
posture whether you're lying down in bed or whether you're sitting or standing to
meditate it's still intentional
intentional because it supports a wholehearted
engagement to be here in our
experience and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths and part of the deeper breaths is is to begin to launch ourselves into
the present moment it's kind of like
um you know maybe a rocket going into space there's a launching engine that
gets it going maybe a booster engine which keeps it going and once it's in
space it's doesn't need much prop propulsion anymore just kind of is there in a
peaceful quiet environment allowing to it to travel along the
Dharma Pathways so the deeper breaths is kind of like okay here I am this is what I'm
doing and then letting the breathing return to
normal relaxing the body
maybe this rocket has gotten wobbly as it takes off into
space And so there's uh whatever Rudders
or whatever it has that it begins to smooth itself out so we smooth ourselves out by
relaxing the
body and quieting the thinking mind so that our travels and meditation
the unfolding can go smoothly here and
now and then settling into the breathing
and maybe I'm allowed another metaphor kind of rowing in a
boat where the momentum forward is with every stroke of
the ore the rhythmic circle of
lifting a paddle and moving it through the water
and so the cycle of the breathing each cycle of breathing like
an [Music] ore where you can give yourself over
wholeheartedly to the onward momentum
of being immersed here now with just
this present aware of what's
happening and if you find yourself pulled away from the breathing
by some other present moment experience be aware of that
peacefully but if it's a strong pull see if there's something in the system the
mind the body the heart that can be
relaxed softened and then return to the
breathing
for
for for
and a rowo you're always in the water and if you're rowing you're always
moving through the water we're always in the present moment
if you give yourself over to the breathing to the
mindfulness you're always moving forward in the present
moment entering the present more deeply fully over and over
again moving on the
path the pathless path here in the present
moment
for
e
for e
with each in breath you're dipping yours into the
water of the present moment and pushing yourself forward into
the present moment through through the present
moment so completely involved in the
activity that everything else can get still and quiet just
this
e
for
for for
and then as as we come to the end of this
sitting to again Center yourself on the
breathing and then Center yourself in Your Heart A Heart Center or
wherever you Center yourself to be close to your kindness
friendliness love compassion Good
Will and let yourself breathe together with your Good
Will and as you breathe the ores moving you forward
into Good Will into the ocean the Sea of Love or
kindness towards the people in your
life so your good will is not static it's
Dynamic orienting yourself to others
even if you don't step towards them your your your good
will inclines leans towards
others rowing in the ocean of good will bringing your good will extending
your good will to
others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings
be
free and may our capacity to have good
will both move us towards
people and something we move through like rowing through the
sea rowing forever into the world with Good Good Will and
[Music]
love thank you for
so hello and welcome to this new five-part series this time on the five
faculties and following up on the hindrances um I want
to point out that last week in talking about the hindrances I talked also about how uh
especially the last three hindrances interfere with our ability to
practice they they inhibit action the first two hindrances desire
and ill will they might Propel the wrong kind of action greedy
desire and hostile ill will we act on those those those those
aren't very good in the in the um the five faculties
it's a little bit the same thing that the opposite so the first two faith and
effort um invol olve action activity engagement and the last three
mindfulness concentration and wisdom are which support
action so the Buddha was said to be a teacher of action and you know that uh
he was a um um kada an
actionist maybe and um and uh maybe Buddhism isn't
often associated with action if we when we're in the meditation traditions of
Buddhism because in hang on a minute I'm going to clear my
throat not associated with action because of uh meditation tradition we
sit still we're quiet and often partly because in the west people are such busy
Minds spinning Minds that it's so and so striving or pushing or trying to do so
much that a lot of the teachings is don't do anything relax settle um just
be just be don't do just be however for the Buddha I don't think
he ever really said just be he was a he was a teacher of action of engaging
being active in the world and there are three ways in body speech and mind
they're all activity nothing is static and the deep immersion into the
present moment where deep Stillness and peace can happen is a kind of activity
it's a way of being active a way of doing that uh brings deep peace and some
people who are athletes or musicians or there's different activities that people
do some of them expend tremendous amount of physical energy but in doing that we
come into harmony into kind of the Mind become still some inner Stillness and
quiet takes over that um it's very you know when we stop the activity we just
feel so peaceful and calm maybe concentrated so activity and being calm
activity and being peaceful and centered and quiet being still even in a certain kind of inner way are not opposed to
each other so the uh first of these five
faculties is usually translated as faith when we do that in English many people
then associated with Western religious ideas of Faith having faith in a tenant
having faith in something else outside of us having a faith in our you know the
purpose of life or meaning or what's most sacred or some
understanding for the Buddha the when he used the word Sada
Sada um it was explicitly a kind of
mental state mental activity that had some kind of desire as
part of it so that's why it's associated with the first uh hindrance kind of
parallel with it first hindrance is sensual desire or avariciousness want to
have things uh Faith this Sada is also a desire it's considered a wholesome
desire it's a desire that for us to engage in the path of practice to engage
to be interested in our from becoming interested and motivated to work for the
end of our suffering and and to start that path to
engage that this is what I want to do is to end my suffering to become free and um and so it's not a faith in a
Doctrine but more of a a faith or belief or confidence that uh there's something
to do and we want to do it we want to practice we want to meditate we want
to live by the precepts we want to live by the eful
path yes uh we want to meditate there's a big
yes behind or comes out of this so-called Faith confidence that um that
is the first of the faculties to call it confidence uh is
Associates more perhaps with we're confident we can do something take care of ourselves or engage in
activity but what it confidence might miss is a kind of heartfelt that's
behind it the affective quality of Faith where faith is kind of can be an inspiring heart
quality and um so somehow the word Sada in Buddhism maybe is a combination of
these meanings in English of faith and confidence yeah I have this um
need to clear my throat today a
lot so um
so I think it's helpful to appreciate that the Dharma path that
we're on calls on us to act and so for example uh
meditating meditation doesn't work unless you do it so to show up maybe
every day to meditate and to do it regularly a lot of the benefits of meditation come from
doing it regularly even if you think meditation is mostly just sitting and being very just letting go very very
deeply so you can just be here without the normal tensions of daily life it's
still the activity of getting to your seat and sitting down to do it but even in meditation there can be a
a delightful and healthy and calming way of thinking of meditation is an action
as well and the metaphor that I gave for the last meditation was that of rowing a
boat on the Sea on the ocean uh you're always on the ocean when
you're rowing on the ocean but every uh stroke of the ores
you're moving forward in the water always arriving in the ocean but always
moving through it always immersing yourselves into the ocean coming going
going and you're going forward into the ocean so here we're immersing ourselves
in the present moment but it's not a static event we're kind of allowing
there's a movement there's a momentum on the path on the moving forward into it
more fully and so the idea that the breathing might be the yours the cyclic movement
of breathing in and breathing out and you might figure out for you yourself
which is which uh is the is the in breath or the out breath the stroke is
the out breath or the INB breath lifting of the ores out of the water you know different people might have different
associations but it's not meant to be astray not that you're looking into the future for something else you're just
looking to be really right here here in this ocean of the Dharma the
ocean of the present moment and there's a movement moving forward and that moving forward in the
practice is not that you're going someplace but you're kind of moving
forward into being more immersed here in yourself in this moment here there's a
dropping away the the water that rushes back off the hull of the boat is all
your thoughts all your preoccupations they just wash away wash away and so we
can just be here in this moment with ourselves in some full way and to have faith that it's valuable
to do this invaluable to have confidence it's invaluable to be on this Dharma
path and to engage in all the pieces of the path that we
understand that um that there is the possibility of freedom from our hatred
freedom from our greed our addictions freedom from our resentments and envies
it is possible to be free of our anxiety free from our negative selft
talk it is possible to free ourselves from these things so that the beautiful
parts of ourselves The Marvelous parts of Good Will and compassion kindness
Peace So that our ethical sensibilities sensitivity can be guiding us to do well
in this life and not to cause any harm we can learn we can find a way deep
way to live a harmless life to not cause any intentional harm the world needs
people like that so to be inspired to feel yes I have faith in the activity
the path the action the engagement this is a this is a PA path of action the
Buddha gave it just is but however we have to be very careful that it's not action
that we're straining it's not an action that we are tensing it's not a competition it's not
a race to get someplace it's um it's uh we have to
find a way to engage in this path in the meditation and the eful path whatever it is that you understand the Dharma to be
in a way that uh the way you do it the way you act is nourishing is
feels good of course you want to do it this is a good way to do it and that's
the art not only is it a Buddha teaching of action
in terms of you have to act but he's also a teacher of action in about how
you act how you engage but there has to be Faith or confidence
or trust or inspiration yes this is what I want to
do so for the Buddha the primary purpose for
Sada was to begin and continue doing the
practice and since that's what we're here for is to practice together that uh
um may it be that your inspiration your confidence your trust your
faith in this possibility of being in a path to
Freedom is a wonderful fuel wonderful motiv
motivator and let not just motivate you in how you meditate or even just
meditating maybe there's a way that this says is's a yes to living a way of
living that lets the Dharma of harmlessness dless the Dharma path of
Freedom Propel you into greater awareness greater
mindfulness greater showing up here and now for this
life for each person you encounter for every activity you do and every way in
which you regard yourself may all those be for benefit for yourself and the
world may you have faith in that possibility so thank
you um and uh so the next four for the next
four days are the faculty of Faith faculty of mindfulness The Faculty of
Som body and the faculty of wisdom thank you