so hello and warm greetings from the Insight Meditation Center in Redwood
City and um here to give uh the fifth of
these guided meditations related to the theme of the road and The Road Less
taken and um one way I'm of
understanding the potential of Buddhist practice is that involves
uncovering a treasure which is inside that we have a amazingly valuable
jewel or treasure waiting for us and um mostly we're too distracted to
notice it to know it and with the business of life or the survival of life
and uh but in order to discover it it's a matter of being
quiet being able to be quiet enough to listen with a silent mind or to feel
with a silent space in the body that this treasure in a sense is
shy or it's uh it's soft and gentle and
so when there's a lot of force and AG agitation or distraction or activity um it covers it
over and so one of the reasons I think uh a contemplative life people who do
contemplative practice like quiet and silence is because it's only there that
uh we can really kind of maybe for the first time tap into this this
treasure and um that we have inside and so
uh to listen to this place of goodness that we have and what one of the reasons
it's so important is that that uh this treasure part of its manifestation or
part of its orientation is to avoid causing
harm because to cause harm intentionally is to live in a divided World a agitated
World a loud world where this inner sense of Integrity wholeness cannot be
known so to uh to avoid harm to avoid lying to avoid confusing
or clouding the mind or agitating the mind
unduly uh it's a place where love and care arise from
of course there's all kinds of love but the love that uh that contemplatives
emphasize that has a source deep within that is available to
love impartially to love all beings to care for everyone including those people
that are our enemies or difficult for us so this treasure
that we have so as we sit this morning meditate
this today the orientation would be will be
to listen feel below the level of the discursive
mind that thinks a lot and maybe that mind doesn't quiet so
much but maybe not to orient or focus on it but rather let it kind of recede to
the background so that some deeper connection can
occur so to assume a meditation
posture and gently close your
eyes and with your eyes closed feeling your posture from the
inside and seeing your body itself your meditative body
your contemplative body wants any adjustments to your
posture that helps you feel more connected more
alive more attuned here in this body
and with that the idea that and in a manner that allows the body and mind to quiet to
settle to be known to be recognized so something can
relax take a long comfortable inhale feeling as much
as you can your body and an extended
exhale relaxing as you exhale
at the end of that extended exhale let there be a moment or even an
instant that you wait to breathe in
just long enough that it quiets the mind around the interest to breathe
in without agitating the mind
and then letting your breathing return to
normal and again for an instant or a moment or
two to pause at the end of the exhale and in that
pause see if you can let there be a quieting of the thinking
mind is settling into the bottom of the of
breathing and as you in inhale relax with the inhale
as if you're making room for the inhale to be complete
and then letting your breathing be
normal and now in the inhale feel the thinking
mind allowing it to be as it is just know the agitation the
energy the manner with which you're thinking
and on the exhale to soften quiet the thinking mind
relaxing any physical tension that might be associated with
thinking
e e
and then centering yourself on your breathing feeling and
sensing the quiet quiet soft place
inside maybe the place where breathing
begins and
ends or or maybe a place within that is itself self
quiet free of thoughts and
ideas but filled with a
goodness with a calm capacity for care and love
the the shy place within that can
feel the difference between something which feels wholesome and UNH
wholesome feels nourishing for us and not
nourishing
e
for
e e
as we approach the end of the
sitting to now listen or feel
sense for that quiet place
within that is a treasure
that is the source of well-being
goodness the orientation towards
nonharming non greed nonh hatred
and maybe it's only an
intuition of this quiet Source
within a place of a quiet
attitude oriented towards what is wholesome
oriented to what is
free free of all
attachments to let the thinking mind become quiet in the way you would if you
listening to a faint sound far away so let the thinking mind become
quiet as you listen or feel to what's deep
inside
e for
and then bringing this meditation to an
end to find within an attitude of Good Will
kindness gentleness
care for the world beyond your body for the people in your lives The
Strangers the neighbors how in your communities and
around the world to open the
heart to be big enough to include all
beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be
[Music] free thank
you e
so welcome to this Fifth Fifth talk on taking The Road Less
Traveled and the emphasis this week has been that there are two different
operating systems within us there's the operating system that's UNH wholesome
and one that's wholesome and UNH wholesome doesn't uh mean that
it's bad or uh in and of itself but rather it
involves a way of activity of the mind that uh might even
have good things in mind it could be generous and loving parts of it but that
the way we engage in it has a kind of tension or has attachment or clinging or
aggressiveness or anxiety connected to it so that there's
a quality of it which is Den nourishing for us rather than being nourishing for
us that is stressful for us rather than um not the not just distressing but
better than that that is inspiring for us that uh brings us kind of enlivens us
in a wonderful and happy way so there are these two different
systems that we have and um and that uh Dharma practice has a
lot to do with becoming free enough becoming settled enough that this we can
start allowing this deeper system to inform us to move through us to carry us
and these are all kind of passive idea verbs in in the sense
that a lot of what we do is we get out of the way way we allow this organic
movement to uh go through us and guide us uh I love the metaphor the Buddha
uses for a particular state of samade that of an uh an uh a lake which
there's nothing coming in from outside the lake to Stir It Up or to replenish
it with muddy water when it rains and the ground is Muddy the mud gets poured
pours into the lake and stir it up and and um but there's no no inputs like
that rather the how the uh the lake gets refreshed is from a deep underground
Source uh spring under the lake bringing pure water CLE clean water in back into
the lake and filling it and so the same way we have we can have this inner kind of spring that uh
that flows and moves us that uh we don't have to do so much but we allow for when
I studied Zen part of the language there was that we don't do meditation uh we
are meditated we don't do the practice we are practi that somehow we put
ourselves in a good posture and Zen you sat in a very clear upright posture and
then the idea was to do very very little but to allow some deeper mov M ment of
um uh to course through us to to be practiced by it and they had kind of
grand they have kind of wonderfully Grand language in Zen where the idea is you're not sitting to attain anything
but you're sitting to be a Buddha you're sitting to be Awakening and this idea
that there's something here that's operating which is uh quite significant
that uh is sacred that is wonderful that is not uh uh the normal way of Behaving
and doing and and and uh trying to make something happen is uh quite
inspiring and so as we um uh one of the core teachings of uh Buddhism is the
four noble truths and for people practicing mindfulness in a sense the path of mindfulness um is complete with
uh deep awareness Ness of the Four Noble Truths in the discourse in the four foundations of mindfulness it ends uh in
um in the four noble truths and what's significant about that is that the four
noble truths end themselves with the e-fold path and uh and that e-fold path
uh can be something that uh that's embodied within us the ancient language
is at the eful we we can be endowed with hateful path some translators use
instead of endowed use the word we possess the hateful path but that's a little bit too acquisitive but the idea
is that it's not something we do but something that's inherent in us that flows through
us and this is a little bit different than how traditional terad and Buddhism teachings are where the emphasis uh is
on the third Noble truth the truth of the cessation of suffering and um so the
four noble truths are the truth of suffering the truth of the arising of
suffering the truth of the sensation of suffering and uh the Noble eful Path and
uh and usually it's translated as the um the pa the uh the the truth of the path
leading to the sensation of suffering but uh it's also can be the path of uh
uh the sensation of suffering what comes out of the end of suffering and the
teravan tradition uh kind of has the cessation as being the final ultimate goal and um and it is by doing so that
kind of Miss uh I think a very core part of the Buddhist teaching which is how we
live our lives and last week or two weeks ago I did this teaching on um from from my
translation of the book of eights where where what's the emphasis there is how
the sage lives their life there's no emphasis on some final attainment of
some ultimate state of of Mind Of Consciousness but rather living
peacefully living wisely living um um
happily that it's attaining these qualities that's important and so the Eightfold Path in the teachings of the
Buddha um is understood in two ways it's understood as certainly as a practice as
eight practices that we choose to engage in and that's more for people who are
beginning the practice or for us anybody at times in our life when we're quite
agitated quite challenged and uh in all kinds of ways it's useful to have this practice to do but it's also a practice
it's also the eight-fold path is um when when we've settled enough and and we can
listen deeply and we don't have any agitation of suffering that gets in the way then it's it's being Buddha it's
being the eful path and um someone asked uh disciple of the
Buddha in the these ancient texts uh what is the stream what is the current
that we enter into when we become a stream mentor and uh the answer is it's
the Eightfold Path we don't we enter into this path a stream a current that's
flowing through us and the eight-fold path has a lot to do with um abstaining
from anything which is UNH wholesome and in and in instead of that what comes out
of us is what is wholesome from this deeper operating system and so um over and over again in
these uh ancient text uh kind of embedded in a way that many people haven't highlighted so clearly is uh
these two operating systems and um and this deeper connection to
something deep and some of the language of that depth is um uh uh uh distinction
between uh that which is worldly and that which is dhic or spiritual within
us uh the spiritual source and then the idea of source is actually mentioned
where the word Yon is used Yoni uh can be the source of Life uh uh and so for
humans it's understood to be the womb and but so there's a way of attending way of knowing way of being
present in this world uh even a way of contemplation of thinking which is not
the discursive mind not this kind of Mind of attachment but rather comes from
this deeper Source the Yoni and and uh exactly how you want to translate Yoni
is uh you know is can be quite personal but uh from this deep Source
within and so the men the the the uh the just this gestational place within out
of which can arise understanding and and more importantly for people practicing
mindfulness can arise a way of attending a way of being of bringing our attention
to whatever is there and so it is so it's uh the very practice of awareness
of attention of mindfulness uh can come from these two sources and many times people who are
new are practicing from the you know the control tower source and uh slowly over
time we learn that the practice can well up from deep inside so it's not so much
something that we're doing but something that we are attuned to something we
allow for something that flows or lives within
us and ultimately it leads to what lives within us is the hateful path and so we
live in a kind of natural way uh because this distinction is between what is
natural and what is synthetic what is natural and what is constructed by the mind like um made up in a sense from our
attach Ms and clinging and so this natural movement of um of having a right
view or the complete view or the view from The
Source having uh uh right resolve or
intention having complete or or uh that
that view that comes from this source and so it's uh in fact the the word SU
that's translated as um right uh if you dig deep down into the
dictionaries and into the ancient text it means it doesn't uh it doesn't quite
mean like right and wrong it uh some people are translated as consumate it's
what it's complete it's What's um uh um is the complete
expression of this deeper source that is available when we're free and um anyway so there's right
intention right resolve right attitude there is right or consant or
attuned or Source uh uh Source uh
Speech there is right action there's a right
lifestyle sometimes this is called right livelihood but that's too narrow for
what it is it's a whole lifestyle that we live that feels right or consument or
and then there's um this right effort just the right way to make effort that
uh and the and the goal explicit here is to have an effort that feels like we're
thriving feeling of abundance an effort which feels like something is growing
again this very different language that that's possible when we understand that it's coming out of this deep source
and uh and then uh write mindfulness and right concentration it's remarkable that
these deep things can be there so in terad and Buddhism we don't say that we
sit like the Buddha being Buddha they say in Zen um but uh rather we say
sit uh like the path the eful path be the path um uh being path and that uh
that is the culmination of this path that we're on so I hope that this uh teaching this
week has been meaningful you for you that it points you to some very positive
orientation and inspiring orientation about the human potential and what's possible and that um and that uh it has
a lot to do in in its culmination and its consummation with a wonderful way of
living in this life that is free and uh generous caring and comes from this uh
deep place that uh is our treasure uh that we have
within and um may you be filled with the wealth of your inner
treasure thank you and um so couple of
announcements um I will be here next week through the the the you know the
holiday next week then I'll be away for a week um and
um and on vacation and then um
um um I wanted to say that uh when I come back in the beginning of the year I
think it'll be the 7th of January that uh the topic will be
for the ongoing series probably you know I don't know how long it'll last but as in the last few years I do a whole
series of of talks and meditations that have to do with I have been doing with mindfulness and meditation anapanasati
satian this next uh uh beginning of next year I want to do a whole series on
samade on on concentration practice something that's often considered to be
not part of mindfulness but which I want to really integrate in into the practice of
mindfulness and then finally um for those of you who would like this end of the year to uh maybe uh make a donation
to IMC if you're interested you can read my uh end of the year letter that I have
on imc's website uh under what's new Under Reflections from Gil and also
you'll find a link to it on this YouTube page kind of underneath the the video
so thank you and I hope these uh Solstice
times uh uh bring you abundance of inner light thank you