so hello everyone on this Monday and um beginning of
a new theme as we move through these five days of the work week the
meditation week together and
um so we can begin maybe to have a little longer sitting than
usual to to
assume kindly lovingly a meditation
posture that has the balance between being alert and
relaxed Alert in the body relaxed in the
mind alert in the mind and relaxed in the
body and if
you're comfortable closing your
eyes or lowering your gaze
gently feeling your
body as if your attention is a gentle
breeze allow your attention to blow through your body and the arms the legs the back the Torso
checking in gently touching into how your body is right now
and let the breathe of
awareness find its way to the body's experience of
breathing to feel the rhythm the massage of breathing in breathing
out as the Torso expands and
contracts and then slightly with not too much effort take
somewhat deeper inhales Fuller inhales and longer
exhales relaxing as you exhale
he and letting your breathing return to
normal with the exhales softening in your
body and whatever is not soft whatever is
tense soften around it
almost as if there's a light touch
surrounding what is uncomfortable
as you exhale softening in the
mind a softening that helps the Mind
settle
relax a softening by which your mind
is more awake more
available for your present moment experience here and
now in this body and
mind and then and settling
in settling into the body's experience of breathing
where breathing is a gentle Rhythm inviting you
here now into the experience of
breathing into the experience of being present
Here and
Now
for
e
e e
and as you exhale follow the
exhale all the way to the end as a way
to settle yourself all the way down to a
grounded settled place in your body
following the exhale to the end gently without any
Force allow the exhale to be little Fuller than
usual following the movements and Sensations in the
body as you
exhale
for for
the more you think the less you can feel the body
breathing the quieter the thinking
becomes the more attention is
available for the body sensing
the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out
e
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to check in again with yourself The Gentle Wind of
awareness let it blow softly through the body and heart
and mind to know
yourself and in the knowing the way you know there's a gentleness a
kindness a care and
acceptance for
and as you check in with yourself imagine or feel and
see if how you're feeling right now could be a beneficial reference
point for protecting you from ways of thinking ways of
speaking ways of acting which cause harm to yourself or to
others might there be a way that you're settled or calm
or more sensitive at the end of a
sitting as sensitivity that gives you
heightened care to not harm self or
other do not easily succumb to stressful activity
a sensitivity for which it might be
easier to be kind and compassionate toward self
and all beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and as each of you is part of the group of all beings
may it be that your happiness is a source of
care for everyone else
[Music]
thank you
so h hello and welcome to this Monday as we begin the week of a kind of
a new theme of teaching and
um there's a discourse of the Buddha discourse sutas and that is called the
UDA suta UD d a y i and um it has the Buddha list five
qualities that are to be established in
uh when one teaches the Dharma so hopefully these are established in me as I teach
now but these five are also interesting because they make an interesting uh
reference point for anytime we're speaking with others are these five
qualities established in ourselves when we're
speaking and uh some of them might be a little bit of a stretch for ordinary speeching speaking
but um I think they're valuable reference points and certainly valuable
reference points also for being your own teacher in the Dharma how we navigate
and find our own way through practice I uh these are included in when
I teach people to become Dharma teachers uh I want them to be familiar with these five qualities and some of
them I put greater importance on than others and um I'll read the discourse to
you and the core of it and it uh there's a context for it and that is that U the
Buddha's kind of one of his main disciples is kind of main attendant
Ananda is is in town for something and he sees that there's a monk named UD
UD who is um surrounded by a big number of lay
people and he's teaching them the Dharma and we're not sure who this Udan
is but uh there is someone else in someone of more or less that name uh
elsewhere in the sutas possible it's the same person who is one of the most
misbehaving monks in the suas who breaks the monastic rules who seems to be
filled with greed and wanting things from people and so he's not necessarily
um Exemplar of being a good monk so uh this maybe explains a little
bit why then the Buddha went back to the bu Nanda went back to the Buddha and said Udin is
um sitting in town surrounded by lay people teaching them and the Buddha uh neither approves
nor disapproves of what he hears um but when the Buddha neither approves or
disapproves sometimes that actually is a sign that he's not so happy um that if
he would clearly approve if uh someone's teaching if he he does at
times so the Buddha then offered five qualities that are to be established in
oneself if one is to teach the Dharma and um so this is how it goes the
Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will steep I will speak step
by step the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak for
practical reasons the DH should be taught for to others I will speak grounded in
kindness the D Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will not speak for
material reward the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak without
wounding myself or others so these are five and um so I
like when there's five qualities because we have these five days of the week week together and so I'll go through them but
I'd like to go through them in a different order in which they appear because I'd like to uh connect them just
lightly to the themes of the last two weeks that were the
core uh kind of foundational teachings uh that underly how I teach
the Dharma and um or you know what I teach when I teach the Dharma that's last few
weeks have been the what and uh as important what we teach is how we teach
the manner in which we teach and I've known people who taught in a manner that
uh seemed so much about themselves like almost like they were praising
themselves or building themselves up to the audience they didn't feel like they were teaching the Dharma they were you
know they were con that how they were teaching wasn't conveying what the Dharma was their words might have been
good teaching but the how was not a teaching for people and
um the um so um how we
teach and so I would like to uh start with the first one um is um I will speak
without wounding myself or others without harming myself for others and that lightly connects to the last two
weeks the first First Quality First Foundation to my core teachings is
um is um suffering and the end of suffering and to heighten sensitivity to
uh to all the things that cause suffering or stress or harm um tension within us and uh if we
use the word Dua suffering as suffering translated suffering too much some people people interpret it to be
suffering as the big cast catastrophic kind of challenges of our life but in
the Dharma the word Dua applies to the whole range from the lightest little
extra tension or stress that we add to our situation unnecessarily to uh the full-blown
challenges of you know existential challenges of being a human but uh clearly the F focal point
of the Dharma is um not being um not
exactly being offended or hurt or may made uncomfortable by reality but being
harmed by it being wounded by it and that distinction is a very interesting
distinction to uh look into because some people are confused by it and so their
response to uh others um um uh is
confused there's a distinction between being harmed and being offended being offended doesn't mean that we're harmed
in any way but maybe we just feel disrespected or feel um very
uncomfortable in a certain kind of way we might feel um hurt we might feel hurt
meaning we feel kind of you know an ache or feel somehow deflated or discouraged
or something but we have the resilience we have the capacity to just go with that and
and um and not not hold on to it not be caught in it but harm is uh when people
when we're harmed when we harm ourselves or we harm others we're causing lasting
damage a wound that lasts for a long time that is not easily uh just uh let
go of or moved you know fall Falls away easily and so to teach the Dharma
without harming self or others and when I teach the teaching people to be teachers uh it's that first one that
becomes crucial don't teach the Dharma in such a way that you're harmed yourself and one of the reasons I
emphasize that to new teachers is that how we are is is a big part of what we
teach and so if you're harming yourself you're not you're teaching harming
yourself if you're teaching caring for yourself then you're teaching the
Dharma and um so for for example when uh I'm teaching with other teachers uh on
Retreat and they get sick I I tell them please uh rest take care of yourself
because that's how you're going to teach the Dharma if um if you have challenges
any kind at all that you need to take care of yourself you actually teach something very profound in doing that
and even though you're scheduled to give the Dharma talk um uh and you feel
responsibility to show up and you know everybody's expecting it um if you show up and you're you're overriding the
self-care that's needed you're not really conveying the kind of inner care
that we want everyone to be involved in the Dharma and um and that uh part of what
Dharma practice is for everyone is to uh understand that the um things are
constantly shifting and changing and and becoming not what we expect did not what
the schedule was and so then everyone practices with
that so um so to so in ordinary life as
well uh to speak without wounding uh oneself or others to to be
in conversations without harming the the uh the relationship um and one of this
heightened sensitivi that can come with something like mindfulness something like like a regular meditation practice
is we can feel and sense uh when um what we say shifts the Dynamics between self
and others we can see that people Flinch or see that people shut
down um I've been in conversations where people said something to me that um it
just felt like they closed the door to the conversation and uh and just said well you know then there's no way
forward now you know they said something definitively declaratively and we're no longer in a
conversation or a discussion it just you know and I in in my mind I think of that
the door's been closed and okay so now uh uh there's a something in the
relationship temporarily or in this conversation now shut down we're not in relationship anymore so that's a kind of
uh interpersonal harm that's caused or loss of connectivity
anger creates a real div div divide between people
hostility uh sarcasm sometimes cynicism sometimes and so to um spend a lot of
time complaining what is the effect that's on other people people who complain a lot are generally very
self-focused and um and not as tuned into how it is for other people as we
could be and so maybe we're not harming other people people but we are harming the relationship between two
people sometimes what we say is offensive and and we don't even know we're being offend offending someone but
if we're attentive we can watch and feel and see their posture shifted their eyes
have moved away that uh the smile they had dropped away or some kind of
energetic quality of their of their body slumps or settles or something and and
um so what's the effect that we have on others so with this orientation that I
did the last two weeks of focus on suffering and the end of suffering that
can translate um uh intimately to how we are in relationship with other people
the Dharma is not only something private and personal the Dharma uh sensitivity
that awakens within us the mind and awakens within us puts us in a a into a
mindfulness field with others as well and so it becomes natural uh to um to be
sensitive and maybe caring for others and oneself so we're not harming either
self or others some people uh it's the other itself that
they don't pay enough attention to there's plenty of people who harm themselves in relationships they uh they
sacrifice themselves or they put themselves down or they limit themselves or they excuse themselves or they
apologize too much always ways which in subtle maybe very subtle is a kind of
self harm and um and so when we speak when
we're in relationships can we avoid harming ourselves and then and can we avoid harming others and I think this is
a phenomenal God for living a wise life and for the theme
of the suta it's a phenomenally important orientation for teaching the
Dharma and um and maybe some of you most of you I suppose are not Dharma teachers
but you might have occasion to want to tell someone something about the Buddhist teachings the Dharma teachings
that you're learning and they're important for you and so then be careful
that how you say it but how you tell other people that you don't harm them or
harm yourself in doing it and um and I've certainly harmed others and or at
least harmed the relationship between self and others when I was uh too caught up in the teachings and uh too enamored
in it and maybe a little bit maybe even too dogmatic about it that I was so excited about teaching it to telling it
speaking it I lost touch with the person I was speaking with so uh thank you very much and I
hope that uh um as we go through these Udo qualities that you find ways that
are are meaningful for yourself so thank you