so I'd like to start uh let's talk with a little story emphasis on
story it's a it's you know one of these stories that uh you know it has a it comes from the
suas and it has a teaching point which will become abundantly clear I think but
I'd like to build on it and this story comes from
um the dega Naya the long discourses at the Buddha if that matters it doesn't
matter so much but so there was this uh individual his
name was piasy and he wasn't a follower of the Buddha and in fact he had he was a I'm
not sure if he was a teacher or if he belonged to a different community that had different views had different ideas
than the Buddha and one particular view that he had that he was really uh espousing and
teaching was there are no consequences to actions doesn't matter what you do you
can do good things and you know maybe something good will happen maybe not you can do bad things maybe something bad
will happen maybe not it doesn't matter you can do whatever you want you know maybe like today that
sounds a little bit silly but I think that there are parts of our Lives we think like oh it doesn't matter I'll do
this there will be no consequences to this small thing thinking these thoughts that are filled
with hatred or something or or oh it doesn't matter that I don't when the
cashier makes a mistake and gives me too much money it doesn't matter that I don't give the extra money back or
whatever it is there's ways and sometimes we think that oh yeah it doesn't matter but this person piy and the Su is
saying nothing has any consequences and if we think about this this is you know 2600 years ago before
there was science or even investigation and so there was this was a real
question this was alive like why do why are things the way that they are how did I get here where are we
going you like this was a real legitimate question and so one was like it doesn't
matter and you could see cuz they might say well I told lies all day yesterday and nothing bad happened to me so they
might think doesn't matter so piy says it doesn't matter and then
there's this follower of the Buddha his name is kasapa and he has a different View and
he asks um and he says to P say why are you why are you like holding on to this
view like okay maybe you might have it but why are you really holding on to this
View and pasy says I'm not able to give it up I'm not able to give up this View
and kasapa says why and piasy says from for as long from
my own birth onwards for a long time I have been repeating this view making it
a firm habit it's just habit just to I just this is the way that I view the
world and that's that's just the way I view it and then py continues he says and
King bity knows that I have these views and if I were to let go of them people
would think that I was foolish or you know he's like concerned about his reputation he's known as somebody who has these views and he doesn't want to
change them because what will his friends think if he has a different view or not
his friends you know other people that are influential or somehow this is not so different than
today right this way in which we want to hold on to these views because we belong to a community and
that Community has those views so if we were to give up those views then people would talk and maybe we even get kicked
out or would have to leave I'm just making up these scenarios but where we can see where this is relevant to us
today I and I appreciate you know these are thousands of years ago this is they're talking about
this and so kasaas says well some people
um can understand things with the use of a simile let me offer a simile why you
might not want to hold on to this view so much and then this suta is a
collection of all kinds of similes that uh kasapa gives to py I'm just going to share this
one so kasapa starts by saying in the distant past a long time ago so this is
kind of like saying once upon a time there was a country and the
population was afflicted by famine and so there were two people one was a
wise person one was a not wise we might say foolish person and they both of them said we are
friends so let us as friends go together we'll leave this country and see if we can find some wealth or somehow bring
something back to support our community our family so let's go together and find
something hopefully will help and so they in turned so they left and
then after some time they came to this kind the Su is described as a vacant
pile so I'm thinking of it as an empty lot and there was this pile of hemp on
the ground you like this plant you know hemp just a big pile of hemp on the ground and the wise one told the not so
wise one oh let's uh take this and we can bring it back let's you know put
this load this up on our shoulders or back as much as we can carry and we'll bring this
back because there was nobody else around for whatever reason this is like abandoned clearly
abandoned so it turns out not to be so easy to get it on their backs and but
they do put on their back and they keep on walking and then um they come to a
village and they're walking on this Village and there they saw abandoned on
the ground nobody around clearly abandoned some hemp thread so hemp that
had been treated and turned into thread and the Wise One say oh what good
luck for us here's hemp thread which is finer which is you know one more step in the treatment of it or let's take
this so the wise one he puts down the hemp and makes a figures out how to
carry the hemp thread and puts that on his back but then the the um the foolish
one says yeah I've already taken the hemp I I've bound it up firmly and it
was kind of a hassle to put on and car I'm just going to keep it so then they walk further on and then
they come to this uh pile of again completely abandoned hemp cloth right we
know where this is going right so this cloth is even further developed and the
wise one says oh this is even finer I'm going to put down the thread and pick up
the cloth somebody's already weaved this into cloth I'm going to carry this puts
it on his back the other person said no I'm carrying this hemp it's been heavy
it was hard to get on and I'm just going to keep on carrying it this is actually Diana's addition that saying it was
Heavy it's just in my mind like carried all this is heavy doesn't actually say that in the Su
but so then um they walk further on and then they see raw cotton which is a
little bit smoother than hemp you know how this is going to go right the wise person's going to take off the hemp
cloth and put on the Cotton unwise one say no I'm going to keep this hemp on my
back so raw cotton and then they find cotton thread and then cotton cloth so
you know this the wise one is taking off putting on taking off putting on and then it comes to copper and then silver
and then gold come upon this pile of gold this is a story right so they come on a pile of gold and the wise one says
wow there's this large amount of gold it's a supreme and massive
treasure you should drop the hemp I'm going to drop the silver which he had you know picked up along the way and
together we can take the the gold and we'll go back to our country and we'll
be able to support people with this but unwise when says well I've
taken this hemp I put it on my back I don't really want to let it go I'm just going to keep on carrying
this so the two returned to the country one carrying a bunch of gold the other
one carrying a bunch of hemp and the person that returned home with the person uh was carrying the gold he his
family and everybody just received him and they were so delighted oh my goodness this is perfect this is great
thank you so much you've made a really big difference and the wise one he was
delighted by this that he could support them that he was able to you know through this Traves and these Journeys
to come back and to bring something but then the unwise person
said oh well here's some EMP and they weren't so glad to see him and he wasn't
as delighted in fact he felt kind of sad sad because he wasn't able to support his family the ways that the gold the
person who had picked up the gold was so then so kasaba is telling the
story to py and kasaba interprets the the Sim he says py you should give up
this view that there are no consequences to actions let it not increase your own
suffering and vexation like the person who carried the
hand and who is firmly determined to not take the gold treasure right so kasapa
is not leaving anything to interpretation he's being very explicit don't be like the person who didn't take
the gold and py says no I'm not willing to give up this view because I've often
taught this view to others so not only has it been a habit not only does he
have this reputation but he's taught it to others so he's so like uh intertwined
with it and he says everyone knows me as being a follower of this view so not
only is he holding on to it tightly he's holding on to the identity I'm the person that has this view there's no
consequences to actions and then kasapa gives a whole
bunch of other assoles some of them are you know colorful and crazy stories and
I'm not going to give all of these maybe at another suit another talk I'll give like one more of or something but but py
he just refuses to budge no matter with kasapa he's saying you know this you'll
reduce your suffering if you can loosen your grip on this view he's not saying
that you have to completely get rid of the view he's saying just don't hold on to it you might have this view but just
stop the kind of the clinging to it so then at the end uh kasapa is like
well you know I don't know what to do I've given all these similes and you're not going to change your mind I'm sorry
and py says oh actually I changed my mind way back then but I wanted to see how many
different similes you could come up with so and I wanted to see like could
you have how much wisdom you had could you do this and and kasapa said well I
don't know kasapa now I don't remember exactly what he said but it's something like well don't hold on to these
views so it's kind of playful right there's this playfulness there but
something I like about this uh story is this idea of sometimes we hold on to
things even though there might be something that makes sense to us but it's not easy to change our
views it's not easy to have a different idea about things or
it's not even easy to let lessen our grip on
views so maybe I'll say just a little bit about like what are
views maybe it's obvious what they are but maybe uh one way to think about it
is it's a it's something like a private private in that it's like
internal maybe a little bit partially hidden it's not something that we speak explicitly most often but this private
idea about our experiences like what we experience like
how we interact with the world and we're trying to make meaning out of them or
we're trying to um make ourselves feel better in some
kind of way but I I appreciate that uh one
person a Buddhist scholar he was talking about how like views are kind of like
memes they're like something that just kind of get repeated and repeated and repeated and through their repetition
they start to like maybe even proliferate their like little derivations of them and something that's
you know catchy and just goes around and around and and the purpose of the view
is actually just to replicate itself just to have more of the
same in some ways kind of like memes are like this right that go viral on the internet right they sometimes the
purpose is just to I don't know what the purpose is actually
so there's this way that views they gather this strength they have this they
maybe I could even say the clinging to them becomes even stronger the more we adhere to them and this word
adhere refers to both maybe the way that we like this View and we're supporting
it as much as the opposite the more we dislike a view the stronger it gets to
in our mind it's just the getting tangled up with it I either through liking or disliking kind of encourages
this clinging instead of like okay there's this view it seems like there might not
be consequences to actions because I know somebody who did terrible things
and they're they their life didn't seem so terrible so maybe there aren't
consequences to actions but there's a way we can say well maybe there aren't instead of
saying because this happened I know don't tell me otherwise I have this View
and everybody else is wrong instead just to say well you know it it makes sense to me but I'm not
sure but there's something about when we doing this holding on to view that often
we don't recognize it's a little bit subtle but it has a big impact on us and
that is there's always a little bit of this agitation clinging itself only arises
when there's agitation then clinging gives rise to more agitation but there's something about views clinging to views
that in particular is because there's this way in which we if we're clinging we're
saying this is true and anything that uh negates this
is wrong this is true and everything else is wrong when we say that there's a way in
which we're trying to say make something permanent
this is infallible it's always like this and we like to make things
permanent because the world isn't permanent
and it feels uncomfortable sometimes we wish there a place where we could
land just rest and like okay this I can count on 100% of the time we're always
looking for that it doesn't exist so we make it up in our
minds it's just a thought it's like this it can never be
otherwise this is what humans do we always do and we need to do this it's
part of maturation of development of becoming an adult is a uh taking on
views and then discarding ones that don't work and taking on new ones so I'm not saying that we never can have views
right now I'm pointing to the holding on to them the insistence of saying this is
true is always true and everything else is wrong so there's this little bit of this
agitation because things aren't permanent and yet we're trying to like always find
something permanent but not only that when we are sometimes holding on to
saying this is true piy maybe was saying that there are no consequences to
actions and he wasn't willing to give up that view because maybe there's this
uh little sense of delight I know I know I know you guys
don't know I know I got it I got it yeah
you guys clearly don't know but I do there's sometimes this sense of like
this righteousness or this uh you know me versus the world US versus them we
got it you guys don't there's this tiny bit of like oh
yeah look at us look at us look at me there's a little bit of delight that
happens in that but then we start to discover oh yeah we have to keep on
propping that up this idea that uh I'm different than and better than everybody else and it requires constant
maintenance constant maintenance and this is subtle this is not something obvious but this
is subtle we have to discard everything that might refute our view and make sure
that everybody knows that we know this and all this right there's this real agitation associated with
this so this leads to more like craving and clinging and we just find ourselves
in this Loop maybe I'll slip in here that uh
today's Martin Luther King Day we're kind of like honoring Martin Luther King and I'm thinking about views and Martin
Luther King one way not saying it's the only way or the best way but one way we could
consider some of the beautiful things that he had to offer the world or some different
views so it's like beautiful like he had the courage to say I everybody else is
thinking this way I think that racism is okay violence is
okay thinking that love and care that doesn't matter so much it's a beautiful
thing to so he he had some conviction he definitely
did but he was sharing them in a way that I don't know it feels like they
were had a Flavor of Love and care as opposed to hey look at me look at what I have and what you guys don't
have so Martin Luther King also talking about
views and the Buddha talked about views in a little
bit different way than kasapa did and for me one thing that's
noteworthy is there's this one sua this uh scripture the early Buddhist
literature it's the if we were to look at like how the PO Canon you know kind
of like the Buddhist lit I'm going like this with my hands it's probably even bigger than this but uh the very uh
first of the sutas is the if they're organized in a particular way so first
not first in terms of the first teaching ever given but just when they got combined and put into books one that's
the first one is all about views it's is brah the Brahma Jala suta
it's a there's all kinds of stuff in this there's a lot lot of things in this but IT addresses the topic of views and
Buddha is you know saying you people of course they have these these ideas they
want to know the answers how did we get here what happens after we
die what is the nature of this experience that's different than daily
life experience is there is there something else and of course these have to be
views because we don't know what happened before we got
here and we don't know what happens after we die so the Buddha he's pointing out that
humans are always asking these type of views and and instead of like kasapa who
was saying well you know put down the hemp and take eventually you know pick up gold the Buddha is saying well
actually maybe you don't need to pick up any views maybe there's just a you know
views arise and then they pass away it's we hold this when it's helpful and we put it down when it's not helpful we
pick this other one it's helpful gravity thinking that about gravity that's helpful most of the
time I'm not sure I can think of a time and when it isn't but
so in this uh the Brahma Jala in the Su the Buddha um talks about 602 different
views there's you know outlined and I'm going to go through all 62 no just
kidding can you imagine but we can uh summarize them but
here I think is something that's really important he's going through all these
62 views he talks about um
the content of them what they are about maybe I'll just give a little overview what they are about the question of this
the nature of the self or the soul or some
Essence is there that some people have this view that both the soul the essence
and the universe are Eternal they just will never end they just last forever
and ever ever some you know religious teachings that have this idea or there's
some uh idea well there's partially Eternal some things will last forever and other things won't heaven will last
forever hell will last forever but maybe beings won't last forever maybe some
things will or some things don't or maybe there's this sense of
well this universe or this existence is it finite or is it infinite does it have
edges does it end anywhere the universe or is it just
infinite and some people will say well it is finite and some people will say it's
infinite and there or maybe they're saying some people are saying doesn't matter just things just arise out of
pure chance it doesn't matter whether it is or isn't it's just a chance it
we don't have to assign what happened before maybe just arose this moment maybe it'll end in the next
moment but for me this is the uh favorite group of there's a number of of
views and these are views that are um espoused or given by the eel
wigglers these like these eels that wiggle it's because these are people
that like vacillate like well maybe it's this or maybe it's that or I'm not sure
but I want to say a little bit more about this it's because that they actually knew that they didn't
know but they didn't want to admit that they didn't know so they were like afraid to lie and
say yes I do know or they didn't want to be attached to their views so they were trying to say oh it's like this or it's
like that or it's not really like anything they were just trying to not say any views or they were afraid that
others might discover that they didn't know even though so they were trying to just be
evasive so that's a another group of views there's a whole number of views that are kind of around that and then
there's theories about the future what happens after death and theories about nibana what is
nibana what is Awakening what is a Enlightenment so those are kind of the
categories and there 62 in these different category but for me what's interesting
is that the Buddha he outlines all these maybe in a little systematic Manner and
then he does not give a 63r view he
doesn't he just says there's all these views and then he kind of like turns
away from the whole idea of the content into the views whether it's about the past or the future or what happens after
death he's more saying he says well where do these views come from why do we
have them and here's something I think is very interesting when I first read this
I was very interested in this of the 62 20 of these come from meditative
experiences and there's this way we might think that oh my mind was when it
was quiet it came up with this view so it must be clear must be true because my
mind was quite it happened while I was on Retreat and there's this way that we can
hold on to it this is true and everything else is wrong we ascribe some uh particular meaning to it because of
the conditions in which it [Music] arose it might be
true but it might also not be true for those of you who've been on
Retreats you know that um you meet with teachers regularly and you describe some of your uh what's happening in your
meditative experiences and there have been more than once where something would happen I thought oh my gosh wow
this must mean x y and z i March into the teacher's office X Y and Z happened
and they're like really why don't you describe that then when I describe what happened they're like
[Laughter] no this is not uncommon so the Buddha is pointing out
even you know with some of the views that arise from our meditation practices don't cling to those
either but he's also pointing out well some of these views that we have are due
to just reasoning that somebody just kind of like we creates a view through reasoning
we kind investigate it and inquire and just through our own intelligence say
Well it must be that beings um don't survive after death or
don't exist after death because no nobody's ever come back to me that has died and said hi here I am I'm actually
dead but I'm coming back and because they've all disappeared that must mean that they all disappear or something
right this is a logical thing to say when the budha is saying don't cling to
those views either so he's pointing to I think even in modern times this is relatable like
we might think that yeah well maybe some religious views we won't hold on to but
these other ones we will because they seem rational or because I had this
meditative experience he saying don't cling to
views and instead he's saying that that there's this uh said look at what causes
views to arise they arise from experiences that we
have that is and we could use this word Vena too some of you might know this
like something is Pleasant or unpleasant or neither Pleasant or unpleasant and if
it's pleasant we have this view like oh this is good and I want more and there's a
little bit of craving that shows up or this is bad it's unpleasant I don't want it I want less there's a little bit of
pushing which is the same thing as craving just kind of like the flip side of
it so he's saying that you know our whole life is with these experiences
things that are Pleasant things that are unpleasant and things that are neither Pleasant nor unpleasant and those that
are neither unpleasant nor unpleasant we tend to not even notice we tend to just
kind of like ignore those not always but we tend to
but the Buddha saying why don't you examine this experience more
closely really they look at it more closely what's
happening and see that they're not as satisfying as we
think sometimes we are holding on to things because they're bring delight and
I'll say also the flip side there's a way in which if we're really trying to push it away that's a type of holding on
to just getting tangled up with it so this there's this way that
experiences do bring happiness and joy because they do fulfill our
desires of course they do of course they do there's nothing wrong with
this but if we were to examine it more closely we would notice is
that things are not completely
satisfactory if we had this desire for chocolate ice cream and we ate chocolate
ice cream like okay I've had enough but there will be a time later in
your life when you'll want chocolate ice cream again things aren't like completely
satisfactory or then we start to eat the chocolate ice cream we start to discover oh my God
I have this sugar buzz and it makes me feel uncomfortable or I oh it's so cold I have a brain freeze or you know
whatever it is it's not 100% completely
satisfactory and if we can notice that we can appreciate the pleasure it
brings Without Really holding on without kind of like setting off this whole chain of
craving because craving leads to clinging
and clinging often is clinging to a view sometimes that view is a view of a
self I'll talk about that at another time but there's a way in which these are all
related but instead if we were to notice that things
arise and they pass away they're not
completely satisfactory in the way that we would want them to be
and not only that they don't have this permanent sub substance they're not like always the same not always reliably
there if we were to notice those things about our experiences then we'd be able
to hold those experiences more lightly and we wouldn't be attached to
them and we wouldn't be making these views from them that we often get attached to to
also so our experiences are giving the kind of like the fuel for the views But
It's Perfectly Natural of course it is and we need views to move through the
world but can can we not hold on to them tightly and can we notice which views
lead to more freedom which views lead to less
Freedom which ones bring more more openness and spaciousness and ease in
our life and which ones
don't is there a way and what is this way like to hold views lightly what does
that mean for I'm going like this with my hands I'm opening with my Palms uh
open what would it be like to not say to everybody around you what your views
are sometimes we spend time with family members for example and they have different
views what would it be like just to pay attention to them acknowledge them love
them care for them and let them have different views instead of saying well you know
actually it should be this or you you know it's that way or something like this that's one way to hold views
lightly is you know because as soon as we start uh sharing them with others in a way
that often sets up a me versus you and I know better and you should change your
mind it's kind of like implicit in
there or maybe what their views what they are saying makes us feel
uncomfortable because we think it's really wrong or maybe they're pointing
to something that's we don't like to see about ourself and it feels uncomfortable
so just to help ease that sense of uncomfortableness we say well no
actually the view here here's how it is just to like kind like change the topic and make the shift the energy
some again I'm not saying you can't ever talk about your views but there can be a
way in which we think sometimes with family members that we have to uh just tell them no actually my view is this
and what if we didn't what if we didn't have to
or what if we said I don't know this is my current thinking because of XY and z
or what if we said well can you tell me why what what uh what led you to have
this View and open up a conversation and then there can be some intimacy and a way
forward and you know something about this instead of this clinging to views
which does doesn't lead to freedom and Buddha talks about how
there's um beings humans partly the way that we're defined
is by what we're attached to what we're holding on
to if we think that uh I'm just making this up if we think like football is the answer to everything then it we'll just
be one that's talks about football wears football clothes and uses football analogies for everything and talks about
you the coaches the players I don't know all these types of things and so we'll be known as oh yeah
that's the person who likes football but what if we're not attached
to anything again I'm not saying that we
don't have views or ideas because that's that's not how to live one's life I'm
just saying not to be holding on to it attached to it and the Buddha is pointing to our
huts and Buddhas those people who are completely awakened aren't attached to
anything so they're not defined in the usual way that we might
Define someone like the contents of our minds right spill out in our Behavior
our words our dress places we go places we don't go you know all these
things but what it what would it be like to not be
defined because we're not holding on and this is the Buddha's answer to
this question well what happens after death to somebody who is completely
awakened say well we can't Define
them this is tricky I'm not going to pretend like I understand this completely but there's something I like
about this I like that it's this pointing to how we limmit things when we are saying
nope it's this way because we're saying well it's not this way it's this
way what if to say you know I don't know maybe that's
okay so to not hold on to
views and if we find ourselves not able to put down the view
maybe we can recognize that oh yeah this is hemp I have on my back and like here's some hemp cloth it's a little bit
more refined I think I'll carry this something like
that I think I'll end there and I'll open it up to some questions and
comments this idea of holding on to views not holding on to
views
thank you that was great um s reminds me of something I
heard about Einstein that he was a pacifist during the first world war but
then he escaped Nazi aggression came to America and he advocated going to war
against the axis and a lot of people from the Press challenged him and said well you're
inconsistent um thought you were a pacifist and he said uh something like I
have updated my view based on new
evidence and I always thought that was that was wonderful flexibility
yeah right and there's a lot it's fascinating when now social media allows us to um just get our own views that
support our uh get have evidence that supports our views right and just like not even come into contact with other
views other evidence but yeah thank you Phil yeah right to update our views with
new evidence new
data anybody else have a comment oh Nancy like there
thanks Diana um you were talking about uh people who say that they don't see
consequences for some things that go bad or there may or may not be
consequences and um visual perception of what
consequences are are not always where it is though right aren't the consequences
really internal and so evaluating those by
external uh views and what's happening with other people isn't really
in a very accurate way of judging I would agree I would agree if
we're just looking from the outside right we could say well they seem happy
even though they did all these terrible things but we don't really know what's going on inside of them yeah yeah thank you
Nancy
okay so thank you thank you all for your attention and wish you safe travels as
you go home and know maybe we can think about uh the views there's a view of uh
maybe supporting one another or being the change we want to see in the world this type of thing something that's to
hold on to but not tightly or openly or softly something like this thank
you