hi everyone we taking a moment to notice
how it feels to be here whether you're engaged with the YouTube chat or just listening to my
voice and take a moment to welcome yourself say hello to your
being whatever state of mind or heart is present for you right
now noticing whatever is there beginning to turn
inwards [Music] noticing your posture
you're balanced over your hip points if you need to make any adjustments take that last sip of tea before settling
into
meditation and softening the eyes perhaps closing them
and inviting a couple of longer slower breaths
deeper and letting go on the
exhale letting go of any EX excess stress anything it took to get here this
morning letting yourself rest and relax
here alert
now and then allowing the breathing to return to normal
letting your belly be
soft your face your forehead the muscles to open and relax
there letting the eyes be soft the
tongue turning your gaze
inward friendly greeting to all that's there
noticing whatever's in your [Music] room Ambient
[Music] sound the contact of your skin against
cloth or
air the feeling of being weighted
rooted supported by the chair or cushion
whatever is Beneath
You supported by this time together the sense of connection
attuning to the sensations of aliveness inside this
body the gentle motion of breathing at the belly or chest
maybe the broader field of sensations of
aliveness transpiration in the body
whatever [Music] form Vitality takes in this body
today and then
resting resting in
that I'll give brief instructions some mindfulness of
breathing but feel free to adapt adapt them to wherever your practice is
today allowing your attention to be
supported by the Rhythm the wave of the INB breath and the out
breath
noticing all the details staying in
contact with the full experience of breathing in the beginning
of the in breath the middle the fullness at the
top of the in breath
and then taking pleasure and the release of the
exhale relaxing
noticing that still point at the end of the
exhale and resting in it for a moment before the in breath naturally
emerges again
allowing yourself to be
nourished by this life's Breath by this
moment we'll practice in silence for a
while
e
e e
and in the last remaining moment of this
meditation consider turning the internal gaze back over this
period of practice
together with appreciation
whatever unfolded these moments of cultivating
connection with your
experience of building the capacity for
attention awareness being with a flow of the
present
moment and then turning that internal gaze
outward or it's the others in your life the others in this meditation
session as well included
and taking a moment to wish them
well may they be happy safe from inner and outer
harm peaceful and
free and may our practice here together be a cause and
condition for greater love wisdom and Clarity in our
lives all of the lives we touch and all of the lives they touch
Rippling outwards and outwards may all beings know the joy and
happiness of s safety Peace and
[Music]
Freedom thank you for your practice
e
e e
so dear sa here we are on Wednesday at least
those of us on this continent it's Wednesday
and offer a few Reflections on the theme of the week which
is cultivating qualities helpful for inner and interpersonal well-being but
especially focused on our our practice and our internal lives as I've mentioned sometimes the
Buddha would tell stories about difficult times and Society myths
often stories of the past and in each case he would recommend ways of making
the Dharma of making meditation practice our home our home land a place
of Peace no matter what's happening outside and in one of these teachings he
was talking to his most dedicated practitioners about ways that
practitioners can cultivate particular dhic kinds of flourishing including spiritual
empowerment or power inner beauty true
beauty happiness heart wealth and freedom and
yesterday we covered true beauty or virtue and today is
happiness so I'm happy to be teaching a little bit about dhic
happiness and I'll start out with a little personal anecdote this is from my
childhood as a little kid I loved two things horses and
reading active and not so active and I was a big reader I would
get completely totally immersed in books on these along road trips my family took
and are like old Buick station wagon the kind with the um wood grain on the side
and my parents would stop at some beautiful spot or um a rest stop a Vista
and they would get out of the car and be looking at this beautiful view and then they'd realize where's Dawn and they'd
have to go back and sort of like specifically jostle me awake so to speak
I was quite awake but I was completely immersed it was my happy
place and I say this because the kind of Happiness the Buddha talks about is a
form of complete absorption in the moment complete absorption in
meditation and that kind of absorption is available at one level or
another to all of us this kind of collected mind this complete immersion in what is
happening so that was my first taste of a collected mind when I was I don't know six
whatever the Buddha describes this kind of Happiness of being absorbed in
meditation as being a skillful pleasure wholesome pleasure a pleasure not to be
feared but to be embraced and this this is the happiness
of samade collectedness a sense of being gathered
together unified what some people would call concentrated though I don't really like that
word aaga or aaga aaga is the poly word for Unity and
it's used both to describe harmonious group
deliberation conversation cooperation and unifying in
meditation and this is not an accident there's no coincidence here I don't
think somehow integrating harmonizing with ourselves brings a kind of joy
interpersonally and personally that shared
present oh this doesn't mean huffing and puffing to get to a certain kind of
meditative state to get concentrated instead it's softening into the moment
softening into embracing being held by embodied
experience in fact the Buddha learned that the opposite being hard on himself
striving practicing austerities and self-denial didn't work so well
there's a story he tells from prior to his Awakening about practicing this kind of
self-denial austerity practice it was actually common in the time of the
Buddha and he had practiced denying himself so much being so assiduous so
dedicated that eventually he was on the brink of starvation and too weak to move and
ended up kind of lying in the grass by the side of the road and people mistook him for dead so they were just walking
on by but he was conscious barely and Along Came so The Story Goes
a woman suato going to the day's work in the
fields and she had with her some rice porridge or rice GRL not entirely
certain exactly what it was but it some sort of liquid based on rice that was more more sustaining than just
milk and she saw him and she could tell that he was just barely alive and out of
kindness out of compassion she knelt beside him and she cradled his head in
her hands and fed him her own meal for the
day sip by Sip and eventually nourished he came to
just a little bit I imagine he sat up he thanked her somehow they parted ways and
so nourished the Buddha sat in meditation again that
day and perhaps it was the kindness The Compassion the connection perhaps it was
the food I suspect it was both but his meditation was
infused with this nourishment and that kind of positive
Association we sometimes have with feeling good in the moment after a good meal after sustaining
ourselves he had this memory from when he was a young
boy and in this memory he's sitting in the shade of a rose apple tree at his
parents estate and looking out over the fields and it's harvest time in the fields and he's comfortable and seeing
his father and the other people and the working these fields and he falls into
this very natural very present state of being absorbed completely
attuned with the moment content at
ease and as this memory arose a kind of wisdom voice came this
is pleasure and this is a pleasure that's not to be feared not to be denied not to be pushed
away but instead to be cultivated that it's onward
leading and it was this moment the Buddha describes where he went away from the practices of
self-denial of striving too hard and into the middle
way a way of embracing meditative pleasure and contentment as an onward leading this
sort of a natural absorption and presence to be a a Hallmark a signal for
that things are going well in the practice right
now so allowing your practice to be infused with this kind
of kindness natural presentence
contentment easeful complet completely natural absorption is a form of meditative
happiness and is a form of onward leading meditative growth so I want to name here in a
technical sense absorption can refer to very specific kind of rarified
meditative States I've talked about that in the past on this program um you can look
back I believe it was last year this morning we're going to talk
more about the broader forms of Happiness addressed
available by meditation and Sade well short of any concentration
State this experience of beginning to gather together this coherence begins to invite joy happiness
ease contentment even early on in
practice trick is to notice moments of it notice
glimmers of it and appreciate it without grabbing onto it grabbing
onto it makes go away so that
noticing initially feeling good in meditation being absorbed in meditation
can start to feel like being carried Along on a stream
momentum and it can be helpful to notice or um sort of compare it to reference
points from other parts of your life so immersion wholehearted
engagement can happen when riding a horse jogging swimming playing an
instrument even programming on a computer it can even be available
sometimes short order Cooks if you look at a really skilled short order cook they're just totally in the
flow everything's happening and they're meeting it as it's happening nothing is extra no
distractions this creates a sense of the self sustaining momentum what chent
miali called flow and it's not so
different than momentum in meditation practice
and it can take a little while to get there for example in riding a horse which I did as a kid and a
teenager there could be a lot of kind of bouncy effort initially and it can take real
mindfulness to begin to connect and find a rhythm but then when the Rhythm emerges
there's this effortlessness this unification of Horse and Rider
the Buddha likened skill and samama to a mind like a well-trained Thor
bread and as this happens even glimpses of it tiny glimpses bring up
Joy this Rhythm can show up as an ease with connecting to attention and then
sustaining it putting your hand on a cat and stroking it as an example Gill
sometimes uses that sustaining staying with the
moment is stroking the cat and as this happens the mind and
body can begin to purr it can bring along Happiness joy kind of a thrill
even a simple kind of joy of being present at times the heart lighting up
with confidence or appreciation
it can also feel like the glow after a good laugh or soften into
contentment like dipping into perfectly temperatured water on a warm
day this softens down even to Serenity a sense that just to be alive is
enough just to be alive is enough so to say that experiences of
meditative happiness joy flow are available to each of us in different
ways it can be as individual as your fingerprint so there's no need to look
for it like something you've read or heard about just trust trust glimpses of
contentment ease joy happiness whenever it arises
in meditation and in life it's onward leading and it's nourishing to a
practice so thank you all very much for listening to my little wrap about
meditative happiness and um I'll offer the reference for this in the chat at the
very end um meanwhile notice notice little glimpses of happiness in your day
or in your practice moments of ease or contentment and appreciate
them and I'll see you tomorrow to talk about heart wealth thank you for your
kind attention