good evening good evening maybe we'll start the recording oh you did
already nice to see you all so tonight I'm going to continue on
this series of talks that I'm doing on like how how much effort do we need to
apply to our practice like how do we not only our practice but to everything that we're doing in our lives how do we like
choose a direction and have this sustained effort many different uh elements
there two weeks ago I talked about these um these five factors of endeavoring
these five factors of that contribute to like doing stuff and the Buddha talked about this
and um these five factors are confidence Vitality Integrity energy and wisdom and
we we can cultivate these and bring them to support us in our whatever it is that
we're wishing to do and then last week I talked a little
bit about um or I gave this story of about Prince bod was somebody who didn't
want to make effort in practice he just wanted to have all the fruits of practice but didn't want to make any
effort didn't want to apply himself maybe partly because he thought it would be nothing but painful you I have to say
if I had that idea I wouldn't want to do it either but then um the Buddha gave him
some teachings that were about this idea of resolve like you have to have a certain amount of resolve
Adana and then I un to that a little bit what does that mean and then today I'd
like to like build on that and it's perfectly fine if you weren't there for the earlier talks but what are some of
the things that get in the way we might hear these talks like okay sounds great
but uh how do I I just how do I do it I can't quite get myself to do
it so I want to this might be another series I'm not sure we'll start with a
little bit here and we'll we'll see how it goes but uh but there's so many things
that like why don't we accomplish the things that we want to accomplish why
don't we achieve the things that we want to achieve why don't we get to where we
want to go there's a lot of things there and I'm just going to like touch
the surface on I'm not going to be able to answer everything of course not but um I want to talk a little bit about
something that the Buddha talked about as supports for this type of
thing and so what are some of the reasons why one is it's
hard and there's this thing about you know trying to do something that's difficult just of course by definition
requires that we get out of our comfort zone that we do something we can like
stretch our sense of capacity our sense of capabilities our sense of what we can
do it's you know to make a shift in this direction or to go further than we've
gone before it takes some effort and it's not easy and so it's not it's it's
often a habit that when we realize that uh or maybe it's not
even we realized when we encounter some difficulties then we just like maybe
turn towards distraction just go do something else that's uh not as
difficult or not as uh demanding or maybe we'll just try to comfort ourselves maybe if it feels like
oh uncomfortable to feel like oh this is is hard I'm going to go eat some bon
bons or Doritos or whatever it might be or I'm going to you know just watch
another YouTube video or turn on Netflix or whatever it might be so this distraction or comforting ourselves is
you know something that maybe even without really understanding why we're doing it it's so easy to just slip right
into that you might have even say and I've I know I've said this a number of times but you know our society really
promotes this here you'll feel better watch this click
here you know buy that you know it's all about
this but there's this thing about maybe you've heard about it the first Noble
Truth right Buddhist teachings there are
difficulties that's the it's just the way the human EXP experience is it
doesn't have to mean we're a bad person it doesn't have to mean that we're terribly failing it doesn't have to mean
that we shouldn't do that it doesn't have to mean anything when we encounter
difficulties it's just difficult and this is the first Noble
truth the truth of Dua and many of you know right Dua we
has this wide range that we can translate it as as not just mildly
irritating seem just you know a little bit annoying to just awful beyond
belief and there's this way in which we might sometimes
think well I shouldn't ever get sick I shouldn't ever have injuries I shouldn't
ever feel disappointed I shouldn't have obstacles to the things that I want I
shouldn't have to confront death my own death or the people those that I love
and care about so often we can slip into this thinking that uh I wish there weren't
any DOA I hope there won't be any dooka this also is part of the human
experience and we might even say it's a biological like a maybe a
Evolution supported this idea that we're not always thinking about everything that's going to go wrong instead we have
this certain optimism that allows us to not always be focusing on
that but this way in which we often have this idea that I shouldn't have
Dua there shouldn't be Dua at all then there's a way in that we become
disillusioned or maybe just kind of run out of steam
when what it is that we're aspiring for when it is some something that we
want a direction we want to go and it turns out to be tough and maybe it's not even tough
maybe it's just uncomfortable and then what just kind of
dissipates right our energy or our
enthusiasm but I think all of us have this uh recognition too that if we're
not facing or accepting in some kind of way that
there are difficulties and the difficulties just increase they don't go
away exclusively or only just because that we're ignoring them or burying our
head in the sand or or something like this there's this way that this uh Dua
increases unless we have this way that we can turn towards it and acknowledge
yes this is hard yes this is uncomfortable yes this is Dua yes this
is awful it might be awful and there's something that happens
when we turn towards it not because it's exactly what we want
maybe it's exactly what we don't want but there's this way to kind of like stop the denying to stop the turning
away and just to turn towards like Yep this I want to say
sucks because right that's sometimes how it is but there is this way in which we can
turn towards these things with a certain amount of courage or a certain amount of like thoughtfulness and some awareness
and attention and the budha talked about this the poly word is
kti I'm going to translate it here as this tolerance this willing to stand when
there's discomfort able to with withand discomfort withstand
Dua and so this way like through the dooka the difficulty the
uncomfortableness is not just trying to fix everything out there like we are
always trying to fix everything out there and doesn't work so well right we can't just do this never ending fixing
manufacturing manipulating creating trying to get everything just right it doesn't
work so instead the focus is on our
relationship to the Dua we can't make all Dua go away this is part of life no
escaping but we can affect our relationship to it I think this is a big part of what
the Buddha is pointing to when he talks about this first Noble Truth there is Dua let's not
pretend let's not uh you know wish that it were different and
let's not blame ourselves when for every single difficulty I'm not saying that we
don't have a role but there's a way we often can slip into this inner critic that gets really loud whenever there's
some difficulties like I must be doing something wrong if I'm
uncomfortable difficulties are just difficulties and so this CTI this
tolerance is this tolerance of it's like adjusting our attitude towards suffering
this willing to have some tolerance to be able to withstand when there's some
difficulty because the alternatives are to when we have this uh Dua is that we
might respond with a this uh I think there's this expression like the nashing
of the teeth kind of like the Wailing you're like no not me I don't want it
that happens but the trick here is maybe like not to get stuck
there because then you're stuck so in rather than this lamentation
or this wailing or rather than um just getting caught and maybe there's some
terrible Injustice there and sometimes we can get stuck there and just with the
uh with the Dua I'm not saying that there aren't injustices
I'm saying that the can we not get stuck there can we say yes this is an
injustice and being able to step away and being able to have a relationship
with it as opposed to just being completely subsumed with it as opposed to feelings of dejection or Gloom or
misery or some of these things that humans we like to do kind of like collapse into some of the
difficulties and so so kti this tolerance tolerance of difficulty is
this way that we can cultivate and develop or our capacity to be with
difficulties develop our capacity to be with hard
stuff and it turns out we can train this up we can intentionally and sometimes it
happens unintentionally just because lots of uncomfortable things me come our way
but you might even say that there's this way in which uh meditation
practice helps support uh being with Dua because meditation is not always you
know perfect or fun or Blissful but there's a way which like
okay I wish that Ding timer would go off I wish that Bell would go off or whatever it might be just to notice like
H I don't want to be here it's like oh yeah this is this is
uncomfortableness maybe feel into it what is it feel like feels like there's energy in the
legs like I want to bolt or maybe there's a lot of spinning in the mind like oh my gosh this is never going to
end but just to be able to notice like okay this is uncomfortable and I'm just
going to sit here until the bell rings I'm not going to sneak a look at my watch I'm just going
to sit until the Bell Rings this is a minor hopefully it's minor in the grand
scheme of things but don't underestimate how powerful this can be to just
practice here like okay this is uncomfortable can I just be here with
the uncomfort without slipping into the all the things that we can slip
into it's quite something it's how something that we do
maybe that's not the greatest difficulty but we do it again and again really can have a big
impact I know I've given this uh story a number of times but uh this is uh was so
clear for me before I started meditating I was doing some yoga
and um a style of yoga I did all kinds of styles but this one in particular was Yin Yoga where you take a pose and you
hold it for a long time in the beginning the pose is comfortable and you're like this is nice yeah great look at me I'm
doing yoga and then one minute two minutes five minutes seven and just the
body does not like it and uh a yoga teacher she I didn't know it at the time
but she also was a a meditation teacher and she was uh here in the Buddha Dharma as well and she'd
be giving little mini Dharma talks while we're like sitting there in agony it was great it just helped me so
much to realize okay that was uncomfortable and I survived it and I
could stretch afterwards and you know shake it off and it was okay just like after meditation you can stand up and
open your eyes and it's okay just that little bit of confidence
so that the next time when I was uh having a difficult conversation with one
of my co-workers I kind of recognized like oh yeah this is uncomfortable but I've done this before
I can do this again and the same way this meditation
practice sometimes we if we're sitting at home we might have the habit of like oh I'm done I want to be done I'm just
going to get up and do whatever I want to do but to just stay and to recognize
izee yeah this is uncomfortable and stay anyways stay anyways or just get to the
cushion maybe you don't even want to you know sit maybe it's the last thing you want to do but like okay this is
difficult not what I want to do but I'm going to do it anyway it's easy to be dismissive of
these small minor things yeah yeah yeah okay we're supposed to meditate all the
time but this is exactly how we kind of gain confidence and stretch our capacity
with difficulties is by being with
difficulties and so there's this way with meditation that we can like tune in
and allow ourselves not to fall into overwhelm that we can kind like be with the experience and realize oh it's not
what I chose but it's okay it's okay
kti this idea of Tolerance this tolerance of a some of
difficulties so I want to say something about what tolerance is
not because there's a way in which we might slip into or think that it's a way
in which we have this uh this passive acquiescence like kind of like this
collap like okay you know instead of like kind
of sitting up with it and being like this is difficult and I'm going to be with it so K is not this passive kind of
like just disconnection it's not like just acquiescing instead it's like no this is
difficult and I'm going to be here as best I can it's also not like cowardice it's
not the wayway of uh running away or pretending it's not there
and nor is it a typee of a denial that it's difficult we're not trying to
pretend that it's different we're not saying ah it's not so bad it's like no this actually is
uncomfortable and that's okay and that's
okay so there's this um poem that talks about this a little
bit and um I love this poem because has a little bit of Whimsy has a little bit
of biochemistry in it right I love biochemistry of course and uh it also
has truth in it right of course so here's this poem it's
called I mean how can you go wrong with a title like this self-portrait as root
[Laughter] vegetable self-portrait as root vegetable by Rosemary traumer she's a
lovely poet she's uh a practitioner and a lot of her poems have to do with
practice it's a very short poem and it goes like this it's science of course how the
sugars in beets will caramelize when heated a process that includes
conversion condensation dehydration collisions and the formation of thousands of volatile
compounds and though it's not simple and though this process of sweetening is not
fully understood sweetening happens every
time is it wrong this gives me hope for other hard and bitter
things just asking the question already I feel myself begin to
soften I'll read it again self-portrait is root vegetable by Rosemary
trummer it's science of course how the sugars and beets will caramelize when
heated a process that includes conversion condensation dehydration
collisions and the formation of thousands of volle compounds and though it's not simple and
though this process of sweetening is not fully understood sweetening
happens every time time is it wrong this gives me hope for
other hard and bitter things just asking the question already
I feel myself begin to soften you can see how she has like this
shift in this relationship to hard and bitter things she's saying okay beats
when you cook them you apply some warmth to them you give them some attention
then they shift they change just like keeping this in mind and they shift and
change towards some sweetening What's happen if we apply some warmth and some attention to other
things in our lives that are difficult maybe they're a little bit like beets maybe they'll sweeten maybe they
won't be delicious but they will shift and something that I also
appreciate about this uh poem is that Rosemary Traer or the poet the person in
this poem the protagonist is H keeps in mind that
things change this is a key Insight right that things change there's this inconstancy
there's impermanence things are changing she saiding oh yeah beats change they used to be hard and bitter
and they become sweeter maybe other things can and then this way of like
just asking the question is a way of of no longer being lost in the difficulty
of what's happening but remembering oh yeah things change and there can be a
different relationship here it can sweeten so Rosemary traumas with love
the self-portrait as a root vegetable so I think that part of like
so tolerance is this uh kti is this um
recognition that there is suffering the first Noble Truth and of course the third Noble Truth is there is not
suffering there's an there's the absence of suffering and then the fourth is there's a path leading to this sensation
of suffering many of you will know that the first step and the eight-fold path is
Right View and Right View includes the four noble truths so the beginning of this
path this beginning of the this uh path towards Awakening includes Right
View we could say it's the beginning or we could also say that maybe Right View is the most important that's why it's
first just to have this recognition that there are things that lead towards suffering and there's things that don't
lead towards suffering and this is like a primary differentiation in our practice that we can work
with so why is it that sometimes it's hard to do things because it's hard
hard and hard is hard difficulties are
difficult but there's another reason well there's lots of reasons but one other thing I'd like to talk about and
this also is the same poly word kti is that like if we have an
aspiration and we have this direction in which we want to go it takes
time these things take time of course we want instant gratification a of course we want things to be the way that we
want them to be as soon as they can be and so this word kti also can be
translated as patience because there's this way in
which we are impatient impatience arises when when
let's say we're standing in line wherever it might be and then this
imagination out of nothing creates complete imagination a different scenario in
which we're not standing in that line just creates something an idea maybe we're sitting at a beach maybe we're
driving our car maybe we're doing whatever and super imposes it onto what's actually
happening and we get irritated this is
impatience and patience is this sense that things have to be different they should be different
this wanting things to be different but it's usually just based out of something we imagined and then we compare it to
what our experience is and we don't like the comparison so we kind of like have this
wish or maybe even insistence that uh it be different somehow but there's this way in which we
are impatient and I've noticed this myself I was kind of like watching myself when I was impatient in a very
long line not too long ago actually the line was wasn't so long it was like you know one person there was one person in
front of me and then the person FR of them was spending a long time with the person that the
clerk and I was watching myself have a little bit of impatience and there's this way I
noticed there's a feeling of um intolerance right the opposite of kti
like this shouldn't be happening there's also a little bit of
like resentment kind of like slips in there too a little bit of anger a little bit of ill will like why are you making
me wait don't you realize I have to do X Y and Z still or you know
something so impatience gets in the
way gets in this way of being a this more sweetening that we
might say about this relationship we could have with the difficulty that's happening
and instead like when there's a certain amount of impatience there's this this
uh um contraction and there isn't a sense of openness there's like we can't
really be open to other ideas or other views we're just kind of collapsed into
this rigidness of uh intolerance and within is this little insinuation that you know somehow we're
Superior or something this isn't the direction towards more
freedom but instead patience this way to stick with
things even when they take a long time to show
results I think patience is one of these unsung qualities for everything
especially in Buddhist practice we don't talk about it so much it's not in that many lists it's it's a
parmy and um as one of the parmes this means we could translate the word parmy as
Perfection and it means that it's connected with Liberation It's associated with Liberation and with
compassion and so patience is a way in which we are open to what's actually
happening and we are having the willingness to do what needs to be done
however long long it takes to be done and this is what leads to
freedom freedom from anything really freedom from whatever it is that
we're trying to get away from that we feel Shackled by takes
time everything takes time learning new things takes time doing things differently changing
kind of like the way that we often our default thinking takes time of course it is
so when we have this sense of patience there's a way that we are just focusing
on what we're doing in this moment we're letting the next moments take care of
themselves but instead we're working on this moment here maybe not working on
we're allowing it to be we're being present for what's happening right now
it's just part of patience you can see or this is part of Tolerance too the same word canti we're just like
okay this is this experience I'm standing here thinking that my maybe
that this shouldn't take so long just to do this simple thing that that I'm standing in line for but it seems like
it's taking an awfully long time and just like oh I can have patience I don't have to whip out my
phone and entertain myself I can just be here it's
okay it's not my favorite thing it's not so
bad have some of this tolerance of the present
moment otherwise we right we have the mind is Think Like when is this going to end and if this weren't happening then I
could do this right there's this way in which that we can get in spinning of the mind but just to kind of stand with our
bodies and with our minds Sy to be there there's also a way that patience
also F has this focus on consistency just showing up again we
didn't get the results we wanted we're not finished yet well we'll do it
again we'll do it again whatever needs to be done we'll just do it
again and again and
again but this recognition right that all these again aren't exactly the
same there's some parts of them that may seem similar but we all know this that
uh probably you take showers regularly but not every single shower is exactly
the same maybe the water temperature is different the duration is different how long you stand there rinsing your hair
or whatever it might be something that we do over and over and over again it's not always exact exactly the
same in the same way for some consistency with our meditation practice
or whatever practice it is that we're doing is a way in which um we can
understand or interpret this what it means to be patient and then maybe something else
that I will talk about uh patience is there's a way in which uh p
patience and not being angry kind of like go together I like this uh one
author Dale write he writes um impatience and anger are not the same
but they live in the same neighborhood idea right impatience and
anger right they have that simmering quality to them and one way in which
they are related is that that they're not opposite so
much but when we're angry we can't be patient and when we're impatient We
Can't Be Without Anger like when there's an impatient we're creating the conditions for
anger and so there's a way in which to as a support for patience may kind like
just notice our anger notice like what is it that uh gets us irrit ated even if
we're not completely angry but that you know like gets under our skin and is there a way that we can
learn to tolerate things getting under our
skin it won't lead to anger if we practice kti it also like supports some
patience and some perseverance and doing things again and again and this helps
lead us towards our aspirations whatever it is that we want to do with our lives
what's important for us what's meaningful for
us of course I could say that mindfulness is a is a support for this
too just being aware of what's happening in our
experience so what is it that kind like gets in the way when we have this we set
out we want to do something we have a goal a direction we want to go and we don't do it one of the reasons is maybe
there's not quite enough Cy tolerance and patience these are
things that often we don't think about we think about like oh I just have to be better organized or I don't know there's
all these you know obvious things that uh we think we should do but I think that some of these qualities are really
the unsung heroes of practice the and the the beautiful thing
about them is that they can be increased it's not like we arrive with factory
settings that can't be changed instead right we can stretch our
capacity so kti this uh one of the parames that the Buddha talked about can
help us with Adana with resolve and it can help us with this
um exertion or striving or working towards something that we it's important
to us and with that I'll open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments beautiful talk very clear and helpful um one of my achilles heal I
have more than one is being impatient and I just wanted to share a comment or
guidance that Gil gave me once and because I talked to him I'm like I'm so impatient and he said uh be impatient
with impatience and it works it works fantastic because as soon as I start on
the cycle it seems like somehow that energy of being impatient with it stop
DRS it it's really interesting so I thought I'd share that little I love it
nugget thank you thank you being impatient with
impatience thank you Catherine yeah anybody else have a comment or
question okay well I wish you all a good evening and safe travels home thank
you