good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all yes you're welcome to move wherever you'd like to be
comfortable and so tonight I'd like to um Begin by talking a little about this
story yes I was uh while I was meditating I was thinking this Buddha
has this uh right with one uh hand down and um the the story behind that is
that oops is that the Buddha he had this um
idea that he wanted to sit and he was not going to move until he became awakened after he had uh renounced kind
of like all these indulgences and aestheticism he had made up his mind okay I'm going to sit and meditate and
I'm not going to move until I become awakened so with a a tremendous amount
of determination and resolve he sits down sorts meditating many of you might
know the story and then Mara shows up now who is Mara Mara it sounds like the
is the is the microphone going in and out no no okay maybe it's just
me that uh so Mara is uh tried to enticed the Buddha tried to you know get
him to not become awakened so I enticed him with things that he thought oh there
we go this microphone I'm going to use another microphone I think that's yeah
this one's just problematic
how is this sound does this this microphone work is it is it on I think so yeah it is on okay I'll use this
one so tries to entice the Buddha with you know all these beautiful things that
people humans get enticed by and when that didn't well that's one version of the story another version of the story
is that Mara attacked the Buddha with 10 different armies and these different armies uh
stand for different qualities that could cause a person to not become
awakened so to say a little bit about Mara I wouldn't say that he's a Satan IC
character sometime he's more he just doesn't want people to become awakened
so he'd be perfectly happy if humans were just rolling around in a sensal
pleasure all day every day so he has no interest in people going to hell or anything like that instead he would
prefer you know that they just have a certain amount of complacency but they just don't practice
or you know don't do anything like that so this is the mara character and he shows up in a number of different
settings um often like disguised as somebody else and then the the Buddha
will say I see you Mara and then Mara goes away and the nuns Mara shows up
tries to uh entice some of the nuns to no longer practice and they always see
him and say I see you Mara and then he goes away but what I want to talk about
tonight is uh one of these uh armies that get sent to the kind of
dissuade the Buddha from practicing and in particular you know can we turn up
that volume just a tiny bit I feel like I'm I'm having to project my voice and this will only last for so long and then
I'll lose my voice yeah so maybe that's yeah there we go thank
you so there's a very creative individual I appreciate this so much his
name is aan Kun Adamo he's a monk at the Forest River Arrow River Arrow River
Forest Hermitage in Northern Ontario Canada he's in the aan cha lineage and
he wrote stories about this for modern
audiences modern being I think he wrote These in the early 2000s I think if he
had wrote them like this last year he would it would include a lot of texting and YouTube WR you know something like
this but it doesn't include that so these stories are of Mara
writing letters to his 10 different armies like encouraging them like here's
how to dissuade this Buddha character and not only the Buddha character I would say actually the letters are set
in modern times so how to just it didn't work for the Buddha but maybe Mara and
his armies can suade us today and it's uh written kind of uh
it's well in this particular one it's a little bit harsh the uh language that uh
Mar that aanad puts into the mouth of
Mara so these are letters from Mara there are 10 letters and um I'm just
going to read one as an introduction to uh what I want to talk about tonight
so uh here's the letter goes my sixth Army so the sixth Army is the army of
cowardice so this is Mara writing to the members of this Army who encourage
cowardness and others my sixth Army you have a special
place in the task of keeping beings in a state of bondage
you weaken the being whom you attack and render them vulnerable to my terrible
aspect I prefer to charm and Delight but I will tolerate No opposition and those
few who fail to be seduced must be terrorized into submission so this is
Mara saying you know I'd rather just make a humans just be seduced into doing
something that feels good and never practicing or anything like that but for those people who won't do that he's what
does he say he wants to terrorize us into submission so then uh he continues and
he says physical cardice is useful in its place but it is the spiritual and
moral type of cowardice that is most suitable for our
purposes being must be koled into clutching at a sense of
security this this is the trick we must play of course you and I know there is
no security but and all beings are subject to the awful realities of birth sickness
old age and death but no matter the dream of security may be a hopeless one
but it is powerful being everywhere are afraid to
risk what they have and can be reduced to spiritual impetus by that that
fear encourage them often to not take
risks if they risk they may grow and if they grow they may awaken so it takes great courage to
plunge into the voidness and this we can undermine this is after all the golden
age of cowardice we can encourage the humans to
make a virtue of their cardice they can call it Prudence or
they can call it responsibility they will get up every morning and put on their hats and take
the subway to their dull grind of a job and carefully planned for their retirement and by that time they'll be
so beaten down that they will slide easily and thoughtlessly the rest of the
way to the Grave ouch this is kind of harsh this is
kind of harsh you know I kind of like this creative way way he's putting it but uh so this uh
auno up there in Canada when he's writing these letters he's having Mara
saying that um being must be ConEd into clutching at a sense of
security we all want to have a sense of security we want to feel safe of course we do and I'm going to talk about this a
little bit more but part of this is the clutching part you know like this holding on so
tightly we all know that holding on tightly is not the way to Greater Freedom doesn't matter what you're
holding on just the whole activity of just um clinging clutching is not the
way towards greater freedom and there's this way we can say
clutching at a sense of security that we might say that we clutch at wanting to
feel comfortable all the time not willing to maybe like take some risks or
do something a little bit different or maybe even to recognize that we don't
control as much as we think we do or to
recognize that you know old age sickness and death is you know nobody is immune
from this it's going to happen to all of us but instead we want to feel security
you know secure or I'll put in the word comfortable so we kind of like uh grab on to these things going to help us feel
comfortable able and then in this uh letter to his
army Mara saying encourage people to not take risks I'll talk a little bit more about
that uh this evening too but it's risky to take
risks right and sometimes we just don't feel like we want that we want things that are controllable and predictable
and you know we just want to go straight line and get whatever we want
but you know life doesn't unfold that way we all know that there's a part of us that recognizes that no matter how
much we might wish for things to be comfortable and predictable or
controllable at least and then this continues with encourage them to make a virtue of their
caradus I mean this is uh you know some of the things that maybe we hide behind
or um I mean this idea of being responsible of course is important and being prudent of
course is important but is there a way in which we hide behind that and not take a little
bit of risks or maybe not um feel some of the comfortable uncomfortableness
I'll talk a little bit more about that this evening so if we're not going to succumb
to uh Mara's Army of cowardness we might say it was to be to be
courageous to Have Courage so what what does that mean to
have courage we might say that it's the capacity to face
fear face uncomfortableness face fear including you know fear of
humiliation or danger or you know some of these things like this so it doesn't
have to be you know the obvious things that are fearful being accosted or natural
disasters or you know some of these things and I'll talk a little bit more
about that I feel like I'm saying that a lot I'll talk about this and I'm not actually talking about them yet but first I just want to def say a little
bit more about this whole idea of Courage because as long as human beings
have something to lose or have the idea that they have something to lose as long as High human
beings are exposed to uncertainty as long as human beings are exposed to risk
fear will be a part of the human
experience it's just part of The Human Experience if you if there were a life
that had absolutely no fear then and it was completely predictable and
controllable then that's actually a life of a God not of a
human so this is the experience that we are having as being a human so I would
say like the maybe the ideal for a human life is not the absence of fear but can
we meet it or work with it can we have some courage in these so many different
ways so the stereotypical idea of Courage of course is the superhero that
is uh standing up to the Beast this
um and maybe we might even say that the story that I just told about the Buddha
sitting down to meditate and uh Mara accosting him with all of his uh those
10 armies and the Buddha continues to sit Mara asks him who says that you can
get awakened and that when the Buddha touches the ground and says the Earth is my witness I I'm worthy I can I'm going to
become awakened so and so in Buddhism we have
this idea of this kind of stereotypical idea of what courage is
but we might say the part of Courage is having the
fear that's in proportion to the actual Danger
sometimes we fear we have a lot of fear for things that maybe aren't that
dangerous but you know our stories our life history all these things you know
sometimes these get out of proportion so part of Courage maybe is to
recognize it's maybe not so dangerous and I say that recognizing that that's
like a logical statement but so often when it comes to fear logic doesn't work
at least for me it doesn't I am much bigger than
spiders but I don't know they give I they I don't I can't explain it they don't uh scare me as much as they used
to but uh you know and I can co- with them but uh yeah there's a way in which
spiders kind of make me feel uncomfortable but you know logic says there's no reason for that whatsoever
so part of this practice a big part of I would say the Buddhist practice is um
this recognition of suffering difficulties Dua
uncomfortableness and then we might say that courage is is order to be with the
suffering to turn towards it to recognize it to acknowledge it so often
we want to turn away we want to avoid the suffering maybe it's due to fear maybe
it's due to Habit whatever the reason I think having
a certain amount of Courage is a way in which to like just turn towards Yep this
is Dua it's really terrible what's happening and to allow ourselves to
experience that in a way that feels appropriate not to tip us into overwhelm but in a way that acknowledges the truth
of what's actually happening without sugar coating or pretending that it's
different and to be sure I'm not saying that we have to like indulge in in uh
the difficulties and suffering there's beautiful things that are happening in the world as well so maybe if I to would
to broaden the statement I would say big part of practice is to see things as they really are the beautiful and the
Really the suffering but so often the suffering we bounce off of we I I kind
of like it like this like you know like when there when there's uh when there's a little bit of moisture on the finger
that hits a hot iron or something it's just this idea that we just jump right off so part of Courage is to be with
some of the difficulties to do anything that's different than our habitual turning away or or habitual
not even um acknowledging it maybe and so that turns
to this notion of the maybe just courage to overcome this pervasive but often not
really conscious for us fear in everyday
life this way that we to to notice and be sensitive to that there are things
are risky and fearful because humans are
vulnerable we are it's it's the truth we're vulnerable in so many ways
physical ways illness aging accidents disease all these
things certainly something the pandemic uh taught us right how many people died
it's heartbreaking that humans are vulnerable
and so risk is just an essential it's a a component of life it's just the way
that it is even though we often try to uh not acknowledge that but no matter
how confident we are no matter how Brave we are or no matter what privileges we
have in our life or privileges we don't have in our life risk is a part of the human
experience and so we are all aware of this of this risk and is there a way
that we can acknowledge that without collapsing without kind of
like shutting down without as um retreating you know um pulling back from
life can we have the courage to say yeah
things aren't controllable and predictable in the way that we would like and that's okay and that's
okay so often we think we need courage for these giant obvious things
but maybe we really need it for some of these everyday life things as well
we don't know guarantees about our health no guarantees about um car
accidents or these types of things it's quite
something but if we allow this the fear to be felt and then to maybe like
overtake us or scare us in a way that uh really
causes us to collapse then there's this way in which the these long-term effects of like just
perpetually feeling fear you know feeling afraid then we just start having this
inability to take risks this inability to be
Innovative in ability to be creative or inability to feel
deeply to feel our
emotions an inability to maybe like think independently have a mind of our
own as opposed to just uh following the group think or something like
this so This PR this practice is asking us to acknowledge their risks not to
pretend that they're not there and yet to meet them with what I'm calling
courage to meet them say yeah there are no
guarantees and to live a life fully
anyway and to grow and develop and cultivate wholesome qualities
anyway even though there aren't any
guarantees and so we might say that courage is needed
to feel Joy Joy or to experience
Beauty there's a way to say yes I'm aware of you know how things
are and I'm choosing to tune into and feel
Joy when it's available to experience the beauty and
be uplifted when the beauty is
available so maybe courage ends uh turns out to be something like uh avoiding
despair when we feel like there's no hope because sometimes this happens right we we experience loss we
experience failure that's part of the human experience it's
guaranteed and so there might be this way in which we' be tempted to as I said
kind of collapse or maybe just to close down and refuse to open up to any new
chances I know uh somebody it was really heartbreaking for
me to see that I just really loved uh his dog you know they they were just
Pals they were just uh friends you know just uh spend all this time together and
went for walks together and all these types of things and then the dog had ended up
with an autoimmune disease and Di died early oh it was so
sad and then a year later just in conversation with this individual was
like saying something about uh dogs it's like no no dogs die I'm never getting
one again it's like oh and then you know maybe two years later like nope I'm
never doing that again it's a heartbreak the heart the first heartbreak of um having this beloved family member die
but a second heartbreak of kind of like closing down and not being open to the joy that having a beloved pet can
bring so maybe courage is the capacity to avoid the despair when it feels
hopeless maybe courage is to instead of having this what wanting to close down
or be secluded or pretend to be or want to feel like
we're completely invulnerable trying to get rid of anything that might make us uh
vulnerable maybe courage is just uh instead kind like including the energy
to live our life to have a this um energy to make a
new beginning often this doesn't sound like something we would call courage but it
does take a certain amount of courage to allow the heart and the mind
to be open so you might say well how do we
develop courage how can we cultivate this so that it can be a part of our lives and help us to
meet this Human Experience
and sometimes um I'll say that Viria this is a poly word that often most often gets translated as
energy but it also can get translated as courage are is related to the word for warrior
and it's like you know somebody who does what a warrior does I guess you know goes into battle or something like this
but related to that is this um idea of Courage so then the question is well how do we cultivate
this first of all say there's a connection between courage and
Trust they're like really tightly uh weed and then the question naturally
arises well trust what what can we trust and this is maybe for all of us to
discover for ourselves rather than somebody saying here you know trust this and if you do
you're a good practitioner if you don't you're a bad practitioner or something like this I'll offer a few things that some
people find helpful and maybe they'll resonate for you and if they don't resonate for you just an encouragement
to find something that's like bigger than yourself that you feel like you can
trust so some people trust mindfulness they trust this idea okay if I can be
with the experience then it's not it's then it's going to be okay like it's not going to
uh um I'm not going to get blindsided by things or it's a if I can like be with
my bodily experience and know what my thoughts are doing then then I'm not going to tip into overwhelm so some
people trust just mindfulness practice some people have a regular
practice of taking the refuges refuge in budha Dharma and sa I haven't talked
about that so much um here on Monday nights those of you many of you may be
familiar with this but this is just uh this idea of I mean like orienting our
life we might say towards the Buddha we could say represents the potential for
awakening the Dharma the teachings that can help that Awakening and SAA other
practitioners that are such a important part of this practice so to like Orient
our life in that direction Buddha dharman SAA some people trust in uh the effects
of like meta practice doing some loving kindness
practice this warmhearted wish for good will for other people there's a way in
which uh and I can I speak from experience having done um certain amount of this doing regular L and kindness
practice just softens the heart and opens the mind and then there's just uh
less fear and more trust or
more connection Maybe with others less being closed something
like this some people have a devotional practice maybe they chant or bow or
light incense or make offerings or you know something like
this so an encouragement to see if there is something that trust that's bigger
than just you because I mean it's this Human Experience is not always easy and
it's nice to sometimes say you know what I don't actually know what to do next or
I don't I can't I don't have Clarity or I don't have energy or something and
then there's a way in which can we dare I say this word surrender to something
bigger than ourselves because there's a way in which if we feel like I have to
do everything myself that's exhausting and we just don't always have access to
that we don't always have the energy or the clarity or
the the wish to do that so one way courage is to develop
you know to feel into for you what is something that you can trust that's meaningful for you and that can help
with courage and bne brown some of you might
might know she's a best-selling author and has a a number of uh books she
writes courage is a habit a virtue you get it by doing
courageous X it's like you learn to swim by swimming you learn Courage by
couraging so are there some small little things that you know I don't really want to do this this makes me feel a bit
uncomfortable but to make friends with the spiders I'm speaking to myself is there
you know take small risks where the stakes are not very
high it's absolutely true that we start to gain a little bit you know more confidence if we take small risks
doesn't mean that everything's going to turn out great we might have some failures and some losses but often we learn the most from
those even though they tend they are the most uncomfortable but is there a way that you
can stretch yourself a little bit to act with courage when things are a little
bit frightening in a wise way of course it's so great to practice when
the stakes are low because there will be times in your life when the stakes will
be high maybe it's having a very difficult
conversation with somebody and it may take a lot of courage to say
what's needed to be said but having practiced in places where there's lower Stakes will make
that easier maybe the courage to say
goodbye you know loss is part of life
and people are we have to say goodbye in so many different ways
but to say it you know with a open heart and to meet what it is that driving to
say goodbye so we often we come to
meditation practice we come to uh this Buddhist practice thinking that it's going to lessen the difficulties we have
of course we do we come here think like okay this is going to make me feel better less stress or something like
this maybe we thinking we'll have some wisdom or some new understandings or maybe even some some cool meditative
experiences chances are that um whatever reason brought you here
tonight or to this practice in general you probably weren't thinking like okay I want to you know learn how to be more
courageous or something like that but I would say courage is a part
of meeting aspects of ourselves that maybe we haven't seen before seeing
parts of ourselves that maybe aren't so flattering I know that was hard for me
to realize oh yeah I really yeah I didn't handle that well at all you know
to just to see that whereas before I had felt like how dare they treat me this
way you know early in practice I kept on seeing all these aspects of myself that
weren't so flattering takes a certain amount of courage to admit that like oh
yeah I thought I was always in the right turns out I'm not as in the right all
the time so this idea of Courage is part of
practice this idea of not that we get to get rid of all
fear but that uh we don't allow it to shut us down or close us down but show
up anyway and that we can learn Courage by
couraging so with that I'll open it up to see if there's any questions and comments thank
you does anybody have something they'd like to say or question about
this this idea of Courage as a way to counter this Army of cowardice
is quite something he says could jol into clutching at a sense of security
like ouch I think all of us want to feel security right but is there a way that we're clutching so much that it's
inhibiting our growth or getting in our way and this is part of what it means to be wise right is to recognize okay what
risks are prudent which ones aren't
and can we stretch ourselves a little
bit maybe I I'll share that is there a question while it goes there I'll say
that um I was talking with Gil and he was encouraging me Dan you you should give uh talks without
notes I was like that's scary I I think I'm going to do this so um I'm
I'm not here next week but uh I I'm gonna do some without notes so we we'll
see how that goes this is Diana trying to be brave have some courage so yes
your comment um yeah I was just going to say I really enjoyed the talk this evening um I think two aspects and then
I had a question so the first aspect I really like the story about the man and his dog um
it just it reminded me a lot and maybe a lot of people had this experience like I remember when I was in a very serious
relationship and I was like oh no never again I never want to feel lost again and you know and like then later I Found
the courage to um so but it took a tremendous amount of courage to like open yourself up to vulnerability again
um so I thought that really resonated with me and then the second part too was speaking about um brne Brown um and a
lot of her talks and her her her research on on courage and vulnerability
um I think it's incredibly powerful but I was I was sort of curious like how
does this practice um help one cultivate courage I'm just trying to figure out I
I think that there's a there there but I just I'm not exactly how how they're so
interrelated yeah that's a great question and I didn't uh lay out a lot of things specifically but one thing
I'll just say here is um there's a number of things we can do
and one is this raft practice that I've uh talked about before R is recognize so
recognize like oh wow there's a lot of fear a is to allow like allow it and
it's just like okay the fear is here like not to push it away just to recognize it's here and then the third f
is to feel it in the body this turns out to be enormously powerful to feel the
lump in the throat to feel the restlessness the wish to run away to feel whatever it is there's a way in
which when we feel in the body makes it a little bit more tangible and it's not quite as um scary it's just an
uncomfortable bodily sensation the mind is going to be making up all kinds of stories and we let the mind just do what
it we just let the Mind do what it wants to and we're just going to focus on the
bodily experience the fear and then might be um helpful
to um feel like the pressure of whatever you're sitting on or feel your feet on
the ground so that you feel grounded and this is a tremendous way great way to like meet fear so raft recognize allow
feel in the body and then the T I'm going to say is trust and the trust here
is trust that you don't have to fix it at precisely this moment fix fix it
another moment but precisely this moment you're just going to recognize allow and
feel in the body and this is a great way to meet things that are
scary thank you you're welcome anybody else have a comment oh
yes over
here thank you so much for the talk it really resonated um and I think talk now
like taking risk of fear of public humiliation um so the question I had is
um why do we have this clinging towards security or really this need for
security when logically there is no security but still there is that need
that somehow even in old age I need to plan things I'm sorry I missed the last part
the uh like in old age even though logically I know there is no security but there is this oh I need to plan
things so that bad things don't happen but I know they're going to happen anyway but that need is always there to
somehow cling to security I don't have the answer to this
like why I don't know why humans do this I know that we do it seems logical that if I had to
guess I would say evolutionary biology those individuals that survived the
saber Tigers Etc were the ones that planned and you know and were able to
protect themselves and so this is something that we've inherited but um I don't have a good
answer exactly why maybe also say that logic turns out not to be as persuasive
as we think it should be right I so you know things that are logical but we see
humans doing illogical things all the time just and I would say like why
because they feel uncomfortable and they'll just want to do anything to feel more comfortable and sometimes that what
they're doing to feel more comfortable is just illogical this is this is my
assumption yeah thank
you thank you that was wonderful um talking about couraging so um I res it a
lot with the way you express the concept of just acknowledging the fear that
you're going through so for example I'm going through a difficult phase in my life right now and just acknowledging
that yeah and being with it versus trying to say no hey everything's fine
so acknowledging it and then respecting it and then somewhat to your point surrendering to you to it in a regular
basis and trusting there's something else out there that will take care of it at some point point I think uh that
really resonated and uh maybe one just thought is a book that I have been
reading which has been really helpful in that is a a book called The Surrender experiment oh and that is literally the
theme of the book which is how do you surrender every day oh very interesting
and who's the author Michael Singer oh okay great thank you the surrender
experiment great great thank you thank you thank
you I have time maybe for one more comment or
sure I forget what I do do I hold it do something just talk yeah you said having your feet on the
ground or something like that um well I when I was breaking up with a boyfriend
all I had to do was stand that's feet on the ground for sure and then I could express myself because I'm didn't
here you know it's amazing right how our bodily
posture what an impact it has yeah yeah great thank you thank
you okay so thank you all and I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening thank
you