Hello friends hello and welcome to uh the 7 a.m. called the 7 A.M sit and uh
talk and um good morning good afternoon good evening wherever you are in the
world lovely to be with you today so we're going to continue uh our
uh theme um of exploring trust um confidence sad Let's uh let's
begin by sitting together and I introduce a meditation related to the be
so so let us arrive let us
land let us land right here right now in our bodies in this moment in
time letting go what from whatever has arisen before in this moment
and connecting with the sensations of the body connected to the Earth rooted to
the Earth present alive for this limited
time here this precious moment of being alive
knowing this body from the inside it's only I can do I can do only
I can know this body intimately from the inside nobody else
can getting to know sense feel the sensations
of touch contact with the earth and the sensations of the breath
intimately letting go of thoughts and memories and we can pick him up later we can pick
him up later but right now
connecting with the breath calming soothing we know connecting with the
breath can be calming and soothing we know this we know why do we forsake the
breath for others for thoughts and distractions and worries In This
Moment no need Dear Heart no need dear mind don't forsake yourself
relaxing and being connected mindful fully mindful of the breath in breath
and out breath to calm the
mind bring Clarity of knowing Clarity of vision
one birth at a
time
e e
softening relaxing the body the heart connecting with the breath no knowing
the breath in breath out breath calming
soothing and the more we know the breath we stay with the breath Ana panas Sati
mindfulness of the
breath the more settled our mind becomes our heart becomes
more clarity we have to see what is happening in our heart space
mind space we know this the more we see it in action it
brings more confidence trust in ourselves in the
practice so simple so simple knowing the
breath calming the mind selling the
heart relax and receive the breath every single breath in and
out
e
e e
knowing the breath knowing the INB breath the out breath breath intimately only
as I can do in this
body and knowing the breath receiving the breath mindfulness
of the breath calms the Mind brings
Clarity clarity of vision to see what's
happening what's arising what's passing we'll stay with the
breath to calm and settle the mind a little while
longer
e
e e
as we rest with the breath calming soothing bringing more clarity to the
mind and heart
stability breath in the body is the ground we can
also open up to noticing a rising and passing away
impermanence the breath comes and goes
thoughts come and go maybe in terms
of images they come or maybe they come with words they come in they
go perhaps emotions come and go states of Mind sounds
[Music] Sensations stay staying with the breath
but being tuned also to notice in come and goes when it
coming and going in permanence when it reveals itself but the primary
object is the breath
e
e e
if opening to seeing impermanence it comes too wide too much just stay with
the
breath having dropped this reflection impermanence will reveal itself but don't look for it just simply staying
with the in breath and the out breath being known from
within
intimately
e
e e
and as we turn to bring this meditation together to a close
notice if there is just a tiny bit more calm and Clarity in your mind heart your
body more settledness or
spaciousness it might show up in different ways but notice it it's important to notice the
shifts through our practice it helps us build trust trust and confidence in the
practice in
ourselves and also notice that you might have had many
thoughts we all do that came and went impermanent where are they
now during this practice they came and went impermanent they didn't stick they
didn't stay they Frozen
past and reflecting on that
also increases trust confidence in the teachings of the
Buddha things come and go they're impermanent
and appreciating yourself for having showed up for having practiced trus in
yourself for showing up without attachment to
outcome our practice [Music] unfolds on its own we just show up we do
our part for ourselves for each other for the world may all beings
everywhere be the beneficiary the of of my practice of my
Goodwill of my intention to be a Kinder
wiser less reactive human being may all beings be well may all
beings be happy may all beings be free including myself
thanks everyone thanks for your practice take a moment to switch the
recordings
greetings greetings everyone so today is day three of our
exploration of uh uh this topic Sada Sada in
poly the word Sada in poly translated as
um I'll put it in chat again s here we
go translated as trust or confidence and
a quick recap of the past couple days uh we talked about we explored how trust
confidence in the practice in the path uh this well
let's just say trust sad is necessary for beginning the practice for starting
it and also for continuing for not stopping and then yesterday we um the
second day uh we explored how uh trust in the triple Jewel which is the
classical language the triple Jewel the Buddha Dharma and S is important for
this path and uh is uh and I unpack that and very briefly the Buddha trus in the
Buddha can show up as oh somebody woke up somebody did uh practice and and
really develop these beautiful qualities a human being just like me so so can I so can I uh trust in the teachings that
the recipes there there's ways to do this um and uh trust in the s in the
community support of the community we're not doing this alone and many many people have done this um and I can too
and I brought in a um a u musical simile learning to play a
musical instruments such as the cello and and the trust that it that we need to see that others have done this and
and that their uh music books and music classes and music you know scales and
practicing available and um and all that so um
today I'd like to turn to exploring um what what gives rise how how can we grow
in confidence uh how can we cultivate sadada um and the three main points that
I want to make today is um growing sadag growing our confidence cultivating our
confidence through practice through meditation practice through
sea ethical conduct and through reflective practice uh with support from
the S so these are the three points I want to touch into today and also connect them with the
themes that I brought into the meditation today so how can we grow how can we grow and cultivate our trust our
trust our confidence um the first one is um really
our meditation our our practice itself um our formal practice I say informal
practice is very important as well for example the practice of say stealth meta when we're um walking around having a uh
kind heart and beaming meta to others th those practices those informal practices
in between times when we're washing the dishes sensing our bodies those are important as well but for a moment I'm
I'm going to concentrate for a moment on on formal practice and I'll come to informal practice
so with formal practice of meditation uh when we sit and
practice um to to notice um for example today I
invited you to to um connect with the breath simple anapanasati and I and I
said little to have a lot of space silent space for you to explore so that the mind would settle the heart would
settle and when we practice for example anapanasati as an example of many many
many practices in this uh vast Dharma offerings but anapanasati is is is a
go-to for many of us it's a primary practice that the Buddha taught uh Manti
mindfulness of the breath knowing the breath in breath out breath in the
body knowing the breath can calm and settle the mind it
does actually not can it does it does when we really do it it calms settles
the mind it brings more clarity so that the Mind instead of being lost in thought
here and there it settles and it can see more clearly can see more clearly the
thoughts that arise in past the mind can see the patterns the patterns of thoughts that we have maybe we have a
pattern of being planning of being a planner we keep planning planning planning oh when the Mind settles with
with anapanasati with mindfulness of the breath we can see our patterns we can
see how maybe we're still resentful we're still reactive of something that happened days ago or months ago or years
ago like wow sweetheart you're still picking that up we get to see it instead of being lost in it lost in it lost in
it and and not even noticing what's happening
so the anapanasati mindfulness of the breath among other practices can really
help us help the Mind settle to see the
patterns of the mind so when we do a practice when we do a meditation
practice like Ana panasa mindfulness of the breath and we reflect at the end as
I invited you to reflect at the end the end to pay attention oh is my mind any
calmer than it was when I began the practice is it any
calmer and you realize oh yeah there's still thoughts of course there are but there's a little more space I'm a little
calmer that reflection alone that added reflection at the
end helps you see that oh yeah this practice works yeah this practice works I can do it
it's working yeah it brings confidence it brings trust and that trust is
important to bring you back to support you on the path so building trust build
trust please build trust as you practice do bring awareness
to how the mind is getting calmer how you're having insights so that's on the
short and during a practice maybe half hour practice an hour practice a day but
also do that in the long um in the longer time span maybe reflect that oh
I've been practicing now say for six months or a year I'm kinder to myself or
I'm less uh reactive in this particular situation maybe there are situations
that you still get reactive but when this particular person says something oh I used to get
really reactive and but now I don't oh okay wow something has shifted or maybe
your friends and family tell you that um something has shifted so reflect reflect
on these shifts on these changes either shortterm during your practice or
longterm over days weeks months years to
build to cultivate trust to cultivate trust trust is so important it's
important to reflect so reflection can help you build
trust and of course not just the reflection but also the doing the
practice itself if you don't do the practice itself there's nothing to build trust upon right so you need to do the
practice um the for the formal practice of sitting meditation sitting and
walking in meditation practice reflect and informal practice in between
times um for example maybe stealth meta you're doing or if you're going for a
walk just general walk being more mindful being more kind um if you're driving again beaming
kindness loving kindness to other drivers stressed on the road these in between practices that are not sitting
with your eyes closed but practice that you bring to your daily life they also
change you one last thing I wanted to point out this morning uh this morning my time
earlier in our PR in our guided meditation I also invited you to notice
a rising and passing impermanence and we can notice that simply uh the breath arises I've had a 100 thoughts during
this 30 minute meditation arising and passing coming and going when you really
see that the nature of the impermanent nature of everything it gives you trust in the
teachings of the Buddha because that opens up to many many more insights that
I won't get into but just so know that that is um that's uh that's a primary doorway
for insights and and growing in trust in the Dharma seeing
impermanence in the time that is left I want to talk about the importance of eth
ethical conduct Sila or Sheila Sila in in
poly ethical conduct the importance of ethical conduct and the five precepts
the five lay precepts abstaining from killing from stealing taking what has
not been offered sexual misconduct false speech and um taking
intoxicants so abstaining from these five the ethical
conduct it helps grow trust in the practice and let's just pause for a
moment and consider so for let's take the fifth one for example intoxicants if if you keep drinking for
example intoxicating the mind and and um
make poor decisions then your trust in yourself erod it's oh even if you're
meditating you're trying to do it but then you kind of uh you're getting intoxicated and kind of falling off it
just it erodes your trust it erodes your trust in yourself it erodes the Trust In
The Practice it just doesn't quite it doesn't support it erodes it it it chips away at
it similarly if you um say tell lies uh
unwise Speech tell lies lying there's re Arch about how it becomes a slippery
slope and lying actually erodes other um actions it leads to other unethical
actions the unethical actions uh if you're stealing it erodes your confidence in yourself it erodes your
confidence in the practice so I want to leave you with
these two Reflections for today so today as you're practicing um please notice please
notice these shifts have Reflections both on how when you practice formally
and informally in short time there is a shift and also in the long term maybe
reflect back to who you were before you start to practice even if it was a week ago notice the shifts that can build
confidence that builds confidence not can it builds confidence it builds trust s number two notice for yourself in your
own life the relationship between your own ethical conduct um and trust and
trust in yourself trust in your practice trust in your growing in your
Humanity so that's all the time we have thank you
all for joining for practicing for building trust in yourself in the
teachings and growing together supporting one another in the community in the S May our practice be benefit to
all beings everywhere um those we know those we don't know our family our
friends ourselves may all beings be well may all beings be
[Music] free thanks everyone see you tomorrow
see you in quotes tomorrow