greetings hello wonderful to be with you again
it's been four mornings on the four noble truths and we've arrived
at Friday the fifth day and my My Hope for the morning for
the day wherever you are is
um that we remember to bring the whole body and the whole being
along as we walk this eight-fold path so let's begin with um begin with a
meditation a simple meditation of
embodiment and the the instructions in brief will
be uh first let's establish mindfulness here with this this
body and then whenever awareness seems to get a little
small shrink then bring the awareness back to
the entire body so we're aware aware as best we can of the whole body at
once so let's begin
taking our
places
really taking our
time to connect with the body as it is right
here
I would suggest making any adjustments that you
need to the posture
such that the the breathing can flow easily and
deeply and if uh free and easy breathing is not
available no
problem perhaps in that case instead of feeling the body from the inside
out you can try sensing the body from the outside
in almost from its
perimeter
bringing the whole body Along on this
path now is a good time to check in with all
of the senses if there's any
tension say in the eyes relaxing the
eyes any tension linked to the ears relax the
ears just so with the
nose even the tongue and the mouth and the
gums
and gently with the whole
body
for
and applying now just enough
energy to bring awareness as best we
can to the whole
body holding the whole body in our
awareness so it can be be seen in one glance sensed in one
glance the whole width of the
shoulders the
distance
the front of the body to the back of the
body and from the scalp to the
toes
with our eyes closed sensing this whole dancing field
of sensation
St
and if after some time you notice the awareness
is growing
smaller to gently invite
the entire
body
for
e
now
sensing the entire
body bringing the entire body along
walking this eight-fold
path no part of our being left
behind and in the last minute of this
sitting i' invite you
to relax any effort in the
meditation and if it's available to breathe
breathe and a touch of gratitude into this
body offered to the
body it's by the body that we're aware by the body we walk the
[Music] path and the mind and body
together that we wake
up may all beings be free from
suffering
[Music]
so welcome again the Four Noble Truths
[Music] the Noble Truth of
suffering the noble truth of the arising or origin of
suffering the third Noble Truth of the cessation of suffering and the fourth Noble Truth of the way the path the
practice leading to the cessation of suffering and I'm wanting to emphasize
this morning bringing the whole body along as we said at the end of the sitting it's the it's the body and the
mind together through which we awaken so I have this metaphor that
helps me remember that the whole body is involved in this eight-fold path and that's likening each factor to
a part of the body this is totally my idea so um let it let it go if it
doesn't land for you so um Right View is like the eyes
that sense that Orient us to our Direction on the path I liken right intention to the head that I associate
with impulses thoughts and choices right speech for obvious
reasons right action and right livelihood like the left and the right
hand together so action and livelihood not so not so
distinguished right effort associate with the belly this um there there are
associations of of power in the stomach um motive Force so right effort
in the belly right mindfulness I link to the the entire
sensing body this whole body's mindfulness and then right concentration
the heart and the association with the heart is uh
actually influenced by the teachings of the T Forest tradition that a heart and the what they say the the
chit um the mind they locate in the chest and they say when when one becomes
concentrated what happens is the it's the chitta that's becoming concentrated the chitta that's collecting so I love
to think of the heart becoming collected in the center of the
being so this metaphor helps uh helps remind me that this whole body comes
along so yesterday we spoke about five factors of the eight the Noble eight-fold Path
we we touched on Right View right intention right speech right action and
right livelihood uh and I divided those factors in a way to emphasize Right View
holding up right View and then holding up the other four in a sort of creative category I called
conduct usually the path is divided into three divisions
uh the division of wisdom that includes Right View and right intention the division of uh Sila virtue or ethics
that includes speech action and livelihood and then this third division
which will be the focus this morning which is samadi
concentration uh that this includes three factors also right effort right
mindfulness and right concentration
so these three factors again I want to I want to emphasize that right view uh is
not left behind no matter where we go on the path we're orienting to uh the next
step on the path and the the goal at whatever distance so uh there's this beautiful
suta um middle length discourse is 117 that is called the Great 40 and there's
this there's this description in it over and over and over again about how uh Right View mindfulness and right effort
all Circle and run around each other I love the the uh Dynamic aspect of uh
thinking of these factors of the eight-fold path running and circling around each other and that right View
and right mindfulness and right effort are all working together um so part of that
teaching it explains what each of these factors is so in this in this teaching
Right View uh right views Incorporated the effort that's involved
is to abandon an unwise View and to enter into
Right View and the mindfulness that's involved is that which keeps us attentive we have
to be able to recognize Right View and recognize some effort that's the that's
the mindfulness so maybe in other words we could say that right view orients US
skillfully effort is the effort to align with Right View that we
see uh and then the mindfulness is that attentiveness which allows this process to
happen so right view Right View stays with us um Right View stays with us as
we as we we move into the this samade section right effort right mindfulness
right concentration let's see in relationship
to the eight-fold path right effort uh is that effort that it takes to enter
into each one of the factors of the eight-fold path as we were just saying the effort it takes to enter into Right
View and let go of its opposite and then that effort it takes to to enter into
wise intentions and let go of the opposite same with speech same with action same with
livelihood now in meditation the art of finding the right
amount of effort is often the main question and that effort uh is is
likened to tuning a stringed instrument maybe you've heard this teaching before
of U the Buddha meeting Sona is having a having a tough time in
his meditation he's seems to be doing everything right but it's not going well for him and the Buddha asks him a
question about his effort and in explaining how the the art of finding the right amount of effort Likens um the
application of energy to tuning a stringed instrument if it's too loose the the string won't play if it's
too tight the instruments Out Of Tune so you have to tune the effort tuning the
effort so circling around with right effort of
course Right View and right mindfulness so right
mindfulness uh there's a there's a contemporary teacher who says that to be
mindful is easy to be mindful is easy what is difficult is to remember to be
mindful I appreciate that um maybe maybe we could say that um
right mindfulness is is a sort of comfort zone in our tradition we talk about it a lot we study it a lot we
practice it regularly um might say we do this with some
energy um and though it's our comfort zone so to speak it takes Vigor uh we see this in the the um Sati
patana suta that uh there's there's a degree of tincy involved in our right
view and clear seeing in our practice of mindfulness
and it's a wonder it it it's just a wonder that the the power of sustained
clear awareness clear mindfulness is able to develop what's beautiful in us
and to support us to abandon what's harmful can you hear the right effort that that comes along with right
mindfulness helps us to grow and the beneficial also part of the part of the
power of mindfulness is the Simplicity of the message method it's so easy to describe that what we're doing in
mindfulness is to clearly know the body this body as
body uh these feeling tones as feeling tones this mind as this mind and
qualities as qualities just as they're Rising not as we wish they were not as
we wish they weren't but just as they are and doing this putting aside greed
and distress in reference to the world it said the Simplicity is just
amazing so let's right effort right mindfulness and this brings us to right concentration why is concentration or as
Gil Gil has been teaching recently complete
concentration so in a way this eighth factor of the eight-fold path is like the culmination of the eight-fold path
in that uh in one Reckoning it arises at at the end and it's been conditioned and
supported by the entire path before it again in this teaching the great 40
uh right concentration is uh is explained as that sort of concentration that's invested
with all of the other factors of the eight-fold path another classic
understanding is that uh wise concentration is related to these four deep states of unification
of the mind and heart called Janna and what I why I want to bring them up is because the images that are
used to teach most of them are associated with water why is that
significant uh you might when thinking about concentration you might think oh laser
beam oh clamp uh I need to I will sternly demand that my awareness be in
one place something like that so rather than the laser beam or clamp metaphor thinking about water the uh the first
the first of the four metaphors being like um sprinkling sprinkling water on
Bath powder or maybe in modern terms sprinkling water on bread dough and
kneading it so that this dough is Unified and there's water suffused throughout it nothing
extra and in the same way in this in this state the the body is filled with
Rapture and pleasure then the uh the second just as another
example is a a state of state of uh concentration collectedness of the Mind
where a Springfed lake is welling up from within and that's liken to the pervading
of Cool Waters throughout the
body [Music] so right effort right mindfulness right
concentration these are the um maybe we could say these are
meditation contribution to the noble Eightfold Path it's been quite a delight this
first week of 2024 that uh we've returned to the Buddha's traditional First teaching on the first Noble
Truth and in uh to summarize we've we've reflected we've reflected on this path
of practice that is to be cultivated that's to be developed in order to
realize freedom from suffering uh with some gratitude to the
Buddha the great physician it's based on his understanding of Dua his understanding of this human
predicament and its causes these are the four noble
truths and in closing I want to say that the truths are noble uh in part because they are in
nobling therefore in nobling truths so the in the Buddhist time of
course uh nobility was something that one was born into but this was not so for the Buddha a noble one instead was
one who had realized a degree of freedom of heart free of greed free of hatred free of
delusion and I'd like to encourage us as we as we close and as we move forward on this path
together um to appreciate and be nourished by all of those Noble moments
when the heart is free of greed hatred and delusion and I'm so inspired by this
that U that each moment that's free of greed hatred and delusion is a noble
moment that we're bringing nobility into the world in a in a direct material
actual way with every every step we take in this world that's free of greed free of
hatred free of
delusion thank you so much for your attention your practice your kindness this
week um hopefully I'll will be back with you soon um and I don't know that I'll
be back before this so I want to say now that um uh Gil and I will be teaching a
retreat together in June uh at Insight Retreat Center so uh I believe
registration opens for that sometime in February so if uh that's of Interest maybe we'll see you
there take care everyone best wishes may all
beings be free of suffering and have the causes of happiness and may we all walk the path
with balanced hearts and minds and view each other with kind
eyes take care