so
um so what I'd like to talk about today is a little bit of a expansion of what I
talked about Wednesday morning here uh the half day sitting we have and uh the simple way is that
simple kind of introduction is that it has to do with a as we practice we
develop a a growing set of reference points that guide us in our
practice and uh so we don't not no longer Guided by instructions from other people from the text but rather from
ourselves because we have developed these reference points of something really good really healthy and wholesome
that's is available to us we know for ourselves and so we know what's how to
go forward we know how to find our way and what is useful and healthy to do
and it's phenomenal to have that shift from you know taking Buddhism as an external reference point for your life
versus having internalized something that you know for yourself as a reference so that is the basic kind of
premise for this today's talk and in the course of it um maybe also it'll give
you a sense of why in mindfulness meditation we put a tremendous
importance on mindful of the present moment sometimes the present moment is I
I feel gets over idealized in our scene and um and
like it's all good just to be in the present moment but it's a uh the purpose of being in the present moment has a
particular purpose particular reason if you understand that it's a lot easier to
do this practice um and um I remember many years
ago there was a Calvin in Hobs cartoon kind of cartoon that uh had something
like um Calvin and Hobbs were climbing a tree looked like a glorious day like today and they were climbing a tree and
Calvin says oh something some paraphrase it something like oh it's so great just
to be in the present moment enjoying life this way sounds like perfect you know
mindfulness and hob says to Kelvin yes but you're supposed to be at school
right now
and um and that was kind of a little bit my problem taking my kids to school when they were in preschool in kindergarten
is I was in the present moment taking them to school but as we walked out of our front door to get to the car they
were really in the present moment with the flowers outside our house the little sticks that were there and like you know
they were really present and there was a conflict between two present moment
moments so the present
moment so um somehow I want to also do as
introduction to this idea of the references for practice that a really big um turning
point for me in my involvement with Buddhism was uh the day I decided to
devote my life to Buddhist practice in the form and that took the form back then being a Zen student to deciding I
wanted to be ordained as a Zen monastic and being a monastic for me was not being becoming a teacher but rather
dedicating my whole life to to uh to Buddhist practice and but the reason
that I had for it was that um um for this was that
um uh I wanted to be able to address the suffering of this
world and I wanted to be able to address it at its root and back then when I was younger
the root I felt was um the attachment we have to self and I knew in my limited
experience of life I knew of nothing else that touched that root than Buddhist
practice and uh I had already been wanting to address some of the suffering of the world I went to uh um you know
very different than what I'm doing now my undergraduate degree is in Agronomy
so agriculture I was going to be a farmer and but in the course of that
education uh I became familiar with uh the
growing potential catastrophe around the world of soil erosion and it seemed like
very few people knew about it back then it was the nuclear proliferation was the big thing that people were focusing on
uh trying to stop but uh my thing was I was so so aware soral erosion was a huge
issue and and um so at some point I decided I actually applied to go to
graduate school to study uh soil science so that I could go around the world and address the issues of soil
erosion and uh so that was kind of the contrast you know between deciding to become Buddhist and and then deciding
not to be a soil scientist and soil conservationist
and um and the rationale that I gave myself for that was that no matter how
successful I was at uh conserving soil protecting the world from soil erosion
which is a necessary thing to do I don't want to diminish the importance of it um I would all it would never really touch
the heart the depth of people's suffering the existential suffering of
people and I would feel like I would always have a dissatisfaction I always feel like like it's not quite enough and
I didn't know if I'd be effective as in being a Buddhist monastic and helping
the suffering of the world but I Le at least I felt like I'd had the satisfaction that I was trying to
address it at its roots and um and that seemed like a
big you know big task and I I didn't quite know what the roots were I had an
intuition this was more like an intuition that was operating based on a number of years of having
practiced and um I had some sense it had to do with attachment and as I said attachment to
self and those kind of uh to say that maybe it's kind of idealistic it's kind of like maybe recognized as being some
of the grand ideas of what Buddhism is about and um and um and maybe that's
good or maybe not um but now we get to this topic of
the reference and the references for practice maybe aren't so
Grand maybe are not so amazingly idealistic maybe they're very ordinary
in some ways and so they're not idealistic it doesn't look like wow you
know this is the end of suffering once in for all and end of attachment to self
wow that would be fantastic Enlightenment thank you and uh and and so you know maybe I
get criticized either way if I do the idealistic thing then the people who want to be practical say well
that's you know that does nothing to do with my life but the people who you know if I really ordinary with it and simple
then the people who say well that Buddhism is much more than that so um it's hard to be a Buddhist
teacher so um but they reference points so uh uh this has been in my mind
a little bit because uh in the last few weeks I had an occasion where I think on the same day I had
um I had a desire for a particular Buddha statue that I had seen number of
them about and and um and I you know I kind of wanted to
have one and not not for myself but I wanted to have one to get one and maybe give it to someplace when I came back to
United States I was in Japan and oddly enough that in the small little towns I
was in the only place that was liable to find this particular statue was at a
um um I think they were called bosi in Japanese um a gravestone
store so I had to try to go to the to the various people try to explain to
them grav stor St why would a Westerner in Japan want to go to grave
stores and I had a hard time getting them to understand stand and cuz my Japanese was pretty
poor but I finally finally found one and went there and so it was a bit of a
project right to get look to look for where I can buy this kind of thing and then uh later in the day there
was an occasion for an uh to consider it was evoked in me a feeling of generosity
of giving something to someone and um and then those two states
of mine contrasted each other and I saw that in some ways when my mind had the
desire for this Buddha statue my mind got narrower got smaller got a little
bit more contracted you know focusing on getting this thing but when the
generosity with was there my mind became more open more relaxed more at ease and
that difference uh is a reference point which of those mind States is more
useful which of the Mind States would I like to live in which of the Mind states do I
want to allow for what I do with my mind is a really important thing what I do with my heart
is a really important thing and which of those do I want to predominate and and and come become the predominant
characteristic of my mind and I know there are times in my life where the predominant characteristic of my mind
has been attachment clinging caught up in greed or desires for something there
are times prominant characteristic has been resentment or anger hostility and
that's what's caught up sometimes it's been fear or anxiety for things that
probably I didn't need to be afraid of but uh I was still kind of you know the
contraction of the Mind the narrowing of the Mind the tightening of the Mind the stress on the mind that certain states
have and there was a time in my life where I didn't know I was having this I didn't know there was any
you know it was just so ordinary to have a stressful mind a contracted mind a caught up mind churning away with its
concerns I just thought well that's this is mean I didn't even think about it I just this was human
life as I started to practice more and more uh an alternative became clearer
and clearer and the alternative was a mind which had no contraction a heart
that was not caught up in something and and uh and had the level of Peace in
it or calm or openness or Joy or Delight all these things are kind of
characteristics of an alternative kind of mind and they don't all happen at once but the different times you feel
different ones and they set up a contrast between something that in
Buddhism is considered unhelpful to have and something which is
helpful something which is wholesome and versus something that's UNH wholesome and that becomes a personal reference
point that becomes the the uh sometimes it feels
sematic so it's really personal and direct and immediate sometimes it feels more
mental sometimes it feels more something of part of our emotional life we really
feel there's an alternative and um so even coming down here today I walked down here and I was
going to talk think about this talk a little bit and walk down and um and as I started thinking
about it um I could see that my mind was doing that stressful thing it was starting to get narrow and focused on it
and concerned about it and and maybe even like what are people going to think and how am I going to say it right so
that no one attacks me you know I mean you know something like that it just little bit like it was
happening and um and I knew better I know an alternative the alternative is
close at hand so for me there's a reference point that uh is uh kind of ever
presentes that is guiding me and so as I was have my mind my thinking mind was
going down that track I knew immediately this is not interesting I don't want to
live my life that way this is not the the world I want to live in that is
caught up in thoughts and concerns this way and fears or
preoccupations and uh so at you know in this context it was relatively easy just
to let it go and um and so it wasn't that I stop
thinking about the talk or what how to talk about what to talk about here but
rather now my thinking the quality of my thinking had changed and now it was like having a
friend in my mind that was you know was it was a friendly mind there was this friendly light kind kind of nice way of
thinking about what was going on that um that uh you know it was you know was
just nice to have that friend there whereas before that mind was me I guess both are me but I wouldn't have
characterized it as my friend sometimes you know the
Taskmaster sometimes you all kinds of you know other characteristics so we have these
reference points and and in these in these that I've described today for myself I think they were more mental
though in mental they were also sematic because the ways in which the Mind contracts uh and gets tight and caught
up I feel a little bit as tension around my forehead around my eyes kind of behind my forehead in the area of the
front of the brain you know I don't know exactly what's going on there but that's what it feels like and I think of the
thinking muscle that I can relax other times it's clearly embodied
sometimes the reference point has been my belly and I have sometimes I have a soft belly and then oh it's all tight in
a knot it used to be when I before I started practicing it was always tight in a knot and then took years for that
knotted stomach to relax and relax and relax and luckily I was not in a hurry
because if I had been and thought that was a terrible person for having a tense stomach I it would have made more tense
and um so but it took years of of my practice to slowly relax that belly and
that made a world a difference and now I have this reference point that's kind of there oh there it is maybe I should take
a look I'm my belly tensed up what just happened as opposed to the Belly tensed
Up and this means there's something dangerous and I need to fight or flight you know uh I've
learned not to kind of let these these these changes in the body and mind
and heart Drive the ship I've learned to recognize them and
say is this what I want to do what's really going on here let's take a deeper look what's happening here and usually
the tense stomach is not useful there sometimes I have what could be considered a tense stomach when I'm
having fun and playing and that seems okay then I'll put up with
it then it's a fine thing to have but uh there are times when it's really an indication that something is off and so
I have that reference point I have had that reference point with my hands my hands will tighten up in certain C
circumstance or I start you of playing too much with my fingers you know because I'm afraid or something and
that's a reference point the shoulders are a reference point I've had a reference point in my
chest where I I feel like my my heart is closed now it was a time in my life I
think I was about 15 where someone um teased me about something or or or
belittled me about something I just just said and um I immediately some I I uh
there was a decision like it wasn't even me it wasn't it was like something deeper somatic that you know something I
could feel something Clos in my heart and I said said I'm never going to show that to anyone again
and it took years for that to open up and relax and and and be willing to share a more vulnerable place of who I
was and so we have these uh things that we do that don't serve us very well and
as we practice they begin to relax begin to Open begin to soften and things quiet
down and the important thing that as this happens is to is to take that
seriously not as something get attached to but rather something that can help
you read yourself become a self Whisperer I love the this phrase you
know they used to be first to started by horse whis Whispers but now it's like now it's everything and this is the
first time I've ever heard someone say self- whisper but uh but I think it's
something profound this idea you know to have that kind of sensitivity to yourself that you really know yourself
deeply and well that a lot of people don't actually know themselves they might know very well what they're
thinking about what they believe and what they will fight for and but they
haven't really tuned into the deeper operating systems the deeper movements that's going on and and often people are
living uh you know one-dimensional life in a sense and as we practice there more dimensions of who we are reveal itself
and what I'm pointing to today is that uh that what reveals itself is that we have this place where the mind can be
relized and at ease the heart can be at ease the body can be at ease in some way
or other versus it can get stressed the
mind the body feels stressed and sometimes the stress is kind of kind of
comes from outside but sometimes it's clearly we're contributing it to it and
um and so we're kind of working with this what's stressful and not stressful in fact uh there's a one of the main
main translators of the Buddhist teachings to English is a monk in San Diego named Tanis raiku who comes here
sometimes teachers and um and uh the the
common English translation of the Buddhist word Dua is
suffering and suffering is such a big thing you know it's like what do we mean
even and but this monk Tanis he translates duka as as stress and
immediately I think it gives a kind of almost sematic reference point a clear reference point and uh and he's actually
said that um I think he's I think he's the one who said it that um getting
married is one of the most stressful things people do now you wouldn't say you know you
know getting married is is the biggest suffering people have I mean especially at the at the
wedding that doesn't that's not quite right but appreciate that it's stressful
that's understandable and so that word stress is really makes it much more applicable this teachings and this
practice that if we always like I do maybe too much emphasize suffering suffering suffering in the end of it
stress in the end of it and maybe this so this idea of stress and the absence
of it becomes a powerful reference point and so this is not idealistic idealistic
ideology it's not necessarily Buddhist you know we have to believe Buddhist
teachings this becomes uh a time when we learn to believe ourselves we believe and see for
ourselves what works and doesn't work and even if the Buddha came here today
and he walked in and he said hey but hey you should stop listening to this guy you know everything I said was wrong
you know you just you go find something else to do because I completely had it wrong and and uh you just forget all
this Buddhist stuff and you would say well that's maybe nice for you but uh I
know for myself I've discovered I have this personal reference point I know the difference between um getting stressed
and not stressed if you wanted to use the big word uh getting involved in
suffering and not getting entangled with it getting attached and not being
attached that is so clear and so obvious that that's going to guide my life because I know one is better than the
other one is healthier than the other one provides uh much more wisdom one
provides much more kindness and support one represents the world I want to live in
the other represents the world I don't want to live in and just imagine least some of you who are not
Saints and just imagine that at that situation a time when you were at your
worst you know caught up in anger and resentments and attach attachments and greed or
whatever it might have been your thing just imagine multiplying that by
the billions of people we have on this planet that that is what's that's the
illness that's spread across the land and everyone has it that's not the world
we want to live in is there an alternative can we live in a world of Peace can we live in a world where uh uh
everyone comes from that possibility in the mind where the mind is free where
the mind is free of its clinging attachment hates resentful
resentments and I think that as we live our social life having these two references are
invaluable because as we get more and more sensitive and that's part of the purpose of mindfulness is to be in the
present moment and then be sensitive to the
distinction between that stress and not stress being open or closed in unhealthy
ways and at some point we can feel
that towards people some people for whatever reason we feel some fear or some
judgments or some little bit hostility or some like negative
orientation but as we as we see the mind go that way we feel the impact it has on us and we
say this is not good for me am diminishing myself to have to to get
involved in that kind of idation and thoughts and judgments and ideas and
because we have this reference point in the alternative then we're much less likely
to get caught in our bias and our prejudice and our judgments and hostilities of
people and I've had an occasion recently where
um someone said something critical of me and um I could
feel kind of the Mind begin to Mo go in the direction of being defensive or critical back or how could you say
that just just but it was so brief because of this reference point that I
live with all the time in this these circumstances immediately I just dropped
it and turned to the person and said can you tell me
anymore what do you mean and um and then I just said
okay and that was enough you know in that circumstance and um and how
different would it been if I responded through the old way of you know defensive and criticalness and how could
you and let me tell you and you know and when you did
it and it wasn't a moralistic thing it it wasn't like the ethical thing is to be kind the ethical thing is to avoid
being judgmental it say deeper it goes down to the
roots it was is it stressful for me or not
stressful is there a better way to engage the world and people and uh and this is what I kind of
mean by The Roots really get down to the roots of where things are where we can feel and sense and know for
ourselves and so so it can be very ordinary in ordinary circumstances this
reference point it doesn't seem Grand and religious and you know ultimately
spiritual but it's but to live this way and fill your life with this way is from
a Buddhist point of view a spiritual life and it changes the world we live in changes ourselves and it has a huge
impact uh on ourselves over time and um
and eventually Maybe does lead to Enlightenment wouldn't that be nice the
small little steps that lead all the way so those are my thoughts today and
um we have 15 minutes before the PTL uh what I'd like to
suggest is that um is partly to so that those of you who want to stay or not
stay uh you can just kind of be friendly with each other a little bit and maybe and so to go into groups of three or so
or four for and have a little conversation about uh What uh what was
useful about my talk what touched you in some
way so that was wonderful to sit here and
listen to you talk I both feel delightful to hear your
seeming enjoying enjoyment in talking about this whatever you talking about and um and I also stood out to me
that that was a lot of energy after sitting and meditating before and so maybe it's good to come back and be a
little bit quiet for a few minutes as we uh kind of to kind of settle things a little
bit and um but you know as I said I offer to if anyone has any questions it
doesn't have to be a question it could be a test monial or something that's important for you to say at this point
but if any questions about the talk or clarification or anything that anybody like to
say so um I have a question uh because you were talking about mind you said I
have two voices in my mind one of them is got so caught up with these um
thoughts that's um you know bringing uh a lot of pain and suffering the other
Mind Is Telling Me uh peace and joy and then a lot of um good things and you
said um they both are me but I prefer the other one um when you said that you
kind of hit me because um I read a lot of books I I know a lot of teachings um they are trying to teach us
I am not my body I am not my mind and I know when you said that I'm like oh no
so they both the both voice are actually me so I am actually my mind so so so I find
that's kind of you know there's a conflict there so can can you please explain that a little bit Yeah so the
first thing I'll say is not directly to your question so it isn't so much for
the way I didn't say this but it isn't is not so much that there's two sides of my mind you know but rather there's a
surface mind and a deeper mind it's that's more how I feel it and the surface mind is very much uh fueled by
uh attachments attachment to self attachment to outcomes all kinds of things that you have and For Better or
For Worse the analogy I have for this kind of mind is uh squeezing a
toothpaste uh uh tube if you take the lid off the t uh
the the off the the tube and then squeeze it uh it'll just keep coming out
and out and out for a long time you can brush it away as much as you want but it'll keep coming out and so the surface mind is a little
bit like that if we're always tense and squeezing it with our whatever attachments stress we have that thing
that surface mind is going to keep doing all kinds of nonsense this doesn't want to stop but
if that's if we stop squeezing it that allows the deeper mind to show itself
and that's the one that tends to be wiser or friendlier or more peaceful and and I think of it as being much more
holistic as long as the mind is Serv as mind is being squeezed by attachments by clinging by resistance and all of Might
me uh it doesn't have access to the full full wholeness of who we are and uh this
deeper mind is more full so that's the way of not answering your question
directly now I'll try to do it more directly um the um yes there's a very strong
teaching in Buddhism about you know the body is not self the mind is not self all things is not self and uh but it's
best to take those teachings in context as opposed to take them as being this is
like you can never say anything about you know this is not me um the in
ordinary language uh it's fine to say you know
you know these you know the the these are my shoes you know and um you know
it's it's okay you don't have to be attached to your shoes and someone has taking your shoes you say well those are my
shoes and and they say well I prefer them to
mine and then you might say okay please take them there's a story with um uh many
years ago 20 years ago I don't know when it was um I knew I have a friend who's a Monk and and he had one of the first but
look like the pre smartphone smartphones it was like a really intelligent phone
maybe it wasn't a smartphone yet but it was like the the next best thing to it and before they came out and um and I
looked at him and I said what do you you you have vows of of
poverty you're a renunciant why do you have that this and he said um well it
was a gift and I felt it was okay to receive the gift if someone ever asked
me for it I would give it to them so I was
tempted so so the um so to say these are my
shoes or you know this is my hair you know you go to a you know someone's going to cut your hair I'm like my wife
cuts my hair and I say will you cut my hair today it's my hair I don't say you know like cut someone's
here then should be cut someone's here today and or will
you cut this hair here and it's not me but it's you know the hair is growing here and life gets so complicated if you
tried to avoid the word my it can be done innocently and it actually points
to something essential something important and what Buddhism is about is not having
any fixed idea of self there's no fixed self no fixed identity
that's where the problem is the fixed idea so but it but it's actually
healthier to kind of have an ordinary simple idea so when I said there's two sides of me you know these two ways of
thinking uh I wasn't essentializing them I wasn't making the fixed idea this is who I am there's probably other sources
of thinking in me as well and um and I'm not assuming that it's you know and and
because it's in my own mind or in the mind that's in this body and
mind then this body and mind is the place for taking responsibility for it
especially when it's causing harm and sometimes it's really helpful to avoid
the these pronouns mine me I it's really helpful it frees something up and
sometimes it's actually more responsible to say it like if you're going to apologize to someone uh you don't say
you know well sorry you know or something or there is apology
here they would like to hear you say you know I'm sorry then it carries more
weight so we have to be fluid and how we use this so that was a long
answer did I address it well enough oh yeah I think so I think so what I
understanding what I'm understanding is it's kind of like saying okay these two
thoughts they are both in me they kind of in my mind you know but they are not like my mind or me you know but they are
both they are existing there in me uh that's what I'm understanding from what
you just exp yeah the these exist and something else that exists in here is now going to use it as a
reference and as practice goes deeper there are times when the Fe there's no feeling even that there is a self a
Central Locus or of self that's part of it it feels much more intuitive or
relaxed or and uh it's a whole different way of operating in the world that's radically different than how most people
operate when they have coagulated around sub notion of self there's a there's a
locust that our attachments some total of our attachments and clinging can give us a a very sometimes very powerful
sometimes very meaningful sense of some kind of kind of Center that this is who I am but if we
bring our attention to that Center we feel it's a little bit of tension a little bit of pressure and what's
fascinating to do when you're quiet and still enough in the mind to bring the mindfulness to that locus of tension
that we associate with this is who I am and see it dissolve like a like the
de on a hot day what what then
so okay so should we do one more and then it's time for the putl and I'll stay here if you want to ask questions
afterwards as we go
but okay hello um this is only my second time here so hi welcome um I have an
array of questions but I don't know the specific thing I'm trying to ask well hopefully your way of answering will
also go inside but um something I've been struggling with is like I feel like
I've been having an existential crisis for like a really really long time and
now in my I think something that you said today really resonated with me that
um was when you said it's really hard to be a Buddhist teacher
and when you were saying like should I be a soil scientist or dedicate my life
to this and that you were saying that the world billions of us they're suffering everywhere and I think now
that I'm older in my 30s I finally realized that I want to heal the
suffering somehow but I don't know how exactly
um and it feels like I'm alone in that like everyone around me doesn't care the
way that I care um yes so so long story short is like
I'm I'm wondering how did you decide to do
something The Road Less paved I guess and also how did you maintain your cool and
be like tell me more okay when I feel like within me it's just so much fire at
sometimes and then sometimes there's water like it's just so hard to maintain my cool yes and when I
just want to yeah I just want to make a
difference but it feels like it's impossible in this Society right now thank you for your question I love I
love do you understand what I'm saying I I love your question your concern and I I take it's very I I'm delighted that
you're struggling with this this is a really good thing to struggle with what you're doing this I wish more people
struggled this way so I know it's hard for you but this is to my in my heart this is really good
that you're questioning looking at this and so thank you for that so that's my
you know affirmation of you and what you're up up against please find your
way with it so that's my my heartfelt response um and now maybe a little bit
more direct to your question um when I said you know it's hard to be
a Buddhist teacher it's hard to be a human being you know so it's just it is
hard in finding our way that you want to that you care enough for the suffering
of the world to want to find some way to respond is fantastic and the response has to be right for who you are
and uh you know and so every different people respond different ways and some
people have certain gifts that they have that that's really the way they do it someone who plays music um might find
it's through music that I do this and I know some someone who was a hospital chaplain who went to visit people who
were suffering in the hospital actually visit children and he was a musician and he'd
go along with his guitar and and uh would sing to the kids and so he he was using his music to really help kids who
were in terrible states of distress so everyone has to find their own way and uh and and so you have to
know yourself well enough to know what your way is but or or you have to experiment go around and look at
different options and um and maybe try to find some people who share your
orientation so you said you don't have anybody around you who share what you're about so I would encourage you to try
find someone and um and then um and then
if you would like to talk to me at some point about you know exploring this territory more personally I could be
available for that awesome thank you okay great so
thank you all for being here and so I guess now the potluck is probably ready
and I don't know how it works out there but but uh it'll be there and it's a wonderful chance to continue your
conversations get to know each other and thank you all for being here