so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour lovely to be with you dear sa
it makes me happy to see you and for today's practice I'd like to invite
us to excuse me tickle in my
throat like to invite us to sit with um with embodiment
tonight and with with trusting that embodiment
coming to our bodies bringing the awareness bringing knowing to our bodies
to the breath can bring can cause can bring
forth a sense of stability and resilience I've mentioned this before
that often um we find ourselves being um overwhelmed by Thoughts by fears by
Future oriented uh Reflections and we become like um
topheavy um uh uh blow up dolls I might I probably have mentioned this uh before
here but I love this this simile of a popup doll these pop-up dolls you might
have seen them that they have sand on the bottom and if they fall down whoop they stand
up again because they have sand on the bottom so if you have mindfulness of the body the sense of resilience here here
here together with kindness and compassion sweetheart here here there
can be a sense of stability as the storms of Fortune as the storms of the
world come and go there can be a sense of stability here here I can understand
this I can withstand this but if the sand is on the top top heavy and we get
overwhelmed by thoughts and fears and stories and what's happening in the
world Etc and you know what I'm referring to we get we get toppled over
ah it's really really hard to write our write ourselves it's really hard to
write ourselves because we are so overwhelmed by the story so again um
very helpful to be embodied to have to be have the sense of stability as we
move through through the worlds there there will be plenty of storms we have already weathered plenty of Storms and
there will be more storms that is that is what is to be human on this on this
Earth lots of storms can we have stability can we cultivate sense of calm
presence to support ourselves to be present for the sake of ourselves and
all beings whose lives we touch so that is our practice tonight and I'm going to
invite silence presence embodiment kindness
compassion um and keep it pretty light not too many words light I hope so that
we have time to settle together okay so with that preamble
like to invite us to arrive and settle in our seat and if you need to shift
left and right left and right forwards and backwards
to find your sit Bones the center of your gravity maybe also roll your
shoulder back a few times open your chest make sure you don't have a
collapsed um posture that your posture is open
if you're sitting on a chair make sure your feet are firmly planted on the floor
with a wide stance white
stance bottom of the feet on the earth if you're sitting on a
cushion make sure your base is wide and stable
and Landing Landing in our sit
bones Landing in our sit bones and allowing our torso to be
tall rising up towards the sky
really feeling that our feet or legs or sit bones or our base our stable
base the sand on the bottom I mentioned or sand on the
bottom feeling the sensations of our feet our legs or sit
bones and relaxing into the breath in the
abdomen e
and as thoughts arise them Arizon pass release them release
them and perhaps kindly gently tell them thank you I'll come back to you later
not now I'm giving my whole heart to this
practice connecting with the body with each breath
sensations of the in breath sensations of the out
breath with kindness Let There Be gentleness in the
body in the heart
if it feels right for you in this moment if the body is called for it given
everything that has been happening in our world the past 24 hours put a put a palm
in center of your chest holding yourself holding yourself
oh dear heart Dear Heart it's been a lot it's been a lot oh
dear heart
allowing yourself to connect no in breath and the out
breath with kindness relaxing the body as much as
possible thinking refuge in the Simplicity of This
Moment's presence in
community
e
e e
letting knowing of the breath to be soothing calming settling nourishing to
the heart it can be you know it can
be Breath by breath the soothing
self
e
e e
here here dear heart here just simply
here in this body
sensing sensations of sitting breathing being
alive not missing what it's like to be alive the
raw sensations of being here
firmly grounding
ourselves and the felt
Sensations firmly and gently grounding
ourselves e
so sweet just be
here present in this passing
moment
e
e e
allow yourself to sit tall like a
mountain with the integrity with dignity sitting
dignified allow the breath to be just as it
is full deep or shallow doesn't
matter Bel long we sit simply sitting knowing that we're
breathing with gentleness and kindness
notice more
stability in our posture in our
heart more uprightness more courage
comes available in our heart
opening your heart your chest just a bit more to yourself
and to
others
e
e e
and before we turn to close let's sit together
pay attention in the body in your heart and
your mind is there more spaciousness
available more stability more
groundedness maybe more peace or gentleness in your
heart maybe just a tiny bit more pay attention by paying attention to it will
help it
grow if there's one word that bubbles Up In This Moment
more something more grounded more stable more upright what
is that word for
you then as it bubbles up Let Yourself inhabit it more
as if you're taking a Mist
sprayer and spraying the mist of this throughout your body your face your body
your heart your mind all around
you all the parts of that your body that needed the
most drenching your yourself maybe it's your
toes maybe the back of the knees that need more spaciousness stability be
playful be playful in your mind
spraying this body and heart with the quality that you're inhabiting and you
like to inhabit more
and may our practice serve as a cause and
condition for more stability more
peace more groundedness more
civility in our world for all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may
all beings be free including
[Music]
myself thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so I'd like to invite you if you would uh before we turn if you want
to share that word u the one word that came up for you at the end as I was
inviting you to spray yourself with this word that you found yourself this
quality rather that you found a little more of [Music]
um and I'll share mine put it in chat
um yeah stability stability is mine so you like to share
yours what came up for you a little more
expansive this passion inner peace
ease calm softer solid than love
lightness spaciousness equinity sweet mist of compassion Ah
that's sweet Community
meta sweet Letting Go embodiment oh I'm
loving these qualities that you're all
seeding planting seeds one more grounded love the image of the sand filled blow
up doll toy yes ground it grounded
beautiful thank you all for yeah filling the space with your
care your love your calm your peace dispassion expansiveness everything
Community embodiment letting go so much
goodness so the practice today was about embodiment really just very simple
it's very simple when especially when the mind is feeling overwhelmed by news
by what's happening backwards forwards Etc what if
Future Past oh oh dear heart Dear Heart come to the body come to the body here
here simply breathing in community simply breathing here bringing awareness
to sensations of the body the breath calming soothing gently holding holding
with compassion with care it makes a difference we can have can have these
qualities that um support us and then we can be more upright and available or not
just ourselves to be nonreactive and not
um sunk not sunken in the world but available
for ourselves and others oh couple of last words coming in tranquility and
soothed we have from YouTube YouTube participants thank
you so on Zoom I like to invite us to uh
to take this opportunity to show up with stability with our feet stably on the
earth with our bodies stable with mindfulness of the
body listening internally listening internal external holding space for
ourselves for one another and practicing meta in small groups I'll put it in chat
again this is a review practicing meta
MTA mindfully speaking and [Music]
listening reading mindfully listening and
[Music] speaking embracing compassion especially if reactions come
up staying on topic and the topic for tonight
is as you bring as you bring your awareness to the sense of embodiment to
your breath what's supported you tonight what supported you tonight and and Al
The Prompt also is what quality if you like to share what quality um came up
for you and H and what this quality means to you how does this particular quality that you named how does it
support you the more you explore for your own sake again you're not speaking
for other people's sake you're exploring on your own ah this particular quality
supports me in the following way for example I offered stability stability it
ah my heart feels more stable courageous expanded with stability there's my mind
feels more grounded it supports me and oh the more I talk about
stability Yeah the more I feel it growing my body and heart so you see I'm
modeling how I'm exploring for my own sake this quality so for for you it's
self- exploration your eyes could be open or closed when you're speaking but if you're listening please keep your
eyes open to witness to hold others witness please take turns briefly
sharing concisely and avoiding cross talk giving advice Etc and let's go in reverse
alphabetical order tonight um first name recording uh
according to first name reverse alphabetical order taking care of ourselves eles taking care of one
another um being gentle as gentle as you possibly can with yourself with one
another and I'm going to create the small groups
now okay friends welcome back everybody's back and uh the rooms are
closed so we have a few minutes for for reflection um
yeah you can either raise your Zoom hand or you can um type in chat your
Reflections questions either about the uh practice or the um small groups what
came up
what did you discover as you uh shared you explored out loud the quality that
was meaningful for you
[Music]
Noella I was just so fortunate to be in um a group with the other two people you
know joining us for the first time because you know I've been doing this
continually for a year and usually I was with people that have been doing it for
a long time right and so this time I felt like I could be the one that
brought the you know experience of practicing this wholeheartedly for a
long time and I could be that person that I have always admired in other
people so just saying thank you yay oh heart I I see heart showing up that's
very sweet no yeah isn't that sweet that is so sweet right as we hang in here
with the practice we hang in here and little by little it's it's like walking
in the Mist right you keep walking in the mid uh and you become drenched by
the Dharma you become that person who's who's just slowly slowly walking yeah nothing special yeah just walking in the
midst oh yeah I'm drenched with the Dharma I am that person who's um holding
the space for others and oh that is so beautiful that is so beautiful yay keep
walking and the new people who joined keep walking oh and so lovely to have new
folks joining us in happy hour just makes my heart very happy yay
yay thanks Noella see I thought I saw another hat
and a couple of Reflections in chat to which I'll get to in a moment Diana
oh still muted asking you to unmute there you go
you're unmuted now I I have felt a true shift
today uh last last night as I went to bed but uh this morning I woke up with
it and then I really noticed it tonight and in the meditation it really
um uh gave expression to it the the physical idea of stability a St I forget
the words a stable stance the the body really planted the backr and I felt that
but I have felt that all day today mentally and the shift comes from a
couple of weeks ago going around with true fear and my heart and anxiety just
uh nervousness and fear and I um so I began
to a little bit Peak and cheat and start to look at NE uh numbers today and and
after a while I could see that there were some big numbers here and there
whatever what and the shift was I began to have a real curiosity and it's still
there with me it was more like I was looking like this stage or that St I started to thinki wonder who these
people are in this state I wonder what they're like what their causes and
conditions were uh they voted by couple hundred thousand this way as opposed like that I
I wonder what that's about and it was just quite simple it wasn't with any
judging it was just more I wonder yeah I wonder what's there and that other St I
wonder I wonder who everyone is it was more like that but in in a open Curious
way I don't have an answer but um I I
just felt just open that was the change on yeah
wow thank you for sharing this this is exactly it Diana beautiful because when
judging or you know with judging mine we're judging oh othering others they're
different they're this they're this bad you know whatever you know the mind can
come up with lots of um uh judgments and yet to be curious to be C bring
curiosity well human beings just like me I wonder what is their causes and
condition just like me cause this curiosity this stance o it it softens
the heart and really that is that is the way to um heal heal
heal ourselves really heal ourselves through curiosity oh beautiful thank you D I
just love hearing about your shift yay thank you thanks Diana thank
you Richard I see your hand I'm going to come to you in a moment I see a couple comments that came into chat um HMA said
practicing what is as is helped me nice nice what is it is what it is it's like
this right now it is what it is this practice of equinity great that's a very
helpful phrase and Mary says to let go of
wanting my feelings and body paints to be different nice nice to let go of
wanting my feelings and body pains to be different to let go of that pushing away
of wanting things to be different letting go of that pushing away letting it be so Richard I will come back to you
because I think you spoke yesterday I'm going to go to Serena first so pulling back pulling forward hearing more voices
Serena please thank
you actually I show the practice I've been coming here for a year I think at
least a year now pretty pretty continuously and um I really uh saw the
fruits of the practice this morning and I was so grateful what arose within me
was um first I was a I was a a bit upset to
hear the news because I worked at polls and I was so tired last night and we
hardly had any breaks I was so exhausted I woken up at 4 in the morning worked
until 8:30 or or thereabouts pretty much no nonstop and um when I heard the news
this so I didn't stay up all night last night so I just went to sleep and when I
woke up and got the news I
um I um I first felt a little bit upset and
then I felt a l a lot more upset when my nephew sent me a a text related to this
which was really um difficult test text and uh so at a certain point I said
you know I drew a um a line and I said I'm not having this conversation with
you by text I'm sorry I'm not doing that and so that was kind of the turning
point for me it was the turning point and
um I got this Tranquility because I saw that this was
causes and conditions in other words instead of instead of being kind of uh
you know uh just kind of entangled by all the these ideas about why this
happened and this and that and the other thing it was
like causes and conditions the conditions were such what this got to
happen and somehow I got some equinity and some
Serenity and I was able to just you know have my um have my courage
back beautiful yeah I have the courage to say well what is my purpose in life
what is it that is it what is am I suppos what am I supposed to do in you know in any situation not only in this
situation and I gave me the courage to just go and do what I needed to do to remember what to remember what my
beautiful remembering what's important I love it thank you Serena thank you so much for sharing this is this is quite a
um yeah Milestone I'm hearing that this is a milestone and I so appreciate you
hearing with the community um it is a milestone to to almost go down the
rabbit hole with a family member of like getting it and and then oops pause stop
not not this is not skillful I will not do this and this is what the Buddha teach is there four wise efforts the
four wise efforts one of the four wise efforts is abandon abandon UNH wholesome
states that have Arisen and you abandoned a UNH wholesome state that was arising in text with with your family
like abandoned we're not going there and when you abandoned it you um there was
this understanding of you know there causes and conditions that had because of this that arises because of that this
arises and this is what has arisen and then what I love at the end you shared is connecting with your um values what
what is what is my value what am I here for um what can I do what can I do with
what I have the capacities I have with the time I have with all the skills that
I have what can I do connecting with your Val oh this is so uplifting it just
makes me so happy Serena thank you for sharing this this is this is lovely
thank you this is great thank you and Richard it's got to be quick one
minute I just want to say that I just don't have the energy for fear anger or
hatred I love it oh my God that's great well said you just don't have the energy
for the he for fear hatred and anger yay love Love Takes so much less energy
though it's so much easier to love and yeah beautifully said thank you Richard
and fit within the the time we had so we have come to the end of our time thank
you all for your practice thank you for your yeah for your presence cultivating
your hearts away from unskillfulness ha away from hatred and fear and overwhelm
cultivating presence care love stability our
values you give me hope thank you all may all beings everywhere be happy may
all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone thank you so much