good morning thank you Christina and Jill and Beni and Nancy and of
course to Gil and Andrea for the invitation to be here today and thank you to you all for being here uh let's
start out by I like to call it Fellowship um if you could turn to your
neighbors and say Hi and then um also also also also wait wait wait I'm very
control ring I'm a social worker so um uh also tell them what is your value
today what is your guiding value today
oo go for it don't forget your names though unless your name is a value
[Applause]
what's your name Phyllis and what's your
value okay I almost heard it [Applause]
[Music]
[Applause] [Music]
all right I could just leave and you guys could finish that it work that's
probably more important so uh my name is Reverend lean
shut uh my pronounce is and all right today uh gosh uh school
has started for many people be themselves or their
family and also just some shifts in life
and things and so I thought I'd talk about what's important uh uh so I want to talk about
the PRI excepts uh I will say that being an
Asian and monastic person uh that though I have practiced
meditation mostly in the convert Buddhist scene
um where actually we think meditation is first but really in most of the Buddhist
World precepts are first and uh before you do a retreat you
take the precepts but in terms of studying and learning uh and I like G um
ordain uh fully ordained in the soosan tradition and uh of course when we get
Dharma transmission it means we can give the precepts before that you can be a teacher but you can't give the precepts
so it's really important in the Buddhist World um however I'm not going to really
talk about them specifically though of course the five are not killing not
stealing sexy not taking what is not no that's stealing not lying and not uh
intoxicating mind and body or I like to say no killing No
Stealing no peeling like Tak off your clothes no spieling talking right
excessively and no dealing so this is how I try to remember things right no
killing No Stealing no peeling no speling and no dealing so those are those are the basic
five in all Buddhist Traditions um and uh here's I'm both and I again
are from the Shu Zuki roshi Lich and this is what uh Suzuki roshi had to say
about the precepts it's called real precepts are Beyond word
when I say precepts the first thing you think of is something like ten commandments or 10 gra prohibitory
precepts of course in the Zen tradition we have 16 and there are 10 main ones
but Zen precepts is not like that the Zen precepts is to study Zen precept
means to understand zazen so it is another interpretation of
zazen is prep technically Zen isn't meditation it's just being with things
as they are which sounds easy hard to do as we all know using words word precepts
we explain what Zen is actually the purpose of receiving precepts observing
precepts is not just to remember what we should do or what we shouldn't do and
how we observe precepts is to practice Zen or to extend our practice to our
everyday life so the idea of precepts is completely different from the usual understanding
of precepts and when I reflected about how
maybe precepts and meditation are different I actually thought well actually I'm going to make the case that
they're not so different in this way uh so I'm going to talk about three
ways of practicing with the precepts one is called stopping one is called
examining and one is Enlightenment or
actualization so in terms of meditation of course there are two main me
meditation grouping and that would be shamata and theana and shamata is one way to
describe it is stopping stopping you stop to pay attention and so uh in the
precepts as you could see uh they start out with the not right not killing
that's what I just said to you all not not not and the reason for that and a
way that you can call them ethical principles or ethical precepts which is usually what they call or Sila or Sheila
is that um it helps you to stop and pay attention and I also wanted to talk
about it as how I learned this because I think uh it's really important for us to
remember uh the sources of our learning and our practice and so I want to share
some stories from my practices overseas how these ways of working with the
precepts for me um was exemplify so one is uh when I was
practicing at the Trum or bamboo force uh lineage in Vietnam in 2006 and
7 uh so my viames is very bad so here it goes uh Tik tonu is uh was a
when they were young he and tick Nyan practiced together in the pur land tradition and then obviously they went
their different ways and uh Tik tonu stayed in Vietnam and became kind of the
Zen in Vietnam and uh so I was there and I went
for 5 days and stay for six months um and I worked mainly with this one
teacher who had the best English in a nunnery uh the monks and nuns were
separate as in a lot of Asia uh the master lived in the middle and uh but
was a big piece of land and um and so in the NY there between 85 to 100 nuns and
I worked with this one teacher to translate the Master's book into English
and uh so uh you know I when I was there
I had some work they also did what's called sa service if you've been on IRC
Retreat you know you clean the temple a little bit right after the first meditation of the day and um so I
was doing some gardening work and I there was a big pink rose and so I
leaned in and I smelled the rose and a teacher a different teacher
went by and my venies again is bad but then when you're surrounded and I did
pick it up a lot better she was like don't smell the
roses and I was like okay um and by the way um I was told
what to do all the time which I'll say more in the second one so I was like hm
but my vienamese was not good and her English was non-existent that teacher so
at the next time I was working with the teacher that spoke English I said what's up with that CU in English you know we
actually have an expression stop to smell the roses which sounds very you know being in life mindful of your
surrounding enjoying life so what's wrong with that and she said well it's
like this that um the precepts are like
um fences at the edge of cliffs because we tend to be go around and we pay
attention and then we just fall off a cliff if we're overly passionate right and we're we're just too excited so
they're like fences to help you from falling off the cliff into passion so it's true you know if you
really well in my sense it has a truth to it which is when you're very riled up
that's passion we can talk about passion different way but in general passion if you're really riled up you might say
things or do things in ways that you will regret later um
and so these precepts as not really helps you to give a clear boundary
they're like a protection fence to go oops not killing what does that mean not
stealing what does that mean right so they really stop you so stopping right
so that's stopping so the second is examining
or uh you could say vasana which is to investigate now vasana is a not as a
meditation practice is much more about investigating it's actually not um just
like H you know that's not really what you're going for in meditation yes you
want the investigation to be full of the how of curiosity of non- judgmentalness
the quality of mindfulness but as a practice is actually a very um directed
investigation of things or an examination of things right so um the
second way to practice with the precept is what I would term as like compassionate connection how is it that
we interact how is it that I take my sense of what are my values as another
way to understand the precepts and then what is the way that I enact it in life
what is my awareness of how I do it not just my idea of it or be it that it's my
idea or that I've taken in as teachings right uh AA which of course uh teacher
tight Force teacher of many people we know um says in short keeping
CA ethical conduct means watching over yourself
watching over your actions and speech the practice involves establishing Sati
mindfulness within this one who knows the one who knows is that intention of
mind which previously motivated us to kill living beings steal other people's
property indulge in illicit sex lie slander say foolish and ferous things
and engage in all kinds of unrestrained behavior the one who knows leads us to speak it
exists within the Mind Focus your mindfulness or Sati that constant
recollecting on this one who knows Let The Knowing look after your practice use
Sati or awareness to keep the mind recollecting in the present moment and
maintain mental composure in this way make the Mind look after
itself do it well if the mind is really able to look
after itself it is not so difficult to guard speech and actions since they are
all supervised by the mind keeping cila in other words taking
care of your actions and speech is not such a difficult
thing you sustain awareness at every moment and in every posture where
whether standing walking sitting or lying down before you perform any action speak
or engage in conversation establish awareness first you must have Sati be
recollecting before you do anything it doesn't matter what you are
going to say you must first be recollecting in the
mind so mindfulness helps us to
examine how we're going to interact with each other right is it from
decency or sense of connectedness maybe when I asked you all to say what is your
value today right how are you going to actually do that if connectedness say
was your word for your value are you speaking in a way that's connecting are you um interacting in a
way that's not killing someone's interaction with you right so it really
is the how I would say now um my practice in Japan I did go
for an Ango or a rain Retreat um and as many of you know in Zen our forms are
very you know lots of forms um and uh
you one may think right that it's just too much it's just a lot of uh
difficultness you know and I will say in Japan if you thought if anyone here has been in a Zen Center in the United
States that's a convert Zen if you think it's hard try in Japan everything
is you're watched all the time and everything is actually not just in Japan
but in all monasteries in Asia um it's because you're being trained so that
your behavior the way you carry yourself of so much of the directedness is
actually on what's called comportment how do you carry yourself how do you
really take those mindfulness the development of the
zazan Mind Z or the mind that's clearly aware of what is into what you do
because as you all well know right if I say okay time now for cookies or potluck
most of you just get up maybe not even have any mindfulness about how you do it
maybe some of you will but you know a lot of us in these transitions we forget in our actions
when things are busy we forget to pay attention and make sure that we're enacting our values in everything we
do and so that's really important um so compartment and how you carry
yourself is really important
uh I will say for from my uh
experience in Japan um mostly you're instructed on how to do things and you
don't get a lot of praise for it um and it's just do it do it do it um and there's a
lot of practice and uh and yet you know um part of that
culture is just not so much about words it's really about again this sense of
relating in a way that we realize that how we hold ourselves and how we
interact with each other um affect each other and that system and in most
monastic systems you know I will say in my experience I did start out in the Spirit Rock tradition first before I got
into zen um the sense that there's no form and insight is actually not so true
in my experience when you go to practice in Thailand say um uh because if you're
in any Monastery or any practice places there are forms when there are monks and
nuns there are forms and there is hierarchy and that's um on one level you
know in the US we like to think we're all equal which of course is not true true that's just an ideal we have um and
yet when we are clear about our location when everyone is aware that location
matters social location matters then it comes with responsibility doesn't it and
it comes with knowing that if you're in the up power position if you if you're
the Abbot if you're the leader then you your task is to take care of the S and
it and so so how um everyone behaves we
learn to move together and then we like to say as one body this is why when we all turn right
it's so that it looks good doesn't it everyone turning right but also it's so
that you don't bump into each other and say oh excuse me because when you're doing that and someone's meditating you
want to hold the container of quiet for everyone so a lot lot of it is how do we
interact in way that may just seem very unprescribed but it's really about then
we have a sense of location between each other and how we negotiate space how we
negotiate holding things right you always hold everything two-handed in
Zen so and you may think it's just Zen but it's actually again in all
monastic settings uh in fact I can't remember it was my one month or two
month but um that's Spirit Rock what was his name anyway one of the teachers um
oh guy Armstrong I believe don't quote me but I'm pretty sure said that when he went back you know for six months not
not not the first time he went to Burma I think it was where he practiced he said oh yeah so many of the um monastic
precepts are actually how to tie your ropes and how to hold it in a certain
way so a lot of it's just compartment and that's really important
because again it helps you to have a clear awareness of your body heart and
mind as it negotiates itself in the world now I love to look up words so
comportment the noun describe both the way a person behaves and also the way
they carry them M themselves their General manner the compartment of a bunch of
little kids at an amusement park is very different then say you know in the
monastery uh this is from vocabulary.com the French the middle French root is
comp I don't know French comport comportment bearing or behavior and from
the Latin which I also don't know is comport to bring together or collect
now doesn't that sound a lot like mindfulness to bring together and collect right to remember the
collectiveness the recollection of what's important in what you're doing
what is your value how are you enacting it so again our Echo acha you sustain
awareness at every moment and in every posture whether standing walking sitting
or lying down before you perform any action speak or
speech in conversation establishing awareness first you must have Sati be
recollecting before you do anything so that's uh
examining so the Third Way is what I would say as Awakening or as
Enlightenment so now you're like okay with us the two methodology of meditation what's the third
one being with things as they are which is Awakening which sounds easy hard to do
isn't it who here would say that they're awaken
n and yet and yet at least from the Mahayana view you are already awakened
but what is it that keeps you from knowing that right and so so in some ways the other two steps help us to
really realize that we are awaken that in fact Awakening is
life right that we wake up to life as it is right not not as our ideas about it
that's in the mind be the past or the future but really what is right here
that's what Awakening to so Awakening we could say to
wholeness or interconnectedness to Harmony to how
things work as they are so we actualize
or realize this now I want to talk about it in two ways in terms of
practice so again I'll just say um in meditation we say shamata and vipasana
but there are many other kinds of practices are there not for instance
chanting chanting is a very useful and very much part of practice and so um you
know uh I belong to a Gen X teacher group and uh recently and we different
traditions and uh recently someone said hm I want to know from your other
Traditions uh what is a way of talking about
love or about the quality of goodness in life and uh another teacher in a
different Zen tradition Soo Zen but a different lineage said oh well for us it's about
chanting it's about chanting and I was like oh I hadn't heard it said exactly
that way however in our tradition Zuki roshi used to say you chant with your
ears not with your mouth you're like Zen Paradox what does that mean it
means we chant not right we're trying to harmonize with everyone else we're
chanting so that we chant together we're not chanting to say hey I know this that
stuff happens mind you but you practice to let that go let that be and and then
you keep on harmonizing so it's a way in which we can understand Awakening as that we are
not alone that we are interconnected that what each of us does impacts each
other right we harmonize together so that's one way I think that
you can think about Awakening and Enlightenment not doesn't have to be
just some great thought somewhere right or idea somewhere now the other one that
I really learned overseas that I will admit took a little bit of work for me
and that is devotion probably most of you did not wake up today thinking oh devotion is
Enlightenment I actually poo pooed it quite a bit and thought you know that's
a little bit excessive um and uh I when I practiced in
Thailand um and I accidentally I really did uh I
had what's the short version um I was doing my two month at Spirit Rock
and uh though I had just ordained in the Zen tradition but I was like I need I need some silence and I need some
recovery um so I blanch my teacher that let me do the twomon at Spirit Rock plus
I always wanted to do the two months and um and then another Monk asked me to go
practice with sakar in Japan but at the time you know you
couldn't get a Visa um without going through the uh
the the diploma place sry not diploma uh diplomatic and uh so I thought I'd go to
Thailand oh and I wanted to go back to Vietnam uh because the first time I went went I moved back and it didn't work out
so I thought this time I just go as I'm from Vietnam right just go but I wasn't sure I could get a Visa so I thought oh
it better stop in Thailand to make sure I could get a Visa right and also I thought hey that's where the Insight
stuff is so I heard about this one um monk who spoke English and turned out he
was an arot um uh lumu buit is his name um
was 92 at the time and I met him at a
monastery and practiced with him and then on the right I also met some German nuns and lay people and we were in a van
on the way back to Thailand or Bangkok and uh they stopped to drop him off
because it was the rain Retreat so he had a benefactor that had a place for him and all the nuns were like o we want
to see your place can we come in and see your place and so we all got out the van and went
in to see his place and then he had a Salah do you guys know what a Salah is a Sala is like a a place where visiting
monastics um hang out right there are two kinds of Salah one is the open kind
uh and then one he had one that was um screened in that was like a living area
and so uh the two German lay people were like hey can we stay here and practice
with him you know Travelers Are Right In tha One Thailand too uh and so I was like oh I'd like to do that um so we
stay there and then they went off right so I was with him for like five weeks and went to different places with
him and um he turned out he was an arot which I
didn't really know um and he was so famous that when I was there um Tai
airlin send them to Gold Card things so that he could just
decide whenever he needed to fly somewhere they would because he always had an attendant he and his attendant
could just go first class and he was like American Idol but as a
monastic no I'm being really serious because on the week on the weekend just
mobs of people would come and give him a lot of money and food um because you
know he can't cook or he can't even cut an apple right that's that's part of his his whole practice is just a practice
right and that's why he always has an attendant and I also can't handle money for and other things but those are the
main ones so now why am I bringing up except to just say hey I got lucky right
um no not that's not the real reason the thing is you know at first I was like oh and when
people come they would hand out pictures of him and also little necklaces and stuff and I was like wow
this is just like you know and um and I thought wow and there were some people
especially in the weekend really rich people who would come and give a lot of money and then they would come maybe I
don't know occasionally but the thing that really made me understand
devotion because I was there with him every day was that there were some Thai
people so we meditated from
3 to 6:00 p.m. every day 3 hours straight and then from 88 to 11: p.m.
every day so twice a day for 3 hours and the reason we started so late is because
he watched um cable tennis he was obsessed by tennis and also um Chinese
kungu movies and so he and he was 92 so they were like hm you you know you could do
this and then we would just get up later but however people but he still ate the
three meals or two meals and in the morning people some Thai people would
travel for an hour or two hour by bus to bring him his breakfast that they had
made at home because he can't make anything himself right and then they would then go off
maybe for another hour or two on a bus to work work and then they would return
to meditate with him every day of the
week now this is the kind of devotion you know not the American Idol
kind of devotion but really the devotion of
really having the values that someone who is completely dedicated and who the
majority of the people in Thailand really understood to be awaken and someone whose whole life has been
spent in making sure people suffering is alleviated or can
end so imagine if your life was that that was the most important thing and
that you're devoted to that continuity and that
possibility right that's that's a very different sense of commitment to
me right not just showing up to practice but really to make sure that this has
happened [Music] and and to validate and to
honor beings whose life is devoted to the end of your
suffering that's huge you know imagine if the United States
was devoted to the end of suffering imagine if most of the world was devoted
to the end of suffering right to not just the the
values of it as I won't lie I won't you know like a self- practice but also an
interaction practice and then to uphold it in a way that's much more than just
about the self or the interpersonal but as a
system as a cultural system that's
devotion what if that's your devotion
so for those who know me a little bit I really like acronyms or ways of remembering things
easily so I've presented for you stopping examining so stopping like
shamata right really the precepts as way to just go whoa let me just stop a
minute in the habitual karmic tend tendy
my reactive tendency I'm just going to stop then I'm going to e
examine right what is happening here how am I am I acting according to my values
am I interacting with you am I interacting with myself am I interacting right in a way that is about
connection compassionate connection and then the last is
Enlightenment which is C SE right which is that actually the
precepts have to be seen to me it's not enough to just say oh I am a moral
person you know when I um one of my Dharma sisters who became
head monk sh so when you become a teacher in the suen tradition not not to
give the precept yet but to become a teacher her first talk she [Music]
said I ordained to live a transparent life and I was
like oops as I had asked to be ordained and I was like oh wow that's that's a
big commitment that's a big commitment right to live a transparent
life to say these are my value and by the way you take the precepts publicly
because when you're going hey these are my values and I am making the commitment I'm vowing to live in this way publicly
and in the Soto and tradition and I think in all the I know in Vietnam
experience uh uh or nation and the public is invited so anybody can come
usually it's just family members but anyone can come and friends it's because you're also asking the community to
support you to live a life of not killing not stealing not
misusing sexuality not uh taking what is not
giving not lying and not dealing not uh intoxicating mind or
body so it's something that needs to be see
right seen or see I will say I struggle because I also like the acronym C
sea right the C and the reason for that and that's why I put Enlightenment and
Awakening uh or awareness you could say is because I think that last aspect of
practice is to realize that we're actually held in a vastness the sea or
the ocean gives us a sense of vastness that there's something here that's holding
that's connects us all that really supports
us to live a life that's awaken and in fact it's always present
and how is it that we practice to know that to know that we're doing it and to
know that this is a value that's
important so we in some ways you could say we awaken to something bigger than
our individual efforts and yet it does take our individual and Collective
actions that's beyond ideals I I think for me devotion seems idealistic but
it's actually in terms of a practice it's a everyday kind of
practice for my students you know devotion sometimes can sound like faith
and I for my students I like to say faith is strengthened confidence so how do we practice so that
we strengthen our confidence that the end of suffering is
possible that in fact we're already
awakened kir roshi says from a chapter entitled Buddha
mind the Buddhist precepts are not Commandments they are not moralistic
rules that deluded people are expected to obey actually the Buddhist precepts are
not rules at all they should not be seen from a
diluted point of view rather than see them as moral
dictates to be followed we should regard them as indicators of the practice of
Enlightenment they should be taken as the Buddha's mind if you do this you can behave as a
Buddha at the beginning of practice you might believe the precepts are moral
rules but you must learn to take them as expressions of the Buddha's
activity doing so you will study your everyday life and before you are
conscious of it these teachings will penetrate your
life in this way you can live naturally the life of a
Buddha thank you for your
attention all right we have a minute or so if anybody has any questions
I do see a hand but I'm GNA if you generally move back I would invite you
to move forward you all
right thank you I want to ask about uh your Aran teacher yeah and what's your
name Phil Phil what was it like being with him could you tell he was different from the
rest of us um well yes in the sense of all the
people around him um you know acted differently towards him I will
say I mean and also the guy was 92 so already has a certain bearing do you
know do you know and he's been a monastic since I can't remember um he
was 12 or something like that right so a long long time at that point um so it's
so so it's I don't really like to say this um
okay but since you ask I will say I mean we acted in very different whenever we laugh we all would gather and bow and
you know whenever you arrive we would you know a lot of comportment kind of stuff to honor
him and uh and he did speak mostly in Thai so most of the time I didn't really
understand what he was saying but the feeling is different and
then one time as uh he was getting ready to leave to go
do a blessing somewhere and we were all gathered to send him off and uh he made
eye contact not that he didn't make eye contact with me before mind you but he
did make eye contact with me and I will tell you I felt completely seen but there was
no me I don't know how to say it any other way and I can't tell you anything else
except for we connected and there was no me and there was no him and that's all I
can say I don't know maybe I make things up I have no idea um
but yes I would say that I mean I he and sake har roshi and the nun I practiced
with in Vietnam I I find them all to be inlight people and different in different ways of expression
yeah yeah I think there was a
yes yes my name is Rob can you hear me yeah um I have a question you mentioned
word context I don't believe I understood understood the pronunciation
correctly sat is it sat or sake Sati Sati s a t e is you t t thank you that's
all h word for mindfulness right thank you literally means to recollect or to
remember which is more the practice of
mindfulness all right anyone
else okay time for food thank you very
much have a a beautiful day