greetings everyone greetings good morning good afternoon
good evening wherever in the world you are and again it's so lovely to see all the hellos and greetings and different
places coming from different places in the world I'm Nikki mapori delighted to be uh practicing together this
week so uh yeah let's sit together let's let's land and let's sit together
how nice to to sit with uh with sa with Community
feeling ah feeling the presence from all around the world
so beginning beginning arriving arriving
again and again fresh In This Moment
arriving in this body in this
moment might have been thinking doing running [Music]
around in the previous moments leading up to this and here we come we
rest we rest for a
moment allowing ourselves to connect with the sense of
stability sense of stability touching the
Earth with our bodies becoming aware that we are
touching the Earth feeling our feet on the
earth relaxing our legs
feeling your sit Bones on the cushion or the
chair feeling these touch
points this points of connection
stability not just metaphors not just nice things to hear but actually try it really inhabit feel
the the connection to the Earth through these touch
points as a source of balance and stability and
groundedness even before you go to the breath which might be
the go-to for many of us before that really spend time settling into the
sensations of these touch
points and allowing your spine to rise up with a
sense of stability uprightness from your sit bones not pushed up but held
up effortlessly there is an invisible string connected to the top of your head
pulling up pulling up vertebrae by
vertebrae letting there be a sense of ease in your shoulders and your arms
your chest and your abdomen relaxing all these parts I'm naming one by
one your sit bones let them offer their own weight and the entire
weight of your torso to the
Earth your legs too upper legs lower
legs and feet
and allowing awareness to to connect to be aware of the
breath through this body the sensations of the breath the feeling of the
breath the tender music of the breath as if a
violin the bow of a violin
moving moving through across this this instrument of yours this maybe
it's more like a chello it's bigger this body this cello the
breath this body and the breath moving
appreciating not taking any note any any note of this breath for
granted listening deeply to how it resounds how it
vibrates throughout this whole
body one breath one bow movement one note at the
time
e
e e
and if there are thoughts stories [Music] memories what's arising in this moment
to see see it with Clarity it's okay it's all
right it's part of Being Human these thoughts these emotions
memories and for the duration of this s practice
asking them come sit it's okay come I'll pick you up later I will pick
you up [Music] later but for now I'm taking
Refuge I'm putting my trust my
confidence in this practice right now giving my whole heart to it right now as
best as I'm able to to see to see how it develops I would
cultivates I'm giving it my best
so gently lovingly
releasing releasing what takes your heart away not
needed right now coming back to ourselves to this body to this
breath connected to the Earth the sense of stability and ease
softening the heart and the body this
breath breath that plays the music of being alive in this body for limited
time enjoying enjoying relishing this breath
like a sweet
song resonating in the whole
body
e e
I'm going to invite you to drop in three
Reflections to support our practice
today and dropping in these Reflections as if you're dropping a pebble in a pond
the pond being your body not in your head but in your body letting them drop and see what
happens as the pebble settles in the
depths of the pond of the Still
Pond the first reflection dropping it in to our
hearts our bodies our bellies
just like the human being Buddha just like that human being I have
the potential I have the potential for awakening
to wisdom compassion in this life I have the
potential I do have the potential the seed is in me of course it
is I can wake up in this very life
In This Very
life and if doubts and judgments come up see them see what happens if you just
release perhaps the self judgments or doubts just for a second you can pick them up later but just what happens if
you release them and allow
this this knowing this conviction that it is possible for every single person
given their circumstances of their lives to wake up it's possible for me to just
land what happens if you receive
it I can have more freedom May that I can have trust in I
can have more freedom than I do right now it is possible it's absolutely
possible I can have more ease and freedom in my
heart I know it is possible I trust it's possible
and let it settle let this settle in the body in the heart in your
[Music] bones I can have more
freedom I know I can it is possible
more
ease dropping in the second reflection in the body and see what
happens other people have walked this path and have had more freedom more ease
more love more compassion more wisdom I know that I see
that others have done it so it's not impossible I know it's possible of
course and I am supported I'm
supported by others on this path like this very moment listening attending
this I have the support of s I'm
supported by a community I'm not
alone I know
this simply showing up together or supporting one another
I am
supported e
and letting it just drop into your body not to think about it it's not a rumination practice just drop it in and
let the breath Let The Knowing of the breath knowing of the
sensations come from this resonance from this
acknowledgement I am supported through an invisible web by so many by so
many I trust this I know this e
and the last reflection I know I know and I keep
learning more about ways that I can have more freedom I can have more ease be
less reactive be kinder be wiser I know there are ways their
practices their teachings their recipes P I know there are I've tried
them they seem to work and I know there is a lot
more that other people have tried other people have done and have
been transformed I trust this is available these practices are
available or known to humanity
and dropping this kind this acknowledgement into your heart into your
body and letting the breath the awareness arise from it
a path is available I know it
is e
so in short the three Reflections I know there
is a path available to more happiness more
ease more peace the path of
peace I know there is a path of peace
I can walk this path of peace I
can I can have more peace and ease and freedom on this
path I trust I can it's
possible and I'm not journeying alone I'm journeying with others all of us
wanting more peace more ease more happiness more goodness in the
world the three Reflections drop him in and return be with the breath in the
body
e
e e
as we turn your bring this sit to a close appreciating myself this being
who's me who's done their best practicing walking this
path appreciating the teachings and appreciating each other appreciating the
community letting there be a sense of delight perhaps that shows
up from all this goodness your own goodness your own practice doing your
best showing up showing up yay I showed up yay as best as I could I showed up
with others to do what I believe is good for me and the
world may all beings everywhere benefit in ways I can't
understand from from the goodness of my actions the
goodness of my practice may all beings be happy may all beings be
free including
myself everyone thanks for your practice so I'm going to take a moment
and transition the recordings
hello again and welcome everyone especially those of you who are
here for the first time I see how sweet welcome welcome to the community of
practitioners um so so the theme for this week is Sada
Sada the word in poly and uh word maybe I'll put the word
in poly in the chat here it goes
this is s which is uh
translated as um confidence or trust sometimes the word faith is used but but
not so much so confidence or trust and we started with the theme of sadada
trust yesterday as an introduction and now today I'd like to um
continue um and as you perhaps noticed with the theme of the
um meditation today the invitations the
guidance um today's topic will be about the What's called the triple Jewels the
Buddha Dharma Sanaa which sounds really archaic perhaps and and like wait how what does that have to do with me you
know but I'll explain because it's really about our Humanity making it personal before I do that I wanted
to share something I didn't share from yesterday uh kind of leftover uh which is um confidence trust
which is needed for any Endeavor for any Endeavor we need some confidence and
Trust so that we begin we have a trust that oh it is possible maybe it's good
you know some some sense of confidence so that we get started and and also it's needed to
continue this endeavor this practice in this case and one thing I wanted to mention
yesterday is that um it's very important especially in
this tradition that that confidence or sadada just going to use the word sadada
it's it's it's rather beautiful that sadada is uh balanced with wisdom with
PA so that it does not fall into um Blind Faith or gullibility
rather um or to cynicism so it needs to be balanced to
this the sense of confidence with with wisdom
so now with today's topic with the quote unquote the classical language trust or
Sada Sada uh confid confidence trust in the triple Jewel let's unpack that a
little bit so so let's say think of it this way you know if you wanted to start
any um new Endeavor let's say if you wanted to um practice um if you wanted
to learn an instrument to play today I've been talking about the cello right during the guided meditation let's say
the cello okay so so let's say you wanted to learn how to play the
cello um first there has to be some sense of a um confidence or trust that
oh yeah it is possible to play the cello this instrument this large instrument
and huge thing but other people have done it you know there's Pablo Casal you
know these famous there's yoyo ma if you're familiar with the you know cello
players uh roster prish okay these are all the cello players I know I'm done um
you know it's possible people have done it it's possible to learn the cello and you see other people so oh is
possible so when you see it is possible for others somebody else has done it so
um this this instrument is not unsurmountable someone has another human being has done it so it is possible for
me to to learn it's possible for me to Advance at least learn a little bit to to play a little few notes it is
possible so that's that's trust
in the Buddha taking Refuge or having trust in the Buddha here which is oh
somebody has done it there's a human being Buddha who's done that so I know I know that there is an inner Buddha it's
possible for me too it's not impossible he was a human being he wasn't a God and he made that very very clear um
in his teachings that he wasn't a God he wasn't a super you know he was a human being that had who had woken up who had
um practiced and had found the way to more happiness freedom and ease and compassion and and uh yeah
these beautiful qualities of the Buddha so so that's
um that's so trusting that it is possible it is possible uh because
someone else has done it compassion wisdom Purity
Etc so outer Buddha inner Buddha outer Buddha inner it is possible for me
someone else has done it and then and back to the musical
instrument example you know that there are there are ways practice you know nowadays
there's an app for everything right so there's an app for everything or there's you know through the centuries people
have taught have learned how to play the cello right through um the centuries
there there is a way to learn you do the scales right first you do the the scales and then or maybe first I don't know
anything about the well let's see so you you kind of learn how to hold the bow how how how to hold the instrument how
to move it you learn the notes maybe then you do the scales then maybe you do
a simple song and then the more complicated one you know all that so the music theory then you start to learn
music theory get interested in that so there's a way there's a recipe for this it's not like okay there's a sh go it's
there's a recipe ah okay so that's taking Refuge or having trust in the
Dharma the Dharma the teachings of the Buddha uh they've been
developed they they're 2700 years old and there's a recipe there is a way
if you want to become Kinder wiser have more happiness more freedom in your heart uh etc etc more peace in the world
this is what you do you know you sit silently you train your awareness to be
calm you train your heart in meta in loving kindness you practice in the in
between times when you get off your cushion you practice kindness generosity to others there's recipes right these
are you the Dharma is vast there there are a lot of recipes there are a lot of
teachings how to do this there is a way so it's it's just trusting that yeah there they I know they teachings of
course I'm not alone like okay go figure this out okay just become happier and
Kinder um so trusting that there is a way there is a way just Humanity has
figured it out we're not prehistoric like in caves like yeah how do I do this thing um
so so there there is a way trusting that there is a way and then trusting that
other people have have done this okay let's go back to the musical analogy so
so yeah there are lots of people who have learned to play instruments in the world you know you can you know listen
to recordings oh yeah cello player there oh chello player there and you know
there's so many people there cello classes or music schools right lots of
people have done it and keep doing it so you can go you know to uh classes you
can go to meetups right meet up and and share your Technique oh I'm doing this
how are you doing this how is this working right so you have a support of a community you're not the only person in
the world who's trying to learn to cello similarly so that's trust in the sa that's trust in the community I'm not
doing this alone and here with with practice um it's um yeah you're
practicing with a community yay and right now showing up sh showing up with
the community worldwide thanks to technology and YouTube here we are we're not alone and you share your good willll
and your heart gets um uh uplifted there other people there teachers who support
you and and share uh what they've learned what they have practiced so yeah
I trust there is support I trust I trust I'm not doing this alone so this is the
trust in uh that is a path so that's the
Dharma trusting that I'm going to go out of order for a moment trusting that there is a path
they're teachings that other people have done it and it's possible for me I can
do this too I I can do this I can I can I can learn more maybe maybe if it's too
hard sometimes to see I can you know I can be fully awaken maybe that's a little uh it might be accessible maybe
that brings you confidence but but trusting that I can have a little more freedom I can have a little more freedom
kindness for myself for others I can have more peace uh just a little more I
know it's possible I know it's possible because there is a way there's a path there's recipes teachings classes
there's a community yeah yeah so that's trust so that's Sada we just unpacked
the trust in the triple Jewel I know it sounds kind of archaic but that's the trust in the Buddha Dharma
so it's quite lovely oh maybe I'll just since there's a minute left I'll share a couple more things with you and that's
it's very sweet so so uh this just really uplifted me as I was researching this talk so in poly uh there uh these
aspects of these um uh three aspects of the Dharma that that uh are emphasized
Dharma the teachings Dharma are the teachings of the all these recipes um one is aaso aaso
which translates to come and see in come and see for yourself you don't have to
believe it uh magically come and see for yourself for for try it out for yourself
aaso I'll I'll put these in chat so that here um there we go I'm going to put in
chat so that you can see see them you can follow if you're familiar with it I
put that in right there you go okay so aaso inviting you to come and see and
then there is opan opo leading onward onward leading the Dharma these
teachings uh are onward leading they lead on you don't you don't get stuck
they they're onward leading just made my heart so happy onward leading and there
also patam
[Music] to be experienced individually by the wise to be experienced individually in
your own heart in your own Humanity by each and every one of us so
these three um just uh really uplifted uplifted my heart I wanted to share him
with you so so sad ah confidence trust in the
Buddha possibility I can too it's possible to have more freedom to wake up
um have more compassion wisdom um in the Dharma their practices they're well
developed uh and in the sa in the community I'm not alone so trust trust
all right so thank you all for joining and
and your prce practice lovely to practice with you and um I look forward
to being together oh yeah an invitation oh yeah invitation I always like to end with an invitation um notice notice uh
your confidence today throughout the day in Buddha Dharma in and yeah it's
possible I can I can have more kindness I can have more Goodwill I can I can
have more peace yeah maybe I just got reactive right now but it's possible to to behave differently next time I know
it's possible I know sweetheart I know it's possible Right notice that notice your trust in that yeah it's
that these ways these teachings that oh yeah I I sat this morning I felt a little more calm afterwards oh there's
there's a trust there notice trust and notice the trust in the community the support that you receive from others
today in order to become Kinder more more um generous more wise more
understanding less reactive and happier for the sake of all beings may all beings be well may all beings be happy
take good care see you tomorrow quote unquote see you tomorrow