we start with a sound of a bell for our
meditation pausing to let the sound of the Bell fade
away
pausing with a momentary
mindfulness being
present
aware maybe being present with the
sound being present with the
thoughts being present with a global sense of a body
sitting or lying
down
pausing to allow an alchemical process to
unfold
naturally arriving Here and
Now what is the felt sense of arriving for
you just a feeling just
sensing words are not [Music]
necessary for me there is a felt sense of in or slowing
down some energetic feel of energy settling
downwards or the body resting down and resting back
back arriving Here and
Now
a feeling and sensing is innate
capacity within the body within this very
being we simply become available to
allow this being to feel and to
sense
being available have a particular felt sense
to
it
maybe there is a kind of a deeper relaxation and
opening a sense of openness in the heart
space in the
body being available feels like
this
it's as if my nerve systems can
relax
my breath can flow more
EAS and the sensations in the body have more
room to dance their
dance
And the emotions and thoughts have a lots of a space around
them
the felt sense of a being
available is unique to
you at this moment
my words are just some
poters at your own home felt sense is a whole
field don't let my words are your own
limit the whole field of the felt
sense
from there's a field of
availability inviting
aligning aligning with our
aspirations deepest
intentions
aligning with our heart's wish to be
free noticing how aligning feel distinctly
different from available and
arriving staying with a felt sense of
aligning
I often feel a slight straight straightening
up of my spine as I
align kind of inner
uplift sense of dignity
a wholesome
feeling aligning feels like
this right now
here there may be a felt sense of a grounding
or grounded coming
in when we feel we're aligned with our deepest
intentions our hearts can be at
ease maybe even slight happiness
maybe a kind of a
trust aligning with the Buddha Dharma and
s aligning with the Noble eight-fold
Path
stay with a felt
sense our body knows
her heart
knows
sometimes right here being aligned and
available there can be a sense of
collected composed and
unified
the felt sense of the body can come forth
vividly
sounds become
clear in silence are pable
from this aligned and available
field open to
receive the felt sense in the
body and our
emotions and the
mind
you may choose to stay with the felt sense in the
body your FAL sense in the
breath the flow of the
breath
movements
vibrations or simply staying what it Al
liess that's right
here
[Music]
where I am the sound of horing
rain is very full
vibrant when we [Music] touching we alive vibrant
receptive field there can be a kind of a
tenderness it's [Music]
enlightening
in this last moments of our meditation
together reconnect with the felt sense of being
available and
aligned what does it feel like right now
for me a wave of gratitude come
forth knowing that we can always
return to this ground of being available and
aligned [Applause]
so so wonderful to be with you all
um it was really nice to sit in the pouring ring I just notice
that let me start to uh lightening up slightly where I
am so today I brought yet another PR
practice a skill to share and this is um practicing with
felt sense you've heard me a lot using this
phrase um this last few days
repeatedly when I first heard this phrase repeatedly on a retreat some
years ago that are offered by uh the teacher Philip
mfet and he would use this again and again um at some point I thought to
myself wow he really meant
it so you've been hearing me saying this phrase again and again and I'll say that
I really made it practicing with the felt sense
so why am I emphasizing a lot um this practicing with the felt sense
is based on a recognition I think of many teachers um or practitioners would
recognize at some point that um we often practice
mindfulness and practice meditation from a very head centered
orientation we lead our our meditation uh from Concepts ideas
beliefs that we have uh we think we're supposed to uh be
with the breath and then we just kind of a manage and direct somehow um from a
very conceptual framework G sometimes so we use this phrase that or this say this and that we
tend to have a control tower approach uh in our meditation and I resonated with that a
lot um I know for myself and the first um probably one of
the first major breakthrough of my meditation is to come un
awareness that um I was really shoehorning my breath into the way that
I thought it is supposed to be using my mind using my head and I was doing it so
much from this control tower that I was literally suffocating
myself it was not until I recognized that that was happening and all of sudden something
happened I realized oh this doesn't
work I have to let loose of this control tower approach or practicing from this
conceptual framework so that opened a whole new
gradual training gradual learning to let loose um of this orientation of a
practicing and I think I am not particularly unique uh many people have
um uh come to recognition that this was kind of a deeply rooted tendency in
US U Philip in one of his books uh spoke about um uh the effect of a practicing
um or importance of a practicing with a felt sense and I want to read uh this
little portion here and so he said learning to access the felt sense of the
larger dimension ality of a body and mind such that you're able to
disengage from Deep seated habits of viewing yourself and the world strictly
in Concepts you may not even realize how much of your inner experience even in
meditation is based on conceptualizing such that your thinking
mind is acting as a filter between your perceived and your actual
experience um this is a really deep rooted force
and tendency um we human beings kind of
learned this mode of operating from very young so it's not a mistake
and that somehow we're operating in this way even when we come to
meditation and yet there is a cost when we live uh in the world of Concepts and
ideas we want to recognize that the thinking Logics a
conceptualization is one aspect ECT of Being Human but there is also a broader
dimension of Being Human that is not boxed up only by Concepts and
ideas so when we're strictly living through our um uh ideas and beliefs we
can be at odd with our actual
experience the concept and ideas can last for a long time but the actual
experiences of what the concepts are pointing to may be changing very
rapidly and so for example uh the idea that I am an angry
person that's an idea it can last for a long time maybe for sometimes a lifetime
you know we kind of identify by that but in
reality that's not even possible we can't be angry at all the
time that's not possible and that our system is not functioning like that but
we can lock ourselves um by the boxes of the
ideas and so that's a form of imprisonment it's duka you in opposite
of a freedom and so um learning to uh
practice with this um felt sense way is
a wonderful approach to un unwind this kind of a conditioning that we view or
relate to the world uh through con conceptual
Frameworks and so we're cultivating practicing with a felt sense and that
allow us to gradually come in harmony with the reality of our
experiences or in the Dharma phe or come in harmony with the way things
are rather than trying to shoehorn the reality into the boxes of our
ideas so how do we do that uh in our guided
meditation um in the way we're kind of already doing
it um we can become available to what's
here and there is a kind of a deep trust in this inner capacity of Being Human
that can feel our way can sense our way and this is a kind of a primal capacity
in US um even right now for
example as we sit here maybe listening to the words if you just
pause take a moment to feel and sense what's
here what's happening for me I immediately know
there is a felt sense even though I may not necessarily have a words for them I
may not be able to describe it right away but it doesn't Trump the reality of
feeling something and sensing something and sometimes the clear
recognition can come forth as I'm staying with the felt
sense and so from the perspective of our practice it's totally okay and valid for
us to just feel and sense without the necessities of
immediately trying to describe what is
happening and as the recognition comes forth let it
be sometimes the recognition can come forth forth with uh images sometimes
words uh sometimes visuals that's all valid and this form
of recognition is a natural emergence a kind of bubbling up from the depth of
our being from the reality of our experience instead of a top down you
know kind of a we're imposing something on our experience so you can see see the
difference here right and as we practice this way what
can happen is we're dropping out of
directing our meditation we're letting the way things
be letting the way things are to be what it
is and as we drop below our sort of abstract thinking mind um things can get
rather simple andir direct we're less caught up by the
stories of our experience a lot of a wanting mind and not wanting mind tends
to come from the conceptual stories that we have and so um it's actually uh more
conducive for us to get collected unified
composed and another way of saying that is it's conducive to
somebody or or a wealth of inner beauty like a delight happiness and
easeful tranquility and as we stay in this
territory what can also happen is our knowing our
awareness can become more clear because we're less jammed up by uh the rapid
thinking or storytelling and so as we stay in this
felt sense Things become more and more
clear we can allow more intuitive kind of knowing
to surface to Bubble Up and so in this way felt sense is also
conducive uh to insights more intuitive kind of
[Music] knowing and so my invitation for the
rest of the day um is um if you wish
maybe exploring feeling and sensing
um uh the way and that you're going about your life and uh without necessarily making
the conceptual Ling and and and cognizing a problem we're simply
recognizing that uh we're opening to a broader perspective of Being
Human and allow all of those Dimensions to come
alive and so so may you open to all the different dimensions of Being
Human and so thank you for your attention May our practice benefit
ourselves and benefit the whole
world