yeah good morning it is is quite nice to be back here and those of you who
haven't been here much um I've been gone for the last maybe five weeks or
something and um I was away for the month of July and
so For Better or For Worse I thought I would tell you what I did my Su for my
summer and as a um as a kind of background for this talk
maybe as a question for you to carry with you as you listen to the talk or after the
talk is um around the topic that in
Buddhism uh it maybe at least in our tradition it's uh less interesting to
ask the question of yourself who am I than it is to ask the question what is
my nature uh what is natural for us here
and when you ask the question what is natural for you that uh can highlight
the second question what is not natural and this of course raises lots
of interesting philosophical questions and protests very quickly but um but uh what is it that
belongs to the Natural World distinct from the social World distin from the
social world and the mental world we live in where we could construct we fabricate we uh make up all kinds of
ideas in which we live in that we don't question we take it as just this is how
things are and but to start questioning the distinction between what
is natural and what is socially constructed is a powerful way to really
begin going deep into this world of seeing ourselves knowing ourselves and
finding a way to Freedom so that's the background and the reason
for that background for this talk is that for uh good part of the month of
July most of July uh I lived in the wilderness I lived outdoors I was about
10 days I was backpacking and uh for two weeks I was
um uh living in a kind of a nature preserve 1300 acre Nature Preserve and
all this was in the forested mountains and foothills of in northern Oregon
Northern and Central and northern eastern Oregon had never been there before it it's quite beautiful to be
there and for most of that time for three weeks of that time uh I was um a
part of the faculty uh teaching a program called nature Dharma teacher
training and this was a uh we took a group of about
maybe originally maybe about 20 people who had already been trained to be Insight Meditation
teachers and a group of about five people who are had long histories of
being guides uh facilitators for bringing people into the natural world into the Wilderness and backpacking and
things like that and brought them together uh in order to train them in
how to uh be able to offer meditation Retreats uh day longs teaching events
somehow that's embedded in the natural world so some of them were back some
people are offering backpacking Retreats some people are offering what's called stationary camping Retreats you go someplace and somehow and then you stay
at some outdoor place and people are camping and and all the meditation is
done Outdoors all the sometimes the eating is done Outdoors the whole day is SP
outdoors and so uh we were so that was that was the focus of the three of those
weeks and it was a little bit the practicum for them taking them into the Wilderness in order to practice there
and and um and good part of it was actually meant to be a retreat for them
rather than the PED pedagogy of how to do this giving them a deep experience for doing it including three days in
which they all did solos and there solo practice in natural world and nature by
yourself away from everyone is um even even away from themselves just really
alone is can be extremely powerful and in all kinds of ways and in
fact it was to hear them debrief afterwards at the end of this was quite
something and um so that's kind of what I did and uh in a few of those at the
end of it I went backpacking with my wife up there around Mount hood and um one of the reflections I had
this uh for a month living you know living outdoors and Hiking
Outdoors um and much of the time I slept Under the Stars just uh I didn't even
use a tent and um was uh coming across I think
the first this reflection first first began coming across a very big Douglas
fur probably considered an old growth Douglas fur and in much of these forests
that we traveled in we were living in um there was very little old growth there
were beautiful forests but many of them had been planted many of them had just kind of sprouted up after things have
been cut down and maybe bit enough decade since they was cut down that had grown up quite a bit but they weren't
old growth and I remember coming across this the big Douglas fur huge
tall wide big and it kind of took my breath away it kind of like it was in
awe looking at this tree and I felt like I was entered a
whole different relationship to time because this tree must have been around for a long time um both the Timeless now
and that long span of History I felt kind of humbled in the
presence of it I felt a little bit smaller than I usually am and uh I had a very different feeling
of my my relationship to the cosmos to The Wider World by being in relationship
to this big tree that's been around a long time I've I've traveled in places in the
world like in Japan where uh you come across periodically also places where there's
been uh lots of Forestry you know there's mountains in Japan that are filled monocropped with it beautiful
cedar trees but they're there because they've been cut and grown it's a big part of the industry in Japan is to have
cedar trees but then you come across a cedar tree in Japan that is 800 years
old wow and it isn't just you come across a stream it's massive massive
massive trunk and this you know gnarled and big and I mean it's kind of like a
power spot or kind of like this is special this is like something and the
mind can go quiet just like wow and in fact in Japan these trees have become um
worshiped you see there's a little altar in the front of it people put their coins there put water there a little bit
of food there to the tree the tree is not going to benefit from that but uh
maybe but um and they say it's the Kami and there's a wonderful term in Japan
Kami no one in Japan apparently there's no consensus in Japan what a Kami is so
maybe sometimes a kind of a God and God in the natural world the god of the tree
but maybe it's not maybe it's just the natural force the living Force that's alive there that's the Kami maybe what
is doesn't really matter people want to worship it people stop and sit and are
quiet and they they bow to that then and uh and so when I was seeing
this um being old growth Douglas fur in Japan I wonder what it was like that
area when it was full of old growth trees what was it like here in the
peninsula when it was filled with massive oak trees there's a few left
here and there you can see some years ago there was a massive Oak Tree on madale pulus on the corner there that
the city felt was dangerous it was so old they felt it was going to fall or break
branches and Fallen cars or something on the kids there near the school over there and the pro the neighbors
protested the kids protested and the kids made these little altars and put
bracelets around the trunk of the big tree and made offerings and dolls and everything and trying to protect the
tree and finally when they realized they couldn't they do even more kind of things to honor the tree
and I you know the kids had no idea about Kami but you know but they this
was special their relationship to this tree but what if what if most of the
trees here in the peninsula were still here what if there were no homes no
fences what what if there was just you go from from St Carlos all the way down
to Mountain View and it's a vast plane of grasslands and these huge oak trees
with no fence lines what what happens to your site and how you see what happens
to your relationship to the land what if there's very few people there what if
there's some grizzly bears so in U
1792 maybe the fir one of the first English people who came to California
was George Vancouver who was a
Explorer Vancouver up in Canada is named after after him and um and I think he came and
visited the San Francisco Bay area in November of that year he was in San
Francisco and he uh he took a party of people on Horseback and rode down the
peninsula to San Jose and as he crossed kind of the the
the area that's the boundary between uh St Carlos and Redwood City so right here
where we're we're sitting today um he um he described this whole area about 20
miles going south as U uh like an English
park with Old English oak trees so I can imagine being November it
would the grass was just getting green and it must have been spectacular with this big trees and open Plains and
and very few people here the lam chin uh indigenous people of Redwood
City from Belmont down to I think maybe Atherton
and around fi and the bay um they people think there were only
about 350 of them at the time when Vancouver came through this is before the Spanish land
grants happens few years later so what an amazing thing to imagine this
peninsula here where we are here this vast plains with massive oak
trees and what would we like to be here and walk through that what was what happens to your gaze
how you look across the land what happens when you stand in front of these huge ancient
trees would it be a very different experience than you walk down a city
streets in Redwood City and see all the fences one after the other and you look
gaze along One Direction and it's like you can't see very far because there's fences maybe you see 30 ft maybe 10 ft
maybe 5T the houses are in the way there's no Grand Vistas unless you stand in the middle of the street and you're
lucky you know no one runs no one runs you over you you can see way down the asphalt a mile or two perhaps you know
that's maybe nice but um but uh but maybe what you can do
if you're if you're kind of tuned in you look up into the sky and in the sky you
see a Grand View the sky you see the clouds and the vastness of it and that
feels kind of special relaxing peaceful to see but just walking through Redwood
City maybe it's kind of peaceful right now there's a lot of wonderful trees here and so it's kind of nice just if
you like trees but but so what was it like for the Lumin the
natives who used to live here still here around the Lumin there's one family left
of the Lumin that uh indigenous people of this area and one lineage and
um you know what was their relationship what was the relationship
of you know when when the natural world was massive was awesome was
created so much was a kind of a peaceful View and place and when the trees and
the sky and the mountains and the waters and the grizzly bears and everything
were kind of part of the territory in the land does it change how people feel
does it change people's relationship to the natural world there's a change how people relate to themselves how they
understand themselves in that and some of us have gone into
the natural world away from the social world have gone in gone camping backpacking sometimes you know just
going for a Day hike in the Park Nature Preserve here in the peninsula will sh change and shift your relationship to
yourself it's so easy living in a social urban life where all the kind of ways in
which life is organized are socially constructed what we wear where we go how we work the
relationship between the different people that we encounter all belong kind of to a social world that's been
constructed and invented fashions that we have Fashions of what kind of bodies are accepted and
appreciated not appreciated uh Trends and what kind of sexuality and genders are understood and
appreciated and how we relate to them there's so many ways race ethnic
that we have ideas and biased and preferences and and uh bump up against
that are challenging and we the Dynamics between different genders this very rich
social world that's mostly a social construct 90% maybe 80% some percent
that uh if you just go to a different culture you see that the the relationship people have between genders
is is uh sometimes radically different than how it is here in California and
how much of it is socially constructed and how much of it is that we think it's
natural and we go into the natural world away from most you know social things
and it's remarkable how much of this socially constructed kind of spinning of the Mind
quiets down the preoccupations the concerns the he did she did they did
kind of become quieter trying to live up to standards which are belong to our
society or family or the people we have around us quiet down and it's remarkable to be able to
step away from the social world the social constructs and just be able to breathe easily and have the Mind become
quieter and little bit that's what we or maybe a lot of it this is what some of us experience in meditation
that meditation itself is a quieting of the socially constructed
world because that's the quieting of the Mind the thinking mind is mostly that's what it
is and uh and then we discover the natural world in ourselves and just as it is awesome to
encounter an 800 year Cedar Tre or to stand looking out at the
Majesty of Mount Hood which I saw many times in the hiking
trip it's possible to sit quietly and and view the Majesty of the
inner landscape to feel the the the
awe of being conscious and present and peaceful that can be
inside there's a natural world inside of us that's available as well and the capacity to go into the
natural world in order to um uh have the social World calm down is
extremely powerful it allows us to begin questioning and becoming wise about the
constructed world that the mind is usually living in what we we can see more clearly what is necessary and what
not necessary whereas we're always living in the social World always navigating it it all that seems natural
that seems obvious that seems Universal that seems like there's nothing else but the step away from it is
powerful so in Buddhism there's been a very long tradition of practitioners meditation
practitioners going into the natural world to practice sometimes they're called Forest
practitioners uh sometimes they're called Wilderness PR practitioners there different names that they use for uh for
these practitioners and um and in the periods in the many thousands of years of
Buddhist history 2500 years of Buddhist history sometimes whole schools of Buddhism have been revived by the forest
tradition by the the monks and the nuns who have gone into the forest to practice and sometime there's been a
tension between the the Buddhist teachers and practitioners who live in
urban settings and urban monasteries and those who step away from that social world to practice deep sometimes alone
deep in the forests sometimes little monasteries Forest monasteries and uh sometimes that
tension has been creative a useful creative tension and um sometimes it's
been really essential because as I said sometimes Buddhism has been revived by it in our tradition the Insight movement
that we're part of here we are clearly uh uh inherited that some of the uh
benefits that came from the forest practitioners in Thailand and in Burma
in the late 1800s and early 1900s and to give you one dramatic kind of reference
point for this is that uh in the 1800s in
Thailand uh the dominant Buddhism of the time did not believe it was possible for
human beings to become enlightened anymore to have some degree of realization that was not possible and
they weren't oriented around doing that so a lot of the emphasis was in study and preserving the teachings but not
doing deep practice but there were a couple of people who decided oh no this is not
possible uh it's possible and they went into the forest away from the urban
Buddhism of the time and went deep in the forest and practiced for years and came back and said yes it's
possible to have some degree of attainment of realization of freedom and uh the ecclesiastical
authorities of the time in the early 1900s no criticize him no no it's not possible it's not possible what you're
doing is not possible right up until 1950s they were being told you can't
they can't do this but uh the those there was two monks in particular who went and did
this and one of them was a man named aanm and uh and his attainment his
realization really made a big impact slowly and um and among his uh his
people who had a big impact was aan sha who went to study with him aan cha was a
teacher for auno aun suito for Jack
cornfield and uh and and this idea that it's possible to practice to the point
of some kind of Deep attainment came out of that and then it became more
popular and by 1950s there was a big shift in Thailand a little bit earlier in decades
earlier in Burma and maybe I don't know when exactly the shift was in in Sri
Lanka but in all these places there was the forest uh monastics who really who
went didn't practiced away from all this that really showed what was possible and
why is it the forest monascus could do this I think part hardly is the support
that this natural world gives us in practicing the natural world teaches us
how to distinguish between the world of social constructs and and the world that's free
of it the natural world also challenges Us in ways that are invaluable for
Buddhist practice going into the Wilderness by yourself even if it's just going to one
day is frightening for some people it's
uncomfortable there are times when it's uh it's championed as a place that's really peaceful and nice and it's
inspiring to go feel the peace peaceful settings of a natural setting sometimes
and people can experience peace sometimes in a natural setting that's greater than any other time in their
life but there's also it's uncomfortable in the natural world there are
mosquitoes Grizzlies there are the weather is not
Cooperative uh you go out and live in the natural world and you know it's not
you know pastoral environments there could be storms and lightning and thunder and and uh fires and here in
California Oregon and Washington these These Days smoke and um and uh I was woken up at
Night by something
chomping they sound like sound like very hard chomping teeth right close to my
head what is that and before I could turn to look two cute little fawns
dashed by me one of the women who was part of the the three-day solo she was sitting
minding her own business meditating and she heard this crashing sound behind her she turned around to see a big bear
running by and another one chose a place to to
uh spend her three days she kind of was very careful and tried to be respectful for whatever was part of the natural
world and and somehow she chose up spot that was kind of the home of a herd of
deer and they kind of like checked her out in the middle of the night they were check out what's going on you know what
who is this person and she wondered whether she should move but you know so you know there's so many things
so the idea of not having the Creature Comforts but to really practice with
renunciation letting go of Comforts letting go of it has to be just our as
we want it to be our preferences and all this this is part of the gift of being in the natural world and for these
Forest monastics who went into the for for us back then they had to kind of let go of so much they had to work with
their fears work with their desires work with their preferences and learn how to let go very very deeply and why is that
useful because if you really want to drop the world of attachments the world
of all these social constructs that we live in and are caught in it really helps to be able to learn to let go in a
deep way to really learn how to be at ease
with discomfort to let go to work with our fear go to the other side of the
fear be in fearful places but not run away and I'll end this talk by saying
that there's a beautiful discourse in this in the ancient teachings attributed to the
Buddha where uh a man comes to the Buddha and says you know something basically
something like this I notice that you and your followers sometimes go and practice in the wilderness in the forest
it's hard to practice in the forest it's frightening to be there and the Buddha says oh yes it's hard to practice in a
forest it's frightening to go in there before I was enlightened I wanted to go into the forest to practice and I
considered yes it's difficult in the forest it's frightening but then he I thought about
myself and I said well if you're not ethical you don't to live an ethical life then it can be frightening to go in
the for Forest but I lived an ethical life so that's I don't have that
fear if uh if I have a lot of the hindrances a lot of desire for sensual
pleasure a lot of aversions looth and toror restlessness and doubt and
uncertainties um anxiety it's hard to go in the forest and uh live there by
yourself and he said no but I don't have the hindrances so he listed at all these things he did this review so I'll go
live I'll go practice in the forest and um and uh and he said I'll go
practice it and I'll work with my fear that comes up that's still left and in
fact the Buddha before was enlightened when practiced in the forest and he he was frightened he got afraid isn't that
nice story we hold up the Buddha as being like perfect and he's never going to be afraid but he was writing and then
it's cute how he he talks about it he says yeah uh sometimes there were you know uh you know these footsteps around
me at night and there was peacocks he he got frightened of the
peacocks walking around and uh but he made a commitment that no matter what
posture he was practicing in when he got afraid he would stay in that posture
until he saw went through the other side of the fear and um and so he had to deal with
peacocks in the biographies out about photographies of these forest monastics in Thailand some of them talked about
sitting and having to confront Tigers you know they were dangerous things and so tigers are roaring around the middle
of the night and they're sitting there and tigers are roaring and they felt really afraid and they said okay I'm
going to sit here and work with this Spar and the ones who
survived wrote wrote wrote biographies biography
and uh so the Buddha went off and um you know dealt with his fear there and then
when he work through his fear then this this particular discourse goes on and just describes how he stayed in the
forest and got very concentrated and his concentration had insight and then became
liberated but then at the end of the story he's talking to this man uh and he says well some of you
might think that uh uh I go into the forest to practice now
that I'm fully awakened because I'm not really fully awakened he said that's that's not the case I go to practice in
the forest for my own comfort and my own my own sense of ease and
delight and I do so out of compassion for future
generations and the usual understanding of why he does it for future Generations he wants to be a model an example of how
to practice and to go into the Wilderness to practice and um and so that was
considered to very very for the Buddha a very important way of practicing some of that might be because
back in 2500 years ago they were still living in the bronze ages and it was you know there were no meditation centers
there wasn't no retreat center he could sign up for you know maybe if the Buddha had lived today he would have signed up
for a retreat he would have gone to IRC or something um but uh back then there were
no such things and so the place to kind of really go have the circumstance the occasion the ability to go and be in
seclusion and practice and meditation day after day in a way that really uh
was not caught up and Complicated by the social World it took going off into the forest for a while and he did that and
then he came back and he would go back and forth between these two worlds and that's been the Rhythm for many Buddhist
practitioners down through the centuries the rhythm of spending time in the wilderness practicing and times being in
urban settings and teaching and supporting people and so we don't have a very rich
uh Forest tradition yet in the United States there are some wonderful Forest monastics who are starting that and and
uh and kind of living that way and um but the lay tradition of inside teacher
that we are um that's only it's only about 20 20 years old that some teachers
like Susie Harrington and Mark Coleman had been beginning to exp experiment with teaching Wilderness
Retreats and so they wanted to pass this on to the next Generation so they
created this teacher training program for people to do this and and uh they
invited me to become along not quite qualified for it I never taught things
in the wilderness like they have but they wanted me along anyway and I felt very privileged to be part of it and and
to be been very important part of my practice uh practicing in these
Wilderness settings I spent three years in Los Padres national forests with at
tahara that was all outdoors and in the forest in Thailand and little there I
was in little cies little little huts and uh and uh in one way or the other
natural world has been a big influence on my own practice and my own um
understanding of what freedom is how freedom is possible and what freedom
is so um that's what I did for my
summer luckily I don't luckily I don't have to write an essay on that so um so we have a few minutes
before the usual ending time if any of you would like to ask any questions questions or comments or anything about
this or anything at all you're welcome to do
so so I have a question about the logistics where do you go to the
bathroom oh uh so the one of the guides there five people who are really trained
to take people and keep people safe in the natural world teach them Logistics and how to put tents up and everything
uh she did this beautiful like I don't know it probably was like 20 minute long
talk about pooping in the wilderness and uh everyone was like wow
they never had such a thorough complete you know but all the details you can imagine and it was it was quite of
inspiring and um but um the idea when you go you know in the wilderness that
uh nowadays especially in many places you're supposed to go um leave no Trace
so uh for pooping you're supposed to dig a hole that's fairly deep so people have trolls with them and you're supposed to
bring your toilet paper out of the Wilderness with you so you bring Ziploc bags and you take them with you and then
because you're not supposed to leave anything there and so there's a whole way of doing that and where where to dig your hole and how to make your hole in a
way that doesn't cause problems for later and thank
you I have this theory that one reason or maybe for some people the main reason
that being a forest monastic is helpful toward becoming enlightened or moving toward Enlightenment is that you just
don't have so much stuff that you own that's precious to you and that you worry about
losing house I think all the precious things in your house your decades long
book writing projects or or whatever achievements you're you have to make sure you keep your
Tri but if you lose your trial you can probably borrow one from someone else anyway not so much stuff to be attached
to what do you think you said you know the primary I think I think it's an important
important reason I think that uh to simplify the life life of radical
Simplicity and it's not just because of stuff but it's also because of responsibilities and caring for the work
and all kinds of things quiet down for a while it becomes more and more simple and I think being able to live a
radically simple life uh and uh and it's sometimes easier to do it in the
wilderness and elsewhere but it also takes a lot of preparation because like what do you do for food
and uh one of the people who was doing the program who's a a um a guide kind
of is um is is a is a uh is taken uh survival
courses Wilderness survival courses like in the desert and now teaches that so they really well trained and she all she
brings into when she goes in I think she wears a cloth some kind of clothes but um she goes in with a knife
goes into the deserts or the mountains just with a knife that's and from that she has to figure out how to sleep and
how to create conditions and find food and water and everything and she's skilled mean she mean she's done
programs to learn this so that's very simple but it's also complicated you
have you're busy trying to figure out food and um generally uh like for
example when people did the solo trip three days in the wilderness um it was pretty simple but there were other
people who had prepared food for them and so they packed up prepared food and and food that could can last for 3 days
and had that with them so they didn't have to cook really and actually they weren't allowed to bring anything to cook with and because of the fire danger
and so it was all prepared so that made it a lot easier monastics often live close enough to they have to live
because they can't monastics Buddhist monastics can't keep food overnight so every day they have to get new food to
eat so uh they usually live close enough to a village where they can go and do
alms and receive the food for the day and uh so you know generally the forest
monastics forest life is supported so then that allows this
different kind of Simplicity but we have to appreciate that it is supported so there's a wide Network that has that
supports and allows us to happen and um so like uh so some of these some of the
people in the training program uh are IMC teachers and so I see that in
the future we'll probably be offering more we've already offered some but we'll offer more of these nature
Retreats and maybe even solo Retreats opportunities in nature and my goal is
to at some point be able to offer a month-long retreat in the natural world where people can do solos and be well
supported by teachers but it takes a lot of it's It's it'll it take a lot of uh
background support and and uh upfront support to make that possible so so it's
not as simple as just getting rid of all your stuff and going in the forest yeah yeah not that's not just that simple so
uh living a life of Simplicity to uh to organize that can be
complicated so I don't want to just glor glorify Simplicity without appreciating
that we have this wider World take care of too and we're and it's very well understood in Buddhism that the forest
monastics have to to stay relationship to society because their food their you
know depending on it their clothes depend on it their well-being their medicine they get so they they um so I
think it's important not to create this hard divide between the natural world and the urban world but to see them in
relationship to each other in a healthy way thank
you over here
so I'm a Backpacker also and I have always felt an experience that the
process of getting ready for a backpack is as important as the backpacking itself because you really do have this
you know you have a backpack in a limited amount of things so what do you take in that process of deciding the
values of what is more important and what do you leave behind yes is a really
it's it's I I don't rush through it I it it's a pro it's a really um just that
taking time with that really brings insight and and a new way of looking at
your possessions when you take time to figure out what to take and what not and what
to leave behind fantastic I love love that point it's very important and
um as a little bit an example of this so I did go backpacking with my wife at the end and um for four days we were
backpacking but she was just warming up uh because uh because uh when we finished after 4
days we were going to end up on the Columbia River we were hiking in Oregon towards the Columbia River and then the
next day she was going with was going to a walk the Pacific CR trail from she's
doing it right now from um the Columbia River from the Oregon border to Canada
so she's a through what called a through hiker so she showed up and she said Gil
we were in the I I picked her up at the airport in Portland and we stopped at a parking lot somewhere industrial parking
lot someplace Gail show me what you have in your backpack what you're taking with you
backpacking with me and so I everything goes out not this not this you don't need
this you don't need this I thought I did a really good job keeping it really
simple but if you're through hiker you have idea is to go super light and um so so I was glad she went
through it because it you know lightened up even more but then there was the things I
didn't let go of and um and so then but then you know
why am I carrying this I had uh like for example I brought I brought a Kindle with
me because I thought you know we're sitting around nice to read a little bit or something and she didn't she didn't
say she didn't force me to get rid of the Kindle she might not have seen
it and then you know but I didn't look at the Kindle at all it's like why am I car Kindle's
heavy and um and so so then I got so so it's not only what you got didn't bring
but it's also contending with what you do bring and
yes another interesting thing is was that I um in that with my wife somehow
because in this this thing in the parking lot moving my things you don't take this that that and um I I had my I
had I use contact lens for my right eye and so I had more contact lenses
than I needed so no just and so in that process of separating that out I didn't
bring any contact lenses with me and I didn't know that until we started the trail so that was interesting to be able
to to to spend you know the four days with the you know certain degree of blurry vision as well and um and that
was just part of the learning part of the contending with difficulties and what's going on and I kind of
appreciated that challenge it was kind of nice to be free of
that so so I hope that was nice to hear that I think that uh I'm inspired by
this idea of uh having a a lineage or having a part of our inside meditation
world have a connection this richer connection to the natural world and we'll be doing that I hope over this
next few years because we uh some of you know now we've we're developing a relationship with hidden villa which is
a Nature Preserve in Los Altos Hills they would like us to come there and practice there and teach
there and that gives us lots of opportunities to do uh uh you know
practicing in in the natural world and nature without having to give up our
Kindle or or such things because go there for the day or
for Retreats or something so easy so so um thank you