so so people are still coming and uh we could use this kind of informally if any
of you have any questions that you want to ask about the practice about
practicing with emotions from last week or anything about the meditation or anything on your minds or Hearts about
this
it's all pretty straightforward easy to do sit down sit down close your eyes and
boom you're like in Bliss and happiness and don't have any
questions um I seem to have when I sit down once I get through a few minutes of
mental turn pretty consistent feelings and I think I described a little bit about this last
week um just kind of like underlying anxiety not huge but there yeah um and I
also have a desire for it not to be there sure sure so I'm just I'm wondering how to how to hold those
things well that's the that's the qu that's the good question because hold it means you're not doing
what not necessarily trying to change it change it or fix it or go along with the
desire and then you know try to blast the anxiety out of existence or something so I so just to hold it just
the fact that you have that desire or that wish to hold it that's fantastic
and even to have that wish is the beginning of some different relationship to it right so so we're
kind of looking for a different relationship and that's partly what the mindfulness does it shifts our relationship to these to our desires to
our emotions to our aversions um you know and so and part of the shift is we
learned like as Yu said we hold it rather than go along with it we hold it rather than get involved with
it so so can you answer your own question now that that you said it you
asked the question so well yeah I'm just not really satisfied with the answer though but you why don't
you say say it say what you what you what what how you would answer it by
yourself that the both the anxiety and then also the kind of layer below it
which is the desire for it to be different are things that I can hold
mindfully and just just as a feeling would a physical sensation would be or
or the breath is just to notice it and to be with it great and do you have any sense of why that's that answer is
dissatisfying for you because you're still in the desire to get rid of it little bit yeah totally
so you're not quite holding it you're a little bit also being it I'm in it in it as well uhhuh and um
so um so there's a few things you can do to support this I mean one is um we have
this technique called mental noting that's sometimes used in this practice and that's a a more emphatic way of
knowing what's happening so many times we just know it non-verbally and we're just present with something but
sometimes a fuller acknowledgement of something really makes a difference uh in some cult In some cultures uh you
wouldn't tell people your birth name because in the had some kind of power over you and there is power in naming
things and sometimes just naming we say sometimes I want to name something that's happening here and some difficult
someone names everyone's angry and everybody say oh yeah someone named it finally now we understand why it's so
difficult so the naming of something can be quite useful sometimes uh it also
helps create little bit of distance from it uh so because if you're still in that desire to change it but you you name it
oh there's that desire to change it desire then you're a little bit stepping back and then it's a little easier to hold it
the next thing you can do is to um uh uh you know the rafting so you recognize it
that's the naming you allow it which is the holding and then you feel it
physically so both of those the anxiety where does that in your body if you can find the location where it's centered
then it's easier to hold it like this if it's just Amorphis it's kind of like what am I doing here and the desire as
well if the desire is strong there's probably some tension or pressure or contraction somewhere maybe in the mind
or in the heart or something behind that desire stronger the desire is more likely you'll find a physical coraly and
then again okay there there's something there it is physically now I can connect to it speaks descrition of screen and can
be used to contr only your keyboard thank you already know voice take your
time Jo the KE if you want to learn how the volume's in the top left side on the very top you
got it great okay so
um so um anyway is that enough for this for now is that it a little bit more
satisfying yes good but what I like to be you know
please forgive me if I need to be forgiven that I turned it back on you because that's what we do in this practice we're supposed to learn to find
our own way with it and uh and you kind of did and then I was able to just kind of offer you some you um stop streaming
oh stop streaming okay well just take your time just relax and it'll you people people will log on again who are
online um the rafting is similar to rain which
is another very similar which I know about um
and I'm working on it sort of in another way with my therapist or whatever but
it's it's hard for me she's always trying to explain it to me and we're doing it in her office and I'm always
like you know and I seem to be able to get in touch with what it's about when I'm with her in her office and she's
talking me through it a little but at home or when I'm in like an obset
situation I have a harder time like understanding all four steps yeah
and like what does feel mean like physically like what does it what does it mean to feel like my
anxiety I only know how to like I mean I know it happens here but it also happens so there's so much churning in my head
that yeah so it's possible you're you're not ready to do the raft you have another step to do first and that is if
you just kind of opened up really wide to get the bird's eyee view of what's happening to you what what would you see
that what would you know and it doesn't have to be exact it
could be a very general there times in my practice where the most General thing
I can say because I couldn't figure out what's going on I would say chaos but what would what would the
bird's ey view provide you what would you because because otherwise you you
something's going on that you're going to therapy about yeah so so so what's the bird's eye view of that experience
for you I mean I don't know how else to say it
except for an an anxiety feeling great great so so so so that's your way of
connecting knowing what it is maybe that's enough how could recognizing it
as anxiety be significant step in
itself um well sort of noting it like you were just explaining
uh what else what else would be why how would it be significant just stay there and just continue anxiety that this is
anxiety just kind of stay with it in that simple General bird's eye view how
how could that be helpful for you um well I hope it can be helpful and
like not bringing back up to my head again which is great great because so so there's something about recognizing it
that way that takes you out of your head yeah fantastic and so where's the other place beside your head
where the anxiety is for for you oh just like in my stomach fantastic so then I would I would
recognize being in the stomach more and kind of take refuge there and enjoy enjoy that little bit so recognizing you
have anxiety you can do and that recognition gets you out of your head and puts you somehow in your
belly which is nice so if so then but the anxiety is still there right a little bit Yeah so so then if you
continue that same process just recognize that anxiety and what what happens
next well when I've done it and it's worked it's it's worked it um I feel
calmer I mean I don't feel as in my I mean I feel less in my head and more just with
my body fantastic so it's possible that the complicated thing of raft this
process puts you in your head too much yeah it does like what where am I now and remembering at all that and so it's
not that's not what its purpose is it's easy to do so maybe you're not ready to use it yet you already have plenty going
for you the fact that you know how to just recognize that anxiety gets you out
of your head it puts you in your body a little bit and you get calmer and then
then then just if there's still some remnants of anxiety do that whole process over again and you have your own
process which is quite significant and keep it simple and and not make it a project that's really helpful because I
do think I analyze it and I'm thinking yeah great thank you thank
you okay so welcome welcome back and
um and uh so um we'll start with the
meditation and the idea is today we're going to do mindfulness of thinking and I just want to say that for
many people thinking is one of the biggest obstacles to meditation because
rather than thinking rather than meditating we're thinking and uh and some people confuse
thinking for mindfulness if you're thinking about what's happening so it's this is not thinking about what's
happening in the moment it's a very different process of just being present and seeing without anal analysis or
stories or thinking about it in some way but thinking is the most common thing that takes people away from the present
moment which is where we want to be for mindfulness because of that it's very easy to be frustrated and it's very easy
to be critical about it be upset and some people come to the conclusion I can't meditate because I'm drifting off
so much um I liked I was trying the first day if you remember how it was the first
evening we met I was trying to present this practice as a way you can can't do it
wrong uh all you're asked to do is to recognize what is happening not needing
to have it be different so like for you just recognizing anxiety is almost enough for you you know it's quite
powerful just oh this is what's happening and uh and if what's happening is your mind is thinking a
lot that's the thing to recognize it's that simple oh this is a thinking mind
you could you could go a little bit further and and calculate how much the California electrical grid could be
powered by your thinking because of the how much you think but um but the idea
is keep it simple so oh thinking thinking and it might only last for a
second or two that you came in the present moment to recognize your thinking but uh that is very different
than just kind of barreling along uninterruptedly in the in the train of
thoughts and what we're doing is if you use the analogy of trains for thinking
is uh you know you come you drive your car you're stop waiting at the train tracks for the train cars to go by and
the next thing you know you're on the train cars so you know you have to get off you
have to wait till the next stop and you get off and go back to look for your car and and U but then there's another train
and you get on again and some people stay on the car some people try to get off but they just go to the next
car and so the idea is to but every time you step off is actually quite
significant consider you know for how however old you
are how many uninterrupted moments of thinking have you had so far in your
lifetime two or three four you've had a few probably probably
that's mostly what you do with your thinking mostly your thinking just barrels ahead and goes on and on and on and on and on and on and changes subject
and does different things it's uninterrupted so what's been going on for a whole lifetime is the habit of
thinking and that habit is well honed well developed it's become a habit
almost and um and what's remarkable so it's a habit that's built over many many years what's remarkable is how quickly
that can begin to change um compared to how long you've been doing it but it's not you're not
going to get to see the effects just once twice 10 times 100 times that you
step away from thinking but stepping away way is actually quite a powerful event for the mind and um and it begins
changing something in the mind radically that you're no longer always moving
along in the same track so even if all you can do for a moment is oh that's thinking and you
step away and gets a little bit quiet and then you start again appreciate you
did it you succeeded that was great and now you now you wait for the next chance
to do it and then you do it again and um and uh and then there's a
way then that as be as become we become more familiar with
thinking thinking itself becomes an object of mindfulness it's just as valid as
something to be mindful of as um the breathing as the body as emotions it's
actually very important to develop a mindfulness of thinking and the mindfulness of thinking is kind of like
having having an overview of it or stepping back and and turning around and looking at it from a distance so we can
start to understanding something about the nature of our thinking that's invisible to us if we're just living in
our thoughts all the time we're just going of following along and as you know there are some people philosopher who
said I think therefore I am and some people really their whole identity is
intimately tied to their thinking they would feel like they didn't exist if they didn't think and part of that
reason is thinking is one way we tell stories about who we are have
conversations that puts us into our identity and who we think we should be and uh and sometimes that's built up so
strongly as who I am through those stories that if we don't have this the thoughts to tell us the stories then
it's like we don't exist it can be frightening for some people but uh you're not going to die
just because your thinking mind goes quiet for a while it's like having a hybrid car and you come to the stop and
oh the engine went turned off isn't that nice it'll and you know it's going to turn as soon as you start your gas again
right so it's but it's so nice or the or the hum in the refrigerator stopped ah that was good so it can that can happen
with the thinking mind in different ways so the first thing is just to be aware that you're thinking and to
appreciate just knowing wow my mind is out of the control with with my thoughts
the um there's all these some people have all these stages of developing meditation and the first stage that you
know you've reached something like succeeded and you're on the on the track right track is when you realize your
mind is out of control you know it's it's uh much
better to know your mind is out of control than to have a mind that's out of control and not know it it's actually
very significant even though it's very easy to be frustrated and feel like I can't do it but in fact you are doing it
you've reached the first level so congratulations and um so um and then
I'm repeating myself now then as we learn to kind of settle down and just be able to hold the thinking mind when
that's necessary that um we start seeing that thought thinking is not just a
unitary thing thinking is made up of many compo composite parts so I like to
make I have a new English word and that is thating there's thinking and there's thating thating is just the Mind
produces a single thought oh that's the hum of the heating
heating system just that's like one thought thinking is
when there's a chain of associations that happen and they one triggers their
next triggers their next so the hum of the heating
system probably people think we should have a quieter heating system in Meditation Center probably people now
are being critical and judging me for not getting the right heating system probably I'm failing as a meditation
teacher because of the heating system probably I need to go and move to another town and try to find a you
quieter place people don't know me because and the mind spins right that's
thinking and you know hopefully you're not as bad is my mind but it goes off and running right but a thought is just
a thought that arises but it isn't just simply that it's a thought with Associated ideas that
follow and all these things build on it but it's also that um I can have that thought there's a sound of the heating
system or I could have fear that you guys are going to judge me because of
that sound the fear then gives few food
to the further thoughts that I have in addition because I'm this is
such a important issue for my identity I mean my whole body is going to get tense
like oh this you know and that tension makes me feel uncomfortable and that tension then that
discomfort is something I react against and and that becomes food for more thinking and more thinking so a thought
is just not an innocent little floating sentence in the mind or image in the
mind it also comes along with a stuff that feeds it that energizes it and keeps it going
what's possible is to begin seeing the system the thinking system how it works
what feeds it what we're the physical side the tension that's part of it the emotional side that's part of it and as
we get start getting a hang of seeing what's going on we start finding that we can leave it alone we can stop trying to
fix it or get away from it or stop it and instead of and in that leaving it alone there's space for uh
awareness to be there there space just to know it in a very easy way oh
thinking thinking with fear thinking with tension there's the tension and so
we start seeing these component parts of it and it becomes a whole different game it's a whole different event than what
we thought it was which was just you know you know some important thought
problem we had to figure out by by thinking ourselves through it does that make some sense what I
say so we start uh so it's it's important with this practice to always
remember it's meant to be very simple we'll start this in a very simple
way uh and then as I talk like with raft it can get more complicated because there's so much so many different parts
of it but it's not meant to make it a complicated analysis it's meant to
support uh you by giving you the map of what what is going on inside of you so
you're better able to see it in a simple way if you can't if you don't know what's in there it'll come up from
behind and grab you it'll kind of you know run the show but if you start seeing how the the whole thing operates
then you can step back and find some peace and calm with it and so part of
the what might be complicated today is really meant to just give you the map so you can you can find a way to be simple
with all of it so let's start very simply so take a meditation
posture and I'm going to give you a very simple word to use
that'll help you to stay to be here with your experience right now no matter what
the experience is you're allowed to be just as you want just as you are but one
word I'll offer you is kind of like a little little support like to help you
recognize what is here just allow it to be what's here just oh this is how it is
you they say this word and then just notice how it actually is and then after a while you can say
the same word again as a as a pointer as a support as a put you in the right
place to notice oh this is what it's like now and seeing that this is what it's like
now can be done simply easily like you're holding the experience you're making space for it like that so I I'll
introduce the word to you uh after we settle into the meditation
so gently closing your eyes and taking some long slow deep
breaths
and relaxing on the
exhale settling into your body as you
exhale and then let your breathing return to normal and then spend some time scanning
through your body as you
exhale relax maybe the muscles of your
face soften your shoulders
maybe softening the
belly and then centering yourself on the
breathing being simply present for a few minutes with the rhythm of breathing in
and breathing out maybe noticing how the experience of
breathing in is a different experience than breathing
out for
and then gently in a soft way maybe a kind
way say to yourself the word here h e r
e because you're here recognize you're here and
then notice what your experience is here in
whatever way it shows it self to you there's no right or wrong way to be
here here and notice how it is for
you and you can a nice relaxed Rhythm maybe every
exhale or some Rhythm you can just say gently to yourself
here and notice what is here for you
and when you've noticed it allowed it before the Mind drifts too far away
say here again again doing this again and
again for
if there's a lot of thinking here and then notice what it's like to
have a mind that's thinking a lot
here e
allow yourself to be as you are but don't go Galloping off with how
you are with your thoughts or whatever is
happening pause in the middle of it with the word
here and then recognize what here is for you at this
moment and if here is thinking just know it as thinking
for
for for
and then to bring this meditation to a close notice
first if there's some way you might be different now than you were when we started
meditating has anything shifted for you
and then you can take a few long slow breaths to feel reconnected and to your
body in a fuller way and feel your body against the chair or
the floor and then when you're ready you can open your eyes
[Music]
so and and partly that was and to trying to point out to you the Simplicity of
being present for one moment without agendas without needing things to be any
different but just taking the moment to here and recognize what's here and then
again so it'd be interesting to hear from a few of you how how was that like
for you what what happened to you what was I like to do that what shifted for
you if uh we can have the mic here is up in the
front um so in just going back to the word
here I just initially like you know I'm thinking about the word here and like um
it's just showing up and block letters in my head but eventually it just kind of shifts to where I'm just experiencing
my body there no other way than just like feeling it I'm feeling the way my legs
are bent and I'm think like go back to thinking where I'm like oh that kind of hurts a little bit maybe I need to take
a better position um but just being able to like feel it great that's nice and
and how did did anything shift for you besides your direction of mindfulness
um I mean I I feel more calm my breath slowed down but um I don't know if that
shifted but that that seems is that nice yeah it was good what it was good it was good and and so okay great thank you
okay yeah I noticed that it did interrupt my train of thought um and
what was nice is I didn't you know yes I went back to thinking but I didn't go back to that
same train it was like a different train but then at least I didn't because often
what happens in my mind is this it does build the longer I'm on
this train of thought it does build my anxiety because I'm then I'm trying to
solve all the problems in my you know life right yeah you know on this at
least for this train but so it did help because it it did bring me back okay no you're you're here uh and then I would
be calm for a little bit and then my mind would start again but I think it's fantastic I mean to have that tool to
have that ability to do that is maybe better than the alternative
thank you and it's a skill that you build and you develop it over time and and every time that you um uh kind of
step away from those trains you're no longer feeding it and
so the more often you start just doing that simple thing the the the fuel
dissipates and after a while there's no more fuel to keep the thinking
going but generally the way people live we're like the crazy coal shoveler on the train we're
just like you know you know just constantly we might be saying stop but we're putting more
and more coal in the
engine um so the word here is helpful and it does does bring me back and then
there's a moment of sort of you know empty mind and then I start wondering
what I'm supposed to be paying attention to um oh I'm supposed to be paying
attention to the sensations in my body so that I'm looking for like the sensations you know oh I've got an itch
over here or oh wait a minute here oh yeah yeah oh what am I supposed to be
paying attention to but so so if you then it said the here a little bit faster quicker then here and then the
next here would be oh here is trying to figure out what to
do so if you had done that what do you think would have happened to
you well I'd be noticing what was going on in my brain great that would be a good thing that that's completely valid
and what it also means is that um you're not going along with that thought sounds like you went along with it try to
figure it out yeah where I'm supposed to be right and but if you said oh what's here and oh it's just a mind trying to
figure it out that's all okay and then you're on to the next thing here and then there a sound of the heating
system does that make sense so I'm trying to convey how simple this can be
that can cut through a lot and uh or to say not cut through but say maybe more nicely um help you step away so you're
not in The Fray step away so you're not being pushed pushed around by the thoughts and going along with them and
that was a for me a great example of you were pushed around a little bit by that thought and what I tried to point out
was an alternative was just to recognize you are doing it oh I'm looking for what where where my attention should be
that's what's in the present moment the mind is looking for something oh okay that's it end of
story one more
for me actually it was very very simple it was like a medium around me and I was dissolving in this air in the room and I
was feeling so great so it was easy easier to do meditation this way right wonderful so was was totally like a
medium music Atmosphere fantastic very nice so yes please yeah yeah hi I'm
actually still stuck on the first lecture and I'm still trying to get into the body the mindfulness of the body yes
and um one of the things I've noticed is um is um you know when I come back into
the breathing um sometimes I get a little too concentrated I think I mentioned
this before when I get too concentrated in the breathing then I have to detach myself into uh becoming a little bit
more relaxed yeah uh and that's a tension that I seem to be having all the time and then I've been trying to sort
of relax it a bit um and you know so that's what my dilemma has been a little
bit so do you so so if I I understand you you're saying that you tend to want
to stay focused on the breathing in the body but if you do that it gets a little bit too intense for you yeah that's
right and you and you feel a tension in your body it's you try to relax then yes I'm trying to relax it so that I don't
get too great so to uh to a certain up to a certain point relaxing the body is
really helpful for this process uh the point where we stop we stop doing it is when relaxing has become a
project because it's not easy to do so we now we're really trying we're struggling to try to relax better
tensing to relax better and um and so at before you get
to that point you want to just kind of relax in a sense the practice and say okay what's Happening Here
here is a mind that's intense with the breathing and the body that's getting tense Ju Just keep it that
simple and and almost like you're trying to be very very simple so you can see it
well it's like I don't know the last few years has been cats somehow in my life
and um and if you if you're a stranger to a cat you don't go right up to it and
look it in the eye some cats you really want to ignore it if the first time you go into someone's house and just turn
away and ignore it and then it feels safe to come to you but if you go over and make a project to make friends with
a cat you're in trouble you know you chase it around come I'm my friend you
know so the same thing with our inner life if you make a project out of it
some things you can't it's not they're not going to stay around long enough to see clearly and well so for you to just
simply hear oh here I'm trying to be with a breath here I'm getting tense
don't relax at some point stop relaxing and just be here with how it is
and then you might see that what's what's shy inside of you might finally
show itself and I I don't know you so I'm just making something up but I know people who've done something similar to
you and underneath of it all there's some fear fear of Doing It Wrong fear of
not getting something fear of being left behind all kinds of things fear of doing it wrong and so oh it's
fear as the cat that's shy oh that's what's driving this
tension and this intensity is the fear and now we do so now we find the fear
now we do we we're here okay here fear okay this is what fear is like I'm
with fear now and then what's interesting is it's probably another
cat if but if you you don't make it a project you don't don't don't up don't up to the fear to try to fix it just
here kind of say here and kind of look at it side of your eyes because it might be even really shy and then you find
something else is under that yeah just one other thing is that when I um doke end the breathing could
you can you turn the volume sorry I okay I'll hold it closer so when I doke end the breathing it becomes um you know the
Mind becomes quite focused there's a there's a point at which you know if
it's not getting stressed then it gets very focused and that's when you can actually do the examination that you're
talking about that it's really focused then you can examine you mean yeah so for example some of the lessons that
you've been saying that is you know watch watch the body watch the body you know feel the breath going to the body
like last lecture um so there's a there's a point at which that is very successful that is I can feel the breath
flowing through the body but to get to that I have to struggle with all that tension about getting into the breath
and all of that yeah so so I mean you're I mean you're welcome to do it your way
because eventually it seems to work no it it's kind of it's iffy sometimes it
works and sometimes it doesn't well then then maybe take the slow take the slow route um and uh when it does when it's
not working take a good look at that and something needs to something needs to be settled in you mhm and once that gets
settled then you seem to have some nice capacity to get concentrated that when
when the when the CH what's challenging settles then your capacity for concentration can come in
easier and when we're really settled and we're no longer mind's not bouncing around and wanting all kinds of things
there's a natural steadiness and subtleness of the Mind where the mind gets fairly concentrated like on the
breathing oh just the breathing wow and you you you're probably not
going to believe what I say but it can be one of the most Exquisite experience of life to just be right there coasting
riding on the on the breath coming and going and it isn't necessarily because the breath is such a great thing what's
the great thing is a mind that is in harmony a mind that's unified not
fractured fragmented not scattered the everything comes together the mind
that's come together to be centered on one thing like the breathing can be
Exquisite but you you you don't go there directly because that's the cat will run
away you have to kind of learn this process slow process patient process
here this is what it's like here is fear here this so this is this is a way to
kind of try to convey to you to keep it really simple and and
um so um now we're going to do more complicated or it's easy to think it's
going to be complicated it's going to be like the almost like the raft and uh we're going to do a
meditation where I'm going to try to help you become more familiar with your own process of
thinking not everyone thinks the same way some people think more in images some people in words some people see
words when they think some people um uh
so there's all these different ways that people think and characteristics around the thinking and so kind of to learn the
map of what we can be present for in this simple way I'm talking about it
helps to have kind of had a survey it's like someone says you know like um you
know just just go down down if you ever been to Redwood City just go downtown it's a small little place place not too
many streets just relax you have a good time and you never been there and you
find those alleys and this way and you get lost uh so some so someone says uh it's really easy but I'm going to go
with you the first day and show give give you a tour and then next time it's easy for
you so I'm going to give you a tour and hopefully then you can build on that to be easy for some of you what
we're going to do might be challenging the what you what you'll see in meeting yourself so just know that that's part
might be part of what's going to happen and if you feel like it's uh you it's too much for you you can open your eyes
and you know look at the ceiling or you know count how many people are in the room or something that uh you know you
know helps you settle again if that's the case okay so
um so take a your meditation posture
and if you're comfortable with closing your eyes close them if you prefer to
have them open maybe half open gazing down towards the
floor and as you exhale relaxing the belly
maybe like so the weight of your torso is
settles down to your waist and [Music]
lower the weight of your body settles onto your sitting bones
here feeling the contact with the chair and the floor
as a kind of definitive statement of recognizing you're where
you are where here is you're here exactly this spot
relaxing the shoulders letting the weight of the
shoulders settle towards the
floor relaxing in the face as if the muscles on your face can
fall away from the skull and be held gently by the
skin maybe relaxing around the eyes relaxing the thinking mind behind the
eyes maybe softening in the mind
and then for the next little while you're allowed to
think and let yourself think but as you think know that you're
thinking kind of like you're you're sitting at a table someplace and person table next to you
is talking to someone and you're just there listening hearing
their voice the tone of their
voice so allow yourself to think but just know that you're thinking here a
person thinking
and then notice do you think more in [Music]
words or more in images
or a combination of
both or is your thinking more a form of emotional
processing almost as you think with your emotions
or is thinking a somatic experience
almost or maybe it's all of the above but how how would you characterize your
thinking
and as you're aware of your
thinking you have some relative sense of the speed of your thinking are you're thinking quickly a
lot of thoughts in a hurry are you're thinking in a slow
relaxed easy way
if there's an inner voice that thinks is it a loud voice or a soft voice
if there are images being
projected are they in color or black and white are
they fast or
slow are they imposing or they kind of at a distance
if you think in words have inner voice what's the tone of
voice that you use as you think
if you think in images is there a mood that comes along like mood music or
mood to the images
if there is a tone of voice or a mood just know it here this is what it's
like for these minutes it's okay to be this way just know it here like this
and as you think either in words or images is there any emotion connected to
them any mood State of Mind
if there is an emotion is it feeding the
thinking or is it a consequence of what you're thinking
and when you're thinking is there any tension anywhere in your body associated
with that thinking tension the mind in the face shoulders
belly and if it is that's okay just know it here is tension
what's the energy level of your thinking is it high energy low
energy is it agitated thinking or is it calm
thinking whatever whatever it is it's okay just know it here this is what it's
like
are there any gaps between your thoughts are there times when you're not
thinking at the end of a sentence or an end of an image and if there's a
gap what should like that gap for you
here here without thoughts is like
this for
then as we
continue can you let go of your
thinking can you let there be a pause where the thinking stops for a few
moments letting go of your thoughts and dropping into your
breathing letting go into your body breathing
and then we'll spend a few minutes just mindfulness of
breathing that's very simple just here inhale is like this
here exhale is like
this for
and the final thing about
breathing is that some forms of thinking final things about thinking
Some forms of thinking are more on the the surface
mind the mind that's try helping us to survive and fight and
flight there's a different source for thinking that's not on the surface but
deep inside the thinking that helps us to
thrive thinking that connected to Joy and love and care
and generosity kindness
wisdom that's not about surviving it's about deep sense of
well-being can you in these last few minutes of this sitting relax into your
body see if your attention can drop down some place deep
within can you find a different place to think from a different Center for
thinking or reference point for
thinking where thinking feels more deep and calm
and it's more likely to have your welfare in mind your care
can you recognize that you have maybe different ways of
thinking some more agitated some more deep calm
and then to end this sitting to take a few long slow deep
breaths again feel connected to your body remember you're in this room with
other people and when you're ready you can
open your eyes [Music]
so probably not a lot of you have had a tour of your
thinking so I don't know how well that worked for you but I'm curious to find
out what was what was most interesting for you were you able to follow enough
and find something that was eye openening or new or something that might be helpful
here any any of
you um um initially there was a lot of resistance a lot of what a lot of
resistance like I did not want to go to my mind um and then eventually it just
kind of happened gradually and assigning the word here
there was like a different energy from when we did the first one it was bumming me out I did not like I did not enjoy
that I did not enjoy um you know sitting at that next table
watching my mind do its thing oh um you were annoyed by your mind I was bummed
up by it it was just making me very overwhelmed is it but was it was a different mind than you usually have or
just that it's the usual mind but you got to see it better yes I think that one oh
um and then it was kind of hard to go back into the body after yeah um that's
so I might have said this before but uh in very interesting exercise or way of
approaching the mind if if it's if it's a bummer of a mind that you you have at
least for now um uh IM imagine yourself that you're supposed to be the friend to that
mind and that you're sitting on a park bench and you're there to accept your friend who's having a hard time and
you're just there to listen that's all and it's possible that bummer of a mind
has never really been listened to and maybe something different will happen if you listen not necessarily to
the words and the meaning and what they're trying to say but something deeper than that maybe listening to the
emotion behind it underneath
it this man over here
um yeah I don't like how my mind is either so you're not alone I don't like
how my mind is either um
uh I had trouble with the idea of thinking from not a surface
place at the very end when I said that yeah I was like I don't know what that means yeah yeah of course that's that can
might it was I don't know what that feels like or what that is like I don't
I don't know how to I don't know what that is yeah it's kind of like someone opens he shows you a map of Redwood City
and it shows you oh look at there's a place I'd never never been wow someday maybe I'll go there so I just is a I
give you the map so there's there's other more to discover yeah but uh to not like your
mind is sad actually it's not that I don't like it I just don't like the images that pop up in my
mind oh so you don't like the content of the yeah I don't like the content of my mind so it's un or what I'm drawn to I
guess I should say okay that's interesting it's a little unfortunate I mean it's a little bit you know that we have that relationship but um uh this
practice is to see that and to hold it kindly and to be with it and something
mind begins to change if we don't participate and just go along the old habits
and if and if we it changes because if we can hold it kindly in Awareness here
oh this is what it's like oh this is what it's like not to like those thoughts but let's let let's at least be
present for it and then something begins to shift on you know you don't you don't have to be the one who changes things
the remember the cat comes if you don't try to make it
come yeah I had a very simar sort of experience um and probably my analogy
would be more like peeling back an onion so the surface thinking was these images of things things I have to do things
that are going on yada yada yada and then as we progress towards the end and
you went deeper there's certainly I think um tapping in very similar to you
with U Less thinking more emotion um sorry what more emotion more emotion so
was it was recognizing and um I I I'm a very visual person so it was
images that were uh evocative and I think with your guidance was
helpful in just being able to sit with them um certainly kind of feel them but
I think experience them in a different way fantastic um and I think that that's
probably part of what's drawn me to this is as a way as a practice and as a way a
tool to go and visit some of those things that I um want to sit with and as you said
right sit next to arm around it and good very nice figure it out so the opportunity with
this practice is to be able to see all of who we are eventually to and hold all of it
in this the The Gaze The Gaze of mindfulness all of it in the Gaze of
kindness um and see and visit places we've never sometimes ever seen and some of them it's going to be difficult
everyone's going to have difficulty that's we no no one's free of that have difficult Minds in some sense or other
but to be able to visit the difficult places but also visit the beautiful places and the good places and and to
find a radical different relationship to it all and the radical relationship of
of kind awareness just here this is how it is actually begin Shifting the territory dramatically it's like if you
have a ecosystem in introduce one new species the whole ecosystem changes and so the ecosystem here
changes radically with kindness or radical with just simple awareness because what it means is you're not
going along with business as usual and it makes room for something else to
happen so one of the you know so one of the one of the important parts of this
of this learning this non-reactive awareness that just allows things to be in in the field of awareness is that uh we can
start being with what's difficult for us in a new way we don't have to fix it we don't have to run away from it we don't
have to feel shame about it we can just oh we can just be oh this is how it is now it's just now just here for now and
then something
shifts I had kind of a um I noticed a pattern in my mind that I've noticed before but my reaction to it was
different this time I was quite excited to notice it uh which is this pattern of kind of always looking for what I'm
missing or forgetting or doing wrong or what's going to happen that I don't want to
happen but it was kind of cool to see it and not just to have some distance from
it not to go along with it automatically right but not go along with exactly um
so that was an interesting piece and and the deeper think to me made a huge difference because it allowed me to let
go of that because it seemed to me that was very kind of surface level thinking uh and so that shift to me I don't know
if I was truly thinking differently or I don't know deeper I'm not sure exactly
but it felt like I was able to let go of the scanning for problems great yeah so
I love I love what you said and what I hope is that um now you don't
take it as given how you happen to be thinking some people don't think why
thinking that's thinking is just thinking and I just have to go along with it you know I have no choice mind just thinking and that's the way it is
but there actually there are lots of choices and there's different ways to think different um uh places to think
from in a sense and um and there's a choice to watch it rather than be it and
that makes all the difference so so let me oh one more yes
thank you um the thing that I found most surprising was it's all verbal it's all words and
um when I had thoughts that weren't driven by
emotions just kind of useless meaning meaningless chatter that was just kind of went away and then when it was fed
like you said by emotions it had a different quality to it so was that was most surprising to see the difference
between those two yeah so yeah good so it's possible to notice sometimes that emotions are feeding the the thinking
and sometimes the thoughts are so strong that they they're the ones that trigger
the emotions and I mean it's it's been said by psychologists one of the leading causes of depression is
rumination because we're saying all these things over and over again that if I say once to myself Gil you're a lousy
guy I mean I can get away with that once but you know but it's I don't notice the
effect but if I start saying it you know 10 times an hour 10 times a minute G
you're really lousy you're I mean it's going to start wearing me down and it's bad news and it's undermining and I feel
discouraged and this must be true and and after a while no wonder I get depressed but that's the you know the
constant thing being said and so many people are stuck in these Loops of the same Stories the same thoughts and and
uh it can be so that's where the example where the the thinking impacts the emotions and then
there's sometimes a a circle where who knows with chicken and
egg who knows where it started but uh it just kind of feeds itself and goes around and
around but there are other ways and one way that we have in mindfulness it kind of break breaks the Cycles by just
noticing it this here is a powerful thing it's so simple that some people
think it's ridiculous but here you break the cycles of a lifetime and uh and it's something new
can happen so now I want to review a little bit all this because this emphasis on
thinking here can seem like this is this is the project now you know you're supposed to do this for yourself now
when you meditate in fact you know this is not supposed to be a big
project uh so the idea with this meditation is uh
find something that's your home base your home and I recommend the
breathing the breathing is a wonderful place for many people not for everyone to develop the mindfulness developing
more clarity of seeing develop the capacity to be with something allowing it to be as it is some days the
breathing feels good sometimes not good sometimes you're controlling it sometimes you're not controlling it
sometimes it's shallow sometimes it's deep we're trying to be just here with this
oh here this is what a controlled breathing feels like as opposed to oh no I can't meditate now I'm controlling
it no that's not the point the point is oh here this is what a controlled breathing is
like oh here it's a shallow breathing well it's a little bit embarrassing to have shallow breath in California after
all we have esin here and the humanistic Psychology was born here and it was all about deep you know deep you know know
cathartic breathing and and not having shallow breathing so I'm a Californian fail
failure no just it just shallow breathing and um I want to tell a story
now take if I may side one this maybe kind of drives this kind of Simplicity Point home so I I I lived at San
Francisco Zen Center for many years and uh they had uh people could come there
as guests sometimes and so someone called up back when there was telephones
and um and uh real telephones and um and uh I like to talk
to someone becoming a guest and the woman said well uh Robert the guest manager is not here now he'll call you
back uh Robert called the guy back but he wasn't home so he called later to for
Robert but then Robert wasn't in so he heard that Robert wasn't in he said uh
to the person at the Zen Center well I guess I it wasn't meant for me to
come and the person is enter said no it just means Robert's not
[Laughter] here so shallow breathing it just means
shallow breathing doesn't don't don't make a whole California thing about it
or whatever and um so we start with the breathing and but breathing also is for
many people is a settling it's a comp you get composed it's relaxing to stay with a breath it's for some people it's
a neutral place to be able to direct the see the attention we have is food
wherever we put our attention goes feeds with that thing so if attention's always
going into our thinking that's what we feed so we're feeding something that Buddhism calls us very wholesome and
healthy which is mindfulness of breathing staying with the breath it it it takes some of the food away from the
thinking some of the food away from the tensions we hold and things begin to relax hopefully a little bit but so
breathing is a default but it's not just about the breathing uh if something else becomes
more compelling like really grabs your attention like you know we don't want to struggle between what wants our
attention and the breathing we just let go of the breathing and we go and take
bring our attention to this other thing oh he my knee hurts so here within with
a painful knee here not liking a painful knee here
trying to figure out what to do here with this and after a while
maybe it's no longer so compelling and then we go back to the breathing and um and then something else
happens then maybe there's an emotion and maybe I'm sad and so then oh here sad this is what
sad is like and I feel the sad maybe and then I feel it in the body and then it's maybe it hasn't gone
away but it's no longer so compelling and then we go back to breathing and the breathing is kind of a stabilizing Force
the rhythm of breathing it's calming it's stabilizing and it can help us from getting too too reactive or too caught
up in the different things so you probably don't want to stay too long with the pain or the sadness just uh
long enough to really feel like you've been there for it and then go back to the breathing because if you spend too
much time with any one thing that's difficult or even some sometimes good um
sometimes the attitudes come in about it like we might not realize we're actually thinking about it rather than being
mindful of it we might be in it reacting to it participating in it fighting it or
something in a way that's not useful we don't even see it if we stay too long so
so come back to the breathing so the image uh that I have for this is set of a spider in a
spider's web the spider supposedly sits in the middle of the spider web and waits for something to happen elsewhere
in the web and then when something happens the Spider goes up to visit and see what's going on maybe eat
it so it's said unfortun of the image maybe and then and then the spider comes
back to the center and waits for the next thing to happen so we just sit at the breathing at the middle of our
mandala or web and then when something happens we go out so so thinking is just
one more thing like that so if thinking is really the predominant thing you can't really sit and pay attention to
breathing be because thinking is so strong then just in relax way now now
you can do mindfulness of thinking and it can be very simple here thinking is happening this is what
thinking is like right now but now you have a little bit of the map so just saying here this is thinking might lead
you to say oh here there's tense thinking here there is calm
thinking oh here there's frightened thinking here there's angry
thinking or here there is you know tension in the body around
thinking so so it isn't like you go investigating it's like a project but it's just like oh yeah now I see there's
more going on here there's more to thinking than just the words or the images or the ideas the stories
and then because of how easy it is to be seduced by thoughts and people can
telling themselves thought saying oh this is really great not to be thinking
anymore not noticing that that was a thought so you want to kind of be a
little bit protected from that so just come back to the breathing and be there for a while so there's kind of a
hopefully a nice rhythm of being with the breath being aware of something else coming back to the breath
sometimes you stay with a breath for a long time you get concentrated sometimes you're not with a breath much because
there's so much else going on um but now you have uh what we told taught so far a
kind of a range of kind of the the map of the things that you can be aware of
hopefully in a very simple way it's not meant to be a project it's not meant to be
analysis uh it's just meant to be recognizing what is and then one day you might have this
wonderful discovery that for yourself you discover the difference between
thinking and thought Oh the mind just had a thought
and that's all it was one thought just a simple thought arose and it went wow look at
that it came and it went wow where did it go you don't have to go follow it
don't go don't go looking for it just oh that was a that's what Gil talked about that was a thought I was a I'm now a
ther I was a thinker but now I'm a ther and U and it's kind of fun because
that when it's just a thought it's usually because the mind is pretty relaxed pretty calm pretty peaceful and
and it's very clear that the thought is not a problem you could have the worst thought anybody in the world has ever
had but as long as it just stays as a thought it comes and it goes it's not an
issue as we go along with this practice um thinking uh the nature of thinking
changes in many ways one of the ways is it gets thinner thinner and softer and people
talk about it like a veil that gets thinner and thinner and thinner and that almost almost till it becomes like a
cloud or evaporating Cloud it just as opposed to thoughts being so dense and
full some people who do this uh start be paying attention to all this Works can
notice that when they're calm their mind feels very kind of luminous or clear or
open or wide but if you uh if you get have a really good intense thought about like
locked into something and you and you say what and you start look at what's the mind like now that I'm locked in it
can feel like it's gotten dark or contracted or tight or small in the mind
and that's fascinating just see the way the mind how your mind feels to you in
different kinds of thinking you have all these all this knowledge and understanding of thinking that's more
than just what the words you're thinking the images you have begins to break the
hegemony of the thoughts breaks the kind of the way we're in its power or caught
by it or believe it automatically it break breaks the kind of into something
that's easier to handle easier to be with if there's a really a lot of of
repeated thinking uh a simple process I recommend notice your
thinking see what thoughts what emotions are underneath it are driving
it and then feel those emotions in your body and sometimes the what's most
important is the emotion sometimes thoughts are like the messenger it's like a signpost that says
hey over here I need you over over here but it's pointing to something it's not
pointing to itself it's pointing to the emotion when there's a lot of intense
thinking a going on it's usually because we have some emotional need something inside needs our attention so it's a
it's so that's one of the ways to do this mindfulness of thinking is thinking
what's the emotion and now can I feel that in the body and now that I feeled my body can I
just breathe with it in the body and then the whole thing might become so much simpler to be with just being there
with it so
um I hope that the the the lesson of
Simplicity came through today because I did there was a lot of
new ideas maybe for some of you to hear and um
so I suggest you try it at home this kind of meditation and this is
something you can do with thinking for example you can just do this and you know if there's a you know if you're
standing in line rather than kind of looking at wondering about what chocolate you should not
buy you might uh just oh this I'll just look at my thoughts and what's going on
here get to know it better might be a lot of little occasions where you can do a little bit of Discovery what's your
thinking like like we did today and and what's it like just to let it be but let it be seen clearly and what would be
like to be a friend for your thinking mind sit on the bench and just listen to it and and attend to it and let it
finally be heard sometimes the thinking mind just no one's ever listens to
it so maybe you do see what happens but listen as a friend on the bench not as
being it so thank you and um you Tom is here if
you want to ask questions of Tom I'm here if you want to stay and ask more questions or have some something that
came up that you want to sh uh talk about and um nna is also up there in the
back she is's also wise about the meditation practice and so you have more
support if you want to ask questions and so thank you and next week will be the last week for this five-week series and
I look forward to seeing you