to be with all of you again in in this virtual saana so welcome
everyone for many of us here it might be particularly prominent in our minds and
hearts that things in the world are not the way we want to be with all of you again in in this spiritual
saana I had to mute myself um that things in the world are
not the way we want today and it can be helpful to remember
the teaching that if we're only free when things are the way we want them they
we're not really free it can call in us to practice more
diligently to practice with even more care with more kindness and
compassion to not add any more suffering to this world
in my first few years of meditation you know I found that um it
would take me a while for my mind to settle especially if there's a lot going on in my life um days like
today uh so I accepted the idea that the first 15 minutes the mind would be
restless and that usually after about 15 minutes it would calm I relaxed about it but also what I
didn't realize is that I was ignoring those first 15 minutes as not worthy of
my careful attention I had a
preconception uh that there wasn't anything worthwhile to pay attention to in those first 15 minutes so why bother
with the effort but I eventually came to realize the truth of the teaching that if we're
only free when things are the way we want them then we're not really
free so as my own practice continued to mature I realized that those same
hindrances that showed up in the first 15 minutes the restlessness the
aversion the monkey mind it would show up at other times but maybe it was
easier to see them when the mind was a little calmer so I started treating those 50 15
minutes those first 15 minutes with a lot of respect and with careful
attention and with care they eventually transformed into a valuable part of my
practice the first minute as valuable as the last even if it wasn't
pleasant even if it was filled with sorrow even with a heavy
heart that the moment moment of impatience are as valuable as the moments of
calm and that whatever suffering might arise now it's even more valuable to
recognize it to allow it to move to allow it to move through
us and then the heart's natural response to suffering is
compassion can we meet our own suffering with
compassion when we have a preconception an expectation we don't tend to look
carefully we see the moment through the filters of our preconceived
ideas of our projections we think we know and when we
think we know we miss a lot we close ourselves off as we're not
curious about what we already know and as we bring an attitude of not
knowing of openness we can see things
newly each breath is new each physical sensation is
new each thought or emotion is new
so let's
sit taking a comfortable and alert
posture and softly closing your eyes taking a little time to settle into
your meditation posture
allowing yourself to be centered on your
body contemplating the body
ENT clearly knowing
mindful free from desires and discontent in regard to the
world putting aide hi any ideas or concerns or
judgments not pushing them away just putting them aside for
now arriving here in this
body allowing yourself to experience the moment
newly not knowing what the next moment will
bring letting the sensations be simple as if you're experiencing them
for the first time every moment new
and from within this body you might become aware of your
breathing in the Simplicity of this moment this
inhale this exhale knowing you're breathing
in knowing you're breathing out you might take a few long slow deep
breaths connecting more fully with your
body with a full in breath you might feel the chest expand the shoulders
lift the rib cage open and exhaling it all settles back
in relaxing relaxing into
it relaxing deeper into the
exhales like a wave rising and falling back into the
ocean rising and
falling allowing your breath to return to your natural Rhythm however it may
be and as we breathe you can be aware that the air outside of
her body is the same air inside of her body there's no separation between
inside and outside the air extends out far beyond
our bodies and extends deep inside our bodies to every single
cell inside outside side flowing back and forth connected by
breathing e
resting in the moment recognizing ing whatever appears
and whatever goes away maybe it's the in breath and out
breath or Sensations arise and
disappear thoughts or emotions allow them to come and
go seeing them clearly allowing them to be however they
are seeing them
freshly not interpreting not
evaluating not assuming not adding anything to the
experience seeing them in
simplicity
e
e e
if the attention has wondered can notice it and gently
accompany it back to the breath to the body welcoming at
[Music]
home
e
e e
end the sitting I'll ring the bell in a
moment when I do you might take a couple of slow deep breaths again before
opening your eyes
for
there's a DST parable about a poor Chinese
farmer a long time ago a poor Chinese farmer lost a
horse and all the neighbors came around and said what terrible
luck the farmer responded maybe shortly after the horse returned
but when it did it brought another horse with him and all the neighbors came around and said well isn't that
lucky to which the farmer replied maybe the next day the farmer's son was
trying to tame the new horse and fell breaking his leg and all the neighbors came around
and said oh well that's terrible you'll have no one to help you farm and the farmer
replied maybe the next day the conscription officers came
around uh to conscript people into the army and they rejected his son because
he had a broken leg again all the neighbors came around and said oh isn't that
lucky and again he said maybe in
China when something bad happens people will say remember the old man who lost
his horse the old man understood the not knowing
mind to not knowing can be seen as an attitude of being
open Suzuki roshi said in The Beginner's mind there are many
possibilities in the expert's mind there are few to learn a new skill
easily is to be okay with not knowing when we think we know something already
what's there to learn we don't allow new
information not knowing can be an attitude of not being limited by what we
know not making conclusions and opinions prematurely staying
open there's room to learn room for new
possibilities holding what we know lightly it can bring an intimacy with
what we don't know and it can balanced Balan The Knowing with the not
knowing into an open mind a mind that's open and
interested we can see people newly not based on the
past was one of the a gift the teacher gave me once you know I had a practice
discussion on Retreat and I felt I gave a bad impression of myself I didn't
communicate well I sounded confused and so I came in next time you know and
apologizing for myself and he said oh don't be concerned I I always see whoever comes in here
newly and it was it was such a gift to be seen that way and it was so
sincere and so can we see people newly not based on the past
path can we see situations newly not based on our
projections and not hindered by resistance that it shouldn't be this
way but it's important to appreciate that we're not always able to
meet the challenging things that might arise and what the future will hold with
openness not knowing un certainty can feel
stressful it can give rise to fear to anger to
grief the future is unknown the AR is to meet the unknown no
matter how challenging with sincerity and
kindness and if there's suffering present within us or around us to hold
it with compassion and
kindness if there's fear you can see it intimately not
braced against it but allowing it to course through the body not feeding with ideas and not
pushing it away staying close to the physical sensations of the
fear and allowing it to move through us these moments of
mindfulness bring wholesome quality to the fear the fear moves through us in a
larger caring space as I said the future is
unknown but the unknown can also give rise to
inspiration if we're open and not lost in
projections you ways to respond can
arise several years ago now um when we first had to shelter in place because of
Co you know we saw that as did we see it as bad luck but at
IMC with the openness of not knowing inspiration arose to begin teaching
online to begin teaching these online Retreats these this morning Sana such
good fortune right we can also think of the not
knowing mind of the great Explorer or the traveler going into an unknown
territory and the excitement and wonder that inspires them what will they learn
who will they meet it doesn't mean that they don't get caught in the river or uh
their canoe capsize and uh and meet unfriendly strangers at times times or
get sick but what will they learn what's
new and we can have both at the same time we can have both fear and
excitement or fear and inspiration I saw an interview of um a
world renowned climber free climber you know a free climber to me is the
scariest SP I can imagine you know they climb without ropes in one moment
without paying attention can be uh uh fatal they asked him aren't you afraid
and he said of course I'm afraid the fear keeps me safe but the fear didn't stop him it
didn't overwhelm him the focus of the climb the steady of
Mind allowed the absorption the concentration in the climb the fear was
just a guide that kept him
save about 50 years ago I was having a conversation with a
relative and the subject of hummingbirds came up he was convinced that hummingbirds
never landed into in their entire lives of course for me having seen them
land I knew otherwise and I told them so but he was dead sent on his
opinion had no doubt they understood correctly I knew they're known for being almost constantly active and spending
most of their time in the air but they still rest on a purge or sleep on
one I felt frustrated I couldn't get through to him my heart contracted in Judgment of him I
felt separate from him disconnected and hummingbirds were
completely inconsequential in my life at the time and yet my heart contracted over
something so inconsequential that was just a point of
view so how do we not cause harm to ourselves and others through our views
and opinions can we meet a difference of view without Contracting our
hearts to not cause harm to others or to
ourselves especially when we hold our view as being very
consequential can we hold our own understanding of the situation with
without attachment attachment to views and
opinions is a source of divisiveness between people an attitude of not knowing can
help us keep our hearts open with other people's opinions other ways of seeing
things maybe allowing for a deeper understanding for something new to
arise that doesn't mean we don't have convictions and work towards them but we
can we allow someone to have a view that is distasteful to us to be there without
pushing the person out of our
hearts suuki roshi said not knowing does not mean you don't
know it means not being limited by what we know
and we hold what we know lightly lightly enough that it might
change that we don't contract around to try to protect
it can we understand what we know and not cling to
it not knowing can mean that there's something to learn in the
situation it can allow for disagreement without Contracting the heart
and we be at ease with not knowing what the future will be not adding suffering Now by
projecting what the future will be what it will hold maybe at this moment things are
okay it doesn't mean we don't take action but it means that any action we
take needs to rise out of wisdom instead
reactivity and remembering that the future is Never As We imagine as we
project we might get many General aspects right but not the
experience the me of 20 never imagined this me half a century later it didn't
come close maybe got that gray hair right that's about it
and when we contemplate the much larger context of the universe so much larger than our Earthly
concerns the study of the universe can reveal that no matter how much science
discovers the reality of what's unknown is so much
greater now we might view that with frustration or it might deeply Inspire us in our
spiritual life there's a concept about the
universe expressed by the Sue Indians of what they call the great
mystery the great mystery expresses itself through the universe in every human
animal tree and grain of sand
to not only surrender to something that isn't understood intellectually but to actually rejoice
in it can we rejoice in the great mystery can we stand at ease in the
great mystery and not knowing
I'm going to read a poem by John
Bram there's something to be said for having nothing to say but I don't know what that is or
isn't just as there's something to be known about not knowing which I would tell you if I
could there must be something to be gained by losing a seed of Victory buried in every
failure or else I would not be
here clearly there's something to be desired about being Beyond
Desire as the sages never Tire of telling
us and there's nothing more fulfilling than emptying yourself
out no ground beneath your feet nothing to hold on
to no handrail no belief only this bright self- sustaining
air and the falling that feels like
floating and may the benefits of her PR practice bring peace and kindness to
each one of us and to everyone we come in contact
with whether in person or through our words and may Ripple
outwards spreading peace and kindness to all living beings in this
world so thank you