hello on this uh Monday Monday morning in Redwood City
California as I sit here at the inside meditation center and
uh for this morning's meditation I'd like to evoke the idea of
wholeness that one of the ways to meditate is to sit with with the whole
of what's happening and to begin that way the best that we can a global experience of the
whole show and it means we don't select out any particular thing to focus on but
rather uh in the way that you might
um kind of gaze out upon a mountain in the distance or clouds floating by in
the sky or outer across um the ocean once at the
beach that um there's a kind of just like just uh broad attention wide
attention to include the whole and if the attention falls on any particular
thing just welcome it and say this too is included in the
hole and um and one way of understanding this is that um we're letting our
attention uh be the widest Circle possible within which
all things are allowed to be all experiences are allowed to be equally
without being for or against without welcoming or unwelcoming any
particular experience that's uh happening and um so it's all included
all allowed here and that's just the beginning
uh with that capacity to kind of include everything with almost with the little
saying this too this too is included this creates the conditions
upon which wisdom can operate where Clarity understanding can operate and
where there can be a wise discernment a wise letting go or a wise picking up or
a wise selectivity of where the attention goes it might be the sense of whole
allows us to discover uh like there's a big circle of everything's included we
might be able over time to discover where the center of that big circle is and we would sit at that Center like
a big round trampoline um we would sit in the middle
of a trampoline the trampoline net would sink right there would rest there so we
find that place in the middle of the hole to rest but first we have to just
kind of be at ease with all this too is included so to assume a meditation
posture and whatever posture you take you might have the attitude or approach
it as if your whole body is included some way in which nothing is
left out sometimes if we sit meditating in a
chair and we're sitting with the legs crossed in some kind of casual way that
uh somehow the legs or one of the feet are not really fully part of the whole
process but if the feet are both legs are both kind of squarely there in the chair and knees more or less at a right
angle and the soles of the feet kind of touching the floor everything's kind of more included in
the process in the posture so that was just an example uh but
uh so it's a sit in a way that there's a little bit of
intentionality in the way that you position your body and that intentionality is to begin
including the whole body as part of the bigger hole
and then to begin expanding through that whole wholeness of the
body maybe it' be nice for you to take some deeper breaths almost as if the circles of
attention expand as you breathe
in and welcome everything in as you breathe out
expanding outwards as you deeply inhale and relaxing settling inward as
you
exhale and then letting the breathing return to normal and when there is
tension it's useful to think of that as a way of becoming partial the way
of selecting or cutting off or over validating some part of the
whole and that relaxing the tension starts making room for all
things to be included
relaxation makes space for all things to come into
their native
way breathing normally on the exhale going through the
body and finding places of holding and tension and on the exhale relaxing softening in
the body
a significant way in which we are not part of the whole of who we are is being
overly concerned with our thoughts and stories and
ideas and that over involvement sometimes involves mental or
physical tension or tightness pressure associated with
thinking and if there is as you exhale soften that
tension relax the
pressure soften the thinking mind for
sometimes we might operate with a spatial awareness
awareness of ourselves in space and location it's possible to feel or sense
or imagine imagine the
space around the
body how we're sitting in a particular room particular spatial
situation and to with the eyes closed to feel and
sense beyond the edges of the body the space the room
the around
us and as if that space is the widest Circle of our personal
wholeness anything that happens within that Wider
Circle is allowed to be known and held in
awareness and every particular thing that happens see it as part of the
whole all of who you are one piece
whatever you're feeling emotionally or mentally or
physically maybe it's easier to let it be there if it's seen as just part of a
whole it's accompanied by everything else here and now
and maybe at the center of it all like the center of the
trampoline is the gentle movements of
breathing
for
e
for for
perhaps in these few minutes
left to sit meditating welcoming
all of who we are forgiving
everything putting down conflict and right and wrong and good and
bad success and failure just to sit here in a very
simple
way all things included as we
breathe accompanying all things
for
e
e e
and then as we come to this end of this meditation to
consider how you are now after these minutes of sitting
meditating how is it that how you are now can help
you to have a more friendly caring attitude for other people
is there some way of being present for all of who you
are might from time to time give you the ability give you the
occasion to first and foremost be present for all of someone
else who they are before judgment before needing to
address issues but it take time to allow someone
to be themselves without us imposing any
restrictions or judgments or requirements on
them maybe that's a gift that brings peace and well-being
and respect to others may it be that this meditation
practice we do allows us to enter into the world of
people with greater equinity and respect and
care maybe even reverence for the whole experience of
being human being that others
have the whole exper experience of this difficult and challenging human
life may we see people with care may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello everyone and welcome to Monday and the first talk in this
week's series and the topic for this week will be what's uh commonly referred
to as the eight uh worldly
winds the eight conditions by which people people get caught by circumstances in the
world the winds that they can change and they blow this way and that way and we're battered around by them sometimes
um the victims of these in the way that because of how much we allow them to
take over or impact who we are and I in to introduce these first I
want to say that um it's common enough in Buddhism and meditation circles
to have some idea of uh an ideal state to attain ideal meditation to experience
where we're just kind of floating in equinity we're just kind of feeling so peaceful and at ease and everything
seems so nice and that that's the goal and if we're not there then we're not really
meditating properly and and you know so we have some fault but we have to kind of figure out the secret of how to get
into this kind of blissful State something something like that in contrast to that I think what
mature meditation is like mature mindfulness is not that we're living in
some kind of blissful State all the time when the practice really matures then there's a keen willingness
a keen interest a keen um
welcoming of taking a deep look at at what gets in the way of mindfulness what
makes mindfulness difficult what trips us up where we get
attached and one of the earliest teachings of the Buddha is that what characterizes a wise
person is um they know how they get caught they know understand and are
mindful of their clinging and and um and their their challenges
so isn't that a wise person knows how to be peaceful all the time but the wise person really understands all their
difficulties and that is the stepping stone to peace and we don't want to
bypass that or override it in order to find some degree of Peace but it's by
knowing ourselves thoroughly that we can come to a place of peace and knowing how we cling how we
get caught and so this is a phen phenomenally important part of Buddhist practice and uh there are some people
who prioritize the lofty ideas the wonderful ideas of Nirvana and freedom
and Liberation lofty ideas of compassion and loving kindness and all kinds of things
that are very you know ideals that are very positive and in doing so they
Overlook the basic foundational work of Buddhism which everyone needs to do
including the the most mature practitioners and that
is to kind of take it really understand themselves really understand how we get
caught how we're not peaceful how we're not equanimous how we're not loving and
generous not to understand it with criticism not to understand it with it that makes us a wrong person but rather
this is the means the ways of opening up more it's a stepping stone to free is
stepping stone to not being caught and the way not to be caught is to
understand how we get caught first so there's this deep work that has to happen and not a bypass it's not jumping
over it's not finding some wonderful solution so we never have to address any of our
issues and um so
um so the uh these eight worldly winds are
examples of how human beings often get caught and um so there are there there
four pairs gain and loss Fame
and disgrace or fame and disrepute and
um blame and praise
and p uh Pleasure and Pain so gain and
loss praise and fame and disgrace then blame and praise they're different and
pain and pleasure pleasure and pain so uh the first one is gain and
loss uh the the weather changes all the time when I lived in Tennessee their
saying was if you don't like the weather then um wait five minutes the weather
changes and moves and it's this way and that way and um we for a little while we
gain the Sun and then the Sun goes um uh the party is washed out in
the rain and then um but then something else happens and so there's a gain in
loss all the time uh we gain something new we buy a new thing we new socks soon
enough the socks are old and they have holes in them uh soon enough we lose one
of the socks socks in the washing machine and we now we only have one of the
pair these silly little examples though uh get magnified in all kinds of ways
that we gain and lose gain and lose abilities we gain and abilities as we
grow and we're young and then as we get older uh there's may be more recognition of losing certain things and abilities
there is uh gaining wealth and losing wealth I've known plenty of people who
have um overnight in a day uh somehow or
other uh lost much of their savings and I've known people who were surprised by
suddenly receiving something that they hadn't expected um I knew one person who wanted
to go to college didn't have the money and then was suddenly surprised one day that
there was Anonymous donation that made the college possible and uh so gain and loss that's
built into human life and um and so how
do we relate to those when they come and certainly there can be Mita
some Joy some Delight that healthy gain and there could be some disappointment with loss but as a worldly wind it means
our inner stability our inner Freedom our inner kind of certain kind of Peace
uh is um uh is sacrificed uh in our relationship to them and the way the Buddha talked about
it is that um uh when there's gain we get caught in
welcoming it and approving it and validating it and when there's loss
there's hostility to the loss there's 's opposition to it one translator calls it
there's a rebelliousness to it and um so uh so there's an attitude there's
a way in which we then interact that's more than just a very simple
appreciation or very simple maybe um feeling of that that was
unfortunate but but we're actively involved in approving welcoming this is
great I really like this and this holding on to it maybe building up a sense of self maybe um uh almost
sometimes it's almost like a drug we G gained something and we're pumped up in some kind of way WI a lottery ticket
with lots of money and now we're all excited and elated and and we can't wait
to start buying everything we want to buy and then the next day we find out there was a mistake and our number
didn't win the lottery and and now suddenly we crash and we've not only
that but during the 24 hours there we've spent our savings because we thought we were getting more and now we've lost our
savings because of it then now we crash and are disappointed and and um and uh
Furious and angry with ourselves and and so we swing from one to the other and
it's just swinging and uh and uh back and forth
almost sometimes as a counter reaction to each other backlash swinging one having our hopes up swing the other
direction and having our hopes crash around uh loss gain and
loss and um so part of a wise life a Buddhist wise Buddhist life is to be
cognizant to recognize clearly as it happens through the day now there's a
gain now there's a loss and um and then
what is our relationship how does that affect us have we is the wind of gain
the wind of loss um pushing us and grabbing us and we're kind of riding the
wind or being pushed by the wind or are we being reactive in some way are we overreactive are we um is there an
enthusiasm and an approval and a welcoming that it's a form of attachment and expectation and thinking it's always
going to be this way or um and when there's a loss uh are we
disappointed in some deep way do we sink are we deflated uh do we think now it's
going to be this way and are we angry do we have sense of hostility this is not
fair this is not this way and you know and um and so the pendulum swings and
some people the pendulum swings with every gain and loss and um and in fact
uh it's almost because the pendulum is in one direction that the other it swings as far as it does in the other
direction if we're really feeling delighted and fantastic about the gain
um maybe how lated we are around the lottery um then we have further to
swing uh when with when we realize we didn't lose the lottery and the sense of disappointment is so much
more and um and is there a different way is there a way of recognizing in a wise
way in a careful way in a caring way this is loss this is gain this is nice this is
not so nice but let's not invest so much into it let's not uh uh tie ourselves to
gain and loss and so in his teachings about these four World these eight
worldly wins the Buddha said that someone who is well practiced that they are ready to see
when there's gain that that is also changeable that also is impermanent Inc constant changing
when there's loss that's also in some way or other it changes it'll change
it's in constant my experience of it is in constant I'm in constant things will
change it's not going to be only lost forever something different happens and
this idea of the changeability of our experience in our life for the Buddha uh helps with a certain degree of stability
certain degree of not getting invested in the pendulum swinging to one extreme
or the other and in doing so rather than dampening some dampening us down it
makes room for a deeper sense of well-being a deeper sense of stability
and feeling at home feeling at peace that is has more to do with our
wholeness our fullness our deep inner connection to ourselves that we don't
have when our sense of happiness and sadness is tied to gain and loss in the
world to things that gain and lo we gain and lose as opposed to some deep inner
place that is not about gain and loss but about a sense of at heness peace
stability here with ourselves that is something that over
time that medit meditation can connect us too and the stability the calm the
Peace of meditation can feel so much more satisfying than winning the lottery
um in fact so much so that we win the lottery the attitude might be well let's
see what happens this is maybe nice maybe not we don't know let's see what happens
now or if we uh lose our sock who knows what'll
happen or something more are serious maybe we'll see what happens maybe this is not so good maybe it's not
um but let's just see let's see what happens next we don't know what this is
going to go to so the first of the eight worldly wins is gain and loss and now if this
seems at all interesting for you you might go through the day today for the next 24 hours looking to
see where there might be uh gain and loss um through the day that will teach
you about how you your pendulum swings more than necessary how you react how
you get caught in it and get attached how you're uh overly welcoming overing
approval of a certain gain and overly critical OPP oppositional even hostile
to certain loss so um please do this with care and
respect for yourself and uh human life is difficult and we want to find our way
through this with Grace so thank you very much