okay welcome uh welcome friends so
um yeah nice to uh nice to be with you and uh let's uh let's practice
together e
so get uh get
cozy but not too
cozy so relax relaxed but a kind of energetic openness
to Body
Mind we've asked the question a million times what is it
like to be human but with a kind of
fresh interest curiosity we ask again
sincerity is the willingness to be
surprised by experience by the moment by life
we can never really
anticipate when Insight will arise
so we just stay evenly suspended over this
moment breathing
relaxing waking
up
e
e e
we emphasize uh tenderness and
vulnerability the intimacy with
experience but what's sometimes gets lost in that is
the vulnerability is what
confers
power strength
courage braced against
pain uncertainty that yields a kind of um brittle fake power
but really becoming porest to the
moment letting imperfections flow
through this softens our
heart but deepens or
power soothes our fear
all right
e e
our heart undefended Body Mind undefended against samsara
undefended against the the intensity of The Human Condition
but undefended doesn't uh lose its
Center doesn't misplace its strength
what doesn't and breaks the song lyric
goes so yeah flexible
fluid that's what uh permits
strength strength of our Clarity of our love
just see if you can uh attune attune to a kind of felt sense
of your
power
e
for for
we cultivate a a certain kind of courage in meeting uh This
Moment knowing that the Winds of feeling will blow but they won't blow anything
over
the energetic openness conveyed in our posture openness of our
chest come with May
I make my heart available to the moment
Aristotle said between recklessness and cowardice lies
courage so find that meeting this
moment
e
e e
when you ink at nothing the LC goes got nothing to
lose dharmically meditatively maybe we say
when you claim no
territory nothing to defend you surrender this somethingness
of your being up to awareness
there no uh no more
defensiveness but a lot of
confidence
e
e e
for e
okay
so I'm not uh not a temperamentally patient person that's not my par of me
you know and when I'm doing something uh I don't like like the
dishes it's not a dignified scene tignan would not be impressed how I wash
dishes um someone said to me uh you wash dishes like Poseidon in a bad
mood that's the god of sea and
storms but in other
ways I'm patient for example
I'm [Music] very patient with
pain very patient with my
grief I don't ask it to crystallize into meaning before it's
ready and sometimes we're in too much of a rush and we
prematurely impose some order on [Music] pain and
that does healing a kind of disservice and so I'm comfortable not
knowing what grief means not knowing what it entails not knowing what it asks
of me not knowing how it will change
me leard um Cohen uh I managed to get
Annie def Franco and Bob Dylan in the uh guided here's
Leonard um I Heard the soul unfolds in the chambers of this longing as the
bitter liquor sweetens in the Amber
cup so all this is to say I'm still finding my ground
after November 5th and in no rush to find Hope although
I know I will and I'm in no rush to find equinity although I know I
will and I'm in no rush to make everything feel better than it does
although I know it will and all ad Dharma teacher can do is
really teach their own heart and and hope that it's useful for
at least a few others and teaching is always strid with
the teachers pain and wisdom with their particularity and I I don't want to hide
that nor do I assume that it's right for you and I'm grateful that um there are
many Dharma voices and many Dharma doors and um
I offer what I can and so the Buddha said um the Dharma
is is uh it's found as a kind of middle path and just that is is just is so
genius a middle path and classically that's
between um self-indulgence and self-mortification
uh between you know obsession with sense senses and um and a kind of
useless punishment of of ourselves and um for me in this moment
uh the middle path is something like between melodrama on the one hand and
insensitivity to suffering on the
other and I've no doubt Fallen prey to
melodrama at times the ways that some concern in my
mind collects so much attention and I just lose contact with the vastness of
space of time I lose contact with the austerity of the Dharma
and maybe sometimes I'll I'll look back on notes that I had for some old talk
years ago and I can sort of see in those notes
like oh okay a little a little swept up a little
precious maybe the vastness somehow got lost and maybe I think like
well you know Matthew you were in some awkward intermediate phase you were
whatever the grief hadn't yet given birth to wisdom and love fully you know and um
and so we're invited to become uh disenchanted with samsara
disenchanted and that is so much more radical than we tend to
realize the space that opens
is amazing but middle
path The Other Extreme is a kind of denial or numbness or insensitivity to
suffering some kind of like muffled muffled
compassion and I got into this path because I cared deeply about suffering
you know cuz I felt it before I knew it had a name
right and uh and why should greed hate and delusion only matter when it's
inside me of course the ascendancy of unadulterated greed hate
delusion outside is
harrowing and yeah I agree the Buddha Focus primarily on freeing oneself from
suffering rather than the Dharma as a kind of medicine
for society as a utopian Vision the Buddha never claimed that the Dharma
scals it's not really a treatment for samsara although it has um tremendous
diagnostic power but as far as treatment I I don't
know in giving up on a kind of utopian dreams this
disenchantment actually has made the suffering more poignant rather than
less and a lot of the care and the movement in my heart feels um
feels you know clean pure but even Pure Heart can be
heavy and some of my care is more like the entangled species of care the pain
of the world somehow resonating with my own clinging with my
own fear and that it's not where our deepest love
comes from and so something that's become
clear to me in the last week maybe overdue you know it's kind of
embarrassing to Tim stamp our insights you know but yeah here I
am and something that's become clear is um is there's a difference between sense
sensitivity to suffering versus fear of
suffering and on the one hand I worry very little but in the end I am a fear type
meaning that um risk is dramatically more
Salient than reward for me from taking care
of a child or something I'm very conscious of the ways they might get hurt
if I'm directing a project I'm very conscious of the ways things can go
wrong um I'm awake to suffering to anich to the way the world trembles in all
directions that's part of why I can be useful as a teacher but I'm realizing
now that um I'm more afraid of
suffering than I recognized more afraid of suffering
and to be afraid of suffering is not exactly the same thing
as actually comprehending it comprehend duka the Buddha
said I don't um consider myself uh you know a
courageous person so I've not taught about
courage but that's what's been coming up for me and compassion involves courage
involves certain kind of maybe it's too dramatic to say
fearlessness but um but involves the recognition I was pointing to during the
sit that that all all this talk about and I talked a lot about helplessness
about refining a relationship to helplessness about porousness about
sensitivity about vulnerability about uh
um you know shuddering in the face of harm all of these things right but but we we cannot
lose you know sight of of um the ways in
which all of that actually directs us towards a certain kind of
strength courage maybe ainus described
um I read U described courage as um a
condition of each and every virtue courage is a condition of each
and every virtue and was reflecting on the you know the parames the
Perfections courage is woven through a lot of that
in Dan you know generosity and renunciation and truthfulness in Adana
you know the resolution
perseverance UPA you know there's courage courage
and um and so maybe it's time to find some
of that very fluid Supple strength we call
courage and nothing needs to happen now it's just you know in me it's a kind of
gathering of the energy a pooling of a certain kind of
um strength confidence
love and I I say all this because um for
me I realized like some part of me was just
um tired of being afraid and maybe tired of the ways that
that fear encumbered my love and so the question what what does
love look like what does your love look like when it's less
afraid may be worth
asking so offer this for your consideration and uh
we'll keep uh keep going and keep uh keep tracking the U evolution of your
your heart in this time I'll do the same we'll gather back uh next
week okay wish you well