I thought we would start with a slightly guided sit and then move into
a little discussion so finding your comfortable a
comfortable posture comfortable way to just uh land in the moment here wherever
you're touching
whatever brings rest whatever brings some
ease coming to this
moment feeling that sense of aliveness that comes
can come when we just
allow a little bit of being
heess just arriving
and if you wish receiving that little
relaxation or that nice feeling that comes when there's an
exhale and it ends
and the muscles and the bones maybe respond indirectly by just
giving you a sense of
ah this is
nice this is comfortable
and along with this Comfort there may be all sorts of other
activities of the mind of the
body and they Co they can coexist exist they can be here as
well but for just these few moments giving a little a little weight to that feeling
of ah this is nice just being here in
community now
letting the breath do what it does on its own
and when we're here sitting together breathing together in silence together
for the most part it's like we participate in
something that's going on that's all
about a sense of
balance a sense of calm
the body breathing we participate in this amazing
Miracle of the body just
breathing we don't have to do so much to participate in the body
breathing always have to this just
sense enjoy that little feeling that comes when the fresh
air enters and we can let go into
that release that happens with the exhale
for just a few minutes here we participate in this Miracle of
Life or we can it's an invitation all of
this for
this way to participate in your breathing is a way of being a caretaker
for your inner life
it's a very sacred process to take care
inside of what's going on inside how it
is what needs care what needs
attention caring with just a simple notice noticing of
oh this is so right
now and if we do that while we're resting and
participating in the broad relaxed Rhythm of Life of
breathing it's like that's the context the bigger
context around what we may
notice in terms of thinking in terms
of
emotions body
things there's a big context all the way around and Beyond
within that offers a sort of
care caretaking for
the sounds that come people still
arriving it's just like us arriving again with breathing
easing sensing sitting
calming and holding it
all for
for for
part participating in what's
here allowing what's here to be here taking it
in carefully caringly sweetly
every sound sensation comes as a contact it appears and it
moves changes and Fades
away every touch
sensation has that first moment when it's
sensed every breath every scent that
comes is also
touched sight objects come and they
move and things come in the mind the same
way they first
appear there can be some involvement with
them or
not there could be so much resting relaxing
context maybe even sweetness of the Silence of sharing this silence together
here in
community that whatever comes whatever
sensation at the level of those senses comes and exists in that big
context that we're participating
in that we're breathing with
very respectfully very
tenderly offering a kind gaze
to whatever arises
for for
for
and how we make contact with what
arises how we make contact with what
comes how we tend in our
attention makes a big difference
we can care for it be a caretaker from a very calm
place that we can participate inside in our breathing if it's available
we can give give a lot of
room to whatever arises our mindfulness is very
flexible mindfulness can look at things from very far away if that's what's best if that's
what's most caring or mindful could get very
close how can you see and
sense in a way that allows you to participate in the peaceful broad
context of being here just just being
here with all this space and all this calm
maybe even enjoying
enjoying what's good here breathing
together being
together can be even
stabilizing a stabilizing Stillness
can be even a little
pleasurable to show us how to help us see the how we attend to
things how we
notice
for
e for
for for
e
good morning again and welcome to IMC I know Jill has an announcement and best I
believe
good morning uh my name is Jill and um I sometimes help make sure the potlucks
are pulled together on the last Sunday of the month so everyone is welcome to
join whether you have brought something to share or not and the only thing we
need to do is when our um Talk is finished today um you'd give us a little
bit of time to pull things together in the kitchen before you go right out there and then we'll gather um in a
circle and say a few words about our gathering today before we eat so uh
welcome all and our our teacher is Francisco Gable
thank you welcome back Francisco thank you very much it's great to be
here thank you for meditating together so today I thought I would talk
a little bit about um 12 ways that we 12 new ways that we might be able to look
at ourselves see ourselves or on the CP of a group of 12 new months so that's
always used to feel I don't really think of it this way but it used to feel like a new beginning and it's kind of a new
beginning time although it's uh here in Buddhism our Buddhism things are always
in a beginning since it's beginningless time and endings are included in
that but these 12 ways come from a list called the liberative dependent
arising and um it's a list that uh like I said allows us to
see ourselves so they're about you these are 12 ways that are about you ways that
we could uncover for ourselves I'm going to talk about these
um conditions these 12 conditions and I'm going to talk about them in a way
that I'm going to be looking at another list of 12 things don't worry there's not I'm not going to
just be listing things and you don't have to think of the 12 and the other 12 um this is just to give you the little
framework of uh of how what I'm going to be looking at um these 12 conditions
are are considered beautiful conditions because they're different from the the
conditions that are looked at that cause suffering these are conditions that lead to Liberation and and knowledge of
Liberation and uh the other list leads to well sorrow lamentation pain anguish
and duka so not so happy but that list is very important the list of dependent
arising because the list allows us to deconstruct and take apart all the different ways that human
beings suffer and create suffering and get stuck in Loops of suffering
spinnings of suffering so they're very important because suffering is
um is uh is kind of endemic to human being and um but it's not a given it's
not a given at all the Buddha in um his Enlightenment
there was a quot um small discourse and uh that's considered to be a very old
discourse called quarrels and disputes in this little collection called The Book of AIDS and uh in it he
talked about the quarrels and disputes that he saw everywhere in
society and all the sorrow and lamentation all around him everywhere he
looked there was an opportunity to see anguish and pain
and this is very humanizing for me how the Buddha looked at that and saw the
opportunity to do something about it by the starting first of
all with what sounds like a dramatic expression but pulling the arrow out of
his own heart and pulling the arrow out of his own heart allowed him to have health
ultimate health health from suffering and this is the view that he
took out to the world he saw Enlightenment as an opportunity to to do this deep healing
work there might be some of the most sacred work that we do this caretaking for this in our
life These inner lives and that instead of some
grandiose Enlightenment that may come and that comes in a certain way but
this path points to this Liberation that's that's maybe better to call a
maturation sometimes Liberation can be a little um can be approached in a little magical
thinking kind of a way how people go about liberation and this instead is is
very here in this body in this
mind for this human being for our
communities for our broader communities and for the whole
world so that's the that's really the intention of uh of
looking at conditions and creating conditions that lead to this maturation
to this Liberation and um we were given these things we have these teachings I find I
think it's glorious to me that we have these teachings that show us how we
can create conditions that lead
to happiness joy deep States of bliss samadi
bliss profound ways of seeing deeply inside of ourselves of this mind to
learn how this mind can be absolutely free of all the things that lead to that
path of Anguish so the first conditions are
especially exciting to talk talk about um here at this point at this end of the
year as we're looking at a new year these darkest of
days here in the north not in the South where some of our friends
are but as we look to start a new perhaps and we start a new all the time
so it's not just the new year we start a new all the time in practice every set
every time we connect to the breath is a new beginning in the Buddhist teachings the
early Buddhist teachings that I base my um my talk my thoughts on for this
talk so the the list goes like this the liberative liberative dependent arising
it starts with having a good look at Dua what I've been talking about the pain the unsatisfactoriness of
life and then from there we are invited to
create these sex next necessary conditions and we can do so by looking
at pain and suffering that's what's really interesting to me that if we stop and
really take a look and a caring understanding of what causes our
suffering these wholesome beneficial good beautiful conditions arise
that's the interaction of all these teachings so it starts with Dua then we
move to the condition of Faith then gladness then
Joy then Tranquility then happiness then concentration or
samade so that's called the gladness pentad it's all about being glad gladdening the mind and
the being that then allows the remainder conditions to where Insight really
begins to go forth toward Liberation the next
condition is knowledge and vision of things as they
are then there's a condition of disenchantment that's not the greatest translation for what really happens
there then dispassion then Liberation and then knowledge of
Liberation so this dooka that I've been talking about that can be translated in so many
ways as unsatisfactoriness as pain dread whatever really hurts uh from
human existence so these this gladness pentad
is telling us hey if you stop and look if you just
pause if you really give yourself the time to see this Dua see what is it
that's causing dooka for you here and now who is the little lawyer of the
Mind who's in controlled that's doing this that's
behind this Dua if we stop and look at that
sincerely we come to faith and faith is uh in early Buddhism not a not seen as a
belief system to believe something to trust but it's more about not believing
it's about no longer believing in that mud that muckety mud of
pain because one of the things one of the ways that Dua works is
that it reflects our challenge just back to us as us we are our
challenge we are that suffering so faith is is not believing
that anymore not using that as a reflection and it's called Faith it's
also can be seen as confidence because it gives a purpose
and a direction oh there is another way there is something else other than
being identified with my suffering identified
with all the streams that lead to to those things that are really
stressful are really difficult for human
beings so faith is a is a Joyful Joyful
condition and these are conditions that we they're called conditions because we can foster them we can adopt them we can
know them and create conditions to let them be in place the condition for Faith
to arise is to Simply
notice there is suffering here who is suffering what is the
suffering and right there we're walking the path we're walking the path and we
have a purpose and a direction and we can take this
path and that already begins to liven things up because we're out of that mud
it's not the only way to just be reflecting back all the streams of
everything that is moving through the the daily mind the non-c
contemplative mind these are contemplative conditions not
worldly in a way things so moving out of the stream
of the worldly things which could be called the karmic stream moving into the Dharma stream the
stream of the teachings or the beautiful Karma which is what the
Dharma is called in the anient ancient teachings so Faith once we have this uh
purpose this directions and this stands immediately brings can being
bring on gladness gladness is this kind of
biological imperative that happens once you we say okay I'm going to do a little
house cleaning here I'm not going to really believe that I'm not really going to just be all
of that that which is leading to suffering whatever that may
be and we stop believing the resentments the cynicisms the
anxiety all the attitudes that are not really
helping the cyclical things that keep cycling through the mind so there's
gladness because suddenly there is a standing with something else and it's like a biological imperative when we
turn to looking inside and and doing something about this this's this
biological imperative and now we're in the Dharma stream and this is the beginning of this
gladness pentad that's moving toward greater greater greater Joy greater
greater Stillness greater greater stabilizing of Mind stabilizing
Stillness of concentration
and so that condition of gladness can progress the more we are
sincere with what's there with what keeps coming up the more sincerity we
have with that we begin to look at the fuel of
those those uh those emotions that
aren't working those emotions that kind of keep us tra in more of the same
emotions in more of the same reactive circles there's a fuel there that's
fueling that the tradition calls that clinging there's a fuel that behind that
fire that burns in the anger in the
fear and we we ask what is that fuel we can ask what is that fuel and that puts
us on the path to Joy believe it or not because our joy is trapped a lot by
this by this other fire the fire
of of the vement emotions because Joy has another fire
the more joy we have we experience that fire of Joy the
fire of Joy gives light it doesn't burn us it doesn't burn us
into a burned wood piece the fire of of
Joy brings light to see to understand to know better to know
more to take in more of the goodness that is arising once we're in these
these wholesome contemplative
conditions but it starts with that sincere look what is what is that that's causing
that fuel in me to to be sad to be
worried to be upset to be confused to be buried in this in
this feeling because if we ask if we just stop and ask we're walking the
path it takes a sincere look a supported look we have to be
careful about how we do this of course we're doing this in the context of
contemplation we're doing this in a context to feel reassured that we're on this big path
we're on this ancient path we're supported by many things in each moment
when we participate in the moment with the intention of participating in the
moment because we have to be respectful of our inner life of what hurts of who's
hurt in order to come to these this condition of
Joy so Joy is this uh light
arising very effervescent possibility that's here now can be here
now in your body in your being
somewhere and the more we clean keep cleaning the house keep working on
what's calling our attention we're if we're listening to what's calling our
attention then the next condition is tranquility and Tranquility is like a
landing on dry ground we've now landed if you visualize
gladness as uh if you'll allow me a little maybe silly
metaphor as if um you're you're going to a stream to take up dip in on a very hot
day maybe one of these streams in Santa Cruz by our Retreat Center inside
retreat center and um you know you're going to the stream with your friend or with
family and so you become glad you're going there you're going to you you're looking forward to this there's a
gladness there's this biological imperative that happens that takes you there and keeps you going to the
destination and then you see your stream and then you walk down to the
stream and you jump into the stream and that Joy at being refreshed at being
feeling that aliveness of that comes when we jump into a stream when we're warm and we're looking forward to a
little s and a dip that feeling that happiness that full body sensation that's how Joy the
condition of Joy manifests and then when we step out of the stream because we've done our swim
and we sit on the bank and we're on dry
ground then we are experiencing
Tranquility the condition of Tranquility so Tranquility is
very stabilizing very much the landing of
all the rising of the energy of joy and gladness and then
Landing to see and to know
tranquility and Tranquility can offer something really wonderful
to that what was that f all with Tranquility we can see into the
craving that was behind that clinging that
grasping Tranquility allows us to see into that grasping and ask and know
about what what is pulling me what is coming together in me to form that way of
being so the visibility is increasing to see further
into what how is this is it that this grasping is forming how is it that this
compulsion is forming so we can it's very beneficial
to have Tranquility to be able to take in
what's what's there because there it's really amazing
if some this quality that human beings have it's almost like
uh like I heard this teacher say once that uh it's looking right back at
you that which needs our attention that which would benefit from
our attention if we pause and are tranquil is looking
right back at us right back
and we can choose to engage with it or not we have a lot of choices that's what
this practice is all about choosing choosing to look how to look to look
with tranquil eyes spacious eyes that give a lot of room to what's
there because many things we got to be a little careful not
every everything needs us to go right into
it we we we want to be respectful of our inner
life and caring of our inner life caring of this called of
attention it's a call to attention that we can look at with
Tranquility so that it Tranquility calms the
craving begins continues that settling process that
allows a pleasurable feeling a wholesome contemplative pleasurable feeling that
reassures us re assures us a lot because we need
reassurance in order to be able to to take a good
close look to things we're not
alone this is not a solitary
path we're very reassured with the conditions in place
that offer that so from
Tranquility that dry ground finally we move to happiness
isn't that nice Tran gladness Joy tranquility and
happiness so we're looking at Dua through these eyes with this
support it's not about suffering at all this path this is
a joyful path this is a very very very joyful path this is a very happy path it
is telling us these conditions that it is happy to do this it is happy
to be sincere with myself about what do I
need it is good because there's this be feedback
system that keeps letting us know that that this is good with these conditions we see that very clearly there is
happiness available after these this
contact with the forces of clinging the forces of becoming the
forced becoming the highly attached becoming the
clinging there's a release there's a release of of our life force that's
coming to the four with all of this and then we have Happiness and
happiness in contrast to Joy I always always used to get confused used by these things like what is joy and and
what is happiness they all sound like the same thing you look in the dictionary and sometimes they refer to each other
tautologically happiness is if Joy was this fully embodied sensation of exuberance and and
connection with the water and the whole body vibrating alive happy happiness is a
more settled embodied feeling happiness is actually available all the
time because our body is in a state of well-being if it's breathing and if it's
not too sick but even if it's sick and I have been very very sick in
my life for about 20 years with pretty severe conditions and i' learned through
those uh illnesses um that there is a lot of well-being in the body as long as
the body is breathing and processing itself in its natural
way the body is full of well-being so that well-being is available to us and it becomes more more clear if we turn
and cultivate this condition for ourselves so there's
happiness and then happiness moves into the really sweet
state of samade of concentration because if we're happy
we're watching we can begin to watch what takes us out of this happiness very
clearly and we can see the forces of unpleasantness that are always a part of
experience because our mind is always categorizing things as pleasant and
unpleasant and in happiness we have now land and did were on the dry ground and
we have have this ability to take a better look at oh I can really connect
and take that cling to that unpleasantness or I
cannot so it's an information field that keeps us really able to see more and
choose more to stay more in that
stabilizing calmness because that stabilizing calmness increases and becomes really pleasurable to be still
and single with everything so we if we're back in that stream it's like we
pulled out of the ground and um in the state of
Happiness this unification of the whole environment begins to Happ happen and we
are one with this environment so it's a singleness of
focus it's not really a concentration it's a kind of a coming together
that's full of tremendous potential for more ability to
see and to feel good and to keep meditating more and to keep looking at
this Dua these arisings of
Dua and there's a harmonizing it's not a technical word but there's a
real cozy feeling of at homeness when we've cultivated this
Samar this condition of somebody we've created all the conditions to come to this
togetherness then we are able to sense the contact of
things and contact is just when a sound comes and we sense it when
a sensation in the through the nose comes we sense it when the mind a
thought comes we sense it so in Samari we're sensing all the six
senses coming but they get integrated because we are with one with everything
and there's something really interesting about somebody because it's usually tied to a lot of easy breathing the breath
becomes very very very easeful and very even almost
non-existent and um the diaphragm in our
body is connect unifies the whole body this is big sheet in the middle of our
body and when we're at one with the breath everything is Unified in the
entire body and that's the some of the sensation of what somebody is like and
this is useful for continuing our ability to
see ability to know ability to understand what we're
sensing ability to keep seeing in a fresh way what
is what needs caretaking how to car take more how to
do it even more and more because it's good it's
beautiful to take good look inside and
try to support healing somebody heals somebody brings us together and it
gives us a momentum to move forward and then we're moving forward to
um to the Insight now begins real insight in the next condition the next
condition is knowledge and vision of things as they are this is when the process of insight begins when we to
begin to go take a deeper look at how things are forming at an closer level
inside and this is a radical shift because if
we stop you've heard if you've heard this myth of Copus pushing Boulders up
the hill that's kind of a little bit the the way that Dua Works in life Dua
Works in life we keep pushing the same Boulders sometimes we're pushing many different Boulders up the hill
again and then that's all we're doing pushing the same Boulders up the hill
again and again and these conditions are allowing us to see that um wait a minute they
they we can just let the B Boulders run down the hill fall down the hill and we don't have to keep pushing the
boulders there is a choice they don't have to we don't have to keep pushing the same Stories the same paradigms the
same set of ideas the same views the same fears or the same hopes
even there's a whole other way of being that doesn't involve any of
that and so in knowledge and vision of things as they are we're just taking the samade
and turning to everything that arises from the six
senses a touch comes and we can connect to it and we connect to
it directly and deeply to sense and get to know its n nature because every sense
contact every mind contact every sight contact every smell
contact every sound every object of the eye has this amazing similar thing it
has this quality of coming and going so it's not
constant and so we're invited to make this radical shift this is not normal
life we're invited to make a radical shift to look at the Miracle of
Life very closely the life movement the life
heat that comes through all the sensations that we can sense and know and we make the shift to step into
this internal world of insight and it's very revelatory because
what's revealed is that there is a continuous movement to
everything so there it doesn't make sense to cling if we cling we
suffer clinging doesn't make sense because it's everything's moving there's nothing to cling to so we trust being in
another state of being that's flowing and we also see that the victim
the person the experiencer the doer all those different postures that we can
take that we do take in our life that also is
flowing and we keep if we keep looking at that we see that that's empty
and that's how Liberation begins we can sense all of this we know
this directly these are not ideas to believe in or to trust we sense it very
directly so it's all shifting and so if it's all shifting if it's all truly empty as we
step closer to the Miracle of Life we're not detaching from it then
we get this very confident posture that can be called a condition of
disenchantment not the greatest translation but it's better to see it as
the condition to say enough already I can say enough already to to everything
to anything because I can sense another the truth of the matter the truth of the
matter is that that things will let go that suffering is not
true that Dua is not true not that suffering is
true but if we cling we suffer so we see into this suffering
thing from a whole other angle kind of like from this internal world we can see
into this suffering that that is part of
life and so we're opening big time the door to Liberation to really having this
mature stance to see into how things form how we
are and so disenchantment is noticing that we're
gripping to things noticing that there is a
grip and then dispassion is can be which we like which is better to call Faith in
away this passion is then allowing the process of things
appearing as they are and not labeling
them this enchantment this passion can blend into this form where see everything that arises a sound
arises we don't really just leave it alone the sound arises and it's got a
label to it ambulance fire truck don't like it but a
sound can just arise and just arise just appear just take a form without a naming
or a knowing it and in life we mix these things up
and so everything has a label and then it's fixed into the label that's the
conceptual framework of how the perceptual process works everything that we recognize we can get a label but it
doesn't have to be so when we're in this realm this nice soft realm of softening
down and looking with a very supported way at how things are the more that we
let things just be as they appear the more we're loosening that
grip that our mind has on this is this way
I am this way they are this way he is this way this is this way that's how
this is this concept is true that concept is not
true not to dismiss or try to come to a truth statement that things are not how
they are or some truth statement about anything it's just to see how they are operating in
here how holding on so fixedly to my
story of me as it
is my continuous story because what's sad about this whole thing is that it
repeats itself it's kind of like we keep repeating many many of the same same
narratives again and again and if we
distinguish the the concepts that we have as opposed to just the flow of the
nature of how things come there's just a things just appear
this thought appears and it can just be an appearance it doesn't have to be a
bad thought so we this teasing part that we do when we're in doing
Insight creates this fading away it's like the Rope a it's like a rope that's
hold holding tying a sailboat to to to to the edge it's like the Rope
the sailboat's tied to this rope and in fading away and allowing things to be
part of the nature of how they are more and more and see the connection to how
that reduces our suffering how that reduces to how we keep ourselves entrapped in the same ways of
being when we when that Fades away the Rope releases
and sets the sailboat free to sail
because we are actually not meant to be tied up a boat a sailboat is meant to
sail just like our being is meant to be who you
are your true Essence not the narrative lives only
something much much much more free so there's a way to let
things ideas be Concepts be and there's a way to let things just appear and then
there's something right in between what happens when there's
neither when it's just being here who are you who who can you
be when we're not the play of the same characters in the
same stories that's what
we're unveiling letting our most deep Essence
to flow out of us without all of the constructed
activity that we're in that is a part of us and that we then
do we don't have to just be a constructing fabricating machine of everything we've inherited from
societies and familial lines and and that then we keep reproducing
ourselves this path is showing us that there's some other way if we allow
these things to deconstruct so
Liberation is when the constructions cease when all our narratives all of our
ways of Habitual patterns of attachment habitual patterns of clinging
stop when we can stop them and it's very cool because the
being that is not full of Habitual patterns full of the constructed ways of
being is a being that is responsive it's not a being that is
reactive it's a be being that has arms open wide to everything and everyone and
anything and that's Liberation Liberation is seeing being in
the tradition as the unconstructed the not fabricated for
this reason because when we're not fabricating the same play of life which
is a bit of a tragic play in a sense if you think that repeating the same three
acts again and again is not tragic um it's not
necessarily happy the same repetition of things so stepping out of that
entirely is Liberation not leaving any traces
behind and then the final piece is to knowledge is knowledge of
Liberation because the Buddha like I said did not was not interested in
some wonderful enlightenment only some amazing Awakening that may
come that comes but what would you like more to know
that you can be mature and at peace or to have a lot of
flashy Oneness with the universe Cosmic Consciousness I'm not sure what these
things are these things may come but for the Buddha it seemed to be an emphasis on Liberation and knowledge of
Liberation knowing how suffering ends a much more human activity to know
how suffering ends because then we can do something for
ourselves and why do this do this because maybe suffering has
run its course for some people maybe they're you do want to say enough we do
enough to suffering we may also do this out of a certain
love maybe a certain love for that doesn't want suffering
anymore maybe a certain love that also doesn't want suffering for other people either so we do it for
others and that may be the last one of the final instructions of the
Buddha go for forth for the welfare of the many for the happiness of the many for
the goodness of the many so why do
this we do this for the betterment of our
community for the betterment of this community the maturing of this community so that this community can do
it for the rest of the world as as well and may it be so for the all of you
this year that this year may be a one fulfilling in all the ways that
bring you peace and happiness and
well-being now I invite you to just take your meditation posture if you wish for a second
and I thank you for your
attention may you enjoy this potluck together here
may we go forth for the welfare of this
world for the happiness and peace of
all thank you very much [Music]