all right so hello everyone nice to be with you
again for our meditation today I just want to comment in advance
about something you may have noticed in the mind which is that our minds are
very associative so you know a sense experience of some kind appears when
we're sitting that tends to be a sensation or a thought our eyes are closed or a
sound um and then the mind has all these associations that come along with that
it reminds us of something or it we react to some of the content or the if
there's an an experience that's Pleasant or unpleasant then the mind has something to say about that so it's like
we don't get just the experience we get all of our a cloud of things around it
right and often these clouds which are innocent enough that's how the mind
functions but often they have um hooks in them essentially so something happens
these other associations are are there in the mind and one of them is sticky in
some way and then we we get drawn into that and we're off on a thought Trail or
a reaction of some kind and it wasn't you know particularly anything wrong with the input or even with the
functioning of the mind but it's that we mistak essentially mistook the
association for the next moment instead of the next unfolding moment of reality
we go off onto a side branch and then several minutes later we realize oh
right I'm supposed to be meditating so the invitation is to
observe this process in the mind and we'll get into that um as we do the
meditation together but understanding these hooks is a um an important part of
learning how to be with the mind and going through
life okay so let's settle in finding a comfortable position for
meditating it's fine if you're sitting or lying down or you could even be
standing or walking and just allow yourself to come
into the sense of being in meditation you can close your eyes if
that's comfortable for you and just allowing the attention to
settle down inward feeling the body in whatever
posture or position it's
in maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths breathing in breathing
out and on the out breath softening softening a little bit more
comfortably into the posture that you're in such that your body is soft relaxed
and also alert upright or straight in some way
that tends to bring in some energy and some dignity to what we're
doing perhaps taking a moment to connect explicitly with the body so
softening into the muscles of the face letting the expression
relax down into the shoulders
softening the
shoulders arms and hands down into the chest and belly
area really feeling the contact point if you're sitting the
seat letting yourself be supported by what you're sitting
on and then down into the legs and feet releasing any bracing that's
there and as always we can invite EAS in the body but not necessarily make it
relax so we just invite that ease through connecting
gently with this body
which just fine as it
is and then connecting into the the mind the
heart how are you sensing any mood that may be
present sensing the energy level
and again inviting some calm presence some ease in the
mind and knowing that at this moment there may be some
agitation and that's fine also we just be with that
becoming aware that the mind is for the moment mindful having a sense of what
mindfulness feels like for us in our mind at this
[Music] moment might feel Broad and
spacious might feel warm and connected it might feel like a cool
Observer might feel very
intimate how is mindfulness right
now and then in the middle of all of that experience
sensing just the simple flow of the breath in and out in the
body we don't need to narrow down onto the breath but just let it be kind of a
simple presence in the middle of experience a friendly presence
perhaps keeping the breath as a a background flow or pulse that we
feel just as a connection opening to the flow of
experience changing sounds my voice any sounds in the room or outside
that you can hear the Natural Body
Sensations that we will become aware of
and Associated thoughts or emotions that are flickering around in
the mind even when there isn't so much
input the mind is
generative a bird song reminds us that we need to add water to the bird bath
or a thought arising from something that happened
yesterday reminds us that we should call a friend today and then we think about our
friend is this a natural operation of the mind but in
meditation we want to stay with each experience as its own
thing each one like a flower instead of creating a bouquet out
of each one we go from one flower to the
next so it's a little bit different process than the Mind normal
operates
under in one way that we get switched in from just being with the
flow to following a thought Trail is
that there's a hook on the experience one of those associations is
not just an association that could be noticed but it has has some juice to
it and then we decide that's more interesting there's a desire there or a
belief some sense that that's the way to [Music]
go one thing we can become aware of is the hook it's actually a a visceral
Sense on an experience a
little bright spot or sticky spot or sharp
spot see how you experience it so being with the flow a bit
and when the mind gets hooked looking back for the hook
before resuming staying with the [Music]
flow
e
e e
so one way that we work with the mind's associative tendency to wander
off is to keep the attention on a single object and just decide to do it that way
and it works well another way is
to allow some of those associations be able to see them maybe
as little flickers to the side appearing but to not follow them and to
stay with the flow of what is most promis in the
moment it can be that experiences start to look like they have streamers
trailing from them associations that we could
follow but we don't it's interesting to see the
streamers are trailing off of each thing that
comes sometimes it's helpful to imagine that we have a mindfulness eraser that
erases those streamers so we just have the bare object or a sword that cuts through them
freeing experience to flow without these trails
see if this resonates in the flow of your experience learning to navigate our boat
through the water without it getting caught in the
kelp and the reads and the other things that could drag the boat
[Music]
down
e
e e
letting experience be released from our
minds books [Music] associations Embellishments
so that experience just unfolds no wind
drag no seaweed holding it back
just flowing
frictionless soone for the
ride
e
e e
as we get a sense of how to unhook or not bite the hooks that
come with experience in meditation we may find ways to carry
that into our daily life also such that we can flow more flexibly
more freely with experience as it
unfolds we're less likely to have our habitual emotional responses to things
or our habitual closing down in certain
situations that was just a hook in the mind and we may find ourselves seeing that
possibility but not taking it noticing that we have other
options and this brings a lot of benefits not only to us but to others
that we're interacting with we can see people more freshly we can find alternative ways of
relating then the habitual paths we flow down lined with
hooks and other people can feel more free in our presence because our mind is
more open more gentle less caught and that can Ripple out in many
beautiful ways
so may it be that we see some see more freshly today especially the people
around us even someone you've known for many decades could you see something fresh in
them today not just the usual way of seeing or
relating seeing what opens up to the mind when we don't take the
easy route of traveling from Hook to
hook and may it be that our world can
find some measure of unhooking from
habitual ideas ideals ways of relating and when that begins with us
there is some Poss ability so may all beings find happiness
peace free flow and an
opportunity to live without hooks
[Music]
so as human beings we live in a world that is Rich with sense
experience the Buddha even defined the world as simply the six sense spaces and
their objects the sixth one being the Mind along with seeing hearing smelling
tasting and touch this is it this is our world and it's a very relevant spiritual
question what to do with the sense world uh I think it's fair to say that
Buddhism claims that it is our mismanagement of the sense world that
brings stress and suffering and that it is possible to learn to handle it well
even to the point of having no suffering no Dua while still having a body and and
all the sense experiences so today we get to the final
hindrance in our list which is classically the first hindrance and that is is sensual
desire so as sensual beings we need to be careful how we understand
this because we are by definition immersed in the sense world it's
actually not easy to understand clearly a term like sensual desire especially
when we're told it's a hindrance so in our framing this week we're exploring
how the five hindrances are UNH wholesome or unhealthy responses to
experience and we're learning how to relate to the hindrances skillfully such that we can discover the
wholesomeness that gets uncovered when we're not under the sway of the
hindrance so to explore sensual desire I'd like to bring in the story of the
Buddha in his quest for awakening so he had the natural wish for happiness that
we all have that's a very nor noral thing for the human heart but he had to
go through a long process of learning to relate to the sense world skillfully
that was his quest in a way and we can learn a lot from his
path so the Buddha started out by relating to sense experience essentially
with greed he was wealthy enough to have access to many Pleasures he was
protected by his parents from the difficulties of Aging illness death he actually lived in the way that
most of us do by default he enjoyed sensual experience as an end in and of
itself and then he pursued additional Pleasant experiences so there could be as unbroken as possible of a string of
pleasantness and this is kind of our default strategy for happiness we have to
admit um but the Buddha found this to be spiritually
unsatisfying and that was important that was a turning point for him um and so he
started out his spiritual Quest by going and learning these very refined formless
meditation states that are very lofty and the body disappears um it's kind of like I'm
going to claim this is like relating to sense experience with delusion so he started out with greed then he went into
delusion he thought he could transcend the sense World by seeking loftier and
more spiritual forms of pleasure and happiness so he's still looking for happiness but he deluded tried to escape
the limits of sensual Happiness by going into higher mental Realms and we have to admit that this
works for a while but in the end it is also unsatisfying because even the loftiest
pleasure are still impermanent um they don't offer a final
solution if you will so in the next stage of the Buddhist practice he related to sense
experience with aversion he became an extreme aesthetic trying to crush his
wish for happiness through austerity practices he said all right if all happiness is fleeing in temporary I'm
going to find a way not to want it I'm going to punish my body deliberately seeking out painful
experiences he became a connoisseur of pain if you will but alas this too did not free his
mind so he was stuck greed delusion and hatred had all failed um and then he remembered a time
from his childhood when he was relaxed and happy his mind naturally entered a
state of unification his sense experience in the body was fully present and his mind was
in a beautiful state of contentment Clarity Tranquility
Vitality it was beautiful and you know this is not the goal in and of itself because we can't
always have conditions like that but the Buddha did see in his memory of this
that that this is the path the path somehow involves cultivating this
tranquil clear presence that harmonizes the experience of the moment and then he
needed to develop and refine that a lot more but that was a really important
insight and the point here is that he had found within the sense World a
wholesome thread that he could follow and it actually involves pleasure um so
it's a path to happiness he could make a path out of this very experience
and then that's what he taught us to do so now I think with that as
background we're prepared to talk about sensual desire as a hindrance so sensual desire is a way of
missing the path in this moment because we mistake the pleasure of some sense
object or the Deep spiritual happiness that we're actually seeking so zeroing
in and fixating on an object of pleasure covers over the open ease of the path
that we could otherwise find it's a major turning point in spiritual life when we realize that the
happiness available from sensual Pleasures is limited and that there is a pathway
forward that neither settles for that limited happiness nor tries to deny
happiness and pleasure Buddha called that the middle way Joseph Goldstein tells a story about
how on a retreat he was reflecting on the Buddha's freedom from greed hatred
and delusion and you know he was having this inspirational reflection and
suddenly his mind switched over to thinking about his favorite comfy
meditation sweatshirt and how he'd like to have several of them in different colors so his mind had been open to this
great spiritual inspiration and aspiration and then it literally collapsed onto a
sweatshirt and I would suspect that we all have similarly humbling experiences
in our mind right things that we've suddenly gotten distracted by so the point with this though is to
start feeling into how um when we buy into sense Des
it Narrows our experience such that we don't really see the whole scope of it
we start seeing partially um there are the physical feelings can be feelings of Leaning
forward or tumbling forward um grasping there's a there's a contraction
associated with sense desire it might feel kind of pleasant you know like oh I
want that it would be great if I could get that um or it would be great if I could hold on to this it's so wonderful
what I have but there is a feeling of um
collapse in that somehow um and it's important to perceive that as unhealthy
I might call it unho because we've lost the whole for this one part that we
like the Buddha liken sensual desire to being in debt so we enslave ourselves to
the Future by wanting to get something or wanting to keep something and then we
have to put out energy to service that desire like we service a loan or debt
that we've taken out so if we're mindful of Desire we can
feel the weight that it places on us it's also important I think to say
and clearly in talks like this that there is no fault in enjoying some
pleasant experience that has come to us and there's also no problem with choosing things that we like or enjoy
when we have a choice if you're going to the store because you need a meditation
sweatshirt get the comfy one you know but know that it can't provide lasting
happiness for you and also watch your mind to see the way it Narrows when it
moves toward something that it finds desirable actually just a few days ago I
was um I was out walking and I passed by one of those little kiosks that offers free
books that someone has set up it's like a book exchange and I took a look because I like books and my eyes were
drawn uh to a poetry book so first I had been looking at the whole street while I
was walking and then my vision narrowed down to the kiosk and then to the book and this is not necessarily bad but it
is interesting to watch and I I read a few the poems and I thought hey these
might be good for Dhat talks wholesome right so I started to take the book with
me and then I realized no this is just desire actually I I don't actually need
this book and I felt how taking the book would add one more piece of stuff to my
life one more thing to have and in that moment it felt burdensome so I made the
decision um not to take it so that's not to say that there wouldn't be a time when
taking the book would be fine that might might happen at a different time that
has to be something that's discerned in the Moment by you when it's your
experience so notice in a given moment is there a burdensome feeling to this
object that I'm zeroing in if yes probably there's you know there's a hindrance there that just
desire so sensual desire is one of the trickiest hindrances because we're continually
engaged with the sense world and we need to fulfill our basic bodily needs like
food shelter Etc and our social needs for community and relationships and
support and yet we have to do so in a way that remains free from expecting
limited things to supply deep and Lasting happiness so the Buddhist texts say that
ill will is more blameable but easier to
remove and sensual desire is less blameable but harder to
remove so that's what we're up against in a sense but we start to overcome UNH
wholesome Desire by learning to see it learning to feel its weight its
stickiness its burden and then we have a chance of noticing what what gets
uncovered we have a chance of noticing the place where the path opens in this
moment the path is a kind of ease that doesn't Depend On Any Given sense of
pleasure being there and a good way to sense that path is to cultivate a calm
awareness within this Rich sense world that we find ourselves in if we
cultivate this tranquil knowing of what is arising whether Pleasant or
unpleasant we can find that that thread of ease that wholesomeness that the
Buddha found that's what the Buddha did in his own practice and we can do it
too so the sense world is not our enemy but neither is
it our Salvation in instead there's a little thread that runs through it called the
path that we can find that consists of an ease that is unhooked from all the
things that are coming in and all the associations our mind
makes so I'll end by mentioning that I'll be here again for all of next week
U we spent this week looking at the hindrances which are UNH wholesome and that's very important um to tune into
those so that we can uncover what's possible when we're not hooked in them another aspect of practice is to
deeply recognize and be inspired by things that are wholesome so that's what
we'll focus on next week now classically the wholesome qualities that stand in
contrast to the hindrances are the seven factors of Awakening but I thought we'd look at a
different list of wholesome qualities that is taught less often in our scene
and that is a list of qualities of the mind of the Buddha so we talked today
about the Buddha's quest to understand how to live freely in this human life
what was his mind like what is a mind like that can do that so if you're
interested in that um please come next week and we'll explore that together so
thank you very much