and here we go so hello hello and welcome everyone uh welcome to happy
hour um and um today today being the eclipse day um
in northern northern America many people were able to see the the complete
eclipse the full the totality as it's called so so maybe that will come into
our meditation somehow whether or not we were able to see the totality of the
eclipse Sun being eclipsed by the moon um yeah that might come into our
practice so tell you what let's sit together and and be surprised see what
arises in the practice of meta and and uh yeah embodiment together so like to
invite you to arrive to
settle arriving in this
moment arriving in this
body letting go what from letting go of whatever has
happened that has brought us to this moment maybe it's been
busy or or full or challenging
or whatever it's been can we release for a moment not pushing away that's a
different energy not pushing away but releasing for a moment to
settle this is a fresh new moment how can we Embrace this fresh new
moment
with our presence feeling our bodies sitting in this
moment and with our
breath
and can we bring invite this this breath to be just as it is in
this
moment
allowing inviting the breath to
embrace this moment of being this freshness of this moment of
being in this body in breath the out
breath like your friend your calming soothing
lulla
spending another few minutes
cultivating embodiment and presence feeling the body feeling the
breath moving through the body in this moment try it
here right
now
e
and now as we are sitting allowing the breath to move
as as it
does and we bring a sense of appreciation and awe the same way
that many have reported today seeing the total eclipse of the
sun sense of awe
in some ways every moment of experience is
aome
amazing
and we for a moment just for a moment receive the sensations of the
breath in this
body with a sense of awe
awesomeness
e
let yourself play around with this perhaps with this sense of awe we notice
something new about the breath we hadn't noticed before or the sensation somewhere in the
body we hadn't sense or we sense in a new
way as if we're watching a total eclipse this worldly
otherworldly EXP
experience just as the eclipse for us human beings does not occur too
frequently giving the span of our limited lives this breath too
this breath even though it is our companion
from the moment we come to the world to the moment we take our last breath but
in this body in this unique
being it occurs briefly compared to the life of
the universe it is awesome it is
awesome
e
oh it's such an uplifting State similar to meta
gratitude compassion
Etc now let's
switch if you like switch to mudita practice gratitude
mudita mudita happiness for the Good Fortune of
others if you did not see the total eclipse
today can you have happiness for those who are fortunate to be on the path of
the celestial event be happy for their happiness as if
it were your own as if you had been
privy to this happiness for their happiness if you are one of the lucky
ones on the path of the eclipse today can you have
gratitude sharing your good fortune happy freely with
others and for those practicing mudita vicarious
joy happiness as if it were your own as if you had experienced this wonderful
event let it uplift your heart heart expand your heart expand your
heart with gladness and goodwi happiness for other people's
happiness
e
notice the more you allow your heart to expand and hold joy for the joy of
others the more joyful you become
uplifted during all kinds of people younger people who were able to
see it children young
adults adults older adults people in their 80s and 90s
[Music]
perhaps or even
hundreds happiness for their Good
Fortune
and now for the third part of this practice period let's try something else on for
size now the same way that in the ancient
times total eclipses were construed or interpreted
as end of the world or very negative Omen etc etc taken so
personally so personally something that was not personal at
all the movement of the Sun and the Moon and the Earth human beings took it so personally
we distraught just
distraught something that was not personal at all and today we get that we
understand it it's not personal it's not because a people
or or a group behaved badly Etc it's not
personal celestial objects they're going about their way causes and
conditions is it possible to bring the same perspective into our lives when we
consider something so catastrophic all right I did this it's my fault it's all
rests on my
shoulders you're bring the same sense of spaciousness of understanding wisdom
yeah there's so many causes and conditions that have made this happen
yeah maybe I have a part in it or at the right place at the right time or wrong
place at the wrong time or other factors but it's not so
personal so many causes and conditions so
many we allow this to bring equinity
spaciousness peace and these into our hearts
e
e and let's bring a sense of
gratitude that as human beings
we we [Music] can see here
appreciate and perhaps understand with appreciation events like this in the
heavens and the Stars the celestial objects that we live on in
Earth with enough development in our science our understanding to
appreciate to feel uplifted by events like this gratitude
gratitude we live in a world where such a thing happens on this precious
planet and that we have appreciation we
can understand it in some
ways much more than early humans
did gratitude appreciation for what is
and as we turn to close this period of sitting
together allowing ourselves to feel appreciation gratitude for ourselves
for having showed up as best as we were able to and without attachment to
outcome however it was or
wasn't we've planted seeds trust
it may all beings everywhere on this planet of
ours and everywhere in in all celestial
objects all beings everywhere all sensient beings May there
be happy may they be well including
ourselves thank you so much for your practice everyone so we
did four practices today inspired by the total eclipse the first one was the
practice of awe the second one was mudita vicarious
joy happiness for the Good Fortune of others then we did equinity not taking
things so personally things that aren't and then we ended with gratitude
and of course if you did see the to Eclipse earlier instead of mudita you would have practiced gratitude as well
so four different practices pretty rich who knew one could practice with a total
eclipse and happy hour in these way kind of fun so so I'd love to invite you to um
engage to reflect to share with one another as little or as much as you
like sharing reflecting on what what worked
for you in the practice or maybe what has moved you uh with
the yeah with the total eclipse today as it relates to practice as it relates to
states of heart and mind how can you allow that it to open you up bring more
meta equinity Mita etc for
you creating the breakout rooms and the invitation is to
um to maybe share one one reflection and
then allow the next person to share reflection and then the next person go around and round and round uh and please
keep it to the practice keep it the practice
um yeah and be kind to yourselves be kind to one
another um yeah how can this how has this practice been for you how can it open your heart up further any aha
moments any challenges so creating the everyone the rooms are
[Music] closed everybody's back and we have some
time for Reflections uh comments questions how
was it and you can raise your Zoom hand please also I'm going to open chat to
everyone if you want to share Reflections in chat how is this practice for you
today this thematic practice with meta and equinity and gratitude
and
a you please hello thank you Nikki it was
great is great there is uh wonderful thinking about all those
people standing out there looking up at at stars you right the Moon Sun um and
all of them having at the same time this body bodily visceral experience of
awe and that this but on a communal level
and um just even for that brief few minutes in
time I I they had it and and then you mentioned but isn't it wouldn't it be
nice if we had that all the time or every moment is kind of miraculous isn't
it not just that one moment it was a beautiful meditation thank you
Nikki thank you so much you thank you so much for also bringing your sense of
Muti and joy really for for for others for the kids and when you were saying
that I had this this image um earlier today I I saw uh uh on on some
website there was an image of these kids with with these Myer classes and they
were on the beach somewhere maybe it was maybe it was in Mexico it was they were on a beach it was this this
festive uh uh you you know occasion where there were so many kids in their
bathing suits and you know they had just bathed and they're looking at the it was just so sweet it just uplifted my heart
uplifted my heart so much that they they got to experience this as well and yes every moment is pretty miraculous this
this thing this thing our lives so thank you you thank you so
much Claire I see your hand thank you wh here we go now I just
want to thank you I like the idea or the way you approached picking a a a way of
seeing reviewing the day it was like taking a having an assortment of lenses
and picking the one that you wanted to look through and then seeing I had a
very busy day today but I could sort of see the totality of it and through a the
way you know a healthy way of seeing it basically uh and through pulling it all
together really was nice so I ended up feeling like you know I've seen the whole picture and I I knew what my
takeaway was it was great sweet sweet oh thank you Claire I'm delighted to hear
this practice today really supported in this integration of this full busy um
totality full day you had on the East Coast that's great that's great and and
to say yeah these are lenses these are lenses that we take on and you know these are definitely lenses ways of
perceiving and seeing so exactly right yeah yeah thanks Claire Ali I see your hand
please hi Nikki thanks hi to see you you too actually I'll I'll share some sidh
show that was going on in my mind while you know was going on in there I'm inan
this app that then there folks that are outside the country and they couldn't see it and this guy was like I guess he
was where J is in Toronto he was just sh in about the uh all these moments in oh
my God and all that my mind straight went into those guys I can't see it they're going to get jealous that's
where my mind went and I came back it says like it's not a big deal I went to kind of like you know ease it up it's
I've seen it like seven years ago I was just kind of explaining to them uh that one and I'm not trying to be
funny either but then the moment of when you were explaining it at the first section of the meditation I went to all
the moments that I have is oh oh I'm not trying to be funny but that's like that came up say or oh oh but the third part
of the show uh in my mind was the uh what was
it I forgot anyway uh
theity no I try I explained it you know to the folks that you know the I went into the darma it was a little bit of
discussion of Dharma about like the light is going to come it's going to go away the dark is going to come it's going to go away oh and then this one
this was like really a m big moment of a for me of all the O that I had in the show was that how small we are I mean
like everybody in the whole world is United and how small really I am we all are yeah and yeah those were the sidh
shows for me thank you yeah beautiful thank thanks for sharing Ellie I I appreciate you know sharing the sidh
shows and this is what comes up in our minds right it's and sort of you know
O's come up you know say oh how about all the people who are in jail you know all this comes up and and let's have
humor let's have humor and this sense of yeah this is the mind the Mind comes out with these things comes out with its own
show um and I also really appreciate this what you added at the end with the
sense of uh wow uh here we are I think you were
talking about how here we are all these human beings on this planet it's it's just a sense of awe again that that for
you naturally came up in his slay in a different way so I'm I'm really touched by that thank you so much for naming
that yeah thank you I see Patricia's hand
please oh okay thank you um I live in St Louis Missouri and we are 99% we were in
in in to of totality and I was at a very large park that has
a big lake and um there were many people not too many people
there were couples there were families there were singles and the eclipse was very
cool but the solidarity that I felt that uplifted
my spirit we were all there for the same thing
everyone seemed to be quite happy and content and together everyone was so
friendly and talking and joyous and it was so
uplifting and the miraculous uh n of the um Eclipse was
amazing but the solidarity and the
joyous feeling I had was even more miraculous beautiful yeah thank you
thank you Patricia thanks so much for bringing this in and I think this is something also um that Ali at the end
was referring to and I kind of lost the point that he was making which is which is similar as as you were making
beautiful that wow um and and also another person I heard this on the radio
who's made an an a astronomy astronomy Professor or I who had had this experience today of totality was sharing
that wow here we are especially with all the differences and
with sorry to bring it up but with an election coming up with all the differences that we're having in you
know nor in this country and North America like H and here we are just forgetting about all that and being
humans together with a in a um that that's that's so touching and thank you
for bringing this in Patricia yeah thank you yeah it it is possible it is
possible it is possible possible um PMA I see your hand I'll get to you in one
second I see one question that I want to address in um in chat first which is um
one of you said I love the meditation I I loved how the meditation had a part to
be happy for others could you expand on it I love that perspective so that is
the teaching on mudita uh mud D in poly
translated as vicarious Joy or or happiness for the happiness of others
and it's a beautiful joyful practice where uh we cultivate we start where
it's easy we think of people where we can easily be happy for their happiness um and then we expand to all beings
being happy for the happiness of others and um and the Dal Lama has said that if you're just happy for your own happiness
you have one chance to be happy if you're happy for the happiness of others your chances increase to S billion or
however many number of uh people there are on this Earth so happiness or the happiness of others it's such an
uplifting practice and there's much more on it and you're welcome to Google
mudita mud and then also there are many mudita periods of just pure mudita
practice in fact we've done weeks of medita practice here at happy hour if you
search uh audiio Dharma for mudita you will find many teachings on that you are
welcome so HMA I see your hand there ask you to unmute
there okay great thank you sure um first of all I'll apologize if I'm going to
sound a little bit pessimistic today um but um everything is welcome bring all
good yeah so I just my heart is very heavy today I just couldn't uh feel the mod I was feel gratitude but um there's
a very young adult who lost his life um this morning and so I wasn't even
focusing on the eclipse um and was a friend of my daughter um it was just a
accident in Big Sir um he fell and drowned so I like okay how do I feel um
Mita for others even though I was feeling gratitude to of course everybody
here and to myself but I just couldn't get my mind off of yeah him and the
family so I was just wondering is it okay I mean not feeling with I know everybody's so happy here and I
apologize but of course no need to apologize and I'm so glad thank you pmo
for the courage to to speak up this is so so important and what is really
important is to be truthful and honest to how you're feeling at at a given
moment so you might come to happier and and the topic might have you know might be
happiness or happiness of others and and you've had something tragic happen and there's so much heaviness and grief and
and the heart goes no I want to stay with compassion I want to stay with with
sadness I want to meet my sadness with um with kindness I want to meet it
compassion is what's needed here for me for the family who just lost their young child and that's appropriate so of
course that's appr so at any time um if you're practicing here on a retreat anything and the instructions
are you know blah blah blah and your heart is in a different place then meet
your heart meet the truth of where you are with kindness because that's where you are that's what's needed not what's
you know we we offer invitations instructions kind which are kind of
General but be uh be attuned to what's needed for you at a given time uh and be
your own inner Dharma coach so yeah maybe gratitude works but no when we're doing with want to turn towards
compassion oh sweetheart yeah this is hard this is hard and that's perfectly fine thank you so much for for bringing
in if you want to add anything else you're welcome to if not it's all good no thank you just want to said thank you
yeah thank you so much yeah and we have time um yeah we have time for one more
reflection and yeah Serena adds um her support to you not everyone
is happy here today it's okay pman somebody else has also added uh their
support here is Jerry Jerry I see your
hand yes so uh not to spoil it but uh uh
you mentioned uh uh in your own comment and then apologize for identifying geopolitical
events and so um uh oh no you're GNA take go there okay okay that's since you
you open the oh no okay so I just wondered how you sit when
like I echoed many of the comments that people said but sometimes I wonder if
I'm so I just try to stay in the moment when I think about these other things
that some of which mentioned and say well things will work out but is that
naivity or denial I guess that's what I just uh yeah yeah yeah it's U it's a
good question and I don't mind that you you're going there at Al Cherry it's fine it's part of our life right it's
part of our world um I think there's a difference between
the um naivity equinity and definitely getting overwhelmed and so anxious that
one cannot do anything so this practice is the practice of the middle way so I
know that personally for me um it does not help me to um to get
overwhelmed it doesn't help me to get overwhelmed um doesn't help me at
all so it's [Music]
um also not helpful to have the sense of resignation because usually it's
overwhelmed that leads to resignation overwhelm leads to resignation kind of they go hand in hand I've heard from so
many people that they get over I'm like ah it's all going to hell and then it's like ah there's nothing I can do so it's
almost like a pair together those two so so what what is skillful to to
realize yeah things things are challenging things are chenging and and
what can I skillfully do can I what can I skillfully do um to to be ready to
support um but to stay but to stay right here and not get into state of e neither
overwhelm nor nor resignation and depression and it's easier said and done but that is the
practice thank you thanks Jerry thank you so much so we've come to the end of
our time together thank you so much for participating bringing your yourselves
your hearts to this practice and also thanks thanks for a very uh um juicy
insightful warm multivaried conversation and really honest conversation we had at
the at the end Reflections what what worked uh what didn't work all good this
is all great so thank you all for your practice May all beings be happy may all
beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone take good care