all right welcome and let me just see how many we
are here welcome everyone good to see
everybody and a wonderful Friday to
you hope the week's been good to you so today we'll wrap up with our exploration
of the of the five spirit spiritual faculties as they're
called Monday we talked about confidence Tuesday about balancing energy in the
practice Wednesday about complete presence yesterday about collectiveness
of mind the steady mind and today we'll we'll talk about the fifth
faculty which is generally uh called wisdom
but because wisdom can be sort of a high bar it's a great aspiration of
course uh we'll we'll we'll take a look at it in terms of
discerning and seeing clearly verbs instead of something to acquire
accomplish achieve like wisdom and uh we'll bring those verbs
into our practice so first
let's sit
together we can adjust our bodies and find our sitting
posture can bring the eyes down or focus them in the middle
distance and maybe do just a brief checkin of the body feeling its weight
in the chair on the cushion
and
uh maybe feel any tension in the body any holding any bracing any Echoes of
the day or hours past any sort of stress that's around preparing for
what's to come in the rest of the day or what Remains of the Day
and if we can just sort of soften around those areas of
tension we don't have to fix anything we don't have to make things
better there's ways in which this is a practice not about feeling better
quickly but about feeling more so just being aware of all that
comes into our awareness
and in the middle of it all we can find our way to the to the
breath and this morning in keeping with
the theme for the day of discerning seeing
clearly when we find find ourselves back with the breath each time we return to
the breath maybe instead of focusing so much on the breathing
today we can focus a little more on the way we know the
breathing what can be noticed as we come back to the breath is how effortless The
Knowing is that knows the breathing
so let's bring attention to the breath connecting as we have been the last few days with some of the natural
characteristics of the breathing the balance the Simplicity the relatively slow pace of
the breathing and just connecting in a way where there can be a little Delight
taken in the way when we connect our attention with the
breathing some of these characteristics that are just natural and easy for the breathing sort of rub off on us rub off
a bit on the mind every time we return there's a chance to an opportunity to rebalance to
touch in with Simplicity to slow down a little bit
maybe to unwind a little bit and just
rest here in the in the breathing and the sensations of the rise and fall of the abdomen the chest the
shoulders or perhaps noticing the breathing in the mouth or nose
and of course the mind will roam the mind will get caught up and snagged by
things this is the the mind being
mind and because we rely on the mind to do these things for us
I always feel a certain appreciation before I bring the Mind back to Center back to the breath appreciate the mind's
ability to do all those things to think about the future remember and re re
rewrite the past to think about other people to think about myself all all those things
have their place and sometimes I find it nice to just express some
gratitude to the mind for its willingness to try to
help maybe provide some solutions or suggestions or ways to fix and then I just go back to the
breath right now without pushing those aspects of Mind away I'm just coming
back to the breathing here and resting the mind steadying the mind gladdening the
Mind resting the mind like we did yesterday
and today when we connect with the breathing
let's notice how the breathing is known this knowing that goes
on so
effortless so light a touch
this knowing that happens in itself is
free the knowing that happens effortlessly when
we reconnect with the breath we can notice in itself is free of agitation
free of attachment it's just
knowing knowing and indistinguishable from what's
known so
easy so this knowing can know the agitated mind without
itself being
agitated can recognize and register strong emotion without itself being
colored by those
emotions snowing can connect with Pleasant and unpleasant B
sensation without being affected by the pleasant or
unpleasant so when we reconnect with the breath each time this
morning let's notice the knowing just the ease of the
knowing we can rest too in this effortless
knowing that's free of
agitation
e
e e
as this meditation period comes to a close we can once again
reconnect our attention with the
breathing and take account of the knowing that's happening and the quality of this
knowing and maybe if some gladness of mind and some steadiness of
Mind have become present
can notice that this knowing seems to register
change changing intensity in what's known or changing quality of what's
known but this effortless unagitated knowing
is an innate capacity that we can cultivate in the
practice maybe letting it lead a little bit following its
lead let's dedicate the Merit of our practice today to all beings
may all beings be safe and secure whole and body and
mind may all beings live at
ease may all beings be free from suffering
[Music]
so welcome again if you weren here for the earlier
welcome welcome
Friday just going to look back over at the chat see what's
happening yeah all looks good
um so today we will finish with this brief exploration of the five spiritual
faculties so-called these five capacities of mind that we each have within and that
can be cultivated strengthened as our practice Deens in
ways that reflect the deepening of practice and also also support uh
practice the fifth faculty PA in poly is frequently
translated as wisdom and I said at the outset that sometimes that can seem like a high
bar uh wisdom and so a perfectly legitimate
alternate translation that Gil points to among others is discernment or to make
it a verb Discerning we can say Discerning we can also say seeing
clearly and uh something about making these
verbs I think brings them more into the realm of something we can we can actually do in our
practice so we can let aspiration remain as our uh sorry uh wisdom remain as our
aspiration and then we can practice day to day moment to moment sit to sit we
can practice Discerning seeing clearly
so first something about
Discerning uh this is something we do all the
time we walk into a room we walk into a space and with this effortless knowing
that I was making reference to in the guided meditation we pick up what's
going on and we probably see some of it pretty
clearly and then there's other things we see less clearly but it's like this in the
meditation to we walk into a room that is we find ourselves in a particular
moment of the meditation and uh we can be aware of
what's going on and within that we can sort of by degrees see more and more
clearly ah this is what's arising this emotional current thought pattern this
bodily sensation and we can just take it as it comes we can take it without um judging
without preference without making up our mind about anything without reacting
quickly and this is this gift of of
discernment that we can know what's going on and we can pause we can take it
in as it's coming on its own terms without immediately reacting in perhaps
a way that we've reacted many times before so this is a key thing about
discernment is that it makes it possible for us to change how we
respond possibly it points out the direction of response and that sort of leads us to
toward a place of Greater ease greater skillful action and the
like the end of the meditation I talked about letting this knowing lead instead
of instead of me leading what if I let the knowing lead what if I let dis
Discerning lead what if I let this scene clearly lead then then what
happens maybe something new discernment or Discerning to keep it
as a verb Discerning allows greater
creativity in in meeting a moment so to give some examples what
what what's being discerned things in the meditation but
also in daily life like what's the attitude of Mind toward What's Happening
Here what's the predominant mood with which I'm meeting this
experience various ways of asking what's my
relationship to this experience that is being known we can ask what what operating
system has been engaged here is this you know reaction
1.0 which which particular uh set of reactive impulses have been activated or
triggered by this situation is the Mind
operating with a lot of wanting in it a lot of aversion in it a lot of concern
with self in it this can be
discerned does the relationship that I have with this experience have stress in
it have suffering in it just like walking into a crowded room
we can start to get very good at figuring out what's going on
here and then um how to respond the Discerning
also helps figure out what we might do in response to a
particular experience other words from here seeing
more clearly if not perfectly clearly sufficiently clearly what's going on
we can frequently sense which direction leads toward less suffering and less
harm which leads toward greater harm greater
suffering and this is a I think a really important thing to notice is that all we're doing is paying
attention the the direction is usually very clear not
always And yet when we get when we get good at this or when Discerning becomes
second nature taking a careful look seeing clearly becomes more second nature it also becomes more
obvious which of which which way of inclining the Mind leads towards greater
suffering and which way of inclining the Mind leads away we practice this in the meditation
so that it becomes easier in daily life it's not the only reason as I said yesterday today we practice it in
meditation because it leads toward deeper and deeper and more um enjoyable
and refreshing and healing meditation in and of itself but it also helps us lean
in towards what's skillful and what's away from what's unskillful in in our
daily life so you can ask yourself what in
this situation seen with discernment seen with some
clarity what action of Mind of of speech
or of body what action leads toward greater harm and what leads toward a
avoiding harm causing on or as Gil has put it sometimes what
might be born here what's waiting to be born here what might be born here that's
new so I think it's useful emphasizing as I've been trying to do all week and I
do a little bit just by taking wisdom from its place as kind of a high bar uh
and softening it I hope and making it more achievable by thinking of it as a verb
something we do instead of something we have something we apply instead of
something we achieve or attain and hold on to as ours something we seek to
perfect is not in other words not something we seek to perfect but something we seek to uh
learn to uh engage learn to take with us as we meet
experience something that is a a a way of meeting experience or a method for
meeting experience and coming to a decision about what kind of action is a
appropriate response so part of part of doing this too we can invoke this idea that it
doesn't have to be perfect it can be sufficient and it's as as we practice we
don't move directly toward um skillful action in one step what happens over
time is that more and more we find ourselves in wholesome mind States and
from these wholesome mind States more and more skillful action uh
emanates and with time the the wholesome mind State and the skillful actions that
follow become the the more natural way that we that we meet
experience so the fact that we still um don't see as clearly as we'd like that
we respond in ways that are the same old ways we've always responded with frequently the same
results that doesn't mean that we can't at the very same time be on more and
more occasions finding ourselves with greater Clarity of Mind Discerning more clearly what's going on here what's
arising in my experience and meet that experience with
something new something that's more creative something that uh is more of a
skillful response than a reflexive
reaction and over time that proportion of skillful action eventually swamps on
skillful action and we become more and more effective at being
fully ourselves in the world so in sort of summarizing for the
week um and this could be done in any number of ways math was never my strong
point there's probably some um way that this is a you know a matter of
um combining five different elements in a myad different
ways but what I'm struck by in just saying what I've just said is that as we
to give an example of how these five factors can be related that as we become
more skilled at Discerning a aware that okay there's some clear seeing happening
here and um in that clear say seeing or because of it or on the basis of it can
see that this way of inclining the mind of speaking of engaging in bodily action
this way is healthier for me for others this way
is a wholesome mind state that emanates in skillful action
with that our confidence grows confidence being the first of these five
faculties with that confidence growing the energetic balance that we talked
about on Tuesday becomes easier and easier there much less time is spent
doubting is this the right thing to do am I all the doubts that come up you
know particularly the doubt around do I have what it takes we come more skilled at Discerning our confidence grows less
energ is wasted or unless heat is given off without any light in the area
of um uh the energetic balance that
energetic balance makes it much easier for mindfulness to be uh to come into
play to bring our attention to things without judging because that's a lot of energy lost there with the judging the
bringing in all the extra stuff we can just meet experience at ease with
mindful atten that in itself is free of all that extra
baggage that provides a basis as we said yesterday for sustaining that attention
in a way that brings great Stillness and gladness to the
mind so that's just briefly that's one way of relating relating these five faculties uh we could do that beginning
with any one of them and talk about how they all of them are strengthened by U
considering a this way I'm going to I'm going to end on this note just to say
that uh it's been a pleasant week in the chat I noticed that uh there's some
exchange for somebody who has just realized that this morning meeting has been going on for four years and I
didn't I wasn't aware of it or i' forgotten it the Gil began with an exploration of the anapan Sati the
attention to mindful attention to the in andout W and I just thought I would uh close
this isn't the end of a four-year cycle or anything but uh it's been true I think throughout these four years
certainly when I've sat in that those same instructions show up
yesterday's instructions glading the mind steadying the Mind resting the mind
that's the third group of the four instru of the third group of four instructions of the 16 instructions that
appear in the anapan satita today's guided meditation focusing on knowing
the change that's going this is drawn I wasn't thinking about it but this is drawn from the fourth tetr or the fourth
group of four instructions that are part of that 16 part of those 16 instructions
in that in that discourse at any rate just want to say that we keep coming back to these foundational
practices the um the meditation experience and the way we meet it the
way we cultivate these faculties and these strengths of mind captured so well in that first discourse
that Gil discussed um this is the heart of the practice so anyway until we next
meet until our pnik cross I wish you all well and uh uh wish you all the best for
your practices and take care