so hello everyone and Welcome to our meditation session and for this uh session I'd like
to uh convey um visually a teaching that I offered at
this Last Retreat I taught at Insight retreat center and but it's meant today
to offer for kind of distinction between mindfulness and
concentration these are two partners in the practice and they work together but
they're distinct in some ways and uh so to begin this kind of
visual demonstration we begin with the notion that occasionally we human beings
are entangled in our concerns we're caught up we're stuck we're attacked
attached and um it could be with people we're entangled with people uh we are
codependent we are upset with them we're just kind of wrapped up around our concerns around them or with things in
the world or even with ourselves and aspects of ourselves and the demonstration for this would be like the
fingers in our hand coming together to hands and being and locking together
just like really locked together and it can really quite make a knot out of it
but uh they're like if I wrap them around and bend them around each other then pull apart I just can't get them
apart if I'm really holding on gripping on tight that then I can't get them
apart I have to release the hands to be able to get them apart so entangled in
things it's possible to be so in the middle of the drama of it all that we're
kind of in it and entangled in something and the metaphor the classic example for
me is being in a group of people who are caught up in an argument about something
and for some reason stepping away maybe leaving the room and coming back in the edge of the group and watching them
argue and feeling like wow that's quite something they're caught up in it and they don't even know it and but from
that distance seeing clearly what's going on that so we somehow find a way
to step away to see from a distance what is it we're
concerned with and that's the mindfulness it is a kind of stepping
away so we can see what's happening we can perceive be aware of what's
happening almost like we're making breathing room for our experience that we can't do if we're caught up in the
middle of there's no room to breathe no room to see or to feel but to step back and so we can see the see what's
happening concentration is to come back and make
contact again like this and I like this image
because it's an it's a gesture of respect in Buddhism and um and so we're not being
aloof from experience but we're not being entangled in it we're seeing it
clearly and in that seeing and our respect for what's there to get to know
it better we stay there we get close to it we feel it and then the soft tender
parts the sensitive parts of the hand can touch what's there in uh some classic Buddhist text
they talk about uh like being like um having a cloth and rubbing a bronze bowl
and just kind of taking it coming together just gently kind of staying with it to feel it to be with it but for
today I'd like to suggest the idea we're we're not being aloof we're being distinct when we're
being separated enough to not be defined by whatever is going on not
by not be shaped by it not be identified with it but also not disrespectful and
aloof just enough so we can see oh that's here here's awareness I'm
aware or if you prefer I'm here even and my concern my emotions my thoughts
they're there and I can see them and then coming together and think and
approaching this is a kind of a gesture of respect that concentration is a gesture
of respecting what's there so we can stay and feel and sense make room for it
so mindfulness is not just being aware and then going on to the next thing to be aware of mindfulness is to recognize
what's there and then get to know it better come closer feel it sense it so
the concentration is lingering with something and that lingering can be a long time it can feel
really good it can be a kind of absorption but it's not absorption like
this it's absorption of just really being resting there together with
experience so assuming a meditation posture and
uh gently closing your
eyes and taking a few moments just by mental Act of
recognition that you are here now at a time and
place that your mind is not need to be caught in things that are there and
then there's a definitive recognition here
now is the place for awareness and have that grounding and
here unentangled here in your
body feeling the weight of your body against the surface that holds it up
that receives its
weight and to take a few long long slow deep
breaths and relax and let go into this
body the clarity of taking your
place meaning in wherever you're meditating this is your place
that you belong that you for now is your
place take your place here now so that you can be
independent of other things around you other things in your life for these
minutes letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale continue to
relax the
body
and then centering yourself on your
breathing recognizing the
sensations of breathing in sensations of breathing
out and how those Sensations are different from each
other
recognizing the distinct characteristics of an
inhale of an
exhale
and for a few moments here to imagine that your ability to
perceive breathing or or to know that you're
breathing is distinct from the breathing itself two different
processes one physical one
mental almost as if if you can step away
from the experience of breathing and observe
it
and then as if two palmed hands The Palms come
together respectfully gently let your
awareness become closer to the
breathing almost as of awareness is there to respect and care for each
inhale and each exhale
so the awareness is
gently massaged or rubbed
by the experience of
breathing where it's clear that awareness mindfulness
attention is both distinct
from breathing and in touch with
breathing lingering in the experience of that
contact between awareness and
breathing
without entanglement without being defined by it
or troubled by
anything respectful awareness respecting each
breath and as we sit
here if you become aware of Body Sensations or
emotions or
thinking know it mindfully by knowing that you're in
some way apart from it you're not defined by it you are not it
but you can be with
it and lingering with
it
e
for
a synonym for concentration is
being steadied steadying
yourself in the awareness whatever you're present for at
the
moment
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting take a three breath
Journey but with each breath with each exhale steady yourself
here settle yourself
here
and to whatever degree you feel steadied or
settled grounded here
prepare yourself for ending this meditation by turning your attention
outward into the world around you to the people in your
lives strangers neighbors the people you might encounter
today and gaze upon them steadily calmly
with a steady gaze gaze upon them
kindly with generous eyes Generous Heart with Good Will and well-wishing
and appreciation to gaze upon others with
appreciation wishing that they fulfill their capacity for joy and
happiness may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank
you
so welcome to this second day of the fifth week
introduction to mindfulness and these first few day
couple of days this week I want to emphasize the partnership of mindfulness and
concentration Sati and some and that
um these two work together and
um and uh the concentration or samade brings a
steadiness brings a ability in the steadiness of mind to have a continuous
awareness of something mindfulness kind of opens the space to be
aware and and concentration of keeps us connected so that there's a kind of a
chance to really uh feel and sense something to really get absorbed in
something uh to really stay present without being
distracted by the baggage as I talked about yesterday that we carry or picking
up baggage or without becoming distracted from what we're paying attention
to the um uh when we the mindfulness being the initial kind of awareness or
recognition of something uh can be engaged in different
ways and it's helpful to think of sometimes that the knowing of mindfulness the being aware of
something that uh with the Mind's Eye the mind's sense um we can have the
sense that we're get really right close to something like really right there
with the sensations in the body are right there with the emotions as they're experiencing in the
body or we can step back 1 2 3 feet
steps and just kind of from a distance be aware of something we don't have to be iMed or right up against something
sometimes it's helpful to step back and um like with fear uh if we're really
really close to fear it might feel like it's too much and almost like it is more
activating activates more fear but if we can step back and uh and with a wide perspective
what lots of room for the for the fear then maybe the fear is manageable we can
stay with it and feel it and I've known people for whom uh they did the exercise
of imagining uh how far back what they have to be in order to feel able to stay
present for something those very difficult and some people talk about you know being you know across the street or
up on a hill nearby looking back at themselves sitting and meditating and then they can be with it but if they're
really right in the middle of the challenge it's just too much for them so
awareness mindfulness can kind of adjust the lens that we're we're present for
the lens can be uh close up the lens can be uh maybe panoramic almost stepping
back quite far and getting the big picture uh it's possible to uh for the
the mindfulness to feel uh very uh kind of uh like a close-up that's a very
little piece of something and it's possible to take in again the panoramic
the big picture and learning how to adjust the aperture adjust the distance
the lens that we're using is very very skillful because some things are
difficult to be present for some things are may be much easier to be with but
even there the useful mindfulness and different circumstances is at a
different distance or different aperture different closeness and uh so for example if
there's a lot of agitation in the mind um it might be best just to step back
and take the big picture oh here's an a here's an agitated mind here's an agitated body and to go in getting close
to any one particular sensation of agitation just agitates us more but other times it might be
something that is uh um that is very particular in the body and mind is
fairly steady and then it could be interesting to bring the attention really close in and just even in a
little square centimeter in the body just be there to feel what's
there and then the the concentration then is the steadiness with whatever
aperture whatever lens we're using for mindfulness To Be steady so that we
don't bounce off easily or get distracted easily so how do the function
of concentration is to steady that awareness stay right here and or to or
or to bring a kind of respect whereas where concentration is kind of the act
of respect that keeps us being present for something um I've been at uh social
Gatherings where someone sees me a little bit across from a distance and and uh like you know someone who just
has to go say hello to a lot of people and they um they see me and they look like they're delighted to see me and
they come over and by the time they're shaking my hand their hand has gone limp and their eyes have gone over to the
next person and so I I wasn't met it was like we were getting ready to meet and
see each other clearly but the person just glances off and so we don't want to do that with our inner experience when
we meditate we want to like to have time to really know hear this with respect so
the concentration is a steadiness the the subtleness and that subtleness and
steadiness of mindfulness can be done at different aperture so the example I'm using of coming together like this might
not be you know what's called for maybe it's like this sometimes maybe it's just like from a distance say
hey hi I see you over there and that sense of hi I'm here and you're way over
there can make it easier to be with sadness or with anger or something that
is uh or just a spinning mind that uh kind of settles something helps us to be
with it and present and um and so mindfulness is a little bit
more um I think of it closer closer to wisdom
that the knowing of mindfulness helps us decide what form of mindfulness what
aperture lens we use and also it helps us uh to decide uh how to settle on the
experience do we settle through our whole body being grounded here and that
sense of being grounded and settled gives us a kind of an independent feeling that I'm I can can be here with
whatever comes up or is a steadiness more mental like just that somehow the
the uh the attention of the Mind relaxes or settles in the into the experience
right there another way of thinking of all this is that concentration is left hand and
mindfulness is right hand and they come together to in a cup hands like this and
so then we hold The Experience difficult experiences like maybe a lot of fear um
can just be held by both of these and because they're together there's a little bit more uh fullness a little
more subtl more more something that can receive in the moment and through
moments there's a continuity and uh all along the way that
uh this continuity and subtleness and attention can be supported uh sometimes
is to breathe with the experience or breathe um into the experience or
through the experience there's something about the continuity of breathing coming and going that creates
kind of like it's kind of like the Beat of the Music there's both the the tune
and the beat somehow and and so and so the beat kind of just keeps going and
and uh studies or kind of grounds the music in a certain kind of way and
so the the beat is the continuity of this rhythm of breathing that protects
us from getting caught in thoughts and reactivity and also uh keeps the
awareness little bit present and supports the concentration supports the
the respectful attending staying lingering just being with it and if you
have this idea of a three breath Journey there can be for whatever you're aware of just be aware for three
breaths sometimes that's enough for it to be fully acknowledged and no longer need to more
attention sometimes we give too much attention to some things where we get
confused between thinking about something or trying to fix something
make it go away and mindfulness itself and to have just three breaths with
something makes it easier just to keep it really simple know it and then let it be and come come back to just grounded
just in the breathing if that thing is still calling attention do another three
breath journey of course you can stay longer with things but there's something um protective about just three
breaths and then gently Begin Again with just the breathing and then three
breaths with something else or the same thing and come back and if that seems too complicated or too busy then of
course you don't have to do it but it might um a nice Rhythm for helping you
stay here present with uh Mindful
and and steadied mindful and
concentrated Mindful and uh centered concentered on here this present
now so um
um so the blending or the marriage or the partnership of mindfulness and
concentration is a great support for this practice and so all the things we've been I've been teaching these last
few weeks each step along the way uh can be
um partnered with a little bit of lingering of staying of steadying steadying with experience steadying
ourselves with Body Sensations with breathing steuding ourselves elves with
emotions studying oursel not with thinking so we think more but studying ourselves we're
studying awareness mindfulness with the experience we're studying all studying
all of ourselves with here to be here so we can discover how to be
independent of what is known how they can be uh we can know but that knowing
that awareness is not entangled with what is known it stands independent and
in that Independence we can provide more respect for each and everything if we're
entangled there's no room for respect even though you might think that
this is respect to be kind of all caught up with someone but if we're like this then the
meeting of whatever awareness knows can be done with
respect so may mindfulness may you keep mindfulness
close to you throughout the day so that whoever you
meet whatever activity you're doing whatever objects you're involved in
washing the dishes that you do so with respect for each and
everything thank you