so uh so welcome folks uh good to uh good to be with
you um okay let's uh yeah let's let's sit
sit for
we'll practice a technique guide us through
something but even reaching for a technique is sometimes
sponsored by Bava
tanha the craving to become the we reach
for technique out of a certain kind of bubbling or
agitation
craving and techniques are beautiful I used one today sitting
but we don't want to act from
compulsivity even subtle
compulsivity and so we explore what would it be like to sit
just for a
minute
undefended certain kind of nakedness without our techniques and
[Music]
routines
e e
what would it be to give up all gestures of
coping to trust
in surrender maybe we say trust in what's already
here e
maybe now having seeing some of this
we take some full breaths kind of
cleansing releasing kind of breath that reaches up
into your shoulders down into your belly might even feel it the kind of ripples of relaxation of
your exhale all across your
body
e e
bringing attention to the affective circuits of your
body those Body Sensations that seem emotional or reactive in
nature often felt along the front axis of your body
but uh intense feeling States will coat your body as if with a thin
film of feeling
and we can appreciate the
location the intensity of the arousal State the valance the pleasantness or
unpleasantness the stability or the changing of the
feeling often kind of love a lamp like
movement of emotional Sensations expanding and
Contracting face throat chest
belly
e e
it's like we're just bathing these feelings circuits
this moving pattern of uh emotional Sensations just
bathing them in our
Attention our
patience radical permission for those uh Sensations to
live out their life whatever that life should be over
long they are before they self liberate as the T saying
is
for
e
e e
we can uh investigate the relationship between this feeling
experience affect anger fear sadness Joy
love tranquility we can investigate the
relationship between all of that and
thinking so one of my teachers shinsen Yang would have
us listen listen to auditory thought
can sense where you hear it spatially of course it's not actually happening there
it's a kind of the genius of our brains but the way that auditory
thinking arises is that a kind of
sound often sensed in your head maybe between your ears
when we don't hear it as sound we simply obey it live in the
confines of the World created by that
thought e
this is uh subtle of course sometimes thought kind of sneaks up behind us and
grabs the attention then we keep waking
up to thinking as just hearing
we listen more and more
deeply
for e
and so we have words and uh
feelings and maybe we now open the kind of aperture of attention
to include both
noticing those phenomena noticing their
[Music]
interactions sometimes a Charged thought seems to catalyze a whole set of
feelings in our body it's kind of the basis of cognitive
therapy
sometimes feeling bubbles up from deep within and it begs for an
explanation begs for a story and we give that feeling a
story we give it words
sometimes that story feels like a way of explaining the feeling neutralizing the feeling making
it
safe just stay poised in
awareness noticing these very Central
experiences Being Human feeling in the
body words in our
mind
e
e e
to have equinity is usually to have
equinity with these two aspects of
experience kind of of urgency fostered by feeling affect in our
body the orchestration of our
craving through words in our mind
so we practice just knowing and allowing blessing these
experiences with awareness patience
love
e
e e
okay so this is from the um stoic uh
philosopher senica uh if one does not know to which
Port one is sailing no wind is
favorable I was talking uh to a friend about kind of meaning meaning
purpose uh and they asked like are there any any Dharma talks about meaning and
purpose I thought about it it's like well the one hand it's
like no there like very very few probably explicitly address those themes
that are maybe more those words are more familiar to western western
philosophical traditions uh but on the other hand the sort of whole of the Dharma presupposes
some ideas about meaning and purpose and I ask myself the question do
I reflect on meaning and purpose not really not
really do I have it I think so but the meaning has been a kind of
byproduct of my love not a goal to which
I've aspired and this topic it strikes me is
is quite tricky right because Dharma talks are meant to be at least partially
a kind of way of inviting folks into a
new view you know
uh yeah come see for yourself right but there's an invitation to a new view and
the tricky part is that meaning involves intrinsic motivation it cannot be
prescribed by me or anyone else to you right this is like very
personal and intrinsic motivation is the the pursuit of a kind of activity for
its inherent interest or enjoyment enrichment
something um we're we're doing uh we're doing it is its own reward in a
way and some of this is drawing on on Research kind of body of research known
as self-determination Theory I can I can post something about
that um so extrinsic motivation is
instrumental it's pursuing a goal pursuing a kind of outcome doing
something to get something rather than doing something because it's inherently
enriching and I don't want to say and no one would say that in extrinsic motivation is bad intrinsic is
good but I think we can say fairly that
thriving thriving is a way of living that is
focused on uh intrinsic intrinsic
motivation that if our lives are going to be you know animated full of meaning
it's going to feel intrinsically motivated and so intrinsic intrinsic
value doesn't it doesn't exist for the sake of something else right so this is
um the couple the researchers Ryan and DC so they write uh consider the value
of wealth if we asked a person why are you working so hard one common answer might be to accumulate accumulate money
or wealth if we then ask why do you want wealth there might again be various
answers one might be because I want to be admired we would then need to ask well
why do you want to be admired again various answers might emerge
because so far we've not reached a bottom line but suppose the person
answers because I want to feel loved when we get to this answer we can
ask again why do you want to be loved but here our interviewee is likely to be
puzzled when it comes to love we seem to have hit an irreducible
one subject might say I don't know what you mean everyone wants love or because love is good at a fundamental
psychological level Love Is irreducible it is a good that explains
itself so you might reflect on your life
what are the goods that are not a means to something else what is irreducible
you know this is not not something you think
you should feel it really must be native to your
heart meaning it's it said um is linked
to satisfying these basic psychological
needs and so basic psychological needs are hypothesized to
be Universal and fundamental meaning that if thwarted we
suffer there and there are no kind of Replacements no compensations for the
failure to meet these three basic needs and in this body of of research it's
it's autonomy competence and related
so autonomy in this context means like being engaged in an activity with a full
sense of willingness volition choice
choiceful and generally that's that's it's linked to doing you know spending
one's energy doing work with a sense of of
Engagement and I would say but it's not limited to that
um Dharma practice I would say itself engenders
some we don't use this language much but deep sense of autonomy like we become
deeply willingly engaged with life whatever shape that
is and there's a certain sense of we also don't use the word independence we
say interdependence but we there's a sense of of Independence and confidence
engendered by practice
feels freely offered our our
energy sometimes um you know a sense of autonomy and
meaning may be may be related to some Leisure you know when we have the choice
to do this or that even when we just have a tiny bit maybe it's just 10
minutes maybe you're busy with the life and children and all of it it's like
okay just 10 minutes but it's like okay that actually maybe rest rest can become very
meaningful rest can become very meaningful sense of of autonomy in the
free flow of where you place your attention the need for comp
uh refers to a sense of efficacy of of finding um channels for your
capabilities and so maslo uh maslo writes um if you
deliberately plan on being less than you're capable of being I warn you
you'll be deeply unhappy for the rest of your life you will be
evading your own capacities your own
possibilities so this is not some kind of grandos fantasy you know it's like
I'm bad at like 1 million things and good at like three and I'm unashamed of
the enormous swalls of my incompetence but I know what I can
cultivate I uh I also associate competence this kind of basic need with
something like wisdom and understanding if you cannot understand yourself your
choices your behavior the behavior of people around you it's very hard to find
life meaningful it becomes a kind of puzzle that we don't quite get and
so part of the sense of competence meeting this kind of basic need is
supported by our Dharma practice where we're growing in understanding understanding ourself and partially
through that understanding the inner lives of others one of the fruits of Dharma
practice is the capacity to predict our own feelings in response to this or that
to predict the behavior of others to understand how their mind relates to
their behavior and this this supports this sense of of
competence in the world not being ambushed by surprises at
every moment we have to know a lot about human
nature about our nervous system about Dua and anicha about
unsatisfactoriness about the changing of all things we have to know a lot about
all of that to navigate the world skillfully to be more and more
competent and then the need for um for relatedness the need for
relatedness um this is uh the sense of of feeling connected to
and cared about by others this is about
about spiritual friendship about saana
about uh family and loved ones and heart
companions it's about those we we serve you
know and um this engenders a lot of meaning you
know I think uh Daniel conoman the the Noel yet at the end of his life was
asked to kind of sum up you know sum up his learning and behavioral economics
and all this stuff and he was like well spend time with people you care about
that was what he said actually an interview when he died just a few days after
it you know we know our life
counts When Love is its main currency you
know that um that engenders a lot of sense of
meaning and meaning in other words um will be Shackled by a fixation
on I me mine yeah we have to know ourself we have to take good care of
ourself we have to protect our boundaries all these things things right um but uh meaning to the
extent that which it's it's where there's a kind of
fixation on me as a kind of Island
uh that that um really really squelches
the possibilities for meaning meaning in other words is engendered by the other
and so yeah these kind of basic
psychological needs you know autonomy competence
relatedness it's connected to um sense of um yeah of intrinsic meaning
meaning in our life sense of purpose purpose and so maybe we reflect on this
as a a way of understanding our own
needs and uh ways in which life might become even
richer so I offer this for your consideration and uh yeah I wish you all
well thank you
okay folks [Music] um so uh so I Retreat next week
um uh at IRC maybe some of you will be there I know some of you will be there
so um won't have class then but we'll be back the following week I think September
4 um okay folks thank you uh thank you all yeah I wish you wish you all well