good to be with you all again on this Wednesday morning for me here in
California and so yeah so good to be with you all this
week we are going to
continue um continue this journey of exploring the symboles of the five
Aggregates or five bundles and today uh we uh include the
exploration of uh the third simile which um the Buddha used the
Mirage that arises um
the uh heat of the noon in the summer this shimmering Mirage can emerge and
it's used to um Al liken the
perceptions Sona which is the PO term um that we often use to describe
this and so our perceptions Sonia is like this High Noon
shimmering uh Mirage I found this really really
evocative and so we are going to practice with this and uh we discover what it feels
like for us this perception and there are many uh words
uh that may be uh capturing uh this um meaning of
Saia and so perception is one and there's also
perceiving conception recognition name
Concepts uh Impressions symbols and all of this can
be a way to kind of capture this aspect of ourselves that's able to perceive
things and it's like a shimmering Mirage uh in the high noon
in the hot season so let's practice and then we'll
explore this a little bit uh in in the daret I'm going to start with the sound
of a
bell so come into a meditative posture
there is often for me a sense of coming home to this body mind and
heart what is a sense for
you at this moment
coming into your meditative
space maybe you're feeling a kind of energetic
settling [Music] downwards or settling back
allow yourself to ease into this
moment now and ease
into this space here
Mindful and a heartful there is often a kind of a
tenderness arise in my heart
even the sense of a sacredness of coming
home to this present
moment the Mind may still wanted to think about the future the
past it's got plans to
do let them be the floating clouds
we are dropping in into the felt
sense right here and now
and sensing the body sitting lying down whatever the posture you may be
taking as you connect deeper with the present
moment there may be a sense of mindful awareness becomes
stable steady
you may feel more available to the
moments or the moments are more available to you
the movements of the breath May register more
fully you may feel
aliveness and kind of a Vitality as you
breathe or you may feel as you
breathe the whole body is animated
en
liened different kinds of a
Sensations may become visible felt out obvious
Sensations have a kind of buzz in the
body maybe an kind of underlying humming
you may notice we are already
perceiving our experiences
allow the mindful awareness to
expand receiving the whole energetic Chi
body or maybe even beyond the boundaries of the body
you may notice the perceptions arise as the experience
happen noticing the sensations feel like a soap bubbles
or the water bubbles of the
rain we yet the perceptions are ephemeral
like the Mirage shimmering [Music]
Mirage of the high noon in the hot
season may have images
words that emerges as your experience
happen and then they fade
away
e e
sometimes the mind can get
excited about yet the images the
perceptions that are
rise and you gently inviting yourself to stay
connected with a felt
sense without pushing over away anything or being pulled into
anything
e
e e
noce how the mind can get involved
based on the perceiving Mirage in the
mind start telling
stories start analyzing criticizing blaming
it's just a perception
comes goes as we experience
something in the felt
sense
e
e e
it's quiet
here and when it's
quiet maybe you can drop in below the surface
level of the activity of the Mind
maybe even below the [Music]
perceiving impressions
trusting the immediacy of your felt sense
experience they don't need [Music] words
images to justify their presence
peaceful nourishing silence
Within
for
e
e for
in a moment our ringbell to end of the sit
again the invitation is to stay in your meditative bubble if you
like and I'll begin the darat by
reading the simile from the
sutta and allow the words drop into the
depth of your being like the stones
settle in the quiet peaceful Lake and let whatever touches you to
have its own effect and otherwise they can just
settle settle down to the bottom of the lake
for
[Music]
suppose practitioners that in the last month of
the hot Seasons at High Noon a shimmering Mirage
appears a person with a good sight would inspect it ponder it and carefully
investigate it and it would appear to them to be
void Hollow and insubstantial for what substance would
there be in a mirage so to
practitioners whatever kind of a perception there is whether past future or
present internal or external gross or
subtle inferior or Superior far or near a practitioner
inspects it P it and carefully investigates it
and it would appear to them to be void Hollow
insubstantial for what substance would there be in
perception and so this word siia as I uh was reflecting at the
beginning of the meditation that there are many
translations perceiving conception name
concept Impressions symbols signs Etc
Etc it's the function miraculous a function of a human mind that is able to
perceive something and give it a
label you hear something outside oh that's a bird bird
singing or you smell something oh that's a Jas and
flowers so we can perceive and this is a wonderful capacity we all have maybe
based on you know leld memories and past
the imprints that we know in our
system yet when we're not careful and present with what's happening in the
this process our usual
relationship with perception uh can become rather
tricky we're often very quick to Short
change the momentary perceptions as a something much more
solid and conclusive as if they are the truth
you know sometimes around me um maybe a
little further out there may be a kind of a buzzing
sound around well you know it could be leaf
blower that could also be some sort of construction that's going
on that immediate the perception is kind of low
buzzing sound in my environment but the mind can leap into a
mirage or that must be the leaf blower that happens at the 7 a.m. in the
morning why would they have to do
that right in the middle of my meditation you can see how this Mirage
and the movies start to get created in our mind where the
reality of what is happening in the
experience is just that we're perceiving a kind of loud sound that's in the
environment and I don't actually know what exactly it is but the mind can leap
into a kind of conclusion or truth or a kind of a
reality now I could be right you know I could be right and this is the
um even more complicated part of the perception apparatus and so if I did
find out that I was right well you know we can reinforce our
belief believe and are hardening our perceptions that we already there and
look at me I got right yes it's absolutely a leaf FL that shouldn't have
happened in this morning at this time and so this is how the perception
becomes a cleaning perception the cleaning and
existing is infused into the immediacy of our
experience when we're not attuned or to stay with our direct
experience and so often uh when our perceptions about
something don't agree amongst a group of people you know that can be a big fight
about what the reality is and this is often how the conflict happens it's that
the people perceive things differently but we they get hardened
into reality uh conclusions and
beliefs and uh that leads to a kind of a bumpiness against each other and because
our perceptions are not necessarily the same it's just the perceptions yet we take a
big leap so that's the danger of this cleaning Aggregates of a
perception and the reality of our perceptions is
that uh they are rather ephemeral as what the simile is pointing
to that that there're kind of a shimmering Mirage in the hot season at High
Noon they feel real but the reality is
it emerges in some form shape and and uh
some texture and it fades away when the conditions change when the weather cools
it goes away I remember once um uh
Retreat I went I had a sequence of experiences and I was perceiving it in a
certain way then I went to report to my teacher about my experience and I
described to him with a great confidence said this must be what I thought it
was and my teacher looked at me and said oh that's just one way to see it
just at that moment the Mirage
bursted so I realized I was making it much more solid and much more
conclusive about the ephemeral perceptions that was created based on my
experience and while the reality is that there may be many ways that the
experience it could be perceived
and they're already gone and then they're no longer
there I can't really be very certain what what what it was
exactly and so that was a really very useful teaching and learning moment for
me now I want to uh speak a little uh about an another aspect of a
perception sometimes this teaching about a perception being Mirage can be
interpretated as if somehow our perceptions are never
valid and I want to just point out that itself is also a
perception so perceiving is a very
important function of a human mind and human beings and we can on this part of
a function to work well enough for us to go about living our
lives without making a total chaos right we're counting on us being a able to
perceive I don't know white rice has white rice and brown
rice has a brown rice and we're counting on our perceptions and so we can pick up
the right kid from school not someone else's kid that's very important
um what the teaching is pointing to is how we and our
relationships uh with this aspect of a function can get um stuck the stuckness
the clinging the existence the belief and the conclusiveness that we have about our
perceptions is what leads to Dua or
stress you may have a perception that someone is angry right now and that's
momentary and that may be very much true very much so but we can build upon that perception
to make a bigger conclusion that wow this person is really an angry
person now that's more than a big
Mirage that's a big conclusion now the person got boxed up
boxed in as a angry person what happens is now it's very
difficult to see this person in other ways but being an angry
person and so that's what um this teaching is pointing to that there is a
Dua in the cleaning of the perception the cleaning Aggregates the per
perception so we're learning to discern this cleaning forces that are
operating to allow us little by little let go of the cleaning to allow the
ephemeral perceptions to just be what they are so that's the teach teachings on the
simile of the Mirage and as a
perception and so I invite you to have fun and enjoy and maybe be humorous
about your perceptions uh in this in the rest of the day practicing with this or
exploring this and uh we'll continue tomorrow so thank you everyone for being
here have a wonderful rest of the day