so it's the tradition near the beginning of the year to talk about some of the
foundational teachings and so I thought I would do a little bit uh of that today but I want
to talk about them in a different way not the usual way I'm often I like to do
this not the usual way somehow I don't know what that says about me exactly but
uh and maybe I'll just uh start with um that the Buddha used a lot of similes
and some metaphors and part of that's what's the fun of some of the sutas is
reading them is really how the Buddha brings things to life with these similes
aimile is a way in which you know something is like something else so
aimile starts with something presumably that you know and that you're familiar with and then this new idea whatever the
Buddhist teaching he's saying oh it's like this thing you already know but for us thousands of years later
we're having to imagine kind of what it was like you know for them back then but I think we
can and many of the similes have to do with agriculture or animals or something
like this so one thing I'd like to maybe or
maybe I'll just add a few things that somebody even counted Caroline rice Davids uh she was one of the very first
uh translators this is back in the 1890s this is when the sutas were just getting
translated into Western languages so this at the end of the 19th century and
uh she counted and I don't know how she did this
568 different concepts for which this the Buddha gave simile that's a lot
that's you know quite something that kind of he's loved to use this way for
teaching and then maybe I'll start with something that maybe would be more of a metaphor than a simil if you wanted to
get technical but it's this [Music] idea that the Buddha's teachings
describe a way to Liberation to Greater Freedom greater peace greater
well-being I mean different people have different relationships to this word Liberation that's fine you're welcome to
have your own relationship with it and what it means to you and why you
practice but the the central premise is that there's a path there's a way to get
to this Liberation this greater well-being and often this is a path we
describe it as a path and somehow this idea of a path when we bring that to
mind it uh often has a sense of like oh yeah there's a clear Passage way through
which a person or anybody any creature an animal excuse
me so a passage way I hope my voice holds
up I don't know what just happened with my voice I'll drink more water
now we'll see how it is okay it's a little bit better so this idea of a path to
Liberation is like this clear passageway in which you know a being
could just walk along but that's not quite the way that
it is because when we have this idea in our mind of a path it's often something
that's there already and we walk along at the sidewalk the road hiking trail it's
there already and we find it and we walk on it but this path to
Liberation maybe the pointing to it has happened before but it's not necessarily
like a clear passage way that just exists instead we are creating it as
we're walking it as we're doing these teachings as we're cultivating these wholesome qualities as
we're practicing mindfulness concentration right speech
Etc so this metaphor kind of breaks down because it's often we start to
think like oh yeah okay if I just get on the path and then it'll be smooth sailing but this kind of idea of a path
is more of a concept it's really things that we are doing that we are
experiencing in this moment but to get back to this metaphor
of the path in the same way that that we walk on a passage way or that we do Buddhist
practices when we're walking on a passage way we bring all of ourselves there of course we do we don't bring a
just one arm and leave the other arm back or you know something ridiculous like
that so in the same way this uh path towards greater freedom and ease and
peace requires all of us all aspects of us all of us even those secret hidden
parts that we're trying to wish would just go away or we don't even want to acknowledge that exist there
our what's in our mind what's in our hearts what we say what we do it's all
of it is part of this path and there's this metaphor not only
of a path but that it was discovered by somebody that was uh in the woods and
say oh wow I think there's a path here and chopped down some of the maybe took
a hatchet and chopped down some of the things that were in the way found their
way along this passageway you know a lot of work and then they found this city
this beautiful ancient city that had been there but it had been overgrown and
they cleaned it all up and discovered like wow this this place is fantastic
it's beautiful and then this uh individual went back and told the king and the
queen hey I discovered this this path to this really beautiful
location and the king and the queen go and they walk on the path and they go to this
beautiful place and say this is great okay we're we're going to stay here and
we're going to move our kingdom here and I first heard this story from
Gil frall and for some reason you know back then I was really touched by this idea
that he said he said it's meaningful that this individual went back and told
the king and the Queen and then the king and the queen are the ones that are walking on this path it's
the sense of nobility the sense of kind of what's Noble in all of us like to be to on this
path towards greater Freedom or maybe a sense of Regal or you know the uprightness or something like this
respect sense of respect for those individuals who are on this
path so in this way liberation ation is like this long forgotten City in the
forest and but maybe just as it's possible you know anthropologists are
doing this right in modern times maybe just as it's possible to reclaim and
then and habit the city once the path is found it is possible to live a life with
greater freedom and ease and peace as we engage with this path
so elsewhere in the sutas there's a little bit more kind of a richer uh
description of this idea of a path that I'd like to share with
you and um it takes place in the context of uh one of the Buddha's cousins his
name is Tissa Tissa he was a monastic he had ordained underneath his cousin the
Buddha and he was having a hard time and he
says I am dissatisfied with the spiritual life you know kind of this formal language like this is not all I
thought it was going to be and he's saying I have doubts about the
teachings so here's somebody who ordained who decided to you know commit
his life to the practice and after doing it for some time is saying I'm dissatisfied and I have
doubts and the Buddha gives him some teachings and some of the teachings are
what a little bit what I'm going to share here is a simile so the Buddha goes um and says to
Tissa he says Suppose there were two people and one was not skilled in the
path and the other one was and that individual that was not skilled in the path would question the
one who was skilled in the path and the person who was skilled in the path would
reply this is the right way walk along it for a while and you will come to a
fork in the road avoid the left fork and go down the
Right Fork walk along it for a while and you will see a dense
forest go through the forest for a while and then you'll see a vast marshy
swamp go through the swamp for a while and then you will see a steep
slope go down the slope for a while and then you will see a level clear Parkland
if Park Place that's beautiful so this is a little bit more
descriptive it's like okay go to the forest and hang a right and go through
the swamp and over the Dell Through the Wood Woods I don't know these types of things but and then the Buddha kind of
like he unpacked that for Tisa well what does this mean what are the how is this
uh these different things that one would meet and walking this path and that Buddha he does give um
precise uh instructions or descriptions but I'm going to embellish them a little
bit more for modern times and make them a little bit more um relatable for us
rather than just um giving the simple answers that he gave
so he's so the t uh I'm sorry the Buddha explains to the Tissa in the beginning the person who doesn't know the path or
is not skilled in the path is you know everybody who's not awakened and the person who is skilled in it is somebody
who's awakened such as the Buddha and then instructions was to go
this direction and you'll come to a fork in the road what is the fork in the road
represent the fork represents doubt the sense of I'm not so sure about
this is this and this I'm not so sure about it can show up in a number of different ways like is this really going
to lead to Greater well-being or do I really understand
what the teachings are we're all sitting quiet for 30 minutes but am I doing what everybody else is doing am I supposed to
be doing this so we can have doubt about what we're doing we can have doubt about the
practice we can have doubt about the teachings like does this really lead to
where that says we could have doubt about the teacher does Diana really know
what she's talking about or we can even say this Buddha person or whatever right so there's so many different ways in
which the doubt can show up and I love that is just flat out there doubt is
going to arise instead of pretending like okay as long as as you just I don't know believe enough it'll
be fine instead doubt is part of the path it's part of the
path we are not asking people to just believe and don't have any doubt it's
the opposite it's saying doubt is going to arise and we work with doubt by
investigating there's a few ways in which we can do this one is to gain some clarity well what is it that I'm really
vacillating about what is it that makes me uh hesitate it makes me not quite
sure if I really want to do this and even just asking ourselves what
is it specifically just that activity of asking ourselves can help bring some clarity like oh I guess I'm just not
sure if I actually can do this it seems kind of hard this whole meditate regularly thing
and people talk about Retreats I don't know if I can ever go on a retreat if I want to go on a retreat this type of
thing so first is just to investigate what is the doubt about like if you can
is there something that you're insure of and if it's about your own
capabilities maybe you can remind yourselves of how you have learned how to do other
things drive a car most likely ride a bicycle play an instrument
maybe different language all these different things and in the beginning there's always this feeling like I'm not
so sure about it if instead you have specific uh
doubts about the teachings Buddhists say this and in this
tradition they say that another tradition they say that but what's the truth and do I have to believe
everything myself myself I'll say you don't have to believe everything I really like to emphasize this tradition
emphasizes especially the way that we teach it here is about what you can experience what you can know for
yourself it's not about just taking on more views and
beliefs we're not asking you to just swallow everything drink the
Kool-Aid and become part of the clan or something like that instead see for
yourself see for yourself but if you are if there is some
specific questions ask somebody ask a teacher read a Dharma book listen to
Dharma talks ask somebody else that you know you know is there's a way maybe to
engage with whatever it is that you have doubt about and the teacher the Buddha gives
very clear uh instructions on how to investigate a teacher and even says that you should investigate a
teacher should investigate whether they are exhibiting greed hatred or
delusion so you're welcome to examine me I'm not a completely awakened person I still have some greed hatred and
delusion but you know I'm up here I'm just sharing it with you I'm not diluted that I'm not diluted
[Laughter] or but so this fork in the road is about
doubt and doubt often we maybe wouldn't assign the word out to it but often it
shows up with just kind of like this hesitation like I'm not sure
maybe I think I um think I had Gil just bringing him into the room uh an earlier
teaching that he gave I remember him early this was some many years ago I
heard him say yeah well maybe who knows maybe those who are practicing Sufi they do a lot of dancing they're maybe having
more fun so maybe that might be go over there so I just kind of like appreciated
this open-handedness right if this if this works for you this is fantastic and you're we're happy that you're here
but you don't have to stay of course so walking along the path you come to a
fork and then the instructions were don't go to the left go to the
right so on the left is this was the
wrong path and we and then the right is the right
path but what does that mean for those of you who are familiar
with the eight-fold path they'll be talking about you know right and these eight elements versus wrong and these
eight elements but we're using this word right not in a moralistic way but in a
way that this is like a the best tool this is the right tool screwdriver is
the best tool for for undo screws rather than a hammer for example so write is in
correct or most appropriate we could also say wise I'll just briefly say what the
eight-fold path is wise view wise intention wise speech
wise action wise livelihood wise effort wise mindfulness wise
concentration here's the pneumonic that I use [Music]
visy view intention speech action livelihood effort mindfulness concentration if you want to remember
those eight that's the eight that they are maybe I'll unpack some of them um a
little bit in a moment but the interesting thing is I think so so to go down the left would be
to do you know wrong view wrong intention wrong speech Etc
but without going into all the details of exactly what they are I think one thing that's interesting to point out
is that the wrong quote unquote just wrong in the sense that it's not going
to lead you to Greater peace and happiness and Liberation in a stable way is that it
lures us it's not like innocently uh just there to the left but there's a way in
which today we have what this new word that I learned recently hyper palatable
Foods right we have things that are just designed to be as delicious and as addictive as possible they're purposely
designed this didn't exist at the Buddhist time right we have uh advertising agencies their job is to
convince us to do things right this didn't exist back then we have media
sources their job is to get us to click and to you know get lost into that or there's other media sources their job is
to get us outraged right so they are purposely trying to I would say maybe
like lure us you know to this other way so it's not so easy just to go to the
right path and part of it is because there isn't like maybe when you first go
down this right path there's it's you can't see very far maybe there's you have to do a little bit of chopping away
of the plants or the whatever is in the way of the Jungle or something like this
it's not like you can see so clearly like oh yeah I just have to go a few steps and everything's going to be
fine but the other way they are luring us with like oh yeah this is going to be
delicious this is going to be fun you're going to feel good so just want to
acknowledge that that it's so easy to go down the other way we all do do in
different ways and we spend different durations of time down there and if you find that happen no problem just come
back over you don't have to go back to the fork just hop
over I love this we start where we are and sometimes where we are is down
watching uh YouTube videos on some social thing you know for an hour and
realize oh my gosh you know how did I find myself
here while we're eating potato chips or
something so then the um instructions were avoid
the left work take the right we walk for a little while and you'll see a dense forest and then you go through a forest
so the forest we could say is um ignorance and ignorance is just find as
just not knowing just not knowing doesn't mean
you're incapable of knowing you just didn't know so this idea of ignorance is often
the reason why you know I'm imagining that it's we have to go down the Right
Fork we take that fork and or go on the path a little bit the first step in the aold path is
View and there's a way in which the Right View maybe I'll say briefly we can
understand Right View as um using a framework to view to see our
experience and there's two elements to this framework this framework or this frame
of reference is actions have
consequences of course we do this is not news to anybody but but it's the thoroughness of
this it's that what happens in our minds has consequences what we say has
consequences you know how we are in the world has consequences and just to recognize that
everything has consequences really starts to highlight the importance of what we are doing with
our life and how we're spending our time and then when we start to pay attention
to that we start to realize oh you know but I don't actually know what my mind is doing all the
time ignorance I don't know you know what I'm saying all the time sometimes
things just come out that's one framework with Right View the second
is there is a suffering and there's reasons for suffering there's difficulties and reasons for
difficulties and there's not difficulties and reasons for not
difficulties this is isn't news to anybody either but just kind of as a framework to notice like oh yeah this is
one of those difficulties and sometimes it can be helpful to inquire and what is the cause what's underline
this so ignorance when we start to have a little bit of Right View we start to see how much we don't know maybe we
don't know what's underneath what's causing the difficulties maybe we don't know how to have less of the
difficulties and to to find a way from them or away from
them so this dense forest is ignorance and often we have to pass through this
and some so much of meditation practice is helping us just to learn about
ourselves notice what the Mind likes to do I'm often saying that I had no idea I
was such a planner I really didn't know how much I planned until I started meditation practice I was was planning
everything so what other things are there to learn with meditation practice we start to do see what is our reactions
when we're physically uncomfortable do we turn to like just anger or hatred or pity or you know poor
me or you know what do we do what are the patterns of our life they start to show up in our meditation practice so
kind of like going through this dense forest is it's part of this way of working through ignorance the other side
just learning about ourselves learning about the world with this
practice and then maybe part of the other way to ignorance is just to acknowledge like you know what I don't
know nearly as much as I thought I did about myself maybe just to know that you
don't know that alone is such like a big step through this
ignorance and then continu in this simile uh of this path after the forest
after you get on the other side of that is this vast marshy
swamp I like this idea of a swamp it's something where you have to tread
carefully and you have to like try to find you know firm ground from one
little area to the next and maybe take each step with uh care so that you don't
fold in with the quicksand or swampy swamp so to like seek out the solid
ground at each step so this swamp um represents this
seeking Comfort or sensuality things that are always Pleasant to the senses
incessantly we are always looking for you know to be as comfortable as
possible there isn't anything wrong with that right we can definitely do that and still stay on um Solid Ground without
sinking into the swamp But It's tricky because we can you know slide
right into just pursuing pleasure after pleasure after pleasure and you know the
psychologists have been talking about this hedonic treadmill a lot for years
they recognize the same thing right then it's just never ending there is no end
we keep on thinking there will will be well as soon as I get this as soon as I do that then I'll be
happy turns out it doesn't work so well right so this endless pursuit of
comfortableness and then maybe I'll say something that uh I heard an interview
um I guess just a few days ago I heard a portion of an interview so just a little
but with David Goggins he's this Ultra marathoner he like runs like 200 miles
or you know something ridiculous like this foral former Navy SEAL and I don't
know all these like incredible things that he does and uh he says I don't like
it I don't want to do it but I'm doing it anyway and I thought oh this is
interesting you're like what uh helps him to do this and
um this interview was with a neuroscientist and the neuroscientist was saying you know they just discovered
that there's this area in the brain that um grows when you do things
specifically that you don't want to do it doesn't count if you didn't want to
do and now you like them then that doesn't count anymore you have to not want to do it and this as this area of
the the brain grows there's more ease and happiness I hope I'm remembering this
right with ease and happiness I remember thinking like oh I have to remember that for the Dhat talk but uh now here I am
at the Dhat talk and I can't remember precisely but this whole idea though and I think all of us know this there's
something that feels good when we're you know we do something that's a little bit
difficult you know to apologize
to not eat the potato chips or whatever it is these things that make our life
better otherwise our life just gets smaller and smaller and smaller like if we're only trying to be comfortable all
the time so the swamp of this pursuing sensual
Pleasures absolutely sensual Pleasures are part of life joy and happiness is part of life I don't want to say it has
to be austerity and nothing but but difficulty but just watch how we are
with h our sensuality we can get lost in there thinking that it finally it will
make it happy but i' I've said this many times here like if it did make you happy
you would not be here on a Monday night right you would be out there doing whatever it is that makes you
happy so after the swamp then there was this steep slope like maybe we can even
think of like a cliff or something like this and the steep slope stands for
anger and despair it's quite something that the
Buddha is just flat out saying this anger and
despair or sometimes it could be dis uh translated as anger and distress some
translators use despair but there's this idea that um sometimes we like if we we
get a little bit angry that things aren't the the way that we want them to
be this is Dua you know the Buddha has been pointing to this but sometimes there's a way in which we feel like well
why not looks like this person has that why can't I or you know whatever it is
there's a way in such we can like feel a little bit angry or this despair like oh
I'm never going to get better things are going to be different are never going to be
different there's this way that um we have
this this strong sense of self we might say that wants to be bolstered and
protected and Polished so that we're always looking good for other people that we're looking good for
ourselves and as long as that's really strong and we're always trying to look good there will be anger and there will
be despair because there isn't a self there isn't this core
to which everything happens instead there's just this collection of
experiences sometimes things look great and sometimes they don't that's just how
it is so this anger and this despair are part of the path of
practice doesn't mean that you're doing anything wrong necessarily sometimes it can be but just part of reason why I
really appreciate this is the humanness that the Buddha is bringing into
this so at the and then after going through
the forest the swamp the steep slope or maybe Cliff then you get to this what uh
the Buddha described as this level clear Park so it's just easy right to if it's
level you don't have to go up and down the hills and it's a park it's designed to be
pleasant and he's describing that is nibana but maybe even if we don't Aspire
exactly for nibana maybe it's just a place that where there can be some more ease because of course there are times
of more ease too it's not always drudgery through forests and swamps and
steepness maybe there's we come to a you know a a landing a
plateau get our get our bearings rest for a minute and then maybe we can see oh yeah okay now I think I time to go
this direction and then at the end of this uh
suta the Buddha says to his cousin Tissa he says
Tissa I'm here to advise you to assist you and to teach you
I appreciate this very much the Buddha is saying okay you're not just out there on your own here I'm giving you some
directions and we could say that all these sutas are about instructions and directions and this idea of a path shows
up in so many different ways and he's saying I'm here to advise you to assist you and to teach you how
toine your ways through the forests the swamps and the
cliffs so with that I think I'll stop and I'll open it up and see if there's some
questions or
comments do you want to um thank you sometimes I question why I
meditate meditate however after I meditate I know why it's very simple
because I feel better and does that is that work is
when you're questioning why you meditate do you are you're still able to meditate
even though you're questioning like why am I doing this I don't know but I'm going to do it anyway
is it kind of like well kind of like that yeah but it's well worth it yes it
even though I have doubts yeah yeah very nice thank you thank you for sharing that okay
sure anybody else have a comment or
question maybe will it's try over here can you walk right over
to thank you this is a comment more than a question just I've been listening to
David goggin's book on audible I haven't gotten to the place where he starts running marathons but I
do know he just got into the uh the seals so anyway it's fascinating about
the Neuroscience of that yes it is fascinating and it's a interesting R to
find that uh and I think we there's a part of us that recognizes when we accomplish something that's hard there's
like this uplift like oh yeah I did it okay yeah yeah so I think the those
neuroscientists they're always finding
something anybody else have a comment or
question Diana I'll um strengthen that comment about goggin
I heard the same thing from Jack Lan now most people don't even know who he is
but he when they asked him he said I don't really like going to the gym I don't really like going and working out
but he did you know and was able to make quite a career of teaching exercise and
doing these incredible you know swimming handcuffed towing a a robo behind him
didn't you ever he he tow a robo 2,000 lb in it behind him
handcuffed from San Francisco to Alcatraz that's amazing yeah wow okay so
these amazing individuals okay so they have something in them that yeah nice
but I sort of Wonder there must also be some part that
knows that there's a reward there yeah you know that that it isn't just
I'm G to do this out of just some sort of ego thing yeah
yeah and I think today just because we're like it's the lure of the to not
do difficult things is so strong right it's sometimes hard and then the idea of
doing something difficult looms so large in our minds like oh I can't do that and
because it's so much easier all I have to do is click this or you know open up the cupboard or I don't know something
and I'll have something pleasurable I don't want to do that hard thing I don't have to do that hard thing or
something maybe just having a regular meditation practice is the hard thing maybe coming to IMC is a hard
thing anybody else have a
comment okay okay well thank you all and I wish you a safe travels home and
may the path home be safe and when you get to the fork of the road turn right
thank you thank you and if you have some questions you're welcome to come up and uh talk to me private