so I want to read just a few paragraphs as a a way of sliding into
our meditation so if you've already started you can just continue or feel free to
close your eyes and the invitation is if what I
read is interesting to you you could play with it in the meditation it's
optional it's just a few paragraphs
I once met a man who was raised on the Canadian prairies we got to talking about the
open space and how it had shaped his Spirit when the wind stops he said it is
so loud that everyone pauses to listen the thought intrigued me how
could the end of a sound be loud but when I traveled to those prairies I began to understand for the
people in the great prairies the sound they hear the music that underlies their
lives is the constant and everpresent howl of the wind to them it is no sound
at all when it is removed the silence takes a different shape and all are aware of
it all pause to hear we need to pay heed to the many
silences in our lives an empty room is alive with a different silence than a room where
someone is hiding the Silence of a happy house Echoes less Darkly than the Silence of a
house of brooding anger The Silence of a winter morning is
sharper than the Silence of a summer Dawn The Silence of a mountain pass is
larger than the Silence of a Forest Glen these are not
fantasies they are subtle discriminations of the senses though all are the absence of
sound each Silence has a character of its own we can meditate listening to the
shape of the silence that surrounds us it focuses us on the thin line
between what is there and what is not there it opens our heart to the
Unseen and reminds us that the world is larger than the events that fill our
days so we're almost at the winter solstice here in the northern hemisphere
that is and it'll be happening in another five or six days so I always
feel like that's a natural time for uh going inward being
quiet uh it's kind of the feels like a time of pause to
me it's like the pause actually at the end of a of a pendulum swing um that's
how the solstices and the equinoxes work is that you know it gets slower and
slower in terms of you how the days are changing and finally it get to the
shortest day and then it's going to swing back the Equinox is at the bottom things are changing quickly and then it
swings to the other side so it has that feeling of getting to that pause and
change of Direction so before the sit those of you
who were here at the beginning I read a little Passage message that included uh listening to the shape of silence as an
invitation and I'm not putting anyone on the spot but I'm just curious if anyone tried it and if anyone wants to um
comment on anything that you
noticed maybe you all just went immediately into samat oh here's one great there's a microphone I think there
yeah thank you so much for bringing
it my experience was searching forence oh
and can you yeah you just hold the button down
there you go how about now yeah okay my experience was I went searching for
silence and I had a hard time hearing
it I heard a lot of sounds and movements and some coughs
and then I I went Inward and I noticed some silence Within Myself
uhuh and I just paid close attention to that and listened nice yeah that was my
experience great yeah there's something about when we go looking for for it the
noise if you will that's a virtual idea but um the noise of that going toward
can obscure the silence so I'm glad you touched it that's
fantastic yeah and one more here yeah hi
best well I always notice that the energy of meditating with the group is
very different than meditating at my home it's a different kind of Silence
isn't it yeah exactly it just feels different here nice yeah great
good thing to notice yeah and here
I thought I would be meditating on silence but that ending sentence which
was something I'm paraphrasing here about the world being much larger than our individual
circumstances hit me really hard and then it just sent my mind off onto contemplation
of that okay how big the world was and how my individual
circumstances you know are are so secondary to the the bigger picture
that's going on is how it hit me fantastic that's also great that's also great I think that's going to touch into
some of what we discussed today so the piece that I read um
mentions that listening to silence is a it calls it a subtle sense
experience and I would say you know the senses there's a way in which our senses
open up when the mind is soft and takes a receptive posture and then we have
kind of a a refinement of the senses and that's often something that
we can experience in meditation it's one of the draws that people have to meditation is that feeling of the
enlivening the opening up of the uh perception in a sense so I want to
reflect a bit today about the way Dharma practice changes our
perceptions and I'm using that word um to mean both what we notice in the first
place um and also how we recognize what we're experiencing and
both of those affect then how we relate to experience so that's kind of the territory I'm trying to capture with
that with that word perception so all of this has to do um with the senses by
which we receive experience right just our ordinary human senses as well as the
Mind William Blake talked about uh cleansing the doors of perception that
was his poetic way of saying it and the doors are these different senses seeing hearing smelling tasting touching and
then also the Mind door we talk about that as a door in Dharma practice
also cleansing is an interesting word there you know it's kind of cleaning up our senses
they get sharper they get brighter um less
obscured more purified in a sense and this happens naturally through Dharma
practice particularly through the practices of mindfulness of awareness cultivating awareness and also somat the
Gathering of the mind or the unifying of the Mind steadying the
mind and I know very well that sometimes it does not feel so ref mind um we don't
feel very cleansed but um you know the mind can be busy or reactive or tired or
whatever but we can get some encouragement about that from the sutas there's uh the Buddha is quoted as
saying the mind is Luminous but it is obscured by visiting defilements and
that word defilements is referring to things like reactivity views strong views that come
in patterns of thought and um actions that we fall into so um so
these are visitors they're they're mentioned as visiting which is a nice way to think about it so as we practice
I think we do experience that sometimes we have these visitors in us and
sometimes the mind doesn't have so many you know the weather can be a little clearer inside so the doors of
perception can seem fresh and bright and practice gives us the clarity to
Notice start noticing the difference between those States we notice um the
obscuring patterns that come in sometimes we actually see them rather than just being lost in them and it
doesn't mean they end they seem to go on for quite a while but we have a greater and greater ability to see when they're
there and also appreciate when they're not there so that becomes a useful distinction that we make in practice
so as we look maybe carefully at these patterns that come in um we're able to
see that there are not only things that you know this obscuration is the word used there're not only things that
darken you know like literally kind of blocking but they also have a can have a
distorting effect so there's like a a way we're looking through a darkened lens in a sense so the shape has changed
in addition to to their not being as much Clarity um so just as a concrete example
we might have a distorted idea that uh our neighbor is unfriendly because we've
never seen them smiling so we create this Distortion oh they must be an unfriendly dower kind of person um but
of course if we then kind of treat them that way um they're going to be less
motivated to smile at us right so we've kind of um there's an unhealthy feedback
loop that can be created by the distortions we have in our mind where we
distort something uh by not seeing it clearly and then that very Distortion
prevents us from seeing what might correct that Distortion right so it becomes self-reinforcing I think this is
well known in Psychology but it's also described in Buddhist practice so the
Distortion is kind of a reaction in and of itself and it creates more reaction activity and all of that is a lot of
suffering for us so um so we can have these distorted
perceptions but then through practice we can have this clarification this cleansing of the doors of perception if
you will and so then there's a feeling as we do this process we can start to
feel oh yeah what practice is doing is kind of aligning or orienting or
straightening out you know the distortion is getting corrected through practice I'm curious if that language
resonates for anyone do you have a sense through practice that things may be feel less distorted
sometimes yeah I see some nods yeah and then there's less struggle you know when
we're seeing more clearly even if what we're seeing clearly isn't that Pleasant
um there's somehow a feeling like we can deal with it when we know we're seeing it
clearly so I didn't just make up this image by the
way about Distortion the Buddha talked in the texts about distortions of
perception they're called vipasa in P distortions of perception so ways that
the Mind warps experience into something that does not reflect
reality and they start out as simply you know mistaking what we're seeing but
then this feedback loop that I talked about kind of continues through repetition and these distortions can
actually Harden into fixed views that can create pretty big limitations on our
life so these are kind of big deal to notice these things but then the Buddha
also talked about what are called Universal qualities sometimes they're called characteristics but let's say
Universal qualities of experience that can be seen when the mind is not
obscured um it's interesting that the three Universal qualities though were
originally called the three perceptions so it's the same term as far as I know
that I hear that from a reliable scholarly source so they originally called the three perceptions so the
these are the three aspects of experience that we would naturally recognize or regard when the mind is
clear and wise and open but we miss them if we're looking through the distorted lens okay so the three perceptions that
are part of Dharma wisdom and then these distortions of perception and interestingly those two lists match up
quite nicely um so I want to um draw that parallel today and then talk a
little bit about how we would um move past some of these distortions like how
do we how would we undistort our mind so just to name them up front the
first characteristic or wise perception is the experience erence of things being
impermanent or Inc constant that's that's wisdom to see that and then the
first Distortion of perception is that we regard what is impermanent as
permanent Buddha names that as the first vilasa so you see the connection there
the second of the these three Universal qualities is that experience is
unsatisfactory it can't be ultimately conditioned experience can't be ultimately satisfying and the second
Distortion of perception is that we regard what is unsatisfying as
satisfying and then the third characteristic uh is that experience is not self and that one's a you know Hard
One to talk about we won't we w't to completely get through that one today but and then the third Distortion that's
named is that we regard what is not self as self so you see maybe the connection
there and it turns out that the correcting of these distortions can come about in a number of different ways one
of them is pretty straightforward it's to pay more attention to deliberately pay attention to experience in terms of
these three wise perceptions if you will we can actually practice that way even
though they will come about naturally through practice so we don't need to try too hard at it but if we're really
feeling distorted we can bring in a conscious um reflection of one of these
three wise ones and then um second way
is by deliberately expanding how we see the world and our place in it so a
little bit like that uh listening to the shape of Silence we can deliberately engage broader perspectives so that we
don't get stuck in a distorted a smaller distorted one does that make sense kind
of like deliberately open up the lens a little bit like was named at the end of
of the piece where I said that we see that the world is much bigger than our particular little issues that's a
deliberate perspective we can bring in that can be very liberating right so
we're going to talk about um both of these and maybe sometimes they're kind of creative like listening to the shape
of Silence I understand that's kind of you know can we really take that
literally and yet if you just try to engage with that something happens you
know several a couple of you named that there is something that happens to engage with an instruction like that
that so sometimes we can be creative to get our mind out of these
distortions okay so what I'm saying overall is that how we see things is something that we can
have some impact on through our spiritual practice I don't think we have complete control over that um we don't
we don't have complete control but we can affect it we can influence it through practice and that's really good
that's what really wise actually to do that so we'll have some examples as we go through these so I want to just talk
a little bit about each of these three wise perspectives or wise perceptions if
you will and the um corresponding Distortion that goes with them and then we'll go on from there so we start with
impermanence oh and all of these by the way each of these three has several different facets and several different
levels that we'll understand them at there can be kind of a an immediate level and then it gets you know that
gets deeper and deeper as we keep practicing so I can say that they can be unfolded for a whole lifetime of
practice um so what I'm just going to do is try to aim to hit maybe a couple
different aspects of each one but it won't be a like a complete unfolding because they're so
big so the first one I mentioned was the first of the universal qualities is that
things are impermanent they change in poly we call it
anicha um or maybe inconstancy is a better word and the Distortion is that
we we see what is actually impermanent as permanent right so this includes
change uh in constancy fluctuation the Buddha talked in terms
also of arising and passing he says notice things arising notice them passing that's all part of pointing to
this it's probably hard to overemphasize how important seeing changes in
Buddhism um but in some ways what's so special about that I don't think anybody
is surprised to hear that things are changing could be like okay come on
let's get on to something a little deeper but it's um it's worth noticing there's a a verse
in the dapada that says better than 100 years lived without seeing the arising
and passing of things is one day lived seeing their arising and passing so the
Buddha is pretty strong in terms of how important it is or how meaningful
valuable it is to see this and if we start reflecting on it we realize that despite it being so obvious there are
ways in which we don't see it there are ways in which we are entertaining the Distortion that things are permanent
when they're actually impermanent as a lightweight example of one time I uh I marked an item of
clothing that I wanted to distinguish with a permanent pen um and you know I
put little Mark on it and then after uh many months of using it and washing it and using it and washing it the Mark was
almost gone and I actually had a moment where I said how can that be I used a permanent
pen okay come on Kim everything is impermanent we know that so even though
the pen says permanent on it it's not really permanent just so you know so you
know there's that but you know more generally we do get shocked right when
things end or break or um go away or change you know um we can be irritated
that it suddenly starts raining after it was sunny you know um or sometimes it's a
delightful surprise right that something changes we think oh this is going to be here forever and then
suddenly like it goes away you know we get an email the next day saying oh you know I changed my mind about such and
such you oh wow so things can change in many different directions right but often we
feel that something has gone wrong when our car changes or our house or our relationship changes in some
way um the Buddha pointed right at this when he talked about being aware of death right we see other people dying
but we don't think it's really going to happen to us we have a memorial this afternoon
right maybe we could use that as a moment to reflect that there will be a time when we're not sitting in this room
either so another verse from the dapada death sweeps away the person obsessed
with Gathering flowers as a great flood sweeps away a sleeping
Village I used to volunteer at a hospice and that was really interesting I would
sit with people who were dying it was a very beautiful practice but I I did occasionally meet someone who was well
into their '90s who was a little bit outraged that they were dying they couldn't quite believe it really it's
almost over um there's something nice about that you know to
carry energy Life Energy all the way to the last moment and yet it was
interesting that um there was a little sometimes clinging to permanence
there so when we see this Distortion that things can last forever there is suffering for us I get
it you know it's understandable I think that in a human life we want stability
so I'm not you know I'm not like dismissing this is a serious um understanding to to kind of take on this
idea of things really being impermanent yeah at the top level of course things change but really everything everything
being impermanent that's actually not you know that's pretty deep we want stability we want steadiness we
want things to be ongoing we work to set things up so that they will last and
that's wise and skillful to do in our life it would be really hard if we
didn't try to do things like that but it's not realistic to expect of ordinary
things that they will comply with that forever right so
you know when we see with the distortion that things can last forever we suffer because it doesn't align with reality so
there's a you know there's some some subtlety there so then that maybe paves the way
for us to look at the second characteristic which has even more subtlety to it and that is that
experiences are not reliable or not satisfactory ultimately um they're not more
specifically they're not reliably pleasing or harmonious for us are
they so this is the the quality of unsatisfactoriness or stress or struggle
it's all captured in a word called Dua which is often translated as suffering
not the best translation you know when it's put forth as a quality of experience we can
understand it immediately thinking about you know this quality of impermanence if everything is changing and not then of
course it's going to be unreliable in the long run that's just the that's just another way of saying this same thing
right so the verse I read from the DAP talked about being obsessed with
Gathering flowers that's the suffering that can come from just chasing after uh
momentary or impermanent Pleasures that we can have we can spend a life um
obsessed with trying to always have it Pleasant every moment
and that's a lot of work it's um yeah it's not a good strategy
for happiness in the S we can do okay you know I get in the same way that we can set things up to last for a while we
can also do okay having Pleasant this Pleasant that and you know to some degree okay we want to take care of
ourselves nourish ourselves but it's also unrealistic to expect that that will always
work Andrew olinsky says conventional strategies for human happiness entail
very ways of maximizing pleasure and minimizing pain that's the conventional
part the problem is that pleasure is not ultimately sustainable and pain is not
avoidable does anyone really disagree with those two yeah the shortcoming of
our usual approaches is that they treat the symptoms rather than addressing the underlying causes of the
predicament which is that unsatisfactoriness is part of the fabric of experience so just to be clear life is
unsatisfactory when it's lived in this ordinary mode of trying to spending all
our energy maximizing pleasure and minimizing pain so we feel if we do that
you may have noticed we feel a constant sense of lack and a constant sense of being unfulfilled or needing something
or having the stress that this pleasure is going to end or that it ends sooner than we thought it would and then we
have to get another one so there's a a sort of a constant doing that has to
happen when we're engaging with that conventional way so um part of the issue
is that we're seeking ongoing happiness uh and I would say that maybe another aspect is that we're seeking
what I what I like to call resolution uh which means the sense of things being wrapped up integrated the
musical cord resolved the loose ends are gone the hanging questions are answered
it's all tied up neatly and we got it and we're done anybody feel driven by
that sense and and then you get to the end of the day and there's still five things left that you didn't get to today but I'm going to get to them tomorrow
and then I'm going to feel fulfilled and complete so this sense of resolution is part of this Dua characteristic it's not
it's not exactly suffering right it's it's more subtle than that it's not satisfying and it can't be because the
world can't do that that's another Distortion that we have is that we think we should be able to get it all together
and keep it that way but that's not in line with reality
there's going to be loose ends you're going to be lying on your deathbed and there's going to be loose
ends yeah so the world is constantly disappointing and frustrating if we
don't understand the quality of Dua so that's a little more subtle but
then it paves the way for the third characteristic the most subtle perhaps of not self um experience is not defining or
referring to an objectively existing self it is anata anata not self and the
Distortion is that we see what is not self as self and and that also causes
problems for us so there's so many different aspects of this U you know
taking things as me in mind getting identified with them um certainly yeah
it's very it's easy to see that in a number of cases like with our body or with our views we take those to Define
us um but in the end there's also a a quality maybe that I'll focus on today
kind of an issue of control feeling of control um who's in charge here really and can I
you know am I the one who can get it all together and keep it that way who's the
eye who's trying to do that um so so the anat luta the quality on the
characteristic of not self that's what it means is says it is not possible it's going to
say the word form which let's just refer to let's just imagine the body when I say it it is not possible to have it of
form let my form be thus let my form not be thus so it says specifically the
characteristic of not self is about the fact that we we're not in control are you in control of your body
completely no no so um and we can we can
I mean really we can see this in a number of very obvious ways could you make yourself three Ines
taller without putting on high heels no could you make yourself 10
years younger wouldn't you like that no no you can't do that yes you would but
no we can't do that so it's easy enough to see that we don't have total control
of the body and it's continuing to age and so forth and that doesn't mean just like the other characteristics it
doesn't mean there isn't something there that we work on yeah we do of course try to you know have some Integrity in what
we do and we try to take care of our body even though it's not really ours and it's going off the deep end anyway
but we do our best and um you know and there's not that there's no influence
you know meditation and Dharma training are definitely ways that we influence all of these things but if we if we try
to confine that to one thing that we me as an agent can do um it's really not
you know it's it's going to be a lot of duka it's a mistaking a distortion of how things actually are so we can see
that um these habits that we call Self or this body that we call Self really is
subject to these other characteristics it's impermanent it's not satisfactory and it's not really something that we're
in control of this gets pretty deep and it's understandable again I'm not I'm
going to extend the of course you know just like of course we want things to be
stable of course we want things to be happy and satisfying of course we want
to know who we are know who other people are and know how we can navigate all of
that it would be so nice if there was actually rule book that I could follow where all my relationships would go
smoothly um so don't feel bad that you have these
distortions I think they're quite reasonable and yet they're not in
alignment quite with how the world is and that's the issue for us that's the predicament we find ourselves in so we
want stability rather than anicha we want resolution and ease rather than Dua
and we want control and an identifiable self rather than
anata um and yet that is a lot of where our
struggle comes from in life isn't it around those three areas so one practice
we can do Buddhism tells us that if we shift
toward more often acknowledging these three Universal
qualities we will shift our eles into a relationship with experience that is
more harmonious that is less struggle it's not going to take away all those
things that we're trying to have it will provide more reliable forms of them we
will find something that is more reliable inside more stable more happy
more I almost say the more control part but um we'll find something inside that
uh is more reliable than trying to make external reality or even our internal thoughts and moods match up with these
things that it doesn't match up with so we can train ourselves to see more accurately and we will find if we do it
if you have enough Faith to give it a try you'll find that it helps I think I
I see a bunch of people here who have practiced for a long time with IMC and think we know that over time it's a
little Mis maybe mysterious is too vague but it's a little surprising amazing
that actually if we engage with the idea that things are totally impermanent that
they're not really ultimately satisfying and that there isn't really a self that they refer to things get more useful
over time why because it's more in line with reality so
then I said earlier that we would also talk about a second way to help the Mind
become less distorted and that is to encourage loosening up of these visiting
obscure obscurations that we have by playing a little bit in the realm of
perception playing a little bit with our perspectives and we can do that it's not
just like any wild fantasy we can imagine is necessarily liberating but if we bring in if we understand these three
characteristics um three Universal qualities we can bring in imaginations
or different perspectives that are somewhat liberating so I um there are actually very simple
possibilities for this maybe I'll name those first so let's say that you're going to a um holiday party or a family
gathering sometime in the next few weeks and you find yourself often subject to
limiting let's say limiting experiences when you're in these situations um it
can be that uh we could just bring in an alternate perspective that might might
be somewhat freeing for example we could instead of saying oh here are these people and they this and that and I get
caught in these patterns how about the idea that everyone is doing the best that they can
you know what if you just like brought that into the Mind before you went in and maybe reminded yourself periodically
as you went through the experience that's a helpful perspective it's a freeing perspective how about the
perspective how can I help how could I help here instead of oh you know I have
to endure this how could I help here here's one that I
use what would I have to let go of to make this easier do you find yourself caught in
something that's unpleasant or difficult what would I have to let go of to make this easier it brings it into right
here so then I'm also going to offer something um kind of a meditative engagement with
a couple of perspectives a little bit like that uh listening to The Sound of Silence at the beginning I want to
invite you into some very large very different perspectives around the realm
of time um so we're not really thinking about them maybe just as I kind of go
through this you might rest in the feeling of what it's like to change our perspective of the flow of
time one thing that burdens us about time is that we often live in what I call personal personal time and
historical time those are two different very common very conventional
perspectives one is the flow of our everyday I have to do this and that between now and when I go to bed tonight
or it's on my calendar for tomorrow personal time then there's historical time the flows of months and
years and decades how things have gone during my lifetime um basically where our society is and
where it's going these are very burdensome uh dimensions of time because
they're I don't need to say why we all know um but then we can take a much
longer perspective sometimes that's really helpful or a much shorter perspective so
we'll do both so in the realm of the long I want to invite you
to a perspective called The Cosmic calendar it might be that the universe is
beginningless like the Buddhist texts say I don't know but at least there is a limit to how far back we can see so
let's say we go back that far so let's imagine taking all of known time and
compressing it into one year okay so the beginning of the universe was at
midnight on January 1st and it goes all the way up and this present moment that
we're all sharing right now is midnight on December 31st what what does that year look
like so I'll give you some little highlights of the year the Earth formed in the first week
of September life began later in
September but there wasn't multicellular life until December
5th the first dinosaurs appeared on December
25th and that big meteor Extinction that killed them happened early on December
30th humans appeared in Africa on December
31st at about 10:30 p.m. the Buddha lived 6 seconds before
midnight and the last 400 years of human history occupi less than the last second
of the year don't think about that just feel
into the vastness of cosmic time now what was that that you were worried
about yeah so just let the Mind open to this sweep of the evolving universe
that's so much bigger than our life and it's breathtaking and it's not at all
meant to say that our life doesn't matter but it's meant to take maybe some of the gripping the stickiness out of it
right and then the other way is really interesting also so instead of you know
instead of the the vast we can we can plumet in to this very moment and we can
um bring ourselves to the richness of everything that's happening right now
and I can't even name there's how many sense impr Impressions actually come in
to the sense doors every moment there's so many of them that the the brain has
to filter them by a huge Factor like millions or billions in order that we
can have the experience we're having now so much has to be cut out it's kind of there like if you just look around
you'll realize that you are vaguely aware of the shape of this room um shape
of whatever room you're in for those online um it's coming in and if it were
to change you would notice but it's not uh actively coming into your experience
in this moment um there are layered and Vivid impressions of Light Of Sound
motion washing over our senses all the time usually people can only get to
opening up to that on a retreat experience where a lot of things have been removed so that we have a more
opening of the doors of perception right but nonetheless if we can open to
that and have an ongoing flow of the immediacy of all of these sense
Impressions again there's no room for a self to form there so these perspectives
I've offered are um validations or ways of touching in with this third
characteristic of not self and we can see in all of these anich
Dua you not ultimate resolution right and anata not self no room for a self
there so all of these different ways I've talked about of experiencing just of
time you know the the cosmic the historical the personal the immediate
they're all just different perspectives actually one is not better than the other one is not the
ultimate but it's really nice if the mind can flexible about being able to touch into
each of those as needed [Music]
so play around a bit and see if that doesn't loosen up some of these distorted
perceptions we can have um there's a some verses called
mindfulness by aan cha one of the Great teachers of the Thai Forest tradition of
last century he said try to be mindful and let things take their natural course
then your mind will become still in any surroundings like a clear Forest
pool all kinds of wonderful rare animals will come to drink at the pool and you
will clearly see the nature of all things you will see many strange and
wonderful things come and go but you will be still this is the happiness of the
Buddha so this ability to shift perspectives when needed and
to reduce the Distortion that we have in our
ordinary conventional way of seeing things is part of what we do through
practice we don't have to do it it'll be done it's part of what is done through practice use a passive voice there so
indeed our doors of perception can become more cleansed can become more in
line with you what's actually happening I need a certain distortion on these
because my eyes are a little distorted but I sometimes take them off figuratively to have a sense of you know
not looking without the without the lenses so here we are at the time of the
solstice a time part of
that larger sense of time of the earth tilting on its axis moving around the
Sun that causes these changes
so maybe taking a pause to go Inward and
sense where the mind is listen to The Silence
consider how you're relating to your life could there be a
shift that includes some of the wisdom we've talked
about because I know it's there in all of us it's just a little change in how
we see
so I wonder if there are any questions or comments we're right
near the end but um yeah let's could somebody bring him the
microphone yeah thank you and if anyone needs to go I know we're right at time
but I'll I'll be able to stay a little bit longer
yeah yeah if it's if the light is on it's on thank you yeah so yeah the
question is you were just reading uh aan cha and he was saying um
at the end he said something like and there you will be or you so it brings up
wait a minute we were just talking about no self so could you uh help reconcile
some of that seeming Paradox uhhuh yeah so he does he says you will see many
strange and wonderful things come and go but you will be still so who does that
refer to so again I think um this is a flexibility of perspective so uh the
question is uh can we use the word you or I or me and yet know that it doesn't refer to
exactly one definable entity the Buddha used the word I all
the time because he was talking with people and I think that's the same for
Rajan sha and so we can a little bit like what does it mean to listen to the
shape of Silence first of all how do we listen to silence and what does it mean to have a shape you know that doesn't
that's not quite literal and yet if we offer our mind that idea H listen to the
shape of Silence maybe maybe nothing comes but at least for me sometimes something there's a response to that
somehow and so in the same way I think it's okay to say you and yet know that
you could be a lot of different things okay great
all right thanks everyone