my name is nikim murri I am in Mountain View California on seated oone land
welcoming you all to this edition of happy hour um and as we always do it's
our tradition to just warm up this space with our friendliness with hellos and
saying where we're zooming in from so take it away
s Fred in Oakland love it we got Fred we got D we
got FR from Oakland we got Don from DC and there was there somebody else true
no from San Diego it was Hugh from San Diego I thought I heard three voices welcome welcome you
all uh Wayne in temporarily in Richmond but hi Wayne oh you're in Richmond
you're not at IRC oh just for a few days for CHR ah sweet nice glad you're
joining that's very sweet New Hampshire Neil in New Hampshire nice hi Neil Mima
from yaka Valley Hi Mima hi Kelly from Oakland hi Kelly
welcome John from Belmont hi John up the road welcome and Noella says hello from
the happiest place on Earth my bed oh my God that's so cute love Noella welcome Noella from the
happiest I love it you have to tell me what kind of bed you have maybe there's something very special about your
mattress just kidding that's very sweet Amelia says hi from Canada hi Amelia welcome we're
International Diana in New York hi Diana our East Coast contingent
hi and Kevin who says hi from Santa Clara hi Kevin
and Claire in New York oh more New Yorkers of course hi
Claire great very sweet ah very sweet and hi Sara from Snowy Toronto good to
see you again sweet that's very sweet snowy B from Snowy Toronto to uh baly
California hello Sophia and Jeff hi from Montclair the East Bay Hills nice
my old stomping grounds welcome good to see you lovely to see you and hi el from
Nevada City nice sweet well I feel like the space has been warmed up lots of
Hello lots of greetings from different places on um this planet so let's
transition to starting to practice together so thank you Neil for posting
information about happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happy hour we
have a low traffic but high in heart uh mailing list that you are welcome to join to get announcements and references
and quotes and things like that and at this time I change settings
to be um uh host only but please keep
that channel quiet because it can be distracting to get chats while I'm teaching and also oh yes to to
acknowledge um the happy hour breakout etiquette which is also in the chat I'll go over more but if you're new you can
click on it and take a look now other preliminaries uh yes turning on
recording for the sake of audio dma okay here we go
great excellent so hello hello again and welcome to high lovely to be with you
lovely to to feel your presence dear Saga
um so yeah there m different themes I have in mind for today and um let's
let's sit together and and I'll um invite some themes that are um related
to the timing of of the holidays especially in the Western Hemisphere or
they're mostly C well I guess anyway they're celebrating different different countries anyway the
holidays let's just put it that way I won't get too theoretical technical trying to figure out where in the world
is celebrated anyway the holiday so that's the theme that will come in with uh the the happy hour practice so so
with that let's just begin let's begin let's begin [Music]
and arrive in our
bodies arriving in the body settling in the
body feeling our feet on the earth our sit Bones on the cushion and if you need
to move and shift left and right really
find the center of the gravity your sit bones sitting
upright the sense of Integrity tall like a mountain sense of integrity and yet
relaxed letting the body be soft and relaxed and yet
upright inviting inviting the legs to soften to offer their weight to the
Earth feeling the touch points between feet and the the
Earth grounded stable well
rooted feeling our sit
bones touching the cushion the chair well
rooted feeling stable feeling stable and upright in our
bodies
stability that's also soft strong back strong back soft
belly sense of
gentleness openness in our heart our front being soft and
open and our back our backbone being stable
grounded supportive
and inviting breath to move through just as
it wants to move
through with each breath feeling more stability more
groundedness and if it helps this next invitation try it on for size
imagining that there is a vertical pole
vertical pole that you know your torso is this vertical pole it's stable and
well grounded rooted into the
Earth and not so much hard but it's a statement of
stability feeling yourself energetically your
energy body your feeling of your body energetically collect
it stable [Music]
grounded around the central Pole
it's helping you stay Ted and the idea here
is as a gift to ourselves as a gift to
others cultivating
stability at a time during holidays when it can be stressful perhaps
so much happening old here there this way that way taking time for stabilizing
T taking time for Refuge with each
breath it's a gift to ourselves and
others gentle kind stability that's the theme gentle kind
stability is a gift to ourselves and
others
e e
connecting gently lovingly with each embrace breath and out
breath cultivating gentle kind stability taking refuge in just being
here this present moment not past not future as a gift to ourselves and
others as a loving gift so if you were calling yourself
sweetheart I care for you so much and I'm going to take this time stay
ize the heart and mind the present moment with the breath as a gift to you
as a gift of myself see how we can shift the attitude
so that it doesn't become a grim duty to sit but as a gift of generosity of love
to yourself and others you interact with just stabilize be grounded present
fully with the breath as much as possible during this practice no
judgments
e e
and if you find the mind is traveling back and forth future and past again
reconnecting with kindness love to yourself sweetheart I care for you so
much for your heart mind that I'm cultivating
inviting you to connect with the breath in the present
moment so you can take refuge dear one calling yourself
dearly however feels appropriate
as if you were speaking to a beloved other addressing yourself
supporting yourself to train yourself thus to train your mind
thus
e
e e
happens if you speak to yourself encouragingly and
kindly as if you're speaking to a younger child and helping them
be trained in a skill they were
learning same encouragement kindness
warmth especially if it's unfamiliar give it a try see what happens even if it seems ridiculous try it see what
happens
then after you support yourself to connect with the breath the body this present moment then
stay stay relishing sense of Refuge Here and
Now
e
e e
notice where the mind is now it's
thinking remembering planning gently say sweetheart come come
settle settle connect with the breath the
body another few minutes of just settling and feeling that this
moment is enough nothing needs to be accomplished taking Refuge cultivating stability and
presence for the sake of yourself and
others
e e
and we enjoy just being here and being
breathed
e e
and as we turn to bring this sitting period to a close appreciating that we've showed up
we've done our best and whatever happened or did not
happen to accept it just as it was just as it had to be
given all the con causes and conditions of our mind and appreciating that we've
planted seeds planted seeds of wholesome
wholesomeness which will flower in their own time letting go of any
judgment and appreciating also the community that's supporting us and
practice practicing with us dedicating the goodness trusting
there is goodness co-created from our practice together and dedicating this
goodness to the well being of all beings everywhere may all beings be well may
all beings be happy may all beings be free including
myself thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so so as I mentioned earlier
um there various themes in my mind and what seemed most um applicable now was was this idea
of cultivating stability cultivating stability when um especially during the
holidays when there's so much happening there's so much seems to be happening um
and also you know there could be is a busy there could be stress there could
be just so much happening so the best gift we can give ourselves lovingly BL
through ourselves into others is to establish a sense of stability calm
groundedness um not to get reactive when
things go wrong which inevitably they do
because this is the human life so this gift of stability gift of groundedness
and and the twist tonight was was the invitation to do it really lovingly
really lovingly addressing ourselves kindly gently as if a beloved
other as if a child who's training being trained in something and just not quite
getting it right okay sweetheart it's all right yeah this is great keep keep
cultivating being in the present moment so that aspect of meta not so much in
the phrases may you be well may I be well may I be happy but in the way we relate it to the practice of
stability as oh just because I care for you dear one I care for you so much I'm
inviting you to be in the present moment and and I invited you during the practice to actually try that on even if
it's felt ridiculous or unfamiliar to address yourself kindly to see what
happened what might have lit up because as as I did that though I
dress my myself kindly but really in this practice I addressed myself just really reminding myself that yeah this
is for your benefit dear we're doing this for your benefit oh yeah something shifted something became available that
was quite lovely so so now we have some time to um connect with with community
in small groups uh if we want so one invitation if you want is to um actually
wait I'm going to bring up mea just so that I speak around these
themes of uh practice as put in chat earlier so it's a reminder that we're
practicing mea meta um in small groups uh as well as a
continuation of our practice um as um yeah treating treating
the small groups also as as practice they're not separate it's not like you just practice and now go and be in the
rooms and just chat no no no this is also a formal practice how we relate to
others how we relate to ourselves it's it's really part of this interactive way
of um practicing is is where the rubber meets the road even more perhaps I would
even go as far as saying that maybe our meditation practice is preparation for this higher bar practice of relational
how do we show up do we show up with kindness and care for ourselves kindness and care for
others so with the m mindfully listening and speaking being embodied allowing
some of the awareness to be in the body embracing compassion notice with kindness if there's internal reactions
or discomfort holding yourself and others with compassion and staying on the topic so
the topic for tonight is um practice that we did the invitations to
to Really address yourself kindly gently with as if you're mentoring yourself to
stay in the present and not becoming reactive or impatience okay sweetheart I
care for you and really reconnecting with the intention it's for my own good
how was that did did that connect did something light up um if not it's
perfectly fine you're sharing for the benefit of yourself to be held witness sometimes when we many times when we
speak out loud other insights come in that we hadn't realize when we're
silent um take turns briefly sharing concisely allowing space for others so
each person uh Will Go reverse alphabetical order according to first name each person will say just a tiny
bit or you can say pass um and then the next person the next person avoiding
cross talk not giving advice interrupting commenting just keeping this space
safe so and and um yeah really it's not so much what you say but how how you
show up how we show up for one another okay I'm going to create the
small groups and um yeah and also if you wanted you can
comment on how is the cultivation of stability for you in um right now in you know in
um um yeah cultivating
stability during the holiday especially do you feel the need for that maybe that
would be another theme to to go around another one more time to see the value in cultivating non-reactivity and
stability especially in these times all right so I'm creating the okay welcome back
everyone Hi the rooms are closed everybody's back and we have some time
for um Reflections how was that what
what did you learn about um yeah this way of practicing and also both you can
comment if you wish from the first part of your practice and when you're in silence and meditating and trying
something new on for size or in the community sharing and and um yeah
hearing yourself share and perhaps more insights coming up from the interaction
so you can um either share in chat I'm going to open chat
now here we go the chat is open you can also raise your Zoom hand um yeah if you
want to share reflections
what happened any any questions comments complaints it's all it's all
welcome yeah
um I have a uh uh sort of
a what did you call it um a light up a lit up experience at
the very end of the meditation I'm usually very very much in touch with my
left side and often focus on my left arm
it sort of lights up my whole left side at the very end of the meditation
all of a sudden my right side was lit up alive and it was amazing I I wasn't even
thinking of doing that it just it just happened which made me feel very uh
whole so thank you thank you for the nice nice thank you so much for sharing this this is so lovely and interesting
and and um uh part of uh what what I'm hearing
perhaps is you know and and and actually let me ask you something Kim did you find that your mind was getting more
settled through this this um practice before the other side became lit up yes
because it was at the it was at the very end and yeah I was getting more and more settled yeah yeah it's it's lovely it's
um so the when the mind gets settled more and more settled it seems like
these um uh you know energetic channels open up in our body right energetic
channels that we don't have so much conscious control over um and and you
know trying to activate your you know the other side that's not really lit up like whereas when we really really
settle there's a sense of contentment in the body the body's like oh here is a flower here's I'm going to B bance I'm
going to balance out the energies Without You Really Trying dear so it's it's a lovely
gift thanks for sharing that and and that tells me that your mind was really settling yeah that's really lovely
beautiful thank you Kim Diana I see your
hand um in my meditation I the I have a light bulb go
off oh wait light up it went boing like that and what it was for quite some time I've
heard you use the term sweetheart in connection with others and I've used
that somewhere along the line in life I learned to say sweetheart to maybe dear
friends or family member or cat in a natural way and the light bulb was that
I would never think of using that term with myself
ever and then it went oh and and so
that's much for me to reflect on and I can't what what an obstruction there
must be to to not even think of it or think of
myself with a term of endearment other than you whatever because you drop
something or whatever you can't do something like that never would have thought of that so it's much to
appreciate about this it was really quite jarring
to realize that so thank you thank you Diana beautiful I'm so happy for you
that it's being seen that is a huge Insight right for it to become available
because we usually go along our lives and we don't examine the way we're addressing perhaps ourselves to see that
oh oh dear this is um and now that you've seen it you cannot unsee it which
is and it's fine it's you know it being jarring is okay as long as you're gentle
with yourself sweetheart you this is jarring this is it still feels awkward
right now it's just awkward when I'm trying it but I'm going to keep trying it's not like natural yet so yeah it
will now that you've you know with with this practice um in this tradition
really awareness is is the lead it leads
everything else when you become aware um everything else will follow on its own
naturally it's not so much a push and shove and trying to make it happen so
now that you have become aware that this um feels like an unfamiliar pattern or
or or or or a unfamiliar way to address yourself with kindness and with
Endearment ah there's awareness there's Sati there's mindfulness and and trust that
rest the rest of it will unfold on its own you don't have to push and shove and
really try it so hard so um let it it will unfold for you I have no
doubt yeah beautiful thanks Diana thanks so much for sharing that beautiful Insight
yay Noella says my group is exactly the right group tonight how lucky we all are
to be here together thank you everyone a it's so sweet and oh makes my heart happy thank you Noella so lovely Amy
says the practice was beautiful and my breakout room was so supportive I feel so grateful to have this community and
these practices through the holidays yay yay me too a much love to you all so
beautiful yeah really a resource such a great resource to have each other s
Community hence one of the triple P jewels that make sense not just the
teachings not just the not just ourselves Reliance in ourselves the Buddha within Buddha without Buddha
within but the community beautiful Community yeah any other um Reflections
questions comments are we
close going once going twice
okay seems feels complete feels complete thank you so much everyone for coming
together um sharing your heart for the sake of yourself cultivating gentle kind
stability and for the sake of others and these beautiful insights arise when we
have stability and kindness for the sake of ourselves and others may all beings
be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone