so good morning or afternoon or evening let's go ahead and get started
together so let's begin with the meditation finding a posture that
is upright and also
relaxed allowing yourself to settle in
finding some balance the place where you're
sitting and just allowing yourself to be
supported by what you're sitting
on sometimes times we try to hold ourselves up in some
way but just softening and allowing yourself to be
supported aligning the posture so that your spine feels
straight and relaxed
closing the eyes gently that's comfortable for
you it's often in the eyes in the eye sockets
softening down through the neck and
shoulders releasing chest the
belly the arms the
legs having a sense of willingness and also trust in being
here in the present
moment bringing the mindfulness into the foreground the awareness of the present
moment perhaps even with a sense of curiosity
how is
this turning in particularly to the sensations of the
body sitting or perhaps you're lying down or even standing
ing this bily form that has supported us throughout
life we can notice that there's a mixture of Sensations in the
body letting go of Concepts like back or
knees or belly or head now moving into the sensations
themselves Sensations like heat or
coolness various kinds of flowing
feelings hardness tension
softness even some Sensations that may not be easy to put words
on as we're not maybe used to articulating them that's
fine just allowing your attention to move through the
body and notice if there are any areas of obvious holding
or habitual tipness that that might be
eased not as an engineering
project but simply out of gentle
interest in being in the present moment in a softt
way and if we find that there are some places that are not so easy to
soften or release then we let go of worrying about
that we also allow the mind to be with the body in soft and gentle
way
e and turning also to
include the mental and emotional and spiritual factors that are present
things in the mind noticing if there
are thoughts and feelings going
on that may be Rel relatively quiet or there may be a lot going on in the mind
it's all fine just
noticing how much activity what kind of moods and emotions
are
present sensing again into whether there seems to be any tension or tight
witness habitual pushing associated with how the mind is right
now and inviting some easing or releasing or
softening also in the
mind and it's done without a sense of judgment that anything there is
wrong shouldn't be happening but again just out of a gentle sense of being
present in soft easy mindful way so we
align with being here and seeing
this
orienting the mind around Letting
Go letting go of tensions in the body letting go
of tensions in the mind in favor of a simple
awareness even if what we're aware of is pain or painful
emotion there's a way to let go of entanglement with that and
just be with it so letting
be
e
it actually takes some active interest and
engagement to let things
be if we're too vadal about
that the mind can be hijacked or get
so so bringing our careful [Music]
attention a soft
way finding just that middle point where we can be with
[Music] things without either pushing on them
trying to do something or falling away from them because we're
not quite connected where is that perfect Middle [Music]
Point
e
and when we find that a distraction has captured the mind in some
way and we simply let go of
that and so let let go of any judgment that arises around
that if it does Catch and
Release Catch and Release each
time was fostering a simple relationship with
the flow of
experience
e
there is wedding be there is Letting
Go and there is letting
flow letting experience Flow In and Out become more and less
intense letting attention be sharp or
Broad it's neither active nor
passive this way of simple
presence
e
as we sit in [Music]
meditation with an intention of having this very simple relationship to
experience letting go of complexity and
entanglement when they occur we can sense that this is a
beautiful way that we could also be in the
world it's not passivity because there's this
engagement known what's present noticing when the mind is
starting to get hooked so that we can let go we can be in the world this way
too generally flowing along but staying
connected and checking if we're getting pulled in to wanting or aversion or
irritation or judgment or ego and having the intention if we can
to relax that complication allowing us to stay simply
present which makes us more responsive and also more empathic with
other people more able to help if we're not
complicated and so the Letting Go internally is also a
generosity externally it's a generous way way of
being with others one that's not focused on
ourself we included we're part of the [Music]
whole but we're not acting as a gravitational Center of
holding things toward us great generosity of presence without
entanglement is quite beautiful maybe we can't maintain it all
the time but it can be an intention that guides our way of being
in the world and when we practice as we have during this meditation session we
strengthen that ability in the world bringing benefit to many others
not just
oursel
so we continue with these four
foundations that are both simple and strong enough to lead all the way to
Liberation the Buddha offered these four foundations of practice to a monk who
was so devoted to the Buddha's teachings that he had ordained with one of the
Buddha's followers without even yet having met the Buddha and he had been
practicing very diligently on his own and they're valuable for us because
they're simple to begin and they lead very deep if we stick with
[Music] them so we've talked about not
neglecting wisdom and about preserving truth and
these can be done right now in a straightforward way and then they can also be done very deeply or thoroughly
keep going so today we'll talk about the third one it's it's usually translated
as cultivating relinquishment but the word that's
translated as relinquishment there is chaga which actually covers a broad
range of meaning it does mean relinquishment or letting go or giving
up um it also means generosity so chaga is the movement of
Mind behind Donna literal act of giving in order to give we have to
release our holding of something so that we can give it so chaga is generosity it
goes with the act of giving so it's interesting to me that
there's this one word that spans a whole range from offering to pay for a
friend's coffee generosity all the way to releasing deep patterns in the mind
such as our view of self those are both chaga it's
interesting so the possibility here I think is quite amazing and beautiful so
if we start with literal acts of generosity in the world and we pay
careful attention to what is actually happening that is if we don't neglect
wisdom and if we Pres Reserve truth then we're putting the mind on a path toward
full Liberation that Letting Go can keep happening more and more
deeply and the verb that goes with it is to cultivate this quality of chaga and
that same verb can also mean to Foster something or to make it
grow so how do we make it grow one way is to notice what the act
of Letting Go feels like before during and after we do it and also to notice
what gets in the way of letting go those are basic ways of practicing so there's a suta that says
that before a beneficial act of giving the mind is
glad and during such an act the mind is confident and after such an act the mind
is uplifted I love that um so you can
notice for yourself when you're making a simple clean totally voluntary
offering like handing your partner a cup of tea in the kitchen or helping a child
zip up their jacket something really simple um how does the Mind
feel are there good feelings present like gladness and confidence and being
uplifted this is something that we can notice in your life you could even notice it today as you go on after this
session and when we notice wholesome feelings like that we are automatically
fostering this quality of CHA of generosity the heart understands
intuitively that this is a good thing to do and when we feel that kind of wholesome happiness we automatically
strengthen it and we make it more likely that we can summon such a feeling even
when it's a little bit more difficult like when our irritating coworker asks
if we can do some extra printing for them since we're already using the printer right now and our first response
is I know that person is often troubling for
me I don't necessarily want to do their printing for them and then then we remember no actually you know I am using
the printer right now sure or to print what you need printed or
whatever substitute what what it's present in your life in that [Music]
realm and then notice also that this teaching says that during the act of
giving the Mind feels confident it's an interesting choice so this suggests that we give in a clear
and conscious way not kind of casually or with a distracted mind mind or kind of you know giving with our right hand
while looking in some other direction um I remember sitting in a
retreat long ago uh with a teacher who said that we might consider engaging
with the Dono with the thought may this act of giving support the full liberation of
the heart I remember thinking wow you know it really hadn't occurred to me when I
put Donna in the bowl when I give at the end of a retreat to have kind of a a
thought like that my first impression was it sounded a little bit grandiose you know may this active giving support
the full liberation of the heart but as I considered it I realize
that giving with that kind of clarity and a powerful intention really would
multiply the benefit of the gift um you know we might need to check
if there's any conceit in that um but I found actually that having that thought
actually made my mind really happy it made it even happier when I was giving and it didn't make it
egotistical so may this act of giving support the full liberation of the heart why
not so if you're doing this kind of deliberate cultivation of chaga you can
have confidence that you're making it easier in the long run to also do the
deeper kinds of letting go some of which we can't really do
deliberately I sometimes work with people who take on the intention to release certain habits of mind for
example complaining was once working with a group um that was their task was
to try to avoid complaining for three weeks and just putting this this
intention into their minds allow them to make some interesting discoveries uh
particular they saw how compulsive complaining can be right so even though
we're intending not to complain it's it has a certain momentum to it one person
caught their mind in the act of complaining um but she said in her words
I did not stop because it felt too good in the moment but afterward it did not
feel good at all can anyone relate to that you catch your mind in the act of
do doing something that you know isn't good for it but it feels so good we just
see it through yeah I'm going to finish that complaint
so it's humbling to see the momentum behind our habits our especially our unskillful ones and we can't necessarily
willfully release those but we can learn about them by noticing how they feel so
she did a really good practice there because she noticed that it felt felt good in the moment to be complaining has
this hook on it that feels good but then she also noticed that afterward it didn't feel good there was actually some
UNH wholesomeness there so when we see this truth of how painful our habits
actually are even in the moment even if we can't let go at that moment the heart
will want to let go so if we can also investigate for
example um what gets in the way of letting go then what we're doing is
we're learning about holding on which helps us learn about letting go so it's
interesting to notice in our mind that we hold on to things long after they have served their purpose you know do
you have any material things that you're holding on to and you don't really need anymore say
in your closet or your garage also attitudes philosophies
principles biases self-images habits of
behavior we start noticing you know what is it that we hold on to what what are
we carrying around we can admit that some of these things are a little
outdated and why is that you know why is that happening maybe out of habit maybe
out of laziness maybe reasons we don't even know it's not so important to know
precisely why we have these accumulations let's say but it's helpful
to Simply feel the tension and the stress of holding on to them and then
again the heart will try to find its way out so Letting Go can begin to happen
when we really open to the truth that's what we talked about last time this being willing to see what's true and the
heart will want to find its way out of any suffering that's unnecessary and we can Marvel at watching this process
happen there's a beautiful interplay between seeing what is true and letting
go so when we see pley that that grasping whether by greed or by aversion
is painful then the heart is motivated to learn how to let go of that grasping
and when we do let go the Mind Settles and clarifies such that it can see
deeper layers of Truth so there's this nice interplay between truth and letting
go letting go of anything that's not needed or is causing stress makes us
feel lighter and clearer and able to respond in different ways to situations
you can see this in your own life like suddenly you'll be able to say and do and think things that wouldn't have
occurred before as an example U one Dharma
practitioner I was talking with told a story about being on a team with someone
who was naturally talented and very easily excelled at the tasks that the
team was doing and she initially felt some Envy because she perceived herself
not to be as talented as this very natural talented person but being Dharma
practitioner she also noticed that Envy is a painful State painful for her
without the other person even knowing that she was feeling it and she didn't try to work directly
with the Envy except to feel the contraction that it brought to her heart
and she also tried to keep her mind on what she genuinely admired in this other
person so she she held both of those she wasn't suppressing her Envy but she also
wasn't letting it get the better of her and there came a day to her surprise
when the other person did an excellent job on something and she felt mudita
which is appreciative Joy the third of the Brahma garas the third of the heart qualities so she felt appreciative joy
for the success of this person and it was pure and clean she just felt medita where did that come from she had
not deliberately done done mudita practice which some people try to do
when they feel envious as they quickly try to counteract it she wasn't doing that but she
realized that the combination of opening to the truth of her envy and having the wisdom to just stay with that allowed
something to shift in her heart there was a letting go into a deeper relationship with this person not so
tinged with her own self-c concern about being less than in some
way so sometimes if we just stay with the practice slowly creating the
conditions that allow us to let go then we'll find that we do let go and move on
this is also part of cultivating relinquishment we don't always have to feel like we're directly working on
quote unquote letting go maybe we just create the conditions in our heart and eventually the Letting Go will
happen so a good exercise in realm of conscious letting go is to take a look
from time to time at what you what you own what you hold on to what you clean to and maybe explore what life would be
like without that for example refraining from complaining for 3 weeks these are
things that we can do consciously or deliberately and we'll find that many of the things that we think we need are
actually just habits that we don't need at all and then in the realm of the the deeper kind of letting go the we really
sort of can't do consciously then we try to tune into the tension that is always
there when we're engaged in greed or aversion or delusion and we try to admit to the truth that this grasping is
actually painful and then give your heart a chance to learn how to let go of
them and when you watch how this process works again and again you gain
confidence that the path is really about non- clinging there really is this fact
Foundation of relinquishment that the Buddha talked about to this practitioner no matter how contradictory
that sounds in the abstract there is a foundation of relinquishment that we
can have and and live from when you see that it makes
sense and then through that we also get to taste the piece of release when we do
let go there's a releasing feeling and that peace is the topic for
tomorrow so thank you and may you have a wonderful day of generosity and letting
go take care