morning everyone it's great to see you all and
be back with you uh be together again this way morning
everyone um so uh yesterday I read you a piece of
the teaching um of that the Buddha gave his
son rahula about meditating like the Earth this is another section of that
same suta rahula meditate like space for when you
meditate like space Pleasant and unpleasant contacts
will not occupy your mind and remain just a space is not established
anywhere in the same way meditate like
space for when you meditate like space Pleasant and unpleasant contacts will
not occupy your mind and
remain so one way of thinking about mindfulness but awareness is like a big
Open Sky and the objects that arise in the mind are like birds or clouds floating
by like rain falling or thunder appearing or
lightning sometimes the sky is illuminated by the
sun sometimes by the moon or stars all the objects of mind just come
and go in that space we can think of awareness like the
vast space in which every one of these objects of Mind occur
like our Body Sensations that come from the five external
senses what we see hear taste smell and
touch but we might feel from the internal senses pressure
warmth pain position balance all our thoughts and memories
feelings and emotions all our
reactions they all occur within this field of
awareness the key is to allow all objects to come and go to be seen
clearly when they arise but without holding on to them without trying to
keep them or fix them or without pushing them
away it's simp simple way of seeing it as aun Sumo
said the spacious mind has room for everything it's like the space in this
room which is never harmed by what comes in and out of the
room so let's
sit so taking a comfortable and alert
posture and gently closing your eyes
settling into your meditation posture allowing yourself to be centered
on your
body allowing the attention to meander throughout the
body relaxing any tensions that can be relaxed
relaxing the face the shoulders the
belly whatever tensions you might find whatever
Holdings see if they can be relaxed if not you can just soften
around
them just connecting intimately with that body relaxing the body
and from within the body you might be aware become aware of your
breathing in the Simplicity of this moment this inhale
Hal this exhale knowing you're breathing
in knowing you're breathing
out you might take a few long slow deep
breaths and with each inhale connecting more intimately with the moment
and with each exhale relaxing a little more deeply into the
moment Letting Go settling in
then allowing your breath to return to
normal staying close to the breath staying
simple e
nothing is needed just here in this
body breathing in and breathing
out like a tree with deep roots the branches reaching into the blue Open
Sky allowing The Winds of thoughts emotions Sensations to come and
go breathing in and breathing out
you can become aware of any sense of space of Stillness in the midst of the
movements of the breath any sense of ease well-being and
the Stillness like the clear Open Sky undisturbed by
any clouds that drift by
resting in a moment allowing whatever appears to
disappear just seeing it clearly not adding anything to
it no need to complicate it with IDE or stories about
it see if you can be a quanus to whatever
arises not being for or against
it if thoughts arise allow them to be in the background
they're not a problem no need to push them away no need to add to them or build on
them just simple thinking in the
background no matter how important it seems it's just a thought that comes and
goes if we don't feed it no matter how complex
or or deep or emotion star we can allow them to be
simple no need to figure it out but allow each emotion to be simple
to come and
go just knowing what's here what's obvious
no need to chase anything just resting in the moment of
awareness
e
e e
if the attention has drifted you can notice
it and gently escort it back to the breath welcome at
home just returning to the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out
e
e e
I'll ring the bell in a moment when I do might take a couple of
slow deep breaths again before opening your eyes
[Music]
so this morning I'll continue with the theme of knowing and not knowing
and reflecting particularly on clear knowing or clear
comprehension an infant can be fascinated by the flame of a gas stove
and climb up on a chair and burn their hand they can be very present with the
flame very aware of the pretty colors but they don't yet have the context that
it's not wise thing to do to stick your hand in a flame this Fuller context is what we call
clear knowing or clear comprehension clear comprehension
broadens the simple observation of mindfulness into understanding the Fuller context of the
moment if we're meditating and maybe we notice our head is feeling warm you know
hope warmer warm and much warmer it clear knowing that realizes or hears
some fire and we better put it out if um we act towards act out towards
someone in Anger yelling at them mindfulness might recognize yelling
yelling uh or anger but clear comprehension makes it obvious that it's
not in accord with their intentions of equinity and
compassion so additionally there are four aspects of clear comprehension that I'll mention you don't have to remember
all four but maybe some of them will particularly resonate with
you these four aspects of clear comprehension um can apply both to a
formal sitting or formal meditation but also to mindfulness in daily life in all aspects of our life
it's the same mind that gets caught in meditation or gets caught in the ins and
outs of her days so the first one is uh clear
comprehension of purpose it ask the question why are we doing what we're
doing and for instance in meditation you know we might be seduced into a fantasy
and it's a really juicy fantasy and we kind of become aware of it but we don't want to pull away we're enjoying it and
clear comprehension recognizes that it's not the purpose of training the mind in
meditation to sit here um massaging this
fantasy so in daily life maybe our long-term purpose is to be liberated to
be free um to open our hearts but our actions may not support a
purpose uh for instance these days many many people find themselves regularly
Doom scrolling uh unhelpfully in our devices and doom scrolling is when we
just go from one piece of news to another even though you may have um already spent half an hour doing
it uh or more um you know maybe our purpose is
opening the heart and kindness and compassion and yet we find ourselves caught in gossiping about people in a
disrespectful way so it can be helpful to take time
periodically to reflect on our long-term purpose to use the intelligence of the
mind to clearly reflect on our deepest aspirations why are we on the path
keeping it close to our lives I often find it helpful to connect
with this daily at the beginning of each formal meditation period
to remind myself to use it as a reference point in my life are my actions aligned with this
purpose really becomes um clear you know if for deepest desperations to be at
peace and we're trying to convince someone else of our point of view um and the contractions around that
convincing that all that energy of clinging it's not aligned with her
deepest aspirations it's not that we don't express our points of view but it's do a
hard contract when we do when we're agitated clinging to a
point of view there's no communication going on and recognizing when that happens
that this is duka this is suffering and that this process is not
alive with intention of being at peace and maybe can allow something
within us to relax then the second um clear
comprehension aspect is suitability or what do we need to do to
accomplish our purpose and even if it's a wise action is it appropriate at this
time you know for instance in in a situ ation daily life maybe you need to give
constructive criticism to someone um but maybe you don't do it
when they just told you their dog died I like to consider what's practical
what are we actually likely to do so in relation to
practice um I had a student that was really struggling hard to establish a
daily practice he had the idea that meditation happened in the morning sitting in his meditation spot but when
he started meditating he didn't have children now he had two very young children at home and time and time again
things came up from lack of sleep family needs um and he'd only manage occasional
meditation and so we explored what might work for him you know he said he saw that he had
to let go of the ideal of sitting in this beautiful meditation area each
morning he developed a strong steady practice eventually by meditating at
work in his office he was much more easily able to carve out the time there
and not be interrupted another of my students found that the best time was to sit in her car
drink her lunch break you know the other things we can
do that um in this area is we can set the bar too high um which can sabotage
us what's practical what stretches us just a little bit just a little past the
edge of our comfort zone where we can grow and some of us said the bar too low
with procrastination so what's practical here how do we move from
procrastination to doing a little bit of something a little bit of sitting a little bit
and um the third of the clear comprehensions and you know each one of these we could spend the entire time
talking about every one of them but I wanted to touch the different areas just a little bit just to stir something in
you um so the third one is the domain of practice you know where do we place our
energy where do we place our effort in our lives where do we place our
time in our daily lives we might ask ourselves where do we get our nourishment to carry out our higher
purposes in life if a larger purpose in life is freedom Compassion or peace um do we get
nurtured by watching the news um and we see clearly the difference between being
informed and the compulsive quality of going for from one thing to another on the
internet you most of us have heard the term monkey mind with the mind just goes
from one thing like one thing to another like monkeys jumping from one branch to
another maybe instead of the internet we should call it the monkey
net um you know maybe calling a good friend might be more
nourishing or going for walk talk or just sitting to
meditate and the fourth um uh form of
clear comprehension is non delusion this asks how the question how
how do we view or experience do we view it from the eyes
of attachment or do we view it from the eyes of Dharma
for instance um being upset because my computer died the day after the warranty
expired would this still be a big deal in my deathbed or maybe we could imagine if
the Buddha had a computer how would the Buddha view
it we don't have to take the behaviors of others personally that's a form of non-
delusion thinking that their point of view their behaviors are about
me and just about their conditions their
process in meditation it involves non delusion is
opening to the moment just the way it is even if we don't see it clearly
you know maybe what we see is confusion but just opening it and ah this is what's here confusion oh this is
what here an uncomfortable sensation opening it to just the way it
is not the way we want it as we bring mindfulness more deeply
into our daily lives maybe we notice clinging once we're well into the middle
of an argument or we find ourselves clinging to a point of view we can
recognize it and step back from it that moment of recognition is a moment of non
delusion and a moment of Freedom each time we clearly see or
clinging and see the suffering it's causing us we can incline to let it go
to see the release of it and we weaken These Chains to bind
us the clearly knowing allows us to understand or experience more
fully what's needed at the moment but it doesn't mean complicating or experience
anymore so hold these categories Loosely it just means seeing clearly if we've
complicated our experience which often tend to do with our thinking and ideas
what are we adding here that's not helpful and if we find ourselves in
moments of feeling disconnected in our lives or cut up in unhelpful ways in the events of Our Lives or events of the
world we can view any situation Through The Eyes of the Dharma Through The Eyes of
practice Through The Eyes of non clinging
so tomorrow I'll continue the topic with the focus on not
knowing today knowing clearly and not knowing and the two complement each
other beautifully so may the benefits of her practice
together spread out to all corners of the world may all beings be
happy may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be
free thank you