hello everyone and warm greetings on this Monday
morning and so
today the guided meditation will be around
tranquility and calm and the idea being that uh when we
let go when we relax when we stop our clinging releasing our
attachments one of the signs of that one of the consequences of that is some
degree of Tranquility some degree of calm or peace or ease
or uh lightness a lightening up and there's one thing to let
go it's another thing to appreciate appreciate the consequences of letting
go it's one thing to have compulsion addiction be caught up in something and
it's something else to become aware of beyond the edges of the
attachment there is some modum of Tranquility of Peace
Serenity ease calm I use all these different words
because different people resonate with different
words so in this meditation I'll guide you a bit to
appreciate the calm that's there or the peace or the
degree of Tranquility which is there when we're not attached not clinging to
something and sometimes that that calm is the calm of recognizing an
absence in the absence of agitation in the absence of
clinging there right there in that sense of absence there's a hint of Serenity of
Peace so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing your
eyes and gently maybe slowly as if you have all the time in the
world take a comfortably deeper breath than
usual and let go release exhale longer than
usual but only to the degree which it's comfortable to do
so comfortably slow inhale and slow exhale comfortably longer than
usual on the exhale re relax your body
especially around the
shoulders and let your breathing return to
normal
and with a normal breathing on the
exhale soften in the face around the eyes
cheeks
around the
forehead as you you exhale relaxing around the shoulders or softening around whatever
tension might there be
there on the exhale softening the
belly
and there can coexist tension
and relaxation different parts of the
body there can coexist agitation and
calm in different parts of the
body find in your body the places of calm places of
relatively more relaxed
easeful
and if there is tension in the thinking mind as you as you
exhale Relax The Thinking
mind maybe with a vision the image of a lake surface of the lake that when
the wind dies the waves disappear
and the surface becomes still and quiet and wide
broad so relax the thinking mind the waves of thinking slow
down
gently lightly
stay in touch with your breathing with a very light
touch whatever way you're breathing let it be that
way without any judgments of
it whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable let it be the way it
is almost as if awareness through the
body is lightly touching in touch
with the oscillation of breathing in and breathing
out
for
and and is there some place in your body and mind a degree of
calm
peace or maybe
ease there might be other places place there might be
agitation tension a
heaviness it's okay that's there but for now be on the edges of it
elsewhere find the places there is calm and peaceful
breathe with that calm gently letting the breath accompany
the
calm
for
and if you find yourself thinking a lot caught up in your thoughts or
concerns or caught up in some feeling of resistance or tension or holding to how
you're feeling let
go relax soften up a
bit and notice in the relaxing letting
go is there some Tranquility some
calm that you can appreciate
whatever degree of calm there is let that calm be a
companion to your breathing mindfulness of
breathing
releasing any hold there is on your
thinking sometimes called the fist in the mind open the hand of the Mind
release the clinging and
appreciate the Tranquility or calm lightness or
ease that might come with letting
go
for
e
agitation and peace can coexist within
us if we identify or are oriented towards the
agitation the clinging it can seem like it's the whole
world if we identify with the peace the
Tranquility if we're oriented towards
that they can make space for this agitation to settle
more can make room for release of our
attachment
e
for
any degree of Tranquility you might feel
calm as you exhale
make a small adjustment to your exhale that is some equivalent for
you as going
ah savoring enjoying the calm that's
here
for
e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting imagine being with whatever calm you have right
now whatever way you might be
settled in the midst of some of the challenges you expect
today however small however big imagining that you don't have
to respond or react right away
but you're allowed to just be there in the middle of it calmly in the way you are
now present
at
attentive
and for you to remain calm in these
situations what did you let go of what was not present that usually
present for you
and in this act of imagination for a few more breaths
appreciating the absence of that reactivity or
attachment you're allowed to be here breathing simple relaxed
and then from whatever calm place you have now extending your good will out into
the world considering the people you'll meet
today and others Beyond them may it be your
wish that they be well that they be happy and
safe and may it be that you contribute to that in how you are with
them may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank
you
e
so hello on this Monday morning and as we begin a new theme for
this week a theme which is a continuation of this series I've been giving
on uh introduction to mindfulness this is part two of that
series and today last week I talked about mindfulness of
clinging and uh the one of the Buddha's common teachings about clinging is the
way that clinging gathers together collects and accumulates over time so
that there is B there are bundles of clinging and um
the so the opposite of that is non- clinging and the absence of B the
absence of accumulated clinging and so what we want to start
noticing in mindfulness not just what's present but there is a time in mindfulness we want to notice so be
mindful of what is absence and any given moment uh there is um
you know infinite number of things which are absent to our awareness so you can be quite busy if you try to be take into
account all of it but in the teachings in this practice we want to notice some the Salient absences that are really
significant in the moment in relationship to clinging the absence of
clinging and um and we want to appreciate that absence to make room for more of it uh the recognition of the
value and the goodness and the healthiness of non- clinging supports
the heart the mind the body the whole system we have to start becoming more
oriented to the world of non- clinging uh growing up many people are
not taught to pay attention to the qualities characteristics of a non-
clinging heart non- clinging mind and what we're anything we we by somehow
rather we get the message to cling more want more be attached have more do more
and uh or because we're afraid we get the message that we have to kind of uh
you know uh clamp down hold back shrink resist and which is a form of clinging
as well but there's something phenomenal that could happen when we start
orienting ourselves to non- clinging and so that's a theme for this week and so
one of the ways that this works is We Begin recognizing the symptoms of non-
clinging the qualities the characteristics of what it's like when we're not clinging as
much rather than setting up a really hard line between clinging and not
clinging either or uh I think it's more realistic to start recognizing that there's a
range uh where maybe it's like a seesaw where there is um uh sometimes there's
more clinging sometimes less clinging but they can kind of coexist and so we might have some minor
clinging but mostly we're peaceful at ease there might be some major clinging
and we don't really recognize that part of us is calm and relaxed and um so these things can
coexist and we want to start recognizing that there is non- clinging here one
exercise that uh can be done is um recognize
something obvious that you're currently not clinging to and maybe it doesn't
have to be something that you have previously clung to it could be but it could be some ordinary object that's
around you it might be that you have no clinging to the light switch on the wall
it never occurred to you to cling to that or be attached to it and and um and you can feel how you can take in be
aware of the light switch on the wall um and you can be aware of it and there's no there's an absence of for or against
an absence of trying to hold on to it absence of associating with building up
a sense of self around the light switch and um now if it's a light switch
in your house maybe it's not completely you're not completely innocent about it but there might be something else you
can you can uh think about that has that quality that something ordinary around
that You' never would have occurred to think about clinging to it and somehow getting a sense of there there is an
absence there and um and absence of tension absence of resistance absence of
identification perhaps and so in that absence there
might be some calm some hints of calm or peace or
Tranquility the Buddha said that Tranquility is the food for
tranquility that if you notice are aware of the ways in which you're calm that
cultivates that just develops more calm and so whether it's Tranquility or
calm or peace or ease that is a word you like one of the things we want to notice
when we is the Tranquility of non- clinging and that's one way of
recognizing it and to appreciate it and to uh you know
I've been in situations where I let go of something but my mind was so oriented to
grasping that letting go of one thing just was meant that I my hands were
ready my my hand in my mind was ready to just grab the next thing the metaphor
that the Buddha gave for this for the clinging mind is a monkey
that's swinging from Branch to branch and uh as soon as it let go of one
branch it's even before it lets go of it it's already reaching for the next branch and so this continual grabbing
grabbing grabbing as it swings along and so in this in this way the
movement of grasping can be so great I remember uh once when my son was
quite small going to the Super Market with him he was small enough that kind of held him uh in my arms as we were
going around shopping for things and I he was very he was sometimes he start
wanting things in supermarket and um but I remember once
um he wanted something really desperately but he didn't know what it was because he just took his arm beh
behind him I was holding him to grab at what was behind him it didn't matter what it was he just wanted it this
movement of grasping and uh so
um uh so non- clinging notice the degree of non-clan
that is present for you when you have some degree of Tranquility some degree
of calm look for the calm of the day look for how you can be tranquil look how you
can be calm um and it certainly it's possible to
overemphasize calm and Tranquility it's possible to get attached to it and it's
kind of a paradox to uh that you know people get calm and then they hold on to
it they cling to it and then they get tense holding on to it and uh there can be a very strong
preference for calm that it would it qualifies as a kind of attachment there can be a lot of judgments about being
not calm which is a kind of attachment as well and the idea is to hold this very lightly it can hold your calm
lightly hold your tension lightly and begin appreciating the
degrees by which we're no longer grasping
clenching uh no longer compulsive no longer being driven by whatever it is
that uh is driving our emotions our thoughts our
our activation of our body and
appreciate calm appreciate so this is a very important
teaching uh for people who develop is practice and maturing it as they begin
to get a greater and greater feeling for or experience of letting go of non-
clinging is to start appreciating what that feels like the field of non-
clinging the the body the mind the heart that doesn't cling it's a very important
thing to feel and feel into that and to take in the goodness of it the wholesomeness of non- clinging and for
today that the uh suggestion is to notice the calm or the
Tranquility that comes with non- clinging
so may you on this day um make your calmness or Tranquility
or ease or peace uh lightness whatever quality
speaks to you the most let it be a theme that runs through your day and and uh appreciate when it's
there take time to appreciate that if to find whether it's there even without
having noticed it because you're so busy doing things make more room for
tranquility and notice if Tranquility is a food for
tranquility that Tranquility supports more Tranquility but more importantly does
tranquility support nonattachment non- clinging
non-grasping non compulsion so so I hope you enjoy a day
of Tranquility at least the exploration of it and
um and if you find no Tranquility at all um I hope you enjoy um how that
highlights what is happening for you and that you can be mindful of that thank
you