welcome welcome to our 7 a.m. meditation and dhad
again yeah just happy to see the chat messages coming in from all around all
around the world
so here we are um we are on the uh five aggregate
simile this week and today uh we are going to speak about the force simile
and we'll practice with it and I don't know how exactly we could practice with it just yet
but uh um because the simile may or may not be
um kind of connecting with many of us who don't
know the trees so much so we'll see how it works so the the forth s simile of the
five Aggregates um is uh uh is about this PO word Sara
Saras often translated as mental formations or mental
Fabrications um it's a kind of uh human mental process or the
force that um is capable of
constructing things you know constructing ideas constructing a sense
of solidity uh based on ideas and
um this construction the constructing force can
construct the other Aggregates that we've been other cleaning Aggregates
that we've been speaking about and so it's deep rooted force and
yet uh this force of construct ing um it forms something that looks
very solid and uh very concrete um very persistent strong
even um but when we look um carefully examine it carefully as what the suta
was pointing to we see all this constructing forces are rather
ephemeral and the Sut use the word void Hollow
insubstantial and so Buddha used thiso of plantin plant plantain trees or
banana trees you know this is in the tropical uh places and you see this kind
of trees and they look from outside the trunk is
solid but if you look internally the tree trunks are formed by
all of this big pieces of leaves wrapping around and around around and
they look like uh solid trunk but they are actually hollow
inside they they can't be used to really make anything uh that long lasting or
sustaining and that's the nature of this Sanara if we look
internally they just things wrapped around around and forming something that
looks solid but they're actually
not so we'll practice with this a bit um
and my invitation is to maybe pay careful attention
to um this force that maybe inside of us
that can make stuff up like you know you may have a certain experience
and then there is a force that wanted to make this a real thing that you got to
fix or some real thing that you're judging about particularly in
relationship to this force of making a sense of a self I need mine based on the
momentary experience that's happening so those are my introductory
words and uh We Begin uh meditating with
this this [Music]
words so take a few long deep
breath inviting yourself love to come home to this body mind and
heart maybe
entering entering into this home here and now
feeling and sensing the global sense of the
posture feeling and sensing the outer
environment the space temperature
and feeling and sensing the inner
environment maybe some
mood
thoughts activities in the mind
and movements in the
body becoming Mindful and a present
you may not necessarily be anchoring on any specific
thing but you're present for the momentary experiences
committed to being present
one moment at a
time it's not a forceful thing but
rather a heart values being present
a sense of a being
home may become
Fuller you can simply rest here
the movements and the flow of the
breath may become more
obvious now the energ energetic AI
body can be more felt sensed
a sway tingling
Sensations you can feel the dense within this body
raone he foamy body
light
Airy maybe bubbly like the water bubbles
and perceptions May float in and
out like the Mirage the shimmering mirage at a high no know in a hot season
softening and deepening in into the sea of
change in the body and in the
mind
e
e e
in resting in a quiet
Stillness you may notice the forces of Saras
that the stitches experience
together into a solid
story believe
a momentary waves of
emotions can become I
am that
emotion e
or something persists for a
while yes Sankara can
claim it's always like this
when this can be seen
clearly we have a choice to set it free
e
e e
there is nothing to
fix staying
in the being and staying in the clear
knowing it has an innate
capacity to set free
what's not
graspable
e
e e
when we're simply being with a clear
knowing that's available here and
now it's possible to release any
contention that's here
and it's possible to feel and sense a kind of a
wellbe that it can hold non wellbe
they don't have to be in conflict with
each
other for
there may be tenderness and a care that's available
that can be
felt
e e
[Music]
s like to read this part of the sutta that uh speak
about uh Saras as a a planting or banana
tree trunks so here it is suppose practitioner that a person
needing hardw seeking hardw wandering in search of a
Heartwood would take a sharp tool and enter a
forest there they would see the trunk of a large banana tree
straight freshh without a fruit but
core they would cut it down at the root cut off the crown and unroll the
coil as they unroll the coil they would not even find soft wood
let alone hardwood a person with a good site would
inspect it ponder it and carefully investigate it and it would appear to
them to be void Hollow and
insubstantial for what substance would there be in the trunk of a plantin
tree so to practitioners what kind of mental
formations there are whether past future or present internal or
external gross or subtle inferior or or
Superior far or near a practitioner inspects them pers them and carefully
investigates them as they investigate them they appear to them to be void
Hollow insubstantial and for what substance
would there be in mental
formations and so this image of um banana tree trunk as I was saying that
the the leaves Co you up and that kind of form the
trunk um but they Hollow once they
uncoiled and if the person is looking for something that's longlasting and
strong and steady stable like you know building something strong which is used
to um kind of point to symbolizes how we're searching for some
kind of lasting well-being a deeper kind of well-being
the Heartwood you won't find it uh in this coed mental formations you know
banana tree trunk because inside um it's a
hollow and so that is the nature of Saras like different uh mental
formations that gets stitched together they kind of call you together to form
an a sort of illusion that something
is solid but when you look carefully that's
not the case I want to use an example to maybe illustrate this I remember on a
Meditation Retreat and uh in the middle of um uh
The Retreat and I noticed and one sitting
there was some experience began to emerge that my mind began to name
it and you know this is X and then there is kind of the force
that wasn't enough as if then it's trying to name it yet another word oh no
it's something like this and then you know it's kind of multiple times in a row it's trying to
name what the this experience is initially was naming this in English
after a while I felt like oh no this doesn't quite capture exactly what it is and and I start throwing Chinese words
at it at some point I noticed wow this kind of like has a
force in this it really wants to nail it then I recognized this wow this is the
force of a sun it's trying to make it a thing you know
based on the experience that's uh floating through and flowing through and
I thought to myself wow there's no end to this you know I can make it this I
can make it that but that they experience just what
it is it may not need a word it may not need an image
it may not need any conceptual ideas to be associated with with it and it
doesn't need any justification like this and so when that was
seen oh some part of me began to soften oh I can just let it
be I don't need to have it must be something
and so that's the momentary Freedom that can become available when we begin to
recognize uh sort of the nature of this momentum the nature of this Force that's
happening and so this is maybe kind of a trivial example but often when this
Force began to uh take its own sort of
uh Ride Along its own momentum
it can begin to create this sense of a self by wrapping around this layers of
mental and physical activities that's happening uh perceptions ideas and
beliefs and at some point we will lose track by seeing the
momentary Ever Changing experiences uh we turn them into sort of
a banana trunk banana tree trunk it becomes about me rather than
the experiences that are changing uh in our
meditation I kind of uh offered some pointers where uh sometimes when we have
certain waves of emotions and the Saras can
function uh by turning the momentary experiences
into you know like maybe I'm experiencing some kind of a sadness or
maybe even extended kind of a sadness then it can be turned
into a I'm always like this that's a
construction that's not not the reality and we can overlay on top of
that even further by declaring this is how I am I'm always
like ever since I'm little and so you can
see this kind of a construct began to limit us and blocks
so many other possibilities that's here too and because of this we can't see Joy
or happiness that may be momentarily available here
too that's present too we can't see a kind of a well-being that may be
here and so that's the danger of um getting lost in the construct the
constructing force and so the Dharma practice offers
us to stay in the immediacy of our felt sense
experience then we can begin to see how the the forces stitch together and coil
this layers of a construct that's how it's being
constructed and in seeing it we have an opportunity to choose
something different we can see oh The Experience are just
experience the AAL Force leads to duka and we can have an opportunity
choose to let go let go of coiling and often this let go doesn't uh doesn't
need some kind of active doing instead uh this letting go kind of um
moving away from this constructing Force comes very naturally when we begin to
see the phenomenon just as is and so that gets released as a
natural unfolding of the Dharma and so
um you know for today uh the rest of the day as uh you go about the day maybe you
know pay attention to uh this forces that may be making stuff up constructing
realities in our heart and mind and just have a lot of humor around this you know
this part of ourselves try very hard to make this life work and um by practicing you can begin
to see there is a different possibility there is a different kind of a well-being that may be
available but not keep feeding into this
Con constructs and so have a wonderful rest
of the day and may your day be filled with this
exploration and the Dharma Joy so be well everyone