so hello everyone and welcome to this meditation on
Friday and um there's a little story from the ancient text with
the teachings of the Buddha where the Buddha talks about his own experience of
going to off to practice on Retreat before he was enlightened and there were
no retreat centers back then so he was going into the forest and um at the end of this teaching he
says um he still goes into the forest to practice even now that he's uh fully
awakened and some people might think that uh the Buddha does so because in fact he's not awakened fully and he's
going to keep he needs to keep practicing but it's not that way he is fully awakened but he goes into the
forest to practice going retre for two reasons for his own ease and well well
beinging and for uh uh to be an example
to be an encouragement or he says actually what he says is out of uh Compassion or care for future
generations and this idea that the Buddha would go and meditate because he wants future generations to
meditate meaning us we're in that and to to a great extent and we're
uh continuing something the Buddha started without the Buddha starting his
teaching starting his own practice becoming awakened and teaching uh there would be no Buddhism and this particular
Gathering and teachings that we have and people would not exist in the way we know it
now and uh and we have it survives down through the generations because from time to time
there are people like the Buddha who would love the who who out of their
love their care their friendship their companionship are
saying meditate it's good to meditate it's for your own benefit and
the benefit of the world to meditate go and Retreat go on a short
Retreat the short Retreat right now from your home on YouTube
and uh and this idea that there are people in the world who are their warmth their friendship their care their um
maybe not thinking about each of you individually they don't know you maybe
but they're there in the around you and extended with this wish for others
including you to yes we pre please
meditate it's good we were and so the the call the instructions the
suggestion the thing that strikes me is that it's being offered with friendship with the friendliness
with good will not assertion not demand not expectation but just out of a
genuine kindness and Care compassion
warmth a warmth perhaps in sharing our common humanity and the challenges of it
and and how to meet those challenges here
meditating so for today in this meditation uh I'd like to suggest if
this is available to you that uh you
meditate uh content or happy or inspired or touched by the fact that this man
teacher from 2500 years ago many people down Through the Ages there's a many
people in the modern world me right now who um uh out
of care out of love out of inspiration out of wanting to address the suffering
of this world are in a supportive way
saying hey we're with you please meditate let's meditate together you're not doing it
alone and uh and maybe be you in your own way your own example of meditating
are setting an example for the future and you'll come to the point where you recognize you're doing it for yourself
your own ease and well-being and also you're doing it to support future
Generations the Simplicity of your dedication and act action of meditating
independent of how well you think you're meditating you're meditating with circle
of support and you are part of the circle to support future Generations May that idea that image
support you uh to have a kind of inspired warmth
or good will for being with yourself being with your breath being
with your body being here and now in this meditation and with that uh we'll have
this meditation be the rest of it be silent thank
you
e
e e
so then as we come to the end of this
sitting to imagine if you will that from the point of view from
the perspective of sitting quietly and calmly that you can gaze upon the
world kindly
that you can gaze upon the world with Good Will and that for these few
minutes if you
can not be troubled by the world because you have something
phenomenally wonderful to offer something very much needed in this troubled world
to offer our your kindness your good will your
care to be able to accompany the world with good
will maybe so that it spreads into the world and into
future Generations the human capacity for meta for kindness for
care may all
beings know that others wish them to be happy may all
beings know that others wish them to be
safe may all beings know that are people people who wish them
peace may all beings know that there are people who wish them
freedom and may those people be us may we go into the world wishing happiness
and safety Peace and Freedom and may we contribute to that
possibility
thank you all and thank you for maybe your
patience or with the various uh technical difficulties we have with all
the electronics we have here but I think now we're set for the rest of the
morning e
so in this fifth talk I'm finishing the series on uh the poems of the Elder nuns
the uh poems of that are preserved that are
attributed to the first generations and they say it in plural because it's often
said to be the first generation of Disciples of the Buddha female
disciples um but rather I think it's they probably composed over a longer period of time maybe several hundred
years so those first generations and uh and um I want to
today Begin by reading a little bit more from the introductory words I've written about these poems that I've
translated and then I'll read uh some of the poems that uh for me uh touches the
warmth and friendliness and support with which uh the ancient nuns provided
themselves or experience that allowed them to do their practice
um so
um the enlightened women who are featured in the terata represent the first generations
of female Buddhists who contributed to establishing the spiritual foundation
for succeeding generations of Buddhists of all genders with few other surviving records
of the first Buddhist women the ter Gata provides an invaluable window into the
lives and religious experience of these Pioneers prior to becoming nuns many had
been wives and mothers some were widows some the mothers of had children and one
was a widow had lost both her children pachara a few of the nuns had been
prostitutes and cortis some had been poor others had been wealthy Daughters
of royalty and high ranking families some were old and weak others were young
in the prime of their lives two had already been contemplative
uh renunciant before encountering the Buddhist teachings
no matter what their background most of these women attained the ultimate goal of the
Buddhist path in fact the attainment of full spiritual Liberation is a predominant theme of the Terry
Gata the importance of this experience popularly known in English as Enlightenment is EV evidenced by the 40
different synonyms and descriptive words used to describe it the most frequently
used words uh having to do with the most frequently used used are words having to
do with freedom that is words that can be translated into English as being
freed well freed released liberated fully released
emancipated set free attaining Liberation and being untied
unfettered so it's remarkable this whole uh
these these
texts and then for many of the women in the terata being a nun included valued
connections with other nuns um they had more senior nuns as
their teachers to receive teachings venerable Utama and an unnamed none approach a
none they Trust venerable via when she had no control of
her mind respectfully questioned a fellow nun for
teachings um Venable Chanda refers to the kindness of veneral pachara allowing
her to go forth as a nun 30 nuns who seem to be a group practicing together
Express their lifelong honoring respect to venerable pachara for her liberating
teachings Vel sundari refers to her monastic teacher as the light of the sa states
that she has attained Awakening in dependence on her teacher having left domestic and family
life Behind These none had Community with each
other so this idea of this warmth and kindness and mutual respect of
practicing together is um is uh
uh one of the characteristics that I read when I read these texts and this stands out most prominently in the first
chapter uh the the uh book is organized in chapters with increasingly long uh
longer verses and the or poems and the first uh chapter is um is uh poems that
are of one verse and uh one of the characteristic of these poems is that um uh uh some of
these is that the N the the meaning of the name of the nun is there's a word
play in the verse itself in that poem that uh kind of plays with that or
revokes it and brings it forth again and uh but through these uh
literally in the poem The Woman is addressed directly in the second person
you know uh but the question is who's addressing the nun and um uh the most
common theory is she's speaking to herself in the second person and um and
in um another uh theory is that it's actually the Buddha speaking to her and
the third theory is that it's a fellow nun who's teaching her encouraging her
or some way but whatever it is to me there's a feeling of this warmth and
care and kindness that comes through it and U it starts from the first verse
with a woman a um a Elder nun who has attained peace
from all passion from all lust and um and then uh she's
told sleep at ease dear Elder wrapped in
the robe you made so just kind of you know just encourage me sleep well now you done
your work you become free so now sleep at
ease um very simple ordinary but expression of warmth and
kindness the second poem is uh addresses muta which uh her name means
freed muta be freed from bondage as the Moon from an
eclipse with a mindset setree enjoy your food debt free the idea of eating
enjoying your food debt free for a monastic is that they receive uh arms they only eat what's given to them by
the Ley and so they're a little bit in depth they have something to return to them and what they return to them is
their practice and they practice to the point of uh Enlightenment at which case
you um we um we can enjoy death free
and then there's punna which means full Puna be full of good
States like the moon on a full moon night full with Insight shatter the mass
of Darkness so practice please practice but there's for me there's this warmth
that's playing with her name your your name is freed be freed please
here is one whose name is ma ma means friend
M having gone forth out of Faith Delight in Friends by cultivating skillful
States attain peace from bondage from
attachment so this idea again here is explicit the light and friends the spiritual friendships that we have that
you can have and here This Woman's name is badra
and that means blessing badra having gone forth out of Faith
Delight in Blessings by cultivating skillful States
attain UNS surpass peace from
bondage here's another one whose name is a mutah freed and now she's speaking directly
for herself well freed very well freed I am
freed from three crooked things for Mortar pesle and crooked
husband I am freed from birth and death what leads to becoming has been pulled
out marriage and family life being a wife and mother was not necessarily a
good thing in the ancient world it was a lot of work and sometimes it was kind of like servitude uh very different from
our our understanding of marriage and maybe in the modern modern world and so
she's celebrating being freed from maybe a very difficult
husband um here's one her name this one doesn't
necessarily directly have a word player with her name but utara meaning
Supreme controlled in body speech and mind having pulled out craving at its
root I've become calm released
[Music]
quenched and This Woman's name is dma so the
Dharma weak leaning on a stick wandering for
arms limbs trembling so you know there was no again there was no medicine that we have today
Social Security retirement homes um you know that people who are monastics maybe
had a monastery to live in but they still had to go out and get food every day and so week leaning on a stick
wandering for arms limbs trembling I fell to the ground right
here in seeing the drawbacks of the body my mind was
liberated so here old age challenges weak not all strong enough to stand up
for herself something about falling she could let go maybe not depend on the
body maybe find an alternative even in her old age and something in her mind
got
liberated and this one is another one woman who
um maybe I'll skip it uh and uh but here
for the sake of time here's another woman who
um similar is actually it's almost the same there's two verses now we're in this chapter 2 and um and so uh it's a
little bit like the earlier one her name is chitt and chitt in this context means
shining bright or beautiful and it has in it the idea
she's a monastic turning over her bowl and now the it seems to refer to the idea
that a monastic can go out uh with their bowl for food but if they turn over
their bowl like this they can't re receive any offerings it's like refusing
something no more of that and uh in 2007 when uh in one of the times that the
monastics in Burma stood up against the government they walked through the streets where their bowls turned up so
that uh people the government officials the military couldn't make Merit by
making offerings to the monks it was their protest so she refers to this in her
poem perhaps as a kind of um as a metaphor a number of these
things might be metaphor in this poem she also talks about ascending the mountain and I don't know in the ancient
world but in some later Buddhism um that ascending the mountain is also kind of U
uh going up on the path of practice to the top um
though quite emancipated uh quite emaciated sick and weak I walking
leaning on a stick have ascended the mountain having laid down my upper robe
turning over my bowl and resting on a rock the mass of
Darkness shattered so here turning o over the bow I think
it it's a metaphor here for no longer uh
taking in the bait of the world The Temptations of the world no longer uh
maybe taking in receiving her own attachments her own clinging her own
delusions no more something inside of her turned over and some people
experience Enlightenment with a kind of feeling like something something flips in the mind something switches very
quickly and um going to turn over and then life is different from then on or
something maybe turns over the bowl and the mind turns over and all the
attachments drain out and
um and so there's one more here time to stop uh her name is Sama meaning
peaceful not that attaining mental peace so her name is peaceful but not attaining mental peace and with no
control of my mind four five times I left my Hut but then eight nights ago
craving was abolished by being devoted to vigilance
in regard to all suffering states by being mindful of all suffering States I
reached the destru ction of craving and accomplished the Buddha's
teachings accomplished the Buddha's teachings so these poems over and over again show that these women in the
ancient world could accomplish what the Buddha taught you can
also you can also practice and um and you have the warmth
of community even the ones you don't know you the the nuns of the ancient
world they practiced for you as well and they're there the ancient nun teachers
are still here their momentum their memory through these ancient texts their
what survives of them the through these verses that uh they're saying you can do
it practice and come and rest at ease find your peace find your
freedom so thank you very much and then one announcement is that
I'll be gone for the next two weeks I'm going back to Norway for a little bit
the uh my parents died in the last couple of years and bring some of their
ashes back home so it'll be a touching visit and uh I will be back in two weeks
and next week Nikki mapori will speak and the following week Ying Chen and now
two ful teachers and you'll be in good hands thank you