okay welcome welcome folks really uh
appreciate all the hell and names and yeah very
sweet lot of names I'm very uh familiar with I don't know who you are but I know
your YouTube name um okay let's uh let's let's
meditate um yeah please uh find find your posture
maybe uh as we We
Begin almost undetectable cra C just the
slightest smile
and just let those uh Sensations Ripple through your face maybe more
broadly
this is not an attempt to blot out uh the suffering given to any life given to
this world
but uh to know some measure
of Joy uh can
coexist difficulty
our mind has a lot of difficulty with
ambiguity the mixed upness of Life
the experience of a ambivalence Ambi
valent different balances
naturally we uh kind of treat each moment as a problem to solve
and we can miss uh simple Delight of
a quarter
smile e
relax whatever can be
relaxed Grant permission for any tension that remains to remain
and find a place for your attention to rest that uh feels
soothing or even Pleasant subtly or obviously
one facet of equinity is letting go of the friction
with difficult experience but there's another aspect which is simply
allows uh difficulty or unpleasantness to be in the background while
[Music] we highlight the subtly
Pleasant just stay there for a minute or
two
e
e e
then uh just let
that Pleasant feeling mingle with your
breathing just like the breath catches
the the gust of
pleasantness just breathe in a way that makes you really want to be
alive breathe in away where we
know each breath is
Donna generosity offered to us to
enjoy
e
e e
maybe uh feels right just to stay practicing in this
way catching the the thread of pleasure and
breathing the oxygen hunger that's
satiated expelling what's been used up the relief
in that lot of pleasure in that
cycle maybe practice in such a way that
the anchor is not with our breathing but the anchor
is everywhere
that there is truly nothing outside the focus space the circle we draw around
the phenomena included contains everything
in a sense our suffering requires mindfulness to collapse
requires identification with some
uh afflictive phenomena
that which we're awake to never fully defines us is never the last
word so we stay wide awake to all the arising and passing
phenomena not trying to Cobble together a kind of vantage point a
lookout we just open
and Trust in
awareness
e
e e
even to make sense of my voice my meditation instructions
subtle kind of
identification maybe that's just fine maybe that's part of guided
meditations but the hunger to make
meaning is sometimes the charade of
Mara so maybe my voice and everything
else just become sound
you let go of my instructions in
order to practice
them
e
e e
okay what good to sit with
you so we'll we'll continue with uh this this theme of uh the Dharma Dharma of
other people um
so relationships um maybe we can say are kind of dance of
of assertion and surrender of holding power and sharing
power of accepting influence being affected being
porous enough to be affected how much how much surrender
does love demand uh not
everything but not nothing and how comfortable am
I uh surrendering My Views acquiescing to the other how comfortable am I how
native to my heart does it feel to accept influence and
alternatively how com am I expressing my needs
asserting uh something about my own heart some people kind of
feel okay only when they're holding on to power and others feel okay when
they're relinquishing power and it's a little bit like maybe
melting and freezing some only comfortable as water others
only comfortable as ice and we really need need flexibility
we need the ability to melt into the other but also to freeze and
individuate and maybe it seems like Dharma is all about melting melting melting melting actually Charlotte jobek
has a very beautiful description of being an ice cube and melting and once you get a little mushy you can't get UNM
mushy you know it's very beautiful this is a little different sense of
um yeah of of freezing as a way of um of
of individuating so I sometimes have have
mentioned this uh exercise I did as a yogi was was was sitting the retreat at
IRC uh 6 years ago with Ain suito and uh aan uh in his capacity as
for a long time as an Abbot and as an elder within the the monastic system
high Forest lineage uh he said very explicitly that he found meditation practices
were insufficient for uh managing the interpersonal
Dynamics within communities and found that some explicit interpersonal
practices were important in uh fostering
communal Harmony and so he shared some of those
practices uh with us in that in that week and for one of them we gathered if
you've been to to Insight Retreat Center uh uh we gathered in the community room
that not the meditation Hall the big open room those very high ceilings and
the light flooding in and um and it was a group of about 40 and the instruction
was to pair now we've been sitting for I don't know five days of silence and um to pair up stand maybe 10
15 ft part from your partner lined up in rows you know one row here one row there
facing each other and the goal is to explore connection and boundaries and
intimacy and the instruction was to walk towards each other
um walk walk walk towards each other and you can either signal stop
move move forward or slow down you know and the
idea was like okay how how much can we negotiate our own
inner life while remaining deeply connected to another person you're feeling into like where
you can be safely connected not relinquish
yourself where you the moment moments where you actually need to U freeze rather than melt and then
melt again and I was in uh I I don't remember
exactly but I was in a weird you know altered state kind of just it was enough
sitting and beautiful Dharma that it was like
um it had made an impact it was very I was kind of like very very thinned out
and very loving very melt very much on the melty side you know and
um and the practice kind of starts immediately like okay pick a partner and
I even though I talk to large groups of people regularly and feel unashamed to do so
I'm actually shy and live to avoid certain species of social awkwardness
like it's my reason for living is just to avoid certain species of
awkwardness but I got to find a partner right and I'm just there as a yogi but
some people there knew that I taught there and that adds a layer of
complexity you know and I remember like okay I'm in this like very melty kind of
state I I don't want to go kind of like slobber on some poor Yogi like I'm this
big dumb meta dog you know like I was just like all right I'm just going to let somebody come to me you know I just
stood there a little Frozen waiting for someone to
approach and then we see how does it feel to be in their presence I knew I
knew the person I knew knew I remember warm you know we didn't know each other
well but I remember very warm feelings towards him and okay how how close can one get
while staying connected to yourself what does it mean to be deeply porous but not
abandon yourself and so this is a kind of dance
of feeling into one's needs sensing one's boundaries sensing when to melt when to freeze
sensing when you can no longer take that person
in and so we're seeing them but we're also seeing our own mind you know we try
to to attune to them but we're they also function as a kind of screen on which
our mind is projected and the Gaze of another especially in the context of all the
silence it's like the Gaze of the others is evocative right we we some sometimes
that can really freeze us into a sense of self and that form of freezing is a kind
of static that interrupts intimacy
often what is it what does it feel like to feel that they see
me that sense of like I'm being seen I'm an object in the mind of the other
and we sense what it might what we kind of model what it might be like in their mind to see
me and there's a kind of subtle or maybe sometimes dramatic pain of duality in
that of an object being seen by another an animal being viewed by another
animal and to even feel like your behind
your eyes is a
liability the face is so potent it doesn't in in seeing in being seen it
does not have to conclude with self we melt we melt and in that melting we
start to sense the a whole kind of Ethics in the face of the other
you look really carefully at somebody's face in their
undefended just relaxation you look carefully at that face a whole ethics in
it and so okay we start walking uh you know walking towards each
other and it feels so good you know there like
how how open can things be how vast can they be just open you're kind of like as
I remember it just like pervasively open
space mingled with meta you know and the field was so bright it was
a bright room but it was the kind of like Luminosity of the mind and everything just so run through
with space and we start to open in this way
and the perception of the other person occurs in the same field as all self
referentiality self and other arising in the same
field and where am I then
the sense of like having melted behind my clo eye you know Frozen behind my
closed eyes located back there that
fully fully dissolves and so this is a kind of state
of like very deeply forgetting oneself who you are how you're seen
what's right or wrong about you every every self
story is a kind of Million Miles Away and utterly irrelevant to the project of
living and almost everything falls away except a sense of
knowing you know and the knowing is very
satiating very un un partitioned space unpartitioned epistemic space is
the way philosopher metzinger characterized
it and so there's all this melting and then what actually happened
was like self view gripped my mind there was a certain kind of freezing that
happened that I didn't notice and and I had the thought like you know I'm a
sensitive New Age guy I should get really close to this
person but I could feel I was
like something was starting to I was like
betraying something I was like like sacrificing my
boundaries because I had some ideal of what I was supposed to be and in
instantaneously like the vast open meta field just
dissolved dissolved
and a very kind of in a sense very um
dramatic form of freezing that didn't have to happen if I actually could have
just Frozen in a more relaxed way right as I'm sensing like oh okay so
now this feels like too much or something's in intrusive about the
presence of the other and I needed to say okay let us pause and I
couldn't and then that is what led to this kind of like the other end of the
spectrum a really deep freeze and so I was you could say identified with
being like water I couldn't be ice but then and I strangely created the
experience of really freezing that inflexibility that
identification with being water uh became a
problem some of us need more practice being like water some being like
ice and we probably all need more practice in the transition of moving
between water and ice the dance of yes and
no dance of yes and no if you you don't trust somebody's yes
you you know uh it's hard to know what their no
means if they can't say no hard to know what a Yes means the dance of yes and no assertion
surrender water ice okay offer this for your
consideration and um uh I I some of you know but I do a
Wednesday night class certain Wednesdays certain Wednesdays today is one of the certain Wednesdays I'll be uh
doing this exact same format 7:30 Pacific on the same channel literally
the same channel same bat Channel and uh topic tonight to stay with this
interpersonal theme talk about um sexuality uh L lust sexuality
Dharma um and uh see you back tomorrow tomorrow morning okay sorry I ran a
little long and uh look forward to to reconnecting