morning friends I say good
morning to those on the west coast here but good day and welcome good
afternoon good evening to people signing in from all
over say good morning those on the west coast here
and I see some friends good morning Richard and Cindy and many others
friends old and new Julie good morning and thank
you for your support lovely to see everybody checking
in greeting one another
and it's seven here on the West Coast so we'll get
underway and before we sit together I'll introduce uh a theme for the week
sort of following on and inspired by Kim Kim's uh Kim's theme last
week which she shared with me uh the other day a a theme I'm going to call the five
knowledges or the five understandings and I thought to myself this morning oh that's kind of a
technical sounding thing and uh uh it's too late probably now to change it with
the uh people who title the week's talks but I think I want to call it the Buddha
smile I don't know if you've noticed this you probably have but Buddhist
statues like this one here uh very frequently show the Buddha
with a a smile sort of a mysterious you could say Mona Lisa
smile and uh I've always kind of been curious about that
smile and I think this week we could we can we can explore aspects of the meditation five
and number that arise as as part of the meditation practice that uh bring sort
of an inward contentment and with it sometimes an inward smile and sometimes a smile that that uh is expressed on our
on our faces or in our spirit both in the meditation and
through the day so I'll say more about the theme it's five understandings or five
knowledges uh as we go the first one of them I'm going to call something like
the um cultivating the pleasant and even the pleasure me in the
meditation so let's sit bring our attention Inward and downward maybe
closing the eyes if that feels comfortable bringing the eyes into
relaxed um sort of middle distance if one wants
to keep them open and let some light
in and what we'll bring our attention to as we settle in as we make contact with
the breathing or with the body with whatever object of meditation
we take as our first connection with the Here and Now
of our
experience we can bring our attention to the Pleasant in the meditation
it can feel quite easeful bring us to rest bring us to
ground can Center us and ground us this meditation practice and this bringing of
the attention directing the attention inward downward
sometimes we characterize the
meditation it's qualities and perhaps it's objective as
as ease or
easeful and even if it's incremental marginal even if it's just greater ease
for this moment greater ease than when the mind is busy planning remembering
Fring thinking about other people thinking about ourselves casting itself into the future looking into the past
again all useful qualities of Mind none of which we seek to stamp out or root
out as we cultivate an inner calm and peace and
ease and maybe today we can connect in this ease even if it's just a greater
ease we can notice that it's Pleasant and even that it's
pleasurable and this is a deep aspect of this practice that this
pleasure that comes in the medic meditation isn't to be
feared the Buddha encourages us throughout the texts on which we base our practice to
cultivate this this pleasantness this pleasure of
the meditation practice isn't to be feared but rather to be
cultivated why because it's an uncomplicated simple
pleasure it's not sticky it doesn't entangle us it doesn't rest on external
conditions it rises from within and it's a deep knowledge a deep
knowing a deep understanding that comes with the cultivation of the meditation practice that this contentment this
ease this is wholesome it leads
onward it points toward Freedom we can trust it we can rest in
it as we do so as we rest in it as we become comfortable with
it it becomes stronger this is how it's cultivated
so just rest easy in this today whatever pleasantness comes whatever ease
comes it's part of the path it supports our
practice it has benefits now in this
moment provides a pleasant abiding in the here and
now and it bears fruit in the
future
e
e e
so as we rest in the
meditation and pretty much no matter what's happening in the
meditation whether the mind is busy preoccupied with the day to come or the
day past we can seek
out any greater ease that comes with the meditation and enjoy it
fully confident in the knowing that this pleasantness of the ease is
wholesome and that in addition to providing a benefit for us personally in the in the
Here and Now of the meditation that cultivating it results
in skillful action and and benefit to
others so we can bring the meditation to a close with this with this idea that we
cultivate the meditation for our own benefit and we share that
benefit the ease we find in the meditation the pleasantness the pleasure
even provide a quietness in the mind
that is useful to us as we meet the world meet others in it
so let's share the benefits of our practice confident in the knowing
that far from depleting the benefits to ourselves when
we share the benefits of the practice it increases the benefit for all
beings may all beings benefit from this ease may all
beings know this ease for themselves may all beings be free
[Music]
welcome again everyone good morning I hope you're
well good afternoon good evening if those are the appropriate salutations
where you are and I'd like to devote the teaching
this week to uh sort of an unusual and
obscure teaching that that comes through one of the more obscure
texts that underg our practice that refers to something called the five knowledges or the five
understandings and as I said at the outset today that seemed to me as I
reflected this morning sort of a technical design ation and so I also want to think of the teachings this week
as being about the Buddha's smile when we see representations of the Buddha here's
one here for example here's another on the I guess that would be the far right of our
screens of the Buddha resting preparing for his final
Freedom Parana the Buddha has a smile gentle Mona Lisa
smile that plays on his features
and perhaps the smile comes from understandings that grow with the
meditation practice and in this text from which I draw these teachings and
I'm going to quote with some some Liberties taken with the
poly the Buddha encourages us to develop the meditation and saying develop your
med meditation practice deepen your meditation practice
and as your practice deepens and this isn't an encouragement it's a statement of
fact that as the meditation practice deepens there will be five knowings
understandings knowledges if we have to give it a noun uh that will arise
naturally as part of the practice the those gathered to hear this
teaching ask what five and five are shared and I'll share them in turn this
week but the first one is this and again here I'm um working with the with the
language to express it a way that I think is
useful for us today I mean here today says this this
meditation is pleasant and pleasurable now and it results
in benefit in the future so let's let's unpack that a
little bit in the next few minutes and before sort of getting into this
specific idea of the pleasure of the meditation and cultivating it instead of
fearing it um there's an important um use of words
right here at the at the in the in the beginning that as our meditation
practice deepens these understandings arise all by themselves and for
ourselves so um this is the mechanism by which or
one of the mechanisms by which these teachings um come to us from the
meditation practice from our own experience from our own
internal uh meeting of our experience instead of something that is um comes
from outside through a teacher through a reading this is a reminder that the
meditation practice is primary and that we can trust it to provide all the
teaching we need and it's useful to have guidance that's why we're here in part
today um with together right with spiritual friends with companions in the
path and with teachers um and yet the injunction here
the encouragement here is to pay attention to what happens naturally what arises naturally in each of our
experiences in the meditation itself so this idea of a pleasant
abiding now with beneficial results in the future runs throughout the teachings
about the meditation that it's not only something that's pleasurable and uh even
Blissful in in the meditation but something that has future benefits at
well let's let's focus on each of these two briefly
um the idea that the meditation is pleasant and even pleasurable I
introduce other teachers introduce with a certain um hesitance
because we sometimes um are afraid of
pleasure that uh we some sometimes are not sure how it fits into the practice
how it becomes or can be part of the path of practice and there can be a shying away from some of the pleasant
that arise in meditation I laugh because you know a lot of times we look for trouble in the meditation we're like
yeah you know here's this difficult thing arising here's this difficult thing arising we look for H we look for
the suffering suffering comes to our attention as it as it as is natural and
as it should and yet there's also in the pleasantness of the meditation there's
also path in other words sure understanding suffering and its arising
is critical to having a path away from
suffering knowing the pleasure of meditation the pleasantness of the ease
of mind the openness of mind the collectiveness of mind that develops in the meditation as it deepens this too is
part of the path
and just to make sure that it doesn't sound like
it's just me saying that I want to quote the Buddha who says in several places but in one
particular discourse that I love says this this pleasure this ease of
meditation I call the pleasure of letting go the pleasure of separating
ourselves from the world of mental activity and regular daily
life the pleasure of seclusion the pleasure of Peace pleasure of the
meditation the pleasure of being awake in the world and then such pleasure should be
cultivated and developed and should not be feared this is very strong encouragement
and in providing this encourage encouragement the Buddha is basing it on his own experience of becoming
awake many of you probably know this story but the Buddha after years of
seeking different paths working with different teachers to in particular that
we know of um among other practices does
a lot of practices of aestheticism privation starvation um living with very
few clothes being open Living Without Shelter living with very little
food and eventually realizes that none of these practices seem to lead toward
the freedom that he seeks and one day sitting under a rose
apple tree he falls into a deep meditative
state of the sort that we cultivate in our practice and he realizes ah this
pleasure that comes with the meditation it's not dependent on external conditions it arises from within it can
be trusted and it leads toward Freedom it's part of the
path and there's a bunch of reasons why this might be so but I'll just give you one since our time is
short um this is so in part because our brains and our bodies are
very oriented towards pleasure for good reasons and reasons that sometimes come complicate our lives
and if we can find and develop in our meditation practice Pleasures that are wholesome Pleasures that bear fruit in
skillful action in the world those can be cultivated
safely and the beauty of the pleasantness the pleasure the ease that come with the meditation is that if we
bring it to attention and if we rest in it we can see we can understand it's a
knowledge it's a knowing that arises from within the meditation itself we can understand that it's not sticky it
doesn't have the complications and entanglements that other Pleasures sometimes
do you'll notice for example that although it's very pleasant we don't want more of it in
quite the same way that we want more chocolate or more you know um
more um more um more PE experiences of
various kinds let me let me put it that way to cover a broad range of activities behaviors
substances uh and the like and so that knowing going oh this
this pleasantness of Mind of body this restfulness this groundedness this
centeredness this collectedness of mind this Stillness of mind with a feeling of
well-being this can be trusted this is part of the
path this does seem to lead toward greater Stillness greater
ease the more it's rested in and the more it's thus cultivated the more it leads onward
toward the sort of ultimate peace the ultimate freedom of of this
path so in a way that's the pleasant abiding in the here and now that this
phrase speaks of a pleasant abiding in here that produces produces yields maybe
is better yields gives way to yields beneficial results in the future and
this is where I think as at the end of the guided meditation we can also um understand the
wholesomeness of this pleasantness in the meditation it's an interesting thing
that if in the meditation practice if in our practice more broadly we find ease
we find Stillness we find pleasure we find pleasantness we're a greater ease in the
world in the world of interactions with other beings perhaps in particular we are not seeking um the same kinds of
externally conditioned pleasures satisfactions and it makes it much more
likely that when we interact with people we can do so in a way that's free that's free of clinging that's free of
attachment that's free of projection that's free of um that's free of
suffering one thing I think is important about this teaching is that important
useful um inspiring is that it doesn't encourage us to do
anything except for as it says in the orig the opening encouragement deep in our meditation practice keep going back
to the meditation practice and notice what arises naturally in the meditation what can be the knowledges that arise
without us having to seek them if we pay attention we can notice oh this feels
good now and it seems to have benefit later
and it doesn't suggest that it's linear or that we have to pay attention to that
we can trust that it has good effects later could be really useful to notice how that's so but we don't have to do
anything except notice you may notice that after and I think this is true for
a lot of us here after meditating for half an hour on a regular basis in the
mornings with Gil with other uh wonderful teachers my
colleagues in uh in supporting Gil in this way um that the day is easier and
our interactions are I say easier I mean more easeful they may not be easier but
they may have greater ease in them and it is always the case it's it's
axiomatic at least in this practice that it's always going to be more skillful to
act with some peace of mind than not so we don't have to go looking for oh I
meditated this morning and then you know I I was my my speech with this my my
interaction with this person involved more skillful speech may be useful to notice that but we can trust that the
meditation produces that effect without our having to do very much at all except
return to the meditation and watch what it teaches us so I'll leave you with that thought
just watch what arises naturally as a knowledge as a knowing as a deep understanding in the meditation and
trust that and if it's Pleasant or pleasurable trust that know that that's
part of the path that it provides a Pleasant abiding in the here and now and
that it results in beneficial action and beneficial interaction in the
future so thank you all appreciate you being here together supporting one
another in our practice and I'll see you tomorrow morning take care