well thank you and um so thank you Hillary for reminding me
about the dayong on
Saturday I did remember I haven't forgotten it but I didn't know the
time so I guess it's 8:30 to 5 you said so that so we um the last thing
that we were scheduled to do when the pandemic began was a day a day long here and uh I came
down early and made a sign and sat on the deck and said nope we're
closed so it kind of for me it comes in a full circle now it's been slightly
more than four years be four years and two weeks that uh since we had that canceled
day long so we're making up for it and if it is from 8:30 to 5:00 those are day
longs where um they're mostly silent through the day and uh I give a few
words at the beginning of the day and a talk at the end and I'm available for practice discussion through the day
there's a whole series of signups during the walking period so it's a kind of a a
wonderful opportunity to engage in your own practice in community in silence and
um when I do day longs from 9: to 4:30 those have uh guided meditation
instructions through the day so so that's so so you're all
welcome to come and I'm I'm certainly looking forward to starting them up
again so um the topic so I thought I would try to offer
you a meditator orientation to the sense of
self the sense of self is um is very
amorphous psychologists who use this uh term sometimes uh will some of the
definitions they give is like the collection of beliefs about the self some people go a little bit further to
say it's the they keep using the word collection the collection of personality
characteristics beliefs values Mor morality choices um you know some people go
further and say hormones and and uh thoughts and all kinds of things
come together but the important thing is that it's a collection so it's a amalgum of all
kinds of different things that are organized together to provide some amorphous sense of this is who I am this
is myself as a collection the uh The Collector the you
know collects things differently different context different situations ations our sense of shelf self can shift
over uh the Decades of a life sense of shelf self can shift over the minutes of
the day depending on the circumstance we find ourselves in the circumstance that
gather together that collect together what we need to get organized to meet
the situation that we're engaged in and so uh if this is the way we
understand that sense of self that it's a collection and that collection is collected different different ways and
different times then what happens in meditation and why meditation can be a
great uh kind of fascinating perspective on this is that the sense of uh that is
that uh as we relax and destress and calm down in meditation there's less of
this collecting going on there's less of this organizing things around this sense
of self or organizing particular way because some of the way we collect the mind collects not necessarily
consciously done is done uh as an activity an active forces in our
psychology in our mind and our body and our emotions they're they these are all
Marshall together to organize a a sense of
self but if some of those things have gotten quiet and still they're not
contributing to building that sense of self in that kind of way and um another
sense of kind of sense of self can arise because it's not using certain things so
for example I think one of the common organizing principles for a sense of
self is um uh
fear desire to protect and so we search around we look
inside we're organizing oursel in such a way to somehow help make ourselves feel
safe and some of those things can happen uh quite independent of any conscious
idea of who I am uh if um you know so it still happens so you I
don't know every two three times a year I think I'm hiking up in the hills here
and I see on the trail a twisted root of a tree or something and my first glass I
see a snake and uh and that first glance it isn't just seeing a snake there's a
physiological response in me for a moment physiological fear or concern
something gets activated and um and then I look at it long enough to see no it's not a it's
not a you know it's just a it's just a root that's looks like a snake a little
bit and um but there's been something's been activated
unconsciously without a choice to begin making myself safe being organized being
organized inside towards safety around the Snake once in Thailand I organized
myself much more dramatically when um uh I was in the
jungle and there was I don't know pretty wide dirt road I think a car could have
probably passed by and um and it was dust I couldn't see very well
and I had a you know film camera over with a strap strap over my shoulder
walking along and um and there was this Branch you know across the road and so I
stepped on the branch it wasn't a branch that was a
snake it was a big snake and so and so there was no you
know I something got organized something gathered together all kinds of MUSC and forces and things and I jumped in the
air spun in the air and threw the camera at the snake you know all that happened kind of
without planning it there was you know I didn't calculate or plan or she like but there was a tremendous amount of of
physiology and also probably some um algorithms that the brain has are
figuring out distance to the snake and direction of throwing and it's a phenomenon a complex event that happened
right there I wasn't I the usual idea of me was not
operating however we have us we have all this stuff that can get
triggered by the life we live that contributes then to this sense of self
and fear is one of them feeling wanting to be safe and what we search for and want when it's dramatic we talk about
fight and flight but when it's not so dramatic there are other things we do um
we search for protection some people search for the people who are going to keep us safe or the things that are going to keep us safe and and um and
there's orientation around what provides the safety we need and our sense of self
then gets very much tied to things maybe externally that this is what's going to keep me safe I need this safety I need
this so we start organizing ourselves um and uh the Buddha
emphasized how we organize this of self U collect the sense of self he he used
the word Kanda which these days translate as bundle how we bundle ourselves together
and um and uh but he also used the an analogy of a of a someone who sews a
tailor or a seamstress I think it's female seamstress in poly um is um that
is sewing together cloth or something and that's a metaphor of how desire is
the seamstress desires are sewing together the collection of things that we all want that to create the sense of
self the desire is as part of the collector and now say collect it but
it's sewing it together so it's that's the attachment the clinging to really keep it globed together
tight so um so it's easy in the course of the day to
be organized as our sense of self by what we're driven by by our desires what
we're consumed with what we're oriented towards this is important what I want to do and um and I should know better but I
see sometimes if I'm at home and I'm doing some my more research work and
writing and things like that um I kind of enjoy doing it but I get organized around that that and then if family come
and interrupts me it's like you know I get disoriented it's like you know
no you know because I have this momentum in this direction and so then I I see
that and then I okay I I to take a breath and let go and the family needs me now and and so but but the the force
is there momentum is there to do one thing and um when I was 14
uh I remember the momentum was uh to go through the entire phone book back back
then they had phone books and um uh which are people's names and then on the
on the left on the right there'd be the phone number but in between there'd be the
address and um uh I went through from the front my friend went through from the back because all we knew was the
girl's first name and the street she lived
on so we went to looked for all the streets the phone phone numbers heard
that street and then we called each number ask asking for
her so that's certain 14 that's a little bit of a you
know Drive to be organized
around and that was after having met her and for the first time in my life I
tried to light a cigarette to impress her which is also a kind of sense of
self what's important who you need to be right and um but I didn't really know
how so I failed so that was hard
so so um so I don't think that particular thing ever worked out for
me so um so you know so we organize ourselves what our choices what our
momentum what we're about in our life by all kinds of things and some of these forces are not
necessarily uh who would you know something we would even choose but it we feel the momentum the force and that
force of momentum of Desire or fear or anger or hostility or interest even is enough to
kind of help organize gather together all these other things for that purpose
and that force that momentum that forward goinging that desires that sews it together that collecting of things
that creates an amalgam of something can feel like it has a real thing it's like
this is who I am this is what I'm about right now but it's not but it can shift and
change uh about 10 years ago I had surgery and I took um pain medication
but I don't like taking pain medication so um I think I maybe took it for two
days and um which was Maybe not maybe it was maybe maybe not well I don't know if
it was long enough or not but uh I took it for two days and um and then I said
enough the next day uh I was still laying in bed recovering
from surgery and I had all these thoughts I said and
feelings I said well I'm really kind of going over the
hill you know in terms of my life cycle I'm on the way down to the
end my kids on their way up they were like you know they're just life is beginning for them they're their way up
it's exciting for them it's great and and I'm going down and there there's no point for me to do anything anymore and
it's you know it's the end you know and I don't know you know it's not really so great anymore and you know this is the
end and you know [Laughter] oh so uh so I called a friend of mine
and uh and told her what was going on and she said Gil that's the withdrawal from the pain
medication and I said oh okay so that made a big difference
for me I still had those feelings and those thoughts but I had I had glommed
onto it i' gotten identified by it my sense of self was defined by these
thoughts by these feelings I was having and all she had to do was say that's the
that's the withdrawal from medication and I didn't identify with it anymore it still went on it wasn't great but I
wasn't making a self out of it and sure enough within 24 hours it was back to
normal you know that was gone so uh I so I've known other people whove you know for medical reasons I've I've had
medication uh for things and um for different kinds of things and my
emotions my feelings my desires my drives all shift around the
medication I had one friend who um had uh for medical reasons was for a month
or so was given premature or medically induced menopause she was in her
30s and uh and she had this wonderful thing she said to me at one point she
said these thoughts I'm having are not me so she had the wisdom not to get
pulled in to what was going on she they were so bizarre so strange for her so she's oh this is not who I am and so
that made it easier for her to stay with it but you know this making a self this
is who I am is a sense of self this is who and it's hard not to when there's a
lot of authority a lot of force behind them you know so like when we're afraid
we everything gets organized around being taken care of ourselves but we never
question uh have we already before we are afraid what is it that is threat
threaten maybe we've already created a sense of self around something that's threaten so for example if uh
status it could be a uh our sense of self is related to how attractive we are
how smart we are who we know um where we live all kinds of things around uh you
know that becomes threaten I need those things to be socially accepted I need these things to fit in I need these
things to get into Old life old age and so we're we're there's something
there which is threatened can be threatened and we've already organized
why are we organized in certain particular way sometimes because of our life
experience uh life experiences can be quite difficult for people uh children
can grow up and what the message they get or gets how they get formed as a
person and their inner sense of who they are their sense of self it can be very much shaped by how their parents treat
them I see this regularly when people come to talk to me that how much that
people who uh weren't seen as children didn't feel loved there was no one there
to support them and guide them and mirror them and or when they or
sometimes when they did try to express their inner life to their parents or people around them um they were attacked
they were ashamed they were criticized people got angry and so they learned that they couldn't who they were
internally couldn't be expressed it was all about pleasing other people or making thems safe in relationship to
other people and everything the sense of self was all organized around what was external to make it just right or
something but maybe they never really had a chance to be see see themselves more deeply know themselves more deeply
their inner motivations their inner desires their inner values couldn't really had a chance to come forward
because they were not mirrored they had no place for it they were they were not affirmed they were not given positive
reinforcement around it and so the self then gets organized without those
things and some some therapists psychotherapists will spend a lot of time supporting people to discover who
they are by reconnecting themselves to their inner drives their inner emotions their inner
beliefs their inner sense of self and their inner ability to uh stand up for
themselves and so uh in my life life I remember I it was interesting in a particular phase of my practice when I
was a Zen student early years of Zen practice uh I was part of what I was
doing un unknown to me at the time it wasn't like I planned it or knew even knew it was happening was I was kind of
reorganizing and discovering my sense of self and and learning what was not
functional and what was functional what needed to happen around it to some degree and uh and some of the things
that happened we kind of it could be described as geometrically opposed to each other what I was trying to do but
that's because a sense of self is multifaceted we don't have just one sense of self that we organize ourselves
around it's contextual it shifts and changes so almost at exactly the same
time um uh in a range of time about year or two uh I had
um um I was living at uh the Frisco Zen Center living in a place where the big
ethos dedication of the place is to live for the welfare and happiness of the world the idea is to be a bodh satva
that really there to serve the world and even to put off put off your own Awakening until everybody else is
awakened first so to be of service and um and so the Zen Center
would ask for lots of service we lived there I was monk that you know kind of vows of poverty and Serv and obedience
kind of and so whatever they asked me to do I did but institutions don't usually
say no for people and uh at some point I was working uh full-time for five and a half
days a week Monday through half day Saturday and then I on on Sunday I had
to take this big buffer and buffer all the floors at Z Center and wait a minute that was my day
off so I I did that for a while and I said wait a minute no one here is going to say no for
me and it was a little hard it was hard for me to say know because it was like a great world religion you who might have
stand up to that my little Gil stand up to you know
Buddhism and um and so but at some point I said no this doesn't make sense I have to stand up and say no this is and so
that was a that was a kind of important step of asserting myself because I didn't know I could it was even bigger a
couple of years later maybe a year and a year or so year later when I went to practice in
Japan and and there I went back to like to the Mother Temple like the one of the where you know the heart of Zen budhism
which in my big my little mind little kid mind was you know again this huge authority figure Father Figure maybe and
there was all right that I had to you know obey or something and uh and I was
uh set up to be there for a for in the monastery for 5 months an intensive
Retreat time and about halfway through I realized this is not the right place for me this is not this is not working and
it's not right and and um and who am I to say that's not right you know and you're not supposed to leave in the
middle and so um no no I know this would came really clear I
know and so this is not right for me and and it doesn't make sense for me to stay stay and I have to be able to now stand
up for myself and say no and leave and that was a huge growth for me to assert
myself to be have that ability to stand up and know what I needed to do so that's a kind of sense of self to
understand oneself well enough and make that kind of choice and then the amazing thing
happened I made this decision completely clear I had no doubt about it I knew it
was a milestone and that allowed something else to happen then I decided to
stay but not for my sake there had been a Japanese monk who had sponsored me at
the monastery and I knew that if I left his reputation in his religious community in
Japan would be maybe destroyed it was a huge deal so when I realized that after I
decided I would go but I'd already made this decision and change but then I didn't
have to go anymore and I stayed PA for his sake I didn't want to have that
impact on him so it's almost like I became stronger as a person and now with
that strength I could use it to for the benefit of someone else and you know and
put aside my own benefit in a certain degree the work that needed to be done had been done at the same time that was going
on I had this very clear sense that there was an attachment to self within
me and I could feel that that had to let go that clinging had to let go but I had
no idea how to do it in fact I was afraid to do it because it felt like if
I let go of that I'm going to fall into a great Abyss that's literally how it felt I mean I couldn't see I didn't see
any Abyss but that's that's how I kind of felt and um and so I knew that that was
something I had to do and but I didn't know how so I went went along and I went
along and then eventually I kind of made a ritual for myself that when I go my
second time to Asia to practice um that trip there will be that ritual now I'm
going to let go I never saw it let go but what I saw was that after a period
of deep meditation long meditation Retreats that that sense of attachment
no longer was there there was still a sense of self
but it was not being sewn together by this sense of self by by by this uh
desire this attachments I had there was a freedom that happened
there so when we meditate it's not just about becoming
stressfree and becoming calm many in the public mind in the United States I think a lot of people think of meditation for
the purposes of stress reduction the stress reduction for us in our practice is the beginning of a
deeper investigation if you can get quiet and still and release a lot of the stress we
have what we're doing simultaneously is we're pu putting to
rest for a while some of the different forces some of the different activities
that going on inside of us that collects that sense of self together and so the sense of self begins
to soften begins to shift begins to be quiet
and uh and it might actually change a lot some people's sense of self changes
dramatically through meditation because they prefer the sense of self they have when they meditate than when they're not
meditating and for some people the dissonance between who they think feel they are when they meditate and who they
are in the active busy world is so radically different that it's it's it's
confusing it's challenging it's it's it's you know something and it was for
me a little bit when I first first started meditating regularly um every
day let's see I yeah so I I did probably was doing it for maybe about nine months
or something and then I went to live on a small farm uh and so every morning I got I got
up to meditate before you know before we went to breakfast and um and I was living with
friends and um but how I was coming out of my
meditation it's like Gil wasn't there like I was peaceful I was calm I was content but the the social Gill the one
who played social games and you know we you know one way or other we're playing
social games often when we're talking with people with my friends and going along with what they want and they with
me and praising and excitement and something that wasn't operating so I'd
sit at breakfast kind of content and quiet and I could feel after a few days of this after a
while I have to make a choice here either I stop meditating or I'm
going to lose my friends and I gave up meditation because
I wanted my friends I wanted I wanted to have Harmony there I wanted to work well there and I didn't know how to make it I
didn't know how to make it work at that point in my life later I learned how to do
that and um so to sit and meditate and feel the mind the body get
calmer more settled to feel the stress go away to feel certain degree of relief
of Peace quieting maybe even some Stillness that is a a vantage
point from which to begin being curious about what is it that we're
gathering together what are we sewing together to make this the sense of self it might be that as you come out of
meditation you you're now you can start seeing what's happening what you're what's what you're
what you're Gathering Together what's happening maybe not right away when you come out of meditation but maybe later
in the day you see wait a minute I'm back to business as usual and now I in
the past I thought this was this was like the fish can't see the water it's swimming in they say I don't know if
it's true but uh that's what they say and um
but uh so we don't see the concept of self that we swim in they're so taken
for granted some people have chronic anxi anxiety chronic fear don't know they
have it I can't tell you how many people I've known have come on a Meditation Retreat where you're they're sitting
long enough to get quieter and quieter where they're watching their mind continuously more and over over and they
discover wow my fear is pervasive I have no idea
how pervasive it was always there operating so people we can have these
forces that organize us that drive us to how we live our life but that we don't
not so conscious of them and so that's one of so as we get quieter and quieter and those things go
to for rest for a rest then we have a a contrast by which to see them more
clearly by and we say oh fear organizes my life
desires organize my life um shame organized my life H
hostility organizes my life and these emotions are quite
deep they are so deep it's kind of like the fear I had with a snake that you
know it's more instinctual than anything that was consciously done when I swirled
in the air and threw that camera down some of these Deep Emotions like shame
and desires and fears and anger
hostility they operate in very deep forces within us sometimes we don't even know how much they're
there but they are the the kind of organizing principles the magnets around
which other things are gathered but when fear quiets down anger quiets
down shame quiets down Desir is quiet down we see well we
see that they're optional we see that they're not inherent they're not always
operating and there can be start starting to be an idea maybe I don't
have to believe them maybe I don't have to make a self out of them maybe I don't
identify them and have have those Define who I am just like just when my friend said
that's the withdrawal you're going through I loosened up I lightened up around my thoughts and my
emotions I didn't realize how much I had organized myself tightly around those thoughts tightly around those
emotions oh look at that look at that and there's an opening there's a
relaxing there's a seeing and the possibility comes that
one day and I'm saying this to make you curious because curiosity sometimes is a
opens doors is a day will come when you
observe the sense of self observe the operating principles that are driving
something inside of you you observe it
from a place of Silence a silent place where there's
nonverbal knowing that's independent free from
what those thoughts beliefs sense of self is say wow look at that there's a
sense of self you don't say there is my sense of self thank you I'm going to keep it
and you better learn what it is I'm going to prove it to you who I am no oh
it's a a sense of self look at that and it's known from a place of Stillness of calm
of Peace that's independent from what is being
seen some people then will identify with that still quiet awareness that's the
self and that's pretty common that's true who I really am and uh when I came
to my Buddhist teacher and said that to him said well you know everything else is not me but this awareness is me he
just smiled and said just keep looking and sure enough at some point
that also disappeared and I saw oh that's not Al Al that also is not self
that's just you know that's just observing let it be just observing and
um so so to use meditation not only to become calm and
peaceful but to you see that whatever degree of calm and peace you can reach that that gives you a new way of
understanding what makes you operate what your operating principles are what
the progam programs are that you're operating on that gathers together organizes itself into this is who I
am and you'll start seeing that this your sense of self is actually shifting
and changing all the time some of them sometimes they they get solidified fossilized frozen into a
particular one but to some degree it's shifting and
changing sometimes I think of it's like the water that takes the shape of whatever contain you poured into the
water into so that we have all these different we gather gather all these different
things into a container and so something takes that
shape and um the Buddha sometimes refer to this as a clay pot that a Potter has
made and the B Gathering Together the bundling of all this
stuff and when we're enlightened then the the pottery
shards the metaphor shifts from where in that we know who we are is inside this
pot and defined by it limited by it uh the imagery changes to image of a very
clear Mountain Lake that the person on person who can
see clearly um good eyesight can stand on the edge of the little Lake and see
right down to the the bottom of the lake it's so clear and in the on the floor
bottom there are Pottery Pottery shards and now the the
water is the container for the shards rather than the pot being the
container for the water so exactly what the water supposed to be in this metaphor is uh you know
it's up for grabs but uh you know it could be your
awareness and what we're trying to do in Buddhism is is to set awareness
free and what What's Left Behind maybe it's kind of I don't know
if you like this metaphor but the shards the broken shards the the
solidified ways in which we limit ourselves by our sense of self I think
the sense of self is always can be a limiting Force but not
always doesn't have to be and from a from a therapeutic point of view people
who use therapists who use the sense of self they they they talk a lot about creating a strong sense of
self that um when I said no to Zen Buddhism I I was developing a stronger
sense of self people who become mature in this practice develop what a
therapist would call a very strong sense of self uh they know who they are they know
who they are in relation with other people they know how to take care of themselves stand up for themselves they
know to they know what they've attained they know what their inner life is like
all the things that the therapist wants to see for a strong sense of self they
have no problem but it's it's not inside of a
clay pot The Clay Pot is inside of awareness
set free so I hope that this talk one of the
purposes I gave it which I said was hope to hope to give you some
curiosity about what it might be like for you to observe your sense of
self from a still silent place
inside and maybe you don't have that place yet but maybe you can have
intimations of it and maybe from that still quiet
place where there can be nonverbal knowing how do you know what happens
when you know and watch the the a the
senses of self as they roll through your life and can you become free of
it shattering The Clay
Pot so those are my thoughts and um
maybe we have a few minutes this is a kind of talk that either we just be
quiet about and just not say anything and live with
or you have got questions and concerns and
protests they're all invited so anybody want to have anything they want to ask or say and Martha in the in the
back the idea of nonself or non attach the idea of nonself or nonattachment to
self is probably the most confusing Concept in Buddhism to me at this point in my
life did I mention that during this talk well did I incorrectly infer I don't think I me said anything about that okay
I heard the part about attachment but is attachment and and self the same thing for you no no
attachment to a sense of self right oh but that's not then if so there can be
nonattachment to a sense of self okay now you're just confusing me
so for you self sense of self and attachment are always go
together it seems that's where I'm at oh fantastic you're in the right place
then keep looking okay but I have a question about
how I deal with other people's projections of me oh yes so so I'm often
the only woman in a group of businessmen uhhuh and there's a certain
tendency that I that I experience that they underestimate me and I notice that
drains some of my energy yes and then there's the experiences where I'm in a
group of people where my work has been very beneficial to them and there's
agulation and that feels even worse which surprised me because that only
came late in life yes and then there's the moments when I'm with someone we're engaging on what feels a really
authentic level um and I'm talking about things regarding my
work um and I gain energy from that I also gain useful connections new ideas
things that help me build what I'm building now um and I'm trying to understand those projections in terms of
this idea of the sense of self yeah what are they and how do I deal with them yeah well I think there's always going
to be projections so they're not going to go away and the question is can we
mean what just talked about is complicated to talk it's the whole ecosystem you've talked about and I
brought it up the E ecosystem of self it's so so many different parameters and issues going on and they shift the sense
of self shifts in different contexts different situations and that's part of both the charm and the and the
wonderfulness of the sense of self when it's free enough to shift and change depending on
circumstances and uh it's also part of the challenge because how can we keep up with all the changes and how can we
manage the different ones where we find ourselves in but this is where if we could develop um uh I think one of the
things we want to develop in this practice is a lot of confidence a lot of confidence in just
being alive and present and clear confident that we can speak up in the
necessary confident we can say no U maybe can't do it verbally out loud to the people there but we know inside of
ourselves that we can make the right choices uh to take care of ourselves to
slow things down or step away or you know and um we're confident enough that
we can uh deal with the problems if we just walk away from something get too
difficult for us and they not worried about being homeless because we're confident enough that even homeless we
can take our ground and be present so there's a phenomenal it's possible to cultivate a
confidence in oneself we that we carry with us into all these difficult and
complicated places so that we don't become um victims of the projections we
don't get pushed around by them we don't believe them we don't depend on them um
and uh so so that's my best answer in this short time I don't I think it's inadequate I want to respect what you
said and and a lot of people here in this room how difficult this is for to
navigate um but if we can do this work in meditation to use it to see not just
to if we just distress if we end up oh I'm so stressful this life of mine and
then we go back the next day and the Dynamics haven't changed then we need to recover again we keep recovering but if
we have we start understanding what get calm enough and quiet enough we can start seeing what is operating there and
what sense of self what what how am I organizing myself when I go into a business meeting what self am I
bringing and that's when I bring the fear self and so I'm looking and organizing myself in a certain way when
I'm going to the meeting where I'm the boss I'm organizing myself and now very
differently and there's choices being made subconsciously and consciously about how to present ourselves how we're
going to be who we're going to be so what we want to do with this practice is to and I can't answer all the
questions for anybody about how they should be with all these different situations but uh we make a huge Headway
if we start being able to observe our own sense of self and it shifting changing nature and the choices
behind it and the emotions the beliefs the all these different traits that come
come into play as we bundle together organize together collect together the
sense of self that okay for now yeah awareness
and confidence I mean to to distill it yeah those two things could take you a
long way I can definitely work with that thank
you someone else we do one more here in the front
can wait for the mic please
and then what you want to do is you want to hold it yeah like this okay um yeah so you talked about fear as sort of
creating a sense of self and just now you talked about um I guess what I
reflect is like the up and down nature of you know maybe getting better and like okay saying all right put my fear
aside and then feel better but then going back down and then fear again kind of creating a sense of self I don't know
if you can talk about how to you know not have this up and down
uhhuh I think that the uh the the orientation with with this mindfulness practice we do is to see it clearly to
really see the pattern to see it operating see how it operates to see uh
the uh the beliefs to see the emotions to see the drives to see the organizing
principles uh of how we what what are we getting caught in what are we getting attached to and what are we picking
up rather than thinking that fear is somehow inherently the right way to be
in any situation it's possible that uh we haven't we want to look observe our
fear in a deep way the fear might need us and until we understand the fear in a
deep way um or bring a lot of attention to it uh it's always going to be there
grabbing us when the the situation arises and there's two primary things right now
that I can think of with fear one is that um uh to find the have the fear our
tendency to fear to um thaw and relax in some very very deep way that uh and then
to that's one thing and the other thing is to understand why do we pick up the
fear why do we believe the fear and and if you can do those two
things you'll go a long way to understand what your ups and downs are about how does that
sound do it sound doable yeah yeah I think so great thank
you okay well thank you and
um so very nice to have you and listen I hope this was gave you something
to practice with and um if some of you want to stay a little bit around to find
it be useful to chat about this with someone you're welcome to stay in the room and chat or outside there and um
otherwise next week we have the putl so that's a very nice time here and uh
and people sit inside they sit outside for the Pu luuck and so so if you're interested in being a little more
Community uh stay for the potluck next time and that's not doesn't interest you don't
stay thank you