lovely to see everybody welcoming one another checking in and as I did yesterday
uh I'd like to just welcome everybody who is uh not not saying good morning in
the chat which is most of us
um welcome
everyone it's a a theme we'll address a little bit
tomorrow but uh before we begin formally today I'll just say
that one of the most important attributes of the IMC practice Community
is its inclusiveness and so I like to recognize
that there's a lot of us just sitting in without chatting and that we're part of
the in group too um I like to say that at IMC there are no
Outsiders and that U everyone's part of the in
group and that's in part because as many of you know at IMC everything is run by
us every Everybody all the teachers everybody who opens the doors and takes
care of the facilities it's all volunteers it's all Donna it's all given
freely as the teachings are given freely by the teachers all right at seven here on the
West Coast um and uh been enjoying thinking about
today since yesterday we'll continue with this theme of the Buddhist smile
the smile that develops in the meditation as a result of the the
deepening of the meditation we we establish and cultivate
the conditions for the deepening of the meditation and with its deepening we can expect five knowledges to arise this is
the theme of the text that guides us this week and uh the fourth of these
knowledges is I'm going to read it here very it's a really interesting one uh in
the original language in which it's presented can I find
it oh where did it go okay um
yeah this one says this meditation is peaceful tranquil unified and not held
in place by forceful suppression so I thought I would call
today's uh talk today's talk without Force so important
in our practice to avoid forcefully doing anything any even small amount of force or
violence or hostility toward ourselves in the practice toward the mind is
counterproductive and sometimes it takes some dedicated effort to let go some of
those habits and for the guided meditation I chose to refer to the Eagle
song Take It Easy those of you of my generation will
already be correcting me and remembering that although the song was made famous by The Eagles it was written by Jackson
Brown when he was a teenager don't know what he knew as a teenager about taking it easy but the song um encouraged a
generation to take it easy so let's sit
together uh bringing our eyes down bringing our attention inward bringing
our attention downward at the same time and
and settling into this familiar place of Greater ease greater
Stillness where freedom is possible and where just that possibility
just the hint of it can give rise give rise to this in this internal smile that
sometimes plays across our features and that we see mirrored echoed in the
features of the Buddha and in the various representations of the of the Buddha that surround us in the
practice we can bring attention to the breathing as one
among several bodily experiences that can help ground
us give us a center point the breath has these wonderful
qualities within it of ease balance Simplicity and slow pace compared to the
world of rushing thought in which we're so much
engaged and every time we reconnect with the breath and as I've pointed out
yesterday and I think earlier in the week every time we return to the breath
far from being uh the source of frustration that it sometimes appears to us can be useful
to think of it as an opportunity to reconnect with the qualities of the breathing that are inherent in the
breathing it's slower than thought it's more simple than the complicated
entangling Place places of range of the mind and it's naturally
balanced we don't have to constantly remind the breath to take in this much this much oxygen or exhale this much
waste gas that the breath balances itself if I climb up to the third floor
to get the Bell so I can end a meditation as I did earlier the breath knows what to do going to need some more
oxygen it's going to move more quickly I don't have to think about it the
breath and of course there's exceptions sometimes the breath is more complicated I myself have some significant asthma
from childhood but in general the breath is
simpler slow and balanced compared to to the world of thought so settle in with
the breath and today take it
easy don't let the sound of your own wheels drive you crazy in the words of the song If I remember them
correctly and today we can take this as a way to return to the breathing we return to the
breath without hurry with gentleness we don't need to engage in
the oh I've I've drifted away from the breath the mind has wandered away from the breath or the mind has become all
tight around contracted around thinking about the future the past other people myself we can just
notice that the mind is thus and then we can gently without hurry as if we're
tugging on the leash of a young puppy to come back and sit in our lap maybe again
and again we do it it doesn't help to yank we can do this with this fundamental
practice of returning our attention to the here and now do it without hurry do it without
Force do it without violence or hostility do it without frustration or a
sense of failure we can do it without doubt sense of inadequacy or we're not right for the
practice or the practice isn't right for us just return keep it simple
take it
easy
e
e e
so gently unhurriedly without
Force perhaps almost without trying
we allow the Here and Now of our experience to to come back to
Center as we do this fundamental practice in the meditation
of opening our attention back up to the here and now when the Mind becomes contracted and tight around
thought planning for the future thinking about the past thinking about other people
thinking about ourselves we can bring attention back to
the here and now we can open attention back up more broadly to our experience in this moment moment in a way that's
gentle the way with the way a way that has no Force no violence no judgment in
it and this is so much more important than it seems this fundamental
instruction in a way has all the teachings in it to be fully present with
our experience without adding anything
extra in the words of the song quoted at the outset can take it
easy we can avoid letting the sound of our own wheels
drive us crazy what do we do with the sound of
our own wheels the Mind spinning what if we just let it come and
go we let the sound of our own wheels on the gravel road on the freeway
come into awareness and then drift away again
as we come to the end of the meditation we can take this attitude of taking it
easy allowing our experience to arise so that we can let it
in and let it go we can we can take the
ease that comes with that the inner smile that arises and share
it we engage in this practice for our own benefit
and we also engage in it for the benefit of others and as we share the
ease as we share the
smile as we share the Buddhist
smile we're giving something away perhaps but it's not in the giving away
diminishing our own ease contentment in the
practice may all beings share in
this contentment and the potential to be
awake may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you everyone and apologies if the first strike of that Bell
was a little louder than a little louder than necessary to
bring people gently unhurriedly back to Here and Now
good morning again welcome and in the chat I want to acknowledge I see some Dear Old Friends uh and very much
appreciate the gesture of practicing together I see Dear Old Friends of my mothers also and acknowledge their
presence and again I want to acknowledge all those of us who aren't engaging in
the in the chat as it as it Scrolls up so we return to the teachings of this
week the five knowledges or understandings that arise
as the meditation deepens the text encourages us to cultivate and deepen the meditation
practice and then just notes that as we do so five understandings about the meditation
arise naturally and I think I've been sort of drawing attention this week to how each of these five help further
deepen the practice not surprisingly this is part of the momentum that we
create in the practice that as we bring attention to these understandings as
they arise we further strengthen that tendency that propensity in our minds in
our lives to move toward greater Freedom sometimes people I'm going to
just Riff on that for a second leaving my notes for a moment notes on my the back of my iPhone
um to say that sometimes people ask or wonder well when teachers when we teachers say
things like cultivate in the practice what does that mean how does that happen there may be many ways it happens
through study through you know one way it happens in the meditation practice is simply a function of how our brains work
that as we bring attention to Wholesome mind states that strengthens them so going
back to the first day when we notice that the pleasure that comes up in the meditation is wholesome that it doesn't
depend on outside conditions exterior conditions that it's onward leading that it points towards greater ease as we
notice that and bring it into mind and hold it there it's stronger and it
creates forward momentum so today um the knowledge that arises in
the meditation is and uh let me see if I can quote the text again where did it
go um this immersion this this meditation as it deepens is peaceful and
tranquil and unified and is not held in place by forceful suppression and this
is the message today that this Tranquility the unification of mind the
collectedness of mind that develops in the meditation isn't a result of force
but rather of letting go and have sort of roughly three things
that come up for me as I as I thought about this this morning with my cup of coffee
one is that for many of us gathered here uh how we got here how we got where we
did in life our professional accomplishments our um successful raising of children or whatever it is um
that we've done usually um resulted from a pattern of Engagement with life that
has in it quite a bit of striving quite a bit of planning quite a bit of um effortful um um setting and attaining of
objectives and goals which is wonderful that the mind can do those things in this practice
there's a way in which we we move into an alternate kind of world where the balance between effort and allowing is
shifted noticeably toward allowing and in this way too we uh in
the meditation and in our practices we're taking it easy we're let letting things arise instead of trying to force
things to arise and you can notice this throughout the meditation practice that um we
provide a certain amount of discipline we come and sit we come and sit together at 7 AM or earlier or later depending on
where you are and in doing that we um exert a certain amount of discipline and
effort to create the conditions for the meditation to deepen but then we let the
medit a deepen on its own and this knowledge comes to us that
oh it's it's in letting go it's an allowing experience to rise and pass
like those tires on a grav road now I'm mixing songs from the 70s and the 90s
the Eagles or Jackson Brown with Lucinda Williams nonetheless we let that sound
of tires on the road come and go instead of driving us crazy and we do that by
allowing it to come up we don't try to keep it from experience and then we let
go so this is this is part of um this is part of um an important part
of the balance of the practice and it's one of the reasons I think that it's so useful to bring attention again and
again to bodily um Sensations particularly that of breathing in which
the balance between effort and allowing is there and is effortless and every
time we make contact with the breathing it's true of other bodily experience too sounds
coming and going in our in our environment for example that we are
directly in touch with something that is balanced between effort and allowing and as we bring our mind again
and again back in touch with the breathing for example um a little bit of that attitude
if you will of the breath rubs off on the mind oh the mind can enjoy finding
this place of rest in a balance of efforting and allowing you know I put a
little effort in here to gently unhurriedly tug attention back to the breath and then I let
go also I allow that experience to arise to be known okay okay the mind's off
planning there's some awareness that oh okay there's that happening I bring a exert I drop in a little bit of effort
and discipline to reenter open back up maybe if things are very tight to the Here and
Now And so there's this constant balance of eorting and allowing efforting by the
way which is probably not English is one of Gill's words and so I love it
efforting and allowing um just in case people wondered where that was coming from balancing
efforting and allowing and it's there in the breath we don't have to make it up we don't have to force it we don't have
to create it we don't have to renew it all we do is connect with the breathing where it's already happening it's
already part of our experience what we're doing is paying attention oh
there's balance here there's balance here and with with time in the mind
enjoys resting in this balance so this knowledge arises for us this
fourth knowledge ah resting here um the Mind enjoys this place of
balance between effort and allowing between efforting and letting
go so that's the first thing I might say um the second thing is this idea of No
Force um I think one way
to just just know this is that it's not at all uncommon I think it's probably
Universal particularly at the beginning of practice that when we become aware that the mind has wandered we we have a
voice inside again it's sometimes that voice of professional accomplishment out there that says dang you know I'm lost I
can't I didn't do it right I need to re you know I need to pull a attention back
to the breath dang it sometimes we use more forceful language again and again
once again and it's very easy for thoughts to come in like oh it's not working today or it's not working ever
or it's not right for me or all those little things that come in and I think
it can be useful to notice that in bringing the Mind back to or attention back to the breathing there can
sometimes be quite a bit of force exerted and that's Force that's we can let go of over time and this takes some
this takes practice to just go oh almost without effort and as you do this more and more those you who've been doing
this a while you know that you can attention can come back to the breathing
almost without effort almost without any trying happening it's just like oh here's yeah
where's Center reentering there's no there's no reason
it should be any different and this is the thing to keep in mind teaching I share that's come to
me in my practice from Gil uh is that nothing is out of place in the practice
in the meditation there's nothing that comes up that doesn't belong here nothing needs to be pushed away nothing
needs to be excluded it's all legitimate part of the practice when we really lean into this
uh we return to the breath with a sense of of coess that's a word I'm making up
actually um of coess it's just like of course of course of course I come back
to center now doesn't uh doesn't mean that anything's gone wrong doesn't mean
that I have done anything wrong doesn't mean that the practice isn't working
it's just uh part of what's here
now the um so this can be to sum up that
second point just that nothing's out of place here in the meditation nothing's
not supposed to arise nothing needs to be pushed down pushed away can all be met very gently with an
open heart oh it's like this now this is arising
now when we do that it's easier to return to Center without
judgment and eventually without much
effort final thing this idea of that this knowledge includes in it this idea
that this meditation that doesn't benefit from forceful action of the
mind is that it that it uh that the meditation is Unified in some way that
it's collected that it brings together and holds
together uh a lovely part of this knowledge that arises can be the sense
that all of us that is all of you all of all of you can be here all of you is
welcome in the meditation it follows on from the second thing nothing needs to be pushed away so
yeah all of the things that come up can be included in this experience no aspect
of ourselves no um no particular course of
thought uh needs to be excluded all of us can be included
I uh have the pleasure of put providing a roof to a close friend Dharma friend
and teaching colleague Diana Clark last night and this morning I want to give her her props for suggesting that not
only can does all of you can be here in the meditation but all of you must be here and this is a really a lovely idea
that one thing we recognize I think and this is part of this fourth knowledge arising is a natural process product of
the meditation deepening is the recognition that all of us has to be included here for the meditation to keep
getting deeper and uh you know maybe without
without any force in that just recognizing that all of it all of it is here all of it has its
place here all of it in a sense must be included and included gently included
without Force so this simple instruction that we
receive and that as teachers we share of returning attention to the breath and the classic formulation is to bring the
be breath back to back sorry bring attention back to the breath when it's w when the mind has wandered away just a
metaphor the mind doesn't go anywhere um but this instruction which
seems so basic I would never say basic it's foundational it has all the
teaching in it that the way we interact with our experience including this
experience of mind the way we interact with it is the practice and we can do so in a way
that's free where we know oh the mind is like this now it's agitated say or it's
at rest we know that and as we become more familiar with that we recognize
that the mind has a preference for ease and as we notice that we strengthen that
propensity we create a momentum in that direction toward
Freedom so to return attention to the breath
when the mind has wandered how we do it is critically important and with time you'll notice
you don't have to do very much just notice that when it's done with ease which will happen by itself sometimes
it's better it's Freer it's more supportive of practice it results in a
deeper meditation so once again I see we're over time and
I could go on and on but I won't I'll close with thanking you uh acknowledging
the presence of this large community of several hundred people sitting together supporting one another's
practice and uh again I encourage you to share the Buddhist smile today as it comes to you from the meditation as it
arises naturally as a as a beneficial byproduct beneficial side effect of the
meditation practice to share um with others thank you and see you
tomorrow