hello everyone and welcome to this meditation and what I've been doing this
week is uh offering some meditation some guided
meditation uh around some of the very basic topics of
um uh inside meditation the way we teach it here at IMC breath body emotions
today on thinking but doing so in a way that um then uh creates a reference
point or a support for understanding the four noble
truths so mindfulness of the body is a powerful support for understanding Dua
the first Noble Truth of suffering and um mindfulness
of of uh emotions is a useful reference point for understanding the cause of
suffering and today I'm going to do a mindfulness of thinking as a reference point to the cessation of
suffering so one of the powerful things in meditation is to understand the
difference between discursive thinking and a quieter more deeper more softer
gentler way of thinking which does not involve conversations
stories um um projections of imaginary Futures uh doesn't involve movies in the
head or great visions of things to come or things past living in memories
there's a simpler thinking that uh has to do with just here and now recognizing
what's happening uh little bit giving ourselves very
simple meditation instructions with what is happening so we're thinking a lot
about the past memories to very gently and quietly have use those thoughts that
bring you into the Present Moment by recognizing oh these are memory thoughts
and I'm very interested them I'm fascinated by them or I'm getting angry because of
them so without any more elaboration just very quietly almost as if you're uh
your own best friend who's sitting and just listening to you and um kind of
reporting back what's happening naming what's going on for you so you can see for yourself
better you're the kindest person you know that's kind of sitting with you and just there knowing seeing directly
what's happening now and so thinking about the future all these thoughts of
conversations we have to have quietly say oh now I'm I'm having a conversation
now I'm uh planning what I'm going to say and and that's what's happening in
the present moment and that feels like a lot of tension in my forehead or in my
brain and with that there'll come a time when you can see that discursive
thoughts thinking stops it doesn't have to stop for long
uh we have maybe there's a long runon sentence of what we're telling ourselves something and then there's a period And
there's a pause there's a cessation an ending before there's a new
beginning and to start seeing the ending the stopping the
pausing in between these discursive thinking conversational thinking uh that
we can have in the mind the story-making mind and to feel and sense the end of
the story The End end of the conversation not because the partner has
ended because it's all in our own mind and so to uh to see it's possible for a few
moments to dwell to abide Here and Now breathing
attentive from attending from some deeper place inside attending with
gentle thoughts that keep you in the present that are about the the present the kind of gentle thoughts about what's
happening now that encourages calming down that have a calming effect that
slows the discursive thinking down and so that you see that the continual there's the
continu the continuity the continuation ongoing stream of story
making that we can live in doesn't have to be
continuous and therefore the impact the influence the
conditioning the emotional quality of that thinking doesn't have to keep
churning our hearts there can be a pause there can be a
stopping and to begin appreciating valuing that stopping that pause that
sensation however brief it might be we often Overlook it because we're so
interested in what we're thinking about we're so racing ahead the like a like
the classic ancient uh metaphor of a monkey that swings from Branch to branch
that as soon as it's grab one branch it's already reaching for the
next and before letting go we're already reaching for the next branch and so there's no pause no stop
so taking a meditation posture
and gently closing the
eyes and take a few moments to be here and now in a definitive way so there's
no question that you're here and now and
maybe that can be done with the support of your body taking some long deep
breaths really feeling your body from the inside out as you breathe
in and then settling relaxing letting
go as you
exhale for
taking some more deep breaths and maybe pausing and [Music]
holding the at the very top of the inhale or the end of the
exhale just very briefly to see if they're in the holding
the breath not breathing that there actually can be some
deeper connection to the body stepping out of the stories of the
Mind a deeper relaxation and then allowing the exhale
allowing the inhale and that pause might be just two
seconds
letting breathing return to normal and for three or four
breaths relax the body as you exhale e
for three or four breaths on the exhale relax the heart the heart
center softening in the heart
and for three or four breaths relaxing softening
calming the thinking mind
and then if it's comfortable for you to Center
yourself on the body breathing wherever it's easiest or most
enjoyable to feel the body breathing in the belly the chest or the
nose
as you feel the body breathing
gently lightly feel that transition from
breathing in to breathing out that moment or
two as breathing shifts
let the thinking mind become quieter so you can sense and feel the
end of the inhale and beginning of the
exhale and then do the same for the between the exhale and the inhale
feeling the end of the exhale how there's a switch
over to the beginning of the inhale
and as you continue breathing when you get to the top of the
inhale notice if your mind has been getting has
gotten involved in discursive
thinking and if it has relax soften let go as you exhale
with the exhale let there be a pause in this story making
mind the mind that has conversations or lives in memories or Futures fantasy
e
at the end of the exhale let there be a pause in thinking
and for the moment or two that it pauses appreciate the
quiet appreciate what has become
still
e
e e
feel just beyond the edges of your thinking
whatever you're thinking doesn't fill the
universe there's a before those thoughts there's an after those
thoughts and there's all the space in the universe beyond the edges of your
thoughts and realizing
that maybe you can have the pause
cuse of your discursive
thinking and appreciate how that part of the mind has become
quiet
for e
we can have a invaluable life
without the dominance of discursive
thinking there can be quieter softer gentler ways of thinking about
the
present that reassures the
mind so the mind the thinking mind the discursive
mind can become quieter
and from time to
time we can be aware of the end of
Stories the end of discursive thinking
for
e e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate
how the ending of story making ending of the continuity
of conversations commentary judgments about
things creates more space for calm for
peace for us to be able to hear a quieter voice
within the quiet voice of
kindness of care of
love that's drown out if we keep living in stories and commentary and
anxious
Futures the end of Storytelling can be the
beginning of deeper
wisdom may it be that as as we go into our life on this
day that we can listen to others more deeply attend and care for others more
fully if we don't see the world and see others through the filter of our story
making mind the filter of living still living
in the memories and or the
projections where the quieting of the discursive mind let us be present for the world in
a way that brings kindness and friendliness to all
beings may all beings be happy
may all
beings be peaceful may all
beings be safe and may all beings be free
[Music]
[Music] thank
you e
hello and welcome to this this fourth talk on the four noble truths and the general
title of this Aries is um the end of suffering and that's the purpose of the
for Noble Truth teachings is that the optional emotional pain that we feel the
emotional pain that arises because somehow there's a
reactivity inside of us somehow there's craving there's a
compulsion attachment that we engage in and the Very attachment itself is
painful and it uh leads to a Cascade of other pains that come when we're holding
on tight to something and leads to disappointment and fear
and um anger and and uh it contributes to the creation of of um an edifice of
abstract ideas of who we are and who we think we should be it's part of our
identity is uh the result of our stories we tell about ourselves and stories that
our society tells about what it means to be a human being or it says who we
are so the first Noble Truth has a lot to do with the accumulation the Gathering Together of all the different
attachments and
conceivable we could be something else than than someone who you know than being the suffering that we
have but in fact the second Noble Truth says that the the Tangled ball of thread
is uh is Tangled is been become Tangled by the force of of
craving other place the Buddha talks about clinging and craving being the
seamstress that sews together this edifice this tapestry of attachments
that uh often is the we're a walking manifestation of and so to begin getting our handle on
this idea of of uh attachment craving clinging compulsion and one of the place to see
it is in the story making mind the discursive mind there uh it can be quite
phenomenal the spinning of the Mind the the Jing the moving on and on on and on
thinking about something and um even if you're successful at letting go and
stopping it just comes right back just there to spin out stories and some people have no trouble
with the thinking mind and the discursive mind because it's they they just believe it they invested in it they
think that that's who they are and so even though a thinking mind
might be the discursive mind might be painful they just go along with it because it has Authority if if we think
it we should believe it and um if we think it then it says something about me
that who I am whatever there's a way strong attachment to discursive thoughts
strong attachment to stories strong identification and sense of self that gets built on uh the domain of
discursive conversational uh thoughts that we have commentary that we have uh
the world of judgments and judgments and and about the world around us and of
ourselves can all too easily belong to that discursive mind that's spinning and
churning and jumping from one branch to the other and uh never letting up and so
the continuity of thinking can just give a sense that we're always supposed to be doing this is what life
is and um but as we get a handle on craving and clinging and attachment and
they begin to soften as we meditate and relax more deeply there are uh Wellsprings inside of
deeper sources of understanding even of ways of thinking that are not discursive
thinking it's not uh running along telling stories or rehearsing stories or
repeating stories of the past and um and one of the remarkable
things that can happen is is that um is a uh the discursive mind becomes quiet
and still and it can be such a relief it can be such a let it a relief and to have
that release and that's why some people distract themselves from their discursive thinking Mind by doing
something that's very distracting uh you know uh reading a book or watching a movie or going for a
walk in a park or uh doing some kind of exercise that kind of uh or going to
sleep because it stops this endless turning of the mind that is not
emotional free it carries a lot of emotional baggage and uh it's almost
like we're creating an atmosphere through uh discursive thinking that then that atmosphere comes back and has a
profound effect on us it can be a create a conditioning for
ourselves and and so to have that become quiet can be such a relief and it's very important not to
think that meditation is about quieting every thinking there is very subtle
quieter thinking uh more like thoughts rather than continuous thinking there's
very quiet quiet thoughts about the present moment that can be come out of
wisdom can come out out of kindness can come out of a gentleness or sensitivity to what's happening that's very simp
simple and doesn't carry the veilance of attachment doesn't carry the the weight
of attachment of clinging of compulsion it just there softly
lightly and we can see that the discursive thoughts and the emotions
that go along with them maybe have stopped for a well have paused and so the second noal Truth uh is the is the
sensation of suffering uh which can happen on many different levels but uh maybe for today the
accessible level I wanted to emphasize is the cessation of discursive thoughts
the ending of it the pause the between one paragraph of thinking we do and then before the next
paragraph begins when there's a s put a sentence and end of a s of a sentence in the mind
um uh take a break with a movie you're looking at in the mind and cause and
appreciate the think the Quiet Mind the more peaceful mind and appreciate the
softer quieter ways of thinking that maybe arise out of wisdom out of
kindness that are drowned out by the loudness of discursive thoughts and uh
that go on and on and so to have that stop the discursive thinking a sensation of it so
we can appreciate something much more deeper and more intimate and more integral to what's happening here um
deeper reservoirs of of Peace deeper reservoirs of a quiet still Place
reservoirs of kindness and love generosity and uh and then we start
seeing at some point that the suffering that came with discursive thinking
begins to Abate as well and various kinds of suffering and stress distress
that we experience we notice that they stop and anytime we notice some kind
of uh distress anguish uh
stress emotional pain emotional discomfort that has stopped that's an
invaluable thing to notice and then the bumper sticker today would be I stop for
stopping I stop for the stop so when you when you've noticed
that something that was troubling you some mental state was troubling you is no longer there for whatever reason
don't just go on to the next thing to do stop yourself and register that take it in
feel the sensation of suffering because it's teaching a very important lesson and eventually the
lesson is that's uh that the uh that that there is optional emotional
pain that we contribute to and that that can
stop that can cease that can come to an end that's the good news so Buddhism it
is possible the emotional pain that might remain then is not so difficult there's
a whole different relationship to it it's part of the richness of life it's part of where compassion might arise or
knowledge and wisdom might arise um and uh when there's no conceit no identity
that that uh no tangle of of a ball of thread in which it gets
Tangled Up in uh s it's very simple emotional pain that we might still
experience the Heartbreak in the world uh becomes very very simple and
does not become a burden rather it becomes a source of
meaning providing meaning meaning of being of have compassion of care of
kindness of living a different way in this world that uh where we're here to
support each other and to care for ourselves so the this third Noble Truth
the sensation of suffering is a truth that it is
possible and and it's not an All or Nothing kind
of thing that we can expect to happen today or tomorrow but it's a step by step gradual beginning to appreciate the
small Sensations and I want to emphasize today is the the quieting the stopping of
discursive thinking which is such a troublemaker for us be
careful that you don't invest too much important in the story making
mind that you don't give it too much authority over you because the optional
suffering that we can experience around our stories has a lot to do by the amount of
authority we give those tho we Grant those stories how much we invest
ourselves in those stories and how much we identify or our sense of identity
gets tangled up in those stories be careful with those and one way to be
careful is to begin noticing and seeing all the little places in the day where
the story making mind stops for whatever reason and if they stop pause for a
little bit even for a few seconds remember the bumper sticker I stop for
stopping and uh then there pause even more to take it in feel the goodness of that and see if
that pausing of stories can connect you something deeper inside a deeper wisdom
deeper love deeper Peace So the cessation
of suffering the third Noble Truth and the way
to develop that sensation and enrich it and expand it into our life so it be can
become fully realized is from what the Buddha call
what the Buddha calls the fourth Noble Truth which will be the topic for
tomorrow so thank you very much and um
may you enjoy Sensations