hi welcome so nice to be here with you all and out there on
YouTube i'm Tanya Weiser see some of you i've seen some of you but um not not
maybe not all of you so nice to meet you i am um a teacher trained under Gil and
Andrea Fella i teach here on Thursday nights and in the eight-fold path program so come on by Thursday night if
you're ever in the mood for um coming doing dharma and then meeting
in small groups and talking about the dharma topic that's sort of the the unique feature of Thursday
nights it's a nice place to connect with SA so I'm
um my what's on my heart or in my mind for talking about tonight is kind of
actually uh this exploring and discussing this idea of the middle way
the teaching of the Buddha on the middle way and um for me maybe one of the
key ways of describing
being on this middle path is being available being available to experience
and respond to life in a particular kind of
way and um it's a there's a receptivity
that we we cultivate in our practice and an
embodiment you know the Buddha directed us to pay attention to our direct felt
experience and then to have these you know co-guiding wings of wisdom and
compassion there and available all helping us sort of find this this middle
way and I would also venture to describe it in a incomplete way but in in my way
of also this middle way between doing and
non-doing you know something that's not exactly doing and certainly not exactly
non-doing so this word available maybe will come up frequently as I explore my
reflections with you and I I you know th this
understanding or this um coming to the this connection with this idea of a
middle way was the pivotal insight that the Buddha had that actually led to his
liberation you know to his complete freedom and you know as many of you
probably know the story goes that you know he started his life in you know
with a lot of luxury a lot of indulgence sensual pleasures and you know sort of a
protected lifestyle and then um he left his home
and his family to pursue freedom he wanted to have a different kind of
experience of life and his first teachers were teachers who taught um
concentration practices these u very refined states
mind states can be quite pleasant and beautiful abidings but what the Buddha
found over time was he could master these quite easily
um and was soon asked to be a teacher of of the the practice that he was being
taught but that they didn't bring him any true freedom there was no lasting
impact of the experience so then he turned toward complete renunciation and
aseticism and ex and pursued extreme restriction in his life and you know
there's this story that he got down to eating one grain of rice a day so and sleeping on you know nails
and all kinds of things that they practice to try and learn how to endure
pain and um to not indulge oneself and any sensual pleasures
so this this um insight into this middle way
um actually occurred as he was nearly dying on the side of this you know river
bank I think he was on and some um person discovered him there and uh
offered him some food and so the Buddha was reflecting on
you know all the striving he'd done in both directions of his life and he thought you know this is the
quote from Majima 36 the suta where he's reflecting on this experience and this
understanding of a middle way and it says you know the Buddha I thought whatever recluses or brahinss in the
past have experienced painful racking piercing feelings due to exertion this
is the utmost you know what he was he was going through but with this racking
practice of austerities I have not attained any distinction with higher
knowledge and vision i have not attained any distinction with higher
vision and and and knowing and so you know this was a
pretty major reflection for him to have and it said that his companions who had
been practicing austerities with him saw him eat and and thought "Oh he's given
up what a waste we're not going to follow or practice with him anymore." And they sort of
left and so here he was you know on his own um and choosing essentially to live
again right choosing to eat so that he could survive and he remembered he had a
memory of his of a childhood experience and this
memory was what sort of cracked open this idea of another way forward
and it was um a memory that I'll embellish with my own associations you know with with the
experience in the simple way in the suta it's described as him sitting on the
side of a field where his father was either involved with plowing or a ritual
of plowing and he was set under a rose apple tree so he was off on the side and
watching and and young right and so here's where I'll embellish
because let's imagine for a minute the scene being a young child with you're
you know been brought to this place by your parent and you've been sat down in
this spot i imagine with a blanket i imagine you know with water or whatever he
needed as you might as a parent imagine setting your child down and setting them up and saying "Okay you know just
relax." And he's under the shade of a tree and it's a rose apple tree so you
know maybe it was blooming and it smelt nice or there were apples who knows but he's I'm I'm imagining he's
quite comfortable quite content and his f he can see his dad so he's like "Okay
I'm I'm okay." And his dad is busy and doing this plowing thing or ritual we
don't know exactly what way he was involved in this and he recalls the experience of
being there and um he describes it in terms
that are of it being radiant of um sort of this pleasant
abiding he actually describes it as a very pleasurable
experience but it wasn't an experience where he was actively generating or
creating pleasure right he was simply
available a a a present relaxed open
content and able to sort of establish essentially what we would
probably call the first Janna of of concentration it's this mind that is
connected and clear about what's happening we experience pleasure in our
body some sense of joy or um this this pleasant feeling of aliveness I might
describe it as feeling the vitality the energy of life in your
body and he was just abiding in this pleasant way so just taking a minute to
imagine this sort of simple setting and this feeling of contentment
that maybe the sun is warm you know this just I don't you don't need to go anywhere he doesn't
need to do anything and he can just sort of attend you know how when you're you
have something like your breath you're watching or your father that's plowing that has some sort of maybe routine or
repetition to it right as I imagine plowing would have and just relaxes into
this pleasant abiding and
so he he actually thought to himself he realized let me get a
drink ah this actually could be the path to
awakening a whole different idea not pursuing this intense experience and not
pursuing intense pain and and denial and in that moment he stopped all
the striving he bathed he ate he let go of
the extreme renunciation he was engaged in and he began down this path of the
middle way and so the Buddha you know in the
teachings you know sometimes we feel like we're not supposed to have pleasure or enjoy things but in fact it's it's
actually important for us to open to this kind of well-being that happens
that has its own natural arising it's not this hedonistic thing that we're chasing and creating and trying to kind
of amplify but rather this open receptive experience of allowing
ourselves to connect with life in the
moment and how it feels in the body letting ourselves rest in these
ways so there's this is maybe again this idea of this not doing and not non-doing
but rather this receptivity this availability maybe even taking a moment
right now to turn your awareness
inward and just see what happens to open up to be a available to
experience whatever sensations of uplift or life or energy or the breath you can
receive right here can you touch into an experience that
feels receptive
available contented is it enough can it be enough to open up in
this way
so just noting what you're able to be aware of and whatever it is being contented enough with
it but could you touch into the experience of being here could you open
yourself up to being available to feeling your breath feeling the life moving through
you
so this idea of being available for life being available to
ourselves to our needs to kind of responding to what's going
on to me is a pretty profound thing
not grabbing at things and not pushing away not spacing out but rather being present and available so this middle way
right
and maybe another word I could use is this kind of intimacy a willingness to be touched by
what's happening in the moment touched by the sensations touched by the impact
of a thought or an experience available you know here
so another thing that I explore when I'm thinking about how do I hold this because it's not in the in the teachings
that we're we're supposed to become flaccid and non-engaged in our lives
right and yet there's also teachings that say just let things be the way they are so I think one thing that is helpful
for me when I think about you know this way of be be something between doing and
non-doing is I think about wise intention wise intention includes the renunciation
of clinging the renunciation of wanting you
know to kind of get this and that and get rid of this and
that and non-ill will is the second part of
wise intention which has to do with cultivating or kind of being in a mind
state that has this wish for well-being for everyone what's called loving
kindness and a sense of caring about the suffering and a mind that is free from
hatred and anger so maybe this non-doing doing of
non-illwill is a real simple noting and not feeding hatred and
anger and instead being available with a heart that is compassionate and with
well-wishes and then this third component of wise intention is
non-harming so this is you know not wanting to harm ourselves others or both
and maybe this is the non-doing or the doing the non-doing doing of
non-harming is just essentially not doing actions that cause harm so there's
a doing in that and it's a non-doing in that
so this Buddha's moment of the under the rose apple tree
moment this kind of natural state that arises also let's put that in
perspective this is something that naturally arose right when when and and
states of concentration will naturally arise when we are present for our
experience in a particular doing non-doing way
And you know this is what helped him in his practice and you know at some point
in my own practice I recognized I had experiences in my
childhood too that helped me when I was having difficulty on a on the
cushion when I was struggling on a retreat and I remembered in my childhood
it was an experiences of going on a boat with my father when
he was fishing now I didn't fish you know but I would go on the boat
with him and I would just lay on the seat and I would just be listening to
the sounds and feeling the rocking of the boat and the sun and I would do it for
hours just hours and I didn't wasn't a you know anxious to get back or to do
anything i was just in this state that reminds me of the Buddha you know what he was doing
sitting you know under the rose apple tree and that that was so helpful for me
to connect with my own memory and so I wonder you know I just
would invite you to think about what maybe you too have had some moments that
naturally arose in your life that were like this where you were just resting down
resting back and available that you naturally accessed this sort of quality of
being quality of presence
yeah so you know we maybe you could nod your heads can
you think of experiences maybe even on a yoga mat in shasana at the end of a practice you know right have you
experienced just a taste maybe or Yeah and so these these reme memberings these
moments these experiences can be very supportive when we're sitting in
meditation to recall and and they kind of just remind the mind we know how the mind knows
how can remind us of that feeling and that can help us also access that state
potentially at various times or at least know what's possible so another part that's um
important when we think about this is obviously well what gets in the way why doesn't this happen for
us more often it's certainly possible we're all nodding our heads you know to
some extent or another and so you know actually one of the things that the Buddha really talked
about were the five hindrances that obstruct this kind of experience so the five hindrances are
sensual desire so this really wanting more pleasure ill will hatred right um
sloth and torper so being so sleepy or so low in energy one isn't really
mentally available you could say that when we have a lot of strong sensual desire we
aren't really available either you know how that feeling is when I got to have
this and we're consumed with trying to get or create or manifest something so
we it's hard to be available if somebody walks up and wants to talk to us we're sort of like you got to wait
and the same with ill will right when we're feeling a lot of hostility it's pretty hard to stop and
listen pretty hard to be receptive to feedback or to even you know even
pausing to pick up something if you drop it you know just something even so simple we can be so
consumed and then the fourth is restlessness and remorse so this energy
of kind of a churning kind of energy an inability to settle in the body and in
the mind again how available can we be
to life when we're really consumed by these very common you know hindrances
that arise for all of us and the last is doubt when we're questioning the
teaching when we're questioning our practice or capacity it's pretty hard to show up for
you know the breath when we're consumed with doubt
and so one of the the simileies that the Buddha uses to describe these hindrances
and the impact that they have is he talks about a river and the flow of water and so for
me I I like this simile this flow of water which actually feels very similar
to the state of being really open and relaxed and available to life to me it
feels like I am there's not this caughtness stuckness and there's this
flow with the experience and the sensations and the things that are going on and so that when this there can be
this momentum that starts to you know go with this flow and maybe simply thinking
about you know riding a raft in a a a river and how you can be carried and and
it can flow nicely or you can find yourself drifting off
getting lost in the swirls and the eddies and you know sort of find the current slacks too much and you're not
really moving or you start to hit the bottom of the river and and then this
flow is interrupted and in a similar way the Buddha is describing the flow of our
practice um as a flow of the river that when
there's these outlets you know like when they open dams for example or there's
all these tributaries that are pulling water off of the river that they disrupt
that energetic flow is going with this
con you know kind of capacity of the mind to consolidate and
concentrate and so this is what he compared the hindrances to is these
outflows that they start to siphon off what really awareness right our capacity
to be available with awareness they siphon off our minds that can imagine
and storytell and that um you know gets caught in thinking and that
energy affects the flow and so just even in my meditation tonight at one
point you know I was sort of thinking a little bit about the talk you know and
oh this or that and then I sort of oh recognized I was kind of in this
thinking space and not just available and present and as my awareness returned
to just being with my you know flow of
sensations there was actually a corresponding increase in energy in my
body felt there was an uplift of energy for me this is like oh this is getting
back into the flow the present moment experience you know the mind is
reconnected with being here being here being
here and in um one of the other sutras the Buddha describes and um the mind
when the mind is free from the five hindrances it becomes pliable malleable
and luminous and this becomes the ground for the arising of true knowledge and
insight so it's sort of like yeah you know like
this feeling of flow this feeling of collectedness this feeling of of
availability there is this malleability there is this ability to to adapt and
sort of shift with things and maybe there's this sense of
luminosity or this clarity or maybe some people use the word sparkle or the light
right this sort of You know how if you're just sitting outside and you are
really there things can seem so clear the seeing is so defined the
colors are so vibrant you know this what is as we
allow more of our awareness to just be here our senses open up they can take in
more sound more sight more smell more sensations and this adds to this feeling
of aliveness in my experience and Ajan Amo he's one of the
poly you know he's a a monk and a teacher and a writer and a translator
and and he wrote the way beyond the hindrances is not through
suppression but through befriending through befriending well
what do friends do what do friends do a a good spiritual
friend how do they support you when you're
suffering anybody want to They listen they listen they They companion
us right they They're there so wow here
again something between doing and non-doing something about being
available befriending being available so we it is a a way of responding to the
hindrances but it's it's not what you know this idea of I got to go get rid of
them but it's also not this idea of I just have to sit back and do
nothing because it it they deserve and require some presence some
response and so how do we befriend them how do we start to be present in a way
with them so that they stop siphoning off our attention and
energy so another really important part of this is this idea of
embodiment right to to be in our bodies here's a quote or a thought we're not
heads on sticks you know we are sensing feeling bodies and this practice is not just
about working with our thoughts it is actually about how we live and how we
are and connected to our body and our mindfulness and mindfulness of the body is the one thing the Buddha said you
have to practice it is foundational for
us and Terra Brock writes "Embodied presence is the ground of loving the
very essence of wisdom and
compassion so when we're in the body and we're con connected to the body we're connected to what's
real we're connected to nowness
and it could be nowness of fear and it could be nowness of love and any of it
can all help us be present and awake and
available so in conclusion I just want to say this
middle way is you know not there's no set perfect
balance the river is always changing conditions are always
changing it's about staying with what's happening and skillfully being with
it not non-doing and not overdoing you know not leaning too far
one way or the other or when we do we recognize that we come back into a more balanced place and sometimes when the
current's really pushing this way maybe we have to lean hard the other way you know and then it'll change and if we
keep leaning hard the other way we're just going to fall in right so it's this adaptability this flow this staying
connected and available and embodied right
so um there's a person Winston Higgins who says the middle way is not a line
but a path not a point of perfect balance but a way of walking with care with
curiosity and with kindness
so may we walk this way together with some care with curiosity
with presence and connection to our experience remember to
befriend each other and our hindrances and ourselves along the
way so with that I'll pause and just see if there's any response any comments any
questions let's get you the microphone
like this it's okay um when you were talking about befriending Yeah i was
thinking of the roomie poem called the guest house where he talks about welcome all of your
feelings welcome them as bring them in as welcome guests and have tea with them
yeah so that's about welcoming yes that's a beautiful poem i use I
reference and think about that one quite a bit actually yes i had one more thought when you were talking uh in the
beginning about um being present i was thinking how how much that
requires a certain equinimity to be able to do that to to be present
in the way you were available was the word you used yeah so being available
means you have to be economous i think that goes together yeah and maybe
there's I have sometimes have this image of you know um outrigger canoes you know what an outrigger canoe
is so it's this big canoe but they have these two um arms and then these
supporting beams in the water and I like to think about this as compassion and wisdom and they they really help
stabilize us right and and that's equinimity which is the stabilizing you
know and is embodied wisdom and compassion so that we can kind of all
right we're in the ride thank you for sharing those yeah
great
thank you so much thank you so is Yeah
maybe just turn the volume up okay thank you so much for uh sharing the middleway
path i love it they're in the middle of doing and non-doing um so recently I
went to I joined the one of the retreat in IRC the 20s and 30s one or several
beautiful beautiful yeah it was very nice experience it was my first retreat
ah great yeah so um I I had great I mean it was challenging but also had great
experience there i felt a lot um my question is like when I come back I felt
the integration process yeah i mean related to what also what you talk the integration process was super hard i
feel like my integration was super slow it took me literally two weeks to get back even though the retreat was only
one week yeah um yeah on my second day that I came back so there was a lake by
my home usually I really love looking at water i love water like looking at water
make me feel peace all kinds of water lake river sea ocean
usually I go to the lake I see the see the water make me feel so peace and the second day when I came back to the lake
I was like oh my god I can't look at this lake it's it's it's it's too much information my mom's like "Where is the
information?" I'm like "It's too much information you can't look at the like." Anyway I took several
days off from the work before I go back to a work but still when I go back to
work um also take it easy but I still I found myself super sensitive to anything any
information the brain is literally shut down yeah well it gets it it you know that is
the point of retreat in part is we get increasingly sensitive
uhhuh increasingly sensitive and the let me you know I don't know if you've heard
about the simileies of water used for the hindrances but it's um
water to me is a metaphor that is used to describe the mind and the mind that
is clear and the mind that has hindrances in it and so the mind that is
calm and clear is like you know a bo bowl of water body of water that you
could look in and clearly see your reflection that there's enough you know
sort of the stability and capacity to see clearly what you know yourself or
what your mind or what's going on but a mind affected by the hindrance is like when you get off
retreat it can feel like it is there's just um this
overwhelm and so it could feel like restlessness and you know sort of remorse and this feeling of like the
water is completely stirred up you can't see your reflection it's like wind
blowing on the water and all the waves and so in a way looking at the water and
and having difficulty maybe it was just sort of reflecting back to you um how jumbled up
the mind felt the other water similes are for desire it's like the water is
rosecoled and so you can't see clearly hint the um ill will is like boiling hot
water sloth and torper is like water filled with um slime and and moss and
doubt is like the water that is muddy and so it's like you know this beautiful
connection you have with the dharma here I think and and noticing in a way you're
seeing your own mind you're seeing the water and you're noticing your own mind's reaction to sort of life and all
the stuff that's happening around you that's just my offering but it takes
time does take time to learn how to practice re-entry
yeah um so I was well so when I reentered to my own life
um because I get so sensitive when I work
and like I notice my body tense up when I'm thinking right when I'm con I
noticed it immediately tense up like the body get heat when I think yes um which
is good because I could notice this yes but on the other side I do need to think
you know so I I felt there is a conflict between
this practice and the using it in my normal life and I believe it should be
able to help me with my normal life but I'm so confused by this conflict and I
was because of this confusion I feel like really need some teachers guidance on this
yeah yeah absolutely it's hard to find this kind of balance and you
know and it's hard to and to notice maybe even like your h the hindered
reaction to the mind and the body's um
response to being back in busy life where you're thinking you know you you're having what
you might call a double hindrance attack perhaps you know where your mind is getting all stirred up your body is
impacted you're feeling the heat and then you don't like it my guess is you don't have like it so you have you know
restlessness and worry and then you have the hindrance added of ill will on top of it not liking
and so you know what we start to learn how to do over time is okay this is the
impact of course I got so settled and so attuned and now I'm noticing all these things I don't normally notice can I
just befriend my experience and not add to the difficulty by wishing it were
different or wanting to get through it or you know sort of struggling with it or doubting your practice you know um
afterwards and trust that over time you will find your way to be with
it all and you know we can't you're right we're we're h
householders you we have the choice we could go become monks or nuns and
renounce our daily lives but we don't have to we can live in this world and
find find our way yeah i think my hope I
always think and believe mindfulness should be helping with our life in every
single aspect and yeah that's the whole I mean it
is designed in that way it it works in that way it does yeah yeah yeah it does
yeah thank you thank you
any other uh reflections additions maybe things people want feel like we're left
out or you know you not sure exactly about you know what I was suggesting or
yeah great right
over thank you for your talk um I haven't heard previously about the
I think interplay between compassion and wisdom uhhuh and um I spend a fair
amount of time uh attending to compassion and I'm just um trying to integrate the
addition of wisdom and one wondering if you have more words to say about that imagine it's a huge topic but yeah so
I'll try and be super simple about it first that it's often called the wings
the two wings of awakening that to fly to sail we need both the wisdom and
the [Music] compassion and the the thing about
wisdom in the dharma is that it's not it's the wisdom
that we earn through direct experience
it's the wisdom that took you to the practice of compassion it's the wisdom that in you
that knew this was harming i'm harming myself i'm harming others i don't want
to do that anymore it's that kind of wisdom and that kind of wisdom that you
know requires direct engagement with the teachings of the
Buddha and then noticing what is revealed
it's that kind of wisdom
yeah I think I I hear you thank you yeah so it it's good to
um Yeah it's good to sort of start to maybe recognize the wisdom that is operating with you in the compassion
world and and it is good to to be attuning to the
balance because it is you know as in all things it is easy to go too far one way
or the other too much wisdom and it's too too harsh and cold and you know
brittle too much compassion and it's soft and mushy and we get lost
so kind of needing this Goldilocks porridge Goldilocks bed this
sort of something in the middle thank you for your
question so it's 8:28 i think it's time to end right yeah
so thank you all and um may you you know may you walk out feeling available
to the night air to whatever next happens whoever
next you encounter whatever next emotion or thought arises may you find yourself
available present and you know in this flow in
this flow with the guardians of compassion and wisdom thank you very much