hello friends hello and welcome to the 7
a.m or whatever your time zone might be of
meditation um lovely to join you oh
there bells maybe there so I am Nikki Mrigapori i'm
joining you from from uh Tuskanyany uh teaching the series on SA on
community on kalanamita basically the relational aspect of the
practice and it's been a delight to uh to join you from the other side of the
pond for actually some of you are on this side of the pond I see you're saying hello from various places in the
world including Europe So very sweet very sweet to be together so can't believe it's already
Thursday uh it's the fourth day of our practice together and
um we've been uh covering discussing the various aspects of
kalana beautiful friendship uh the different ways of uh being a good friend
how can we be a good friend and recognize good friendships uh instead of superficial friendships
and and today uh I'd like to um
transition to uh both doing a practice and also later speaking about um
building bonds through the four means of embracing others from the angutaranaya
432 and um this is from the sanaha suta
which means son means together ga means to hold to gather to grasp which
basically literally means to gather together to support one another to embrace one another what are the ways
to support include embrace care for gather protect um there are different
meanings that we can we can bring here and these four ways I'll say them because I'll bring them into the
meditation these four ways that are mentioned in
this saha suta which by the way sounds like sa right sauta but sahasuta ways to
to create social cohesion these principles these grounds for social
cohesion and relational harmony
are dana generosity giving pavaja kind speech affectionate
speech aacharia beneficial action
service and samaata sama ma nata which is
impartiality equal equality treating others fairly without bias um and in a
humble in a fair equitable way as as equals so so these are the four
principles that um in in this suta that
the Buddha talks about how they they create they they are the principles for
creating social cohesion harmony relational harmony so in the in the guided meditation I'd
like to invite us after we get settled of course with our bodies uh into a
sense of presence um I'll invite this feeling into each of
these one by one as a member of the community us as a
kalyanita as how in my heart can I tune into these frequencies as if you know
these old radios they had they had dials and and and how can I tune into this frequency
that is that is present in my heart to make it more audible to make the song of
generosity more audible the the song of of kind speech more audible etc etc so
this is this is the invitation for this morning this afternoon whatever your
time zone is so with that in mind let's uh let's begin let's let's
settle let's settle and arrive let's settle and
arrive in our
bodies arriving arriving
every moment a new
arrival and we let go of whatever was happening
before the thoughts
concerns plans all of that can we set it down can we
release just for the period of this practice giving our hearts
fully giving our hearts fully
Settling relaxing the body softening the body relaxing the
mind relaxing the body the mind dependent on the body the body dependent
on the [Music] mind relaxing our heart
whatever is arising in this moment softening allowing it to be just
as it
is
feeling the body in the seated position or lying down whatever posture you have
in this moment turning awareness inward not
outward but inward as if you're greeting greeting yourself
greeting this body limb by
limb how are my feet hello feet greeting feeling
receiving can there be a sense of generosity with the body
kind speech with the body even if there is pain discomfort
presence can't there be still generosity kindness evenness of
heart the feet with the [Music] ankles receiving the sensations of the
knees kindly the sitbones inviting them to
soften to offer their weight to the earth
inviting our chest to open to
relax our heart to put down its weight just for a moment to
release dear heart it's
okay our neck and shoulders to relax to put down the proverbial weight of the
world just for this little while can pick it all up later just taking
refuge softening our brow especially if it's furoughed
usually greeting softening allowing the breath to move
through settling easing
soothing sensations the inb breath and the
outreath or it's most accessible to be known
and as we're sitting the sense of embodiment feeling
the breath receiving the gift of this breath the
generosity of this lifegiving breath breath we
soften and land into a field of
generosity that has supported us through our life that we've been a part of this
giving and
receiving allowing our heart to feel a little brighter
perhaps recollecting in our heart the sense of a recent act of generosity
we've received not just with money or
resources or things but maybe with time with kindness with a
smile
with someone's
care again not making this into a thinking practice but dropping this reflection into the
heart tuning into this frequency and allowing the
heart to be uplifted
the more we tune into this frequency of generosity the more we see it and the more we act out of it
ourselves perhaps now allowing ourselves to
recollect some act of generosity maybe a kind word a smile a time some time we
spent extra time caring for someone or resources our
material resources stepping out outside of
ourselves allowing our hearts to be uplifted by this act of generosity donna
Any acts of giving or receiving with the generosity of
spirit which can include giving receiving receiving
graciously kindness of speech beneficial
action and an open part receiving others impartially equally or being received
with
openness any of these is enough just sitting tuning into this frequency
allowing your heart to feel bright not making it too
complicated in breath outreath very simple
also to say sometimes when we want to recollect goodness the opposite could
happen all the challenging times or when we fell short might come up it's
okay that can be a a purifying practice bring kindness bring kindness to
yourself if that's happening and by bringing kindness again
you're brightening the heart and mind the more we tune to goodness generosity kindness
etc the more we see it we more act out of
it for the sake of ourselves and
others keep it simple in breath outreath
And there be a sense of gratitude appreciation for the acts of generosity
of spirit openness of heart that this being who is you has
received from another being or has offered to another
being feeling into their appreciation their gratitude their brightness of
heart
we have received and we have given so
much goodness so much goodness
let it imbue your heart space your mind space your
cha your mind heart space
and opening our hearts to the generosity and kindness of
showing up to practice together as a community and
appreciating yourself this being who is me thank you for showing
up for aligning your actions with your intentions for goodness
wholeheartedness cultivation waking up and if judgments are arising oh
you're sleepy you're distracted thank you very much for your opinion dear judgment and let it go it's
okay we don't have to believe every thought we have bringing gratitude appreciation to
ourselves for our own generosity and kindness for the benefit of all
beings may all beings be happy may all beings know their own
goodness engage in generosity of spirit receive generosity of spirit
may all beings be happy may all beings be [Music]
free thank you everyone thank you for your practice
now it's nice to have the church bell and also the song of the
birds as you can hear them in the
background so appreciate sitting with you practicing
together this earth feels like a cozier
place as we come together as we come together in this way this community in
this sa this worldwide sa how beautiful how beautiful it is
so I'll take a pause for the transition
oh I think there was one bell right somebody said no bells for me i thought
there was one bell which hopefully you heard maybe not hopefully there will be more bells later we'll
see i can't control the bells here the church bells they come and they go so
here we go it's like the like the
um Yeah so many conditions in life
so today as we continue as we continue with our series
[Music] um on community on friendship on noble
friendship spiritual friendship kalana on sana really this relational aspect of
the practice which the Buddha has said sana is all of the path it's not just
half of the path it's the entirety of the path is is this friend's spiritual friendship is is support of of
likehearted like-minded likehearted practitioners
so continuing in this theme today I'd like to talk about um what I mentioned a
bit earlier this suta um from the angutra nikaya
432 which is called the
sanahuta sanahuta the
sanahuta excuse me is son again meaning together god to
grasp to hold together literally means gathering together embracing supporting
these are the four means of inclusion embracing supporting care gathering
uh protecting etc and in this um suta the Buddha says
these are the four means by which one sustains and gathers people
together and the saha here refers to the principles
and grounds for social cohesion and relational harmony it's what glues it's
what binds a sana together it's the ethical emotional glue that binds any
group together trust fairness care service it's what binds us together as
humans as communities and the uh different teachers by the way
different translators have have translated these four have given them different uh titles the the phrase in
Pali is Vati and Bikubodi says the four bases of
social solidarity tanisariku says the four grounds for embracing others i like
embracing it's there's a sweetness to it um sometimes in the Mahayana context
this shows up as the four means of gathering and in interpretive one is uh
four ways of creating unity and a less common translation is the four means of
support so just in giving you nuances of these four these four are generosity
donna kind speech a vaja beneficial action service acting
helpfully aiding others supporting others is uh atacharia
atacharia and the fourth one is uh impartiality equality participation
uh the poly word is sama sama which is relating to others out of without pride
or bias being humble being fair being open inclusive
i like to say a little bit about each of these because again so important
communities friendships relationships don't happen out of happen stance they
take deliberate conscious intentional action to to uh foster this this um a
community a sa could be a sa of two sa of three could be a sana of hundreds as
we have here so the first and the foremost as mentioned and also by the
way in the guided meditation I mentioned them briefly and I also mentioned uh
generosity of spirit because in many ways we can think of generosity of spirit
uh really capturing all four of them when there's generosity of spirit there's also generosity in action with
our resources there is um kindness in speech there is acts of service support
and there's also this u seeing others as equal embracing others not with pride or
con you know looking down upon anyone but there's a generosity of spirit has humility as a part of it so I I like
that as a shorthand and yet we're going to unpack each of them a little more in
the time allowed so generosity dana dana
the Buddha says in This saha suta on gutra
432 through giving one wins the affection of others and generosity is
not transactional here of course it's a fundamental relinquishment of clinging
that opens the heart imagine opening the hand it opens the heart and it nurtures
the field of relationship of friendship And this act of relinquishment opening
the hand letting go is is the same act of generosity the hand that lets go of
something can give it to someone else al you know it's also the same act of letting go of of um what we're clinging
to or maybe even resentment etc it's the same the same liberating act of opening
the hand of letting go of softening our grip and and there is
um there is modern psychological research that um acts of giving
generosity when we are generous ourselves it it activates it the the
reward system uh in our brain pain in our in our bodies the reward system
promoting happiness and social bonding so generosity literally brightens the
mind literally lights up the mind and strengthens um social ti social
ties a few words about kind speech pavaja pyavaja
um as as relational nourishment the Buddha says through kind speech one
binds our others to oneself i love the way he puts that through kind speech one
binds others to oneself and kind speech
again I think I spoke u some some time ago in these series about kind about why
speech and and can expand it to a whole week so there there's a lot of teachings on why speech and kind speech but uh it
also includes truthfulness timeliness and it it being beneficial uh uh in from
majikaya 58 um and also speech that is uh gentle pleasing to the ear
affectionate etc agreeable to many from Angutra Nikaya 5198 so there's a lot about wise
speech and kind speech uh and and first and foremost right to be truthful
truthful timely kind and um yeah there's so much to say
about speech I'm just going to to mention very little here in saying that
of course kind speech wise speech beneficial speech timely speech truthful
speech it it as the Buddhist says I I can't say it any more beautifully than he has it one binds others to oneself
one binds others to oneself so kind speech strengthens trust and
communal bonds couple of word a few words about
the next of these uh four the third one which is called beneficial conduct which
is atacharia atachara atacharia there's the last ah is long
atacharia which is the grounds of goodwill uh in action and the Buddha
again in this suta in angutraaya 432 says through acting for others welfare
one enders oneself so it's it's such a beautiful way that he's talking about
right we're both uh being of service to others um as well as there's benefit to oneself
benefit to oneself and others through these acts of of welfare for the sake of
others and these acts of welfare of course include offering help in the
times of need emotional or psychological support um actions that arise from
compassion and non-harming and often described as karuna in action compassion that moves
compassion that moves and there are so many Jataka Jataka tales and Jataka
tales are the stories of before the Buddha became a Buddha he he was reborn
as so many different animals and in every lifetime
uh when he was a bodhicattva he had this vow of of awakening um he there's so
many stories he offered limbs and lives and time and effort and energy to the welfare of others and of course his
teaching has been an act of of care um for the welfare of others it is said
that after he woke he awakened under the bodhic tree he didn't want to teach because he thought nobody would get it
it's so obtuse what he teaches and and out of compassion out of care for the benefit of others he took on the
difficulty of being misunderstood and you know all the stories and the sutas of of of uh of
teaching so and there's also of course modern research uh which aligns with
this that helping uh behavior predicts increase relational satisfaction and
trust and there's research uh by Algo and Jonathan H uh that uh that supports
that acts of service build build deep reservoir of mutual
goodwill and the last one I'll say it very quickly impartiality which is sama nata samaat
sata sata fostering respect the Buddha says through treating others equally one
dissolves divisions through treating others equally one dissolves divisions
so here the idea is having a stance of humility which is free from superiority
conceit favoritism and being evenminded with equinimity and unshaken by social
status and blame blame um and gain and gain and uh treating others basically
breaking barriers of hierarchy and fear and treating others um and and and
Buddha demonstrated this by treating kings untouchable monks lay people with the same basic
respect and presence so can we treat one another and other people we meet with
the same basic respect and presence in fact I'll just add something very quickly here in this village that I am
in Tuscanyany this friend of mine here was commenting that what is what is so beautiful here in this village the
barista at the at the coffee shop is treated with the same level of respect
as as anybody else in town and and that's really uplifting to to really see that in a small village in this small
community so three reflection questions today again which of the four relational
practices of that I mentioned are most alive in me today which of the four
relational practices are most alive in me today where could practicing one of
these transform a strained or stagnant relationship where could practicing one of these
transform a strained or stagnant relationship and lastly do I offer these
to all or only to those I already prefer do I offer these to all or only those I
already prefer so again which of the four of these is more alive in me today
um where could practicing one of these transform a strained or a stagnant
relationship for example is there a challenging relationship that by bringing more generosity by giving that
person a gift could open my heart uh will open their heart without any
expectation of return at all but just to open my heart and give them a gift and
um do I offer these all to to everyone equally or only those I prefer
so so thank you all thank you for your presence your generosity of presence to
to hold together uh to hold each other in this way in this community and
wishing you well wishing you ease and uh I'm waiting for the bell sometimes we
have bells here at a4 to the hour quarter to 5:00 p.m but apparently not
today we had them yesterday oh well it is what it is so wishing you well everyone may you be well may you be
happy and looking forward to seeing you tomorrow for the uh last uh for the
denimo for the end of our our series on SA take care of yourselves and be a good
friend to someone today okay take care bye everyone