so settling in into your body
just connecting with how you are in this moment
can there be a a sense of allowing yourself to be
just as you are
sometimes I I feel like meditation
and mindfulness can be like a dear friend
who comes and sits with you and is really curious open
wanting to be there with you and saying "How are you
how are you right now
and that friend not judging how you are
not trying to fix or change anything about you
just willing to be with you i'm here i'm here with you
mindfulness can be like that friend in a very deep way
opening to this experience
the body with its sensations and feelings
with a breath
and the mind receiving
experiencing
[Applause] How are you in this moment
can there be that friendliness of
connecting with how things already are in this moment
receiving whatever is simple
easy to connect with in this moment
for many of you that may be the breath or body sensations
receiving
what's here
what has come to be
body sensations as they have come to be
the breath as it has come to be
emotions perhaps even thoughts
can be recognized as they have come to be
all of our experiences arising
lawfully in dependence on conditions
what has come to be has come to be independence
on everything that's led up to this moment
and how we are relating to it in this moment
so receiving what's here
what's obvious easy to connect with
at times our mind settles and connects with an experience like the breath for a
period of time
and the attention is often also drawn to other experiences
we can notice that shift of attention recognize
that the attention has been drawn to some other experience and then just know that receive that
that's what has come to be
it may be something that's lasting for a short time such as a sound that comes
and goes
or it may linger a little bit and hold the attention for a little while
this friendly receiving
recognizing this is what's here this is what has come to be
and for many of you the attention may also gravitate back to the breath
and that's fine just receiving how you are
in this moment
another piece of how we are in this moment
is noticing recognizing what our relationship
is to this moment's experience
so often our habits of mind of wanting things to be a certain way of
wanting to hold on to things that are pleasant get rid of things that are unpleasant
of confusion or perhaps ideas or beliefs about what should be
happening
so often those habits of mind are so familiar that we don't recognize them i
kind of come up behind the scenes and start
evaluating and judging what's happening without our consciously recognizing it
and so it's useful from time to time to check in
how am I with what is happening not just what is happening but how am I
is there a wanting something to happen a wanting something to stop happening
a confusion an idea
or perhaps there could be a relationship
to the experience of allowing it's okay what's here
if we notice a relationship of wanting or resisting
the very noticing of that the exploration as a friend oh that's
what's going on for you right now that's okay
something unpleasant is happening and resistance is happening that's what's going on right now
what begins to open us to an allowing attitude
to even resistance and wanting and confusion
it can be quite interesting to see what happens when we become aware
of wanting or resistance or confusion and know it like that friend oh yeah
that's what's here i can be with you with that
there can be some spaciousness and ease that holds that experience
and we can be in a space of seeing how does that relationship then change or
transform through the simple meeting
of experience that's what's happening right now that's
what has come to be
and then we can touch into and recognize the experience of the allowing
this is what it feels like to not be in conflict with what is happening
our hearts understand this is a helpful direction
in that space there's learning that happens around
what has come to be understanding
that begins to arise that helps the mind to begin to
transform
in the space of that friendly attention
resistance and wanting held in that space of friendly attention
they begin to fade begin to weaken
get a little thinner
hand in that space of friendly attention
the qualities that come along with allowing
attention warmth friendliness wisdom patience
compassion they strengthen
And there are definitely times when something comes up so strongly
an aversion a resistance a fear a confusion
that it's really challenging to just simply meet it with allowing
it's like it overwhelms the mind
and when that happens
simply allowing is often not actually the right thing
because in that space we can just get pulled into the rabbit hole the
whirlpool of that reactivity and get lost
and so we have to know with wisdom
when we can be with something with that allowing attention and when
it's too strong
and when it's too strong we have some skillful means
redirecting the attention away from that difficult experience
to something that's easy to connect with easier to connect with
that may be the breath
it may be a more general sense of the body sitting here
it may be opening to the experience of hearing
something that lets you connect
and stay present not by pushing away or fighting
resisting or repressing the difficulty
it's more just of a redirect turn to another experience
basically our practice is really simple
we sit and receive
experience for many of you receiving the breath in
a simple way
noticing the experience
holding the possibility of a friendly allowing
perspective that meets
what's happening
mindfulness being like that friend i'm here
i'm happy to sit with you whatever is going on
[Music]
good morning everyone and again welcome to IMC i know Melody or Lauren has an
announcement
good morning my name is Lauren um happy father's day to anybody who is a parent
or a child of a parent we are doing our mindful our monthly mindful parents
group today uh at 11:15 our topic today is equinimity the paramy
of equinimity uh we welcome parents of or and caregivers of children of any age
from infancy through adulthood even if you've never come um please drop in today it's our last group until October
so we'd love to see you and uh please ask me any questions uh after the talk thank you
hi my name is Nancy um this is just a notice to our community that we lost a
longtime SA member who um helped and was a former librarian named Mary Rodriguez
i've had a number of people ask about her recently and I just learned today that she passed on June 8th and in her
memory I'd like to kindly remind people to return their library books thank you
thank you both of you so most of you probably know that the
entire center as well as our retreat center runs on donations
and all the teachings are offered freely so if you're inclined to make a donation there's a box near the front door with
the teacher's name and then another slot for operations and I believe our electronic kiosk near the library door
is also working and you can always donate online so our teacher this
morning is Andrea Fella she's a co-guiding teacher right here at IMC and
at the Insight Retreat Center she's been practicing insight meditation since 1996
and teaching insight meditation since 2003 she is particularly drawn to intensive
retreat practice and has done a number of long retreats both in the United
States and in Burma during one long practice period in Burma she ordained as
a nun with Zeda Shanaka andrea is especially drawn to the wisdom teachings
of the Buddha her teachings emphasize clarity and practicality and she teaches
residential retreats for IMC and other retreat centers around the country good
morning Andrea thank you Martha hi everyone
so uh I'm happy to hear that the topic for the mindful parenting group is
equinimity that is also my topic completely unplanned we did not
coordinate this
yeah the uh the topic of equinimity um sometimes in
these you know conversations I'm having with people these days that there's the question how do I cultivate equinimity
with things as they are with the world as it is right now how do I cultivate that equinimity and then there also
might be the question do I want to cultivate equinimity
so I want to talk to that today talk a little about what equinimity is
what it isn't and maybe offer a slightly different perspective on equinimity
that um may shift your thinking about hopefully
maybe shift your thinking about do I want to cultivate equinimity right now
so the quality of equinimity one of the words the polywords oopa
often translated as equinimity there's a lot of words that we use in
maybe kind of synonymously with that so you know equinimity isn't a word that's
frequently used in our everyday life but words like allowing accepting
balance of mind non-reactivity
non-conlict those are words that can evoke some of
the quality of equinimity joseph Goldstein brings in the the
phrase impartiality not towards or against
anything
and so some of those words kind of have the sense of
like accepting allowing they have this sense of just
kind of almost the flavor of I have to be okay with things as they are
and I'm going to talk a little more about that in a moment but I want to also speak a little bit about what
equinimity is not so those some of those flavors like um
impartiality can have a little bit of the flavor of a little bit of stepped back disconnected
and that's not what equinimity is it's not stepped back it's not disconnected in fact equinimity can bring us closer
to what's actually happening it's not
indifference or apathy those we could think of those as kind of maybe the near enemy of
equinimity they kind of sort of have the flavor of equinimity that I'm okay with
things as they are but it's it's got a quality of being detached and not not
not connected fundamentally equinimity is a quality of being connected with
what's here and fully acknowledging
what's here is what's here and that's the piece I'd like to I'd spend a little
time with this because my understanding of equinimity
is that it's a a state of mind that comes from a space of very deep wisdom
that understands what has come to be
as what has come to be it's not fighting what has come to be
it's not denying what has come to be it's fully
recognizing what has come to be what's happening in
this mind in this body what's happening out there in the world conditions have led to that it has come to be
it has already come to be it's happening already
so the state of the world everything that's going on it is
happening equinimity understands that what is arising now
what is happening now has come to be in a lawful way based on conditions
we may not like what has come to be and I think too that this quality of
equinimity it's not it's not it's not about liking
or not liking what has come to be it is really about that cleareyed recognition
this is what is here this is what is happening
so it understands equinimity comes from the wisdom that understands the conditioned nature of experience
conditions conditions have led to this moment
some of those conditions are
related to human hearts and minds
this is the teaching on karma that um when greed aversion and delusion
arise in the mind it tends to put greed aversion and del create more conditions
for greed aversion delusion in this mind but it also puts greed aversion and delusion into the field
it puts anger hostility hatred into the field it puts desire wanting craving
clinging into the field there's a there's a we are not only a product of the of the craving and clinging and
aversion and greed and everything that's arising in this mind but we also receive
it from the world and contributed to the world when that's what's happening and
so this is a piece of the world this is a piece of what what
goes on is that there's this arising of our human conditioning and we don't just
condition ourselves we condition each other there's a back and forth kind of conditioning that goes on
there's also the conditions in what's you know in nature you know the weather
conditions of genetics conditions of the laws of physics all of that
what's happening right now is arising based on lawful conditions
and so equinimity one piece of equinimity One aspect of equinimity is understanding
and recognizing that what has come to be is what has come to be based on lawful
conditions and
resisting or fighting what has come to be kind of binds up energy
kind of creates a kind of tension in the system that um
kind of and it also resistance aversion greed to what's happening you know
creates a tension and a binding up of energy in our own hearts and minds and It also tends to put that resistance
that anger that frustration that wanting that greed that confusion out into the world
and so with the mind that understands this is what has come to be kind of like
in this moment in this moment there's no point
resisting what is already here because it's already here
and that you know if we resist it there's it resistance aversion greed they take so much energy
If we explore the possibility of understanding that not fighting what has
come to be again I'm talking about what has come to be to this moment
not fighting what has come to because I think when we fight what has come to be to this moment we're often like we're
fighting the past it's like we're trying to figure out how can I change the past
if we can open to the the space of okay this is what has come to be without
resistance with a cleareyed recognition yep this is what's here
that creates space for
wisdom to arise that
can step forward into the next moment with wise action
and that wise action can arise when the mind is not fighting
conflicted that wise action can arise connected
with compassion with wisdom with kindness with ethics with the
understanding of non-harming as a a ground
these qualities come quite um
let's say more not maybe not quite easily but more easily when we're not resisting what has come to be
i think sometimes we have the idea that equinimity especially with the words like allowing accepting you know we have
the idea that equinimity means non-action
but what a space of equinimity can do that really fully accepts and understands this is what has come to be
that space of wisdom then also understands that
the conditioning going forward forward you know what what's happened to the past until now that has been lawfully
conditioned and what will move forward from this moment is also lawfully conditioned putting more greed aversion
and delusion into the world is going to create more greed aversion and delusion
in the world and so the the wisdom of equinim that
equinimity is grounded in not only understands that what has arisen to this moment is conditioned but that what
comes next conditions what happens
and the teachings of the Buddha point to compassion wisdom kindness
being um motivators of action
i think we often think you know we we have this kind of sense of
action coming from Oh
so much of our action comes from habitually
spaces of greed aversion and confusion delusion
and we might have the feeling that if I didn't want something to happen why
would I do anything if I didn't want to get rid of something why would I do anything
those mind states which are so they're so human
we share these all of us share these motivations of greed and aversion and
and act on them and
when we are acting on them when when greed is acting on itself when greed is
is acting in our hearts and minds it cannot understand
the perspective of another possibility of something else that might
be able to act in its place
so greed and aversion when we are caught by those states of mind they cannot
fathom that there's another quality in the heart compassion
wisdom that want to act also
not out of hatred not out of confusion not out of fear not out of desire but
out of wanting to alleviate suffering
so equinimity is the mind state that's based in the wisdom understanding deeply
understanding conditioning not only the conditioning that has come to this moment but also the conditioning
going forward it also I think that wisdom also
understands you know even acting out of compassion acting out of wisdom
taking skillful action that there's so many conditions going on
in the world so many different you know the Buddha
talks about the just just in terms of the conditions around karma
the Buddha says that the web of the conditioning around karma is so vast
that if you try to contemplate it you will go mad you can't follow back and say where
did this this event come from you know like you you can follow some of it you can get some of a sense of where this
came from but it's such a vast interconnected web that it's it the
Buddha says it's one of the things that can't be fully contemplated
and so there's so many conditioning so much conditioning not only in karma but also in in the the laws of the world of
nature that this wisdom also understands that
actions that are put into the world
they they may or may not have the effect we want and the effect when we want them
but that doesn't stop us from continuing to be motivated to try to alleviate
suffering it doesn't stop wisdom and compassion from being motivated to try
to alleviate suffering to try to create conditions of well-being
internally and in the world
so I think there's some similarities in a way between what we cultivate when we cultivate equinimity in our own hearts
and minds one of the key ways to cultivate equinimity
is to notice what's getting in its way to notice the reactivity to notice
the tightness the constriction the confusion
and so when we when we meet that often you know when there's confusion
constriction tightness fears arising aversions arising uh unpleasant
situation unpleasant experiences arising pain is arising we often experience a resistance to that
internally what we can explore there as I I mentioned in the guided meditation you know we can explore the possibility
of first of all recognizing because habitually our minds will go to when
something's unpleasant it will go to aversion when something's pleasant it will tend to go towards
wanting leaning into and so those things come kind of quietly they they often are
kind of hidden behind the scenes in our minds and so we don't clearly consciously recognize them and so we may
begin cultivating equinimity cultivating this quality of understanding
the conditions by recognizing that there is the unpleasantness
in this example you know there's unpleasantness of pain for example and there's an aversion to it when we can
recognize by checking how am I with something how am I with this experience
in in our meditation this is in our internal experience how am I with this
experience oh there's not liking there's aversion sometimes when that aversion is clearly
seen there's the allowing of that there's a kind of the mind can be balanced with
that oh right that's what's happening there's painful s there's painful experience and there's aversion over and
over again I've seen when I've noticed that oh right aversion that's what's happening there can be a relaxation in
the heart and mind there's the there's a kind of a sense of okay yeah that's
what's going on this is this is the the quality of equinimity that allows the
mind to clearly recognize yes this is what's here there's pain and there's resistance to the Right
the seeing of it helps the mind to have some balance with it and then in that
space in our internal meditation sometimes that's all that needs to happen
we can recognize at times that just allowing the aversion to be there
creates the conditions for it to weaken for it to to to fall apart i've seen that happen over and over again it's
like when I recognize oh the aversion's there when it's clearly seen in our in
in our meditation often that aversion just you know it
doesn't have any traction anymore so it it falls away and then we get an understanding of what it means to just
be with the challenging situation with the mind that's balanced
with the aversion having fallen away so sometimes in meditation that's all
that's needed that quality of allowing and acceptance and just meeting this is
what's here unpleasant aversion that's what's here
oh aversion weakening aversion falling away unpleasant and okay
oh aversion coming back unpleasant aversion
allowing that that can be a process in in meditation
and there are also times when you know the aversion itself the situation the
aversion are so strong that we get pulled into the
uh the whirlpool of it into the rabbit hole of it and in those moments it's
useful to do something else to not simply I mean like the that the the
understanding the wisdom that comes with equinimity of understanding the conditions here are
overwhelming my capacity what's skillful what's a skillful action
so equinimity in that case isn't about simply what we we might think of as allowing
it's it's about skillful action the equinimity understands
this is you know this condition is pulling me pulling me out wisdom
understands that and so brings in some tools maybe redirecting the attention
there's there's there's I won't go through all of these but this one kind of popped into my mind during the during
the sitting there's five uh a teaching about five um methods for working with
things when things when thoughts and mind states get overwhelming and one of those is a skillful
redirection you know taking your attention out of that thing and putting it into something else and that's often
what I suggest in in the meditation there's several others and one of them
and these I think will be useful as we think about applying the these tools to
our relationship to the world and equinimity in relationship to the world
the the the first one is contemplating the drawbacks of the
reactivity contemplating that yeah this reactivity
puts more junk into the world puts more puts more you know reactivity into this
system so contemplating the drawbacks of of the
um the the challenging mind state and those challenging thoughts another one
is to replace them with something skillful like meta for instance
so those are those are other possibilities those are kind of bringing in other tools in our in our practice to
allow us to navigate
when things get so strong in our hearts and minds that we
just can't settle back and know yeah this is what's here aversions arising
difficult situation and aversion is arising
we can take this kind of approach and I think that um
kind of exploration around the conditioned
nature of experience in the world
and that we condition each other to meeting
the suffering the conflict that's present in the world
cultivating the capacity to be with things as they are creates
the conditions for us to have more of a sense of balanced action in the world i'm right now going to read something i
was going to save this to the end but I'm going to read it now this is um
a reflection on he uses the word acceptance but he's really talking about equinimity this is
um a Zen teacher Daishin Morgan to accept means to receive what is
offered circumstances of life give rise to conditions and our acceptance of these
conditions is just the acceptance of things as they are what is not meant by the idea of
acceptance is any agreement or disagreement with the way things are acceptance is about basing ourselves in
reality not about making judgments of liking and disliking or of agreeing and disagreeing to accept the situation is
to be grounded in the actual state of things without getting lost in ideals or fantasies of how we would like it to be
we then have a good basis from which to see what action may be called for acceptance does not imply inertia on the
contrary to be grounded in reality gives rise to a true response
and so this is what we can explore in our relationship to what is happening in
the world first I think it's crucial to meet what
is happening with a clear mind
to cultivate that capacity and understand too I think that conflict
conflict is a form of suffering there's a a teaching um in the
in the text that's um called the exposition of non-conlict
and in that in that uh teaching that's in the majica
it says that we need to understand the state with conflict and the state
without conflict so what do we think of as conflict we think of conflict as
resistance of fighting of disagreement
of wars
different perspectives different understandings that can't be resolved and we feel like
it either has to be my way or their you know it's like each each side seems to feel like it's it's their their side is
right and there's not a a kind of can we meet in the middle somewhere there's there's a kind of a a a
pulling to the the opposition
this teaching says the state of conflict is a state beset by suffering vexation despair and fever
and it is the wrong way and the wrong way here means the wrong way in terms of finding peace ease and
happiness so it's it's um again the Buddha all of
the Buddhist teachings are pointing towards non-suffering nonharming non-suffering
one of the interesting things I think about that um
that sentence is conflict is a state
beset by suffering vexation despair and fever so it's a state
It's a condition that has come to be
it's a state and so this is something that can be
explored we can explore conflict internally we can explore conflict
externally we can you know kind of look at what is going on here get to know the
conditions of it see how it has come to be so we explore it the same way we
might explore something happening internally a state of conflict happening internally
and so this space of exploring conflict in this way can help us to have
a little bit more balance equinimity around what has come to be
and to look at from a place of
compassion nonharming what actions
are skillful to take in this moment remembering some of those other
teachings like pointing out the drawbacks of what's going on
that's probably a useful thing to do cultivating the wholesome qualities
and cultivating that perspective of wisdom of understanding the conditioned
nature of what's happening
i do believe that the world needs more of this
approach of understanding
and action from compassion and care without deliluding ourselves
and also I I recognize that
we're going to need to act when we're not aquatamus so what do we do there you know what's
what's what's maybe skillful to do
internally in our meditation when we're not aquatamus we
we bring in some skillful means you know when it's too much when there's
too much um uh reactivity
we bring in some skillful means about how can I balance the mind here how can
I balance the mind aware aware of our reactivity
can we ground in the intention of wisdom so aware in with reactivity that we tend
to act out of reactivity when reactivity gets strong and now speaking about
thinking about the world and acting in the world when reactivity gets strong
we tend to act out of it it tends to be guiding our actions
there can at times be that recognition yes reactivity is here i'm I'm not going
to be able to you know um get past this reactivity right now but
it may be possible in this moment to ground myself in the intentions of
nonharming of wisdom of compassion
and and committing to acting skillfully even even not not trying to
con convince our minds that we feel something that we don't but committing
to those basic ethical
conducts refraining from killing refraining from
creating harm out of speech refraining from harming through our
sexuality refraining from taking what's not given
those basic ethical ethical conduct can be our
our guide when we're experiencing reactivity so to to to try to act with the
intention of nonharming even if we feel reactive it is possible
i've watched this in my own mind in small ways you know to see how it's
possible to change it's kind of like I I I I pick up the intention of what the
opposite of what's going on in my in my experience is and I try to let not let
that reactivity leak out into my behavior into my action so I let my
actions be guided by the intention
while still fully recognizing yeah the heart the heart is not
balanced here the heart and this is this is
this is wisdom this is a this is the cultivation of
equinimity we understand that we we have the this happening in
our mind this is what is arising yes if I had the choice I would turn off the
hatred i'm not able to do that right now and can I act
from a different lens
so using ethics as a a kind of a guide
and then there's this cultivation of equinimity related to actions of others
that are causing harm how do we how do we deal with that how do we relate to that
i think a lot of the a lot of the understanding around this you know the compassion around this can arise when we
recognize that everyone is acting out of their own
conditioning we see our own conditioning you know
that we we as meditators get to see how much
stuff is going on in our own hearts and minds we get to see the the aversion the
anger the hatred the confusion i remember at one time so clearly seeing I
was so angry at somebody and then in the the observing of it I couldn't turn the
anger off but I could I was watching it and in that watching that anger I saw
that there was a part of the mind that so wanted the other person to suffer
that like startled me it's like wow
that that was like it was it was a little bit of a moment of waking up and seeing the
seeds of war are right here
that wish for somebody else to suffer that's the seed of war
and seeing that was so humbling and it made me in that moment was like
"Oh my gosh no wonder the world is such a mess." Multiply that by 8 billion
interacting with each other no wonder no wonder
that that moment gave me both the understanding and the appreciation for
my own conditioning but also of seeing this is not about just me this is and
this is what's going on in the world this going on multiplied by 8 billion
so recognizing the conditionality
of what's going on in that conflict
the other side of the conflict that's been conditioned also our side's been
what what we're experiencing has been conditioning that their experience has been conditioned
and so that that for me creates some conditions of compassion and humility
if I had lived their life what might I be doing right now i don't
know so that's a piece again that's that
that's the reflection on equinimity the the reflection on the conditioned nature of experience one of the main conditions
that leads to equinimity and just as we need to hold ourselves
accountable for ethical action and I think this is an important piece in our
own hearts and minds we need to notice you know it's like yes it's conditioned and
there's some capacity that this being has to recognize what is being what is being
put out from this being is affecting others and so holding ourselves accountable for
what we what we how we are in the world and this practice this meditation
practice gives us some tools to kind of have a little bit of a gap before we
react to respond rather than reacting
so we need to hold ourselves accountable and we need to hold others accountable
accountable to behave in ways that are ethical
that are kind that are compassionate
and that's a challenge right now i don't have the answers
but I do deeply believe and feel that the
the direction of greed aversion and delusion
is not the way and that the direction of wisdom
compassion kindness is the Okay
i'll just read a little bit of this paragraph again to end
to accept the situation is to be grounded in the actual state of things
without getting lost in ideals or fantasies of how we would like it to be we then have a good basis from which to
see what action may be called for acceptance does not imply inertia on the
contrary to be grounded in reality gives rise to a true response
may it be so thank you for your attention
and um I'm happy to hang out and talk with anybody who wants to afterwards for
a little while so but it's time to end so thank you all