okay it's the top of the hour many different hours depending on
where you are in the world wherever it is i hope you're having a good
day and welcome welcome to our uh weekday morning sit and darmat and today
is the um third day of uh this week's investigation of
what the Buddha called the world the six internal sense spaces and uh their
objects the avenues through which we come to perceive and conceive the world
that's language from Ananda um a monk one of the Buddha's disciples
his his cousin and attendant so we perceive that is we take
in through our senses and we conceive we develop ideas and concepts about what is
perceived and our experience of our world comes into being through the interaction of these
so I talked about the I talked about the sense of sight on Monday and then
yesterday about hearing and today I'm going to talk about two senses that are very closely
related taste and smell and we know now because of
science that um the sense of taste is really dependent upon the sense of smell
that it's difficult to detect flavor if our sense of smell is not operating i
don't know if that was common knowledge in the Buddhist time you know those those two uh senses are always spoken of
separately as far as I know in the in the sutras in the texts but I'll talk
about them both today and often together in concert and of course if I didn't
conflate two senses sometime during this week five days wouldn't be long enough
to talk about all six of them so there's a practical reason for it but it makes
absolute sense so yesterday I mentioned um a story that
Ajan Cha used to tell about practicing outside a village where there was a
festival going on and he was getting irritated by the loud music that was
playing and uh and how he finally came to realize that it wasn't the sound that
was bothering him it was him bothering the sound and uh yesterday my husband
commented that he's always been a little bothered by that language because sound
itself can't be bothered no but which of course is true but my sense is that what Ajan Cha
was pointing to was that all the bothering that was being generated was being generated by his own reactivity to
the sound he was blaming the sound for his discomfort and maybe blaming is a
kind of uh bothering and there's a really important
lesson in that story that I want to be more specific about today um I mentioned
yesterday that people often have a tendency to uh to blame the object of
their sense perception for their discomfort for their stress for the desire or craving that arises in them um
when we see something we don't like the tendency is for us to focus on what we
see as the source of our discomfort we conflate our reaction to the sense
contact with the actual sensing of it we forget uh the difference between nama
and rupa that Gil talked about last week appearances and mental
activity when we hear a sound that we don't like we tend to blame the sound for bothering us just like John Shaw did
but the sense contact did not cause the the discomfort that our reaction did did
that our action was actually the discomfort the problem is the way in
which we're conceiving in reaction to the perception and that's that's what's
called in the sutas a fetter that arises in the mind in the chitta in the
heart and there's a teaching about this in the sutras that I want to just quote from um another monk uh comes to sit by
Sara who is the Buddha's foremost disciple in wisdom always often called
that and here's Here's a here's a quote from the
suta after an exchange of friendly greetings and courtesies this other monk
sat to one side and as he was sitting there he said to venerable Sar Puta "Now
tell me friend Sar Puta is the eye the feder of forms or are forms the feder of
the eye is the ear the feder of sounds or our sounds the feder of the ear is
the nose the feder of aromomas or are aromomas the feder of the nose and same
with the other senses he went on concluding with the mind is the mind the
feder of mental activities or are mental activities the feder of the mind and
sorry responded no my friend the eye is not the feder of forms nor are forms the
feder of the eye whatever desire and passion arises independence on the two
of them that is the feder there the ear is not the feder of sounds
nor are the sounds the feder of the ear whatever desire and passion arises in
dependence on the two of them that is the fetter there and he goes on with
each of the other senses concluding with the with the mind again the mind is not the feder of
mental activities nor are mental activities the feder of the mind whatever desire and passion arises in
dependence on the two of them that is the feder there and of course desire and uh
passion that just that's a kind of shorthand for all the kinds of uh mental
complications that arise out of uh out of greed hatred and delusion that that
can arise in that space so the feather lies in how how we
are relating to what is happening just as as we did with sight and hearing in
the past two days we want to make the distinction between the tastes and smells that we sense and then the mental
activity that that comes along with them to see where that activity might be
creating some kind of knot you know some obstacle to to really feeling free to
being at ease so with that uh with
that uh intro we'll uh we'll sit now let's sit let's
meditate
so finding your your good meditation
posture a way of sitting or lying down or standing whatever posture you happen to
be in whatever posture works for you that allows you to feel awake and
aware alert to what's going on in your experience and also relaxed
and again I'll I'll invite you
to do a a brief body scan just letting your attention move through the
body touching any places where there's
tension and just maybe using the
breath as a kind of massager to let those areas ease
up them soften as much as they're ready to go
let the chest and belly be open and soft so that the the breath can move in and
out really freely
let the belly be soft so that it can just expand on the inb breath and and
gently fall on the outreath
if you like to spend a little bit of time with sound um that can be a nice way of
settling just attending to the the sounds in in the room where you
are the sound of my voice in a very receptive useful way just receiving the
sound not reaching out for it as we've uh we explored
yesterday just inviting a sense of receptivity into the awareness into the
mind and the body
and moving moving the attention to the breath tending to the rhythm of the
breath maybe in and out like a like gentle
waves just climbing up a beach and slowly
receding over and over again little bit different each
time never the
same
inviting the rhythm of the breath to calm the body and the
mind in and out rising and falling
and as you as you sit just attending to your breathing or maybe being open to
other experiences sometimes thoughts will
arise maybe in response or reaction to what's happening in your
meditation maybe due to uh you know triggered by memory of something
something in the past or some anticipation of
something to come something in the future and just note just
notice the ways that thinking complicates the inner landscape the way
it's different from just receiving the sensations of
breathing other sensations that you're
experiencing just notice that notice the effect in your
body is there tension associated with
with thinking when it arises
constriction in the mind
and then as you sit you know just know that it's possible to
recognize the difference between what is happening in the body as we sit here and
the mental activity that accompanies It comments on it reacts to it analyzes
whatever the activity is can be done in a very simple
way just noticing and then see if you can just
let it go let it all [Music] go soften into a simple receptive
presence sensing the breath sensing other
sensations maybe sensing the metal activity in the same receptive way not
getting involved in it not taking part in
it just be simple
any any kind of calm or ease that you feel as a result of sitting this this
half hour any sense of rightness
appreciation and you turn that outward and offer it
to those around you those farther out to the
world to all beings
with a wish that all beings may be
safe that all beings may be
happy that they have the strength to meet what comes in their
lives and that all beings everywhere may be free
[Music]
noah welcome again hope the bell wasn't too
loud seems quite loud to me
so there was a reaction to that the sound in my mind the sense oh I did
something wrong made it too
loud so um in that teaching that Saruta offered
the other monk that I was uh uh talking about before the sit um he continued to
ex to he continued with a a simile to explain what he meant by a feder arising
in uh in dependence on the
two the sense space and its object it he
said uh excuse me he said suppose that a black ox and a white ox were joined with
a single collar or yolk if someone were to say the black ox is the feather of
the white ox or the white ox is the feather of the black speaking this way
would they be speaking rightly and the other monk said "No my friend the the the black ox
is not is not the feder of the white ox nor is the white ox the feder of the black the single collar or yoke by which
they are joined that is the feder there what lies between them the single
collar or yolk and then Saruta goes on to say that if the sense organs were
actually the feathers of their objects or vice versa there wouldn't be the
possibility of liberation because if that were the case there would always be a feder present
they would be fettered to each other as long as we are alive and our senses are
operating there would be no escape you know it would be like being tied to a a
perch like the falconer's hawk not allowed to fly
free but because the feder arises independence on both because it is a
knot sort of between them that complicates their relationship we have
the potential to uh to untie that knot to that fetter and to and to be free to
fly and at the end of uh of this suta Sar
Puta describes how the sense bases and their objects are all still operating in
the Buddha but he isn't fettered by any of them no reactivity arises in him in
relation to the sense spheres he sees and hears and tastes and smells and has
thoughts but his relationships to those uh sense activities is not complicated
by unhealthy desire or aversion or a need to take possession of the activity
you know to create a self around it i think this is so important to
remember you know the end of the world in the Buddhist sense doesn't come
because we've uh we no longer have the use of our senses that would mean we'd be dead it
comes when the senses are allowed to operate as they naturally do and no
fedters arise instead what is present is clear seeing equinimity generosity care
meta qualities that arise from deep within that become our natural way of
relating to what's happening once we've thoroughly thoroughly let go it's a gradual process
of course so when we're attending to what's coming
in through our senses dealing with some habitual reactivity that's creating
stress in our lives whether um it's a craving that's really pervasive or
something uh that's something that's more on the aversive side that's that's pervasive anger or irritation or
disapproval judgment that seems to arise maybe in particular situations whatever
it is It's really useful it's really useful to remind ourselves that that reactivity is
something we actually have some power over it isn't hardwired it isn't built
into the activity of the senses in some permanent way it's really what our
practice is about but I think we probably all know that recognizing uh what is uh
obstructing us and seeing you know can it be let go what good is it doing us
the feathers that arise they might be you know really deeply ingrained conditioned from a really early time in
our lives but they're still something that we can work with something to come
to know with with deep sensitivity great sensitivity and eventually we can let go
of them and the beginning of becoming free beginning of becoming free of
anything is recognizing that it's there knowing that uh whatever it is is
conditioned and conditioning is changing all the time and we have a role in that
process so today I'm going to focus on on smell and taste and uh boy these two sens these
two senses are really a big part I think of what drives many people's uh sense desires you know food and drink of
course and and that's what mostly fills this realm I imagine food and drink what
comes in to our mouths and what we smell actually odors there have other other
sources um but what we All the flavor of food um
scientists tell us is made up of both taste and aroma um and you know a lot of
people uh during the COVID pandemic and also as a result of other illnesses have
lost their sense of smell and um and many are still affected by that and and
uh uh I know I've heard just many people several people say that when uh when
their their sense of smell came back they were uh so grateful when it
returned because when when their when it wasn't operating they just lost all interest in in food and uh in eating and
in cooking for their for their friends and families all that the tongue can taste
without the sense of smell is the very basic tastes of sweet salty sour and
bitter all the nuance is lost all the things that delight
us that maybe give rise to feathers
there are aromomas smells odors you know that give rise to a a big variety of
reactions in people and you know conditioned on past experience mostly conditioned on past
experience cultural conditioning you know plays a plays a really big uh part
in this uh in this area tastes and odors that are considered uh really foul in
some cultures are highly regarded in in others both personal and cultural um
conditioning affect how we relate to all the things that we smell and taste you
know just as a really simple example you know you might notice how one person can
find the aroma of beef on a barbecue you know just really delightful enticing
while someone else is just disgusted by it so you know we know the reaction is
not inherent in the smell itself it arises dependent on our relationship and
how we relate to the smell or taste and that that is conditioned we relate to uh
all our experience based on prior conditioning on on memories and
attitudes of mind that often we aren't even conscious of and noticing how our reactions to
different odors and tastes change over time that that points to the the same truth you know the same thing the
pleasure or disgust we experience is generated in our minds and the as conditioning
changes the the reactions in the mind
change some foods um uh we call uh comfort foods you know
different people of course have different comfort foods and um it can be
illuminating I think to notice what arises in the mind when when uh we smell
or taste those particular foods what what is it that actually feels comforting in them you know they're not
inherently comforting or just nutrition for the body or maybe just not nutrition
but something that we like to take in what are the mental associations you know with the food that make it feel
comforting memories you know my husband uh um mentioned mashed
potatoes in this regard just a couple of weeks ago he was feeling a little bit
blue a little bit stressed and a buffet was serving mashed potatoes with
mushroom gravy and he ended up with a stomach ache some hours later because he had
seriously overdone the spuds you know because of the emotional resonance the flavor had for him what is the comfort
he's looking for it was a hook a fetter and and you know there are a lot of
people who use food for comfort occasionally probably me most people I
would imagine use it occasionally for comfort and there are some who do it
habitually who really um are kind of uh addicted to using it in that way and
and they often suffer for it in many many ways
slowing down you know noticing the effect of each bite in the mouth in the
mind looking to the mind and heart to see is there is there some kind of craving here that has nothing to do with
nourishing my body you know the craving is in the mind and the taste doesn't
cause it used to be an exercise that was part of
every uh intro to meditation class series and I think uh I think it was
also used in MBSR um students would be instructed to
mindfully um eat a raisin or a dried cranberry just one to uh to smell it
first you know just take in the aroma although raisins don't smell very much I
don't think um to feel the texture of it in the mouth to chew it very slowly kind
of letting the tongue really get involved in the taste and then finally to swallow it sensing it going down the
throat And people would often comment that after chewing for a little while the
taste became uh neutral or even
unpleasant it's an interesting uh kind of exercise i think usually we don't eat
slowly enough to allow ourselves to you know continually kind of track the the
sensations that are going on in the taste buds and the aroma receptors which
we have re aroma receptors in our mouths you know we don't think of of odors as
arising in our mouth but apparently they do i think usually when there's some kind
of craving operating in the the taste uh smell arena we tend to eat in a way that
prolongs the flavor that we desire either trying to get that next hit of a
pleasant flavor in quickly you know or maybe letting something uh something
like chocolate melt slowly in the mouth you know savoring each moment and then
maybe often wanting another bite as soon as that one is swallowed think I might
be giving myself away a little bit here with my references to chocolate and of course we see in uh in
alcohol addiction how strongly debilitating the craving that arises
between the senses of taste and aroma and the liquid tasted can be and that
craving of course it we know it destroys lives and addiction is a you know it's a
very complicated process and I don't mean to imply that all we need to do is
uh is to notice the craving and know it as something that arises out of prior
conditioning and somehow we'll just let go of it but that is the beginning of course and the same with dependence on
food we talk about stress eating or anxiety eating need to recognize the
triggers there recognize the conditioning that pushes us toward looking for comfort in the foods we love
or the drinks we think we need investigating our experience to the uh
our relationship to the experience of eating and drinking of tasting and sensing odors what is the
hook what is the hook
we assign meaning to smells you know often especially smells associated with the body that the human body produces
odors and and most of them uh give rise to aversion and and most people there's
even shame associated with many of the odors that the body produces but they're just odors in themselves you know
perfectly natural we assign meaning to them that they don't have usually some kind of negative
judgment or shame if it's our body producing the
odor dependent on the sense of smell and the odor smell some kind of reactive
mental process arises that obstructs our ease and freedom that that gives rise to
to dooka to pain
and I think we know that smells are especially powerful in evoking
memories i think of there's a a plant that blooms here in the in the foothills
and the mountains where I live uh cenothus California lilac it's often called and when I every time I smell it
in the winter after the rains have come and it started to bloom it brings out memories of hikes from when I was a a
teenager in days in the garden long ago when I'd catch the scent of course a
French author Marcel P ended up writing a 3,000 pages of of fiction based on his
memory of a little cookie Meline
so sometimes memories evoked by odors might be really beautiful memories evoked by taste as well might give a
rise to appreciation joy and sometimes there are hooks yeah
and as we develop the the deep sensitivity to what's arising in us we can give more attention to what it is
that gives rise to the beautiful mental states as we gradually gradually
Untie the helpful unhelpful feathers feathers not feathers
feathers so remember that in every moment there are only two things
happening there's what is happening and our relationship to what is happening
and the fetter the knot that that really it characterizes it comes to
characterize our relationship to what's happening in a way that obstructs us and
sometimes it's really subtle and sometimes it's very obvious but it's something to tune
into it's something to recognize and just to know this is what's happening
and this is reactivity
thank you thank you for your attention and uh
I'll see you tomorrow and we'll talk about uh bodily sensations
tomorrow so I hope you have a day filled with uh
appreciation and gratitude for for what is good that comes through the sense
spaces