and I'm curious before we get formally started here if um anyone has any
observations from noticing moments of simplicity or contentment or um anything
that took you away from those moments yesterday and pop that in the chat or
silently reflect on it consider what cultivated contentment
What supported simplicity if it emerged for you
yesterday so with that
With that the invitation is to settle into a posture that will support you
this morning posture that balances a
simple groundedness in this
moment and allows from some relaxation settling
in perhaps allowing a couple of longer slower breaths
and tuning in to whatever soothing
qualities simple qualities of
breath invite your mind your heart your attention to be present
and when you're ready to let your eyes
soften allow your tongue to soften and let the attention go
inwards noticing the weight of your body
perhaps the sounds in the [Music] room or wherever you are
all of the sensations in the
body grounding through your
feet your hip points letting your hands relax
and then [Music] attuning attending [Music]
settling on your primary object of attention your primary
anchor perhaps sensation of the body or
sensation of breathing
and the invitation now as you're settling into
present awareness is to intentionally call up an
image just a simple frame in time or felt
sense of some time where you felt Very relaxed at ease
comfortable
safe and to
receive the feeling tone and the emotional
tone of this memory
what does it feel like now in the body in your
heart recall a moment of [Music] simple pleasant contentment
rather than getting lost in that image or thoughts about
it acknowledge it allow it to
inform your feelings in meditation right now
allow that sense of simplicity and
contentment to spread through your own body heart for the moment
breathing it with breathing [Music]
through the experience of this moment
allowing the attention to be called by the breath
inviting the breath to spread [Music]
through your whole core
allowing the moment this
moment to fill the attention and rest
on the sensations texture motion of breathing
if distractions of there and and pull the attention
away acknowledging
them noticing them as [Music] thinking or hearing or feeling in the
moment
and appreciate the return of awareness of
this here now
Perfect
if the heart and mind are not steady the invitation is to call up a
feeling of a time of contentment
safety let that feeling resonate through your body now in this
moment breathing with
it allowing
Any feelings of
groundedness simple pleasure
breath to percolate through all of experience
from time to time rededicating the
[Music]
attention to this moment
allowing it to fill [Music] you perhaps being nourished by each
breath connected to this moment
as we approach the end of our sitting
together the invitation is to notice
Any ways you might feel more settled
present even a hair's breath more
relaxed to also recall
recollect any bits glimmers of goodness throughout the
meditation hold them in
mind let them nourish your body your
practice the heart of your practice
and then perhaps with an internal gesture of
generosity offering the benefits of this practice out towards the others your
life touches
may they be safe happy
healthy may they be peaceful at
ease and free
and may this practice be a cause and condition to bring
about more love liberation and
peace in our hearts and in the
world may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
so friends the theme for this week as many of you
know is um it's stories inspirations for
insight that I'll be unpacking over the course of the week and I'm weaving in some kind of
practice tips and um things that have worked for me and for practitioners I've supported to
support insight as it arises in practice so we'll start with an opening story
this morning which is um one that some of you are probably well familiar with but we'll be evoking
soaking some of the wisdom from it so as you may know the Buddha went
through a long phase of practicing austerities in his practice he had this
little band of um spiritual colleagues and um together they did these practices
that were common in ancient India where it was basically punishing their bodies
starving their bodies eating less and less drinking less and less over
time with the idea that it would separate them from being bound to the um
entanglements sensual pleasures and karma of their lives at one point he
describes in the ancient discourse as being down to a grain or two of rice a
day so it was in this period before he was awakened he was still striving for
awakening that um this story unfolds he is sitting under a tree quite
starved and thin and nearby a young woman the daughter of
some wellto-do farmers had a dream encouraging her to go make a food
offering to someone and she um trusted this dream
she went out and encountered this emaciated man sitting under a tree and
was moved to offer him rice porridge kind of a high quality food at the time
and although the Buddha had been committed committed to this path of austerity and we think nowadays
deprivation for quite a while something stirred in him and he accepted the
offering and ate it and the myths around the ancient
teaching of his awakening describe him um being nourished by this and I imagine
by the kindness of the offering as well and going to sit in meditation and in
the discourses he describes a memory from childhood arising of being in the
shade of a rose apple tree looking out over the fields at his father um the
king in a plowing festival kind of a happy time and that in this
content relaxed way he became absorbed in the moment very
pleasurable And as he sat there in meditation this memory arose and the
recognition came to him oh this is a wholesome pleasure this is not to be
feared and that memory and that recognition caused him to let go of this
austere kind of punishing way that he had been practicing and conceive of the
middle way of Buddhist practice in some versions of this story
he actually became awakened that very night so familiar story to many what
inspirations towards insight what qualities supporting our minds might be
evoked from this i invite you to evoke your own
and when I reflect on it it strikes me that the Buddha actually received three
forms of nourishment nutrition for his practice that day the first was the
physical nutrition of food the second was contact with this
person's generosity and kindness and the receptivity of be being able to take it
in and this nourishment this perhaps nurturing of kindness appears to have
shifted a mood or quality in his heart and
mind and that brings up the third form of nutrition that he received that day
because that change of heart somehow called up an
associated related memory from his childhood which in of itself inspired
this wise voluitional shift in his practice
so let's talk about those second two forms of nourishment contact with
nourishment because the way the Buddha appears to have processed his experience
has wisdom that might inform or support your practice my
practice so the Buddha was literally practicing austerities in a way that he later discovered weren't helpful
now as then it's really easy impossible
for anyone to have this kind of inner attitude of austerity stinginess
contraction self-punishment all of which are unhelpful attitudes to the
practice there's even a milder version of this which is a scarcity mentality
the same experience in meditation can be very differently received very
differently framed in terms of a lack or a loss or a problem or on the other hand
in terms of absence a beautiful kind of spaciousness even dissolution allowing wisdom
mindset qualities of mind are core for example there's three different
ways that practitioners I've accompanied have um related to the ending of a sublime
state of concentration of Janna one the state ends and like most humans
ending something very pleasurable or unusual or interesting the person grasps at it tries to keep it feels irritated
bereff at the fault for being distracted or maybe makes up a lot of stories about
what's wrong with them or what went wrong or how great I was that it happened all of that
such grasping aversion story making it isn't necessarily a mistake per se
overall because it's part of the training however it isn't onward leading
in the sense of um helping to evoke insight in the
moment it's part of the muck that the lotus grows from so very human so very
understandable okay another way second way practitioner might relate to the
same exact event the dissolving of a concentration state it's gone they might
accept it lightly and shrug like oh gone okay and there's a lightness and a sense
of equinimity or even delight gratitude for having had it
so that that's a more wholesome onwardleading way of relating and then
third a practitioner might attend to the end of the exact same beautiful
experience but attending to it with continuous mindfulness and attention and
notice all of the details of the change in their state of mind and the change of
what's arising in the moment and experience the end of that
concentration state as insight same event three different
mental conditions and qualities of mind and I want to stress these aren't
necessarily anyone's fault or that they should be lionized for them their conditions coming
together to recognize our part in those conditions is noticing appreciating and
gradually cultivating more and more capacity for mindfulness awareness steadiness and for
noticing the qualities of mind and that brings us to the story
what the story implies about how the Buddha related to the memory of being
this content absorbed kid under a tree so early in my own retreat practice
I definitely became entranced with similar memories maybe you have too most
of us are one memory arises and all of
the sudden all these unfolding similar memories come along cluster along for
the ride or um we might compare why can't it
be like that now or get um pulled off into other trains of thought in this case like
related trains of thought about trees or childhood or family or even farming
it's clear from this story that that's not what happened for the Buddha that
night instead rather than being entranced he was attentive however he
didn't necessarily follow the basic mindfulness instructions that are often
given and simply label that memory as thinking or remembering and discard it
instead he took the wisdom from it he allowed it to inform him in the
moment so this isn't an invitation to discursive thinking in your meditation
but rather an invitation to be open to the quiet wisdom the quiet messages that
our psyches may produce as the heart and mind settle
settle as a sense of kindness and safety contentment and simplicity begin to be
more accessible more wisdom also becomes
available it may take the form of a still small voice that speaks a few words that turn
the practice it's quite a different tone and sensibility than internal chatter or
narration or it may take the form of an image like being under a tree
there's an art to being able to sense the goodness the wisdom in the content
of whatever is arising in our minds while seeing the content and the arising in
the present moment oh thought
of if we're not pulled into thoughts as realities they become potential signals now and then or simple
ways of knowing very simple for shifts in the practice that can move the mind
closer to insight freedom happiness
a way of using our dharma intelligence to include the content of the mind and
heart as well as the process and if done with discernment without magical
thinking without assigning retroactive meaning then we can experience
conditions and connections in the moment that are like a breadcrumb trail towards
insight it's a different way of structuring
understanding present moment experience some people some teachers SAI
is one call this inclusion of both process and content 5050 mindfulness or
5050 awareness one teacher calls it 360°ree
awareness for some people at a certain point in the deepening of samadei or at
certain levels of approaching insight visual images are common like this or
felt sense in the body if there's continuous mindfulness and awareness and
by continuous I don't mean all the time little bursts of continuity are fine a
few seconds is all it takes if there's this continuous awareness of our general
mood mindset or mind state even for a few seconds such memories arisings in
the heart and mind kesthetic heard seen can become part of
a wisdom oriented way of seeing like signposts in the
moment pointing to a wiser way to navigate our hearts minds and inner
lives so in conclusion wise nourishment
invites depth of practice and insight i want to encourage you over the
next 24 hours to allow a kind of receptive kind quality of mind and see
what emerges what might release from a contracted or scarcity mentality
this kind of nourishment of the goodness within helps to develop discernment to deepen wisdom about
relating to both the process of our minds and hearts and lives and
everything that we see within them thank you for your kind attention