Welcome, welcome.
It's nice to practice together, to meditate together.
So, I'm just returning from a teaching and meditation retreat. And for those of
you who haven't been on retreat, I'll just say that uh um everybody who participates has a
conversation with a teacher. usually more than one. So what that's the
retreats are in silence, but there's a particular time when you meet one-on-one with the teacher or in a group with the
teacher to talk about how your practice is going or questions you might have about the teachings or describe maybe
some difficulties or what's going well, this type of thing.
And it's not uncommon. I was noticing this. It's not uncommon for people who
are like maybe having a beautiful practice and they're unfold their their
meditation practice is unfolding and deepening in a way that we would expect.
That's, you know, not uncommon. But maybe they've like touched into a little
bit different experiences than they've had before.
for example, maybe just feeling settled and calm more than we usually are, more
than we can, maybe with just a a single meditation session. But you know, after you've been meditating, sit and then you
walk and then sit and then walk, the mind and the body, they can't help it. They just start settling down. And that
might feel unusual like, "Oh, wh what is this? I'm not used to feeling this calm
or this relaxed or this settled or this connected or this uh easeful. And it
might feel like am I still alive? You know, this feeling of maybe what we associate with vitality or passion or
something like this isn't there in the usual way or that that or we've become
so associated with just having this little bit of agitation. there's that thing I have to do, that thing I have to
take care of, this problem I have to solve. You know, the our life is like just one long to-do list. And when
that's gone, it can feel a little bit unusual
or sometimes what can happen as a this settling
happening then our sense of the body starts to be a little bit different.
It's sense our perception. Not always, but sometimes it can feel more spacious
and easeful and there's certainly we're in touch
with the body. We know what's happening, but it's less the anatomical body. It le
feels less like the body that's going to show up on a CAT scan or an X-ray or something like that. And it more just
feels like a collection of sensations that uh they're just there in some kind
of way. And for some people that feels like wait wait wait wait wait am I still here in the usual way or sometimes like
the maybe the head starts to feel really big or the pressure against the body starts to feel really strong or
something like that or maybe there's this way sometimes
there can be a feeling of energy moving through the body and uh in a pleasant
way usually but it's not our usual experience like oh what what's this
energy etic feeling that's going on. Some people report like a little bit
like their finger in a in a light socket.
It happens just to a small subset of people. But so I find in these uh
practice discussions that I'm having with all these practitioners that are on the retreat, I do a lot of like yeah
that's fine. It's absolutely fine what you're experiencing. But there's this way in which sometimes
there can be fear that arises when we're having new experiences. I'm talking
about them and meditation experiences that can arise when we're on retreat, but you know, just going to a new
uh any like new experience, going to a new gym, like okay, I want to look like I
know what I'm doing, but where are those machines that do the thing that I want? or where's those cardio machines that do
the things that I want or or going to a new grocery store and like oh where is
everything like I don't know this isn't like the usual one whatever it is maybe there's not fear at the grocery store
but just my point is there sometimes just when things are unfamiliar
sometimes there's a little bit of fear and so there's this way in which we can
practice with this in a way that can be a real support for our life that is maybe there's um
in the particular when I was talking about these meditation experiences there's a way that these meditation
experiences that I described are usually happening with this settling of the mind
and the body which generally is a pleasant experience.
It's nice to feel some at ease and some settling and some collectedness,
but then as I said, there can be some fear. And then as soon as there's a little bit of fear, it kind of like hijacks our attention
away from what otherwise is a pleasant experience. Might be a little bit unfamiliar, but it's pleasant.
And so one thing can we do and this is a practice is to just learn can we orient
can we incline the mind can we orient towards that which is pleasant
that which is feels like spacious or feels I'm using these words
collectedness or steadiness maybe there's a sense of warmth too maybe
there's a feeling like oh the heart isn't so constricted and tight or the mind isn't running around quite as fast.
So when the fear is just a mild fear and it's happening
at the same time there's something pleasant. This will be a practice. It's
not something we can automatically do. But a just to acknowledge both of these
things are happening. And can we intentionally incline towards the
pleasant and then our capacity to be with discomfort and unfamiliar just grows
will continue. So we're not ignoring the fear. We're
not pretending like it's not there. We're just not letting it take over.
But of course there are times when fear in other situations is stronger when
fear is really has a big pull on us.
And so what can we do then? What are some of the ways we can be with fear? Whatever ways it's showing up in our
lives. I'm generally not talking about the fear that's there with imminent
danger. You know when we see a car coming towards us right and we have to get out of the way. I'm not talking
about that. I'm talking about the fear that arises often from worries we have
about the future or the fear about you know our health or somebody else's
health or something like this. So when that type of fear is arising how
can we be with that in a way that feels like it's supportive with our life in a
way that again we're not pretending like it's not there. We're not ignoring it. We're not suppressing it and but we're
not letting it push us around so much. What can we do? We can investigate it. H
fear is here. What is fear?
Like what is the experience of fear? What is the sensations this collection
this constellation of experiences that we assign the label fear?
because I had a uh I was there was a time when uh I had just some medical
condition which my heart would beat faster. It turned out to you know be fine. I eventually just figured
everything out and got stuff stabilized. But before I knew that I'd be I remember
this in particular giving some talks not dharma talks but some talks in different settings and I would feel my heart
pounding. I'm like, I'm so nervous and like what can I do? And I was feeling like I why am I so nervous? And then I
could just see like my confidence kind of seeking sinking. Like I thought I was prepared, but I'm so nervous. And then
when I started to speak, my heart was pounding. And then I just thought like I don't know. I could just my sense of
myself started to all this doubt came in. Do I not know how to talk or give a
talk or what's happening? And it kind of did not go so well.
But it turned out to not be fear. It was just my heart having a faster heart
rate. So even things that we assign fear doesn't mean that they're actually fear.
But those things that were those collections of experiences that we're assigning fear, we can investigate them.
What is the bodily experience? Maybe there's pound, maybe the heart is pounding and going fast. But chances are
maybe there's like a clenching in the gut or sometimes for me there's like a
lump in the throat or something when I'm afraid. And also there can be a sense
like the body wants to move doesn't want to just stay there. It wants to do something. So there's this sense of
restlessness uh in the body. And we can also notice that there's this thoughts
like they um the the quality of them is like they have a certain pressure and they're going fast and maybe are blurry
and blurry what you know like not so distinct. And the content of them is all about
like what might happen. Not what's happening right now but what
might happen in the future. What's going to happen? Or it's like what does it
mean about me as a person? You can say when that little anecdote that I told about uh when my heart was
beating fast I started to have all like all this what does this mean? Does this mean I don't know how to give talks?
Does this mean that I'm not prepared? You know there's this way in which we our sense of self kind of gets uh
brought into it when often and that sense of self takes the form of thoughts
when we are having fear. So there's bodily sensations, there's thoughts about the future and thoughts about what
this means about us as a person. Usually those thoughts are they're not clear to
us. It's just a collection that's happening.
And the third thing that's often happening is there's a shrinking awareness. It's like, oh, we just come
so concerned about this whatever it is we are afraid of. We kind of aren't noticing
the bird singing or the sunshine or the feeling of the chair against our body if
we're sitting down or who's in front of us necessarily. We aren't noticing much else except what we're afraid of. And
there's this way that this kind of constriction it's kind of unpleasant as opposed to
just this relaxed openness and this relaxed awareness.
That's a third thing or this kind like shrinking awareness. And then a fourth
thing of course is all the aversion we have. We don't like it. We don't like
the bodily sensations. We don't like having those types of thoughts. We don't like the awareness being restriction
being restricted. I don't like it. Make it go away. What can I do to get rid of
it? So all this is in the mix when there's a sense of fear and we can bring our
attention to any of it. All of it.
The point is can we be present right now with the experience?
Because bringing mindfulness to any aspect is helpful. Because what happens
when we start to have this sense of fear, but we're able to just uh notice a
sense of confidence grows. It's like, oh yeah, this is
uncomfortable, but I can I can handle it. I can be with it.
And with this confidence, of course, the fear diminishes because implicit in fear
is the sense of I can't handle it. I won't be able to handle it. This will be
uncomfortable, terrible, horrible, be awful in some kind of way and I won't be able to handle it. Otherwise, we
wouldn't be fearful. Right? So there's this way in which confidence develops
by just being mindful as best we can of any of these aspects of the fear. Bodily
sensation, thoughts, shrinking awareness, aversion. There's four things. You might find something else
that's happening to you. It sounds, you know, like, oh, that
sounds like a good idea. But it's not always so easy to do, right? When we're
in the midst of fear, of course. Of course. And that's why when we have
fear, when we notice we're having fear and really mild, unthreatening
situations, just mild because we're in unfamiliar situations, it's helpful. Can
we just tune into that fear? Or can we tune into any pleasant experience that's
happening with it? That also builds confidence a way in which increases our capacity to be with the fear.
So notice how I didn't say
do whatever you can to get rid of it which is our usual response right to
fear like the we have this aversion. we don't want it and then we're maybe we're
trying to like solve some problem or figure it out or get mad at it or lash
out at people, lash out at ourselves. I'm a terrible person. I shouldn't be afraid of this. You know, logically
there is no reason to be afraid of this.
There's this way that uh maybe wanting to avoid it or make it go away. So this
is aversion which turns into avoidance or turning it or this sense I I have to
fix it. Both of those, the fleeing and the fixing, the wish to flee, the wish
to fix, both of those turn out to just be things in the mind usually. Sometimes
we're jumping up and actually doing things. But yeah right right now I'll
talk about what's happening in the mind that there's this way in which we are like in
uh injecting more and more thoughts into the thinking apparatus. We're already
having this thoughts about well what does it mean about me as a person and things about the future. So some ways
we're disconnected from oursel and then the way in which we try to fix or flee
the situation turns out to be more thoughts. So then we are just in our
mind with lots and lots of think thoughts and we're disconnected from
what's actually happening. What's actually happening probably
uncomfortable but not actually threatening. If it is threatening, then do whatever
you can to, you know, get out of uh harm's way. Absolutely. Right. Of
course. Don't know when the car is coming, when the bus is coming straight towards you, don't think about, oh, how
does this feel in the body? Of course not. So is there there's this way that the
aversion actually perpetuates and often increases
the fear because it's adding to that element of
thoughts. That's an aspect of fear. The more aversion, the more fear.
Less aversion, less fear. They go together.
This is really helpful to keep in mind that the more that we're trying to push it away, the stickier it gets.
This idea of the Torah baby, right? This uh I don't remember the story exactly, but this is what I do remember is that
there's this sticky uh something sticky and then you want to get rid of it and
you push your hand towards it and it like, oh, it's uh um I can't get rid of it. So then you put the other hand and
then oh no and then both hands get stuck and then you know the left foot the right foot and then you're right you're
just completely stuck with this stickied thing fear in fact I would say
even all experiences are the same this is such a key
um key recognition but of course you don't have to take my word for it please
don't just take my word for it find this out for myself explore this
what happens if I just if I orient towards my bodily
experience maybe it's unpleasant but it's happening right here in this moment
I'm taking um energy away from the thinking disrupting the momentum of the
thinking maybe even orient towards intentionally orient towards a neutral bodily experience
towards something that's there that's happening but uh isn't uh fueling that
and you'll discover as the aversion goes down the fear goes down I'm yeah
there's also this way in maybe some part of what the these thoughts are the way that we're judging ourselves thinking
that we shouldn't do this so just note that too like in this collection of thoughts there's this
whole bunch of um that are turn out not to be so helpful.
And there's a poem I like to read here that uh of course it's by Rosemary Tramer. She's one of my favorite poets.
I read her poems often. And uh the name of this poem is called
Moose Musculus, which happens to be the Latin name for mouse.
This is Moose Musculus by Rosemary Tummer.
Today, fear is a mouse that scuttles between thoughts and feeds on whatever
it finds. Nibbles on my certainties, gnaws the
coating off my circuitries, and pulls the stuffing out of each moment.
Those arts droppings in the hallways of my mind. I thought it was worse when fear was a
tiger, a badger, a wolverine. But the mouse of fear finds its way into
everything. Makes nests inside my minutes, discovers
passages into my inner walls, then scratches against them at night.
It never goes near the traps I've set. No, it scampers around them. Its soft
feet pattering its smart its small dark eyes noting everywhere I go.
I love this line there. Those are its droppings in the hallways of my mind.
This way that you know just finds its way in. And I'm pointing to you how a
lot of this is in our mind. And so can we orient towards something
else? But I want to unpack this a little bit more about some of these thoughts.
So the there's a thoughts often are about the future as I said
an example like what what will happen to me maybe in general or specific
like we might have like these vague notions of unsettledness like uh am I
going to be okay in the future? Will I be all right
in the future? Will it turn out okay? What what will it go wrong? go poorly,
go badly, what might go wrong or maybe there's this way and on this on
our for our physical well-being, our emotional well-being,
maybe even our survival, right? Will I have enough enough money? Will I have a
place to live? I mean, these types of things in terms of security or
relationships or possessions, right? Of course, we have these types of fears.
Have this uh this fear that we won't be okay. We have this fear that we won't be
happy, that there won't be well-being. This is normal.
Humans have this. But is fear. So having those then
reacting with fear. But fear tends to push us around and
try to convince us that we should distract ourselves or that we should I
don't know some avoid our things. But what is it that helps
increase the likelihood that there will be well-being, that there will be security, that there
will be happiness. We have this fear that there won't be
but what can we do that will increase the well happiness well-being
and that is cultivating qualities of the heart
cultivating qualities of the mind those that are helpful and skillful and
useful of course we know this I mean dharmat
talks are all about this so often. But there's this way in which we like Yeah.
Yeah. I know that mindfulness would be helpful. Yeah. Yeah. I know that
cultivating some warm-heartedness, some mata or loving kindness or some
compassion is helpful. Yeah. I know that generosity helps uh support a sense of well-being,
helping others, helping ourselves or Yeah. Yeah. I know that equinimity is a
good thing to actively cultivate and like we all hear about this and yet we
often aren't doing it in a way that's kind of be impactful
in a way that uh really helps create the foundation for us to have well-being and
the happiness in the future. There's this way in which because it's
an we aren't putting the investment in now that can help ensure a future that will
have bring some ease and well-being so that we'll have less fear about the
future. Because when we cultivate these
beautiful qualities, they bring happiness. They do. They bring a sense of well-being.
Whether this is mindfulness, which is what we're doing here. Sometimes I've talked a little bit about meta practice.
Maybe I'll bring some of that in. But equinimity or um generosity or
compassion or some of these this old this whole uh host of inner qualities.
So this is how we take care of the future instead of just having fear about the
future is to invest in these qualities.
Paying attention to our mindfulness and daily life. Can we bring some kindness
to our interactions to others? Importantly, can we bring some kindness
to ourselves? There's this way in which the inner
critic just kind of like just running the show so often pushing us around. But
what would it mean to say, you know what, I'm really gonna work with the inner critic
in a certain, you know, like in a committed, diligent or intentional way
or I'm going to work with mindfulness in daily life, not just as part of a meditation practice or I'm going to work
with cultivating some warm-heartedness so that it becomes more and more the
orientation or the um maybe the inner mood food or something like this
because there's a way in which when we do this then the future starts to unfold in a
certain way differently and even if some of those things happen
of uh well will everybody like me and will I be uh okay
even if some things don't go exactly how we wanted them to and let's be honest how things do go exactly as we want them
to, we'll be okay. We'll be okay.
So, I'm not saying that we don't have to take care of our livelihoods and plan for the future. I am not saying that. Of
course, we have to do that. But can we do that as a way of care
instead of fear? And is there a way that this uh when
these all the worries that tend to have such a
big impact on us and influencing so many decisions that we make?
Is there a way that we can create the conditions in which those worries just start to diminish and instead we're just
focusing on cultivating our inner qualities and noticing the relationship
that we have to the present moment just tuning in. Are we meeting right now this
experience with openness? Are we meeting this experience with
curiosity, with mindfulness? Are we meeting this experience with
kindness? As best we can, as best we can. I like to slip that in
there because it's so easy how the inner critic can like, oh yeah, I'm not open
or mindful or kind. And there was that time when I got really irritated with
the driver and who was going 25 miles an hour in the 50 m per hour zone or
something like this whatever it might be. So as best we can
and so this is something that actually makes a difference.
Cultivating some of these qualities really helps uh the us have a future
that doesn't that the not only does the future different but
our worries about the future start to diminish
and there's this way that we have a some some people might have like an
investment portfolio like okay you know I want this to grow as I age, you know,
this type of thing. Often that's associated with money, stocks and bonds or whatever. But is there a way that we
can also have an investment portfolio for our inner life too? Can we invest in
mindfulness as we do here or warm-heartedness?
And there's lots of resources. It's there is an embarrassing amount of
resources on audiodharma.org as well as you know there's so many apps
and books and YouTube videos all these kinds of things so
I have to wait
excuse me sorry about that but what would it be like to just say you know what I am going to invest in something
whatever feels like I don't know feels rich for you whatever your intuition
suggests or something like this and the way to have then will there'll be less
fear in our lives and I kind of like this idea that uh I I
was talking about how aversion increases
fear aversion towards anything but aversion towards spirit, for example. But what if we bring warm-heartedness to
our experience? Warm-heartedness is the opposite of aversion. And so these
unpleasant experiences just go down as we bring warm-heartedness, loving
kindness, compassion, openness, even curiosity to them.
So this way of considering the way that we are just in our daily life as a
support for our futures as an investment for our future also so there's less
fear. So maybe I'll just
read this poem again because there's a way in often that we're just not aware the impact that fear does have in our
life. our our fear about the future.
So this poem is Moose Musculus by Rosemary Tramer.
Today fear is a mouse that scuttles between thoughts and feeds on whatever
it finds. Nibbles on my certainties, gnaws the coating off my circuitries and pulls the
stuffing out of each moment. Those are its droppings in the hallways
of my mind. I thought it was worse when fear was a tiger, a badger, a wolverine. But the
mouse of fear finds its way into everything.
It makes nests inside my minutes, discovers passages into my inner walls,
then scratches against them at night. It never goes near the traps I've set.
No, it scampers around them. Its soft feet pattering its small dark eyes
noting everywhere I go.
So making an investment into wholesome qualities as a way to not only in the
present moment diminish the fear but also take care of those thoughts about
the future which are so often laced with fear. So, thank you.
With that, I'll open it up to see if there are any comments or questions
about uh what I said here tonight. I talked about like wholesome qualities,
but I didn't really go into depth about any of them. So,
my apologies about that, but chances are you know a lot about them.
Yeah. Can we We'll use a microphone.
Thank you, Jim. I um I was just wondering if you could
um repeat what you said about cultivating
um was it wholesomeness or was it that whatever was skillful helpful that the
things that that if you cultivate them help with reducing the fear one piece of
that again and what those what that is what does that look like when you're meditating or what does that look like
otherwise? What does that mean? Yeah. Yeah.
So mindfulness if we bring mindful to an experience of
fear as I was just talking about then we'll notice that there's bodily components and mental components and
aversion and this but there's this and let's say this um so we notice that
there's this constellation and then there's this aversion to it but if we bring mindfulness to his mindfulness
isn't aversion And the aversion is is fueling the fear.
If we bring in something that isn't uh aversion, then it the fear goes down. So
that's one thing in which in the present moment when the fear is there, we can work with it. But not only that, just
cultivating the capacity to be with fear in an example um helps us to meet
everything in the same way. And then our life unfolds in a way that's not being
dictated by fear. And these qualities help create
more openness, more
ease, more happiness. Does that make sense? It's a little bit ciruous. Yeah, I could
see why you were asking this question. Thank you.
Does anybody else have a question comment?
And maybe I'll just throw in something here too. If we look at our fear, it's so much about the future. So I could
have just done a talk about how to take care of your future, cultivate these
wholesome qualities, openness, warmth, mindfulness, compassion.
I could also done a talk of like how to meet fear in the pre present moment. It's the same type of qualities very
often. Mindfulness in particular,
loving kindness maybe. Yes. Yeah. Can we can we use that microphone
please? Uh you were talking about um having um
negative experiences maybe fear um negative thoughts and pu we want to push
them away. Um, it's true and but I wonder because when
I have negative thoughts often what I do is bring myself back to the present and
is that the same as pushing the pushing them away or you know that was well
maybe I'll ask you a question. When you say come back to the present what what does that mean? Oh I might focus on my
breathing. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I would say that's not the same as pushing them away. Like like you're aware the
thoughts are there, chances are, but maybe they're more in the background and the breath is more in the foreground or
something like this. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. pushing them away is a way in which what
I'm talking about is like a it's I'm going like this with my hand like a shoving them down and repressing them
and there's a way in which uh a thought can come up and we just immediately
distract ourselves and the distracting turns out to be enormously effective
that we like oh I'm no longer have that but what when we're just turn towards the breath that's just bringing to the
present moment experience and the thoughts don't disappear.
They just they come back. They come back, but maybe they're less authoritative or not pushing you around
as much or and not even as troubling or bothersome. They're might be unpleasant, but they don't have as much
momentum or I like this word authority. That's going to give to Bill here.
So if if I really dislike fear, I I can handle just about anything else. Um
rejection, loneliness, disappointment, that's all fine or I can work with that.
But I really don't like fear. Um it's very uncomfortable for me. But but when
it comes up and if if I'm fearful of someone
then it's I I don't just look at the fear
that's too uncomfortable. So I kind of do a little side step or jiujitsu move. Um put my attention
somewhere else. So, what I've done a couple of times that helped was to do loving kindness practice for many people
that I know. And um and then I put it off as long as I can, but after I've covered everyone
else, I'll do loving kindness for the person I'm fearful of. And um you know,
it helps a lot. You just feel better afterwards. Excellent. Much less fear,
actually. Excellent. It's one of these wholesome qualities we can cultivate is loving kindness. It's kind of a trick. I
I don't feel like I'm cultivating something worthwhile in me. I'm just, you know, kind of doing what I can. But
but it does help. Yes. Right. Opening the heart, softening the heart. And it's
also right. It's the anti-version. And it's the aversion that kind of really
fuels and make the fear bigger and bigger. It's interesting to me that you started by saying I really don't like fear. Just
being honest. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. No, I don't think anybody likes fear. It's uncomfortable. It's uncomfortable.
But maybe I'll just offer one thing also is that if you wanted you could just be with the bodily experience like oh what
what is the bodily experience of fear? And then just to be with the body experience and let the thoughts just
kind of take care of themselves and just be with oh yeah the a beating heart
feels like this lump in the throat feels like this something like that. When is fear? That's advanced practice Diana but
I'll work on that. Yes I will. Thank you. Thank you Bill.
Um, would you say there's uh like counterpoint
emotions to fear kind of like
like when if we dig around in our fear or like engage our fear
kind of mle through it able to like embrace embrace and just be one and
be okay with our fear? Would you say that there's like counterpoints
that are cuz you call it like a negative emotion like the downsides of been with
fear? Oh, I'm not sure. I don't understand the word counterpoint. I guess what I'm saying is that maybe fear isn't so bad because there's probably
something on the other side of it. Oh, very nice. Yeah. Yeah. I would think
like maybe joy or maybe even ecstasy.
I see. I'm not sure. I think I think if we look at it in that way that this
maybe fear is not, you know, really such a bad thing. Very nice. Yeah. But sometimes logic
isn't always available to us when we're in the middle of fear. Like think like, okay, there's something good on the
other side of this. Sometimes that uh doesn't help us. But I I appreciate what you're saying. Do you do you have a
You're saying joy. Do you is this has this been your experience? I don't know. I was just thinking about
why you're talking. I guess my thought is you know that life is only so long.
Like an emotion like this can be horrible. It's pro, it might be
actually something really really good because
if if we can like engage our fear or kind of accept it or mle through it or be mindful of it somehow that you know
the it'll probably kind of just kind of turn into something
positive. Yep. I would agree. I would agree. And I think in that sense it's just an emotion.
It's not like a It's not like a brick wall. It doesn't
have to be. That's right. It's just a collection of experiences.
That's all it is. But and they're usually uncomfortable. Maybe that's the part though.
Yeah. I was just thinking of like what would be a counterpoint. It was just kind of something I was thinking about or like you know o opposites. Yeah.
Well, I would say I started talking about how sometimes there's fear when we're in some unfamiliar territory.
Sometimes there's a way in which on the other side is fear is uh more
confidence. It's like oh I learned something here and now oh something that I was afraid of I'm not afraid of
anymore. And so there can be some and with that can be with confidence maybe
some happiness or you know ability to I don't know there's all kinds of things that can come from confidence but joy
too. Yeah. Like oh I made it. It wasn't so bad. you know, maybe something like that.
Thank you. Okay, so we're at the end of our time.
So, thank you very much and I wish you a
lovely rest of the evening and safe travels home. Thank you.