so good morning or good day and welcome to this
uh period of time that we're going to explore we're we're exploring insight
for for insight meditation and
um when i practiced as a san francisco zen center there was a quote from the
founder suzuki roshi that went something like this you're perfect just the way you are
and there's room for improvement
and uh maybe i would say we're perfect just the way we are but there's a possibility of further
growth further transformation so this emphasis on being perfect it
goes along with how in the modern mindfulness movement there has been a
big emphasis on mindfulness being non-judgmental awareness where mindfulness is practiced
with a kind of a radical acceptance of how we
are and that's true up to a point that uh or in a particular way
it's true that um this radical acceptance
non-judgmental awareness means we don't condemn anything or resist
anything but we also see clearly that's the insight piece and we see where there
can be improvement we see where we have
tendencies thoughts impulses actions that we do that are not in
harmony with a deep settleness a deep freedom a
deep integrity that is possible to live with
and uh we are looking in fact to not live anymore acting on impulses
of greed hatred and delusion we are looking to become to grow our capacity
for wisdom for peace for joy for love uh
wonderful capacities that we can develop and if we have the opposite of that we
want to somehow see it clearly we want to see that we have attachments
clearly and so this radical acceptance or non-judgmental awareness is not meant
to be an alternative to a realism about what we
want to address what we'd like to change what we'd like to transform
and so part of the art of insight is to have insight have clear seeing of our foibless clear seeing of
where it is that we could change in a way and to want to change to be
available to that change to prepare ourselves for that change partly by seeing more and more clearly
uh what's actually going on for us not pretending otherwise not have
some kind of simplistic or naive acceptance naive non-judgmentalism that doesn't see oh
this is not so healthy what i'm doing what i'm thinking what's going on and uh
let's uh see it more clearly let's see if we can have some better understanding of it and better
relationship to it but the art of this as insight practice
is to see where we have foibless see where we have possibilities for growth
see what we'd like to transform and to change and to shed to do all that
without it being doing it without a reference to judging
ourselves without a reference of being critical or upset or discouraged with
ourselves without building ourselves up and so the radical
acceptance is not that we and and non-judgmentalism is not that we don't
see that we have foibless that there's an evaluation a clear seeing but we
don't use that information as uh data or evidence or or
reason to then uh uh build up stories that were wrong
or bad or the world is bad or it's hopeless and just not adding on to it
just very simply look at that i have anger this anger is not so useful anger
has hostility in it let's take a let's look at it clearly
let's not run away let's not push it away let's not justify it let's just see
it this is something that we want to grow i'm perfect just the way i am but
here's an area of improvement so part of the foundation of insight is this ability to see clearly
um you know what we would like to see changed transformed so to assume a meditation
posture and to take some
time to come into the posture to have an intimacy with your posture maybe swaying
back and forth forward and back in a way that
you're looking for a sense of beautiful alertness beautiful sense of
the body is going to be present here with where where the sense of
awareness arises out of the body out of the sensations of the body
not leaving the body to be somehow
offline in meditation but to have an intentional
posture even lying down it's possible to add some intentionality to it
maybe simply by how you position your hands or your
arms and then gently closing the
eyes and preparing yourself to be aware to be present for
yourself with care with kindness with a without judging yourself
as good or bad but as bringing awareness as a kind of
medicine a kind of self-care a kind of generosity of
goodness to attend to ourselves our inner
life and that can begin by taking a few long deep
breaths relaxing on the exhale
letting the breathing return to normal and with a normal breath continue
to soften relax in the body where the feeling the body and
relaxing the body is done gracefully beautifully
and as you exhale to relax the thinking
muscle the thinking mind softing softening
and then having settled a
bit here and now check in with yourself
how are
you is there anything about how you are right
now that maybe is not so useful for you or helpful for
you in some deep way
something you're thinking about some mood some
attitude and if there is let it
be without judgment of being good or bad
but as
something that would be good to
transform to change to to
shed to leave behind and we begin that
process not by trying to do that but rather
to see be aware [Music] know feel this part of
ourselves in a beautiful way in a graceful way giving it
breathing room to be itself without participating in
it an honest
self-awareness maybe of some way that you are that doesn't serve you doesn't serve the best of you
and then in the middle of that breathe with it breathe through
it as if
breathing brings care and
kindness brings a calming force
and having done that for a little short while now settle in with your
breathing settle in steady
yourself maybe spend a little bit of some minutes here with the samadei of
breathing just breathing
if your mind wanders off in thought maybe that represents a movement
of mind that doesn't really serve
meditation it's not about being here and
now hold the distracted mind kindly beautifully
openly and have the desire to bring the mind
back to change the circumstances of the mind
to let go of the distractions and begin again here and
now with your breathing
and as we coming to the end of this
sitting take a few moments to feel any way in which you're more
settled or calm sitting here in meditation than
than you were at the
and if you are there's be is there some some way
that you're calm and settled that can guide you show
you how to be aware of your inner foibless your inner
challenges is that you would like to transform or
to shed but
first to learn how to hold them calmly with a settle mind and settled
heart being aware without any
impulse to try to change them or get rid of them or judge them
just first to see them and to
know spaciously quietly calmly
yes this is something that would be good to
change and first let me be with it
as it
is and is there anything about how you might be calmer and more subtle
may be clear with your mindfulness that that teaches you some
way how you would like to be in the world with other people
to meet them with calmness with subtleness to meet them with care and
clarity so that you can be friendly or
caring so that you can have space to be well wishing for them
you have the time to gaze upon others with good
will may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of us live our lives to contribute to that
[Music] possibility thank you
[Music]
so welcome to this fifth talk that introduces the topic of insight and today i would like to
emphasize that the classic teachings on inside meditation are offered for a purpose or
to say it differently that um uh inside meditation
uh is designed for a particular for a purpose maybe you can say many purposes
uh but the purpose to institute to in instigate a certain degree of change
transformation within us and uh the most classic buddhist uh
purpose is to become free of suffering to become free of attachments and
clinging and it's a remarkable goal in how thoroughly it changes the
foundational operating system of a human being is it amazing uh that this is
possible and that people experience this other people will see it as more
modest goals purposes to live without stress is a common thing in these
days mindfulness is offered as stress reduction uh to understand oneself better to be
more self-accepting to be uh to just to get settled enough and see clearly enough to
be able to see the world with eyes of love and kindness so there there's many
many purposes people can have but the the purpose is to have some transformation and change and so part of
the practicing inside meditation is to have some sense of what purpose you have
for it um do you have a vision for how you'd like to change how you'd like to
be different do you have a sense of what what why you're doing this practice and um it's not necessary to
have that that when i there was a period of time when i practiced that i didn't know why i practiced i just knew that i
was doing it but uh sooner or later when as inside
practice one of the foundational element of it is to have a a uh a directionality
a purpose a a some motivation for doing it that's more than just being present
in a clear full way um it's uh it's to
uh have a transformation and uh it's kind of a
meant to be a natural motivation a natural inclination
uh this desire to to change that's no different than if you have a thorn in um
you know a finger that you would maybe want to pull it out if you have a thorn in the mind um
it's a kind of a natural to want to pull it out if possible and um so uh to see this as a
natural thing having some desire to change some desire to take out a thorn
it does not mean that we're caught in detachments that we're caught in desires that we're doing an uh unddist thing
where we are not supposed to have any desire just to be with what is in a naive
way no the the purpose of being present for uh way things are to be with things
as they are is to serve a larger purpose and the purpose is to become
free free of attachments free of stress free of uh uh you know distracted mind
an agitated mind so e everyone each person will have a different maybe a
purpose uh and um but uh it does involve
knowing ourselves well enough to recognize that there's something here that we want to change and
transform and um and it doesn't take a lot of you know self-awareness to
appreciate that we have some foibless we have some things that we're not necessarily proud of or not necessarily
so happy or about it because it's not healthy or it's actually harmful maybe
it's not dramatically harmful but while it's happening it's actually kind of um
a drag that it's going on or you know it doesn't feel like we have we're in full
integrity and um and so one of the descriptions of what happens in practice
meditation practice is that um uh it can be you can be described in an
analogy that um say that you're driving a car maybe it's a nice you know it's a
jeep or something across a really dirt bumpy dirt
road and uh and it's difficult to go because it's bumping a lot and you shake
king the car and bumping and and you try to drive slow enough but it's still you know jarring to go up and down and uh so
it's hard to do so at some point you figure out uh you know little bit of a
solutions you get a really soft cushion to sit on and that makes it a little easier but it hasn't changed how much
the car is jarring and bouncing around and uh but then lo and behold you
come to a paved asphalt road that's completely flat and smooth maybe newly
paved and it goes "ah it's so good to be off the all the bumpy dirt
road." but then you notice that that you hadn't noticed before that there's
something a little bit wobbly about the axle of the car and in fact every turn of the wheel
there's a little jar a little bump a little knock that goes on and u doesn't
seem so good for the car doesn't seem so safe and it um it uh but you you
wouldn't have known that that little knock and little u uh you know hiccup of
the of the axle uh was there as long as you were on the road that had all the
bumps and everything you needed to be off it to see it and and then you maybe
fix the axle and then you go back onto that dirt road and it turns out now the dirt road isn't so bad that some of the
difficulty you had was because of the wonky axle so in this analogy as we live
our busy life active life you know a lot of thoughts a lot of concerns preoccupations
um it's difficult to see uh the axles we have that are wonky that
ways that we are little bit off and so the purpose of samadei and mindfulness
meditation is to calm down get quieter and as we do that we start discovering
what we didn't see before that something is not quite aligned something's not quite right and um and and then maybe we
settle that we get the axle fixed and we get uh it isn't just like a one-time
thing then we got quieter still more focused and then we see there's another
area where it's now we're quiet enough still enough to notice another axle that's a little wonky and so it could be
progressively the process of deepening in inside deepening in samadei reveals
deeper and deeper areas of attachment of clinging that we have and this is not
bad news this is actually good news because we can only free ourselves or we
can only transform what we know and see so to the degree to which uh practicing
uh mindfulness practice brings bad news in that we see ourselves more clearly uh
we should really learn to see that as good news ah good i see it now this is
what i have to include in my practice i don't want to go back onto the really bumpy road so i don't even see what's
going on deeply inside of me i want to kind of really practice with this the best i
can and um so part of the uh doing
insight meditation is to have some sense of purpose that supports you to go
really deeply in the practice to be able to address and meet all the ways that uh
your inner life is challen challenging or challenged and um and to be able to then
hold it in a good way in a beneficial way and one of the ways is to be able to
be with it in a relaxed spacious way uh where you don't see that having an inner
foable is a crime or having some kind of anger or attachment or clinging or
strong desires uh makes you a wrong person uh this is what human beings do
what what's really healthy is to see it and know it it's really healthy then to
hold it in a spacious way and not use it as a dart to
criticize oneself to make on to judge oneself because what the mind is doing
or producing and um and then to have a desire for change to be motivated for
that change and most importantly to be willing to
change to kind of be open and and prepared to not uh hold on to the most
cherished attachments most cherished ways of being most cherished ideas of comfort um so that we can't really do
this deeper work of going into um uh all the dark corners of our mind and hearts
so part of uh purpose of insight is transformation is transforming changing
freeing aspects ofelves ourselves that we feel are not so useful to have not
helpful that bring suffering to us bring distress to us bring um debilitating
emotional pain to us of some sort and um and in the process of that
transformation uh we also want to uh recognize not just what we would like to change uh in the
that because we want to get rid of it or not have it there we also want to recognize our potential the capacity the
seeds inside of us for healthy states of heart and mind for our goodness our
capacity for kindness and joy capacity for happiness and peace the capacity for
resolve and and uh truth and integrity there's a lot of goodness that
we can be developed through through insight so sometimes the insight practice reveals areas that we want to
shed sometimes in insight practice reveals the areas that we want to
grow and uh mindfulness is a remarkable remarkable
uh uh practice uh mindfulness or attention clearly seeing is kind of like
a light that um uh uh shines on what's
healthy it grows if it shines on what is not healthy within us it tends to take
its nutrient away and um the nutrient is comes in the darkness uh when we have
the hindrances we don't see what's going on and how we're feeding the hindrances but when we uh have light we stop
feeding it and they fade away if we see in the darkness we don't see our
goodness but in the light we can see it and more we see that it tends to grow
so this two-fold transformation that insight instigates or supports and um
fading away what doesn't serve and bringing forth more of what does serve
without it being so intentional or it's not an engineering project a lot of it
has to do with seeing clearly and appreciating the intention
for a transformation appreciating a ch a possibility to change to
improve and to quote again uh suzuki
roshi the founder of san francisco zen center one wonderful attitude to have
for all this is the idea that you're perfect just the way you are but there's
room for improvement and part of the practice is to allow for that improvement of ourselves
so um with that we've offered you some foundational aspects of insight insight
meditation practice and how it works and um next week uh we'll start getting into
it uh where there's a more direct introduction to um five different forms
of insight areas domains of insight that um that come into play as we practice
and it's useful to see these different areas so that um you can see more clearly what's
happening so thank you and i look forward to continuing