good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all it's so great to practice together I don't know I I hope it's nice for you guys too that we're just sitting
together there's something really uh beautiful about
it so I just tonight I wanted to talk about sometimes there can be a Feeling
of we're just kind of stuck like maybe we don't have a sense
of that we're really going anywhere maybe we don't even have a sense that we
should be going anywhere but uh we have this feeling of okay maybe we are
meditating regularly but there's not a feeling of
Vitality or movement or juiciness or r nness maybe there's a sense of dryness
about it or maybe there's this feeling that just for not like going anywhere I know
that there was a I often am keeping a notebook of some
of my ideas and that kind of help inform my drama talks but also my practice and
uh there was a time when I looked at this uh notebook this is some time ago
and I realized really I was thinking and worrying about that years ago also and
here I am you know so there can be this way in which we feel like H there's not
not much uh happening and then if we there's this
way in which if we look at it carefully we can often notice there's this slight
disconnection there's this slight separation from our our actual
experience instead we're lost in our thoughts lost in Concepts lost in ideas
lost in speculation we think we're meditating and we think we're practicing just like
we have before but there's often it's because there's something we want to
avoid so we disconnect just a little bit and that just that little bit is a way
in which we just end up spinning in our mind and not really going anywhere we're
not connected to what's actually happening in the present moment it's more we're thinking about the present
moment or thinking about the practice and what I'm pointing to here is a subtle difference it can be easy to not
recognize it but maybe one way to a clue
can be the role that words have if there's a lot of words whether there're
sentences chapters or novels there's a a way that the ner the
words can take us away from the experience feeling the pressure against
the body from the cushion feeling the temperature of the air feeling the tension in the shoulders you know
whatever it is that uh might be experienced and there's this way that
sometimes it's not all the time but sometimes what I'm describing could uh fall under the hindrance that we call
vcha doubt doubt is this way in which there's
this uh vacillation there's is the mind is kind of spinning there this not quite
engaged it's not that we're completely absent but we're not completely engaged
either maybe there's this where we have some reservations or as I said we're
trying to not feel something but in order to make sure we don't feel that we
don't feel anything else either or just have this indecisiveness or maybe a
sense of Suspicion like this isn't quite right or I shouldn't be doing this or I
can't do this or you know something like this kind of things that have that flavor of not being sure not uh kind of
like committed and um in with the practice with this way in which we're
hesitating and so so and I'm actually I'll say that if we do pay attention we
might see that there's this family of or a loose collection of thoughts as that's
often is what's uh being experienced there's a kind of like a certain
direction or family of or orientation that's uh happening in the
mind and there's often when um I'm teaching about doubt it's some of you might know it's uh one of the five
hindrances one of recognized I mean thousands of years ago the Buddha talked about this as something that can get in
the way um when I've talked about this before I've talked about that an
antidote a way to work with this is investigation to kind of like roll up our sleeves and get in like what's
actually being experienced or what am I unsure about
what questions do I have and try to like nail them down
but sometimes this whole idea of Investigation turns out not to be so helpful sometimes it's great and exactly
what's needed and can help um provide the traction that's needed to have a
sense of a vitality and juiciness and aliveness in our
practice but sometimes investigation can just lead to more thinking and we could
say that more thinking was the problem to begin with and then we say oh just investigate and that gets interpreted as
thinking and then we're just thinking is upon thinking and we're just
thinking instead of like uh really get engaged so I'd like to offer something
tonight that is a little bit maybe more specific or something that
um can maybe provide some direction of how to gain traction when we feel like
we're stuck or a little bit disengaged or I'm not sure exactly what the words are to
describe it and this is
um maybe I can summarize it in the like really high level is to bring in this
notion which is called s is the word in poly has a really clunky English
translation it's called clear comprehension
I guess it's you know it's good enough the ja is related to jity which
is knowing p is like really knowing and some p is
uh kind like knowing it's Al we'll just say really knowing so clear
comprehension this how it often gets uh translated and it's very similar to
mindfulness and often can be synonymous so in the Su some of you
might be familiar with this they talk about Sati s so mindfulness and clear
comprehension but when you really look in the suit does it's really difficult to tease them apart like what exactly is
the difference however uh maybe like 800 years after
the Buddha or the death of the Buddha there was a some people who are were
writing commentaries you know like interpreting the teachings of the Buddha and they wrote you know just a
tremendous amount and they were like defining the terms and providing the backstory for uh
some of the characters that are in some of the stories and something like this and in these commentaries they flesh out
this idea of clear comprehension which I think could be useful in this uh scenario when we feel
like things aren't quite going just not going or don't have traction so in the
commentary so this is not the words of the Buddha but almost a thousand years later still that's quite some time ago
that's what 1500 more than 1500 years ago they um defined a clear
comprehension they put it into these four categories and I would like to unpack these as a little bit just as a way to
help us maybe get engaged so rather than just I'll just
introduce one category at a time so here the first one is just to have this
sensitivity or to tune in what is the purpose of what I'm
doing why am I doing this whatever it is you might be doing this is something you
could be doing in meditation but it also could be you know just in your daily
life but just to sometimes have this sense of like what because sometimes what we
think is the purpose isn't the purpose for example you find yourself standing
in front of the refrigerator with the door open now why am I what why am I here
with the the door open and you might say well because I wanted to open the door
of the refrigerator and so I did okay that's one answer but there could also
be well I don't want to feel loneliness so uh I'm just distracting Myself by
looking in the refrigerator I don't want to feel this sadness so I'm making a
snack I'm going to go to the grocery store later and I'm just going to take inventory of what we have and what we
don't have right so there's all these different reasons why we might or I'm
going to cook dinner for my family I love them I want to take care of them this is part of what I do right
there's so many reasons why we might open up the refrigerator this is just like one
example but there's this way in which if we're going there because we are trying
to avoid something else we're using it as a distraction then often we
won't really be tuned into to what we're doing there and so if we can ask
ourselves well what is my purpose here this can be a way in which we get
engaged and maybe we say because I want to distract myself because I feel
awful that is fantastic even to just to say because I feel awful like sometimes
even just to say it out loud and to recognize I feel awful I don't want to feel this and I want to distract
myself that is being with what's actually
happening wanting to distract this is good practice to just
be with what's happening wanting to distract is what's happening we're not
saying that you have to feel the terrible thing that will arise in its good time it'll get metabolized when
it's ready to get metabolized but to maybe could Fe just recognize yeah I I don't want to feel
sadness anymore I don't want to feel loneliness anymore I don't want to feel whatever it is I'm standing in front of
the refrigerator with the door open or another place in which we could
use this um idea of purpose is with our
speech with what we're saying we could have just this clear or sorry this quiet
in the background sense of why am I saying
this is it because um I want them to I want to impress this
person is it because I want them to like me
is it because I'm trying to help them I see that they're in some distress and it's making me uncomfortable and I don't
want to feel that so I'm just going to try to make them fix their problem so that I'm no longer distressed or maybe
I'm talking because I love them and I want to connect with them and care with
them or maybe there's this way that um we just find ourselves speaking
impulsively and we don't even know why we're talking we're so this is a great way to get
connected with ourselves to ask you know to have some this query like why am I saying this this has uh been a practice
for that I've been doing for some time don't always remember but wow it's
really powerful really powerful to just notice that uh what are the things that
motivate our speech sometimes we just feel like we need some attention that's okay but can we maybe
just acknowledge yeah I'm feeling disconnected and so I'm talking to uh
connect with people or or to show how much I know but there's this way if we find
ourselves complaining or explaining there's often a way in which
that's also a way of avoiding just like standing in front of the refrigerator snacking if we're complaining and
explaining I think there's one other aing but I can't remember
it yeah it doesn't come to my mind right now but but if we find ourselves doing
that there's a way in which uh we're um
also feeling disconnected from ourselves and wanting to distract ourselves so we
could just ask why why am I saying this or maybe we can have um ask
ourselves this when we or sit down to meditate why am I meditating do I have a purpose in mind
for this even if it's the same answer every
time there's a way in which just asking the question why am I doing this what is the purpose here you might find because
I want to find more ease and freedom in my life because uh I believe that um more
calm and steadiness is available because I recognize that my day unfolds
differently if it includes meditation and even if you find that you're saying
the same thing again and again there's just this orientation towards why am I
doing this because there can be a way in which okay I'm doing this again because
I'm supposed to I'll put the timer on and I'll sit here and you know there's this way that we're just not really
showing up we're sitting on the cushion but we're not not really showing up but
we only have so much energy in this life only have so much time in this life and
it can be really helpful to to kind of like align with what's important what's important for us what is what do we want
to spend our life energy on what do we want to spend our time
on and then maybe I'll just say that pointing to this like Reflections or
these contemplations about is this aligning what is the purpose and is it
aligning with a purpose that I want maybe we find ourselves watching Netflix
and off a lot like is this uh what I want to do with my
life Netflix wants you
to so maybe these are types of questions maybe if when we're out for in a walk or
out for a walk or in the forest or outside and sometime it can be nice
sometimes to drop in some of these questions like what is important what are some of the things
that are important for me and what are some of the when are the things that I'm spending my time and energy with are
they aligned with them and then the second aspect of Clear
Com comprehension is this uh notion of uh
suitability we might say like is it is it the appropriate uh thing to be doing
or is it uh fit the situation is it the right response is it suitable what we're
doing whether this is on the cushion or in daily life or whatever we might find
ourselves is I mean the obvious or maybe I should say the maybe it's a cliche
this idea of um maybe trying to get water from a rock if you want water then
why are you going to the Rock and not pounding on it you should be pounding on a coconut or
cutting up an aloe vera or you know something like this or going to the stream of course you know these types of
things so how this might show up and I've seen this uh in meditation there
was a time when I was uh teaching what we call happy hour couple days a week it's still going on um 6:00 to 7:00 p.m.
it's online Monday through Friday and um for a few years I was
teaching this couple times a week uh just and it's loving kindness and compassion practices heart heart
practices and uh I would have like a um a little Q&A at the end and I was so
surprised how people were really sincerely wanting to cultivate the
warm-heartedness really wanted to cultivate some you know softness of the
heart and then the questions that they would ask they would be so mean to to
themselves I can't do this I'm a terrible meditator um something's wrong with me
there wouldd be this way in which they'd be so mean to themselves and not even recognize it like we're we're trying to
cultivate kindness and warmth and openness and yet they spent the whole time beating themselves
up it's easy to do this right especially if beating oneself up is a familiar
thing and we just think it's the normal way to be but there's this way in which it can be
really helpful just to ask is this uh suitable what we're trying to do the
way that we're approaching this whatever it is we'd like to do are we approaching
it in a way that's suitable for us and recognizing that all of us of course are individuals we have different strengths
and different life situations or in different seasons of Life different
energy levels different Health you know this is this is what it means to be a human is you know these change
throughout our life and we just ask ourselves giving given this the
circumstances of our life is the way that I'm approaching what I would like
to do suitable are we putting in the right
amount of effort too much effort or not enough effort or something like this
because there's this way in which just even asking the question even if the answer isn't quite clear can be really
helpful it's a way to kind like get us engaged again with our life with our
meditation practice with whatever's
happening maybe I'll say that um you know Buddhist practice this movement
towards greater and greater PE Peace and Freedom and ease and well-being it's not a linear you know step one step two step
three step four I mean sometimes we teach it in certain steps but that's not
how it goes I mean nobody's life goes you know just in a straightway linear to
uh to perfect Enlightenment but there's always things
that need to be Revisited and maybe there's an domain of our practice which is really unfolding and Bloss boming but
maybe there's a domain in which we feel kind of like stuck maybe we have some of this doubt that shows up some of our uh
inner critic shows up and we find this revisiting this again and again and again but there can
also be times in which there's some real openness and spaciousness and ease and
we might be like cycling through that is so this suitability this question of
suitability doesn't mean that we have to say well I should be on step three now because I was on step two whatever step
three might be instead just this
recognition that given who we
are and the what we're the direction we're trying to go is it appropriate is our
response appropriate and then there's also having
said this there's also a way in which we can also recognize that trying to spend
time figuring out what is exactly is the what is the meaning of life what is my
purpose that's not what I'm pointing to here there can be some questions about
this like well what what is my purpose I'm not going to there isn't one
answer to this and if you're looking for one clearcut answer you may find
yourself swirling around looking for that or waiting for
that there can be a way in which we have some clarity and it feels like the answer is somehow to support others or
to be um a way in which to bring some more ease and wellbeing just into the
world but that gets expressed in so many different ways countless different
ways so I don't want to suggests that we have to like find this one meaning or
purpose so also this idea about suitability of course can get carried
into our daily life just in the same way that uh maybe it's the same family maybe
we're with the same group of people the same family members for example so maybe a very similar setting might even be in
the same location but what's suitable well if
we're having a remembrance or a funeral or honoring the death of somebody what's
suitable there is different might be the same people same location for a sweet 16
birthday party very different and so just for us to have some sensitivity
well what is what is like this moment asking for what is this
situation asking for and and that's an interesting way to put it what is it asking for as opposed
to what do I want if we're just going to always be pushed around by our
preferences what we like what we don't like then that's we're going to kind of often be spinning our wheels just
chasing chasing chasing chasing our preferences turns out they don't get
satisfied you might have noticed that there's this hedonic treadmill right that we're always just
looking for the next thing so the
suitability the third dimension of this clear comprehension that could help us
if we're feeling like stuck or not quite engaged in some kind of way is this idea
of the domain um the word in poly is
Goa and uh it literally means uh cow
walking cow walk so we can understand it like
pasture so we would say like domain so where where is it that uh like maybe we
could say cows hang out and are nourished and protected that we would
say where are we nourished and protected what what what is our domain what is our
pasture where is a good place for us to hang out literally and figuratively but
figuratively the Buddha pointed to these found foundations of mindfulness that is uh bringing some
attention to the body uh feeling tone Fad in up mind
States chitt and I guess what we'll
call D so the poly word is dhas but it's hard to translate that uh categories or
the types of things that are in the dhas is the five hindrances for no truths
seven factors of Awakening these are the type of things that are in that fourth category so of the recommendation of the
Buddha is the domain is to be with your experience between those four categories
will be all of your experiences the bodily experience and
the mental experience if we could divide it those two ways all of that gets
covered in these foundations of mindfulness so that the domain points
to just being with these channels of
experience whatever is being experienced doesn't mean it's uh what we want to
have happen or doesn't mean what we intended to doesn't mean that uh we might have sat down and said okay I'm
going to do mindfulness of the breathing suitable for I want to have some settledness and so that I can have
some better well-being and then we discover we sit down and then our back is just killing us and then we discover
okay I'm not going to do mindfulness of breathing I'm going to be with this uncomfortable experience in my
back and then noticing how the mind is wanting to make lots of stories about
it so well that would be an example of just using kind of like the domain is
just being mindful of these I we could say these
uh four Avenues of mindfulness but maybe it's
easier to say what's not nourishing and that is just this mental proliferation
just the way that the mind can spin and spin this what I'm calling like doubt this hesitation this
vacillation that's not nourishing so instead to spend our energy our life energy and
our attention on what is nourishing
and then the last category of uh clear comprehension
s is non delusion I'm like but how does that
work when we're having delusion we don't know because we're diluted so there's this way in which we
could just say it's about being aware of our thoughts just having some awareness
of thoughts and not to get pushed around by them to recognize that sometimes when
we're going to go to a new place meet a new person be in a different situation or even if we've been to it
before we often are have we're fabricating a story about how it's going
to be or maybe we are rehearsing a conversation we're going to have with somebody that we're going to meet it's
perfectly appropriate to plan but there's this way in which we are just cooking up this whole scenario 100% in
our heads and then when we get there right of course it never goes the way that we
thought it would never does am I allowed to say the word never there that's I I'd
be surprised I'd be surprised if it does never precisely the way we thought it
would so this non- delusion is to recognize oh this is just a story I have
about how it's going to go and to recognize the storess of the story
instead of thinking like oh yeah this is actually how it should go and then when things start to go differently start to
complain or uh feel frustrated because our expectations aren't being met or
something like this so This non- delusion is to recognize oh yeah I have a story about this I have these ideas
and it's just a story or maybe there's this way of that
we can look at our thoughts with some meditation practice we can the
mind can be settled and we can just notice when thoughts are arising and see them as like oh wow look at that instead
of getting lost in it and then we can reflect we didn't make that thought
arise we didn't do anything to make it arise we didn't control the content of
it we didn't control the duration of it we didn't control the thought that followed that thought these things are
just arising and there's this way with this recognition of how we aren't controlling
them there can be this well there's a way in which we're not that's not who we
are like it's these aren't you know inherent to who we are as individuals we
are not our thoughts even though so often we feel like we are there's a way in which we feel connected to them but
just to notice how we we aren't doing anything to have them arise that can be
some non- delusion is to not take our thought so personally thinking that
we're making them happen or not making them happen or something like that so this idea of clear comprehension
purpose suitability domain and non delusion these are four different ways
four different levers maybe four different approaches that we can bring to our experience either on the cushion
or off the cushion as a way to help get re-engaged as a way to help us uh feel
like um bring some Lively uh some aliveness maybe some Vitality to our
practice and maybe undo some if there's any sense of stuckness and this
stuckness sometimes is in the form of doubt about 100% of the time but sometimes this sense of Doubt is H what
is the stuckness so maybe in this way there can be this
movement from stagnation to Clarity this movement
of maybe a stuckness to non
stuckness and with that I think I'll open it up and see if there's some questions or comments thank you
I remember when I played uh quarterback at Ma you know high school and at
throwing an interception and Son as the coach would leave me in the game and just said keep playing and it showed a
kind of faith in me you know as the quarterback right I'm wondering what role faith has in all of this because
your intuition is very shy right it doesn't he doesn't want to get you know smacked away so what does faith have in
helping that to come forward I think I thank you for asking us that's a great
question um I would use the word a certain amount of confidence but faith is actually a great is a great word too
I think that's uh you're right it takes a certain amount of faith and confidence to even like for example engage with
what I was saying and to stay in there yeah thank you for bringing this up I think it's a great point
yeah thanks for the talk um it's given me a lot to think about I think personally um one thing it reminded me
of or got me thinking about is um struggling with the concept of softness
of heart um so i' love to hear a little bit more about that or um it's kind of a
relatively new topic for me in addition into like the uh Insight pieces that we
normally get but how to develop a softness of heart is would be of
interest okay maybe I I'll say briefly about it one way there's a number of
different ways you can practice with it and one way and that uh I like to teach
is that we start by bringing to mind a lovable being whether this is an actual
being or an imaginary one so it's often just like kittens and puppies and babies
or grandkids or so somebody with whom we have an uncomplicated relationship and
we have this you know we have this tenderness towards them some care can
also be maybe somebody in our past who was a coach or a mentor or a guide that
really helped us and we have like so much appreciation for them so either of
those things and then we connect like we bring them to to mind like imagine them
could be one way and we connect with uh this sense of appreciation or care that
we have and then there's certain phrases that we can repeat to help kind of um
excuse me to help uh what's the word I'm looking for maybe
to um nurture that uh connection in that sensation and we just stay there for a
little while and it's quite simp thing how if we say it just naturally starts
to grow on its own if we allow it so start where it's the absolute easiest
this is the key people want to start where well I'm having problems with my co-worker I'm going to try to have warm
feelings towards my coworker but it's to really start where it's the absolute easiest and hang out there for quite
some time in fact it can be a long time it can be months it can be just there's
something cuz often maybe if I've been talking about stuckness part of uh
sometimes stuckness can be because there's a way there's a part of us that is starving for some of this warmth and
care and tenderness and so there's a way in which just hanging out with uh cultivating it
that's the word I was looking for cultivating it can be so supportive for
us really just uh can bring also some vitality and energy and juiciness to our
practice is is this helpful yeah thank
you anybody else have a comment or
question okay so I'm wishing you all a wonderful
rest of your evening and safe travels home and may you not feel stuckness but
instead feel some of this juiciness and vitality of life thank you