welcome welcome hello good evening
while we were meditating the thought arose like "Oh why didn't I do this earlier?" I don't know it's just I just
love sitting with you guys and just think like "Oh I should just spend the whole day here at IMC and whoever shows
up and sit with them or something like this."
Excuse me so last week I introduced this idea the simile of the raft
many of you might be familiar with this simile it's a well-known one gets
interpreted in a number of different ways and different emphases put on
different parts of it and last class well maybe I'll introduce
the idea what it is first so this uh it's part of Majima 22 the algatupama
suta kind of hard to say simile of the snake so it's in a suta that has a
number of different simileies but this one is simile of the raft
and it goes something like this imagine a person in the course of a journey
arrives at a great expanse of water whose nearshore is dubious and perilous
and the far shore is a sanctuary free of peril
but there's no fairy boat or bridge to cross the water
so the person thinks what if I collected grass twigs branches and leaves and
bound them together as a raft and supported by the raft and by paddling with my hands and feet I should then be
able to reach the other side of the shore the simile continues but I'm going to
stop here and talk about last week I talked about the nearshore being dubious
and perilous i'll say just a little bit about that but today I want to talk about the far shore and next week I'll
talk more about this idea of a raft so maybe I'll unpack a little bit more
this um this simile this idea of going on a journey we could say this is just
one's life one way we can consider it as a journey
it's not the only way and not doesn't work in all situations but one way could
be as a journey and this great expanse of water there something like that's
getting in the way that we just find ourselves in contact with or seeing or noticing or
experiencing and we could say that well even the
sutas talk about it can be considered like a flood like you know this thing that makes you feel overwhelmed there
something that's just uh coming this way and there's nothing to be done it feels like except to be swept away
and we don't like this feeling of being swept away feeling overwhelmed
but also there's a way in which we could understand this great expanse of water as just this existential dooka
i'm using this word dooka i always like to uh define it this way there's this huge broad range to just this mild
feeling like something's not right to oh my gosh this is the terrible most awful
thing that's ever happened so this one word for this wide range duka
and so there's this way in which sometimes when we encounter some terrible diagnosis for ourselves or for
a loved one this is some existential dooka like wow okay my life uh maybe
it's going to end in a way that I wasn't expecting or at a time I wasn't expecting or this person whom I love
maybe they are going to have some adjustment to their lifespan their
expected lifespan or or Maybe they're going to have a lot of pain or maybe we're going to have some a lot of pain
nobody wants this but often there's it can be avoided this is something that
life brings to us sometimes or maybe there's this way this sense of
dooka is the sense of like oh I just my life would be okay if only
if only those people over there would start behaving better would just
uh get it together or do what they should or you know the list is online
those people over there or maybe it's like oh my gosh if only this person over here
if only I had more willpower if only I could like force myself to do all the
things I know I should be doing but somehow am not doing or maybe if only I were different in some fundamental way
or it's amazing the things that we come up with how we think we should be different it's never ending right or it
can be endless and so this idea of the nearshore is
where you find yourself and it's only the nearshore because it's compared to something over
there otherwise it's just your life right that's happening but it's the nearshore
because it's not over there and over there is this far shore this idea that we have that somehow it's better it's
not in contact with this dooka somehow it's going to be better maybe it's not
clear to us exactly how or maybe it is clear to us of how everything would be fine as soon as we get there and we know
exactly what there is going to look at and so I want to talk a little bit about
this idea of the far shore
some of you might uh know this that sometimes it gets uh defined as nibbana
nibbana is the poly word for nirvana which is a way for awakening or
enlightenment or something like this it's not something that gets talked
about so often there a number of reasons for this I can imagine
maybe I I'll offer some one reason is it's guaranteed to not be
satisfying you're not going to get a description that feels like oh okay I got it yeah
okay yeah no problem it's there it doesn't have it's not possible for it to
have a description that is completely satisfying because the mind
that's trying to understand it is not the mind that can understand it
there's this way in which we want to we we do this all day long and it's very
helpful and useful where we there's an experience and then we slap a label out
of thin air in some ways you know it's a mental event stick it on and like oh okay this is frustration
and then we have a relationship with this word frustration meanwhile the relation the experience might have ended
or completely changed and is no longer that but we slap a label on it and then we have a relationship with the concept
the idea about it and nibbana
it's it's about not having concepts it's about how concepts are concepts they're
not actually what's being experienced they are about it's about just this um
it's sometimes defined as non-clinging and clinging ing happens in the obvious
ways please don't leave me i'll do anything if you don't leave type of thing that we can do whether that's we
don't want uh individuals to leave us or we don't want experiences to leave us
but it's uh this non-clinging and the gross ways and the really subtle ways
are the clinging to the idea that something should be clear and
stable and have a label and have some constancy to it and nabana is not that
so it usually gets described in terms of what it isn't it's not clinging
it's the ending of greed hatred and delusion so what's
what's being experienced when there's just nothing but clarity and no
resistance none it's for me kind of the way that I'm uh
imagining it especially in the context of this uh suta of the simile of the
raft there's a way in which we might imagine like a river or a creek or a stream this
flowing uh body of water how things just move and how sometimes like we can take
a bucket stick it in the water and say oh okay here's what this is what's in
here is the river and kind of not realizing like oh no
actually the river is this moving thing this is the same idea I was talking about with concepts there's this way in
which we scoop up some water And okay then we start working with this thinking that it's the river but it's not and the
non- delusion non greed non-hatred is the way in which we're creating this
scooper and we're doing the activity of scooping
and looking into it we could say that's one way we could this is greed hatred
and delusion is uh doing that this is really subtle and it's maybe doesn't
make any sense but maybe it does in some kind of way too this recognition of
wanting to solidify or raify or uh make something solid and permanent
and stable and something like that it's this really fundamental
uh deep maybe wish that we have because it's tied up with this idea of like okay
I just need a place where I can rest where everything is stable and happy and
clear i just I just I just haven't found it yet i just got to keep on looking i got to keep on looking oh it's not here
okay i got to keep on looking and we can spend our whole life looking for this place where oh I can finally rest and
where we've arrived and we never have to seek again
that doesn't exist and it turns out to not be a problem
that it doesn't exist it's the thinking that we need it that's
the problem not the absence of this final place to rest
so another way in which we might understand like freedom maybe more generally if not exactly nabana is uh
this absence of uh identifying with things this absence of
having experiences be all about me
like for example just like you know maybe sadness arises wave of sadness
and then there's the thought it's not uncommon for thought patterns to arise
oh I have to fix this I can't have this no this is not good I don't want this
there's a sense of oh this is a problem and I have to fix it or
um maybe something another way we can identify with it is oh my gosh this
sadness again i don't want to experience this again i you know I spent a decade so sad i I I I thought I was over it and
I got to do something different i've been trying to outrun this my whole life and here it is again
i'm not saying that any of the none of this isn't uh actual experiences
what I'm saying is the stories the narratives
that get attributed to an experience are extra
they don't need to be there it's just sadness it's just sadness
it doesn't have to be a problem it doesn't have to mean anything about us as a human doesn't have to mean anything
about us as a a failure or a success or
happy person or a sad person it doesn't mean anything
it's just sadness that's being experienced and it arises
and passes away this is a radical idea this is a radical
idea that uh things just are as they are they're being experienced the way
they're being experienced i'm not talking about uh passivity i'm
not talking about being uh half comedos or something like this
right where you just uh totally disconnected from experience
i'm talking about just recognize it feeling the fullness of life and like oh
here's this experience oh there here's another experience that one uh arose and let away oh here's another
one rose and uh passed away and just realizing that's actually what life is
and it's beautiful so I want to talk about some of the
ideas that we might have like unknowingly bringing to ideas of what the far shore
is or what freedom is and often when I'm talking about this in dharma talks I'm using the word peace ease and freedom be
and I'm using these words because I want everybody to be able to find what's meaningful for them maybe ease is really
what's meaningful for them or maybe peace is or maybe freedom or maybe different days it's different i I want
all of us to be able to find uh what's meaningful for us or be able to relate to this in a way that's meaningful
instead of saying oh it's about some thing that you don't understand or or
maybe doesn't you're not interested in
so here are some common ways and I know and I certainly
had all of these i I absolutely had because unknowingly
I did and I see this happening in a lot of people too in the absence of our
talking about what is freedom then people just fill in the blank of course
they do of course they do and what gets filled in the blank in terms of like okay well what is freedom really or or
is there yeah what is is there a big range of it is there just one type or
you know all this type of stuff what happens is that we often are failing in
the blank with what we want of course and what kind of the dominant culture
suggests is something that's the fruit of a spiritual practice or something
like this so these two kind of like inputs uh fill in the blank of what uh
nibbana or awakening or enlightenment might be
so one idea that we might have it's this
permanent state of equinimity we might say that there where nothing is
disturbing where there's no longer being agitated
or no longer feeling like a little bit triggered like oh that was a little bit
uncomfortable or you know like just being chilled out about everything all
the time maybe feeling completely unbothered or serene or completely
centered and never uh pushed uh off uh center even just a tiny bit
and this is very compelling because so much of our world feels turbulent
the outside world certainly feels turbulent the our inner world can feel
turbulent there can be a whole morass of stuff going on in there so of course we
have this idea that oh it's uh it's just going to be complete peacefulness all
the time complete calmness all the time and maybe I'll even add I mean we do
experience moments of calm and moments of peace when we're meditating and it
can feel like a certain liberation a liberation from the turbulence a liberation from the stress or the chaos
that uh we might be feeling this whatever degree of calmness or peace or
ease that we're experiencing so it must feel like oh okay awakening will be more of that
and in some ways it is but I'll talk a little bit more about uh that i first I
want to just um highlight some of the ways we might be thinking about it
and right that doesn't sound bad wouldn't it be nice to never be bothered
another uh way in which we might think about it is like have this complete
uh self-acceptance like fully embracing and loving and welcoming all aspects of
ourselves every part of ourself not having any bit of this uh inner
critic or any sense of shame or any sense of insecurity having like nothing
like that but instead feeling perfectly adequate and sufficient and as opposed
to being inadequate and insufficient sometimes like oh nope I'm perfectly fine as I am
that could be a way in which we imagine that uh uh a awakening is
and of course we bring this this idea because I mean this inner critic that so
much of us uh have is painful it's really and wrecks havoc in our lives in
so many ways and wouldn't it be great if it weren't there any longer
or maybe we have had some experiences during meditation when there has been
some warmth and some warm-heartedness for ourselves either that arose spontaneously or maybe it was something
that we cultivated with loving kindness practice or maybe just there are some states of uh samadei some states of a
collectedness unification that have that feeling like
this feeling of wholeness that uh with a flavor of um well-being
that that feels can feel like such a relief and it also can feel like
empowering like okay I I'm okay I I can meet
whatever needs to be met or I can take care of whatever needs to be taken care
of that's another way in which we might uh
think about awakening and again this is perfectly legitimate and of course we
have these ideas and there's this way in which it can be even helpful to have
these ideas or maybe another uh idea that we might
have is that uh I've heard this expression a unity consciousness
um I don't think you'll hear that very much here at Insight Meditation Center it's
not part of our tradition our lineage this idea of unity consciousness but
where the maybe the separation of self of of the notion between self and
everything that's not self dissolve these are meditative experiences uh they
can be known um this idea of being merged uh with
everything I know that um early in my meditation
practice wow Wow for a long time I felt like I didn't know what freedom was but
I'm sure it had to be crazy wild you know for me like the weirder the
meditative experience the better so I just felt like I had to cultivate weird
stuff just because I felt like it certainly couldn't be ordinary whatever it was and uh that turned out not to be
such a good idea i'm telling my teachers weird stuff and they're kind of looking at me like "Dana
what are you doing and I tell my friends and we would laugh
about it and talk about it." But yeah it turned out not to be such a good idea because I wasn't paying attention to
what was really important instead of maybe I had I had some
experience that I assigned a whole narrative and meaning to and you know all this extra stuff and it just turned
out to be like a culdeac it just like oh well h there's nothing to do with that
and so forth and then coming back to practice but I mean of course this idea of
wanting to have some transcendent or maybe you have had some experiences that
have felt like that or that felt uh um like maybe sacred or like the most true
or real thing that you've ever experienced or and maybe it's changed your life in some kind of way
it turns out this is not so uncommon people who start a meditation practice
not everybody some people have had a glimpse of something and maybe it's not
clear to them um in some setting in their lives maybe you're in the midst of a crisis in the
midst of uh using substances of uh some sort or in the midst of some other
tradition or sometimes just spontaneously and then they're trying to find a a way back to that and they're
using meditation as a a way back so this uh you know I'm using this expression
unity consciousness but it also can just be any kind of like non-ordinary state
that felt like oh this this is important and I need to get back there
yeah and the problem of course with this is that uh it just really highlights
that oh I'm here if we're always uh chasing something over there there's
always like am I there yet am I there oh no I'm here this is very subtle that
happens but it pretty much guarantees that you will not have that experience again which is to the great frustration
of everybody who tries or and then you're like I could go on
with this list right but maybe uh one more thing I'll say too is that maybe we have these ideas that um all our
relationships with everybody all our interactions with everybody with all beings will be healthy and mature and
that uh we'll communicate clearly all the time and we'll understand what everybody is saying very clearly and
there'll be this uh uh intimacy that feels appropriate and tender and uh
nourishing and some kind of way and that will happen like with all people all the time
of course we would like to have this because so often we feel separate we
feel alone we feel like maybe we don't understand other people we feel like other people don't understand us
of course we would want to have this of course we would want to live maybe
without this fear of rejection or a fear of abandonment but instead this
recognition that uh this recognition of a connection and a
understanding in some way with other people
so these are some of the ideas that we might have about the far shore they're
perfectly legitimate and it's quite a something how this practice
a mindfulness practice and maybe some um some concentration some samadei practice
and maybe a little bit of study can really help move along towards those
goals absolutely absolutely
but there's also this way that even the whole notion of a far shore can be a
trap just as I said because it makes you feel like it really highlights
oh I'm here i'm not there and then it's really subtle but often
what happens with that is like this is a problem i have to fix it i have to get over there i'm clearly I'm not doing
something right what am I not doing right or those people over there clearly they aren't doing something right
they're that's preventing me from doing this or something like that so that's one way
but it turns out that it's this isn't a journey of distance of
space it's a journey of perception or a shift
in our relationship to experiences
as opposed to having just the right experiences
the far shore isn't elsewhere it's not somewhere else it's what arises it's
what opens it's what's experienced when we stop struggling
to become to become
to be you know put ourselves in a little box i'm like this and these are my
qualities I have and you know to kind of like raify um ourselves it's it's what
arises when we let go and there is no clinging this really radical letting go
so it can be a trap because we are always looking over there but also what's implicit in that as I mentioned
earlier is that we're measuring we're using the erroneous metrics like oh I'm
not having all that complete experience that I really want therefore I must be doing something wrong meanwhile we're
not noticing those moments of ease and spaciousness
that are spontaneously arising maybe we're cultivating them and developing them but those moments of when there's
not a lot of sense of self or clinging
i remember this one time that um this was during a a retreat at a retreat
center where I was uh spending a lot of time sitting outside in nature it was
just lovely just to be outside and do my meditation outside and I would like sit
walk sit walk you know in this little area that I had found
and um I remember this one time I don't I was
doing sitting meditation i don't know remember what uh caused me to open my eyes but I remember opening my eyes and
I was sitting like up on a hill and I could see like a certain expanse like
you know down into the valley a little bit and just uh seeing this hawk i think
it was a hawk i don't know it was a big bird that one that doesn't flap its wings
and uh and it was just soaring
and going down and then up and maybe around in a circle and there was this
way that I felt like just this beautiful like oh I was soaring too and there was
it was like just the most beautiful experience of like I don't know this uh
sense of ease and spaciousness and like this
flight but sometimes you know even those types
of experiences or even minor ones when uh
I was um near a kind of like a river not too long
ago and this feeling of uh oh just to
like jump in i just felt like oh let's just jump in and then just allowing the
current to carry me it was just like you know this sense of ease and it was just
so much fun and uh spaciousness like nothing need to happen except it not to
run into something of course but just this these feelings of ease and spaciousness that arise whether they're
big things or small things if we're often thinking like oh no I have to have
perfect relationships or I have to um feel complete or I have to get rid of
any feeling of inadequacy or I have to do something or other then we will tend
like oh yeah that's nice but I'm still not there but it turns out that these
moments are really what practice is about or maybe we are having some uh thoughts
about ourselves like ah you really should uh do the dishes before such and
such happens because if you don't do the dishes then
I don't know what would happen actually what if you I don't know we have this uh all these stories it's kind of hard for
me to make up stories when I'm uh in the sitting up here maybe at home in I don't
know so that was a story too right
but what one thing I wanted to say is that uh if we have this idea of what
freedom is then we might not notice those times in which thoughts arise and
we're like okay yeah whatever those are just thoughts and we don't pay any attention to them we don't make them
mean anything about ourselves we notice like okay that's a story and I mean it's
okay minds make stories you don't have to make them be a problem but there's times in which we often aren't noticing
how often we're not getting caught up with thoughts
because we think that awakening has to look a particular way and we're so we're being dismissive or just not even
noticing but the way towards more freedom is not getting caught up with
thoughts and this is happening we're just not noticing
so there's this way in which we can understand that I'll use this word awakening there's a lot that could be
said about this and there's also a lot that could not be said I guess one way
to think about it is that it is not a
constant state it's not a location certainly but it's
not this continuous bliss or peace or
something like that it's not fixed it can't be it's not fixed instead it's
um it's the it's not being pushed around by
the uh whatever the experience is so it's not um it's a radical uh shift
in our relationship to what's happening so maybe there's some irritation arises
and it's just irritation and it goes away and it lasts for a moment and it goes away
and it doesn't mean anything about the person it's just like oh okay irritation
happens when I have to stand in line in a long time
and I'm in a hurry i didn't give myself enough time and in a hurry and I have to stand in line at the grocery store or
you know something like that and the grocery clerk is talking and talking and talking to the person in front of us and
they're going on and on and on or something like this right so it's not like it's just like a moment of
frustration arises and it's okay
so it's this this non- clinging this unbinding
this uh it's the this radical letting go
it's maybe like anger arises and then it just
arises and passes away there's no rumination about it like I can't believe did you that person cut me off and where
did they learn how to drive and don't they know what they're doing and don't they know who I am and you know all this
kind of stuff it's just oh there's a little maybe something of some anger and there's no
resentment there's no residual there's no rumination it's just something that arises
it turns out that this is what freedom really is it's not being a bliss blob
instead it's like mental events are still occurring but the relationship is to them is
different there isn't any identification we're not adding anything
there isn't any adding of what it means about me as a person about the world in
general it's just an experience
so it's not about maybe what is happening and it's not that we're in constant bliss it's more that everything
is it's how it's being Yeah that's not even
quite right um how it's being experienced or or their
relationship to them it's a it's not a permanent feeling it's
a lack of adding anything extra
to experience and then it turns out that adding things
extra is where uncomfortableness is where dooka arises
is from all this stuff extra that we add and part of meditation as the mind
starts to get quieter and quieter we start to see the more subtle ways in which we're adding things that are extra
on this i can imagine this is not very satisfying to hear about
but maybe there's this way we can understand it uh like maybe there's just like greater
flexibility that um there's a disappointment that arises like oh okay
I thought this was I was going to do this today or I was going to meet this person today but oh that's not going to
happen oh okay and then just pivot and do the next thing instead of you know any heaviness about it like oh I can't
believe that they changed at the last minute or I rearranged my schedule to in order to accommodate them or you know
something like this something like this or maybe there's a the reactivity is
just uh maybe there isn't this uh bursting
or responding instead of like "Oh wow okay that was uncomfortable."
Some interaction with somebody and it's just an uncomfortable experience that
arises and passes away
so what if the far shore is not like something over there to reach what if
it's you know not over there but what if it's what remains
when we stop seeking when we stop always looking for
something to be different or something to you know match our ideas of
what freedom is like it's an interesting thing because as
long as there's seeking by definition there is not finding
and yet we are so used to seeking seeking seeking what happens if we just put down the
seeking and then finding happens this turns out to be pretty powerful
so all the subtle ways in which we are seeking Or what if the far side is not like on
the other side of that great expanse of water but it's on the other side of
clinging it's on the other side like seeking
clinging we can use different words for this uh the way in which
we're adding things that are extra to our experiences
so maybe you can just be sensitive to or open to when do you taste moments of
non-grasping non seeking
non clinging when are they being experienced
chances are they're happening and meditation practice just allows it
to be noticed and for it to happen more and more and
or what happens when you're not trying to fix or protect or defend your sense
of self or bolster your sense of self what what hope is there something that
opens up when you are no longer defending the self or
protecting or bolstering when that whole self project relaxes
and then what opens what's available
and can you rest there
even for just a portion of a breath
one second less than a second
this is what's being pointed to is the far shore and this metaphor is you know fun or
helpful to talk about but it also can help feed this trap that uh the far
shore is over there somewhere
so I'll stop there and open it up to see if there's some comments or questions
thank you i didn't leave a lot of time for
questions here
jim I think Jamie has a question
uh your description of unity consciousness I think is the best
description I've heard of something that happened to me first spontaneously when
I was about 11 years old and uh maybe a couple times since then and um I've told
teachers about it and they haven't been really uh impressed by
or they they they've said things like "Well was that nice for you?" And I said
"Yes." But um yeah it's it is a it feels like a
transcendent experience but it's um I guess I haven't really experienced that
leading me on to um I'm sorry you hadn't experienced I hadn't experienced it a feeling of that
it was sort of leading me towards anything deeper maybe
so just a comment I guess it feels kind of cruel right when we
have experiences that are really meaningful and yet they feel uh uh
evasive and we can't have them again and yeah it's it's kind of a cruel thing
i'll just speak from my own experience and feeling like wait what what you know like I don't know if like and what am I
doing wrong and you know all this stuff gets added on top of it i don't know if that was the case for you but definitely
for me so thank you
um I'm reminded when you talked about uh extra um it helped solidify
u in my mind the the idea comp in in
addition to last recently here someone was talking about um
the the the dharma was a talk a part of partly about um someone that felt in a
moment like they had messed up and had omitted something that should have been
included and winced and went up to the teacher at the end and apologized and
the teacher's response was mistakes happen the wincing was extra and that helped me
realize what that was about so thank you yeah you're welcome you're welcome
okay so here we are at uh 8:30 so thank you for your attention i wish you a
wonderful rest of the evening and safe travels home thank you
if you'd like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me ask a question