okay uh welcome uh welcome folks um
yeah good to uh good to be with you so um
yeah let's uh let's uh sit together
like uh nectar settling to the bottom of a glass of juice tanhan says That's
And there can be some measure of tranquility when we're not trying to
keep all the balls up in the air
when we're not trying to suppress as if uh keeping uh 50 pingpong balls
submerged underwater
we let what's in the air come to the surface
what subterranean come to the surface
how uh radically might we relinquish
the attempt to control experience
and maybe we think the mind calls out "No no no no i have to control my
attention i have to do the meditation i have to do the letting go we have to
make progress
we have to come to trust that
you're already enough doing nothing
whatsoever
maybe we uh follow wherever the thread of interest takes us
what is this what is this moment this life
this suffering
When there's a curiosity investigation dhamma vaya
doesn't matter where the attention goes animated by interest
interest is for itself
but turns out to be a very conducive intention
to the development of our practice
so often our attention is a kind of appendage of our
wanting
can we be awake in such a way that we're not extracting something from the
moment
but instead offering our attention ion is a kind of
blessing
settling back kind of receptivity
no more bartering with samsara
just put all of your hope into this moment
[Music]
okay folks good to uh practice with you um
so um I'll be away for for a few weeks actually
um avoided this but uh so far for um
certain Wednesdays but uh next three weeks I'll be away actually in New York if any of you are there i'm at uh New
York Insight be nice to um maybe uh see some some uh YouTube people in real life
if uh you like I I think I'm there the 29th um uh doing a benefit for that
group and um yeah and then I'll be back um July
9th certain Wednesdays so um
okay
so uh one of um one of my uh friends fellow
dharma teacher and um uh very kind of intuitive body worker
sumatic experiencing practitioner
Um he we would um be in like the teachers
office at Spare Rock during a a walking period or
before a a talk or guided meditation or something it was just a few of us in the in the office and he would just kind
we'd be like sitting around talking and he would just like pick up my leg and
just start massaging it and manipulating it and um it wasn't weird for him it was
like okay yeah and uh he knew that I kind of had uh an old meditation injury
that had sort of hardened into um some chronic pain and um whatever he was
doing I just let him do it felt very good it felt like uh there was
wisdom in his hands and at some point he would sort of like
ask like what what does your leg want to do and I remember one time it was like okay
it wants to wants to sort of kick the air it wants to like move out forcefully
and it was a movement of some kind of aggression you know is how it felt
and he said um uh that's right you know yeah there's
there's some movement of fight in the fight flight freeze kind of thing there this is this needs fight there's some
fight that hasn't been completed and the energy
um needed to be guided into movement to complete something
and um that was a very particular context but I
begin with that because the question arises for me is like what what does it um look like to
channel anger aggression into something useful
and anger is kind of a little taboo maybe in
dharma circles is very easy to disavow very clearly belongs to the bouquet of
afflictive emotions you know and um and
sometimes it's more comfortable for us to say that anger
anger is just the armor or anger just protects us from some more fundamental
feeling that you know sometimes say like oh yeah anger is the the secondary
feeling before that fear or grief for shame or something lies under the anger
and our preference is for the less
aggressive spectrum of feeling maybe we have more okayess in a way in the scene
with fear or grief and anger is sort of like no that can't
be the primary thing that can't be the bedrock or something so we we can disown
that and um we maybe say like well it may be
part of our defense that we say anger is just a distorted expression of fear or
something like this yeah okay and I I've spoken almost glowingly
and without regret about grief but rarely about anger certainly not
glowingly and I've done that for a reason i do think there's less less wisdom in anger
often than there is in grief but even with anger it's not zero wisdom
now in in uh kind of opening the door to anger we want to be uh careful
and anger aversion is is literally like
you know one of the three pillars one of three well wellsp springsings of
suffering you know greed delusion right and um
and if we've paid attention to our own minds or to uh others we we know that
anger um can can destroy us you know can
destroy those around us can destroy communities and societies
and uh from the samuta the the what's the one thing oh godama whose killing
you approve the killing of anger is the response with its poisoned root and honeyed tip
this is the killing the noble one's praise for having slain that one does not sorrow
yeah poisoned root honey tip
fair enough and I'm not there but I I can envision uh a
mind free from anger as radical as that is I can envision a kind of uprooting of
aversion so thorough and an understanding of causality so deep that
anger does not arise because I I do feel
not pivoting to talk trash about anger but but
Um I do feel like anger in the end is a basic confusion an impoverished
model of causality and I can see anger is never the last
word there's always something more to be seen
and at some point our emotional system may find ways of expressing our love and
our boundaries in such a way that does not involve rage
but until I'm that free till I'm free
from that and my emotional system really is changed I need to listen to my anger
and to extract its wisdom to untangle the delusion and the wisdom to find a
way of making that movement that I was being invited to make that kicking of my
leg that doesn't harm anyone to find a way of kicking that kind of
expresses force but clarity
and all this is to say that um
uh I've been agrieved angered
by the proflegate moral vandalism
of our president and the wanting
cruelty that delights in uh inflicting suffering on imagined
enemies and um
and when somebody asks me how I'm doing you know I like there's a dimension of my heart it's true I can say honestly
extremely happy and in a sense that well-being is not
oluded by but it coexists with a lot
of heartache and anger over so much unnecessary suffering
and so can I extract the wisdom from my anger
can I untangle the wisdom from the delusion that I also know is there
and what what I'm asking myself what is a wise
powerful expression of the energy of no what does that look like
and we need to kind of turn to
our moral heroes you know I read um the
recent I think it won the Pulitzer bio a very um biography of King
uh quite superb um Jonathan I and uh it's a book for our times
and um in that um uh biography argues that um history sort
of mistaken kings nonviolence for passivity
and it's it's sanitized and polished the legacy in a way that does um doesn't do
justice to just how radical and
uh fearless the approach was and the book argues that um we've
forgotten that the approach was more forceful than most anything the country had seen
and moral outrage it needs a place to go like that energy
at the leg it needs a place to go but I don't want to dis kind of um
distort the energy i don't want to express it in a way that comes out sideways you know and when I do that I
always there's a kind of instant karmic reverberation sometimes even just giving
a dharma talk I'll just like something's not quite aligned in my heart there's
something uh self-indulgent or
um melodramatic or self-involved or something i'll feel it afterwards
and I I I with this I I want to find a way of
expressing this energy cleanly in my life in my teaching in my practice
and um and when the feeling is not kind of
expressed or discharged um is not channeled in some way it sort
of rattles around the cage of the heart mind and that rattle
compounds the pain that kind of passivity and the inactivity compounds
the pain it's easier to get angry when there's no movement of the energy out
and so action you know sometimes the only way
to actually discharge the pain of that
and so okay as a dharma practitioner what what where does this energy go how
is this alchemically transformed in a way knowing you know just how much faith
we develop in love and just how how profound the moral you know
persuasiveness of love is so much more persuasive
than unmitigated anger
okay it sounds paradoxical but can one's anger be
inform one's love and I had the sense that in King that something like that
happened that he kind of mastered that process of
um of moving the energy of outrage
moral outrage into a courage and love
and so this is February 1957
70 years ago uh King uh wrote "In speaking of love at
this point we're not referring to some sentimental emotion it would be nonsense to urge people to love their oppressors
in an affectionate sense love in this connection means an
understanding of goodwill when we speak of loving those who oppose
to us we refer neither to aeros nor filia
we speak of a love which is expressed in the Greek word agape agape means nothing
sentimental or basically affectionate it means understanding redeeming good
will for all people an overflowing love which seeks nothing
in return is the love of God working in the lives
of humans when we love on the agape level
we love people not because we like them not because their attitudes and ways
appeal to us but because God loves them
we don't have exactly the same theological language to pull on but it's
close enough it's close enough to love because God
loves them yeah and we put it all all the the movement
of the heart into expressing our uh care
so I offer this for your um consideration and um
uh yeah may we uh find ways of of
expressing all that's wise in us okay I wish you uh wish you well see you
in July