so hello and welcome and welcome to this meditation session
and the topic these days is the is insight and insight
um uh I think it might be useful to see kind of the word play a little bit
around the word insight in that it means something similar to having something in
view if it's in view then it's within within eyesight something we can see so
in in sight is something that also comes into the domain of our mind's eye our
perception so sometimes I consider uh insight to be closer to revelation
than it is to understanding something we don't search we don't
analyze we're not uh uh but we something comes into view when we uh walk up a
hill and then we see the surroundings they come into view it's a there's
somewhat of a receptive quality to it a discovery reality appears to us rather
than we going to reality and mindfulness meditation is the
meditation practice where we become available to have things in view the
direct experience of our life comes into view because our distracted mind that
takes us into the past the present into fantasy into commentary
into planning has quieted down the mind is not jumping around so much and so now
we've come to a place where there's an amazing view and we don't have to work
at seeing that view we just sit here quietly keeping it in view keeping it in
sight allowing what's here to show itself to us so to do that we prepare ourselves
prepare ourselves by understanding at the beginning of the
meditation that the that the goal of the meditation is to be present with what
is and if what is a distracted mind thinking about the past and present we
enter the present moment experience of doing so this is a mind thinking about the
past this now is a mind thinking about the future here this is the place where
we relax and hold reality in
view so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing the eyes and as part of this prep
preparatory work to take some fuller breaths
maybe when you breathe in more fully pause before you
exhale it can be a momentary pause so that you choose to begin the
exhale with a letting go and releasing
relaxing at the end of the exhale so the exhale is longer
fuller the little pause at the top of the
inhale is a moment to bring you more fully into the present moment
and then letting your breathing return to
normal and as you exhale to relax in your
body tension in the body is kind of like exerting
pressure on the thinking mind so it thinks
more as the body relax there's less pressure to think
so softening in the
face around the eyes
as you exhale softening the shoulders
relaxing giving in to the weight of the pull of gravity
as you exhale softening the belly
and as you exhale a broad general general
relaxation of the whole body
and as you inhale to feel the thinking
mind the thinking muscle pressure or tightness
As you exhale to
soften the thinking
mind to quiet the mind
and then as you now center yourself on your
breathing breathing in an easy breathing in in an easy
way and when you get to the top of the
inhale experiment with a momentary
pause that brings you more into the present moment and maybe it's an occasion to let
the thinking mind become
quiet and then exhale
relaxing into the present experience of your body as you exhale
The pause at the top of the inhale can be for just a half a
moment just enough to pull you into the present more fully to quiet the thinking mind
and as you exhale relax at the end of the exhale
release in the body so the exhale
continues for a few moments more
and for a half a moment pause before breathing
in for another moment
of being present being pulled into the present
moment around The
breathing with the thinking mind becoming
quiet and then breathing in
With these momentary pauses the end of the
inhale perhaps the exhale comes into better
view and pause at the end of the inhale
exhale the inhale comes into better
view the lifegiving experience of breathing
can be appreciated for what it is and what it does
by keeping it in view
where there is breathing there is life
to let the thinking mind become quieter so you can better
feel
observe experience the lifegiving movements of the body as you breathe
as if breathing is a sponge for any tension and preoccupation
and pressure to think
allowing everything to enter the rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out
at the end of the
inhale the exhale comes into
view gaze upon the exhale as you
would seeing some natural
object that's a delight to gaze
at at the end of the exhale let the inhale come into view
like watching maybe the gentle swells of
waves moving by the ocean washing up on the shore
hold the breathing in view
and after these minutes of meditation what else comes into
view without thinking about it
what else besides breathing do you now have a better view
of what do you see about
yourself what is revealed
and for whatever that's revealed breathe with
it let it too rest in the gentle rhythm of
breathing so you don't do anything about it just
see just observe from the vantage point of
breathing in and breathing out
and then as we come to the end of this meditation there's a way
of staying close to breathing that makes it easier
then to gaze upon the world with without getting caught in thoughts and
judgments
agendas to let the world and others come into
view where the eyes are
not marshaled by desires and fears and judgments
where the eyes of perception gaze uses upon the world
calmly and is available as a conduit for our
goodwill for kind regard of others
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to our series on insight and um now for the second week
I'm going to introduce to you five areas of insight that uh might be significant
for people who do insight meditation and um and somehow
understanding that there are different forms of insight different objects of insight can help us put each into
context and so maybe we better understand uh what the classic Buddhist idea of
insight insight meditation is aiming towards and all these forms of insight
are valuable and um but uh we don't want to be limited by any one of them we want to
be able to appreciate each one in its own way but not think that this is the
this is what insight is by itself
so um the word insight is uh as I've said you know comes from the word
vipasana which means uh either to see clearly or to see distinctively to see
each thing that occurs in a distinctive kind of way in its own right and um so what that means is we
don't use a discursive mind to start creating lumping everything together in some kind of way but uh rather we are um
uh letting each thing stand for itself so we know it well and so that the thinking conceptual mind is not uh so
busy analyzing uh conceptualizing about our experience taking us away from it in a
certain way so the word insight
um is uh sometimes I've in a kind of um kind of um evocative way I like to
think of it as um as the synonym as being revelation and why I like that as a
synonym is that uh revelation is not something that we uh are searching for
uh necessarily or that we're responsible for uh it's something that just seem
suddenly seems to appear that's a meaningful understanding a meaningful experience um but that we didn't make
happen we didn't uh feel like we constructed it or thought it out or
analyzed something it just it just appeared somehow in a way that was surprising and gratifying
meaningful and so insight has that quality that we're not trying to
construct insight or figure something out with the figuring out mind we're uh
using the meditative mind to become quiet and still so that we're not
distracted we're not caught up in the world of concepts uh so that uh uh and
instead can kind of see things directly thing our life comes into view might be
less grand than the idea of revelation um the our experience comes into
view and um so come be it comes into
sight and uh rather than looking we're seeing looking being this
active effort to kind of zero in on something seeing means a kind of uh
relaxed receptive um awareness of the present moment here
and so there are five different areas that that uh in which insights can occur
where some new understanding some new um clarity some new meaningful way of
experiencing our life can come into view so the first is that uh uh personal
personal insight and that means uh we see um we understand something new about
ourselves that's unique to pretty fairly unique to us has to do something about
uh we understand something about our history what happened to us how we were conditioned and shaped by things uh we
have a new insight into what happened to us in the past um we have insight into
the kind of uh thoughts we have the biases we have the orientations we have
the beliefs we have that might be operating unbeknownst to us but they are in the background and sometimes it's
mystifying why certain things happen but then uh we kind of at some point get
quiet enough in meditation that the quiet mind um is seen and we say "Oh
that's what I'm believing that's why everywhere I go um things are look
dangerous because I'm always thinking uh thoughts of catastrophe i'm always
imagining that the worst will come and no wonder every place I go seems dangerous because I'm constantly
projecting or seeing through this catastrophi catastrophizing kind of mind
or for me um I used to uh I saw at one point in meditation that in the back of
my mind very very quietly but quietly doesn't mean uh unimportant it's kind of
like the lens through which everything else was seen was I had this strange belief that if any meditative experience
was happening to me it was not the real thing i didn't know what the real thing
should be but I I had steeped doubt about my whatever myself and my own
experience that I could never feel settled or at ease with whatever experience I had there was a very subtle
anxiety a very subtle agitation very subtle kind of like holding myself back
from experiences meditation because of this very background thing so other
people might have something like that as well but it might not be uh as uh you
know um it might not be the prominent kind of background belief that of many
people and so u but this is a personal kind of to me it's a personal insight I saw oh it made a huge difference to see
that it's almost like as soon as I saw that the veils were cleared and now I
could just be with my direct experience of meditation in a much simpler more easy way uh content to be just let
it be what it is without having to some idea that it's not quite up to
snuff and so there's a whole slew of personal insights like that that become
available when the mind starts getting quieter and quieter um sometimes uh if
we're thinking about it's very concerned about something uh the mind has is operating sometimes uh
offline and uh and we're sitting quietly we have enough space in the thinking
mind gets quiet enough that some of the offline kind of insights revelations
understandings will pop up um many years ago when I was a new Zen student I
worked at a bakery and my job was to uh prepare the
uh wets and the dry uh ingredients for the bakers that came in early in the morning to make bread and different
things so I'd have these two bowls all the all the wet stuff all the dry stuff the eggs whatever whatever that was
needed that was wet and they would just mix it in together in the morning when they came and um so one day I was
sitting meditating and my mind was fairly quiet and peaceful and minding my own business and suddenly there was like
little explosion in my mind and uh and uh my mind said the salt and something
inside of me maybe because I'd been making the doing this work for some time it was deeply in my body something
inside of me knew that I left the salt out of one of the bread one of the head
um preparations that I was doing so I had to call him as soon as soon as I could i called the bakery and told them
and and so they uh were very happy with the results because they put a sign
up salt-free bread and uh it was snapped up people bought
it so uh so this way in which uh personal insights of different kinds can
appear when we're doing uh meditation and um I don't want to uh
dismiss the value of that these at all but what I'd like to uh suggest is that
for the purposes of mindfulness meditation we don't want to get too involved in these personal insights if
they're impactful and you want to spend time to reflect and think about them um the recommendation is do it afterwards
go for a walk with a friend journal about it um spend other times so that you don't um condition yourself to think
that meditation is about thinking about things that that's where you're going to kind of have all these aha moments
and the reason for this is uh I I like to present this an analogy that if you
go into um an apartment building a tall building a skyscraper because you've
been told that there's a fantastic and very important view from high up and um
and so you get into the elevator and it takes you up to the second floor and the second floor opens and there's a amazing
party um uh show going on that just seems so made
for you and all your interests so you leave the elevator to go see this party
this show and you're there for many weeks before you realize hey wait a minute I was supposed to be going up in
the elevator and um so you get back in the elevator and you go up and it opens at
the fourth floor and there is World War uh uh three and um and you see you know
the good cause and and uh who's who's the good guys and bad guys and you're
ready to you feel like you have to responsible to join the good cause and you're out there uh on the fourth floor
fighting the war and maybe then it takes you many months to realize hey wait a minute I was in the elevator going up
and so then you go back in the elevator and now you go up and uh and the elevator opens in the seventh floor and
there's this person that you can't believe the person standing there ready to greet you it's the person of your
dreams you've been dreaming about this person for years and here is the person
who is clearly going to be your life partner clearly going to be provide everything you need and you can't
believe your good luck and so you get off the elevator and it takes you some years before you realize wait a minute
I'm going up the elevator so in this way medi when meditation is
working it's like you're in in the elevator and uh and
uh and uh and then when you have certain revelations certain insights certain
thoughts certain fantasies certain things that you can't believe how good they are or how important the the right
cause is we get off the elevator in order to engage in those and plan and
work and fight the good fight and um but uh the idea when you're doing meditation
is don't get off the elevator trust the process it's working uh if these different insights
these different self-standings come up different topics are important for you come up appreciate that but don't get
off the elevator sometimes when I meditate um there will
be things more than just salt uh things will arise say oh that's actually
important to address thank you and I'll say thank you and they'll say later not
during meditation and um and if you're worried really worried about forgetting
something so important you could have a pad pad next to you and just write it down so that you can put it aside but uh
the idea is here if you're doing mindfulness meditation uh the personal
insights self-standing that comes along is invaluable and very supportive but
the idea is don't get sidetracked by those in meditation itself or at least
don't take them as being the only reason we're doing meditation some people when
they hear the the idea of insight then will assume that oh now I've gotten an insight now I know what insight is i
understand something very important about myself that's going to change my whole life for the better so thank you insight that I got
my insight i'm also appreciate that you know very significant forms of personal
insight can happen and um and the idea is remember there's actually many more
important insights that going to come that are part of this p this phenomenal
path to a deep liberation of the heart a deep freedom from some of the deepest
um challenging cha uh operating systems by which our whole psychophysical system
is operating and to really drop down to see that in a deep quiet way that we
want to go into that uh see having insight into things which are more universal things that are shared by all
people and not just personal for myself and that'll be the topic now for
the next four days so uh I appreciate very much um
this opportunity and and we'll continue tomorrow