so hello and welcome and welcome to this series of
guided meditations related to
samali and one of the very important aspects of samadi
meditation is that it's uh deeply
attuned deep ly connected to our subjective
experience and the contrast to that is
objectifying our experience or being with the objective
experience and but there's wisdom to both sides there's no not much wisdom to objectifying
exactly but we often when we suffer around ourselves or suffer even around
others there's a strong tendency to be caught up in
objectification seeing the objects so seeing objectifying ourselves
seeing oursel as an object of our ideas our
projections our fantasies our
thoughts about what the future will look like thoughts about the past and
building up all kinds of stories about the past and there's a removal a stepping
away from the sub the immediate subjective world and not subjective in the sense
that subjective because of our opinions our
preferences our likes and dislikes but some a much more deeply subjective
experience of being in the experience of our
body the embodiment to be sensing and feeling the
quality of our immediate subjective
experience and one of the things to notice is whether in our subjective
experience are we in fact viewing it through some idea some
concept some sense some idea of self of me
myself some idea of how I'm supposed to be some idea of what has happened to me
of course things happen to us but then we live live in the idea of that some
idea of what's supposed to happen in the future some idea of what meditation is
supposed to be like what we're supposed to experience what's supposed to happen and we're seeing the world
through the filter of these ideas the alternative
here is to feel to sense the immediacy of our of
the quality of our subjective experience is it does it
feel Pleasant or unpleasant does it feel whole or
partial are we focused on a very small piece of the
whole and can we open up to feel more of the whole experience that's here and now
and oddly enough one of the ways to focus in a very partial
way is to identify ourselves with just a piece of the full Human Experience we
have to identify ourselves mostly through our body or through our Pleasure
and Pain or through the stories of our life or through the concepts and ideas
that we have inherited or made up even to think with we are
Consciousness limits the full subjective
experience so to sit with a quality of our inner
life subjectively so it's not an object to fix to
manipulate to judge to comment about it's just something to feel and
sense so to assume a meditation
posture and to gently close your eyes
and to maybe tell yourself that all of who you think you
are all your past and your memories and your
judgments all the ways in which you see yourself through the conclusions your
thinking makes it's okay to put that
aside as you're going to to
meditate we are entering into a sacred World in
Samar the sacred world of our subjective experience here and now
in and of itself and now with your your eyes
closed allowing the present moment experience of body mind and heart to be
as it is feel the quality of
it does it feel good or not so good is it comforting or not
comforting is it settled or unsettled
you're allowed to be whatever way it is it's
okay is the inner life peaceful or is
it conflicted and putting away the ideas of
all that just to feel what it's like to be peaceful
within what what it's like to be conflicted
within and then to help you enter more deeply into this Temple of
samadi or at least into the entryway to gently
lightly easily take some deeper breaths
as you feel your body more fully as you
inhale imagine that you're entering your
body and with a longer exhale settling into your body
with a deeper inhale entering into your arms and hands
feeling them for what they are and as you
exhale softening relaxing the arms hands
fingers
as you breathe in easily
deeper enter into your legs and feet to feel the
sensations of life in your legs and feet
feel it on the inhale relax your legs and feet as you
exhale
maybe still breathing a little deeper than usual but easing up a a bit so it's more
easeful enter into your whole torso as you breathe in and settle as you exhale
and as you breathe in enter into your neck and your head
feeling the sensations there and as you
exhale soften in the neck in the
head and as you inhale
in some simplest way that's easy for
you feel your whole body or open up in a way that as if
you're going to feel the whole
body and as you exhale to settle the whole body
settling into the settling Place Point within the grounding
point maybe at the end of the exhale deep inside from where the inhale
begins and perhaps as you breathe normally you can feel the
hum of of the body maybe a subtle sense of vibration
or flow or
tingling that's broader wider in your body than any single thing you can focus
on
as you breathe in breathe into that
hum as you exhale
release the body
and as we continue now in the body breathing with the
body body with the breathing
notice when you lose
touch with the body more with the whole
body notice how your thought thinking being pulled
into thoughts ideas pulled into treating things as an
object separate you from something which feels more whole or
holistic in the body
and then if you can relax back into the
body here and now this subjective experience of your
inner life known through your
body
for
e
for for
notice inhale thinking might take you out of the body
away a pulling in back from the deep subjective
experience and that relaxing the thinking mind allows you to settle
in to the Simplicity of the body here
breathing
for
e for
the mind can rest more deeply if it's not thinking so
much and if the mind can
rest maybe you can settle and rest deep into your
body settling into the settling
point
e
for
e e
and as we come to the end of this
inning if you feel your way into the quality of your inner
life inner being how is it now coming to the end of
the sitting
and if you could relax into settle
into your body even
more what would you settle into what would you enter in your
body what deeper subjective experience or Fuller wider subjective
experience and if you have relaxed some of the
objectifications some of the preoccupations
some of the ways of being in the world when we're filled with desire and
aversion doubt and
fear imagine that you're able to be open and
kind open and friendly
open with good will for the people you
encounter and that staying deeply connected and in touch with
yourself allows you to remain kind and friendly
without being pulled into the world of
objectification and may we
Aspire for being available to the world with kindness with
friendliness with good will either seek secretly no one needs
to know or through the acts of our
body our
speech May the treasure we carry through the day be our good
will for others may we
wish have well wishing that all all beings may be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we stay close to these
wishes may we go through the day with a deep
subjective capacity for a warmhearted good will
[Music]
thank
you e
hello to this uh Thursday talk and the ninth talk in the zatti
series and the last three talks uh kind of focused on the
hindrances uh one of the purposes of those talks was to help you see in
yourself the ways in which you limit yourself through being caught in the
hindrances the hindrances involve some kind of thinking some kind of
projected Concepts ideas onto the world onto others onto ourselves
some kind of being caught in preoccupation and in doing so we in some
degree are lose touch with theirselves of course people might not
feel that or think that because they think they are their thinking they are
their aversion they are their desire and so there's no problem they're
really in touch with themselves they know exactly what they want they know exactly what they don't want they
are their fear and so you know that's
that's who I am but if we go deeper in we can feel how these hindrances being
caught in the thoughts and the ideas of Desire aversion fear doubt
regrets that all these are a kind of limited world we we uh narrow the focus
to those preoccupations and the important thing to understand as we go into samade is
that we become partial we become fragmented we become divided we become a limited part of a
whole of who we are and Somali is a process of becoming whole the classic
language of that is unification uh gathering together all
the parts of ourselves so they can be uh working and connected in a harmonious way
together and um so
um uh so today and tomorrow I want to talk a little bit about how the process
of identification uh does the same thing
and classically that that's the steps the Buddha takes um
this to develop to go into this deeper deeper quality of being he first talks
about overcoming the hindrances and when those have settled down enough then the next stage is
something even deeper that still involves some kind of Concepts ideas
projections some kind of um limiting ourselves but now it's uh deeper and
sometimes we don't even see it as a kind of thinking a concept and that is the ways in which we identify ourselves who
we are and there are different ways that we
establish this is who I am at least in the moment that uh we kind of have a we
in doing so we limit ourselves we Short change ourselves we're not available to
the whole and fullness of who we are so you know this morning I brushed my
teeth and um and if I had thought wow Gil you
are like really skilled at brushing your teeth you're like a really
good uh tooth brusher and uh maybe the world has never seen someone so good at
brushing teeth and and I just really know how to zero in on the different teeth get them really clean boy am I a
good and I'm you know this is so important that I'm going to have to come down to IMC this morning and
really let all the people on YouTube know like this is like that's really it's an essential element of who I am a
tooth pressure and how good I am in it and you really need to see that and understand that so you appreciate who I
am and to affirm and confirm my very being as a toothbrush her well it's
ridiculous and I apologize to talk in such a silly way but it it's intentional
to be focused on this simple identity of being a toothbrush her um I kind of lose
touch with a lot of things I lose touch with u maybe all of you I lose touch
with a sense of the world and the wider sense of who I am I lose touch with the
fact that at this moment I'm not brushing my teeth and I have more
important things to do at this moment to sit here with you and try to share the
Dharma and um and to share it no way that I feel connected to myself to my
body to the very sensibility inside the quality of inner life that I've learned
through Dharma practice and so that can be that in many
ways some people get very identified with their physical appearance and that becomes their way
they limit themselves of who they are and of course if you ask them and say are you your
here they don't really say no of course not but functionally people can be
that's that's how they Define themselves as they their sense of well-being and how they want to be seen by others can
be through a physical appearance some people identify themselves very much by their comfort
how pleasant and unpleasant how comfortable and uncomfortable things are and it's a crime against humanity to be
uncomfortable and we have to fix it because that's who we are some people very strongly identify with
their values their ideas their Concepts that they their judgments that they
have and uh some people identify with their stories and um their fantasies of the
future their stories of the past and some people identify with this kind of
quality of just enness or this quality of Consciousness or cognition the one
who who knows and in the early Buddhist tradition each of those ways of
identifying yourself has the risk of sacrificing the
whole and uh it's not necessary to be locked in and be defined only by this
way and then live through that way and well you I don't have I don't
want to convince you this way the reason to to talk about this is the degree to
which you understand it um the um um the idea is to learn to
see and recognize in yourself how you're living in a truncated way how you're by being
preoccupied or caught in some identity then now you're left out a lot
of who you are and uh and that's the discovery process that prepares us for Sadi
to realize the limitations we put ourselves under because if we try to develop some
body while we're in those limitations of uh the way of identifying
ourselves in a certain way we actually uh stand in the way of samadi so for
example if we identify ourselves as a poor meditator that just even if there's
might be some truth to that in some kind of way doesn't matter if we identify
ourselves that way and stay living that identity hold it on like a badge or hold it on like a
coat then we're limiting ourselves from this moment the fullness of now we don't
need to live through the lens of being a bad meditator or a good meditator we
don't need to live Moment by moment all the time through the lens of being a
victim or being someone who's ill or someone who has certain challenges we want to respect everything
about ourselves everything so it's not like pushing any of this
away but the gift of somebody is to learn that we don't have
to limit ourselves by any of this and so the task for today is not to break free
of that not to be different than who you are but can you begin dealing your
subjective experience in such a way that you can see that you're living in a
partial view a partial view of your direct experience partial view of yourself in
your direct experience that you're prioritizing certain things over other things that you think some things are
more important and of course in the moment there are things that are more important
than other things and so to be fluid and move between that of course that's the way to
go and uh but to not carry something with us and keep ourselves limited and
boxed in to one different mode the Buddha when if he he had an
orientation to identify people by what they're doing in the
moment and that's enough I'll end with a short sense
story there were two uh Buddhist practitioners who are
talking about the respective meditation teachers and um so the first one talks
about all the Miracles that their teacher could do they could fly through the air walk on
water see through walls through all kinds of kind of disappear reappear in
different places all kinds of amazing things Supernatural things
and then the other one who's a Zen student the other the first one was not a Zen student some other form of
Buddhism but the Zen student said oh well my
master when she walks she just
walks when she eats she just eats when she cleans she just cleans
and the first one said oh you have a great
Master oh and bow down deeply this idea of just being what
you're doing and enter into that with your whole
being that is how you can be identify yourself in the moment and if you're
sweeping you're the sweeper be that fully with a wholeness of who you are
not to limit Yourself by past future ideas so that when I'm sitting here with
you giving a Dharma talk let me be here fully for this
unconcerned in this moment what a great toothbrush her I am that would limit it
that was not relevant in this moment so may you
not limit yourself and if you do great that that's what you want that's what
you want to see happen because the task for the next 24 hours is to become an
expert really skilled really attuned to noticing what it's like to be limiting
yourself to the objectification to the partiality to particular
preoccupation which doesn't allow you to be fully here for what you're doing uh learning that don't don't
overlook that don't feel like you have to be anywhere else don't feel like you have to be
whole the task here is to understand how you limit yourself how you limit
yourself maybe with identity so thank you very much and uh
continue tomorrow