great wonderful
so
like to take a moment just to mention um for those of you who maybe weren't here
yesterday the theme of this week is practicing with the five elements
and um how the practice with the five elements relates to insight the
experience direct experience of insight and this is intended to tie in to gil
fronstall's ongoing series on insight so if you didn't get a chance to listen
to yesterday's talk it does offer a lot more background and orientation you're
welcome to do that if you wish and um meanwhile to take a moment if you
were um tuned in and practicing yesterday to consider for yourself or if
it feels right to share now or later how um practicing with the elements
especially the earth element may have appeared for you in your practice
and consider any key takeaways
from this series so far
[Music]
feeling of groundedness so with that we'll start
and i'll read and consider any other responses later with that we'll start
with the meditation this morning so um
adjusting this earthly body maybe rocking back and forth on your sit
spot or adjusting how you are on your cushion or chair or mat
taking a couple of longer slower embodied breaths
perhaps
allowing a slight smile on your lips or relaxation in your face
and allowing the outreath to settle settle the attention inward and downward
and when you're ready if you haven't already allowing the eyes
to close
allowing the breathing to be natural
and noticing the quality
of sensation on your skin
there's no dryness or moisture
sensed by the skin perhaps
[Music]
you notice qualities
of moisture or dryness in the breath as air becomes breath
perhaps in your nostrils throat
just noticing allowing the in and out breath
to be however they are today but attuning
to any wave like motion of inb breath and out breath
perhaps a wave like motion of the abdomen
moving up and down
movement of the diaphragm chest belly
allowing the whole body to be present
with awareness at the forefront
into tuning to any sense of motion
aliveness in the body
while maintaining primary attention
on the wave like motion the flow of breathing okay
allowing the attention to settle
again like sediment through water
settling into the moment the flow of the moment
distractions or thinking arise and they will
graciously fluidly shifting the attention
back to the moment
perhaps noticing moisture or dryness in the mouth the lips
the eyes
feeling into
the pulsating aliveness
of this living body the whole body
while being devoted to attending to
the flow of breathing and the flow of the moment
as the attention settles
noticing the ripples of sensation
no matter how slight any sense of pleasure or energy
flow of energy through the body
perhaps at the base of the pelvis or belly
or through the torso attuning
to wave like grass
allowing it to massage any contentment
ease embodiment
through the whole body allowing the mind to float
within the moment
as this sit begins to draw to a close
the invitation if you haven't already is to open to all of embodied experience
the shifting changing scintillating flowing
qualities of sensation in this moment
allowing everything just to move through
no need to get involved
and then as we draw this formal time of meditation to a close
attuning to any sense of goodness
any settledness fluidity
calm or peacefulness any glimmers of goodness
from this meditation and savoring them letting them nourish your practice
and from there invitation
is to let those qualities any benefits here ripple out
through your own mind and heart and life
to all of the lives you touch and all of the lives they touch
outwards and outwards
may all beings be safe happy
peaceful and free and may our practice here together be a
cause and condition for greater love liberation and peace in
the world
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
so welcome dear sana and while um
i'm taking a moment to sip tea before the dharmat i would just like to make a
short announcement and that is that if you enjoy um sitting
with me and with my dear colleague kim allen both of us imc teachers we're
actually co-eing a retreat um through my home sa my other home sa the one that i
lead insight santa cruz and um it's in the gorgeous redwoods in benlmond
california down here outside of santa cruz and it has a much smaller lottery
than a typical inc retreat so i'm going to drop the link in the chat for those of you who might be interested in in
signing up in just a moment
and um
the topic for today is a continuation of um
the series this week on insight and five elements practice
and there are different levels of five elements practice but to say
that um all of this is in context of the insight unfolding that gil is teaching
over these weeks and that um
they can be taken literally or as like material stuff and i spoke to that a
little bit yesterday okay it's a bronze age framing but we can kind of open our minds to all contemporary
elements in the periodic table if we wish um they also can be the qualities of
experience direct experience in the moment so today i was talking about
moisture during the meditation for example or flow so we can attune to those embodied
experiences that is a practice kind of direct practice and then there's
the level of inspiration or analogy simile and for example at the end of the
dharmat yesterday i mentioned that a later buddhist tradition the tibetan tradition had taken the buddha's simile
that the mind could be like the ground for the seeds of cultivation of our life force of good or ill and the
tibetan tradition sort of unpacked that and likened the mind to the earth element so it's not a literal
um kind of assertion but more it's in all of this
is intended to inspire so um today in the following days i will be
um addressing both the contemplation piece of this contemplating how this kind of way of
interpreting or understanding experience might support insight
as well as a direct experience of the elements in our practice and finally how
they might inspire us towards insight
um the five elements is one of many practices in this case it fits into the
body part of the four foundations of mindfulness which is in of itself a skillful
framework and then within that there's a number of skillful means mindfulness and breathing being the most common
that um can help to support insights into ana and constancy anata not self
and others so in terms of
insight through the five elements one key modality is contemplating them
internally and externally and this is easy to do with water for
example when sipping tea
when does tea become body
so let's start with internal and external contemplation with a quote from mainstream science
and i was looking around to sort of fact check some of this talk yesterday and
ran across a wonderful series of um posts on a substack
that um quoted and referenced scientists as long ago as the 19 early 1930s
and one of them basically named that in mainstream science even
back then as today and i'm quoting it is a common belief that blood is modified
seawater and the tlddr on this the too long
didn't read is that concentrations of sodium and potassium in our blood plasma
are remarkably similar to seawater and this is true of many animals including
humans who from an evolutionary perspective emerged from the ocean and
in a sense we still carry that salinity within in a sense our blood streams
are ambulatory oceans that call to the ocean that we feel and
at the seaside that soothing quality there's something about that that can
evoke a sense of this internal flow this internal wavelike
sensation our bodies are over half water some people's bodies are over 3/4 water
so that's kind of a bigger picture of this internal external
contemplation so on the practical level in the
commentaries within the body traditionally the water element is represented by blood sweat and tears
also by urine salivos and ovial fluid etc my um dear colleague and friend bob
stall every year does a meditation on what's called the 32 parts of the body
which unpack the ancient understanding of this and the way that these organs
um connect with the other elements
so that's the tradition and then in terms of felt experience
it we of course can attune to the qualities associated with the water
element flowing melting dampening wetness or conversely
freeze or fixity coagulation dryness is
noticing the experience of the body in the moment noticing that flow
can be a direct experience of inconstancy wherever
the experience of your body is in this a direct experience of that river of
change river of nature
so i'll name that the commentaries also say that it's impossible to directly
experience moisture that it's a quote unquote mental capacity to imagine it
and i'll just name that is not my experience water feels wet
so you can play with that and just check out it's a useful um exercise to do to
notice how much of what we feel like our direct sensory experience is actually
concept versus sensation
recognition versus sensation
also from the ancient commentaries water's function manifests as cohesion
expansion and holding together
so cohesion consider the differences between dust
and soil water is key
the association of water in the ancient teachings with social cohesion is also
strong so strong that when meta loving kindness is described in those same
commentaries as a social relational force of cohesion
it is described in kind of poetic terms of making moist or adding wetness
samati is described the same way as wet can imagine in ancient india much of
which is quite hot wetness was prized
there's also on a more inspirational level
considering the way that the that water and the water element links us to all other life
not just all other life now but all other life in the evolution of this
planet this is from scientist michael mcclennon
he writes "there's about the same amount of water on earth now as there was in
the mesazoic period all water that is breathed drunk and
urinated by living things remains as part of the planet's total water content
also included i might add is water absorbed by the skies which are now
thirstier more absorptive because of climate catastrophe climate
change in other words
the general point is that we the water we experience today in our bodies rivers
oceans skies aquifers embedded in life and oceans and trees
is almost exactly the same water element that's been here since the inception of
this planet vast inner penetrating cycle of change
sometimes meteors come in and bring water or ions and and individual water
hydrogen elements get sort of escape the atmosphere into space but overall the
vast majority is the same it's not personal it's not self
we borrow water for a while carry it around in our ambulatory oceans and
bodies and then it becomes external again
to add an ancient mythic scale and this is from the samuta nikaya the
connected discourses the buddha mentions that over lifetimes
you have cried more tears than there is water in all the oceans
i find that to be very poetic whether you believe in rebirth or not
on a more contemporary level this is a simile that spontaneously came
to me years ago that in a sense we can consider ourselves
our identified selves our bodies like clouds the cloud can drift from here to
another town or another country it gains and loses its water droplets
it changes shape yet remains a cloud all of its parts may change over yet the
cloud remains a cloud until
conditions change and it returns either to the earth through rain or to the sky
through evaporation like that while our mental identity
remains in flux we are processes or processes in constant flux
until we melt back into the all so as this cloud similly highlights
water like i've said many times about awareness is a shape shifter it changes
form manifestation dependent on conditions
just like we do and eventually when the rain falls that oceanic cycle
continues the buddha advised his son rahula
to make his meditation like water if you make your meditation like water
agreeable and disagreeable things will not invade the mind and remain and like
him we can take water as inspiration fluidity adaptability energetic flow
through the body
and in fact in the later tibetan tradition that i quoted at the end last yesterday the mind's continuity
and adaptability is represented by water the buddha said of the dharma the dharma
just as in the ocean there is but one taste the taste of salt so in this
dharma vineia this dharma and discipline there is one taste the taste of freedom
water also represents the capacity of the soft fluid and adaptable to
radically transform what is hard and rigid
consider the grand canyon or mountains eroding into rocks boulders riverstones
and eventually sand in the ocean
and with that i'll close with another terry gata
inspired poem this from utra life had always been hot sweaty work
first i learned to control my hands then my mouth then my mind
as things slowed i sank down down to the bottom of the heart's sea
there i dug out the root of all craving and swam back to the surface
the water had grown cool and outside everything had grown cool
as though the heart had traveled north
so thank you sa for your kind attention and if you wish
between now and tomorrow notice internal and external water that fluid
relationship and how water might inspire your practice and your actions
thank you for your kind attention