Hello everyone and welcome to our
meditation beginning of the week and continuing in this series for this
year on samadei and insight and for this medit. meditation. I want
to evoke a a image from my son's
first second grade, no kindergarten class. It was that um every day when uh
he came to class, we would bring him to school and bring him to the door of the
classroom and the teacher would be standing there
in front of the door, the open door and uh standing there in a
I would say a kind of a dignified way, a kind of a kind way, clear way.
a way that felt like the teacher was fully there for what was coming and ready to receive and but also not uh but
also very competent, very calm and clear and and uh organized and ready for
anything. And the teacher would stand there in front of the door, right next to the front of the door. And every
kindergarten kid who came in, the teacher would greet very nicely. I
forget if they teacher shook their hand or or what how exactly the greeting
went, but every every kid would be every day would be greeted with this very
clear wave from the teacher. And so samadei
is what allows us to be stable, strong, clear,
organized in a certain way, settled on ourselves, so that whatever experience
comes our way, we can greet in the same way. Whatever comes our way, we can see
it clearly. We're not pushed around by it. We're not caught in it.
We're not uh defined by it, but we're just there with it because with this
feeling of rootedness, this feeling of being complete, whole
here, so that each thing that comes our way can be seen, greeted, respected for what
it is. And there's room in the classroom for it. It's just one seat in the class.
It's not the whole world just this thing here now.
So this applies to suffering. The per one of the purposes of of
samadei is so that we are not defined by our suffering. One of the purposes of
insight of mindfulness is so we can know something and not be defined by it, not
be pushed around by it. But we're there to
know our suffering to greet it with respect with clarity
with rudess not being defined by it but ready to be respectful for each act of suffering.
So suffering doesn't become the whole world. Suffering doesn't become something to reject or to be frightened
by, but something that we can see clearly,
so clearly that we see that it's just a piece of the bigger picture of life. It can be
big and monumental, but it's still just one piece. There's more. And samadei
provides the more, the stability, the wholeness, the calm.
And insight provides the more the knowing that is not
making it into everything. And there is what's known
and the knowing of it. And as soon as they see the difference between what see
the difference between what's known and what's known and the knowing of it, we
start to become free and respectful. We become that teacher in the classroom
door that's ready to s greet everything respectfully.
And so suffering is known. Suffering happens within a wholeness of
experience. We're rooted here to know it.
And we start seeing that suffering like everything else
is part of the river of change. Imagine.
So assuming a meditation posture,
a posture for being rooted,
stable on whatever surface hold your the weight
of your body up. a chair, the floor,
a bed, whatever it might be.
And to feel how the weight of your body settles
on the surface that holds it up. The surface in which your weight
meets the pole of gravity.
And as you exhale, allow yourselves to settle in
to the meeting of your weight
and the pull of gravity against that surface.
Maybe making small adjustments
so it's more comfortable, more rooted here.
and then arising from
that stable rooted contact. Feel the rest of your body.
How the weight of your body moves through
your torso.
And if you feel any weight
that exists there because of the pull of gravity
as you exhale, relax
into that pull. Let your weight settle.
Almost without trying or doing anything,
allow your inhale to be fuller
to expand more fully through your torso, your rib cage.
Not so much making yourself breathe deeper,
but yielding to the inb breath
and then yielding to the exhale.
So the exhale is more extended.
And as you exhale,
relaxing your whole body, a kind of yielding
to the pull of gravity. Yielding to the
desire for tension to unwind.
and then letting your breathing return to normal.
And now with the inhale, feel any tension, pressure,
forcefulness that might be in the thinking mind
as you exhale. soften the thinking mind.
Ever so gently quiet the thinking voice
or slow down the images of thoughts.
Rather than living in thoughts, let thinking
exist within a wider field of calm
spaciousness.
Then settling into
the body's experience of breathing.
without making a lot of effort or any effort at all.
See if you can recognize there is the experience of breathing
and there's the knowing of it.
The knowing of it could be verbal, it can be nonverbal.
Very simple. uncomplicated knowing
of the that you're breathing in, breathing out.
And knowing that's part of being rooted,
stable here in this body here and now.
And if as you're sitting here there's anything that might be called
suffering, stress,
emotional discomfort. Feel
the experience from a rooted,
respectful place. Know it
where the knowing is clear, free of what is known.
Like a teacher knowing each student coming to the door.
The teacher rooted, clear, fully here,
knowing the student clearly, respectfully,
but not losing
the calm, steady clarity that the teacher wants to convey to the
students.
See if you can avoid being defined by your suffering.
Let it be part of the larger experience of now.
One more thing to know, to greet,
and to be ready for the next experience,
to be with that.
Watching the smallest movements of the mind
to be sensitive to how there might be stress,
destress. in the mind.
And rather than ignoring it because it's subtle or big,
think of yourself standing at the door of the classroom.
greeting it while being calm, rooted, clear
where suffering and stress is simply one more thing to greet.
Nothing more, nothing less,
nothing to get involved in.
And as we come to the end of this sitting
to feel whatever degree of stability,
calm, centeredness might be here in the
present moment with your body
and imagine meeting the people of the day
going through the experiences of the next 24 hours
greeting each thing. It's one more thing to greet
from a place of stability and clarity, openness
to know each thing without being defined by it,
pushed around by it, caught in it. just to stand and
be present.
And just maybe that will allow
good will to be part of your attitude.
A field of goodwill, an attitude of goodwill
towards yourself, towards others,
towards the whole world. May all beings be happy.
May all beings be safe.
May all beings be peaceful.
May all beings be free.
And may my samadei and insight
support me to offer this gift to all beings.
[Music]
Thank you.
So, welcome to beginning of the week as we continue this series on insight
And the three insights that are core to the insight meditation practice
is having this deep observation, this deep
clarity, deep recognition of
change, of stress and of nonidentification.
And um and I choose those words carefully as an alternative to some of the usual ways of
saying talking about these three characteristics, three insights,
recognitions that we have. And um
and the focus currently is the second one duka
the rec deep recognition the capacity to recognize to perceive to know
suffering stress distress in such a way that uh we find our
freedom in it. we find ways in which we can grow spiritually and develop
ourselves. Uh rather than being overwhelmed by suffering, finding a way,
a natural way in which the heart, the mind, the inner life can grow and develop into
greater clarity, greater calm, greater care, love, a greater kind of sense of
wholeness. uh by how we recognize how we're present
for the suffering of our life and um and this of course is not easy
and this is why now we're on this you know we've done six months already now on samade and insight to prepare prepare
the ground for a deep useful way of engaging with suffering
and it comes and that's long preparation is a way of having a deep respect of
suffering, the challenges of it, the difficulty of being with it, but also the opportunities, the the the richness
that's possible by bringing this practice into the middle of it.
And um in uh there is a teaching that
goes back to the earliest time of Buddhism that says there are three types
of duka. The word now in the poly the ancient language the word is duka d u k k k k k
k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h and um and it's usually translated as suffering, but in its core it means pain
just or or strong discom discomfort or pain that can be physical and but it
could also be emotional and um it could also be uh quite deeply
embodied or rooted in us to become kind of the core operating principle from which uh not operating princip but the
core fuel for how we operate. We're reacting and adjusting and and uh and uh
and to our deep suffering in how we see the world, how we see ourselves, how we engage in the world.
So the tradition talks about three types of duka and sometimes it's helpful to
distinguish these three different types and uh and in a sense there's many many
characteristics of our suffering. There's many kinds of suffering, many
ways of understanding it and recognizing it. And different teachers
uh will emphasize different parts. Buddhists have been addressing this issue of duka of suffering for 2500
years. So you can imagine that over time things have shifted and there's been
different interpretations, different recognitions, different ways of working with it, different emphasis that goes
on. And so if you go through uh to the history of Buddhist teachings and even
in modern world listen to different teachers teachers in different terraan
traditions teachers in Burma teachers in Thailand um teachers in America uh
they'll they'll you'll find different teachers emphasizing different aspects of duka
and um so it isn't that they're contradicting themselves each other but
it's that there are just you know so many different ways ways of looking at it and the task is to find out how it's
useful for you to see it so that uh you find yourself not caught in it, not
entangled with it, not being undermined or deflated or overwhelmed by it. So
there are these three kinds of duka and uh the or three kinds of pain. There
is pain pain duka duka it's literally called there is the the duca of change
and there is the duca of mental constructs. So the first one is just straight
straightforward uh uncomplicated physical pain that can
be o mild and it can be overwhelming but
it's it's not there because of our psychology. It's not there because psychological reactions clinging. It's
not there because we're caught in attachments. It's there because uh it's
just straightforward physical pain. And um and for that we need to have a
wisdom. We have to have wisdom to know how to manage it. And uh we have a lot
more ways of managing physical pain in the modern world than they had in the ancient world
where the Buddha he used the power of his mind in order to deal with his intense pain as an old man. And uh he
would go into deep states of concentration. And he said sometimes that's the only time he got relief from
his uh old age pain that he had in the last years of his life. But you know to
be wise about it and one way to be wise is not to feel that we have to always endure it or that we should always find
uh use our practice to find our freedom from it or relief from it. Sometimes we
need medication. Sometimes we need medical care. something all kinds of
things that uh are useful. Uh but not to see it as a a personal
fault, not to see uh duka duka as as something that uh we
need to somehow criticize oursel for having, but it's something that we need to be wise about how to live with and
handle and find our way with. The second is um this uh the suffering
of change. And uh and here the assumption is that uh change isn't always welcome and um
and or that we want change in a way that's not happening. Uh change is
happening different than how we want it. And so uh and even if it change happens
in the way direction we want either way there can be attachment. There's
clinging and there's the suffering of clinging to something and then having it
change and go away and then that clinging then feels frustrated, feels
feels distraught and so there's a kind of suffering. So the suffering of uh
change also requires wisdom. But to some degree it requires the wisdom of
acceptance. That uh to some degree human life in order to find some way to live at peace,
at calm and steady. To be wise, we have to accept the fact that things change.
We get old. We get sick. We'll die. Other people get old, they get sick,
they die. Um the things of our life shift and change in ways that um uh we
don't want but still they change. Uh there can be natural disasters that
happen in your town, in your neighborhood, and that's a change. And
um and so to be able to somehow navigate the change uh with ease, with calm,
without the attachments being a wind drag, without being protesting against
the very nature of change, which is inherent in this natural world that we're part of. It's all things are
always changing. And of course we can have some role in changing things in the
right direction. Of course we can have some role in keeping certain things the way they are for a while. Uh we can uh
let our cars last longer by changing the oil or being careful how we drive or
something. But we want to be caring and careful but not be attached. And so the
the suffering of change um is when we somehow don't haven't accepted change as
a given and find a wise way to navigate with it. So deep acceptance,
no protests against the natural movements of change. And the third, the
one that's really core to Buddhism is the suffering of the mental formations.
This is the suffering of craving itself, the suffering of attachment, the suffering of the way that the the mind
engages in things where there is suffering, tightness, stress, uh
clinging, um resistance, pressure, um irritation, annoyance built into the
various ways in which we engage, relate to what's happening in this world. And
here is what the practice has the most power to work with. Here we're learning
not to accept things, but we're learning to or finding a way to have a deep
letting go, a deep relaxing of this added addition on top of our life that
we we contribute which is we contribute clinging. We contribute uh grasping,
craving, resistance, animosity, hatred, greed, jealousy, envy, covetousness,
um all kinds of things that we add that all of them that are characterized by
tension, stress, a tightening, a pressure that uh feels very
uncomfortable. And so this the the suffering of mental formations is a suffering which is
inherent in the movement of attachment in in all its different flavors and
forms. And um and turns out that this is the attachment that is most deep inside of
us. That maybe is for some people is is right there the core operating principle
from which they live and understand themselves and um define themselves.
And now this is the one that we want to be able to see with a tremendous clarity
with a mind that's very calm, still quiet, rooted. That's part of the whole.
This is the function of insight supported by samadei is to be able to
get so such a feeling of centered calm a sense of wellbeing
that we can see some of the deepest deepest places of suffering where we're holding on tight.
And that is one of the great wonderful maybe you can call it paradoxes of this
practice that the deepest suffering we have we
want to prepare ourselves to meet that by cultivating a good amount of settled
calm well-being that our sense of well-being sense of
joy or happiness that can come with samadei and insight um that becomes the
field within which we're ready to encounter some of the deepest holding
clinging patterns in our life. And so um so this is a a path of
preparation of being wise not to address things directly and force our way into a
peaceful state. But we prepare ourselves create the conditions so that we can be
present for the deepest clings we have in a way that allows for the deepest letting go of that kind of mental
constructs that involve clinging. attachment.
So three kinds of dooka. Duka duka, the duka of change and the
duca of mental formations. And uh each of them requires a different
kind of wisdom, a different approach. And um and so it's not just one way to
be with suffering. It uh we have to have some wisdom and understanding of which
ones we're working with. So thank you and um in this process may
you suffer in a way that uh supports you to reach the end of suffering. Thank
you.