welcome welcome nice to see you all it's nice to
practice together and today I'm going to continue
on this theme of it's January it's the beginning of the
year and you know it's not unusual for us to have this idea like okay you know
to assess maybe how the last year went and what I'm going to do this upcoming year
and heaven forbid we might make some resolutions all those things that we think we should be
doing and making a little joke out of it sometimes it can be really useful right
to uh set an intention at the beginning of the year
maybe uh start with a meditation practice or boost your meditation
practice or you know eat all those things that we know we should eat and
not eat those things that we know we shouldn't eat and exercise more all these things all these
things so there's this's way that uh January I might have mentioned this last week I can't remember I don't think I
did that I was kind of pleased to discover that it was named after this Roman god Janice right to of
beginnings and so it's not unusual maybe that there's this sense of
beginning with the new year and in the Buddhist tradition we don't
really emphasize Beginnings there isn't really this uh
pointing to Beginnings so much of course Beginnings are implicit within endings
but in the Buddhist tradition and maybe I'll just say as a
little aside when I say Buddhist tradition like Buddhism is really vast there are so many different Traditions
within it so Within this lineage this tradition that we practice here at
IMC there isn't a creation story I I never really thought about this before
until I until I did I guess thought like oh yeah there's like not an emphasis like how things
began there instead there's this idea that things arise due to causes and
conditions that things happen because the conditions are there for them to happen and that's how things begin so
then instead of just you like one particular thing that was a beginning in some way you might say there's not a
beginning and in the same way something that I really appreciate also about this tradition that um the only kind of like
um celebration that we have here at IMC is one that's common in Southeast Asia
and that is this uh visak we pronounce it vak there's different ways to pronounce it and this is like this real
efficiency like okay the Buddha's birth so that's the beginning but it's also
the day to celebrate his death and also the day of his Awakening
which is also a beginning right just all these kind of put together like just in one celebration that happens on the full
moon uh in the month of May usually in the month of
May and we might even think like well what like the symbol of Buddhism is a
wheel right with eight Spokes and this kind of implies this uh ongoing movement
it's not like a beginning and an end but something that's in
motion so instead what we talk about uh here in this tradition is about the
endings of suffering the end in of
difficulties like that's bringing this to an
end and of course the word is Dua that I'm translating as
suffering and uh Dua stands for this I kind of like this one word for such a
wide range little bit of stress on one end just something mildly uncomfortable
to something horrifying just tragic terrible things
that are happening on the other end so this one word for this wide range so for
the end of Dua is where this uh focus is on with
Buddhism and we might say related to that this ending this idea of ending the
ending of Dua but also this encouragement for us to notice and it's
a big part of practice is to notice the changing nature of
things in some ways you might say everything's ending and everything's
beginning and it's true that when you have a some real subtleness and some uh
often this happens on Retreat you can start to see oh yeah things are like flickering they're not as stable and
constant and as we imagine them to be as we are experiencing them to
[Music] be and so this idea of beginning maybe
is there implicit in this state of ending we might say the ending of Dua is
the beginning of peace wellbe
freedom so this idea of beginning like beginning in January I know that uh when
I lead uh guided meditations I'm often using this phrase begin
again so that if you're if you're using the breath as the anchor of your
meditation it's natural for the mind to drift away again unless you've been on a
retreat or sometime then the mind can really stay for a long time but usually if you're meditating for example just
coming here for 30 minutes of course I should say of course the mind is
drifting chances are you just came from a lot lot of doing maybe from work or
something and the mind is busy and so that busyness gets carried into the meditation and it takes time it takes
time for the mind to settle so the Mind drifts and then we just begin again with
the anchor which most often is the sensations of breathing we just begin
again so this idea of beginning again without this sense of oh you're going
back to the start as if you had never done anything now you just begin
again and we might say that this idea of beginning again is inherent in this idea
of cultivation of developing building up some of our
capacities as skills that we have could be mindfulness like what I uh
just described you know with the mind just coming back and just coming back and then the mind just starts to get the
hang of you know just hanging out there with the with the anchor but the same as true for loving
kindness maybe we're have a specific loving kindness practice when with that
the Mind might wander and but we come back again to this state state of you
know Wishing Well wishing others to have peace and happiness and
well-being we might even say this also about uh ethical practice right Sila
ethical practice the behavior the way we show up in the world the way that we treat others the way that we treat
ourselves this again is like begin again when we find ourselves maybe gossiping
something that's you know not helpful or taking that which isn't freely offered
in a way that I know there was a time when I was working uh I used to work for the US
government at one time and uh there was this real emphasis on don't take any
extra paper or pencils or anything these are us taxpayers are paying for this don't take anything but then when I went
to Corporate America after that they're like just you know take whatever you want and a lot of people were right they
were just taking stuff home that you know didn't really need but maybe I don't know why they were taking it home
but so just these are subtle thing not subtle these are minor things taking
pens and paper but there is this way in which uh
if we find ourselves maybe not following as closely to some of this ethical
ideals of not causing harm and not taking things that are not freely
offered to just begin again like oh yeah okay I used to do that let's see what
it's like maybe if I have a real commitment to my ethical
life for me this was a big movement in uh my I would say my spiritual
life in the beginning it was hard to meditate I just yeah had a hard time
with it but I thought well okay I'm going to give it a go with this these
precepts of um specifically um not I'll just say not
telling lies there's different ways we can translate it but cuz I used to
I used to say this a lot oh sorry I'm late the traffic was bad the traffic wasn't bad I just was
disorganized and just didn't leave the house on time or something like this or sorry I'm late there was you know I was
just make up some story about why I was late and I said you know what I'm going
to see what is it like to not tell these little white lies which we tend to think are like inconsequential who cares there
just a small thing turns out that they are consequential because I had made this
commitment to myself I wasn't going to do that anymore I had to show up on
time and showing up on time meant I had to be a little bit more organized and it
felt better to be a little bit more organized and to show up on time and not have to apologize it felt good to be
showing up on time and this just had these repercussions in my life my friends noticed like oh you're always on
time but this is something a small example I'm giving but this idea of beginning
again whatever we might choose that we want to cultivate mindfulness loving
kindness some of e ethical practices this commitment to not causing harm this
commitment to working towards a way in which there can be more peace and ease
and well-being so I'm going to say uh here's
a short little poem that talks a little bit about this it starts by talking
about endings and then it turns towards
Beginnings those of you who hear me regularly will not be surprised who the poet is it's Rose Mar
traumer uh she's just such a wonderful poet and um she wrote this poem at the
end of December in 2020 so we all know what 2020 was like
like and so she was reflecting back on that year when she uh wrote this
poem it's called bonfire of the
heart I throw in any tallies I've been keeping the ones that record who did
what and when I throw in all the letters I wrote in my head but didn't
send I throw in tickets I didn't buy to places I didn't visit I throw in all
those expectations I had for myself and
the world last year and countless lists of things I
thought I should do I love watching them ignite turn into
Embers to Ash I love the space they leave behind
where anything can happen love this last line I love the
space they leave behind where anything can happen so this idea that endings leave a
space and she's pointing to anything can happen it's like this beginning there might be something new that
arises there's this way that even the notion of Beginnings as a sense of you
know possibilities has this this idea of maybe this opportunities that uh we
aren't aware of or hadn't even thought of before so beginnings of course are
associated with endings but there's this maybe there's this uh way in which part of Beginnings
also have this uh inherent optimism something this idea of like okay something new can arise it's possible
this grind that I feel s stuck in perhaps maybe it's possible for
something different to arise but it might require that some
endings happen some of the ways in which we are holding on to our sense of self
some of the ways in which we are holding on to ideas of how we think things should be or how we think things should
not be not that we have to give up any ideas
of how we imagine the world could be or some of the ways in which we would like
it to be but it's the holding on and clinging to like No it should be this
way no I want it to be this way can we just hold these things
lightly can we hold our ideas our hopes for the world lightly this way in which
we hold on tightly just reaffirms this sense of me against the world sends up
this sense of of all these problems out there US versus them and everything has
to get fixed out there instead of this sense of well you know maybe there can be some growth that happens
here so starting a new after some
endings so the Buddha in his life story of course he had a number of beginnings
and we tell part of his biography we often aren't focusing on this instead
often there is this idea you know he's held up as an idealized uh individual somebody who has um attained
Awakening it makes perfect sense to do this one way we might understand that is
I would I would my understanding he was an extraordinary person but in this
tradition we really highlight the humanity of the person who be became the
Buddha and in this version of his story everything is part of what the tradition holds but I'm going to change a little
bit some of the emphasis that we place instead of everything that was um
wonderful or idealized point out some of the ways in which he had to begin again
had to begin again over and over quite a few times there's this way in which you know
of course we are beginning again too when we're cultivating things with whether it's mindfulness or whatever it
is in your professional life or in your personal
life so many of you know that uh the person who was to become the Buddha
started out as uh having a life with you know we could say of
luxury with uh lots of sensual indulgences and whatever ways uh we
might imagine probably that was being experienced but then he realized oh
there's something more and I want to seek
it so um the way that this gets captured in the ancient Buddhist L literature is
that he wanted to seek the Supreme state of sublime peace Supreme state of
sublime peace notice it's not some great
philosophical uh thing that he's after it's just he just wanted some
peace I appreciate this very much so he left his uh life of sensual
indulgences and all this uh niceties and luxuries and began with learning some
meditative practices was able to achieve some meditative
States but then he realized well that actually wasn't the Supreme state of
sublime peace even though some of those meditative states are very pleasant it's
not the highest and when they end they end and they always will it's not like
you can get into those States and stay there forever so then he began again with okay
well this didn't work these medit attaining these meditative States maybe I can try some of this um
asceticism extreme asceticism that some practitioners were doing at the time and so he was doing a
number of um practices including not eating so practically starving himself
to death and he he's at this time he's practicing with uh five other
individuals and so the six of them are doing this extreme aestheticism and uh the person who was
to become the Buddha says yeah this isn't the Supreme state of sublime peace either and I
don't think I can get there from here because I'm he's not saying this but there was just so much
suffering so then he has a Insight he has a memory about earlier in his life
he had had some meditative states that weren't like these really high meditative states he was um practicing
earlier but he felt like okay from there that felt like there was some ease there
so then he started to begin again with a middle way not sensual indulgences not
ex self mortification but something that had some pleasantries but also had some
discipline the middle way and it was practicing that way in
which he became awakened and then became the individual that we call the
Buddha so he had to Begin Again a number of times like you know trying practices
until he found a way and then after
Awakening then what and it seems that he wasn't sure
what to do he had thought well he was hesitant to begin teaching he thought that I'm not sure
that I'm going to teach and the literature says that if I were to teach
the Dharma others would not understand me and that would be wearing and
Troublesome for me so he's saying yeah I don't think anybody else would get it how do I explain this to
others but then he is convinced to teach by a deity that comes down and convinces
him tells him no no no there are people that will understand so he he does he
begins to teach and he has in his mind who is he going to teach and uh he settles on
teaching those five individual uals that he was practicing with before the ones that were doing the
asceticism and on his way to walk to where they are it's about 130 miles or
so so it's a you know it's a journey uh to walk there and he he meets
somebody who uh says UPA is his name and
UPA meets the Buddha soon after his Awakening and notices wow there's some
something different about this person here and he says your faculties are
clear your skin is pure and bright who is your
teacher so this would would have been a common thing to say like who is your teacher like who is your who do you
follow but they noticed like okay must have been what is this that your skin is pure and bright and your faculties this
could have been like his eyes seemed like something's different about this person that just became awakened and
like who's your teacher and I'm imagining the upaca is wondering well maybe I'll go you know to that same teacher because clearly you've had some
benefit and uh maybe I can go to that teacher
too and then the Buddha replies uh I'm excerpting some of this I
have no teacher and one like me exists nowhere else else in the
world I am the accomplished one I am the teacher
Supreme so opacus shakes his head and say if you say so and turns around and
walks away so I kind of like this like okay so the Buddha he begins teaching but the
first person he meets he's not able to teach that person instead he kind like
Pro proclaims that he is the Buddha and UPA was oh
okay and shakes his head and turns and walks away they they say they he walked
um I forgot what the expression is it's like an alternate route you know he kind of wanted to avoid the Buddha so for me
is kind of an interesting thing so even his beginning teaching didn't uh go you
know wasn't like he immediately knew what to do So eventually he comes to this group of
five that he had been practicing with before and they have a different
reaction they see him and they can see that he has been eating and looks better
and has more energy and they say amongst themselves they see him in the distance
and they say to themselves Let's uh not uh treat him give him the honor or
respect of a of somebody that's coming to to meet us we'll just treat him like
somebody that we know and um they show
up and they see him and they recognize oh yeah
something is different about him and then he has a conversation with
them and they say okay yeah we recognize something has shifted in you maybe you
can teach us so then he teaches them but they don't all immediately become
awakened only one has the first stage of Awakening kund is his name and it takes
some time because the it's reported how they are going out for MMS round so that means you know every day they're going
out to get more meals it takes some time before the first person becomes um
awakened and then it takes a a little bit more time for all five of them too
so now there are six people in the world that are awake the Buddha and he helped five other people his former uh
companions when he was an athetic so he began with people who were
already spiritual Seekers and then the sixth student uh
the Buddha went to the opposite extreme to a very wealthy lay person who had no
interest in the spiritual life his name is Yesa
and teaches him and he becomes awakened and then I'll just say then y's
father and then y's mother so here's the first woman and then y's wife is uh the
second woman so persons uh let's see six seven persons 8 and nine to get uh
awakened are women I just want to slip that in there
so this idea about Beginnings right this little biography
of the Buddha I kind of like start the new year often kind of like talking about some of this and I'm highlighting
how we had to begin again it's not like everything was easy and fast and
simple and so we begin again and you've had chances there are
lots of Beginnings in your practice first time coming to a meditation center first time coming to IMC first time
meditating maybe first time going on Retreat or maybe you're feeling inspired
that uh sometime this year you'll go on a retreat if you haven't or maybe going to a day long a whole day of practice
here at IMC or something like this so this idea of
beginning such a like an inherent part of practice to begin
again but I'll also say well what was the beginning teaching what was the
teaching where did the Buddha begin or let me say a different way how did he
start beginning or what what was the beginning thing that he taught to lay
people to Yesa he started with generosity he started with teaching
about generosity because generosity is this movement right of like letting go or of
uh giving or opening up or unclenching unclenching our minds or our um ideas or
with uh maybe with time or our resources generosity doesn't have to be about
money can give people the benefit of the doubt so it's this movement generosity
this movement of the heart and mind about letting go and we might say that
this whole practice is about letting go letting go of all the ways in which
we are holding on and limiting ourselves I'm not saying that we have
to accept everything and be passive I'm talking about this the opposite of this
movement of feeling like I need more I need more I need more this way in which we can feel like
okay things will be okay or I will start behaving better or um doing showing up
in a way that I want to in the world as soon as something else happen as soon as I've
acquired whatever it might be acquired that new job acquired uh something in a
with a relationship a um retired or as soon
as our life situation has changed in some particular way or as soon as you
know I've done X Y and Z it's endless so there's this way we feel like
we have to either acquire experiences or we have to acquire money or acquire
objects or acquire respect or acquire whatever it is relationships
before we can start practicing and so much of this practice
is about letting go is the opposite movement and if we find it difficult to
even uh think of this idea of letting
go then we can just have some curiosity about well what is it that's underneath
this idea that I need to have
more to be sure I'm not saying that we shouldn't have more money I wish everybody all the wealth that they need
of course that would be great right just imagine the how the world would be if everybody felt like they had enough
wouldn't that be fantastic of I'm not saying that we have to just accept for what what we have I'm
pointing to this idea like this discontent this feeling of no I I I need
more and what's underneath that what's fueling
that because this Sublime peace is not going to come around as long as we're
ignoring that this feeling of no I got to have more whatever's here is not good
enough I refuse to accept it I have to have more there that's often this underlying
belief that we have that we're not even noticing and it kind of like fuel some
drive to do a lot of good in the world so this I'm not saying that uh we
should just be Bliss blobs or something like this and pointing to this can we
let go of this idea
that the Sublime peace or any kind of Peace can only be found in the future
can only be found when things are different generosity is kind of like
this opening it's pointing towards this letting go and this generosity with literal
things with our time or with our resources helps us to learn about
ourselves helps us to see see that what is it that uh what are some of
these beliefs about what's really valuable what are some of our beliefs that we have about what we need more
of and part of the way that generosity is the first teaching is it helps us to
understand ourselves more understand okay what is it that I
think is valuable what is it that I think that uh maybe some people deserve
and other people don't deserve or you know some of these beliefs that we might
have because Awakening is the greatest letting go it's the deepest letting go
it's letting go of this sense of that there is this uh Essence this inherent
core um to me and to which everything's
happening like there's this Bond changing thing and everything's just happening to
this and as soon as this thing feels good then everything's going to be
fine but with practice we start to see actually there isn't anything there is
there isn't a inherent thing it's just a collection of
experiences that we're just having over and over you know again and again and again that's turns out to be all what life is
but you don't have to just because I said it you don't have to believe it and you don't have to try to make sense out
of this either this is usually it's something experiential it's usually something that with a meditative
experience or something that can be like oh wow yeah there really yeah there isn't a self fear actually in the way
that I thought so it's not something you have to adopt is a
belief so part of the reason why the Buddha was talking with yes and this beginning with generosity is because
letting goes this this movement is all about what this practice is about and
generosity we help to learn about ourselves what are some of our beliefs what is it that's fueling this
sense of that there has to be more instead of this letting go but not only
that this generosity like literally being generous with our time time or
giving people the benefit of the doubt or with our expertise it also helps build
community gen generosity is a way whatever we're generous with in whatever way
volunteering I know that uh through volunteering I've like in different organizations different places
I've really have had a a sense of community like PE us coming together to
do something you know to something that's important to us so generosity is also a place that
builds community and this practice what a difference it makes if we have some
community so this idea of beginning again beginning with whatever is
important for you something that you Aspire for and to recognize that just be
beginning again I like this idea again recog it's like honors and
respects the human tendency to not do things in a straight line we're not
machines we we are off you know get uh distracted we lose our
motivation we sometimes uh get filled with doubt
you know all these things whatever is happening can we just begin
again just begin again and the Buddha just began again and if you feel like
well with your spiritual life you're not sure where to begin or maybe you do have some clarity but I can of offer a good
starting place for all kinds of things is generosity for your spiritual practice for working on your
relationships or your professional life all these things generosity can be a
good place to begin so I'll end there and then I'll
open it up to see if there's some questions and comments thank
you do do we know how long it took yasa and his wife to get enlightened after
the met the Buddha the story is the same day they
met come awakened that's the story that's the
story there's a story the uh the Buddhist literature is filled with all kinds of people who meet the Buddha and
become awakened and also people who don't who need time and have to practice and who are monastics under him or
followers or lay people under him and who don't become awaken and immediately so there's a whole range of people in
the sutas wouldn't it be nice well actually maybe if you meet a Buddha right
maybe do you think there are there are people nowadays who meet somebody and
get in light that doesn't happen anymore if it happens I don't know about
it
anybody else have a comment or
question yeah uh thanks for the talk um I think um some parts of it reminded me of
some concept I came across and there's a newsletter um there's a concept of uh
not knowing um and then there's a phrase associated with it which is like not
knowing is not the same as knowing nothing but it's this idea of holding
beliefs lightly um and so part of what this talk is
inspiring me to do is to try and like um build that intuition for how to become
more comfortable naturally I'm a pretty I would say like anxious thinker tend to over um over anchor on oh I know all
these things therefore it might lead to XYZ risk um but the idea of not knowing
is pretty refreshing so I don't know if you have more kind of comments on that as a concept or ways to get more
comfortable with that but um that's just kind of what I'm what's going on after
this talk yeah yeah yeah not knowing it's uh this is a great topic and uh
especially like uh I'm somebody who I spent my life trying to know things to figure things out and uh it was uh such
a relief when I realize it's like oh we don't have to know things and this
uh but what I think it requires is a little bit of
uh yeah confidence that okay things are going to unfold the way they're going to
unfold whether I understand them or not or whether I uh yeah whether I
understand them or not
and so how to work with this is to recognize sometimes the freedom I guess
a few things I'll say one is there can be a certain Freedom like okay I'm not going to try to figure that
out and just like not try to figure something out whereas you know there's
cuz there is a nice feeling like oh yeah I just got it like that's like a nice uh
feeling but there can also be a feeling of uh a nice feeling with you know what
this can just be how it is and I don't have to try to figure it out because so
often I mean some things we can figure out like why isn't the checkbook balanced like usually those things with
numbers we can do right but why is it that this happens when that doesn't happen I can't think of an example off
the top of my head but to there's something about like you know it's just
that way and I don't know why and that's
okay there can be some real Freedom there so to not
knowing and then I'll say that um
often what the reason why we do want to know is because there's some unsettledness underneath there's some
like uncomfortable like okay this and actually The Knowing
is a distraction trying to trying to figure it out turns out to be a distraction from something that's
uncomfortable and the uncomfortable thing is an emotion or um a disturbing
thought or something like this and it turns out that as long as that uncomfortable disturbing thought is
there we will always we will just find more things to figure out just as as a way to distract ourselves from often our
life so it's not like okay as soon as I figur out might there be a moment oh okay I figured that out yeah but then
there's that other thing and it just never ends it never ends
so that to be okay with not knowing makes space for us to stop distracting
ourselves from what's actually happening which might be bad news cuz we might be
I'm saying it's bad news because it's not what we want we we're trying to figure things out in order to not be
with what is but to be with what is is the way forward this is how you'll find peace this is where the this the peace
is is to actually be with what is and not always distracting ourselves with trying to figure things
out thank you well set yeah back there
I feel like I'm having a really warm response to and I'm going to try and
choose my words carefully here but like you highlighting the fallibility of the role model of the spiritual practice we
have and it's one thing I've always kind of enjoyed is that he always had to start again and as you were sharing
about starting over for the Buddha I for some reason popped in my mind his relationship with his son Rula
like he pieced out like I'm going to give you a name and I'm gone and then he
his son comes to him and then going through and teaching having to start over and over with his son over again
like teach him as a monastic and just I know with relationships in the new year that just really touched a sweet cord in
my heart so thank you thank you thank you Conrad yeah I kind of skipped over that
part of the story those of you know the budh story know that uh the Buddha left
to on his spiritual quest uh right after his son was born and there was like wait
what maybe I'll talk about that another Dara
talk okay so I see that we're at the end of the or it's at the half hour 8:30 so
thank you all for your practice and your kind attention and I wish you a lovely rest of the evening thank you you