good evening welcome welcome nice to see you all nice to
practice together I wanted to talk a little bit
about thoughts tonight in other settings I've been talking about thoughts and I like to
talk about it some more here because there's this way like when we sit down and meditate like we just
did for 30 minutes there often can be this sense of like dang it where are all these thoughts
here or there can be a sense of like why is the mind so busy or if only my
thoughts were different or would go away or something like this even if it's uh those expressions
weren't explicitly said in the mind there can be
a way in which we have a little like resistance or aversive relationship to our thoughts especially when we're
meditating when we're not meditating we love our thoughts but when we're meditating we uh often or you know wish
it it would go away or be otherwise in some kind of way so in this tradition as many of you
know this not about getting rid of thoughts we don't have to do that turns out you can't in a way that you think
you might be able to anyway but really what's being pointed to is just noticing our relationship to
thoughts so it's more about noticing and just how how we are
engaging with thoughts how we're being with them are we all in like in love
with them and being entertained by them or we when we wake up from being in Lost
in thought thinking like oh shoot I'm supposed to be meditating oh here we go
again when you're lost in thought while you're meditating no no problem because you're lost in thought there's like
nothing to be done right you just are lost in thought you can't make yourself
not be lost in thought so somehow I know at the beginning of my meditation practice somehow I thought that uh I
should be able to wake myself up but doesn't work that way probably you've noticed that we
don't have this uh way we do this uh we can't like just force things to the way
that we want them to be and I say this a lot and if you could
you wouldn't be here at a meditation center on a Monday night you would be out having whatever thoughts you wanted
whenever you wanted so maybe it's helpful to just
um just say briefly well why is there often just this incessant flow of
thoughts while we're um sitting down to meditate
one way or one reason it might be is that it can support a sense of feeling
safe that's probably not what's on top of Mind instead what the mind is doing
it has this sense of like I got to figure this out I got to solve this
problem I got to get to the end of this I got to make this be different in some
kind of way and there's this way that um we feel like okay well if I only figure
this out then everything will be fine and then I'll be safe and comfortable
maybe maybe that's a another way of thinking about
it but there's this way in which um trying to figure things out or try to
solve a problem really takes us away from what's
being experienced from what's here right now
and it turns out if we want to be safe really it's just to be with what's actually
happening because the harm is going to be you know in this moment I'm not saying that we don't have to plan
sometimes we do have to plan I'll talk a little bit more about that later but if there is a feeling of
wanting to be safe or feeling unsafe then it's to be with our experience like what's being heard with what's being
seen what's being experienced with the body I'm I'm rocking like this like
often you don't to feel your feet on the ground and feel like oh I'm I'm actually
here or maybe there's just a lot of thinking because that's what we've been
trained to do that's what we've been conditioned to do certainly we have an educational program that supports
that lot of thinking of course and many of us have had professions jobs that
really supported a lot of thinking and we got rewarded for our thinking and so
this is you know of course we've been doing this our life long it's not going to stop just all of a sudden so that's
another reason why there might be a lot of thoughts but here's one that um I had which I didn't even really notice that I
had in the beginning of my meditation practice and it was with a meditation
teacher uh who kind of pointed this out to me and that was I had this like
discomfort with just not knowing like I felt like oh I just have
to know everything I just you know I don't know I just felt better and I couldn't like say
exactly why so some of you may know I'm like trained as a researcher right so this was like suited me perfectly just
go figure things out and I loved it when I was a research scientist like I just have a question hm
I wonder if it's because of this and then go design experiments and do experiments I just loved it it kind of
like supported this idea like to know things is like the most
important we don't have to know everything it turns out we feel
uncomfortable like not knowing things but there's this way in which just this
wanting to know is Just Thoughts talking to other thoughts talking to other
thoughts talking to other thoughts so often it's um in some ways it's just a
distraction it's a way in which we're trying to feel more comfortable and because we figure like if I just knew
everything I would feel better but often what's going to help us
feel better is to align with the reality of the
moment but so often the reality of the moment is exactly what we don't want
it's too hot it's too cold they didn't talk to me the right way I should have
done that thing I don't know there's just so many ways in which it feels like
not quite right so we often like just kind of Escape into thoughts and try to figure
something out there's this way that that's uh can be a certain type of entertainment but I'll talk a little bit
more about entertainment in a moment but also it's it's just a distraction from the present moment
experience if we're okay with what's happening then there isn't this push to
leave this moment so there's this way that thoughts
you know we don't can't control them of course not anybody who's ever
had a song stuck in their mind sometimes because like an earworm right
NOS like oh why is this song still happening here you didn't make it there you didn't put it there and you can't
make it just go away it just shows up again and again right so these things they just arise
spontaneously out of our control they're just uh that's what
thoughts do that's the nature of thoughts it's not something that we're intentionally trying to
do so maybe instead of this idea that we have to get rid of our thoughts or that
uh we should have only maybe I'll just stay there instead of getting having
this idea that we have to get rid of our thoughts instead can we have this maybe
um aspirations for different types of relationships we can have with our
thoughts instead of trying to control them can we have some different relationships and one relationship is
can we not feel harassed or hared by our
thoughts is there a way that we can say wow that's kind of annoying that that
song is stuck in my head well okay that's just the way it is and let it be
okay even though it's not what we want cuz there's this way of trying to
make it be different or that little bit of irritation that shows up or trying to figure out like why is this song in my
head that's this way in which we're fueling them interacting with them but
then if we have this idea okay I don't want to interact with them so I'm not going to so that they'll go away but
there's still that secret I'm trying to get them to go away so I'm not going to think about them but it's that trying to
not it's trying to make them go away that's going to have them persist so can we just have a
relationship that we're just not harassed or hared like yeah okay this is what the mind is
doing we don't have to take it personally we don't have to make it a problem we're not making it happen it's
you know we're not uh choosing to have these thoughts and just allow them to be there
the best we can I'll talk a little bit more more like how we can work with some
particular thoughts there's a maybe another aspiration we can have with our thinking
is can we discern maybe helpful from unhelpful trains of
thought Buddha talked about there's this um whatever one thinker thinks and
ponderers upon that will become the inclination of the mind so with this recognition right that
we in some ways we're kind of like making these grooves in the mind with things that we think about a lot
whatever we think about a lot just becomes easier and easier to think about it so if we can notice well what's
helpful and what's not helpful if these grooves are going to be made can we have some helpful grooves made as opposed to
some unhelpful ones and the Buddha talked about this this was part of his path towards
Awakening when he discovered or noticed oh there are some thoughts that are
helpful and some that aren't some that lead to suffering Dua and some that don't and then he
talked about when he started to investigate he like kind of like boiled it down to thoughts of Cruelty not
helpful causes Affliction and dooka for myself and probably leaks out and causes
it for others too thoughts of ill will just this not
cruelty not harming but just like aversion and wanting to push away turns out not to be
helpful and thoughts of sensual desire just thinking about how you're going to satisfy every desire you've ever had or
something like this also turns out not to be
helpful so there's this way in which when we can feel into or maybe just
logically notice like follow so trains of thoughts like yeah yeah it's not so
helpful then there's a way that some of the power behind them some of the
Authority or some of the momentum behind them can start to lessen so just to make this
observation is this leading to something that's helpful or not is this helpful or
not helpful and helpful we can Define as leading to more ease leading to more
peace leading to more freedom I keep on saying this and then
I'll talk about a little bit what to do with uh things that aren't helpful if you find yourself stuck in something
that's really not helpful I'll talk about that at the end here but something that I think is
really fascinating is here's the Buddha is these his teachings preserved in the
poly Canon thousands of years ago here's somebody who's saying you know all this
thinking is tiring and it's straining he was just maybe pointing out
how if we really notice this like always trying to figure things out or always
trying to entertain ourselves or whatever it is it's turns out to be
taxing but we don't notice it's taxing unless we have a meditation practice
that we have a experience some calmness and then stability and then we can realize oh
yeah this calmness compared to what my mind is usually doing is quite
something this certainly has been my experience and I think this is uh one way we could say we could describe this
whole path of practice is just starting to notice just more and more subtle
levels of agitation we think like oh wow this is
fantastic and then a little bit more meditation practice or maybe it doesn't even have to be meditation practice
practice we start to say oh yeah there was that little bit more agitation I didn't notice that's even a little bit
more quiet and a little bit more a little bit more we could say this is the entire path of practice so in this way
we could say subtle is significant like seeing subtle agitation
subtle way in which thinking is tiring taxing and straining can be a support
for us to not always be pursuing it
but then we can um and then maybe the third aspiration we might have for our
relationship to our thoughts is well can we if recognizing that planning is
really helpful appropriate we need to do it we do need to solve problems there
are plenty of problems to solve big problems small problems lots of them we
need thinking so is there a way that we can
learn to think well like to use thinking to actually
solve problems to help ourselves to help others to make the world a better place
to help us find more ease and freedom this isn't necessarily during
meditation practice but is there a way that we can learn to think well as opposed to
maybe just simply a agreeing or disagreeing with what we hear in the media or social media or mainstream
Media or whatever it might be instead of just like oh I don't like that that's terrible oh yeah this is good this makes
me feel good can we do something a little bit beyond that to solve problems can we um think in a way that really
leads to a place that is can we think in a way that's helpful
that leads to a place that has more freedom so there's this way in which thinking
well you can say includes asking questions like what what do I know about
this what what do I not know about this what is not being said
here what what what if I were to look at this from a different
direction we could say that the Buddha did this as well as part of uh his
Awakening process too he asked some questions starting with like well what
is it that is we could paraphrase and say the big
problem he identified it as death it's the big problem and he's like well what what
causes to death why is there death what's what is the leading to death came
up with an answer but then he didn't stop there he came up with another like well then what leads to that and why is
this like that and thinking and think like thinking in this way and pondering
and coming up with a way that pointed to direct
experience as part of a key part of uh finding our freedom so can we use use our thoughts
this most likely is not during meditation but at other time in a way that ask questions and has
a commitment to finding the answer as a commitment to solving the
problem otherwise there's this way we'll just spin around and around and around I'm sure all of us have done this right
there can be this feeling of stuckness like I can't figure this out I don't know what to do but there's a way in which we can't
find our way forward I'll talk a little bit more about how to do this in a meditation
practice but one way to do this to help with the
thinking outside of meditation which we really do want to use thoughts to solve a problem or to
plan it turns out it can be really helpful use a pen and
paper kind of this oldfashioned way remember those pens and
paper there's something like when we write something
down then it kind then it doesn't it have to be kind of like held in the mind
in the same way and then there's a way which we can write something else down and then we can like draw arrows or Draw
X's or Circle things or there's a way in which we can get the stuff out of our
mind and onto paper can be a really helpful way I'm not saying this is the
best way for everybody but for some people many people it's really helpful
there's a way in which we' gone to keyboards it's we can do this if you
have a facility in doing this but there's a way in which a pen and paper kind of you know engages the hand of
course and the feeling of the pen against the paper but there's something about drawing a line connecting things
or crossing things out or making a bulleted list in the margin or something
like this can be really helpful this is what I do to organize talks I uh and it's fun for me to look
back in the chicken scratch I have and it's all kinds of stuff and turn the
page this way and write a little things and then I look at it and then H I'm not quite sure and then I then I go to the
keyboard and start to organize some of the stuff that's on the
paper so this way in which if we want to have this aspiration to use thoughts to
think well that is to really solve problems instead of just swim around in
them ask questions have that real commitment that you actually do want to solve it there's
a way in which we can get lost just there I don't know how to explain this
maybe you have had this experience where you want to solve something but
it's also a difficult thing so you want to solve it and yet you also want to be
a little bit distant from it so that you don't feel the emotional
discomfort things that are hard to solve are often difficult because because they have some emotional content that are
some of our buttons are getting triggered or something is um maybe a underlying emotion is trying
to Bubble Up in some kind of way so can we say well I'm going to try really want
to solve this whether this is a big giant thing how do I prepare for my
vacation in two weeks or is it you know how do I have this difficult
conversation with my co-worker who is always correct ing me or how do I tell
my partner that um they're not doing their share of the
housework again but I want to uh make this not be confrontational what are
some ways that I can do this in a way that I'm not falling into these old patterns and not so that we don't get
into the same fight that we often get into whatever it might be
so maybe I'll just say that um I I did uh mention this idea of entertaining
thoughts so maybe I'm transitioning now to talk about meditation in particular
we might notice that some of the thoughts are just entertainment certainly outside of that
either but thinking about well let's see so you know that room I really should
put up some different window coverings because it doesn't really matter match the furniture in there or maybe I should
paint it a different color or whatever it might be might have some decorating ideas or we might have some uh thoughts
about sports well who should play are they going to put that person in the infield in the next game I'm saying this
not really knowing baseball very well so I'm but you know just there's this way in which we kind of uh just think these
types of things it's just a way of the Mind entertaining itself
and then we can just if we find this happening we could just maybe like Drop in a question or maybe you could just
even reflect on it right now is there a fear of
boredom does this seem like the absolute worst thing that could ever
happen how many quadrillion bazillion dollars are spent to make sure that
nobody is ever bored it's quite something
right boredom it's not so
bad and it turns out if you have a mindfulness practice you can never be bored
again just feel like oh this feels like boredom what does boredom feel
like sense of impatience there's some restlessness maybe there's irritation
with whatever I think should be happening instead or something like
this but there's this way just we kind of fall into thinking which often isn't
helpful just so that we won't be bored but instead if we notice there's this
little thing that we just want to get our phones out can we not take our phones out and
just be with the experience of boredom and just get to know it
it turns out to be quite interesting which is fascinating that boredom is
interesting so just an
invitation then maybe I'll say so here are some things if you find yourself in
meditation some things to work with if you find that you're um there's
a uh compuls or obsess compulsive those
these are words that don't sound so great but there can be a way in which there's a lot of energy behind thoughts
and some spinning and feeling like they're uh have a lot of energy behind them so here's
something to do here's some things to do one just drop in the
question what will my next thought be
ask yourself now what will your next thought
be this can be fascinating to kind of like be looking
and like waiting for thought and you notice there's a small little Gap a
small little Gap while you're waiting for the next thought which the next thought is most likely oh this is silly or wait oh
that's that's am I doing this right or something really fast that we often
aren't noticing as a thought but just that dropping in what will my next
thought be does two things it shifts our relationship right we're no longer lost
in the thoughts We Now The Observer and it disrupts the momentum of
whatever was happening these two things can be really powerful and you can just
again and again drop in these things what will the next thought
be there's something about when I practice with this that uh like the like
sitting back and looking at thoughts kind of like connects to just this
vastness this openness this space like there's no problems they're just hanging
out saying what the next thought is going to be there's something that's can be really beautiful about this because
it makes it easier and easier for this vast spaciousness to open
up so that's one thing to do if you find yourself with
meditation and you there's or I guess it doesn't have to be in meditation in
daily life what will the next thought be maybe one thing I I'll say is that
sometimes it's helpful if we find ourselves um with a lot of thinking and a pressure
behind thinking to remind ourselves okay these are just
thoughts like nothing out there in the external world is changing we're just
thinking because there's this way in which uh we we tend to link some like
our thoughts with what's going to happen or might happen or will happen or
something like this if we can just say it's just mental activity it's just what Minds
do we don't have to take it personally we don't have to make it into a big problem this is just what Minds do
there's a way that can help support a a certain amount of relaxation and ease with this recognition of okay this
doesn't have to be turned into a big problem cuz thoughts are are actually
just if you really look at them are only pointing to
thoughts which are pointing to other thoughts which are pointing to other
thoughts which are pointing to other thoughts right there's nothing out of here that's actually happening it's just
thinking it's just thinking and so there's this way kind of like noticing
not only the in insubstantiality of them but how they're just happening inside
here in this uh thought space so that's a second thing if you can bring this to
mind so maybe just remind yourself about this when you find
yourself with this certain amount of thinking a third thing one what will my
next thought be to recognize it's just thoughts mental activity the third is
can you bring some car osity to the experience the experience of
thinking but that might be a little bit hard so maybe just expense experience
whatever is happening sounds sites pressure against the body you know
bodily Sensations feeling the clothes against the skin these types of things
just like bring the some of the energy towards other sense doors and then kind
of like take out some of the energy that's going towards thinking so it's a third thing to do is
just go towards uh another sense
door if you're meditating and you feel like oh wow okay
I I this is not helpful and I'm really caught up in this it can be really
helpful to just systematically do a body scan tune into the bily experience on the
head on the eyes from the mouth the shoulders upper back lower back chest
belly hips legs and feet and just kind of a few seconds in each
spot and just checking them this gives the Mind something to
do which can be really helpful and kind of like take up some of the bandwidth and it also is a way starts to
help you get more embodied and then when you're more embodied thoughts are less
uh spinning around and going elsewhere and things like this so a body scan can
be really help just intentionally doing this um systematically through the body
then if there's a lot of energy around thoughts when you're meditating you could do some meta
practice because meta practice is using thoughts so it's also kind of like using
some of the mental bandwidth but it's using some of the thoughts in a way
that's uh positive and supportive and what I mean about me meta practice those
of you who U many of you might already have a met to practice but it's something bringing to mind
um somebody who's dear to you and you might send some good willll
may you be happy may you be
healthy may you be safe may you live with ease so just these four phrases and we
could just repeat them may you be happy May may you be healthy may you be safe
may you live with ease and this can really just change the
inner Ecology of the mind this sincere wish
for somebody that we care about somebody that's dear to us and to be wishing them
well can be really make a difference and not there's something also about the Rhythm about just saying
these phrases over and over that just naturally start to settle things down bring some uh stability and quiet to the
mind so that the mind isn't just uh thrashing
about so I offered quite a few things here if you find yourself really kind
like lost in thinking ask yourself what will the next
thought be I love this one I I think this is fun it's h can be surprising and
can really it just it can be a little bit of a shock to the mind in some kind
of way it's not used to being asked what's going to be next recognize it's just mental activity
they're just thoughts that are happening and there's a way that noticing that can
bring a little more relaxation and remove a little bit of the urgency that might be
there bring some curiosity to the experience like to other sense stors
what's being heard what's been seen what's being felt in the body do a body scan just systematically
go through the body or do meta practice these are some of the ways in which we
can work with thinking not because we have to get rid of thinking but just so
that we can um have a relationship with our thoughts that really support some
well-being and that can be support some greater peace and ease and freedom
because when we start to pay attention we start to notice we actually are wrestling with our thoughts or we're
lost in thoughts it's either one or the other usually but they're just useful
companions can we have them be useful companions instead of being harassed or
hared by them and maybe I'll close with this
short poem it's by Rosemary
traumer it's called could I say it and really mean
it by Rosemary trummer a pomegranate tennis racket wide
openen Lily B basically anything can act as a trojan horse to get those old ideas
close to me and dang I'm confronted again with all the ways I've let down
the world in all the ways I could have I should have done better how many times
have I tried to escape these thoughts I've run Mountain races and
written thousands of pages and wept a spring flood and confessed and bled and
still they find a way back to me
Sometimes They Come knives drawn but more often they come wearing fluffy robes and
slippers making themselves at home I cornered one
today looked it right in the eye what I said what do I have to
do it shook its head and said all I ever wanted was for you to say thank you
this this different relationship to our
thoughts so I'll end there and open it up to see if there's some comments or
questions thank
you we'd like to do we'd like you to use the microphone so people can other people can
hear uh you mentioned you have a background in research can you tell us
more about that if you're comfortable sharing I'll just say I have a PhD in Biochemistry and I used to do cancer
research in a laboratory white lab coat the whole B whole whole nine yards cool
thanks any else yeah right behind you hello hi um I was just was wondering
if you have any advice in terms of um people who struggle with chronic um
health issues and whilst meditating and doing the body scans um how do you kind
of um not focus on the painful parts of
that there's a lot I could say I'll say briefly two things one is it's really
helpful if you can to not use the word that uh rhymes with the word rain and
starts with the letter P instead to really think about is this
a stabbing or is it a throbbing is it hot or is it cold is it
moving is it like dynamic or is it in one place is it diffuse or is it uh like
really pinpointed so that is to kind of like zoom in and maybe like describe The
Experience because it's there it's already there so that's one way because
there's one way in which we slap a label on it that then we have a relationship
with this label oh my gosh this is uh further evidence of my imminent demise
you know there's this way in which it all these rightly so appropriately that we have this when
there's I'm just going to use this word pain when there's pain then um we might think it just sets off a whole Cascade
of thinking thoughts about doctors and emergencies and what's wrong with us and
all these types of things so instead to maybe zoom in is one
way um another way is to zoom out and that is I'll just say briefly we
could say um to notice not maybe during a body scin if we find ourselves getting sucked into oh my gosh this uh whatever
the discomfort might be can you um turn your attention to other sense doors
sounds is a really good one because that uh there's a way and just I'm just going
to open up and listen to sounds and just let sounds arise you don't have to figure them out you don't have to know
anything about them because opening up to sounds is a way that uh often um
brings a little bit more spaciousness and then maybe the third thing I'll say is um is there a neutral or a pleasant
experience in the body and as best you can can you rest the attention there that's often not easy when there's
discomfort it really is compelling and calling for us so I'm not saying that
all these will be fast and easy but they definitely are ways forward is that
helpful thank you somebody else have a question or
comment there was a hand that went up over here somewhere oh or oh sorry Elena
um I you know feel like when I am struggling with thoughts
and I try different things like You're suggest suggesting in meditation like
doing the body scan or doing a meta practice then I start then I start
judging myself that I'm jumping around to different strategies and then I think
that's like wrong or something do you know what I mean yeah yeah and how long do I do the meta practice should I just
do that the entire time or can I then do a self- compass you know self-compassion
may I you know be happy may I be and then I start well I'll think about her
so then I'm like start then I just do that and then I don't know then I judge that I'm having monkey mind as far as
like my strategies I don't know if that yeah yeah no this makes perfect sense you're highlighting we could just spend
the whole time doing like h two minutes of this practice two minutes of that practice two then jumping all around and
like this kind of stuff and then one more thing is that I've heard like you pick one thing to focus on like your
breath or your the no feeling the breath in the nose or the stomach or the you know abdomen I mean and then like I'll
switch and be like no I want to I'm feeling it here no now I'm feeling it there and then I again it feels like I'm
doing something wrong or something yeah this is such a a great comment thank you there's a few things I can say
about here so often if uh we start our meditation practice with the wanting to
settle the mind and calm the mind and it's really helpful to choose one thing and to stay on it just as you've heard
but if you find that you just can't do that I think it's really helpful to switch because there's concentration
practice is uh just stay stay stay no matter what but here I'm not talking about concentration practice I'm talking
more mindfulness practice where we're being with what's uh arising and if
what's arising is there's no I just can't settle the minds are all all over the all over the place then we just work
with what's arising a mind that's doing something rather and then do the a body scan as
best we can and I do agree it's probably best to if we switch I'm using
this word best loose ly maybe maybe here's what's the most
useful instead of saying rules we could set a North star is where
where does it feel easeful where does it feel
easeful and yeah maybe that's that's uh the
direction so if you feel like you're doing loving kindness practice but you're getting wrapped around the axle
trying to decide who to do it to and like all these kinds of things which happens right if there's this pressure
of of speech a pressure of thinking then there's chances are there's something
underneath some emotional thing that we don't want to see and that emotion is still there so it's going to pop up as
thoughts or with the busyness with the mindfulness or it's going to pop up as
body scan jumping all around or something like this so I didn't say this
I could give a whole another talk on thoughts but maybe it's you could drop in is there an emotion that's fueling
this so I just said a lot of things so one is maybe to choose a North star what
helps with ease if you find that you're just doing this and then doing this and then doing this maybe drop in the
question is there an emotion under here that's fueling this agitation that's showing up in in all these different
ways and thank you so much you're welcome you're
welcome okay so we're at uh 8:30 here so
thank you all for your kind attention and you're welcome to come up to here and talk to me if you'd like and I wish
you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you