Hello everyone and welcome and welcome back to IMC
and uh certainly nice to be here and it was very nice to be broadcasting from up
in the mountains yesterday. And um
so in this theme of these last weeks of insight, the first and the and in in the
tradition the most important insight is into usually we say impermanence in English
uh ana inconstancy and uh in this tradition
uh impermanence is closely assoc associated with the idea of emptiness
and one way is that things that are constantly changing
uh there is no center or ground that stays stable. There is nothing
which is there's no place to stand. There's no um essential
uh core or essence uh existentially
ontologically with anything. It would be a little bit like
uh maybe very much like someone who likes to uh kayak in a river, someone
likes to surf. The water is constantly changing and the ideas about the water might not
be changing. In fact, someone might be daydreaming about how wonderful it would be to float on a river thinking that
it's going to be exactly like there was uh it was before. And the idea of river
is stable. But uh when you're in the water ex experientially
everything is moving and shifting. There's no solid ground to stand on in
the ocean in the river. And so there's things are always shifting.
And so as we develop deep samadei, as we become very still
inside, very quiet in uh in the meditation where the world
of concepts, ideas with which we construct much of our
reality is no longer operating. And everything we feel is shifting and
changing and moving. At some point we also see
that mindfulness itself, awareness itself is
also part of the shifting and changing is also part of what comes and goes.
and and we find there's no place to stand in the river of time, in the river
of now. And as soon as we take a stand, then we're resisting the flow of the
river. And so there's art of this practice is to get quiet enough
and at some point turn the attention around 180 degrees to look back at uh
the source of awareness, the source of mindfulness. For some people we call it
maybe the source of consciousness to see that there is nothing there to
stand on it. It itself is shifting and changing, dissolving and reappearing.
And uh and this at some point as we get deeper and deeper, every time we look at something,
it's already shifting and changing, including the looking, including the agent who is doing the
practice. If we look for it, to feel it, to sense it, to experience it, there's
nothing solid there. It's all just shifting and moving and changing.
And to experience that while in samadei, while being really still and quiet and
peaceful, uh can feel really wonderful
because there's freedom there. There's freedom from holding on to anything,
freedom from taking a stand, freedom from resisting what's going on.
And so this idea of the insight into ana into constancy
at some point when we samadei is strong uh it becomes 360 degrees
everything is included nothing outside and um
of that change changing or constantly shifting for some people that's disorienting
but if we turn around the attention to look at the place of disorientation.
There's nothing there that also is empty. Everything is empty
because everything is a part of a process of change.
So to assume a meditation posture where we begin
by finding stability
We begin by finding our ground to to sit on, to lay on, to stand on.
So it's clear we're here.
And then gently closing your eyes.
and feeling your way into your body to where there's stillness in your body.
At first, it might be very tentative feeling of stillness.
And as you exhale to let everything around the stillness
relax
as you exhale. Feeling if there's any solidity or contraction
or pressure associated with thinking
that thinking mind, thinking muscle.
As you exhale, soften
the thinking mind.
feeling the area of your heart center. And is there anything there that feels
solid or contracted or
like there's a a location there where things are a little bit more
centered.
As you exhale to relax around the heart center, soften
and dropping deeper into the area of the belly, the har
feeling what's there
and to allow Allow the belly to soften
the tension there to begin loosening
and becoming aware. here
in your belly, in your chest.
Becoming aware of the alternating rhythm
of breathing in and breathing out.
Inherent in breathing
is change and inconstancy.
Unless you hold your breath breathing.
Keep shifting and changing.
And in your breathing, can you find a place of stability or a
grounding spot from which the breathing begins?
Entering the experience of the body breathing.
Everything is empty.
If you turn around to look at anything which is solid,
anything that feels a gathering point for something that's
stable and constant.
If you look at it clearly, you'll see there's no center.
And if there is, breathe with it.
Let it soften and relax.
Let it dissolve.
Any sense of solidity, permanence,
anything that seems unchanging in your direct experience
is a construct of the mind.
Relax the mind deeply.
Let go of the doer, the knower.
letting the shifting changing waves of breathing in and breathing out.
Support you to let go into the emptiness of all things.
Where there's nowhere to stand and nowhere to fall.
Whatever is solid, wherever you're holding on,
look into the middle of it to See its emptiness
and there find your freedom.
To be aware like space
where awareness has room for whatever arises.
Being aware with silence
so that no sound or thought is blocked
but can flow freely in in the silence
to be aware with stillness.
So awareness isn't ruffled by anything.
Being aware of emptiness,
the emptiness of awareness itself.
Nowhere to stand, nowhere to fall.
Everything is shifting and changing and flowing
with no essence, no ground
that stays stable.
The only stability
is the floating in change.
And then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate the emptiness of awareness
where we can be aware Aware but not resist.
Aware but not assert.
Aware and not afraid.
Aware without wanting.
And to offer this way of being aware
to our friends, our family, our community.
So that all beings will feel that they belong to us in our
awareness. That we are everyone's friend.
that we have space and time for whoever we encounter.
As soon as we have not the space or the time, chances are we've solidified around
something. Holding on to something with past pressure in it.
Living in the vast emptiness of a shifting, changing world of
experience.
Let us have space to be aware of everyone
with kindness and care with time
and openness.
May in the emptiness of our
mind. May we wish
happiness on all. May we wish safety for all.
May we wish peace for everyone.
May we offer freedom from suffering to everyone.
May how we're aware of others be the avenue of a gift,
the gift of attention. Empty attention
that has space for everything. May all beings be happy.
[Music]
Thank you.
So hello and welcome and welcome to this continued series on insight
for insight meditation and I think now we're on the 17th talk on this topic
and uh continuing with the subthe of insight into impermanence, inconstancy,
change as this is one of the most important insights that this tradition offers. And
it the other three important insights that are really the transformational insights
um come out of insight into change. So the uh insight into inconstancy
insight into uh stress and suffering the and the
third one the insight into uh what's called not self. So we'll go through these three in the as I teach these uh 7
a.m. through the summer through next while. And right now I just want to keep
focusing on this um impermanence because it's so foundational.
And uh in this terraoden tradition um there are teachings on emptiness and the
primary way of understanding emptiness is that it's synonymous with the concept
of anicha impermanence change in constancy
that um and what anything that's constantly shifting and changing has no
inherent solidity no inherent thing thingness there that lasts over time
and um and so it's as I keep like liking to refer to it's like a river that's
flowing that um you can't find a solid
place in the water that's unshifting unchanging. It's always dynamic. It's always in flow moving and um and then
you know unless it becomes ice but the river is not you know ice the river is
the flow and the flow and so um in so we would say in
terabadin Buddhism that the river is emptiness of any inherent so solid place
that makes the river what it is. What makes up the river is the flowing
changing molecules of water. And um as we settle into meditation
and below the level where we're going to argue or have concepts or have ideas of
how things should be or how things are, but we are settling the the thinking mind, the analytical mind, the the
constructing mind gets quieter and quieter. So we're now living with
awareness in in the um in direct experience, the experience of the
moment. And this is why samadei is so important for insight practice because
samadei is what allows us to be centered in the direct momentto- moment
experience as opposed to being away from it because of this concepts, thoughts,
ideas we have. And some some way of thinking can have give the idea that
something is permanent. And there's two reasons for that. One is that uh ideas
are unchanging. You know, like the idea of a door, the door that's there, the door doesn't change.
And so the door is unchanging. Um but the experience of the door is
changing all the time. I'm looking at it. I'm not looking at it. I close my eyes and I don't see the door. The idea
that it's still there, that's just an idea. in direct experience if I'm looking at
the door that um uh the awareness of it
is shifting and changing and um and so in the direct experience
the door doesn't change but the way I'm constantly being perceived the perception is shifting and changing and
moving all the time and if we now turn that kind of attention not to a door but to anything
that we feel inside is who we essence of who we are. This is my amness. This is I
am this uh I am whatever you fill in the blank. Um if that is something that
feels permanent, feels unchanging like we have been a you know then if we
really turn that uh movement of direct experience
experiencing directly what's actually there apart from the thoughts and ideas.
We see that there's nothing there but these but thoughts and ideas. any sense
of solidity that's there or permanence that's there begins to dissolve
begins you know and if it's like a like pieces of ice in the river that then
melt and fall away and to become become part of the flow and changing nature of
the river and it's profoundly satisfying
to be able to sit in meditation get quiet enough to perceive that everything
is nothing is solid solid. Everything now has become spacious, open.
Everything has become easeful, still, quiet. Um, and in that spacious quiet,
um, there's experiences for sure. There's perceptions for sure, but those
are constantly kind of flowing and moving. Sometimes they can be experiences happening quickly. Sometimes
in a very quiet, peaceful manner. things are just come coming into awareness and
receding and come arising and passing appearing and disappearing
and um and because the mind is gathered in the moment. It's not distracted. It's
not spinning out. It's not pulling back and judging and reacting and having preferences. It just right there in it.
there's something that gets very peaceful and very happy to just be there
in that flow and that in that uh and that the the changing nature of
phenomena as I said yesterday it becomes kind of the the the
organizing center for this gathering of the mind into
harmonious centered kind of uh um attention.
And uh and it's an attention where now we see in the direct experience
everything is empty. Everything nothing has any inherent
um self inherent essence that's just unchanging unmoving.
And the reason why this is so powerful is that the movement of clinging to
something only gives the only seems to work if it's there long enough to hold on to.
But if uh so if I you know have a striker I can grab it because it's there
long enough to grab. But if the if the SP if the striker is just comp you know
constantly disappearing then as I grab it there's nothing to hold on to. There's something
in very deep meditation where uh we see that what we're what we
cl what the mind wants to cling to is only concepts and ideas,
wishes, uh projections and that in the deep
sense of everything is empty, everything is changing. By the time the mind goes to grab onto something, it's no longer
there. And um and but before that it's
the very sense of grabbing the where we think we're grabbing something
but it's the grabbing gives a sense of solidity the because it gets tight. It
gets like an fisted or a knot or something. And then it seems like yes something is solid there. But if we open
the fist like this what happens to the fist? The fist is not there.
And um it just now there's just openness.
So the um um the opportunity for deeper
meditation just like in deeper jam practice and deep samadeium we talked about earlier this year. we enter into
kind of a we enter into and abide in a very different kind of world than the
world we ordinarily live in going around taking care of things. And so there's a
there needs to be a willingness to um to drop the ordinary perspect perceptions,
the ordinary way of thinking in order to really become quiet and still enough to
be able to uh sense, feel into the empty
nature of direct experience and find the freedom in there. Find find
the delight in there. Find the the uh deep sense of being at home
that can't be there if we're holding on to something like this. Like this is how
we want to be open-handed, open, relaxed, at peace.
So um so the um so the important point I'm
trying to make here is that as insight meditation develops what we're entering
into and abiding in is direct experience direct perception of experience where
the experience and the perception itself is seen as a a flowing river. the river
of now that every experience is shifting and changing. And if we look deeply at that and find
any place that's not flowing, any place that's gotten solid and holding on, gotten frozen, if we look at that kindly
and gently, it too will dissolve into that flow of change. And everything
becomes change. Everything is shifting and changing. And there we find
the the fist of attachment, the holding on that we have begins to loosen up,
begins to relax. And the function of this deep experience of inconstancy as
an insight, the deep revelation of seeing things constantly change is not
to live with this kind of insight all the time.
The purpose of it is to how it helps to melt the attachments we have. How it how
it helps us to soften and let go. And so we get a very deep personal experience
of what it's like to not be attached. And in this insight tradition that I'm
teaching from here um they say that when uh that uh in the in in settling into
opening into this deep experience of constant change in meditation and feeling the freedom of it um this gives
a person a pretaste uh of what liberation will be like the
ultimate liberation. It's a it's a kind of getting a kind of a sense or a smell
of what what's possible in terms of a dramatic shift of letting go that the
that is the purpose of this insight practice.
So I hope that this um um
uh makes sense for you and um and then probably tomorrow we'll do one more day
on this impermanence um insight uh and then um and then start
moving into the uh so maybe the little more challenging ones that are very
important also for this insight tradition. So, um thank you very much and um look
forward to tomorrow.