okay folks so uh so welcome nice to
um see your names places
um yeah let's uh let's practice together
just um remember I remembered um yoga teacher saying something
like how you get into the posture is uh as important
as where you get to or something and
uh that can refer to literally the posture of your body but also how you
take a kind of inner Dharma posture posture of the heart and just
um get into that posture
carefully you sense all the different parameters of your being
being maybe subtly shifting as we come into
Stillness
not in a rush to put your heart
into some particular
posture your attention into some particular shape
just finding your
place
e e
and just sensing if there's uh anything that uh [Music]
needs the blessing of uh awareness
patience in order for you to be
here to be
available for your
breathing e
and just checking what image you have of your own body the way that
image gets refreshed often
to the extent that there's uh self-consciousness that um associated
with any part of your body
just relax
to the extent that there's anything Your Body Sensations that um
hurt
soften
e
for e
feels uh irresponsible to stop
clinging even for a few moments
but uh whatever alarm Bells go off that make
that feel unsafe just breathe into that
and breathe knowing the beginning and ending
of your inhale beginning and ending of your
exhale
e
e e
our mind is always uh foraging in some sort
of seeking some small small scrap of
peas but the uh the budha said uh peace
is only found through relinquishment this is what we really want
something that actually satiates
us food for the heart Sant CH
said
e
e e
there's some kind of uh pain or heartache mind can very quickly just
bless that with
compassion
equinity restlessness and agitation just find what's
stable breathe into it just touched with uh some measure of
Tranquility there's aversion a will
just a quick surgical strike
meta just
quietly helping
phenomena melt into uh
non-existence
e
e e
[Music]
for for
okay so um question from
uh the uh chat line whatever that thing is um so uh person wrote um can you give
some guidance on etiquette for approaching meditation teachers like is
there anything that really annoys you about people who sit with you and engage
with your Reflections way people approach you or not it's Etc conversely is there
anything that makes you really happy about the way people approach and engage with
you um I like this anonymous question portal
you people just say things and um that's
good so the first um the first thing that I thought of
when I saw that was Michael Scott from the office
and um kind of if you're unfamiliar sort of
very loving depiction of delusion and
self-absorption but loving for sure and um I there's some clip I don't
know what it's in the context of or whatever but it's Michael Scott at his
desk you know do I and says do I need to be likeed absolutely not I like to be
liked I enjoy being liked I have to be liked but it's not like this compulsive
need to be liked like my need to be praised so you got to find the clip
that's very good and um that's just the first thing I thought
of that's not what I model my life around but I suppose the question is like what
do What do teachers want from students and
uh I'm not totally sure but but what actually came to mind was almost
nothing but not nothing so teaching is um is merely a
kind of aspect of practice one takes care with
it and anyone who thinks they're a
teacher it's not a teacher and teaching is it's partially
just a kind of practice of of service you know and the currency is compassion
sympathetic Joy uh
once um Ain suito was talking about the the Buddha the the Buddha's decision to
teach for 45 years instead of didn't need to do that didn't need to pad the
ego make money but just moved by
care and uh remember uh John being quite you know
getting emotional just reflecting on that uh shinzen Yang said uh this about
teaching said when you've had an exceptional meal you leave a nice
tip teaching is um is a devotional practice you know it's kind of an
expression of the uh of love for the for the lineage for the
dhma and giving a talk giving a Dharma talk is like writing a love letter to
many people at the same time and you just kind of hope someone reads
it mostly um I feel like it's a teacher's job to be highly flexible
meet however the student manifests meet however the student expresses themselves
in other words no code of adquate really come as you
are and the flexibility is about
giving the student a kind of unpressured space to see their
mind and so much gets um stirred in relationships with teachers
and teacher plays many roles and represents
many things and psychotherapeutic models of
transference are not always on point but often somewhat relevant um you know a
relationship forms even if one has very little or no contact with somebody with
a teacher something happens and so um and if one does have
more contact UM then that's that's evocative
terrain and there's our own you know I know from my own history with teachers
almost none of whom I had much direct contact you know so when I say my
teachers I was not like you know nurtured all along the way with a lot of
individual attention or something like that it was not like that it was just practicing with people
um and so there's our own historical material the ways that
teachers function as a screen onto which our um deep conditioning early
relationships are dramatized the shadow cast by those
Dynamics and in you know in the classical Freudian sense like um Freud
said something like there is there is no love that does not reap produce infantile
stereotypes you know and um teachers can
disappear behind the veil of projection they become just an object in the world
of the student and sometimes a
compliment is more about the person offering it than the person to whom it's
directed The the emptier a teacher gets the easier it is to see the
movement of one's own mind you there there's been times when I'm you know sitting
Retreat and um and the teacher is just
like I don't know all I perceive are the movements of my mind whatever is evoked
in the field you know but um it's not merely about the
student it's a relationship this is more modern kind of um understanding
of therapeutic relationships in this context in in the course of therapy but
may be relevant for Dharma relationships too so this is um Drew Western and Glen
Glen gabard um they write uh transference is not simply a def defense
or displacement of libidinal energy onto the therapist as Freud
proposed it is not simply the activation of an old representation lying in weight
indeed transference is not really about transfer at all it is about the continual
construction and reconstruction of thoughts feelings wishes fears patterns of relating and
ways of regulating affect in the context of a new relationship
experiences that can only be understood in the context of old
ones now those Dynamics because it's um those
Dynamics can be a kind of vehicle for healing we can
perceive our minds our needs longing in with more and more
clarity in the context of a of a relationship and in that process
sometimes idealization um is is a maybe a phase
but it's not the last word and spiritual maturity is the
accurate perception of self and other the Toleration of
ambivalence the integration of the you know the the the coexistence of strength
and flaw in self and other student and
teacher it is um the teacher's job I feel to offer
something without strings ATT Ted in the sense that
um the teaching Dharma teaching is an offering that does not establish
debt does not establish
debt I I don't wish to burden you with uh implicit demands of how um to be
viewed or treated that's just kind of static for your mind to contend
with and I want to do whatever I can
that's create kind of open space for your
mind um so what I believe teachers want from
students probably you know the simplest way to
put it is uh
sincerity and that's a word I I first think I heard that when I was sitting
Retreats with um with Rodney Smith and um Rodney said that that
sincerity is the manifestation of the heart when it is freed from the
authority of self sincerity is the manifestation of the heart when it's freed from the
authority of self uh teachers do
not uh uh want to relate ego to
Ego and sincerity is
the I don't know it's a certain kind of fluidity and a willingness to
examine um what um what Agnes callard calls like
loadbearing questions the answers to which support
one's life to be willing to examine loadbearing
questions that's sincerity certain kind of willingness
not to know that I associate with sincerity it's really it's stepping out
of the bureaucracy of ego TR
said and when I'm in uh kind of amidst sincerity in a in a
sa the sense of self Fades very
dramatically and I can be as silent teaching as um as in my own
practice um but when there isn't there and that's why I'm careful what context
in which I I teach um when that isn't there when there isn't
sincerity some modum of sincerity myelf congeals in a ferocious
way and I feel kind of ashamed of what I care
about you know you only talk about love with
certain people
and there's a distinction that's become important uh to
me um that I I sometimes say like the need
need to be loved is distinct from the wish to be
understood and the need to be loved is a wasp
n no no praise is sufficient for the ego
it tolerates no goodness outside itself insatiable live by the ego die by the
ego and that's no way to live that has faded
dramatically but the wish to be understood is the
sense of like hearts meeting in the Dharma and my sensitivity to that over
the I don't know 15 plus years of teaching um that's
only grown and I'm most um touched when
people are tracking my heart closely listening very
carefully and relate to me not in my role as
teacher but we we meet in the open space of of the
dhma and I'm touched when my goodness is not
elevated as some special possession but reminds you of your own
goodness a teacher doesn't want to be
loved but to uh
dwell in what we both
love offer this for your consideration
and um yeah see you uh be back next week
actually doing Gil's uh I'm the sub for Gil next week so if you want to join the
7 amm Pacific I'll be there
and yeah I wish you all um a good week