good
evening so I'm going to start the talk tonight with a
poem it's by Rosemary Traummer of course those of you who come here often know
that I'm often reading her poems she's a beautiful poet and a practitioner Buddhist practitioner or
meditation practitioner so this poem is called When the Stakes
Are Low when the Stakes Are Low by Rosemary
Tramer for the fourth time in four weeks I slip my spade into the dark soil of
the half circle garden i make 20 shallow
holes then lift the pansies from crinkly from crinkly plastic containers and drop
the rootbound squares into the earth within hours the small brown bunny
arrives with his pink twitchy nose and his small round lump of soft bunny
body and while I wash dishes I meet through the window his innocent unbleing
gaze as he consumes a dozen deep purple
petals in small efficient tugs he looks at me as as if to say "You
love me and I do." a crune at the bunny how
cute his small ears how perfect his bliss how good he is for eating his
pretty bunny food tomorrow the rest of the blooms
will be gone in a week the le the leaves will be gone too every single
one and I will go buy more pansies
how sweet it's become this path of surrender the strange joy that rises in
me when I see my precious pansies nibbled to the
roots now that the stakes are low it's much easier to bow to the way things are
for the price of pansies I can practice again and again how to find true delight
in this art of letting go true delight in this art of letting
go and we could say so much about Buddhist practice is about learning
this and that's a little bit what I'd like to talk about tonight because there's this way that uh
letting go is just part of helps a way in which
helps us navigate the constant change of life maybe we don't even think about it
but there's this way with this letting go helps us to reduce stress in some
kind of way if we are insisting that things be the same every single time then that's a recipe for
stress things change people change the weather changes this durations of
daylight change right all this we know this we know this and yet there's sometimes there's this way in which we
like have an idea of how things should be and we're holding on to that idea and
the holding on of that idea causes stress and discomfort dooka we might
say for example you might have this idea that you would um spend some time with
your friend and uh one afternoon but at the last minute your friend cancels like oh shoot we were going to
go for a hike and there could be this little disappointment and anger and
frustration and with this uh friend but you could just let go of like oh okay
great now I have some time to do
nothing go for a hike by myself sit and uh watch the clouds go by
do something else this letting go of things have to go the certain way that we're planning or maybe
this shows up in meditation maybe uh during a meditation period we sit to
meditate we're hoping for peacefulness but then we find that the mind is all over the place and can't
settle at all and then instead of fighting it
instead of think like oh when is this going to settle down and seems like other people are can meditate why can't
I meditate i've been doing this for so long and I still can't do it or you know all these stories that we come up for
ourselves but if you let go of the wish for stillness letting go of that wish
this this uh implicit in this wish is things are not okay now and I want them
to be different if we let go of that that
invites calm even though there might be some of this agitation in the mind there can still be this
calm so as as I said briefly this idea of letting go as part of the
foundational teachings of the Buddhist teachings one way we can understand this
is if we use the four noble truths as a framework for Buddhist teachings there's
different frameworks we can use and this is just one of them the four noble truths some of you might be familiar
with this the first is the truth of dooka and duka is this really
interesting word that uh in English it stands for I should say in Pauline it
stands for this wide wide wide range to just this minor irritation annoyance to
horrifying absolute worst thing so this big wide range often gets translated as
suffering it could be translated as stress get translated a number of different ways but the first normal
truth the truth of dooka things oh Lee Brazeni translates
uh dooka as bummer things can be a
bummer i kind of like that it has a certain playfulness to it and then the second noble truth is that
there's a cause of bummerness there's a cause of duka and
often we can understand that as clinging or grasping or craving this kind of like
really wanting and holding on to the third is there's also the ending of this
dooka and then the fourth is and there's a path that leads to the end of
duca and so I'm going to highlight the second noble truth that there is this
there's a cause for duka for suffering for stress for things being a
bummer and that cause is craving or clinging or grasping this kind of like
really holding on to and then there's a lot of teachings of like well how to abandon how to let
go of the clinging or the grasping and that leads to the end of
suffering so this idea of letting go is like just inherent in one of these core teachings of the Buddhist path but not
only that it's also the fourth noble truth this path that leads to the ending of suffering some of you might know this
the path is known as the eight-fold path [Music]
and step number six is about effort you know what we apply our energy
towards and those uh we play our energy towards this gets so complicated four
things but one is the abandoning of unhelpful
states this is what we put our energy towards is abandon those things that aren't helpful helpful for the ending of
suffering so in some of these core foundational teachings is this whole idea of letting go uh abandoning
renouncing um can't right now at the moment speak
of any other English words i just I looked it up uh earlier today and in
Paulie there's like half a dozen words that have this meaning just because this is such like an integral part of the
teachings but there's this way in which we might feel uncomfortable this
idea of letting go because after all like society and media and all the advertising industry all this kind of
stuff is about more more you need more get more buy more be more it's all about
more there's so much we uh there's this uh real movement towards like uh
instituting a sense of lack or insufficiency or inadequacy into people
or into anything really just so that there's this real sense of it's not
enough you got to have more whatever it is more stillness when you meditate more
friends more friends that show up on time when you want to go hiking or I mean just more cars more houses more
stuff and so this idea of like well what letting go this opposite of movement of
acquiring in some ways feels maybe a little bit radical maybe it's a little
bit uh revolutionary in terms of it's so different than the message that we get
so often but there's also this way in which
letting go can might feel like this sense of renunciation and we might feel like well
I I don't really want to be a monastic i don't really want to move into a cave sell all my beans and shave my head sell
all my belongings shave my head and move into a cave or something like that or
maybe there's this way that letting go feels like surrender in some kind of
way so just the way that we've been socialized this whole idea of letting go
it sometimes can feel not so attractive especially when we have this feeling of
there's not enough not enough love not enough care not enough attention not
enough security and safety this idea of letting go can feel pretty threatening
so there's this way this sense of deprivation or of lack of safety might
be associated with our ideas about letting go but I'm going to point to kind of
like what happens when we actually do it but before I get there I want to say the Buddha never talked about that you have
to get rid of your belongings or you know give away everything and that you can't have wealth or personal
possessions we come through a tradition that was uh preserved by monastics so
came through kind of like the monastics um teachings we're not monastics and so
there were teachings that were for lay people and there was it was about how to use your money wisely to support having
more freedom for you and your family most the majority of the teachings are for monastics and they have that little
bit of this flavor of a renunciation but instead this Buddha he
said that uh is we don't have to get rid of our wealth or our possessions but to
let go of what's not useful what's not helpful what's not skillful and so much
about this practice is about our discovering for ourselves what is useful
what is helpful helpful for having more peace more freedom more ease for having a
sense of sufficiency adequacy so this pointing to letting go
of that which isn't helpful and there's this uh way in which he has
there's a quote from the dhamapata it's uh letting go is not this
denial or aestheticism instead it's related to this
happiness as uh rosemary trauma in this last line of this poem the delight in the art of letting
go this quote in the dharmapata is if by giving up a lesser
happiness one could experience greater happiness a wise person would renounce
the lesser to behold the greater so part of this practice is for
us to understand what are these lesser happinesses and we might say that some of these are just some of pleasures that
are fleeting and might even be causing harm to us ourselves those are lesser
happinesses some of these greater happinesses is this uh sense of well-being a sense of ease sense of
peace and freedom so there's this way this letting
go is really pointing to it should bring some delight it should bring some joy it
should bring some happiness so and along these lines this idea of
letting go or abandoning or renouncing what if instead of we
translated as this way of giving giving up like up
above and there's this way like giving up above can be almost like a way of
maybe like there's an altar or that we're um giving something for a higher
purpose or something like this this maybe like making an offering or an act
of generosity perhaps maybe maybe like those pansies
for the little bunny right you know this act of generosity in that poem
so this maybe this letting go is more of a movement of the heart and it's maybe
has this uh flavor of um something that's beautiful and that is uh is
associated with uh more spaciousness and
ease because letting go is not so much about what you lose it's not so much
about what you're letting go of as it's about what you gain and the Buddha
talked about this so there's the obvious obvious things there's this letting go that has a sense of
relief some time ago i uh put on a blouse that I used to wear to work back
when I had a job in corporate America and I thought I would wear it for a particular occasion and I put it on and
I was like "Oh my gosh this boss is so itchy and scratchy how did I never
notice this before i just took it off and put on
something else i didn't have to debate should I let go of this should I not do
this?" or something like this it was just like "Oh this is uncomfortable i'm going to take it
off." That's what's getting pointed to here that's what's getting pointed to and part of the practice is for us to
learn what is uncomfortable part of how we learn that is by learning what's comfortable like
experiencing more and more states of ease and some well-being and some of that happens with meditation practice as
the mind and the body settle there often not always there often can be this
greater sense of well-being and ease that then highlights all the other
places where there's this tightness and this gripping and striving and straining
in a way that's not so helpful
so one of the things that we gain when we're letting go in in a way that is
helpful is some of I would say joy or happiness and that Buddha pointed to
this in some teachings i'll just mention this briefly this idea of this gladness
pentad so letting go leads to gladness which leads to joy and
tranquility happiness and concentration and then seeing things clearly so this
is a cascade that gets pointed to over and over again in the Buddhist teachings
so this idea that gladness and joy tranquility or happiness are integral
parts of the practice i would say they're required actually because we
need to have some lightness of being to do letting go as well as to help us see
clearly see clearly about ourselves the ways that uh the things that we're doing that are leading to dooka and the things
that we're doing that helps us to have uh less dooka so the Buddha pointed to this
gladness pentan as letting go points to that but there's also this way in which
this letting go is sometimes is letting go of those things that are obstructing
or obscuring or getting in the way of what's in our hearts what's already
there is just getting obscured this can be the seven factors
of awakening i won't go through this whole list but uh I'll say that happiness and
concentration are part of this uh these seven factors of awakening maybe I should go through the
whole list let's see if I have it in my mind mindfulness investigation energy
joy concentration equinimity is that seven six
is happiness joy serenity concentration
there's seven factors of awakening i said six of them we'll find I gave a a
number of years ago I gave a talk in each one of the seven so and then I did something about the seven together a few
times and you would think I would have learned it but uh right now I don't have it in my head so these things that are
in our hearts get exposed when we're letting go of those things that aren't helpful including the seven factors of
awakening and these are factors these are elements these are qualities that really support
awakening greater freedom and peace and ease there's also the Brahma vaharas
these are like four qualities of the heart loving kindness compassion
sympathetic joy and equinimity these are these heart qualities of love we could
call it the four faces of love this is all inside of all of us sometimes we
just have things that are getting in the way and so this practice of letting go is
part of just letting go of these things that are either keeping uh what's obstructing it there in place or uh
actually letting go of the last little bit there to release the these heart
qualities so what are some of the things that we
can let go of to make this a little bit more
tangible grasping to objects it's not objects themselves that we have to get
rid of to have more ease and peace it's the grasping it's the belief that they
are going to be lasting sources of happiness and therefore we have to hold on to them to make sure that we have
happiness objects are not lasting sources of
happiness i like some objects we have to maintain
we have to uh there are batteries we have to uh take care of or and we have to clean
them or they die and we have to replace them or what if they're perfectly fine
for our whole life but then when we die I mean they're just go to the next
person or to wherever they're going to go they're not something that's going to
bring us these lasting source of happiness that we really want they do bring pleasure but there's a lot of data
that shows that when you're purchasing something like for example on something like Amazon when they measure kind of
like the delight in individuals brains measured with uh different neurotransmitters the biggest hit of
delight is when you put the item in the shopping cart not when you buy it not when it
arrives it's when you put it in the shopping cart and it can just stay there
so I this is a practice I do sometimes i just put things in the shopping
cart without buying them i don't need to buy them
so everything changes but you know things aren't like what maybe at what
time was it seemed like a lasting would provide lasting sources of happiness
maybe this object isn't changing so much but we're changing this little stuffed
animal that we had when we were a kid right maybe that seemed like it was going to be lasting source of happiness
and maybe we had a blanket or something that we took around with us everywhere we had favorite toys or something like
this and you know as an adult it's clearly we have a different relationship
with it so this is one thing things to let go of it's the grasping to objects we can
have objects as part of our life but it's this holding on to them and insisting
that they stay the same and in insisting again and again that they make us happy that's a recipe for
disappointment of course it is and the advertising agencies are betting on this
that you'll just be satisfied with something just for a short while and then want something else
something else to let go of or this clinging to our views so long and so often we have this
idea this is true and everything else is wrong i I know it's right and those
people over there they don't know anything they're wrong of course we need views
we need to be oriented in the world and we need to be inspired and have a
direction in which we want to go it's this clinging to them thinking that okay what I have is
what I understanding is the right one and I don't know what those other people are doing but they're clearly wrong
was um very interesting this morning i was
uh teaching a a class and uh we as part
of the reading they they had read something and uh we were going to discuss it and
people they started uh having comments about what the reading was and then I just dropped
in who the author was and the context in which it was written the what they were
reading was written All of a sudden everything
changed it was quite striking to see how oh just a reinterpretation of everything
and understanding everything differently i said maybe three
sentences and everything changed for them and they understood everything
differently this is a good reminder for us we think that I mean we have certain
amount of information and we have views based on that but how can we be sure
that there won't be some other new information that will change our ideas
our views so instead can we hold this well my current understanding this is
what I believe this is what makes sense to me now this this is uh from what I've seen
so far this is uh my view on this instead of saying this is right and
everything else is wrong having this provisional understanding
wow this your life will just unfold so much easier if you can instead of this
idea of we're right and they are wrong i'm right you're wrong because then we
have to defend what this right is and we have to defend like oh no no no they if
we see that those people over there if they happen to do something that's helpful or good but then we have to
discard that because it doesn't fit our idea of them being bad and us being good and all kinds of mental gymnastics we
have to do to maintain this so instead it's like yeah this is my provisional understanding this is
what makes sense to me right now and it just leaves the door open that some more information might change
our ideas change our views to things to let go of clinging to
views clinging to objects clinging to views including to views about
ourselves i'm the person who doesn't do this I only do that or something like
this it's amazing the views we have about ourselves and so often they're not
uh complimentary in the sense of like no I can't do that
i can't drive on that windy road or I can't um I don't know there so many
things we have this about
ourselves things to let go of clinging to objects clinging to views let go of trying to control
others if only those other people would get things right do things the way that they I think they
should there's this way in which be kind of like uh implicitly or trying to like
possess them in such a way that they can will do whatever we want them to do whether these are complete strangers we
don't even know if they're just hypothetical people that them over there or maybe they're
even partners family members children aging parents these types of
things it doesn't work and it's
annoying has you have you ever had somebody try to control you right it just doesn't work so there's this way in
which we often set up this battle with like well if only this person would do
this you know because we care for them we love them we want them to do something we know it'd make them feel
better but for whatever reason this person doesn't want to do it can we be okay with that
can we be okay with uh recognizing the autonomy of other people doesn't mean
that we don't ever make suggestions or support them or things like that but we stop trying to control them we let go of
trying to control people and instead we find this way in which we can
just love them just love them the way they are
so in this way if we are letting go of this clinging and grasping and
controlling which doesn't work in the way that we hope it will or won't doesn't provide the peace and ease that
we're imagining it will there's a way that it can lives
provide some spaciousness in our hearts and minds there's this way if we're always
chasing trying to fulfill all our desires or all the things that we think that we
need if we kind of soften that then there just seems to be more space in the
heart and mind and time in the day if we're not always chasing
things with we're letting go there's also provides some clarity with regards to okay well what are desires versus
needs sometimes when we go on uh meditation retreats there's like really simple and
the accommodations are really simple and they might be comfortable but really
simple or when you travel maybe you just bring a subset of your belongings and there's this way this recognition of the
simplicity really highlights oh yeah I don't actually need so much of this stuff that I own i'm doing fine with
just this small bit that I brought with me so we start to have maybe with this letting go of stuff we start to have
more and more clarity about okay what is it that we really
need there's also this confidence that grows with this letting go because as
I've been pointing to there's this sense of
um often the sense of lack or inadequacy or insufficiency is driving this uh
desire for more but if we're letting go of some of the clinging and grasping
which is tied up with desire for more then there starts to be more of a
feeling of okayess there starts to be a feeling of
this is sufficient this is adequate somehow we have this idea i
know I certainly did feel like okay well I I'll feel better as soon as I have
this and then you know I managed to get this oh okay well that didn't work okay
now I need to have this work hard do something other and then I get this oh yeah okay well that
didn't work okay now I need to get this right this is well established this hedonic treadmill is a way to understand
it we just could spend our whole life chasing after the next thing trying to
get more more and more
so what are some of these ways to support this letting go this letting
go one cultivate a feeling of
abundance cultivate a feeling of abundance you say "Well that's nice Diana but how do we do that how do you
cultivate a feeling of abundance?" Be generous in whatever way feels would be
generous for you your time your expertise resources be generous in some
kind of way this is a definitely a way to feel like a sense of abundance
if you find yourself that uh you're for example on Amazon shopping
for this thing or that thing or something like this just when you uh remember ask yourself do I really need
this do I really need this and maybe you put something in the
shopping cart and say well I'll come back and buy it maybe another time then
chances are when you come which happens for me when I come back if I say oh I don't need that but just ask yourself do I really
need this or when sometimes you have this
feeling of like it's not enough I need more whatever this more might be more
stuff or more attention more love
everybody has this feeling they could have some more love but when you have this maybe idea
about there's not enough you can ask yourself when has it ever been
enough when will it be and I'll say for me I was asking this
question that that's the biggest change in my life i had a perfectly respectable
job and I felt like my life just wasn't going the direction i don't know i just
had I had enough stuff i just didn't feel like my life was going I I don't
know i just felt like it's not right but I felt like oh I need more money i need more status i need more
security and it wasn't until I realized when will it ever be enough i
will always feel like I need more i will always feel like I need more so I'm
going to stop working anyway in this particular setting in
this particular corporate America setting that turned out to be a huge change in my life that's not appropriate
for everybody my life situation allowed me to do that at that time but it was my
asking this question when will it be enough when has it ever been enough what will it take for me to finally feel like
I have enough and was what I doing was I doing
was what I was doing going to get me this feeling
so one more thing about this what can help support this letting go this
movement of releasing and releasing clinging and grasping is to practice letting go for
short moments many times letting go of this clinging for
short moments example of things in the shopping cart but not buying them okay I
just put them there or maybe the example of planting flowers and letting a bunny
rabbit come and eat them watch the the little bunny rabbit eat them and then just
notice the mind state and just the feeling of this little small little moment of letting go whatever it might
be not the third cookie or not uh watching one more YouTube video or
clicking on or one more hour on video games whatever it might be whatever it might be for all of us it's something
different but when you kind of like let go of this just notice how that
feels and celebrate it appreciate it this is how it works it's not We
can't like browbeat ourselves into letting go we can't uh threaten ourselves with letting go it's all about
feeling the delight this little bit of uplift this joy this happiness this
happens when there's a letting go that in a way that's helpful not 100% of letting go is
helpful we don't want to let go of things that take care of our health or let go of our responsibilities for
others that kind of a thing but notice doing these small bits of letting go and
then noticing the uplift in the heart after that happens this is a tremendous support for letting go
but it does take time it takes time to stop like trusting
the like the promise or the allure of objects or unh wholesome activities
unhelpful activities they're seductive and it's not easy not easy to let
go of always wanting more but and it takes time
then maybe I'll just read this poem as a closure
here for the fourth time in four weeks I
slip my spade into the dark soil of the half circle garden
i make 20 shallow holes then lift the pansies from crinkly plastic containers
and drop the rootbound squares into the earth within hours the small brown bunny
arrives with his pink twitchy nose and his small round lump of soft bunny
body and while I wash dishes I meet through the window his innocent
unblinking gaze as he consumes a dozen deep purple
petals and small efficient tugs he looks at me as if to say "You
love me and I do." I crun at the bunny how cute his
small ears how perfect his bliss how good he is for eating his pretty bunny
food tomorrow the rest of the blooms will be gone in a week the leaves will
be gone too every single one and I will go buy more
pansies how sweet it's become this path of surrender
the strange joy that rises in me when I see my precious pansies nibbled to the
roots now that the stakes are low it's much easier to bow to the way things
are for the price of pansies I can practice again and again how to find
true delight in this art of letting go thank
you and with that I'll open it up to see if there are some questions or
comments yes I kind of liked that uh this poem had a bunny and it felt like this time of year there are
bunnies this morning I saw some baby ducklings made me so happy
so if we're in a relationship like it could be even just a boyfriend girlfriend but and it's causing us
emotional pain how do you know when the answer isn't letting go of it being a certain way but actually leaving that
relationship
how do you know when it's what was the first what was the first option so if you have like a relationship that is
causing you to suffer so you could say well I need to let go of it being a certain way that maybe I wouldn't suffer
so much versus maybe I need to leave this relationship yeah so this is part of the art of
practice and I would say it's part of the art of living is when there's suffering that leads to more suffering
and there's suffering that leads to less suffering and this is maybe the question you're asking yeah
and I think that uh maybe it's helpful to make a distinction between harm and
discomfort so if harm is being caused that's not the direction you want to go if there's
discomfort anger sadness you know confusion whatever it might be that's
but that then it feels like uh it's uh the discomfort can be um you can get to
the other side of it and move on versus harm and sometimes people if sometimes
discomfort feels like harm and so the part of is just really to feel into what
is the difference and I don't know if this is helpful or not
anybody else have a comment or question maybe back here
yeah thanks for the talk and for the poem um there was a part of the poem that I've been trying to uh
interpret uh which is like uh there's the part of now that the stakes are low
or stakes are lower so I interpreted it as like her realizing
um her recognizing this situation with the bunny and saying "Oh the the stakes are
low." um you know because I'm surrendering or
whatever she's actively making this situation low or another way is she's
also um recognizing this as one of the many situations in life where like the
stakes are low indeed um so I've been trying to like riff with that and think
about like is the idea that you want to pick out situations where you know the stakes for sure are low or just every
situation find a way to like make the stakes low by you know surrendering
regardless of how high you think the stakes are but I thought that was an interesting line so I'm sure there's
different ways to interpret it but yeah that's fantastic i love what you're bringing up i think we can do both we
can let go of the things where it's easy or we can let go of the idea our our ideas around things so that
let that for example the idea that something will be a lasting source of happiness and uh then that makes the if
we realize it's not going to be then the stakes become lower
this is an interesting line now that the stakes are low and it's also right the title of the poem when the stakes are
low i was interpreting it um as something that was happening in her
personal life that uh I was assuming that there was something when the stakes were high
that that's implied in the poem that we don't know what they are but I I like
your interpretation a little bit better yeah yeah we got to recognize the bunny
and there's other bigger things happening maybe yeah yeah or maybe it's because the the first
line is for the fourth time in four weeks so she realizes oh this is what's
going to happen but maybe earlier maybe the first time it happened the stakes were higher because she was upset and
actually expected to have pansies in her garden or something like this i don't
know
okay well thank you all for your kind attention and it's time to let go of the
time in which we're having a dharma talk and uh I wish you all wonderful rest of the evening and safe travels home thank
you