so hello everyone welcome to this meditation that's part of the
series on samadi and as an introduction I'd like
to say that samadi is a very
personal experience in a very personal way of
being in the world being with oneself and so no one including myself
can give you precise instructions precise metaphors
precise um uh that are you know tailor made for each individual for you but I'm
hoping in this series that I'm teaching enough that there'll be things that are
even just one thing that really supports you really helps you as an entryway into
this a mind which is undistracted a mind which becomes clear
and really enters into uh the meditation in a in a meaningful way for you in a
deep way and uh and one of the ways to
understand uh the instructions i g am giving is that they're all meant to be
ways for you to understand yourself better so even if some of the
instructions I give here doesn't work for you um that doesn't mean that you
should dismiss them or or ignore them but rather uh there are a means by which
you can understand yourself better to understand what doesn't work and by that
maybe have a better sense of what does work or or maybe there's ways of um what
doesn't work and teach you something about how your mind how your own mind works and so that you can have more
clarity and understanding so with that in
mind the um the emphasis I want to make
today is that in the unification the
inclusion uh inclusivity of Samar practice that uh can also involve what I
call uh organizing ourselves bringing together all the
desperate parts of us and kind of bringing them together almost like a puzzle pieces that fit together that are
working together or maybe maybe it's an unfortunate uh metaphor but uh rather
than puzzle pieces with maybe it's like building blocks Lego blocks that we put
together so they all fit together nicely as opposed to uh having a
centrifugal force in our thinking that spins us out into many preoccupations and concerns and we keep uh spinning we
keep scattering ourselves scattering our attention scattering our focus our
concerns because we have too much going on and too many things and too strong a pull into the fascinating worlds of
desire and aversion and fantasy and so it's not just simply that
these thoughts and activities pull us away from the present but they also pull apart the mind they
pull apart the body if we get tense and preoccupied there can be a tensing and a
lifting that um that kind of removes us from a settled unified
feeling sometimes that lifting goes all the way up into the head and we mostly live in our head where we're no longer
uh all the all the building blocks of who we are hasn't come together so that
they are settled on each other and the thinking mind also can be
um sometimes not even in the present moment can be ahead of ourselves behind ourselves in another place but
physically we can feel sometimes that the energy the thinking mind the tension
the activity agitation the um the um the
uh what's activated maybe in our head in our brain brain maybe is it the the the
you know in the front of the brain or maybe it's uh the brain is now more kind
of zeroed in on the eyes or um and that's got the mind has gotten small or
it's gotten maybe mostly we're preoccupied on the left side or the right side of the mind or um there's a
kind of way in which the mind starts feeling not complete not whole not settled on itself and there's a way of
organizing the mind bring at all the pieces together um and now so they were right
there similar to how you would organize your body if
um if uh I don't know there a lot of a lot of examples I could use but if
you're going to play pingpong uh and you're ready for someone to serve the ball to you um you would
kind of get your body ready organized and the whole body is coming together
to be there for that activity the orientation of the mind's attention is
now oriented and and U brought into the
tabletop the other person's hand the ball just right it's organ everything's kind of organizing itself in order to be
there for the game of ping pong and um and the same thing with the mind and
this is where most people don't have a very good sense of the physical physicality the physical sensations of
their mind and what is activated agitated energized in the mind and where
and what's included and it's not or the directionality of the different kind of centrifugal forces of thinking in the
mind and preoccupations and the mind too can come
together into a whole into a settled interconnected
peace and so that'll be the instructions today and it'll maybe work for some of
you and for those of you who don't uh maybe it'll maybe it helps you see and understand something about
yourself so to assume a meditation posture that is a posture of organizing
your body so that as much as your body as
possible is now going to be participating in the
meditation how your feet are
positioned so the feet themselves support attentiveness
presence being grounded maybe The Souls of the feet are touching some
surface maybe the positioning of the legs
and if you're sitting on a chair or a cushion the way that the cushion chair
receives the weight of your body can you move a little bits way back
and forth so that weight feels grounded
feels full feels
solid to support being
here and adjusting organizing your torso your
spine to be here participating ready for
anything in
meditation gently closing your
eyes and without just as you're
breathing feel your body on the
inhale feel where you're agitated
tense where you're activated maybe so there's
a prioritization of certain parts of your body at the expense of others
feeling that on the inhale and then on the
exhale to relax the
body settle the
body with the idea that as a body settles on
itself the body is coming
together being organized so that all the parts
are somehow cooperating or here in the same way
and is there any way that's your body your chest your heart any part of your
body is energized or engaged or
activated by some emotional
state and is it a state that's more likely
to take you away from kind of a wholeness of who you are to have you preoccupied with a
particular State emotional
state and just knowing
that feeling how that emotional state might be alive in some part of your
body feeling that as you inhale and on the
exhale relaxing the emotional state relaxing
the body associated with that
state and maybe the emotion doesn't go away but maybe it's allowed to settle
more deeply into some place where you feel more grounded with
it where the wider body is there to hold it or support
it so it doesn't need to be a
preoccupation it's okay
and then on the inhale feeling any Sensations associated
with the thinking
mind is there any tension or pressure
contraction any activation
agitation in any parts of your head anywhere else in the
body that seems connected to
thinking and is there a preoccupation with thinking with thoughts
that takes you away from yourself divides you from the rest the
whole a prioritization of the concerns you have
and as you exhale soften the thinking
mind let it
relax maybe with the image of a wide lake with
waves that the waves begin to settle and slow down and get
smaller until the lake becomes wide and flat and
still so the thinking mind quiets slows
down settles becomes Broad and
still maybe allowing all the water of the lake all the activity of the
lake to rest on the lake
Bottom where the weight of the
mind is allow to settle into the body
in that settling if there's any sense of the
mind having different parts different pieces where not everything is
included as you exhale let all the Mind
settle together into a settling place
where the mind the thinking mind can be received and
supported
reassured that kind of reorganizing of the Mind
so everything comes together and however close and whole
complete the Mind may feel Orient the
mind to rest Focus
include the experience of breathing
where every exhale brings allows all the parts of
ourselves to settle together into the experience of
breathing the Gathering Place the settling place
and is a way of organizing the mind to be more here
and unified let your thinking mind
be involved with the thought of the
count of counting the exhales one to
10 and if you lose count no problem begin again at
one counting not as a strain and not as something to worry
about to be successful at but each
count a settling a relaxing helping the mind come together
in an organized
way to settle into the Gathering Place of
breathing
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to allow for a full Fuller
settling on the
exhale and even if you're unsettled in some way to
feel the way that you are settled
now settled in your body in your heart
in your
mind maybe with every exhale a
soft wholeness in this settling all of
yourself letting go settling
in gathering together on the in the Gathering
Place maybe at the very end of the
exhale letting go here
and from this subtle place to gaze upon the world
kindly to gaze Upon This World
peacefully to take in and include the whole world
compassionately almost like you're inviting it all in to sit and be settled with
you almost as if you're making space and room
and accompanyment with the world
so there's a whatever comes into your
orbit also has a chance to settle be at
ease being settled and gazing upon the world
kindly may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may the way that we can be settled on ourselves
be a support for the welfare and happiness of others
certainly at least May the ways that we get agitated
reactive not spill out to
influence more of that in the world may all beings be happy
thank you
so hello on this welcome to this series of talks on
samadi and uh samadi is not an abstract
topic for intellectual interest only but it's a topic about ourselves
about how we can be present and engaged in really whatever we're
doing and it's with the general focus of the series is on medit
meditation and that's that connection to samadi is so strong that sometimes the
word samadi is a substitute for the word meditation and
um and but really the ability to be fully present oriented organized
absorbed in anything um makes anything a subject for
somebody and for those of you are going along with this series and wanting
to cultivate uh samadi uh in
meditation it's greatly supported by beginning to take what you're learning about yourself about how you can be
settled how you can be oriented organized
simple um settled still spacious the way that you can bring that
into different activi in your life so it's not just something you do in
meditation but something that you're beginning to um spread through your day
so that when you come to meditation you're already familiar with the territory you're all you haven't been
out of touch with it for a long time and it's it's it's more easy to uh be be be
connected to it and I learned this when I was in the monastery and I had very
busy full job in the kitchen being a cook for the large
Monastery and uh didn't have a lot of time for meditation but uh I started to practice
this uh in the monastery with the activities I I did and uh and uh I carried I had a
question that I carried with me that was my kind of my contemplative question for
the year I was in the kitchen there and that was the question uh how can I
participate more fully with what I'm doing in the kitchen and so whatever I
was doing if I was chopping vegetables if I was washing pots and pans if I was
uh putting together ingredients in pot if I was um walking around with a dirty
pot to bring it to the sink and there were other people working whatever I was doing how could I be in that
activity in a sense of really participating in it and why it was important for me was right away when I
came started work in the kitchen I didn't want to be there and my mind was elsewhere and I had other plans and
other aspirations and I was preoccupied with other issues with people I've been
talking to or doing and and I felt myself scattered I felt myself um uh you
know being kind of uh propelled out of the present moment propelled out of what I was doing um
and and I the what I used as my um as my
antidote to that as a way of learning about myself as a way of was how can I
participate with what I'm doing here so the consequence of that at some point
after some months of doing this uh if after the medit after working in the kitchen I would go to the meditation
session kind of almost you know directly I I would show up in the meditation already concentrated already there
present and it was relatively easy to uh enter into
samade and um and uh so this is a plug for you to participate to organize to be
start taking some of these lessons and you applying them into your daily life where you can where it makes
sense and one of these ideas in the theme of unification inclusion that's a
big part of it is the idea of uh that might work for some of you is to
organize your body mind and heart to be uh to be
participating in the settling in the Gathering at some central place within
so at the heart or Center of your breathing or as for me it's uh I I'm I I
was uh trained and spent decades now attending to my breath in my belly the
movements of the belly the sensations there the subtle feelings of pressure and release of pressure as I breathe the
softness keeping it soft for years uh for the early years of practice I held
my belly always tight and tense and I would relax it and soften and soften and
it took a while to really have that be settled um
uh and uh and so to um to to have this participating
there to organize yourself and um and I have this sense
some they not always available to me but there are sometimes where when I sit down to meditate I spent some time
feeling and sensing what the thinking mind is like is it tense is it tight is
it scattered and um and sometimes I can feel that I could kind of bring it
together and organize it kind of have put all the pieces together like the the
maybe the my mind has five major pieces blocks or something and I have this
sense that I can kind of like just like I could take a deep breath and and bring
my shoulders down and there's a organizing my body here in the Torso in
the the here or the weight against my my seat I can do the same thing with the
mind I can sense and feel my mind a little bit and then as I exhale I kind
of like imagine I'm putting the pieces back together and so the Mind becomes whole all the parts of the Mind are
there and to what degree this is only a something of my
imagination or to what degree it is something that feels you know more actual that's going on and I'm putting
the Mind back together um uh is not that important for me what's important is
that um the tensions I feel the different ways maybe it sometimes feels
like the blood is going in different places or the blood is going all into a central place not flowing into the whole
brain and so there's some kind of way in which I feel the brain feel the thinking
muscle and um and then kind of let it settle and come together gather together
let it kind of uh spread and and what happens often is the mind gets settled
and qu calm it tends to get feel larger more spacious it feels like it's
expanding partly because any idea of a uh outer limit like of the mind um is an
artifice of my of imagination and uh that we are unconscious of how we're doing it and um
and if we no longer boxing the mind in with a concept idea that it's just inside the skull or um there can feel
like there's no barrier no limit to the size of the mind and and uh when we
don't imagine a limit to this edges of thoughts the edges of the
Mind there can be a feeling of It kind of softening and relaxing so this
unifying and then relaxing um and with the risk of offering too many images uh it's it's um
the image that worked well for me also is out of a a surface of a lake that's
spreading and becoming wider and Stiller and quieter not pushing it but kind of
allowing it so this organizing of the mind having the mind
oriented and then in that orientation bringing together the other
pieces of the mind so it's everything is working together settling
orienting organizing things and one way uh that I
in the last meditation that I emphasized was get everything kind of coming back
coming together in the Gathering Place the GA gathering spot that's at the
center of all things not to exclude anything not to be laser focused but
kind of a soft round bold for attention where everything is
rolling down flowing down coming to where it comes together and everything
can settle there and be resting in the weight of that sides of that bowl resting in the in the lake Bottom the
bowl of the lake so um I hope that this some of what
I said today uh will be uh useful for some of you and and as
I said in the beginning of the meditation I don't expect that all that I'm teaching about suadi will be feel
right for all of you and that it's all a piece all kind of you know fit for who
you are somadi is a deeply personal phenomena it's very personal and unique
to each person how they discover understand their own mind body and heart
so that it becomes whole it becomes organized becomes fully
gather together so there's a feeling of being whole and here and absorbed in
what we're doing without being scattered in in distracting thoughts and
activities and feelings and um and uh so if anything
that I say doesn't work for you you're welcome not to use it but maybe it's even more important if it doesn't work
for you take some time to use it as a mirror to understand yourself better
what is it about your mind that maybe why it doesn't work and is there something else like it or different
thing that does work for you the more you become familiar with yourself and
what the elements of who you are are
then uh the easier it is to gather all those pieces and unify them into the
absorption that is samadi so um
thank you very very much and uh um we'll continue tomorrow thank you