good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all last week I had the great opportunity to go for a
hike down off a Skyline Boulevard maybe you guys know and it was just quite something it
was walking on the Ridge and like looking down into Sian Valley like oh
look there's that place and that place and then walking a little bit further and see like wow look at the fog
coming in off of the Pacific it was just beautiful it was just so
beautiful and this was a park you know that's freely offered just drive up park
your car put your shoes on off you go I just felt like my heart just uh
filling up with so much gratitude so much uh appreciation just for this
simple thing of spending time outside having these views and having the opportunity
the capability capacity I won't always have this I haven't always had this capability to walk right some
distances and just this recognition that the fullness of the heart
of the appreciation and maybe the nourishment in some kind
of way of the beauty just created the conditions in
which there could be something else like it stayed with me
for quite some time just this uh feeling of being filled up like you know not
needing anything more
so it's with that it's a little bit of a backdrop that um kind like chose what
I'm going to talk about tonight and also with this recognition
that you know I there's that I'm offering one little
piece of uh the Dharma one little angle in there could
be another time in which I'm approaching it from a different place with a different emphasis
and different uh pointings maybe I'll do that next week I
don't know we'll see but to start us off I'd like to uh
read a poem by Rosemary traumer of course right for those of you who've been here well
you know that I really appreciate her poems and I'm interpreting this poem
that she wrote after meditating out in nature and part of what she's talking
about here and the title of this poem is on a day when Stillness seems
possible again this is by Rosemary traumer on a day when Stillness seems
possible and the river is a long white stroke of roing and continuous surge
and the grass gone to seed waivers in the wind then
Stills waivers then Stills and the swallows
spiral the leaf Shadows spangle and the Ants sprayed a path
across the stones but I rhyme today with the
Cottonwood trunks my own body unmoving in the breeze
it feels good in this moment to be more tree than Cloud more silence than
song so easily the Stillness opens me softens
me how simple really to do
nothing how is it I so often resist there is no know in me now I do
not notice it Stillness has made a home in me and there seems to be nothing the Stillness
refuses comment seems to say there's room here for
everything it opens me wider the world rushes
in I love this idea I rhyme today with Cottonwood
trunks like what a playful way to think about you know I feel I'm more like a aligned with uh these trees that are bit
more stationary isn't that great to think about oneself as just like I'm rhyming
with something as opposed to I'm like this more kind of like you know there's a rhyme here there's a might rhyme with
a whole number of things but uh right now there's maybe kind of like an align ment
with and then this idea Stillness has made a home in me and there seems to be
nothing the Stillness refuses come it seems to say there's
room here for everything so this idea that there can
be some settling some Stillness some
quiet and this quiet is not from barricading oneself
separating oneself putting tucking oneself away you know from anything that
might be disturbing instead the Stillness is saying yeah the Stillness
is here it doesn't matter what's coming doesn't matter what's uh being experienced there can still be this
stability and steadiness that allows the world that is
with the world not pushing it away not demanding that it be different she says there's not a
no inside but instead just allowing some
settledness so there's this way maybe you've uh encountered this that with
meditation there can be this these moments of some of this Stillness and I
might call this some contentment some sense of that we don't
have to change anything right now we don't have to like Express anything
right now we don't have to run away from anything right
now we don't even have to assign some special meaning to the experience we can
just be with what's being experienced and some with some Stillness
we can let things be
so this idea of contentment this feeling that uh everything is
okay sense that things don't need to change right
now and it's maybe this contentment is without this agitation of needing more
and more and more and without the agitation of oh no things have to be different this isn't good enough this is
inadequate this is insufficient this is not good enough
sometimes the sense of agitation may be subtle and sometimes it might be obvious
obvious that we experience in our daily lives or that we experience in
meditation and the same way contentment might be subtle it might be just a small
little corner of our experience or it might be
obvious if you happen have the good for to be out for a hike and seeing some
views and feeling your This Heart being filled up with
appreciation or whatever it is might be for you maybe it is a meditation session that uh allow some of this Stillness to
be experienced this whole idea though of
contentment for some people this idea is actually kind of a dangerous
idea because there can be this way in which we think well if there's any contentment then that must undermine any
effort to make things better then then there would just be
this passivity there would be um this way in which we would just sit around
and eat Bon bonss or something all day this type of thing
there's this way that we might feel like well if there's some contentment then we won't be out there fighting the good
fight we won't be out there working with the terrible oppression and
tyranny Injustice right this stuff is out there we see
it and so people feel like no there can't be any contentment because then people will just allow the status quo to
get worse and worse and worse
so there are certainly things that we should not be content
with but there's a way that we can allow this Stillness some sense of contentment
to fuel us to support us while we work with some of these things that
aren't right I use that word
right and certainly our economy depends on people feeling like
they have to have more right so there's this uh discontent
and like no no no no you need more you clearly you need more and so there's this sense of like
well go out and purchase things or work long hard hours
you know this kind of like nonstop keep buying stuff keep working
and so we might say that this idea of just to experience and allow some sense
of contentment is a radical thing to do I know certainly in my earlier
professional life that's contentment certainly was not uh promoted or suggested or even if
I had said that to my boss probably would not have gone over very well I'm very content with how things are you
know even that if I had done really well or something like this
right so there's this way in which contentment can be such a support for our
life but often it doesn't you know have this sense of that it's um you know
supported by our general Society or something like this and that's okay
that's okay so I want to say that contentment maybe I want to just be explicit about
this it's not about complacency it's not about just
tolerating it's not about this resignation it's not about passively
accepting everything it's more
about you know allowing the I I am uh this for me it's kind of feel like the
heart is filled up like there's a sense of
enough but there's a way in which even the whole notion of contentment can feel like a booby prize too right we feel
like no no no I want that big flashy bubbly big happiness I want that
champagne corks popping off and bubbling things or something like that and if you
have that idea then contentment doesn't sound very interesting at all
or maybe you have this way that if you just find yourself always wanting more
and more and more and that there's a certain amount of uh craving or whether
it's like on the internet click click click click click and you just find yourself you know finding more looking
for more information or some figuring something out or maybe the whatever those short little videos
are that they kind of feed you one after the other so that before you know what hours have gone by or you know it's something like this if you have that
kind of idea of like no no no I like this more and getting stimulated so much
then contentment that's just the idea of it could feel horrifying right because it's not about
that or maybe you have this way of that showing up where you feel like
complaining or grumbling or things you know aren't this way I didn't realize I
used to be a person that complained a lot I didn't recognize this I don't complain
so much now but I just thought that was what people did I mean that was I don't
know I just thought I I don't know why I what I thought actually I just complained a
lot things were never quite right and if you have this idea or if this is your
way of showing up then this whole idea of uh contentment also it just feels
like I don't know like you're failing and some kind of way or something like
this and then maybe I'll also say if we're filled with aversion to
others there's a way in which contentment can feel like no no no I can't feel content because then there's
a way I'm it kind of feels like I'm letting them get away with something like
my agitation is somehow affecting them which you know of course it doesn't
logically when we think about it but there can be this way no no no if I experience contentment somehow I'm
that's not being loyal to my aversion to an individual or something like this and
often we're just not recognizing the toll that takes on us how taxing it is
to always be agitated so contentment is really
related with happiness we could say it's a version of
Happiness we could say but happiness in the usual parlance not the Buddhist way
we might talk about it but again out there what the media might say or magazines or social media or something
like this might say that happiness is a lot about getting what you
want whereas we would say contentment is more about than not
wanting so it's more like this uh shift in this
perspective whereas you might say happiness is more like a shift in ownership that you now have something
that you didn't have or you got rid of something that you didn't want or you know something like
this so there's this way in which contentment
is this absence of craving this absence of U you know things needing to be
different because there's this way when we really feel like oh I need something
whether it's an object an experience recognition uh attainments you know
whatever it might be whatever it might be whenever there's this feeling like oh yeah I definitely need
something there's this way that we can have this fall under this enchantment that well as soon as I get
whatever it is out there there's this way that whatever it is out there kind
of gets sprinkled with some magical thing that thinks like okay well
as soon as I get that then I'll be happy and it'll be a lasting source of
Happiness so there's this way in which contentment
is pointing to this absence of craving and craving is this feeling of
insufficiency and so it's letting go of this or is it an act of letting go it's
allowing this uh insufficiency or inadequacy or something like this to not
blossom to not uh take hold and of our minds and hearts and think that
something magical out there is going to to be a lasting source of
happiness I mean I've said this before if there were things out there that were lasting sources of happiness you would
not be here on a Monday night in a meditation center you would be happily with whatever it was that brought you
the blasting source of Happiness right but there's a way in which we kind
of forget this okay well just the next thing is going to work
so this idea of contentment as I was like alluding to
earlier this this practice is not just about to just be
content with everything but it's about having a wise relationship between contentment and
discontentment if we want to say that there is a time for contentment and there's also maybe a time for we could
say some wise discontent M and that is to be with our suffering
to notice oh yeah there are difficulties some of them are subtle
some of them are obvious some of them are really quiet and we don't even
notice them until maybe there's a certain amount of Stillness maybe we don't notice them
until we are rhyming with a cotton wood tree and we start to feel some of that
agitation so there are definitely times to be
actively addressing some of our suffering actively addressing some of our craving actively addressing some of
our attachments or
acknowledge and work with and be with uh some of this uh
discontent and is there a way that maybe we could say can we be content that uh
here we're offering a practice in which we can do that which we can be with some of the
difficulties mindfulness and mindfulness is part of
the aold path which can help find us support this way to more and more ease
more and more
freedom there's this way that we can meet our difficulties and notice what's actually
happening to be with the reality of the
moment as best we can holding it being with
it so what are some of the ways that we can cultivate some of this contentment
that allows us to hold or maybe creates the conditions than which we can our
Capa we can hold some of the difficulties that our capacities
increase one way we can do this is during meditation
or just in our daily life we can just ask ourselves sometimes What In This
Moment In This precise moment is truly
lacking not in a conceptual way like in this precise moment just to experience
in and for the moment we might feel like well I'm alive I have a breath
those of us in this room it's not super hot it's not super
cold we hopefully have a feeling of
safety hopefully we have enough
food so this way of inquiring well what is it that we really need what do we
sense that we're lacking if anything and
what do we feel like we need can we do with less can it be okay
to have less sometimes we might have
less can that be
okay can we honor our commitments to
non-harming not harming ourselves not harming others sometimes with c cing
that uh creates the conditions in which there can be harming and subtle ways and obvious
ways so it's not a personal failing when we have craving when we recognize yeah I
guess there is anything that I technically lack but I still want more chocolate
brownies whatever it might be
it's part of our conditioning a part like as I was saying earlier to really have this sense of uh you know you need
more and so it's we can just recognize that that uh often this feeling of
needing more we don't have to take it
personally so we could just ask in this moment this precise moment what is truly
lacking we can also
explore when do you feel the least content when is it what are the
conditions in which you're feeling kind of the absence of a contentment maybe when you're in a
hurry or maybe when you're on a spending spree or some that can be easy as click
click click or it can be like oh impulse by near the cashier oh I already spent
this much money I might as well buy this oh wow look at this okay I'll put this in the basket as well or
whatever when when do you feel like the least content when you when do you feel that like you need the more more and
more could be maybe when you're on the internet sometimes I I find that uh the
internet it can be has this uh forward leading momentum it's kind of like
designed to do this right it's hard to just go on there look at one thing and then turn it off or you know something
like this so maybe that inter maybe that's when you feel the Le least contentment when you're reading an
article or something and then it has some links in there and then they're just like oh well maybe I'll follow that link and then you go to this that
whatever it might be so that's something else we can do to
support a sense of contentment is just get curious about well when do I not feel it when when do I feel the least
amount of it and that could just be some information for you to recognize well if
I want contentment in my life just be sensitive to these areas how I'm showing
up to these areas how often I'm doing these
activities I would say is maybe that poem that I read at the beginning suggested meditation
can be a way in which to cultivate some contentment which to allow some of this
stilling or this settling of the agitation of wanting more and
more this could be a way that could be support and also the meditation can um
help us to maybe uh touch into experience have insight about understand
better our desire like what is it that uh or that we feel
like we need or that we want or maybe it's uh our uh aversions what is it that
we feel like we just can't tolerate and can't be with and it's making us feel
discontent with uh what's
happening there's also this way in which uh meditation if we have this commitment
to like stay meditating for a certain amount of time maybe all of you have had this
experience maybe there's a time when you're meditating and there's like this grip of I really want something I don't
want to be meditating I want to be uh doing something else anything else
maybe there's this way in which we have this commitment like no I'm actually going to wait until the timer goes off
or the Bell Rings or whatever it might be so meditation is also an opportunity for us to discover can we be at ease in
the midst of wanting in the midst of yeah okay
craving really a lot of desire a lot of wanting is here and it feels like this
it feels like uh maybe like a leaning forward in the
body might say or maybe there's the uh mind uh starts to have a real Focus away
from the present moment experience and more on like the object like oh yeah as soon as I get this thing or I do this
thing or it's all about something that's going to happen in the future and you're kind of like disconnected from what's
happening right now so meditation is a way in which you can start to notice that where there's
this movement uh towards just thinking about the
future and then the last thing I'll say about something that can be supports this uh contentment this cultivation of
contentment is maybe some gratitude practice this isn't specifically a
Buddhist practice but there's something about just having
appreciation it just makes it so much easier to be have some contentment and
to be present with what's
happening so there's this way in which maybe to appreciate the
good things that others have done for you that you have benefited
from for some people they keep a gratitude Journal I've heard from a
number of people have that has been like really transformative for them to
regularly do that I had that as a practice for some time do have a gratitude journal or or
maybe there's this uh also can be a practice of
uh appreciating what you have by imagining how your life would be if you
didn't have some things it's like just mentally subtract some things and how
your life how would it be different this is a way that maybe you can support some
sense of
gratitude and then maybe it's also
um can be helpful for gratitude is maybe to acknowledge and honor and respect
some of the difficulties you've had in your life too don't have to dwell on them but just
to recognize like yeah you know it has been a journey
to get to this moment here and there's this way that kind of
like appreciating like that there have been some rough patches maybe really really difficult
things maybe you're in the midst of a rough patch I'm using this word rough patch as uh something minor but maybe
you're in a some really midst tragedies in your life in
your family or something like this but just to it can be helpful to
maybe sometimes think or cons re honor and respect that yeah okay there have
been these in my life maybe I am experiencing one right now and is there
this way that um can help us appreciate things that maybe at other without that
framings we would be dismissive of or not even
acknowledge food is an obvious one if there have been times when there weren't enough food
and then when you do have food you just appreciate it like it's quite something if you had times when there wasn't
food so I think I'll end with reading this poem
again it's called on a day when Stillness seems possible by Rosemary
traumer on a day when Stillness seems possible
and the river is a long white stroke of roiling and continuous
Surge and the grass g to seed waivers in the wind then
Stills waivers then Stills and the swallows
spiral the leaf Shadows spangle and the Ants braid path across the
stones but I rhyme today with the Cottonwood
trunks my own body unmoving in the breeze it feels good in this moment to
be more tree than Cloud more silence than
song so easily the Stillness opens me
softens me how simple really to do
nothing how is it I so often resist if there is a no in me now I do
not notice it Stillness has made a home in me and
there seems to be nothing the Stillness refuses come it seems to say there is
room here for everything it opens me
wider the world rushes
in thank you I'll open it up to some comments and
questions on this uh idea of
contentment so how much of finding peace is the inner equilibrium versus your
external life like for example marrying the right person having the right job you know things that bring fulfillment
right how much is the inner and how much is the outer in terms of being at
peace yeah this is a great question so right all of us we trying to have the
outer marry the right person have the right job and these kinds of things but
I'm sure you've noticed we don't get to control the external things right even though you marry the right person and
have the great job it doesn't mean you know tragedy doesn't strike somebody else in your family for example or
something so this practice is pointing to where can we find the peace this
equilibrium that where that doesn't uh allow us to get off balance when the
when tragedy does hit when things aren't working in the external world
so we work with the the external world but we also work with our relationship
to the external world and that relationship is where we can find the peace are we always demanding that it be
different if so that's you know it's exhausting and agitating
so thank you thank you
you mentioned how you used to complain a lot I
remember a time when I got angry a lot
and I would not have said I was an angry person I would have thought just the
opposite and then if I got so angry that I couldn't deny
it you know I still diffused it by saying or discounted it by saying well
of course I'm angry these people over here are behaving like that of course I'm
angry um I didn't understand yeah yeah right it takes a this self-
understanding is such a big part of practice too right these things that we understand about ourselves and it's not
I think it might have been Gil I heard say once it's a self- understanding and then these things that we understand
about ourselves is rarely good news it's like we have this version of
ourselves and then realize oh yeah like I didn't think I was a complainer I realized oh yeah I'm complaining a lot
wasn't until somebody pointed it out to me oh wow you're right so and when they
pointed it out did you say oh yeah you're right or or did you resist I complained of course I'm complaining
because this isn't right and that isn't right right yeah yeah thank you Bill
as you were saying content the word contentment over and over again I um I thought maybe contentment is a dose of
self-actualization and um you know as you're younger maybe you're
content not as much as you are when you get older hopefully hopefully the path will take you to a place where when
you're older you can feel more content and perhaps self actual
self-actualized just the thought I had I see and Stan I missed the verb so
contentment and some and self-actualization but I didn't miss I missed what you were saying I think
they're synonymous speak a dose I think I said a dose
of contentment is a dose of self-actualization oh so you think like maybe with maturity
and uh some yeah if you're on a path whatever that path is and um maturation
process just a thought yeah it's an interesting thought so are people uh
content when they're young when they're in high school when they're in midle they have doses of contentment doses
yeah but then they have this feeling of wanting to get out there and do
something what's more like this when you're younger I see I see yeah this very interesting idea kind
of the relationship between like psychological health and uh contentment yeah it's an interesting
idea and maturity yeah thank you for bringing that
up anybody else have a question or
comment thank you just thank you yeah thank you
okay I feel content so I'm wishing you a wonderful
uh rest of the evening and um if you like you're welcome to come up here and
talk to me as afterwards here and drive home safely thank you