CL from Salt Lake City and Hugh says hola from San Diego
and Richard says hi from Aquin Ohio and
Sarah says salom from Toronto hello salom Sarah hope you're well
it's hopefully so and the uh Zoom the
zoom room is is uh active and so is YouTube YouTube is now also uh flowing and and friends can
join us W can join us there couple more hell hi Erica from Connecticut and hi
Jess from any other last minute hello before we
transition okay the space has been warmed so let's transition at this time I change the settings so that um
unmuting onone be possible so that this space stays quiet and I also change the
chat settings so that uh chats will just come to me hard to hear oh wait let's go
oh oh I see what happened oh thank you thank
you my my um yeah that was the problem um this just fell for some reason so
okay thanks for uh this audio okay now you guys because you gave me a thumbs up
at the beginning so it was here but somehow it fell off my ear uh good okay
I just appreciate the yeah we co-create this so yes uh volume okay so where were
we yes I was changing the settings just just in time so the um uh chats will
come just to me but please uh keep that channel quiet with questions unless you can't can hear me If This falls again
it's not going to fall again but you can let me know if the audio goes down and thank you Neil for posting information
about the happy a Google Groups if you're new to happy a we have a um
mailing list uh it's low in traffic but high in heart I like to say that you are
welcome to join and there's also a breakout room etiquette uh that I'll go
over later but you're welcome to click on it and take a look at it now so these are all the preliminaries
and um last but not least I'm going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma and here we go great so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour
lovely to be with you lovely to practice together so for today's uh practice for
tonight's um or whatever time zone you are for this moment may not be night
where you are uh practice I'd like to lead a a um more stilling more silent
more embodied um expression of meta and
compassion and I'm going to be uh yeah starting with meta leaning into
compassion and compassion essentially is when meta Goodwill friendliness holds suffering holds pain or any challenge
that there might be in the body or in the heart so we're going to go back and forth between these these two these two
practices so that's the that's the plan and um I won't say a whole lot more
we'll just explore and discover as we go how does that sound let's uh let's get
settled let's get settled and arrive in our
bodies in this moment in time arriving
settling and then iding ourselves to first and foremost feel this feeling of
just sitting here having your body what does it feel like to be sitting here and having a
body to have a body and can we
relax into this
body and notice if there are areas of tightness and holding in this
body how is the neck how are the shoulders
can we have a sense of kindness about the neck and
shoulders and invite them to invite them to relax to release
however much is
available or perhaps simply bringing a caring attention to the neck and
shoulders we don't pay enough attention with care to this
body how about
we bring we gently gently bring care appreciation
gentleness friendliness the muscles in the neck and
shoulders and proverbially put down the weight of the world just for a moment we can all pick
it up again all the worries and Fring if we choose to later but right
now choosing choosing to put it down putting the weight
down just just this
moment and then inviting or hands also to settle to
relax as if we were breathing with our hands let let our hands take a breath
these hands have been doing so much perhaps feeding
us cleaning us working whatever they've been doing
so much whatever they've been doing maybe give them a moment of rest with care and appreciation in
goodwi what does that feel
like perhaps borrowing from the practice last night we engaged in what
is not wrong in this moment with these hands but is not
wrong they are not broken in my fingers they're not bandag right
now what is not wrong this moment right now
and can we invite our feet to to also relax our feet and our legs to offer
their weight to the Earth with
friendliness dear feet dear legs especially dear
feet V [Music] to they carry the weight of the whole
body quite an accomplishment the fine structure of the
bones muscles wow relax de your
feet rest de your feet dear dear feet thank
you for all the steps you've taken
today e
and inviting the sit bones also the area of contacting
connecting settling releasing this body onto the cushion or the chair the sit
bones relax offer their weight their weight to the Earth to gravity for
and can we invite the breath to flow just as it is Flowing any
way he wants to
flow and allowing the breath to be
received through the Body Sensations of the breath
within the body receiving them with kindness
gentleness with friendliness to this entire body
[Music] breathing digesting
healing pumping blood all that this body is doing dear body e
and appreciation friendliness for the dear mind planning usually thinking forwards
backwards past present future no need to do that right now but not to make an
enemy out of thinking and the mind and the emotional
states can there be a sense of spacious
friendliness with what it's like to be human to think to
feel having a spaciousness about it not diving into it right now but having
goodwi equinity yeah this is what it's like dear me be human yeah
appreciating the whole the whole catastrophe was a smile
and if the mind starts to feel busy and
active we release gently with friendliness release the thoughts and come back to the breath the sensations
of the breath in the body just rest just rest nowhere to go nothing to
do just rest with kindness [Music]
gentleness a reprieve for a
moment
e e
maybe allowing one part of the body
to to come forward to receive bit more
meta a bit more friendliness
Goodwill what part of the body is moving if there if all the parts of the body
were standing in line one part is like oh I need a little more love need a little more love tonight or appreciation
might be could be a part of the body that is challenged perhaps maybe it's
the back lower back mine is stepping forward like yeah I'm hurting a bit I can receive a little more love if there
was no discomfort might be say the hands like oh yeah I've done a lot today I can
I can get some more love or may you went for a walk a fast walk in the feet step
forward in line and say oh yeah I can re I can use a bit more love a bit more
meta perhaps if that feels appropriate allowing that part of the body to be
wrapped in more care the whole body wrapped in the blanket of meta but this part even more
so appreciation with care and if this part that's volunteered to receive more
metti perhaps in pain or has a bit of discomfort
maybe this practice then becomes a practice of compassion because when
Goodwill friendliness meets pain we're practicing compassion just as
simple as that
so simply bringing Goodwill kindness to the body to this part of the
body Shing e no dear part of the
body appreciate you I care for you may you have
ease maybe there are words maybe it's wordless just ra radiating radiating
Goodwill and
care wherever it's
needed
e
for
e for
if you're working with areas in the body that are challenged can you imagine that
you're putting a soothing self a soothing
s which is enriched with your care with your love with your
friendliness that part of the body giving Extra Care Extra Care sharing
Extra
Care not to get rid of the discomfort that's not the purpose it's just to care
just to care because if we have the agenda applying meta Goodwill in order
to get rid of what we don't like it becomes an aversion
practice allowing it to be just as it is and showering showering with
care
for e
and as we're showering our body body part particular
part of the body can we bring this meta
[Music] Goodwill to the whole to the gestal to
the complete whole of the body parts and this being who is me wishing yourself
well I wish myself well I hold myself with kindness and care may I have ease
may I be happy may I be
healthy may I be
safe may I have ease in whatever order you like whatever
order these metaphases work for you or perhaps
simply I love and accept myself just as I am or I wish
to grow to a place where I love and accept myself or whatever
Nuance or maybe just sticking with I wish myself ease may I have
ease may I be a friend to
myself
e
e e
can there be kindness both to yourself and also if the judgmental thoughts Rising
they're pretty kindness to them to these thoughts and a very lightweight
lighthearted gentleness oh here they are the
usual the usual Army of judgmental thoughts you don't have to believe
them
e e
and as we turn to bring this meditation to
close appreciating appreciating yourself or having showed up as best as you able
to planting seeds
planting seeds of kindness and
spaciousness wholeheartedness friendliness and trusting that there's
been co-created goodness in our practice together and with generosity sharing all
this goodness with all beings everywhere May the cultivation of my
heart be a cause and condition for all beings everywhere to be happy to
be free including myself may all beings be
happy may all beings be free
ding ding
ding that's our verbal Bell thank you all for your practice thank you for your
practice so the Arc of our practice
tonight was we started by um parts of
the body wishing ease inviting ease settling in the neck and shoulders
putting the proverbial weight of the world down for just this little while KN that we can always pick it up after the
the session but just to have a rest bit so that we can have more stability to be
in the world as things keep changing and shifting and being impermanent in the way that they
are and challenging in the way that they tend to be so neck and shoulders or hands
inviting them to rest having gratitude appreciation IMB them with appreciation
our feet similarly inviting the breath to flow as
it likes to flow with appreciation and then the whole body sense of Goodwill friendliness
gentleness So Meta as a way of know gentle friendliness for body
parts and I invited you if there's one body part that needs more care to wrap
it in more care and if that body part happens to be in pain or suffering
having a difficult time then our meta practice our Goodwill practice becomes compassion practice because remember
care or meta Goodwill plus suffering this hold suffering that's compassion
compassion is equal to meta plus suffering meta Plus Pain Goodwill plus
pain so in that way meta Goodwill shape shifts into compassion when it meets
suffering and pain and it shape shifts back into Goodwill when we're meeting
perhaps the body if there's no suffering or pain so we explored that a little bit
and then I invited you if if you're opening up to the whole body body parts
then well guess what this whole you know my my self my dear self is made up for
all these parts so can we wish ourselves well may I be well may I be safe happy
healthy have ease or whatever phrases work for you and and staying with those spaces so um that was roughly the Arc of
our practiced or a few other things um that was roughly the arc so so with
that with that I want to invite a particular practice tonight as we go
into um small groups together and the
I'm going to describe what the invitation is and then I'll I I'll lay out the small the uh breakout group uh
guidance so so the invitation for the prompt tonight is the prompt is um what
part of the body needs needs the this moment in time is the
whole actually I put the guy uh I I'll get to the um uh breakout room
guidelines in a moment but the the the um uh prompt is what part of the body
needs more care in this moment in time um
and in a small group for example if I was if it was my turn the small group I
would say well maybe I'll dedicate you know this this period of this you know
the two minutes that I'm or the one minute that I'm checking in to my lower back it's it's been sitting a lot today
it's all tied and and I just appreciate that you know my back really does so
much and it's been injured before and it's hanging in there and thank you back just
this sense of appreciating and really bringing bringing meta hearing yourself
speak out loud with kindness because a lot of times with our body parts we
we're angry we feel like they're letting us down or or um it's not so much this
meta filed relationship that we have and if there's no discomfort maybe you decide oh my hands they've been typing
all day and they've answering emails and they've been working thank you hands I so appreciate um that that these hands
are doing what they're doing or my feet or whatever or maybe your whole body that it's you know not so bad today yeah
of course you're aging and and all of that as as everyone is but you know today it's U the the body just bringing
more meta so so uh going over the guidance for the
small groups and standing for mindfully speaking listening E standing for
compassion embracing compassion staying on topic and the topic today is how what
part of the body do you want to give more meta more compassion perhaps to if there's a challenge and um maybe you
you'll have a minute or two to if you want a minute to speak about that and
we'll go in reverse alphabetical order um you'll say something and please make
sure everybody else has time to also uh mindfulness out loud uh give
some meta to to any part of the body that needs more care and support or
maybe the entire body taking turns briefly and avoiding cross talk so um if
any questions you can share in chat but otherwise I'm going to go ahead and create the the breakout rooms uh for us
to have the opportunity to to speak out loud to practice out loud in the small
groups and see what it's like to acknowledge to actually to appreciate these bodies that we often take for
granted we take them as work hes or or goodness knows
so so breakout rooms here we go I'm
creating them now and remember as long as you're kind you're um yeah you're
you're kind you're being generous to yourself and to each other
you're doing this practice right so um I going to open the breakout rooms take
care of yourself take care of each other here we
go
e
e e
the rooms will close in 5 seconds okay the rooms are closed everybody is
back welcome back everyone so um how was it what happened
I'm also going to change chat settings if you want to report on either the meditation or or this practice of of uh
for for the sake of yourself speaking out loud in the group being held witness
and uh just giving some more love to to to the body part especially if they're challenged any any discoveries any aha
moments or any challenges you want to ask questions about can raise your Zoom
hand if you like you can type are your Reflections or questions in chat for the sake of everyone how was it
what what
happened Andy says we had fun connection nice oh that's sweet
nice Diana I see your hand
please this was a wonderful meditation really bringing me back
to all that's good and present and so I really enjoyed it and and got a lot
benefit from it I have a question about something you said earlier um about
meta shapes or shifts into compassion when there's pain for
me I mean it just seems like it happens automatically that is that what you
meant in other words sometimes a com compassion comes without me thinking
oh I need what do I need here what it just pops
up is that part of that's that's exactly it that's what I mean Diana that's exactly it so so you know sometimes it's
a surprise what's that it's a surprise somehow yeah yeah it just shows up yeah
so I mean a couple of different things I think one is um uh yes it's it's lovely
that it comes up when it's needed right oh yeah that since you've practiced compassion and for so long and part of
happy hour and there was pain pain or suffering or difficulty oh compassion is is is the automatic response of the
heart instead of beating yourself up or beating somebody else up like well you're having a tough time today well
get it together girl like instead of that like oh sweetheart you're having a hard time okay do you need care do you
need what do you need in order to to to be able to uh feel better and be able to
to meet the world in a wiser way right so so that's the the automatic response
that comes up right instead of the former the latter that's one that's one part of this but I was making a
different point Diana the point I was making with the shape shifting is the
following sometimes uh some people have this conception that compassion is one
practice and meta loving kindness is a different practice but what I'm trying what I'm saying is that yeah they're
their join at the hip it's really meta it's Goodwill so Goodwill is the basic
expression of friendliness of the heart and when good Goodwill comes across
someone who's suffering or if that someone is ourselves um there's
suffering there's pain when meta meets suffering it becomes compassion it shape
shifts it's the same thing it's not of a different ilk it's just the circumstance
of what it's meeting but it's the same kindness Goodwill care of the heart it's
not a totally different practice it's the same practice of the heart that now is meeting difficulty that's what I mean
I thought that's what you were saying I just thought it was a Wonder it's just if it's something for me to wonder about
as in a Wonder all right thank you thank you a miracle a miracle or something El to me
thank you sweet thank you so much and Claire V
you're still muted Claire try again an an extension of Diana's question would
empathy fall into the same mix yeah so so that's a really good
question and think of empathy as a constituent of compassion it's not
empathy is not equal to compassion empathy is is a constituent so
so we need empathy to feel our own pain
it sounds strange to say that but to feel someone else's pain and to think of that aspect is the meeting of the pain
the acknowledgment of the pain right so compassion has two aspects it's it's meeting acknowledging of the pain and
then holding it with care okay so the empathy is meeting of the pain is just
meeting and if you end it if you stopped at empathy that would be empathy
practice um and empathy practice alone without that care warmth kindness can
Veer into empathic distress because you're just feeling the pain oh this is painful oh this is hard oh poor you this
is you can Veer into actually uh pity also or or uh empathy distress which
some people think of as compassion fatigue but it's actually empathy fatigue so so empathy is a constituent
but it doesn't have the complete picture of of um holding the difficulty not just
meeting it but also meeting it with kindness and Care warmth so empathy and
some people consider again going one step deeper you can think of empathy
especially as your empathizing with someone else's pain as the the way that
say our bodies Our Hearts our brains light light up and and they um there areas in the brain that become more
activated when we see other people being in pain so there studies where if you
see someone for example being poked by a needle then you feel pain like ouch ouch right that's the mirror neurons that's
the empathy you're empathizing with someone else's pain that's not compassion right compassion would be
ouch that's painful oh I'm that's hard oh dear one this you know how uh I I
wish you well I wish you freedom I wish you ease from this pain there's that care that you bring and different areas
of the brain light up when it is compassion not just the the Mir neurons the prain centers but also the filial
the warmth the care areas of the brain get more activated when you do compassion practice because it's both
it's feeling the pain and holding it with care and that I cannot EMP ize that
enough make sense thanks Claire thanks for that
[Music] question any other questions Reflections how was it I would love to hear actually
if anyone would like to report well how was it in the small groups uh offering
more care to a part of your body out loud acknowledging Valery
um yeah I it was really good for me I
was telling my small group I had this thing happen last night where I was in a community of people I really care about
and there was a couple there that I see a lot of places and I really care about
them and uh they're very sweet and I she asked me how I was doing and I told her
I wasn't doing well that I was waking up in the middle of the night like in Terror and very quickly it became
evident that like she's like a very different
political side than I was and she started saying some things that I just
was like what are you saying like and um I wasn't expecting it at all and I made
an assumption that that you know we were maybe closer
together on some things and anyway I had such a reaction to her and I had to
leave I had to like leave her company and then I was sitting in a a reserved
area that she had sponsored and and that I felt so hard in my heart with her like
I just didn't like how I reacted I didn't like and it was colding both not
me not liking what she was saying and then not also not liking my reaction and
I I kind of settled myself and resourced myself and then I went back to her and just offered some loving kindness to her
like I told her how important she was to me in the community and how much I care
like how and it's so funny how much I can care for her and then when I hear like things that I I don't like how how
I was rejecting her and so I didn't I mean I just went to her and just apologized for my reaction and just
offered my loving kindness to her and she was very gracious and she hugged me and
um it was very loving and for her I don't I don't think she had any
reactions but um but it felt so good in my heart to offer that to her but I noticed during the meditation I was
still feeling a little of that contraction around her and so it was the meditation was really helpful for me to
just offer love be in loving kindness with people that I don't agree with or
um so it's really powerful very helpful and and it's a
practice right yeah it's a exactly we're always learning and and and I really
appreciate how you shared that uh you wisdom arose as you were sitting in this
area wisdom arose oh dear you know this is not how I want to show up in in the world I want to show up with with
kindness I want to show up with loving kindness even if I disagree with with people I want to show up with kindness
seeing for their humanity and and how you actually corrected this just I'm I'm
so moved really so moved by by that may may all of us have the wisdom to um to
notice reactivity and and bring loving kindness to others to ourselves um yeah thank you for sharing
I'm really I'm really feel like I'm practicing listening staying listening and I just was surprised at my reaction
I think because I wasn't expecting it in the setting but uh yeah you know we keep
practicing and noticing reac activities and holding it with kindness compassion for ourselves and others thanks Valerie
yeah Sandy uh we're at 7 pm so this has got to be quick okay um I Valerie really
appreciate what you just shared get it and what was really quickly what was the
Imaging that shows up in the brain around empathy could you restate what you said just before Valerie's question
do you remember what yeah yeah um so so the um so with compassion practice two
areas of the brain become more activated more active one is the areas that that
get active when when we feel pain when we feel our own pain and when we feel other people's pain right when we if you
see somebody else in pain the areas of the brain that that get activated when you are in pain get activated that's one
the other one is the area areas of the brain that have to do with with family and love and care and warmth those areas
get light up so both of those okay okay okay so and and those are two different
parts of the brain or the same part two different parts two different okay thanks you're so welcome so we have come
to the end of this edition of Happy Hour May May we be kind may we be
compassionate to ourselves to everyone else to our bodies to others bodies in
this human life it's tough to be human no matter which side of the the ocean
the aisle the whatever you're on May all of us have peace and ease may all beings
be free including ourselves so thank you
all