so I would like to talk about one of the
really basic practice teachings in our
vipasana uh
tradition and in general the teachings
we give tend to be practice teachings
they're uh teachings that really focus
on how to support people to practice
mindfulness that makes the most sense on
Retreats and uh where that's really the
focus and but that Retreat focus is so
Central to us that sometimes that spill
spills over and uh and it's one of the
primary things we're doing is giving
practice instructions that are relevant
for meditation and then indirectly
sometimes or sometimes directly we talk
about how it applies to everyday
life but these practice instructions
that are coming out of the teachings of
the Buddha um uh sometimes it's amazing
how modern they seem it's like wow this
this fits just into our world just as
well as it probably did 2500 years ago
but that's a long time ago and that's
like the bronze
Ages come to IMC and get teachings from
the bronze
ages I don't know if that would you know
give people maybe give people kind of
pause to come
here and um so in recent years uh I've
uh been very fortunate to have some
contact with uh some of the modern
developments especially here in the west
of new ways of understanding human mat
human maturation human
concerns um that's had a big impact on
me uh one of them is the developing
field of chaplaincy pestal care and uh
there's a whole set of values or human
needs that are cons that are uh seen in
chaplain SE is that the chaplain meets
in with people and that list is
different than any list that I've ever
seen in
Buddhism and but they're speaking to
fundamental things that about being a
human
being um I sit on a local in a hospital
Ethics Committee and I'm inspired by how
in the last probably 50 years the field
of medical e uh medical ethics has
really uh been de grown and developed
and there's very clear uh ethical values
that are held in hospitals these days
but and it's inspiring to to go to this
committee and hear doctors and nurses
medical staff uh reflect on how to care
for patients with these values and some
of those values also are not directly
spoken about in uh in uh in in
Buddhism and maybe even
avoided and then uh the other is modern
psycho psychology where there's been uh
ideas of uh human development the stages
of human development like Eric Ericson I
think he has five stages of human
development and and U and some of those
uh forms of psychology have positive uh
states that are kind of the Fulfillment
of these different
stages and some of those also aren't
touched on in Buddhist
teachings so so that's interesting so do
we just stay in Little
Buddhist
little um
enclave and be content with that or uh
or not and I find it very enlivening and
interesting to to have to see the
interaction between these two these
different
worlds and um and sometimes uh I feel
like I learned from them sometimes I
feel like the Buddhist orientation casts
a different perspective on other things
are developing in the West and gives me
pause or gives me kind of a different
slant to understand
them and uh so from um one of the things
that uh uh fundamental to
chaplaincy is a topic of meaning meaning
making meaning and purpose and many
times when meaning has been ruptured in
people's lives even when it's
unconscious the meaning they assign to
their life or have when that gets broken
and often in chapy situations where
Chaplin are needed it's because
something dramatic has happened that
what gives people meaning in their life
has been broken or ruptured and and uh
sometimes betrayed even and so um so
being able to respond and think about
points of view from meaning and purpose
and it's seldom that a Buddhist teacher
talks too much about topic of meaning
per se or purpose per se and when I was
a Zen student it was almost taboo
because the teachers would say someone
asked what's the meaning meaning of life
and they would bark back no
meaning and uh what's the purpose no
purpose and but what they didn't then
follow up on usually was to explain that
this teaching of no meaning and no
purpose fit in was within a larger
context that had a lot of meaning and
purpose um and so you had to kind of if
you didn't understand the larger context
of why they say say that it would be
just confusing sometimes and uh so there
was meaning and purpose there even
though that to say
that and um in um in the world of Ethics
one of the kind of the
fundamental uh ethical principles there
are autonomy and dignity that everyone
has autonomy and everyone has dignity
and uh and that is a little bit bit hard
sometimes to fit into for some people uh
if you've kind of spend too much time
listening to Buddhist teachers like
me and they've EMP emphasized that not
self not self realized not self and
suddenly autonomy and dignity seems like
but now we're back in the world of self
and how are these supposed to work
together and then uh in modern uh you
know psychology and stages of
development um you know there's the idea
of
maturation and uh and that exists in
Buddhism the idea of maturation
sometimes is called um uh ripening
because they use uh uh metaphor from
Plants fruit ripening to this process of
spiritual
maturation and um and I love the idea of
uh using the word maturation for um how
people develop in Buddhist practice
because um uh it some of the classic
ideas of the stage of development are
kind of quantum leaps and you you make
this big leap into a whole different way
of being that transformation and then
there's almost like a status difference
between people who enter these different
levels and people who don't and and it's
little bit arbitrary to make these kind
of absolute Quantum ideas of Leaping and
I think the idea of maturation is slow
and gradual process of of developing and
growing is much more um
peaceful it's much more socially polite
it's just much more kind of allows us
not to be so caught up in goals and
being a perfect or just being attaining
something we want to just allow
something to slowly grow and develop and
it might look like stages like Eric
Ericson has these five stages or phases
of human development but even there I
think it's a little bit problematic
because uh who wants to who wants to be
identified as someone who never grew out
of the first
stage you know when you're a little kid
and um but if you see them these uh
these things as being five different
areas of maturation and the with
different areas of where we need to
develop so the classic teaching I want
to mention today is called the five
faculties five capacities that we have
that can become strengths as they as we
mature and the class usual way of
describing these five in English is
Faith effort mindfulness concentration
and wisdom so I would like to present
them in a different way today I'd like
to present them as uh confidence Freedom
love
wholeness and meaning and
purpose so uh faith I want to call
confidence effort or energy or exertion
I like like to call
Freedom and the mindfulness I'd like to
call
love and uh concentration Som I'd like
to call
wholeness and uh and wisdom I'd like to
call meaning and
purpose and I think that switching the
words like that provide us a very
different orientation to understand how
profound these five faculties are these
five capacities we are are and how as as
they get developed and come into
fulfillment
become strong that uh they bring us
these wonderful qualities they bring us
confidence they bring us a sense of
Freedom they bring us love they bring us
wholeness and they bring us a meaning
and
purpose classically these uh five are
sometimes paired so that uh faith and
wisdom are paired and effort and samade
are appeared and then mindfulness is
never need doesn't need to be paired or
balanced with anything else it just
stands for itself so in this schema I
think it works the confidence and uh
meaning and purpose work together if we
have a clear sense of meaning what is
Meaningful for your life and what
purpose then we can talk about having
confidence for that meaning and purpose
if we have a clear sense of it so that
and then the pairing of of uh freedom
and
wholeness uh uh in my mind it it implies
that we can't really talk
about kind of a spiritual or really
mature humanistic kind of Freedom if
we're not
whole uh if um there's a lot of emphasis
in Freedom as many of you know in the
United States that it it's kind of
selfish it's kind of like you know I
should be free to do whatever I please
you know to be
politely and um and uh you know there's
the freedom to shop freedom to you know
what doing all kinds of things uh but um
but the
um but what I'd like to propose is when
it's selfish or self-centered Freedom uh
it actually is not healthy for the
person doing it because the person is
not whole if we have a sense of real
wholeness that comes from samade comes
from meditation practice then we'll feel
how we become divided in ourselves
fragmented when it's selfish the sense
of Freedom we have and but for freedom
to come out of sense of wholeness where
we don't fragment ourselves provides
much more meaning and purpose for the
freedom we
live and then uh mindfulness I I relate
to love and partly because that's what I
discovered in the years I practiced it
that it's hard sometimes to separate the
kind of clear attention to something
that is mindfulness from love that
somehow seeing clearly is an act of love
and as I've often have said uh this is
represented by the experience of young
children or adults who come and talk to
me and say that as young children they
feel they were never seen the parents
ignored them or you didn't Overlook them
or the parents was too busy or too angry
or too drunk or something and um and so
they felt like they never were seen and
cared for and not to be seen as a child
is equivalent to not feeling loved and
it can be really detrimental to be seen
is a form of love for adults uh maybe
the equivalent is to be listened to that
to uh to be really heard is is a way of
being is way to hear someone well is a
way of loving someone it's such such a
deep need we have to be heard and
understood and so mindfulness is that it
fits into this capacity to see and to
hear and to do that for ourselves to
really be mindful here clearly uh is a
way to have love for oneself to bring
love to see the world through the eyes
of mindfulness is a Kind of Love is a
kind of care for the
world so um so the first one
confidence paired with meaning and
purpose paired with wisdom is that the
the wi the idea of wisdom in Buddhism
early Buddhism in the bronze
ages is that um wisdom has to do with uh
understanding that we have a
capacity to not
suffer we have a capacity to not to do
things engage in activities that
afflicts us
that diminishes us that undermines our
well-being that drains
us and um and and we have the capacity
to do the opposite we have the capacity
to do the things that uh make us feel
nourished develop what's wholesome in US
develop a sense of uh well-being and
goodness in us rather than Badness in US
rather than under you know and that that
distinction is necessary in Buddhism for
the ultimate purpose of Buddhism which
is uh to grow and mature in a way that
brings us to the end of suffering to Dua
brings us to the end of the emotional
pain that we contribute to
ourselves there might still be emotional
pain but it's not something that we're
contributing to our heart is not adding
or suffering our heart is not divided
our heart is not Contracting our heart
is not involved in activities which
undermine us and to be able to see this
clearly well enough can give a
tremendous amount of meaning and purpose
to a life there's meaning and purpose to
come to the end of suffering there's
meaning and purpose to do the things
that allow our our life our inner life
our heart to thrive the budha use the
word Thrive to come into a sense of
abundance come into a sense of
fulfillment
to mature and grow and ripen in a to
become
full and so there's a very positive
orientation to the capacity of human
development in early Buddhism that that
that the guide for it the whole approach
to it is very simple it doesn't require
any Supernatural beliefs it doesn't
require any great metaphysical beliefs
it requires a heightened
sensitivity to feel how our body our
hearts our inner mind our inner life
prefers to be whole to per prefers not
to add pain and suffering to us add
stress to our system prefers to be
involved in those things which are feel
inspiring feel good for
us and um and maybe that's not enough
for some people to inspire some people
because they
want really Grand ideas spiritual IDE
you know Supernatural ideas Cosmic ideas
Cosmic Consciousness great states of of
Altered States Of Consciousness that's
the
purpose u in some ways Buddhism is a
pretty humble
religion because its goal is simply
only to end
suffering and so to have a sense of that
possibility and then to have confidence
in that that that's meaningful to have
confidence in that as a
purpose without the confidence that this
is useful then why practice there has to
be some confidence and that's that's the
goal that's the purpose that's what's
possible and so those two go together
we're not talking about confidence in
some AB abstract way you know I don't
have enough confidence I'm supposed to
be more confident what but you know but
I don't know what I'm supposed to be
confident
in uh but this provides the wisdom
provides guide guidance for where we can
find our confidence where we can develop
our
confidence and as we develop as we
practice then not only we have
confidence in the purpose but we also
now have confidence in our capacity to
practice our capacity to make a
difference to engage and that comes into
the second faculty which is effort or
exertion or
application and which I tie to wholeness
and so to apply
ourselves in this practice like to do
practice mindfulness practice
meditation um because the meaning and
purpose was to not suffer not to add
stress we apply that confidently to how
we make effort in the
practice I've practiced you know sat
down to meditate with the idea that you
know I'm going to really get
really concentrated now I'm gonna really
kind of Blast away my you know all my
thoughts and and I'll just be like the
you know the Dharma the Buddha's gift to
my town my city and you know I get a
badge that says you look at gil I've you
know I'm the great Blaster way of
thoughts and can you know just not be
distracted and it'll be great I'll be
praised by
everyone you know maybe exaggerating a
little bit how I thought but it's there
something like that certainly went on in
my mind but those kinds of thoughts
added stress and I I those when
something like that was going on in my
meditation practice it I I it turned out
it was actually very
successful uh for me in terms of uh
creating a
headache so you know eventually I
learned that this doesn't work this
attitude I have about how to practice
straining and pushing um or sometimes I
was really trying to avoid something you
know really something was coming up in
my meditation some emotions some
unresolved emotions that I really needed
to look at um but I didn't want to look
at and I would put up walls I'd put up
resistance you know it's I I you know
tense up so I wouldn't have to feel it
and um eventually I learned that didn't
work either that what worked is to open
because the resistance is another form
of undermining myself is another form of
being divided is not understanding the
meaning of purpose is to open to
everything so we can find a way to
mature through it not to
avoid so this idea of having a clear
sense of meaning and purpose is a
protection for the effort we make so
that we kind of always checking out am I
practicing in a way that feels good that
I enjoy or seems right to me when I have
to face what's difficult
and then wholeness the idea that
wholeness is uh is we start discovering
all the ways we live in a divided way
fragmented way all the ways we pushing
things away or we're over prioritizing
certain parts of ourselves so we're not
present for the whole if we have strong
desires and ambition we might miss the
whole of who we are if we have strong
aversions and hates we miss the whole of
who we are because we're so so fixated
and focused on an object of our desires
the object of our aversions we don't see
the fullness of who we are and so it
turns out if you don't the fullness of
who we are the wholeness the undivided
the
unfragmented um that actually feels much
more nourishing it feels much more this
is the the soil or the ground in which
things can grow and mature and that's
part of the function of samade practice
in Buddhism is to create the conditions
that's creates the let's let's who we
are be all of who we are be
complete warts and all so that something
it can be fertile soil for something
grow and develop fertile soil for
something to wither away which doesn't
serve
us and then we come then to the the the
middle uh which is uh mindfulness that
that needs no balance needs no that
because mindfulness is often seen as a
form of
wisdom uh not the wisdom that you would
necessarily have articulate
through ideas of meaning and purpose but
the kind of wisdom that comes from
having direct immediate contact with our
lived experience here and now the
contact that get it feels that uh if you
step on a nail you would know you should
not push down with your heel because you
start feeling it going in oh better take
it out it's you you get the you get the
message right
away and uh so with mindfulness these
messages come in and the stronger the
mindfulness is the more subtle the
messages are from the psychophysical
system this is good this is not so good
this is nourishing this is Pleasant this
is enjoyable this brings happiness and
wellbeing this doesn't bring happiness
and well-being it brings the opposite
but to really get quiet and still to not
override the experience with a lot of
thoughts and ideas and
expectations um and that ability to have
that kind of mindfulness that is so
sensitive to the caring of what's
supports us and what
doesn't uh maybe start seeing it's a
form of
love because we have inside of us
something inside here that wants to care
for you something inside of you that
wants the best in you that wants wants
to
avoid
harm you know it's not so different than
you know taking your hand off the hot
stove right away something inside of
your nose to do that they say that uh
that instinct to not take your hand off
the hot
stove never makes it to the brain or it
the the it responds before the signal
goes to the brain it's so basic in the
whole nervous system that's even you
know the brain the mind we don't
normally think of doesn't have to even
operate something very deep inside of us
something built into our very structure
of Being Human Being I believe has
something in it to want to care for us
there's there's and that I would like to
call
love so we all so the
possibility as we mature as we develop
in this practice is to bring these five
areas to
fullness it's possible to come into a
fullness around
confidence it's possible to come into a
fullness around a sense of Freedom a
freedom to be able to
act without
restrictions at least through our hearts
what our hearts motivated to do as part
of our
wholeness uh fulfillment in love and
care care and
compassion a fulfillment in terms of a
sense of wholeness being
complete now that I'm getting to be
old you know I'm 70 now so some people
consider or on
edge approaching it depends how old you
are what you think 70 is I'm
approaching when I was 20 I would have
looked and that's
old so
changes but uh but you know it is an age
where I begin thinking about you know
the end of life and you know what my
life has been like and and I feel kind
of a certain satisfaction and feel like
I've had a good life and that feels full
that's felt full because there sense of
wholeness in it so that's a nice thing
to come to and but it's not enough to
rest on that because I'm still the
system that I have still wants to
practice it's a constant coming into
wholeness coming into Freedom a constant
kind of reference point to what's
meaningful and
purposeful so maturing into wholeness is
is always a
process and then uh
fulfillment coming into completion
fulfillment or a matur maturity into a
real sense of meaning and
purpose so that's kind of at the root
we're rooted in it we're dedicated to it
it informs us yes yes the purpose
there's a real purpose that I want to
stand in and be part of that's different
than um going on
Netflix or shopping on
Amazon different than what a lot of
people tend to do fill their time with
but what if that meaning and purpose is
like that's what has most meaning for
you is what you fill your time with and
that's one of the things this practice
can be part of some people feel like
this has gives the life the most meaning
most purpose and it's not
selfish because in this system in this
meaning and purpose built into this
psychophysical system in the love of it
all and the care of it all is love and
care for others and for the world it
can't be any different because our own
well-being is intimately connected to
our
connectivity to others and if we're
living being in the lived experience we
really know how to sense and feel and be
be present to listen and to see others
so that our seeing and listening is an
act of Love are people's well well-being
is kind of like our own so of course
there's going to be love in how we live
our
life so these are the five areas that we
become strong and develop and this is my
attempt to try synthesize bring
together Bronze Age
psychology
with the concerns of Pastoral
Care Medical
ethics and uh and modern
psychology I hope that was okay to
do
so confidence
Freedom
love
wholeness and meaning and
purpose which of
those is the strongest for you maybe
none of them are strong but which of
them is
strongest and which is the weakest maybe
they're all strong but which is the
strongest and which is the weakest in
you which of the five you think is can
be improved you could work on
which is strong that can be applied to
the others to bring them
along
confidence
Freedom
love wholeness meaning and
purpose
so I've come to the end of what I want
wanted to say and um thank you for being
here