hello everyone and welcome to this morning meditation
and one of the possibilities that can come from
meditation is being refreshed and one of the great refreshments is
becoming simple is simplicity of being
and one of the values of developing samadei
with the inconstant changing nature of experience is how it's endlessly
refreshing it simplifies so much in the mind just
be and as we stay with the changing nature of the present moment experience
resting in it trusting it relaxing with it
uh we start seeing how it's the thinking mind
that uh uh more often than not
keeps us in the old groove keep us keeps us in the old familiar thought patterns
that sometimes can be debilitating undermining us
and uh and to step out of the normal stream of
thoughts and thinking into this different stream of direct experience direct sensations
and develop the samadei of change samadei of inconstancy samadei of of uh
the changing nature of the present moment is Uh
one way to be refreshed one way to appreciate a simplicity of being
simplicity of mind simplicity of thinking no longer needing to interpret
no longer needing to judge and evaluate no need no longer a need to remember or
plan or fantasize
that for the duration of the meditation allowing oneself a simplicity of being
with direct experience and that samadei of change
is one of the one of the places to experience that is with the changing sensations of breathing
so to assume a meditation posture
and
the meditation posture I find it helpful sometimes to
view it feel it as kind of a temple
and I'm entering a sacred sanctum sacred
space a sacred grove of trees someplace that's
special by assuming this posture
and to gently close the eyes and to feel
whatever is familiar about being in your meditation posture
maybe making small adjustments in the posture to be a little more comfortable
and then to
take a few fuller breaths where the inb breath inb breath is a time to feel more
fully your torso and the exhale a time to relax settle
and letting your breathing return to normal
but still stay close to the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and as you breathe in feel the muscles of your face
and as you breathe out soften in the face
as if your muscles of the face can fall away from the skull
as if the rhythm of breathing in breathing out is a bit of massage for
the face through feeling and relaxing
breathing in and feeling the shoulders exhaling and softening the shoulders
where the gentle rhythm of breathing
is there to help you connect to your shoulders relax your shoulders
and then doing the same with your belly
and if the belly moves as you breathe feel the belly as you inhale
releasing the belly as you exhale
staying close to that rhythm alternation of breathing in and
breathing out
and on the inhale become aware of whatever sensations
are associated with your thinking mind
maybe energy activation a little contraction or pressure
maybe you think from from a particular location
where there's some subtle sensations of a gathering
coalescing of as you exhale
to relax the thinking mind
and then to relax into the body breathing
wherever you feel your breathing in the body wherever it's easiest for your body
itself to experience the sensations the rhythm of breathing
relax into that place
and maybe at the beginning of the inhale the end of the exhale
there's the gathering place for attention
awareness
as you breathe in and breathe out
orient your mind
towards breathing almost like from the back of the mind
back of the skull
you establish a direct line like the light of a lighthouse
that touches down on the physical experience of the body
breathing
as you inhale receive the sensations of inhaling
as you exhale allow the sensations of exhale
to come and float away
like gentle waves washing up on the sand beach
and receding this constant movement and change of
breathing in the body
and you might notice how thinking can pull you away from that
into old habits of thinking
into the repetition of familiar themes and ideas and feelings
for now return to breathing
reorient yourself to the radical simplicity
of the rhythm of sensations coming and going as you
breathe
like the sand that continuously feels
the movement of the waves coming and going
in shallow water by the beach your body continuously feeling sensing
the changing nature in the mind
becoming simple quiet
as it enters the samadei of breathing
relaxing the mind letting go of the complexity of thinking
in favor of the simplicity of the body breathing
letting that be a vacation a sacred Sabbath
from all the thinking that you normally do
simplicity of breathing
with a little bit of simplicity
maybe there can be a little bit of samadei of simplicity samadei of simple
breathing
a gathering a settling together
with breathing at the center of all things
a center which is shifts and changes and oscillates moves
gently in the body
and awareness receives it
awareness doesn't go out to find or search
but settles back and receives the experience of breathing
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
with your eyes still closed imagine gazing upon the world with a
receptive gaze
where the world experience of the world comes to you
you don't have to search
you don't have to do the looking but allowing
the world to come into sight
and imagine that you can do that with the people of your lives
and as they come into view as they appear in the mind and your memory
to appreciate the simplicity of seeing
that wants nothing searches for nothing
a seeing which is receptive and fresh
and in that receptivity that freshness
to wish simplicity of being
freshness joy safety and peace
to others as you experience for yourself
may it be that how we learn to be in meditation the simplicity the peace
the non assertiveness the care
helps us to go out into the world to care for the world itself
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this
continued series on insight and today I want to emphasize that
insight I think of insight in this insight
meditation as being more like revelation than it is as searching
as it is straining to see and understand something it's a understanding it's a seeing that
reveals itself to us that we're not searching for something
we're allowing something to show itself to us
but we're preparing ourselves for to be good re recipients of this what gets
shown to us and so practicing samadei quieting the mind getting focused and
still cultivating a simplicity of being with our experience so that the mind is
not jumping around so much but the mind settles down the mind gets steady and
quiet and so and then the insights of inside
meditation uh again is not a searching it can arise
out of the real radical simplicity and all the insight that you need in a deep
way comes from can come from resting experience with the breathing
and the one of the primary insights that we're looking for or waiting for or allowing for insight meditation is that
of inconstancy change impermanence
how things are constantly arising and disappearing appearing and disappearing
and um and that and that insight that revealing
of change uh can happen completely with the breathing all that you need to see and
change and impermanence and constancy can be experienced uh first and foremost
in the changing experience of breathing and the advantage of this is the breathing is relatively simple the
advantage of this is the breathing is the mo sitting in meditation is um is
the largest movement the biggest kind of generally the biggest changing sensations that we experience and so we
don't have to go searching for it it's there for us to experience generally
sometimes breathing is counterindicated when people get uh maybe uh too anxious
around the breath or it's too awakens difficult emotions
or sometimes the breathing gets very very subtle but generally uh uh medit in insight
meditation the way I was taught was having the central focus be on breathing
and I found that really beneficial icial to help with the simplicity of the practice that uh I wasn't looking around
for things to have insight about i wasn't looking to have insight um the we
talk about the insight into impermanence change and constancy um but the idea is
not to go looking for that so much but to relax and open to receive it uh to
let it find you rather than you find it and it will find you if the thinking
mind is not predominating if if we're not seeing the world through our thoughts if we're not uh the only
part of the world we're seeing is thinking we're inhabiting inhabiting our
thoughts living in our thoughts consumed with our thoughts making up worlds with
our thoughts if that whole movement can be quiet for a while and we step out of the stream of
thoughts the constant stream of thinking all the time and and step out of that
stream and into this other stream the river of change within us and today I'm
emphasizing the breathing to help with that simplicity of being and to get uh
gather ourselves orient ourselves not just around the the breathing but but uh
allowing ourselves to take in all the sensation sensations of breathing that
come and go it might simply be recognizing the coming and going of inb breath and out breath it might be seeing
the individual sensations that uh occur even within an inb breath or within and
out breath and in doing that uh one of the
advantages is we can see how much uh we disconnect from that and we return to
the old habit of thinking and thinking is a leading cause of all
kinds of psychological challenges depression can be come from a lot of
rumination thinking about oneself a lot is said to be one of the leading causes for
um all kinds of psychological challenges because if we're thinking about
ourselves all the time we're repeating usually often challenging thoughts debilitating thoughts undermining
thoughts and um or an attitude that is not so healthy often with ex excessive
self-p preoccupation and so to get refreshed willingly to be refreshed or to
trustingly that it's okay to put that aside it's okay not to be thinking so
much about oneself thinking so much about reality thinking so much about our desires not only is it okay but over
time we begin appreciating that it's really refreshing it's really healthy
it's really beneficial to keep coming back to the direct
experience in the body and you know with breathing and to and the rhythm and it
it's easier for the mind to get focused to get centered
uh if there's actually a subtle movement in the focus of attention it's almost
restful for the eyes restful for the mind to follow a simple ordinary
movement that comes and goes that arises and passes or that flows peacefully
through us and so um the as I many times
say that it's like sitting in the riverbank and watching a river go by or sitting at the beach and watching the
waves come up on the shore and down and um
and I can do that for long periods of time it's something very refreshing and nice and renewing to watch uh the very
simple rhythm of something coming and going and so to ride that to surf on the
movements of the breathing to uh receive it to let it wash over you uh and let
enter into the samadei of breathing and um as an alternative
to the kind of unhealthy samadei of thinking where we get absorbed in the
world of thinking and for some of us the level of concentration we need to be
with the breathing is comparable or maybe the same uh as the absorption the
concentration we have for our thoughts there's a phenomenal kind of zeroing in
focus on thinking which many people have at some some point in their life and um
and we're learning what to do here is to kind of turn that around
so rather than a straining somebody straining focus on thinking
there can be now a wholehearted relaxed focus on the breathing
and in having insight around the changing nature of breathing
um to not be looking to have insight but uh
cultivating a receptivity cultivating a simplicity cultivating ing just an
allowing of experience to be seen uh carefully
and um and um until really the magic of of um
insight reveals itself to you that uh you can certainly sometimes see in
constancy and change but to the magic of it is when it it
really begins to um being absorbed with it or settled on it or it begins to be
compelling and you're right there with it in a delightful way and some of the
some of the qualities of samadei some of the johnic factors of joy and happiness
can arise with this receptive open entering into the world of change and
changing nature of uh the breathing
so uh the same thing can happen in daily life where we discover the the delight
the joy the benefit the refreshment of stepping out of our thoughts in daily
life and being here for the simplicity of our experience here and now the
richness of it it might be more boring than reading a great novel or watching a
great movie but there's the art of meditation is to teach us what that it's
wondrous to be alive to be present to be conscious and to be here connected in
the in a threedimensional way or multi-dimensional way with our present
moment reality rather than in the two dimensions or one dimensions of mental
preoccupation so um insight as a form of revelation
so thank you and um may the world of change moment by moment
be refreshing for you