welcome back i'm happy to be back again
continuing this series on freeing freeing the thinking mind
so in my own practice um over the years sometimes I felt the need to gladden my
mind and heart to inspire myself so during different periods of my practice
I begin the first several minutes of my meditation with some form of bringing
inspiration to my sitting um an example is something I used for
quite a while was imagining an honored guest coming over to my mind sometimes
the Daly Lama sometimes the Buddha how would I be if they were visiting my
mind you know I'd be really welcoming i'd clean up my environment i'd pay
really careful attention to everything they said so the idea is is that can we treat
ourselves as our honored guests and other times I begin my
sittings with you 5 10 minutes of loving kindness phrases a simple version of meta towards
myself and all beings may I be happy may I be
peaceful may I feel safe may I be free and then may all beings be happy
peaceful feel safe be free and so
um I I like still like to begin my sittings with just a little bit of uh a
warming of the heart in some way that touches me uh so let's begin this sitting with
another version of gladdening our hearts and minds
take a comfortable but alert posture gently closing the
eyes begin with taking a few deep breaths and with each
exhale settling into the body relaxing any obvious tension or
holding
Think settling into our seeds into the
earth or cushions
and then allowing the breath when you're ready to return to
normal getting a sense of the whole body
taking a minute to allow the attention to meander freely throughout the
body relaxing any obvious tensions
en close to the body you can begin to notice the
movements of the
breath finding the area where the breath feels like
home allowing your attention to rest [Music]
there settling into the rhythm of the
breath resting in this body in this
breath in your Home
now take a moment to connect with a wholesome quality that might particularly nourish
you at this time some form of
goodwill maybe kindness goodwill
love gratitude peace any form of goodwill that that
feels particularly nourishing to you
You might imagine that you're bringing this quality to the center of your
chest and in the center of your chest is a warm
sun and you can fill you can permeate that sun with the
goodwill whatever form you chose
and now allow the sun to radiate outward into the whole body maybe beyond your
body and as you breathe this sun can pulsate with each
breath with each exhale it radiates outward filled with kindness
goodwill love
peace a warm sun in the heart radiating outward
and whenever you'd like you can return to this simple
rhythm of breathing in and out this simple
opening to our lived experience however it
is not putting anything outside of our hearts
if the mind has drifted if it's become
lost gently welcome it back home
it's good to be [Music] home back to the rhythm of
breathing back to this body here and Now
[Music]
the thank you um so thinking is an essential part of
human experience and uh when we people begin
exploring the mind um they soon find out that the mind has a mind of its own and
then most of the thoughts we have um arise automatically just one after
another and it's easy to believe that that's just the way our mind is that all
we can do is observe it and sometime sometimes thoughts are
just really strange too you know i know um if you think about our dreams which
are kinds of thoughts you know they're um they can be quite unusual
but in addition to observing our experience um the Buddha taught us to take
responsibility for our thinking and that when our thinking is harmful to us to purposely change
it um an essential part of the eight-fold path is the sixth step or wise effort
a simple way of describing wise effort is that it's the effort to let go of any
unh wholesome thoughts and states and to cultivate the wholesome
and helpful ones um the unh wholesome thoughts and states
are thoughts that are based on ill will or greed and the helpful ones are the ones
that are based on goodwill generosity love compassion
so because we tend to we tend to teach that mindfulness is being with our
experience just as it is allowing things to be and nonreactive
awareness a letting go sometimes we might not give attention
to the other side of effort the part that stresses the cultivation of these
wholesome thoughts and states that support our wholesome thoughts and states
and this mindfulness practice needs both of them letting go of the unh wholesome and
the nurturing of the wholesome of course just by meditating
regularly and paying attention to the mind we're already cultivating the
wholesome mindfulness is wholesome concentration is wholesome we're
developing patience but there are times where can it can be
very skillful to consciously bring in something more directly like the qualities of the heart
I mentioned or ideas that inspire us like the Daly Lama
visiting we often don't even realize we're telling ourselves unhelpful
stories harmful ones
much of the time the most helpful practice is to drop the story and find
the feeling but at other times it might be more helpful to tell a better
story it's important for not to be a huge fabrication that denies her experience that denies her suffering but
just a different way to consider it
an example might be let's say we're out for a long hike and it's almost the end
of the hike but instead of returning home we just realized we took the wrong trail and we're now over an hour away
and it's really hot and we ran out of water and we're really thirsty and our
feet hurt you know we messed up we might feel angry with ourselves and we might
trudge along despondently hurting and miserable
but without denying the reality of the situation without denying the fact that
we're thirsty and our feet hurt and that we made a mistake what if we saw this as
a hero's journey with the hero trudging through the desert thirsty and hung and
hurting there would be a sense of dignity a sense of presence as we finish
our journey
or maybe we're meditating and the mind is filled with a recurring aversion over and over we try
going back to the body back to the breath and there it is again it's hindering my meditation we might
think but what if we look at it with the idea of what can I learn from this the question can bring a wholesome
curiosity into the process where we're no longer caught in the
aversion into trying to get rid of some thoughts trying to get rid of something but now we're learning about
it or sometimes you know when we're really caught in something like that you know it's like just recognizing oh this
is duka this is why I practice being aversive is
painful and we can bring compassion to our suffering i'm hurting may I be free
of suffering and that changes the story
completely in this
path um I'll start with a story instead um uh you know one of the scientists who
studied happiness Daniel Conorman uh spoke of two aspects of the
self the experiencing self who lives in the
present they feel the warmth of the room you know we notice the light lighting
we're listening to this talk in meditation is the felt sense of our experience the moments of our
lives this moment to moment sitting here listening feeling the body it's
experiencing self the other aspect is the remembering
self the remembering self keeps score it maintains the narrative of our lives boy
that was a great meditation the remembering self is a storyteller we what we actually keep of
our experiences is a story that was a great meditation doesn't come close to the 30 minutes we
just spent showing up and some of them may not have been
great some of them may have been great uh but that's just an evaluation the way
we remember it what tends to define a story are the
changes uh any major moments uh doors slammed in the middle
of the sitting you know and the endings you know maybe we're really calm
at the end of the sit in researching
happiness one of the things they found that is that there's a great discrepancy
between the quality of her momentto moment experience and her memory of
it that there can be significant difference between being happy in our lives minute by minute and being happy
about our lives or with our lives um and the story that that uh he
tells is about a man who was at the symphony and um you know he said for the
first 20 minutes the music was awesome it was just amazing he was deeply deeply
moved by it but near the end there was a horrible screeching
sound he said it just ruined the whole experience that was a terrible
symphony but it really didn't he still had those 20 wonderful minutes but it
was the memory that was affected and that's what he
kept that was the symphony that got ruined by this loud screeching sound
but his conclusion about the concert wasn't true and that's what we often do about
our lives you know we come up with conclusions with ideas with me and and
assume that that's reality and these stories that we
habitually tell ourselves they have a very deep effect on us
the experiencing self lives its life continuously those moments are lost
forever how many of the moments of or whole lives do we
remember and most of them are ignored by the remembering self that's most of our
life but the quality of how we spend these moments is essential but it isn't essential to
remembering self and it's a remembering self who makes the decisions in our
lives so for instance for our experiencing self we can ask how happy
are the moments of our lives that's what's important for the remembering self we
ask how satisfied are we when we think about our
lives they're very different what brought happiness to the
remembering self was achieving goals success
status what brought happiness to the experience self was spending time with people we like or activities we
enjoy when we think about life it's very different than how we
feel when we experience it
in mindfulness practice we bring the remembering self closer to our
experience that's part of what sati one of the meanings of sati to remember so we keep bringing that
remembering self very close to our experience so you can see clearly and
appreciate or momentto- moment experience and that helps decrease the
discrepancy the Buddha taught that um whatever a person frequently thinks
and pers upon becomes the inclination of one's mind
attention is like food when we repeat the harmful stories we feed them they
grow stronger so if we have a lot of judgmental thoughts it becomes easier to
be judgmental if we have a lot of insecure thoughts it becomes easier to be
insecure to feel insecure but if we have a lot of loving
thoughts it becomes easier to be loving so it's very helpful to shift the mind
away from unhelpful thinking if we're in the habit of
judging people negatively seeing what's wrong with them seeing what's wrong with people that's
what we tend to see the most but by purposely taking time to notice what we
like in someone it begins to weaken the judging habit and especially with ourselves we
can shift from focusing on we think is wrong with us what isn't good enough to noticing
all the good things within us our
intentions our stories are just stories they're not the full reality of
our lives and they're not even true many of them are not even true
but they shape our lives they influence our lives and as we bring mindfulness to the
stories we tell ourselves we can reshape the stories in the service of more and
more freedom of more and more happiness of more and more
love so may may all beings be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings feel safe and may all beings
everywhere be free thank you