so welcome to this meditation session and to
begin to assume a meditation posture that
is supportive for you to
feel embodied an embodied connection to here and
now it's not so much that you're going to use your
mind to direct yourself to be here now but
to start with the body and when you're careful with your
posture this is the beginning
of coming into the present with your body as if your body is the very
foundation the beginning the source for being here and now
and so being a little careful with your posture adjust making small
adjustments you might sway back and forth sideways and even forward and
back as a way of finding a
midpoint for your sitting bones your tailbone to hold your
weight if you're sitting upright if you're lying
down to adjust your to a little bit rock back and forth to adjust your shoulder
blades so they're a little bit more down your
back those sitting maybe can sit with a little straighter but bringing in the
spine between the shoulder
blades and there's an art to closing your
eyes where you do that quite consciously
carefully attending to the eyes as you close the
eyelids and allowing the eye eyesight the eyes to
rest and closing the eyelids is a practice of beginning to turn your
attention into the body so you can feel
sense the body more fully
closing the eyes and in a sense what we're
interested in is the subjective experience of the body if we live in our
heads in our thoughts where we direct our attention
to the body the body becomes the object
but the body is a field of sensations with the
eyes closed what we actually experience is this field of
sensations and they are just as much part of ourselves as a thought
is in some ways maybe it's more deeply who we are
because all the sensations of the body connect are connected to a
deep mental feel of understanding
responding feeling that in a certain way is the
foundation for how we understand ourselves so not to hold yourself apart from the
body be here in the body be your body for a few
minutes and as you
exhale soften the
body relaxing
the body and as the body softens and relaxes it can have a nice effect on the
mind maybe the mind begins to
relax feeling your body more fully as you inhale
releasing into your body as you
exhale and then centering yourself on your breathing in a certain way breathing is
at the nexus the crossroads of almost everything that
goes on in your body breathing adjusts and changes
depending on our emotions level of agitation or
energy and as we relax and settle and get calmer the breath slows down
the heartbeat slows
down stress hormones in our body
reduce centering yourself on your breathing
at the end of the exhale taking a moment to
pause don't breathe in right away pause just long
enough to feel where deep
inside is the urge the original urge to breathe in
and as soon as you feel that then allow yourself to
inhale starting from that place where the original urge the
first urges the deepest
urge and follow the inhale
calmly relaxedly accompany the whole length of
your
inhale and let there be a short pause at the top of the inhale
becoming quiet in your mind so you can better feel the urge to
exhale and then release the
exhale relax with the exhale
accompany the whole length of the
exhale and feeling the whole sensations of breathing in and breathing
out continuously allows the influence of
awareness the influence of feeling and sensing to
spread beyond the edges of breathing the sensations of breathing
letting the thinking mind
quiet during the transition from breathing out to breathing in
and for the thinking mind to become
quieter in the change from breathing in to out out to in
and then a small image metaphor
for being focus focusing on
breathing imagine you're going to thread a needle and you want to do so in the
first attempt so on the
inhale you line up the thread and the hole of the needle and you allow yourself to be very
very still and quiet so everything is quiet
still and then the
exhale it's like you focus on the exhale the sensations of
exhale very carefully and precisely as if you're threading the
needle but again letting the thinking mind become
quiet so you can be fully there for this
delicate and precise act of threading the exhale being right
there to the end
threading the eye of the
needle by sensing
feeling the whole length of breathing
out preparing to do it by feeling the whole length of the breathing
in quieting the thinking mind don't have to stop thinking but let
thinking become quieter calmer
where the eye of the needle that you're focused on is whatever is
pleasurable whatever pleasant and sensations there are related to
breathing maybe it's a generalized sense
of pleasure well-being goodness
sweetness around the edges of breathing
feeling that as you breathe
in and in its precise way pass through pass your awareness
through the eye of the needle of pleasure
well-being as you
exhale as if you're entering
Gently calmly with a
loving dedication
enter into your breathing the
pleasure well-being of
breathing and abide
there rest there over and over again gently with
each inhale and exhale enter and abide
whatever sensations of pleasure or joy
well-being are here as you
meditate enter into the subjective feeling of that
as if that's who you are more than your thoughts and
ideas and as you breathe feel it as you breathe
in enter it as you exhale rest in it
like a gentle massage entering and abiding
when you come to the end of your exhale pause for a brief
moment until you feel the urge to breathe in
give in to that urge and as you breathe
in imagine that your field of awareness spreads
outward through your body beyond your body out into this room
you're in place out across the lands
and that as you exhale you're abiding
resting in the middle of this wide field of
awareness breathing in and entering the whole
world with awareness with your imagination
with your sense of spatial s spatial
awareness entering a wide field that you breathe
in and abiding in it as you
exhale almost as a subjective field of
becoming awareness that embraces the whole world
and then letting
that wide field of
awareness become a channel for your good
will for your care your
kindness as if you're able to
nourish the whole world by the unseen ways in which our
kindness travels through our speech our act actions our
thoughts may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and if nothing else may this practice show
me how I can free all beings from my own desires aversions and
projections maybe we can start with that may all
beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this next talk on samadei
and we have now reached the point of uh immersive
samadei which the word in poli is janna j h a n
a and there is some idea that demology of janna might be uh connected to the
word for a flame and if that's the case then it's um the
um a candle flame which uh it's completely out of any kind of
wind and so the flame is completely still but it's luminous and
dynamic and um and so this luminosity and dynamism of samadei
um that comes when things are really completely still and so we're kind of
entering almost a kind of a stillness that has dynamism in
it and uh and uh so it's the fully full stillness is partly fully in the present
moment fully just here and to think of it as fully in the subjective experience
not the subjective interpretation of this experience not the subjective
opinion about the experience but the subjective sensations of it the feelings
the direct experience of it um so you
know you could watch someone uh go for a nice dip in a peaceful quiet
safe lake and you can just appreciate that uh they seem to be it's just a
luxuriating and the cool lake in a day when it's really hot or a warm lake day
when it's cold and um but it's you know it's out
there it's kind of objective it's very different to go into the lake oneself
and feel how subjectively ah this is good the subjective experience comes
with a feeling ah this is good now I'm here this is really feels nice um and so
the feeling of niceness of goodness is very subjective and it's very kind of
embodied it's not a thought that's not an opinion it's not a conclusion it's
something that's deeper than that and that's one of the reasons why to go into deep absorption the thinking mind gets
very very quiet eventually in deeper states of concentration thinking mind uh
especially the discurs the thinking mind seems to stop entirely or almost
entirely and but for to go into the first Janna what stops is discursive
thinking there's no more telling stories no more coming to conclusions and having
opinions there's no more thoughts about the past and the future these are all
story making mind the discursive mind and so that level of the mind which takes a lot of energy takes a lot of
abst ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab ab abstraction and ideas and bringing them together into kind of in a story
into a conversation that becomes quiet." And so what happens instead is there
might be still very simple thinking but it's thinking just about being here he
it's almost like we're telling ourselves oh good stay here oh this is good and
so at some point there's this transition then where the ordinary discursive mind
becomes quiet and sometimes that can go happen kind of quickly kind of suddenly
we feel something shifts or changes or turns upside down or settles in the mind
and now that mind is the thinking mind is no longer there the discursive mind and sometimes it's some inner
feeling that of being kind of arriving boom We're here and there's no doubt
about it then the mind doesn't want to wander off we've entered and abided in
the first Janna the the um uh this arrival here still is dynamic in some
ways and the the the uh important qualities that are present is something
called vaka and vichara which uh is we've talked about this earlier has to
do with um uh one way of understanding it is applied attention and sustained
attention entering and abiding applying like stay right here it's kind of like
the movement you do with uh kneading water into flour uh massaging
something it's kind of the the movement of um um of uh uh you know a bird that's
lifting itself up off the ground by gently maybe a very big bird flapping
its wings calmly and fully um powerfully and uh so it needs to do that flapping
it needs to lift and push down uh there is a kind of connecting and sustaining a
kind of um um you know placing yourself on the slide and then sliding down
placing yourself um in the waves and being carried by the wave of uh kind of
entering into and then abiding there so there is a kind of very gentle and if
there's any thinking involved um it's the thought of stay here go here be
here some people think that it's a very there's a this uh these two qualities uh
speak vara are a little bit more thoughtful
with thoughts that are a little bit more evaluating it's more like oh yeah here
this this is where to be ah this is good this feels nice it's kind of like we're
we're really getting close and into this experience of samadei and kind of
becoming without trying to attain anything get anything just a very gentle
kind of being present feeling it one analogy is like putting a taking a cloth
to polish a brass bowl a bronze bowl and
um and and then touching it and then uh gently kind
of rubbing it the ancient analogy would is that of a bee that um is kind of just
it's a comes to the edge of a flower and then walks around the top of the flower
looking for the nectar kind of getting to know it or just flying around it um
so connecting or being and circling around stay here enter and abide
and in particular what uh supports this is uh is the joy the the thrill the the
goodness the pleasure of the the pleasantness something that we enjoy
about the meditation itself and sometimes this initial Janna that
enjoyment the joy the the enjoyment the pleasure um it's kind of dynamic
It's it feels a little bit like the flame that is uh completely still but still there's a kind of you know that
inside the flame there's this wonderful movement that of um of the heat of
the and um and so there is this kind of of feeling of um of um
uh this uh applied and sustaining it's a
little bit like uh blowing on the flames sometimes um like a like a bellow or
you're blowing and and it flames gets stronger um then you stop blowing and it
gets quieter there's a kind of dynamic relationship between now staying there
with the experience staying with the pleasure and the pleasure kind of gets a
little bit stronger or fuller because we feel it we sense it we make room for
it and then as that happens um what's uh
very useful to do and maybe even important to do is to let that pleasure
let the joy to spread through your body some people in these janna uh are little
are tight or a little bit concentrating too hard there's a kind of narrowness of
focus kind of one pointedness of focus that the mind has gotten tight and uh
maybe even the the the eyes have gotten tight a little bit uh something's often
kind of contracted and then the the ability for the body to be unified and
whole and things flowing through it gets limited and it can feel like some of
this dynamism of the the good energy um is blocked then gets stuck someplace and
some people it's in the forehead there can be kind of a tightness and tingling
that's quite strong sometimes it's in the spine sometimes times it's other places and
the idea is to keep softening keep letting it spread just
gently don't make it it this is not shouldn't be a project um like so don't
don't be looking to do anything or make anything happen but there's a way there's a art to just kind of being with
it um entering and abiding connecting and sustaining and and this abiding this
resting is what spreads spreading it out spreading it
out it's um kind of maybe like um uh you
are blowing on a flame the flame gets larger and you feel the warmth spread further out into your body and that
warmth that spreads because it's get it's warm not because you're making it spread um and um so it's a it's a
wonderful world it's maybe a little bit unimaginable for people who don't get close into this state that um this is
what's going on but it feels really right it feel you can feel and as we
enter into this first Janna that the alternative of going coming coming out
of it and getting uh back involved with the usual preoccupations with the usual
uh kind of hindrances of the mind desire and aversion doubts anxieties that um is
uh that's not as as uh doesn't feel as healthy or as good or as satisfying or
as meaningful as really being here fully like now we've entered our life in a
complete there's a sense of vi vitality or aliveness or goodness or you know
this is satisfying so um
so we can't wish ourselves into this exactly we can't force ourselves into it
and um and but uh if we sit with sincerity then from time to time this is
what we begin dropping into and um and so the instructions here are not meant
that now you're able to actually do this but It may be hopefully you give you a
feeling for it a sense of it so that you it's kind of a little bit uh a sense of
showing you the landmarks of what's up ahead and and then if you come to that
place you see the landmark say oh now I know where I am this is a good thing and it may be easier to be here and there's
not a few people who drop into the first Janna and they get so excited they pop out they come out they say well this is
really great so um so stay
calm enter and abide in the deep calm and peace of uh of being immersed in
this here and now practice so thank you very much and
um we'll continue talking a little bit more about the first Janna for the rest of this
week thank you