So, good morning. Can I check the sound again? If it
changed anything, it's good. All right. Um,
and a good day for those who are joining through the the uh invisible
electrons and the web. So, I'm very happy to be here. Feel like
I haven't been here for a while. So it just really uh evoke a sense of a coming
home and so good to be with you all this morning. Um
so I brought a teaching today um that's inspired by um a suta. This is called
the simile of the elephant's footprint. Some of you may know this and those of
you who are interested in uh reading sutas might have come across this um
and and this particular simile elephant's footprint um this teaching is
deeply connected with the teachings of the four noble truth
um and I'll say more about this particular teaching
um and the for noble truth um is something that um taught across many
different Buddhist traditions quite well known
and uh the perspectives that I will be drawing um from uh for this teaching
will come from uh something that's inspired uh by this particular simile
and by this particular teaching and as well as um some of uh my ongoing
reflections. So the teachings of the four noble truth
uh I'll just uh briefly mention it and then we'll uh dive in a little more
and so uh this is um uh there are four
truth maybe enobbling truth and I personally feel a little shy
saying the word truth because it evokes many different associations with it that
may or may not be helpful. Um, but I like the sometimes the translation of it
um, saka and the pali word and and also means real, something that's real that
we can feel tangibly uh, in our own lives, our own experience.
And so the uh first thing that's real called the truth is the noble truth of
aduka. Um translation of aduka might be suffering stress and this is where the
challenges starts. Um often in our cure culture we don't
like it. So uh you know it's easy to skip over very quickly from the first
one. But it continues and that there is also
uh the origin or the cause of duca and
that is craving, grasping, clinging and there is the end of dooka
uh which is the craving the very craving can end grasping can end
as it gets better. sometimes they don't listen long enough to get to. And
there is a practice path that allows us to cultivate our own hearts and minds
that um allows the fruit of ending duka
to come forth. So it does get better as this teaching
unfolds. And this is a rather signific
significant teaching and that the insights into this four
noble truth is what liberated uh Gautma
for Goatma to become the Buddha. And so it's insights into this four things that
are real in our lives that brought liberation for the Buddha.
And and the tradition uh sometimes holds that
this is the first teaching the Buddha offered. And some of you may know this.
This is the uh the teachings on setting in motion the dharma wheel. And so the
teachings began to turn from the very first teaching that the Buddha offered
and it began to roll on and on and on all the way to today this point.
And so it's a first turning of the dharma wheel. And this is the teaching
the Buddha offered uh which is the four noble truth and the insights the 12
insights that arose through the practice.
And yet uh the teaching can often be overlooked and and then practitioners sometimes can
uh feel that I got it, you know, I know this and and um in uh kind of a culture
um maybe modern culture that uh we're not always so friendly to pain and
distress. And so we can be uh conditioned to quickly uh skip over the
teaching and it just kind of turning away from it.
And so our relationship to this teaching uh can be on the surface level.
And Ajang Suchito uh said this four noble truth teaching is an advanced
teaching. Um uh it calls forth our attention, our curiosity,
our interest in this. In the first turning of the dharma
wheel, the Buddha uh before he taught um he uh
contemplated and he thought, you know, like a who
should I teach first and um uh it occurred to him, you know,
he couldn't just go on the street and tell anyone, you know, look, this is what I'm going to teach you. And uh he
actually reflected he thought oh uh maybe it's this um uh he was
practicing with the five aesthetic um practitioners for a long time. his
aesthetic um companions uh who had practiced with him in various
ways in the spiritual training spiritual practice before uh the Buddha
uh went on his own uh and all the way uh led to his awakening.
So he thought well uh and this is a a a group of people
uh who may have little dusts in their eyes. You may have heard this phrase
and that maybe I should begin with them.
So he went about and found the five aesthetic practitioners, aesthetic
um companions and uh offered the teaching uh of the
four noble truth and the 12 insights to them.
And we're very fortunate uh in the course of unfolding uh this particular
teaching, one of the five got it. So this is uh venerable uh Kondania.
So uh the suta said he opened the dharma eyes. He saw it, he felt it and the
Buddha felt it. He got it. Wow. You know, so the Buddha got really fired up
and he said, "Wow, okay, someone will understand this."
And so he went on started teaching the remaining four and
he just kind of kept on going and right from there it launched his 40 plus years
of teaching career and I feel very fortunate you know and
this is the beginning of a forming of the SA beginning a forming of the long
teaching um uh uh endeavor that the Buddha uh
launched in and then we are the beneficiaries of this first turning
and sometimes I would imagine what if none of them got it what would happen
so I didn't let myself thinking about that too much but so here we are so I
feel very fortunate and And uh
what I was also struck uh is uh in the parini pana suta which is a
long suta that uh documented the last days um of the Buddha's life. Um
and here the Buddha again highlighted the teachings of the four
noble truth. Then I want to read uh a little from this. And then he said, "Practitioners,
due to not understanding and not penetrating the for noble truth,
both you and I have wondered and transmigrated
for such a very long time.
I feel so tender. Just listen to this.
He knew and he didn't say just you you and I you and I because we didn't
understood this for noble truth and really penetrated it
that we wandered and transmigrated for
such a long time. It really touches me to hear this.
And then notice also uh the words that are used and that is uh not
understanding and not penetrating it.
And so this is not this a kind of a surface level we just got it you know we read it somewhere and then we just okay
now I'm done with that. But it's penetrating it. Penetrating it have a
flavor of kind of there's a fullness of human life knowingness
not just in our intellect. And I've been reading uh this book um by
Philip Moffett called Dancing with Life um the four noble truth and then 12
insights teaching. And so uh here uh he says in this book
the for noble truth uh is not just a summary guideline a creed or a statement
of a philosophy but an actual practice of insight and a
realization in and of itself. It's a teaching on how to live wisely.
That's quite something. How to live wisely through this? Is this our something
real? It's in our lives.
So I am um personally affected um by
um my dharma teachers, my teachers and u maybe their teachers in how um they have
spent decades reflecting uh articulating practicing with this
teaching and I know for for Gil Gil Franto for probably decades in IMC See
um the first teaching of the new year is the four noble truth teaching. Some of
you may know this may be aware of this. Every year new year the first talk that
Gil Gil gives is around a for noble truth and it's never the same.
Um and uh uh Philip Muffet who wrote this
book, Dancing with Life, and he would tell us that he spent years to write
this book because he had to practice with it. He had to reflect it, contemplate it um a
lot and it's ongoing process to this day.
And so uh for me, you know, I dedicated my life this year around the for noble
truth. So you're kind of receiving a little bit of vibe through my own
reflection and contemplation and practicing with it. And I have to
say confess that I haven't gone very far in this whole process. I feel like I'm
kind of repeatedly going from um the basics
and I feel like I'm not in a big rush and I really enjoy the process of it
and so uh today I hope and this also evokes some curiosity in you.
So um I want to go back to the simile of the elephant footprint.
And so this is suta the teaching was offered by the Buddha's great disciple
one of the chief disciples Sar Puta and he offered a very detailed
elaboration of the four noble truth and he started this with a very powerful
simile. So this is what it says. The footprints of all creatures that
walk can fit inside an elephant's footprint.
So an elephant's footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same
way, all skillful or wholesome qualities
are included in the four noble truths.
And for me often in this similes I like to just stop kind of imagining a little
bit what what does it feel like? What does what what evokes in me? And so I
paused and just thought a little bit, you know, about all the animals I can think of that walk
how big their footprints are. And I realized this feels right. You know the
elephant footprint is probably the biggest that can hold hold it all. And
so in this way the four noble truth teaching has a flavor of encompassing.
It's all encompassing in some way. And sometimes you may hear uh the
teachers would say like you know um uh the Buddhist teachings can fit all fit
in the for noble truth teaching and the Buddha taught uh duka and voduka
and and kind of that's the short hand but this particular statement uh is a
little different uh from that particular inter uh uh um kind of uh pointing
and here Saruta said this that is very specific and he said all wholesome
qualities are included in the for noble truth. The poly term is a cusola sometimes also
translated as skillful qualities. So all skillful wholesome qualities are
included here. That's very specific
and it's uh for me it's intriguing. It's re intriguing. It caught my
attention when I read this and um it's somewhat
ironic uh because often uh our associations
with the for noble truth teaching is a little bit kind of
grim a little bit like ah we had to kind of grind our teeth or something. But here
it says all wholesome qualities are here are included in this.
I just loved it. You know that caught my attention to kind of keep going. What is
he pointing to? And uh I thought that's a fantastic way
and wonderful way to begin this teaching. So how do we understand this?
And Saruta is uh quite an uh kind of amazing teacher. And so he unpacked this
uh in a great detail uh for the rest of the suta.
And I also say a little bit about Sar Puta maybe that help uh us understand
how he was unpacking this teaching. uh he's a quite a unique teacher and
unique practitioner. He has a very unique mind and quite detail oriented and uh has a
um um well maybe I'll just read this that uh Ajang Sugato who commented on the
Suta speak about spoke about Assari Puta's quality and his contribution in
teaching the dharma at the times of the Buddha and maybe all the way down to today. So he said this suta is a master
class on the methods employed by the Buddha's greatest student Sar Puta.
He begins with the four noble truth then proceeds to unpack them systematically
leading to a lengthy analysis of the four elements.
But the unpacking takes a surprising directions as the Sariputa draws on
unexpected layers of the dharma to illustrate a familiar teaching in new
ways. All the while he conveys warmth and compassion
illustrating in his manner of teaching the connection that is also the topic of
the teaching. Sar Puta's emphasis on forable truth is
shown elsewhere as well where he's said to focus on teaching new
students as far as a stream entry. The current suta illustrate how he did
this carefully explaining uh fundamental
concepts and showing their realworld impacts while offering pragmatic and
reassuring uh advice along the way. He introduces
all the major wisdom teachings demonstrating exactly how they fit into the four noble
truth. That's quite some skill, isn't it?
And I really appreciate the Saruta quite a lot. And he seems to have a capacity to kind
of uh in a way flip the ladder down all the way to the ground. So we can kind of
go this step by step to kind of understand the teachings.
And so sometimes um his teachings are uh not necessarily what uh exactly the same
as the Buddhas. But the Buddha often appraised to him um because he has this kind of capa
capacity to allow people to know and uh maybe sometimes the teachings are
offered as kind of a dropping breadcrumbs
but you can't quite feel the whole thing and then you know and then the Sar Buddha has this capacity to really let
you see the see the whole thing in the whole picture and then also know the
details in some way. So how did he unfold this?
So he started with the overarching teaching uh the noble truth of
suffering, the origin of the suffering, the sessation of the suffering and the
practice that leads to the sessation of the suffering. But then he didn't just stop there. He
went deeper. Um
and he drilled down um by teasing apart this higher level uh
concepts, ideas into a more more granular and uh immediately
felt kind of experience. So for example, he first explained kind of teased apart
what does it mean by duka? what is it? You know, so he kind of unpacked that
with a list. You know, there's illness, aging, death, and there is association
with the things that we don't like, we don't want, and not getting what we really liked. And so there is all this
unpacking he was doing. So we can begin to relate to this for ourselves.
Yeah, that's right. That's right. But again, he didn't stop right there
because that is a still at the conceptual level that we're understanding.
And so she he unpacked all the way to the immediacy of the felt sense of
experience uh which the teachings sometimes pointed to as the element.
The elemental nature of our experience that this embodied experience
has the earth element and our bones, our teeth that is solid,
firm, steady and there are uh water element that the
fluidity of it and so it's dropping down to the immediate felt sense experience.
And so you can see that that the the ladders got flipped down, you know. So
now he's talking about this duka not at
our thinking level but it's our experiential level that the experience
is like this. Sometimes is pleasant, sometimes it's
unpleasant. And so for me sitting here, I have a
fair amount of tightness and tension around my hip. And
then there's some pain that's been there for a while. And that's immediate
here. Oh, this is how it feels like.
And for me uh this is rather gamechanging that we are uh beginning to uh deepen in
this process of a penetration penetrating
and um Saruta invited us to drop in our experience here and now
and this is where the wholesome qualities begin to emerge.
And so in this process it almost feel like uh as Puta was taking the students
on a meditative journey. Now you're feeling and sensing in your immediate
experience and several effects began to emerge in
this process and this is my own reflection. I may be
departing a little bit from the suta that the first one I wanted to point out
um the first wholesome qualities that many of us might begin to feel as we
drop into the immediacy of our experience is that we are in a raw
direct relationship with our lives. The vibrations in the body, the flow of
the breath, the tinkling sensations, the vibrations of the sounds.
What you're feeling is a kind of aliveness.
Wow. Sometimes I have this feeling. It's like
I'm in this really alive feeling with my
own life. And just now as we were sitting
that was the sound of the fan air conditioning and sound of the people
moving sound of the breath and the inner sound at this this kind of
soundsscape. It just feels like the the vibratory feeling of life
and that's enlivening. I don't even know what all all the words
that we might describe, but there is a certain kind of wholesome quality when
we're in the immediacy of our experience. And what it can contrast is our ongoing
uh movements of wanting, not wanting, pushing away that actually is deadening.
we can begin to know this for ourselves. So the first wholesome quality that the
Sar Puta is pointing out in my own experience is when we're dropping in in
this experience and instead of trying to push away, deny, avoid all the pain we
have and then trying to get on to the things that we really want.
There is aliveness that comes forth
in maybe in the midst of the difficulties in the midst of the pain
there can be aliveness and it's meaningful. It may not be a meaning that you even
know what the words to say about it but you can feel and this is a meaningful
meaningful way of relating to our lives. And then the second quality
is as we began to stay with this experience just as it is in this raw
form in this a more direct form. And what Sar Puta was pointing out was
that more and more clarity began to emerge.
We can begin to see how the experience of pleasant and unpleasant
is different from our reactivity to the pleasant or the unpleasant.
They're not the same thing. Sometimes when we're not seeing this clearly, they just kind of lumped together as a jumbo
or like it's automatic. It's not good. But what we can see is oh pleasant is
just a pleasant and our judgment of whether this is good
or bad is another thing is a separate thing. They don't have to automatically
connect and our identification with it is yet
another thing. You know, maybe someone criticized you.
Actually, I was criticized last week or two and it was unpleasant.
And I I won't say it's pleasant, it's unpleasant.
But our often the knee-jerking reaction of I need to defend myself would just
come up, right? But in that moment, fortunately, I did not have um I wasn't
present for it. I just let myself feel the unpleasant and that wasn't a kind of this
reactivity coming up. And what allowed for me is to notice,
oh, there is a more to this criticis criticism than what it sounds like.
It was very intuitive in my system. I didn't even know what it was, you know? I just felt like, "Oh, there's more to
this." And so I paused. I didn't respond. I didn't react. And I
just kind of let it go. There was a space for it.
and and a while later, maybe hours later, I discovered
and the person was going through some real challenging diagnosis.
And so this capacity to be able to drop in this um felt sense experiential way
gives us opportunity to tease this apart. So here is something ouch you
know it's a dooka and here is the reactivity and in this reactivity of judging trying
to fix this we actually have choice if we're not flowing with our reactivity
and we can say oh I can let this go I don't need to flow with my judgment
that I am a a failure that's just extra. So that's another um
quality of a wholesome quality that can flow from this.
And then yet another wholesome quality can emerge
in this process. And that is as we begin
to notice that more and more that there is this choice in us that can let go of
the grasping, the cleaning, the judging, the fixing.
There is actually more freedom. There is more peace and a harmony that's
available in us. And so this is being pointed to as the
third noble truth. that possibility of oh if there is no continual feeling fueling
this wanting mind there can be moments of harmony peace
with what I'm experiencing whether it's experiencing in our own
hearts or what we feel in the surroundings that we're interacting with.
And so that also becomes available to us.
And and we will not or we will also notice in
this process is um
we lose our mindfulness and uh it's not automatic
that we are able to simply somehow stay with our experience in this direct immediate
way and you know losing to our stories, our beliefs and
and uh we began to notice, oh, this heart and mind is to be
cultivated. And so yet another wholesome quality
that can emerge which is being pointed to as the fourth noble truth is we give
ourselves over to the practice. We offer ourselves to practice
sincerely.
And so um so in this way um what is
being pointed to uh in this four noble truth each of each of the four noble
truth began to um uh manifest themselves as wholesome
qualities. wholesome quality of being with our
experience as they are including uh the pain and the pleasure, difficulties,
challenges and then that's a wholesome quality and
then pointed to as the first noble truth and the wholesome quality of clarifying
our lived experience the first arrow versus the second arrow you know the
reaction reactivities. And so we can begin to clarify this in ourselves
and the wholesome quality of possibility of having freedom and ease
that's available to us when we're letting go of our claiming existing
demanding and wholesome quality of giving
ourselves to the sincere practice.
sometimes and I know some people would ask you know um
if things ever get easier through the practice.
I like that question and I I I reflected about that question a lot.
You know, on one level, the conditions of our lives are often
not under our control.
It's hard to say how things might be getting easier or hard,
whether it's because of broader environmental were in or because
individual situations. Yeah, in my household there was a
broader household there was a car accident.
Not easy, very difficult, very difficult for many people involved.
Um but this practice through this practice what we're
learning is to cultivate a kind of a capacity that allow us to relate to our
lives and our life events, life situations with more and more or or in more and
more wholesome ways that allow us to have a sense of ease, a
sense of a harmony in the midst of a difficulties.
And so in that way, whether you call it easier or better, I
don't know. But there is a possibility. There is a
possibility. And this kind of a wholesome orientation
is more and more independent of the life situations or the conditions that we're
in. And this is what this teaching is pointing to
that how we relate to our lives
is the empowerment that each of us has.
And so as uh all of us connect to this teaching in some way maybe in very
moderate way you know we just we just heard this you just have us a little sense of it.
Um my invitation is um to know what is
called forth from this teaching is to let the teaching come alive.
So it's real. We can have a real felt sense of it
and let that guide us in how we relate to our lives.
So, thank you. Thank you everyone for your attention.
Um,
we only have a few minutes. Maybe just, you know, a short comment or
um a question. I'm happy to stay over and after and uh respond in any way that
I can. Anyone like to share a comment or share your own reflection or a question?
Just a short one before we end.
Um yeah, thanks for the talk. I I think uh one of the things I'm learning and
maybe you can speak to it is that I don't actually want I'm not actually interested in freedom
as much as wanting what I want and then the path is like getting me to be more
peaceful or more this or more that. Is that something that you've
encountered yourself this like I don't actually want to be free, I want to be happy kind of thing.
Yeah. So that's good. I don't know what all the words might be, you know. And so, uh,
it might be worthwhile, uh, to turn that question around to see if this is what,
uh, if this is my aspiration, um,
how am I relating to this aspiration? How does it manifest for me right now?
if that's what's uh aspiring for me. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you. Yeah. Thank you.
If there's another short one or a short comment, there's one right
here. Right here. Yeah.
I just I really appreciated the piece about pleasant and unpleasant and
how we think about that. Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah. We have a lot of
associations about pleasant, unpleasant, what can mean to us. So this is a a real
worthy uh process in our practice is to begin
to tease that apart. kind of like what Sar Puta is pointing to. It's like, oh,
there is a pleasant, there's unpleasant. How do we associate with this? You know,
it's like immediately I don't like this. I would rather it go away
or um I'm fearful, you know. So, so we can
begin to tease apart all of this. So, it's great. Thank you. Yeah.
So maybe we'll end uh with a dedication of marriage together and I really um
feel grateful for us to uh have this opportunity to practice together and to
learn the dharma practice um and to learn the dharma teachings together.
Um I still feel that resonance of this first turning of the dharma wheel kind
of we're in this long stream and then so um may whatever benefits that arose out
of our own practice and our own learning may it ripple out
in all directions. So all the beings everywhere may they be
benefited in some way. Maybe it's a kind of ease of the heart,
clarity of the mind or healthy vital bodies.
May they all be happy. May they all be peaceful.
And may we all everyone everywhere
experiencing liberating wisdom and compassion in our own hearts and minds
and everywhere for all beings. Thank you. Thank you everyone.