Good morning friends or good day friends. Just want to do a sound check to see if
you're able to hear me. Okay, maybe I'll pay attention to the chat box.
Let me know if you can hear me.
All righty. Thank you. Thank you for those who are giving me thumbs up. Sounds good.
Yeah, I'm happy to be here. Just seeing uh some of the familiar names and the
ones that I don't know. So, welcome. Welcome everyone. to the 7 a.m.
King IMC. So, I'm happy to be here.
So, I'll dive in. And this week what I brought with me is
uh a set of reflections around uh water related simileies.
And so I feel like I've been swimming in that. And so I'm going to um bring that
with me and channel it uh in this 7 a.m. meditations and uh dharma reflections.
And so uh this the first uh first session
uh in our meditation I'd like to invite everyone
uh to imagine you're stepping into the
flow of our moments by moment of life
and to really feel and sense the aliveness from within our experience.
And I'm going to start uh with a poem. And this is a poem by David White. So
see if you can find the poetry here.
Maybe let yourself settle into a meditative a posture as you receive this
words. um poetry and
uh image images often express things that may be hard to
express in words. So this is a poem called enough.
This few words are enough. If not this words, this breath,
if not this breath, this sitting here,
this opening to life we have refused again and again until now.
until now.
With that stepping into the flow
of life in this moment right now,
right here,
gently softly.
Open yourself to this life. Sitting,
lying down, whatever the posture you're in,
stepping inside. Feeling
and sensing the sensations,
the flow of the breath
just as it is.
becoming available to the lived
moments here and now.
It can feel tender.
There may be a kind of stir in the heart.
A life
This opening to life feels like this.
Your cells in the body may respond [Music]
to this.
The heart may respond to this.
In this last couple of minutes of the meditation together,
as you step into the flow of your own life,
touching aliveness from within.
Allow this opening to expand.
Maybe there is a way that you can meet all life
with openness. Care
and respect.
And may this eating life in this tender open way
bring nourishment. harmony
and a peace to all life,
all forms of life.
May all beings know life deeply
and may all beings be free.
[Music]
So good morning and good day everyone.
And so this week I'd like to share some reflections
um based on a uh
polycanon suta. Um
oh I'm just noticing people can't hear me. And let me let me uh check to see uh
if uh you're able to hear me now as I'm speaking.
I'm just going to give a moment to make sure the sound is okay.
If someone can type in in the chat box, that'll be helpful.
Okay. All right. Thank you. I can see it coming through. So, all right. Then I
will continue. So um this week and I brought a
polycanon simile uh which is related to water.
It's a very simple and maybe very well-known simile.
And for me um uh the simileies often
have a very powerful uh symbolic kind of a meaning and
they're quite rich. And so the similes often are very layered and have multiple
dimensions kind of multi-dimensional quality to it.
And and I wanted to uh read uh something from an author Robert Johnson uh who
wrote this uh in relationship to symbolic language that people use and
and he said speech is literal and rational and it cannot easily contain
the depth of the mystery. For that we need symbols and a symbolic language.
I resonate with that a lot. I feel that sometimes
uh maybe often um Buddha is trying to convey something that is hard to
describe using words. And so so often he resort to using
symbolic simileies, symbolic rich simileies. And so in this way different
aspects of the simile can point to something that's deeper than the literal
meaning of the words and they can allow us to kind of stay with what is being
pointed to uh in a more engaged way. engaging with the body, with our uh
emotions, with our uh uh psyche or psychological uh aspect of being.
And so it can uh connect with a deeper part of ourselves. And so I hope uh this
uh this form of a symbolic exploration can be useful and maybe evocative in
some way. So this suta that I'm going to bring in for this week for us to explore is uh
called crossing the flood. Some of you may have heard this and this is the
first suta, a very short suta from Samuta Nikaya.
And uh the suta is a short uh captures a
short conversation between uh a glorious deity. That's it.
a glorious deity came to visit the Buddha in the middle of the night and
asked the Buddha a question and the Buddha responded um to the
question. So I found it quite interesting you know why deity I don't feel like I know and
but it's interesting and so this is kind of how I enjoy reading the sutas I don't
feel like I always need to know the answers um but they're curious
and so I like to read this uh and even more curious is uh the question and
answer. So this is the part I'm going to read to you
uh which is the question and answer between the two and there are only four
lines here. There is a lot in the four lines. So here it is.
How dear sir did you cross the flood? The deity asked.
By not halting, friend, and by not straining, I cross the flood.
But how is it, dear sir, that by not halting and by not straining, you cross
the flood? The Buddha answered, "When I came to a
standstill, friend, then I sank. But when I struggled then I got swept
away. It is in this way friend that by not halting and by not straining I cross
the flood. And so it's very short conversation
a lot details to unpack. So I'm going to start very slowly with
the susuta in this week. I'd like to first talk about this symbol
of a flood uh oga that's the poly term
in poly canon suta uh uh there multiple times and maybe many times the symbol of
a flood is being used and they're often representing
powerful forces that cause stress.
suffering and I'm aware uh the power of the flood
in nature and I'm aware of what's happened recently
uh in the United States, the devastating power of a flood. It can cause a lot of
pain for so many people and I feel a kind of heartbreak just to
name it right now. And in the times of the Buddha, uh,
sometimes he stayed in the places that tend to experience a flooding.
And so he knew the destructing power force of a flooding.
But in his teachings, he has a specific appointing of this
force of um that we observe
uh in human lives. And he um equated flood with the forces
of greed, hatred, delusion, the end endless greed.
One of the sutas he said greed I say is
the great flood. The antless wanting antless pushing away
not wanting aversion. Elsewhere
uh flood is uh uh interpreed
with the flood of sensual desire. Endless wanting for comfort.
Uh pushing away uncomfort and endless taking birth in
identification with the things. endless taking birth in uh you know I am
this way I am not that way into this kind of solving
and then uh the flood of wrong perspectives mistaken perspectives
can have um challenging can cause a lot of difficulties for ourselves and for
others and then flood of ignorance not seeing and not seeing actually
causes flood.
And so those are some of the um meanings of being pointed to by the Buddha. And
for me, I often ask myself to just pause, kind of reflect for a moment this
word flood, what comes to your mind?
You know, for me, uh, the first sense of it is the kind of overwhelming
amount of water, uh, that, um, a kind of, um, uh, the
normal river channels or normal water flows can't handle.
Like our normal life flow um has its ups and downs you know has its pleasant
unpleasant has its uh grief and joy and so there
that's part of the being human and sometimes the teacher will call this uh
the a realm of opposites and that's normal part of life flow
that's natural being human being like that. And yet
when and there is um unpleasant our uh allergic reactivities to this
uh that we don't want this, we want to push away can often overwhelm us.
And so this overwhelming amount of water can come forth and they overwhelm us and
they cause more dooka, more suffering
and they are dangerous and they can cause stress and dooka uh
in small ways in our own minds and heart and they can have effect all around us
and maybe even in a bigger uh um space they can have a broader
force for humanity
and some examples of this uh kind of flooding you know the activity sometimes
I like to think of this uh not as a noun but as a verb flooding being flooded or
adject adjectives we may experience experience loss. I
think all of us uh will have experiences of loss
and they are unpleasant and they may be even painful. Physical capacities,
mental capacities or loss of loved ones or a job. They are unpleasant.
But our our um resistance to it or our uh uh immediate
reactivity to fix or the uh reactive
um emotional forces of a fear, anger, resentment
can lead us um into actions and speech at mental
activities. uh that began to flood ourselves and others. Maybe we start blaming
ourselves. Uh we think things should not be like this. Maybe we start blaming
others. You know that we we can see this kind of effect in ourselves and in
others. And so through the practice
we can learn uh gradually to begin to be present for this experiences
and pause in the moment of experiencing loss which is a normal flow of being
human. we do experience loss
and instead of collapsing or resorting to reactive forces
flooding our minds and hearts we may be able to ask ourselves
what's the bigger perspective here how might I relate to this loss
that how How do I relate to experience
without being flooded by the regular um
reactivity reactive forces? It doesn't mean that immediately we'll
be able to do this, but coming in contact with this,
maybe beginning to open ourselves up into some possibilities.
What can we learn from this experience?
So today um my invitation is maybe to practice
noticing in your experience. Um, are there uh times that you can
begin to differentiate um the normal life flow moments your
experience and the reactive forces that tend to uh
uh cause cause additional layers of aduka. And so
noticing if there are choices that becomes available to us that we can
actually choose not to be flooded.
And so thank you for your attention and may this exploration be fruitful
uh for you and for the people that we all encounter. And we'll continue uh in this
exploration uh in a symbolic way uh in the rest of the week. And so thank you everyone.