so uh so welcome folks Nice to
uh see your uh see your names Yeah a lot of
uh a lot of uh old dharma
connections for the years
Um okay Not sure what uh see what how we
meditate but we're going to
meditate Um yeah So
finding finding your way into uh your posture
And taking a few deeper breaths Much deeper
like uh nectar settling to uh the bottom of a glass of juice Let's take that on said
A million ways to suffer but only one way to
be free
So we marshall our
uh courage to stop trying to solve our life
And in that gesture of u renouncing the impulse to solve our
life it's the uh implicit understanding of our death
That won't get solved either
And the poignency of
that helps us be free now
helps us surrender
Just paying attention to whatever is restful in
you The settleness of your
body The silence You might listen to the
blankness behind your closed
eyes the soothing that is uh Buddha Dharma Sana
Go We attune to what's restful Rest
We uh relax and let go so that we can
receive our breathing more
fully Noticing the beginning and the ending of the inhalation
followed very quickly by the beginning of the exhalation and the end of the
exhalation And sometimes people find it useful to place the attention elsewhere maybe
the hands or feet the bottom of the exhale
And so there are five distinct points the cycle of breath
We put down our redemptive
hopes and
worry Clinging cannot do what your heart wants most
We can't exactly will our way to letting go will our
way to surrender
We uh relax and soften widen
Amen Develop uh conditions that uh
make letting go feel more
natural
develop the the confidence that we don't
need to keep tabs on our
life at all times
At some point the doingness of attention wants to bow down to the
effortlessness of awareness
that we've entrained enough
stability somehow under awareness But
awareness is not manufactured in the
house of
self And so we take our cues from
that which is patently not me
[Music]
Okay good to uh sit with you
Um so it was uh I think humor grieving awe
surrender today uh courage I've been in a lot of videos
over the course of my dharma life mindfulness before this uh you know
doing stuff with IMC before co you know in videos um with
mindful schools for some years with uh Megan Cowan Chris
McKenna and um and those made their way to a lot of
people and um and so sometimes people have seen me
in videos a lot but never in person And one of the most common things people say
when they see me in person is I thought you were
shorter I find very endearing I thought you were
shorter I'm not saying courage is this correlated with height or something but
I do kind of hear it as like I thought you were maybe even less courageous and
uh talking about courage today Teachers speak about courageous
effort but not often about courage And I don't consider myself temperamentally
speaking a courageous person Uh I've not taught about it I
don't feel like I know quite enough about it
uh um temperamentally kind of risk averse
and uh harm avoidant meaning I've been very
careful with my body and mind and careful with the bodies and minds of
others Um but I'm trying to
um take stock of the ways that fear manifest in my
life and the opportunities for uh for courage
So dharma talks they're always partially addressed to uh the
speaker and there's a kind of disorientation in courage a sense that
you must do something and know yourself in a different way
sense that you cannot know exactly how your heart will be at the threshold of a
courageous gesture that you may discover something
new about yourself It's intimidating What kind of pain or
disorientation might this bring if I take this step off this ledge
now all along the way there's um a fair amount of courage needed in the path you
know just to start the path m sometimes it's just desperation that might be it
but often mixed in with that is something like courage
aspiration you know entails some measure of courage because we don't know what we're trading in what we're
heading Um the path is about uh remembering what
we've always loved but it's also about learning to love new things And to love something new entails
a measure of letting go of something old and that takes some faith some
courage Um Ayakma um she said on the spiritual path we do
have to try something new In fact the spiritual path takes quite a lot of
courage because it means chucking the old without knowing what the new one is
really like If we don't have that courage we can't go on such a
path because um fear is such a pervasive
experience Uh courage is needed at various points along the
spiritual path
Um yeah I have a lot of respect for fear how pervasive it is And generally
we say on this path that ignorance is the wellspring of suffering But fear strikes me as even more
primal more closely linked with clinging
more potential to and it's not to demonize fear you know it's you know I
think probably wise to be afraid of extremely dangerous
things but um but the kind of pervasiveness of fear
in the mind can distort cognition and feeling in
profound ways and threat sensitivity and fear
It's so deeply woven into our brain I I often cite the uh brain scientist um K
Thai She says something like fear has an authoritarian command over the rest of
the brain you know And so um when the dharma teacher
says you know uh casually uh just let
go some part of us you know really is really skeptical about
that you know really skeptical because clinging is what feels like maintains
our safety Thinking is what feels safe Thinking might be painful but not
thinking that's a lot worse Worrying worrying for all the pain
involved in it feels like the best option we have given a
niche and fear
um disrupts the process of letting go We need courage What's on the other side of
this surrender of this softening of this letting go we need courage to
see and just we we study fear and worry
anxiety those are all a little bit different but um we study this at the
kind of micro level How does fear constellate in the mind
how does it make experience more dense how does it necessitate
clinging how does it disrupt attention fear disrupts samadei The gathering and
unification of our attention doesn't feel safe to take our eyes off threat even for a
moment So we marshall
courage takes courage to open you know to the truth of duka you know that there
is suffering truth of change that we talk about it so casually
but it's really not for the faint of heart Yeah you know this when something
big shifts when the ground becomes groundless when the line as Michelle
McDonald says between everything being okay everything not being okay the
thinness of that line is
realized Takes courage to open to this takes courage to open to ourselves Uh
you know man Kant um described like the sincere intention to be honest towards
oneself That's the heart of spiritual practice and self-discovery is a kind of
courageous act you know
and if we sit retreat um there are times
deep in retreat deep into the silence when our brain feels um highly
plastic you know no friction in
it And that makes um bliss and love and peace much more
accessible but it also opens the door to states of terror
too And sometimes it's kind of a nameless dread You know there's no
object of the fear Sometimes the fear is fear of um bodily dissolution
or annihilation or uh you know total
loss of control and uh it's really hard not to
be in problemsolving mode when the terror runs deep you know
And sometimes it's right to just problem solve our way out of it It's
fine But sometimes we just wait the uh the IMC teacher May uh
Elliot um said uh when you get lost in the woods you know like the impulse is
to go looking for help to go you know find someone So you know but um she said
uh the advice actually is to stay still let the help find
you And um yeah the way she said that touched me
you know to let the hope find you And
uh so in in cataloging kind of the fear
and courage on the path strikes me that um that fear has made my life smaller
than it might have been And
um there's a difference between sensitivity to
suffering versus fear of suffering Now I've always been ever ever
since I was a kid you know very sensitive to suffering in myself and others And generally speaking that's
been a gift that I've been careful and tried to lead a life that
does not trespass on the hearts of others um that's sensitive to their suffering
to my own but I'm recognizing that I'm I'm
more afraid of suffering than I realized And there's a way in which
Buddhism can be marshaled as a a means
of controlling suffering you
know and we never say it that way We talk about being free from suffering
letting go all these beautiful things I don't walk those back But there's another sense in which maybe maybe
um the path has been about controlling my
suffering And we don't say it that way but maybe that's how my fear construed
it And fear involves the need to control and the
aversion to um the sense of being out of
control And developing courage likely means we must relinquish the need to
control the willingness to experience helplessness the willingness to let help
find us
And yesterday I was with a group of um SA IMC SA members and teachers and um
was just inspired by um their presence and and the phrase that I was sort of
felt like I was like attuning to each the kind of courage of each person You
know everybody has their own species of goodness their own species of
courage And the phrase that came up you know which is not a phrase it doesn't
sound didn't sound like my mind you know but the phrase that came up in me was
don't die a coward You know that's not language I use It sounds
very Marshall And yet there it was
St Aquinus said um courage is a condition of each and
every virtue Courage is a condition of each and every virtue Everything that's good
depends in some ways on courage We can see this in the parameies the
perfections dhana renunciation truthfulness aditana you
know um resolution compassion meeting suffering grieving courage courage It's
needed It's needed And I've been asking myself and
I'll ask you um what what does your love look like
when it's less afraid
it's a time for moral
bravery Okay Offer that for your consideration
Uh thank you Uh thank you all Thank you for having me and um I appreciate the
uh um sweetness of this uh morning crew and
the sa and um um uh Gil will uh be back uh Monday Keep
going Okay folks You uh take good care See you uh somewhere on the Dharma
campus