okay folks so uh so welcome
um H nice to um see a lot of uh yeah a lot of
familiar names I um yeah happy to to be
practicing together so um yeah let find uh find our posture
whatever that is for
just let the uh reality of goodness soothe you soothe your heart
it's almost unimaginable how much
ordinary goodness there is
and we here together try to take that ordinary goodness as a kind of object let
it motivate our um our action consolidate our love
commitment resolution
Adan e
usually we direct our attention to our breathing
to body to feeling s
s maybe we just U let uh goodness
soothe any uh agitation worry fear and then see what's left in the
mind where the attention goes
e
e e
can feel like meditation puts pressure on
oursel to perform some intenal intentional
ritual to be good to not get lost in thought
to d da da da da uh it's not that meditation puts
pressure on the self it's this self puts a kind of pressure on
awareness e
ego dramatizes everything Maybe
makes um life feel dramatic melodramatic
we just relax surrender up the sense of self to awareness
and meditation starts to do
itself
e
e e
we must um forgive our minds a very deep level
and through that process of forgiveness we come
to trust our mind trust awareness
trust love e
the goodness of your mind doesn't depend on
you
e
e e
the more we cling the more World there
is as we cling the less World less
World a more
alive just take our cues from the
silence
for
e
e e
whatever can be enjoyed enjoyed in the uh the field of
your experience really enjoy
it if it feels overshadowed by
other things just enjoy what can be
enjoyed
e
e e
okay so uh TS um TS Elliot's poem Ash
Wednesday um often not a scholar I don't know what
I'm talking about but apparently often read as a a kind of conversion poem is
conversion to uh angli anglicism and
um and um yeah I think from Unitarianism to
anglicanism so begins this way uh because I do not hope to turn
again because I do not hope because I do not hope to turn Desiring this man's
gift and that man's scope I no longer strive to strive
towards such things why should the Aged Eagle stretch
its wings why should I mourn the vanished
power of the usual rain
and twice in that um that that poem he uses the phrase
that's been quoted quite often in Dharma talks uh teach us to Care and not to
care teach us to sit still this part doesn't get quoted so
much but the very next line is pray pray for us sinners now and at the hour of
our death pray for us now and at the hour of our
death and generally I've uh I've understood that teach us to Care and not
to qu care in a sequential way there are moments of care but then there are other
moments when care is absent
and I've described a kind of dialectic of love and rest love and rest the
urgency of of love
and yet we know that even love beautiful love fatigues the
heart and so we must find ways of resting not closing the heart but
resting and I've been preoccupied in trying to work out
my own own kind of um life and what kind of
what what a good life entails working out this relationship
between compassion and equinity like what is the kind of
balance point between nihilism and frenzied inefficient
suffering and we know it doesn't take long to realize that a path devoid of
compassion is kind of dismal pathetic
really and yet caring is
costly and so there's love in the face of suffering
compassion and then uh love in the face of powerlessness it's
equinity and we move between those modes sequentially sometimes caring sometimes
that care is absent and as we practice that this this
sequential Rhythm gets smoother the kind
of stickiness the holding on the ruminative mechanisms that keep the past
alive settles out quite a bit and the trace of the last
moment is a bridged tears in other words
in uh In This Moment laughter in the
next each moment very fresh and so the the poignancy
of of grief need not cast any Shadow
over ecstatic joy to care not to care
is it possible though to to care and not to
care simultaneously not
sequentially one description or manifestation of of
emptiness is the simultaneous experience of car car Ing and not
caring it is the uh the experience of of of utter problem
lastness this moment as it's come to
be in its imperfection is without
error and we rest in that sense of the the eror errorless of it we rest
in progressively the perception of no
thing like the things of perception start to to drop out to melt
away and in a sense what becomes more prominent than anything is the three
marks of existence Dua anicha anata you
know un unsatisfactoriness impermanence not
self emptiness we might say is the perception of of less and
less you know like in the sense of like empty it's not like a metaphor you know
the perception of less and less with more and more aliveness
it it's the kind of tranquilizing of
perception and from the um TR
Su um the lesser lesser discourse on
emptiness uh we're first transfixed by the perception of the the busyness of
the village and then the perception of the village drops away way all the agitation
of that perception drops away just the perception of the the animals or the human
beings then that drops away it's just Wilderness perceiving Wilderness
refining out the more agitated forms of
perception and the Wilderness drops away as just Earth less and less perceptual
disturbance and so the the kind of basic agitation of ssara like is being
progressively um refined refined
out and we keep noticing absence the absence of coarser
phenomena and it's so striking where
um we're beings that long for peace but accept mere
pleasure the perception of the Wilderness drops away to
increasingly subtle forms of of
somethingness but not much something perception of Infinite Space
no body no mind space without anything on the other
side of it and so this is
um this this is a kind of um not
caring not caring to teach us to Care and not to
care this is not to care in the sense that happiness happiness is um it's
independent of the sensor the ordinary sensory World very
independent extremely confident in the mind in goodness in the Dharma
path and so there's less and less but there is still mind there is still mind
everything before sensation there's still
mind so the the Raa um just as if there were a roofed
house or a roofed Hall having windows on the North the South or the East when the
Sun rises and array has entered by way of window of the window where does it
land on the Western Wall the person replies
if there's no rest Western Wall where does it land on the
ground and if there is no ground where does it land on the water they reply if
there is no water where does it land it does not
land and then the the the Buddha response is
um where Consciousness does not land or increase that I tell you it goes on to
say has no sorrow Affliction or
despair there a very beautiful image we can know it it's not
exactly a metaphor it is like
light that light is like um light from very distant
stars and maybe even as
terad maybe you can say that is a very benevolent
light you might say there is care just the
way light from distance
Stars warms
us so to care not to care
simultaneously offer this for your consideration and
uh it'll be away next week but we'll
um start back up uh after that uh I think February
5th okay folks may you uh be well