okay Uh welcome welcome folks Good to be with
you As for a theme meditation theme I got one
comment to make it NBA basketball
related which brings to mind a recent event This will not be the theme of the
meditation but I was watching the Warriors um against the Rockets
uh tense game and uh with my nephew who's
14 and you would say I was not in a well- reggulated
state I was kind of like I I don't even sit when I watch It's like I just I'm
kind of I don't always watch I can't I can't But um sort of like pacing around
and kind of exaggerated grunts and fear and hope and just pirouetting back and
forth from dread to
relief and uh and he wasn't doing that well
himself but he is 14 and at some point he said he calls me mana cuz when he was
a kid he couldn't say Mad or Matthew and um said "Mana you're a meditation
teacher." Fair enough Fair enough And it's sort of
like I don't know I need some things to care about that don't matter It's a
little how it feels but it feels like it matters but it
doesn't Anyway may we send lots of love and
kindness to Steph Curry's hamstring
and we will now meditate
Okay settle in
relaxing everything but the brightness
Just filling out your body with light
the center of gravity just dropping
down into your belly
There's a lot of gravity here on this part of the universe
We just uh appreciate the way in which the earth
holds us fast
and take some uh fuller breaths through your belly
Man the softening Softening
And just like uh the location of a phone might be pinpointed by
uh how it pings to different cell towers where it
is in relation in reference to those towers
We ping to certain reference points in experience to locate ourselves
the felt outline of our body before it gives way to
space our
preferences our so-called life our plans
Ping to the tower of uh
craving aversion
And we locate ourself in this Hey
What would it mean to be here without reference points
without referentiality
We're good at uh noticing
phenomena Just we tend to hold on too
long Like we need to
Make sure all phenomena are
safe Not hiding some secret we need to extract for our life
How gracefully might we put
down sight and sound sensation and thought
become uh tolerant of [Music]
endings things
dissolving Not needing to pick something new
up Not needing to remind ourselves
of who what where why we are
live in the know where you come from and though you have an address
here Roomie invites
even sense of I'm the
meditator or I'm teaching meditation
Just another ping
[Music]
Okay Um so attention
and love have important connections And if you if you
fragment the attention love gets compromised
to And um makes some sense to me that uh the
technological uh frenzy the kind of regime of
technological frenzy under which we live might be correlated with increases
in hate and fragmented
love And um this was published in
2019 draft form by a group that called themselves friends of attention I I do I
did not do much research I just came across this They may be lovely people It
may be a cult but this is their manifesto Edit it down a little bit
So in the present and worsening state of things the faculty and the power of
human desire suffers from monoculture the overultivation of one or
maybe two forms of a desire in addition to one or more primitive spasms of the brain stem that
resemble but are not desire Desire is impoverished and it has
fallen and the grammar of desire too both its call and its
response Instead there is the continuous circular generation of immediate
satisfaction of miserable debased desires a thing that masquerades as
freedom of attentions on the rampage It resembles an infinitely
scrolling buffet of choice where even the most thrilling of
confections made up of the same dye and corn syrup as all the rest
Constant invitations to self-expression are instead solicitations to evacuate the self in
which in the end stages one simply arranges a series of
attractive objects within the empty bobble bedcked frame of a thing that was
once a person True freedom of attention is a burden that uplifts its bearer When it's first
assumed it feels like it's opposite like unfreedom But in fact it is what happens
when a human in full and conscious possession of her freedom and power of
attention forges a path through space matter ideas and time Attention is a
form of love Yes love as one expects is the answer But we do not yet know what
love is or could be The house of attention has many
mansions Attention transforms mere points of space or points of reference
into rooms corridors and labyrinth Attention is a trap door
opening down Anything given sufficient attention will open into an
abyss of knowledge experience and
desire Attention is u the most basic currency
of being human most basic currency of our dharma practice
And yet we're vulnerable The attention is very
vulnerable And because technology has so
effectively scaled greed hate delusion you know it's almost like the
second noble truth has gotten worse There's a cause of suffering You
know craving is the cause So you know it's I don't know Maybe it's
ill advised to say something's gotten worse That seems very deeply baked into
human nature and kind of impervious to to many influences But it seems like
it's worse The ease with which certain desires can be expressed has made the cycle of
craving acquisition momentary satisfaction and then heartbreak
tighter That loop is tighter and the information economy like
a fresh pain each hour confronting
us reminding us of our nearly complete helplessness
And we kind of are chasing that helplessness with debaseed desire
compulsivity And then maybe the dharma is supposed to provide the perfect
consolation to all of that But we know it doesn't it won't
And it's almost like our our
power our power is dwarfed by our love Oh that my monk's robe were wide
enough to gather up all the suffering people in this floating world So Ria's
lament and then we we sort of acclimatize to frenzy and it feels almost
like we owe the world or we owe our helplessness that
frenzy and we wrongly assume that in that frenzy we're
suffering effectively
Naomi Shabn slowly is not the full poem Slowly
slow clean one drawer Arrange words on a
page Let them find one another Find you
trust they might know something You aren't living the whole
thing at once That's what the minute said to an
hour without me You're nothing
given sufficient attention anything will open into an abyss of
desire And we we don't typically link attention and
desire Even desire sounds like a bad word in Buddhism Sometimes that's used
interchangeably with craving but not here It strikes me that that um patient
attention careful attention
uh deep attention cultivates a certain kind of desire a certain kind of
engagement fidelity It's through that kind of
patient attention that dharma becomes a passion project
And we recognize maybe at the end of a day maybe right now maybe at the end of
a week or on the first day of a retreat that we've been glancing off the
surface of life And that makes irritability and agitation much more
accessible And so like staying maybe with a piece of
art lingering a little longer than we might
we stay with experience Just stay We risk
boredom We risk
impulsivity Took a long time to do that painting
Let us see
attention they go on to say transforms mere points of reference into rooms
corridors labyrinths and that kind
of transformation is important in uh for
love Attentional stability kind of staying risking
boredom is important for love the kind of gradual opening of a of a point into a
space point into rooms corridors
labyrinths Simone V we have to uh wrote we have to try to cure our faults by
attention and not by will Attention taken to its highest degree is the same
thing as prayer presupposes faith and
love Absolutely unmixed attention is prayer If we turn our minds towards the
good it's impossible that little by little the whole soul will not be
attracted there too in spite of
itself Shared that before That's what come back to it now What would it be
to cure something through
attention In the dharma we might say that
um wise attention refineses out the forces of
grieving delusion Or we might say that faith and love
follow in the wake of letting go We
cure our faults by attention not by will by offering
ourselves up to something not by
engineering And little by little the whole soul will be
attracted towards the good I think that's right Part of
why we don't stay quiet is that we have to give up our hate
Hatred just cannot withstand kind of
patient deep tension We might still have to say
no But the embraciveness of hatred becomes self evidently
painful and it's not the most effective way of saying no
This is the prayer of
attention and uh our love depends on it
offer this for your uh consideration and
um be at retreat next week So won't have class but
um be back uh next week the
21st And uh I wish you all uh well take good care of uh your attention your love