so uh with that reminder for me uh there is a famous story in Buddhism
of the Buddha supposedly when he was about six or seven um it was a springtime it was
apparently a nice spring day and uh his uh father was uh leading the
ritual first plowing of the season so they were out in the field plowing this
it was kind of a a little bit of a festival maybe like we'll do next week and uh and then um but because everyone
was involved in the plowing they they left this little boy alone and he felt safe secure comfortable being there and
um and he was under they say a rose apple tree i love it that they remember the tree that he was sitting under so in
the shade watching the the all this happen in front of him and maybe he got
a little bit absorbed in what was happening he felt content and happy it was engaging for his eyes maybe and he
was following it and in the process of that he got concentrated and um and entered into a
relatively light samadei but still was a it was an inner
state of well-being of unification of being settled and peaceful and uh and that was nice for
him until he was about 36 six and uh and then by that time he had
spent years uh practicing as an aesthetic about six seven years trying
to find a way to liberation in the systems of India at the time and none of
it worked for him and uh and so one day he was sitting meditating and u probably
because he's the tail end of his aesthetic period he was probably looked pretty emaciated he was kind of extreme
extreme aesthetic of sorts but he was sitting meditating and um he remembered
that experience from about 30 years before and uh and he recognized that
that experience was onward leading that experience was was uh had tastes or
flavors of the liberation he was looking for that this that it was pointing to the possibility onward to liberation in
a way that u none of his previous practices he did and none of the uh
somehow showed that to him and uh he got I don't know if he got excited but he
got inspired that uh this was uh the way to liberation and that uh this kind of
deep state samadei settled quiet peaceful was not
to be feared not you not to be afraid of that this this way of being so when he was 36 he
remembered this experience and that was uh kind of his entryway to uh that
experience kind of remembering that maybe he felt some of it um by memory and so then he started his path and he
got in got into that state again and then from there built his samadei until
he got strong enough samadei that he was in a good state for his awakening
so a childhood experience of well-being of being settled peaceful at home comfortable uh probably not something
you strong enough that some of you if you had something like that as a kid occurred to you to tell anyone uh it's
just some of you maybe had something like that as a kid and the garden I had under the kitchen
table and uh I put a white sheet over it and made myself a little tent and the
beautiful sunlight would come in there i was so safe in the kitchen i think my mom was cooking so nice wonderful sounds
around me that helped me feel kind of cozy and uh and I remember feeling so
peaceful so at ease and it was it was a feeling of probably purity or very clean state
just underneath the white sheet the white light coming in and me just being so cozy and contented there
and um so uh it was an experience that he
had once he was enlightened the Buddha started teaching and uh and they say the way
it's classically taught in Buddhism he taught the dharma and the dharma is the
closest thing closest word probably to that corresponds to the English words
religion or spirituality so those are western terms that are
relatively complicated for some of us and some of us avoid one more than the
other or some of us are happy to use it and not use it you know it's it's a complicated words the whole word but but
the the c the the comparable word in uh in India was dharma
dharma and in this and the dharma has many meanings but has two primary
meanings it means means the teachings of the Buddha and it means the experience
that he's pointing to like the experience he had as a six-year-old per something very personal
uh personal process a personal experience something to be experienced for yourself and both those terms for
dharma are encapsulated in um a very famous it's part of the liturgy this is chanted by
monastics every day where they chant the qualities the characteristics of what the dharma is and begins by saying uh uh
the dharma well taught well spoken by the
Buddha is and so uh and then they then they
describe it's the dharma the qualities characteristics of this thing called dharma and uh and u so in one way he's
saying the teachings taught by the Buddha is this way but as you hear these
five characteristics it's not just his teachings it's the the the dharma the
inner process the inner connection that we are to have in doing this practice uh
this is what this inner connection is the inner dharma this experience this feeling we're supposed to have so you
have you see this play goes back and forth these two meanings and what that represents for me is that uh uh to
whatever degree Buddhism is a religion it's a religion that is based on our own
personal experience and um so that so those five characteristics are uh the dharma is uh
to uh is uh here and now it's it's here in the present moment the literal
language of it is um uh it's visible here and
now so visible you know something you can experience sense and feel for yourself that it's
immediate it's not something you wait for in the future you'll get the rewards in a sense there's something about the
immediiacy that we can experience here and now it's like now what there's really about is not it's almost like
what it's really about is not about time and then it is um uh it is um onward
leading meaning that there's something about it that uh that kind of opens a
door or puts you on a trail puts you on a on a road that's onward leading or puts you on a slide there's something
there there's a feeling there's something's opening for you there here come this go forward
here and then um it is uh and then now they're using a very
colloquial expression for the next characteristic um that literally says
hey come and see come and see for yourself um usually people don't they
translate a little bit more sophisticatedly they say uh inviting inspection the dharma invites inspection
so this onwarding this dharma come and look for yourself there's something about the nature of this experience that
is kind of requesting or inviting you and if
this dharma is to be found in yourself then you can imagine it's the heart's request it's the heart's inspiration
it's the heart's longing or desire that uh is inviting you come here
deeper deeper into what whatever it is last characteristic of the dharma is
that it's to be experienced by the wise and this is a very nice way of speaking about
you to be experienced by the wise and um and no it's actually it's more more
detailed than that it's to be experiience erenced personally to be personally experienced by the wise so
there's very individuals like this is something you can experience um and some things in life
you can only really experience for yourself you can't ask someone else to do it for you and uh and there's
something about the movement towards spiritual freedom inner freedom freedom of the heart you can't ask someone else
to free their heart so you don't have to you know that doesn't you know I guess
it'd be nice for them but it doesn't really do something for you if you you
know you know contract it out to someone else to do it for you you know the meditation is really great and uh and
I'm going to get take my all my money and I'm going to get it's so great i'm going to pay 10 people to meditate for
me so I don't have to you know it's ridiculous you know
there's no point meditation is something you're supposed to be experienced for yourself so the same thing with
liberation so this personal experience and so as a seven-year-old six-year-old
he experienced something that inspired him when he was older and uh and the in
the what's called the word for inspiration in the ancient language means um literally means something like
to have a feeling for the purpose or the meaning or the goal that the word is ata
in Pali and some of you know Sanskrit it's ara so it has multiple meanings but
um uh ata vda uh which I mean to have a feeling and this vda can be inspired be
aroused but more often it means like a feeling and then uh or a knowing a deep
knowing and um and then to be um uh have this
dharma inspired in the dharma this dharma feeling this dharma move movement
inside the heart and so this kind of inner feeling that we can have and the reason I'm giving this talk
today is because yesterday uh we sat under the Buddha tree here
uh meaning we we had a dayong retreat here and uh it was really nice to sit
here there were about 45 people meditating and I mean really ever since the pandemic people coming to these
dalongs they seem to sit so well you know they're quiet and intent and
they're very sincere and dedicated and and during this dayong I
saw I don't know 16 people for 15inute meetings to talk about their practice
and there was something about every single one of them they had a wide range of things they wanted to talk about but
every one of them came with a certain kind of sincerity where they were coming to talk
about something that was important and something about them had gathered together in some kind of like they were
connected to something inside some kind of in this is important I'm here to to
share something that's valuable for me even if they were what they were talking about was their suffering their
challenges in life it's like there was a kind of a coming together and I was so
inspired by this by some kind of inner something inside of them that had
gathered together to to to engage in this in their process of of the dharma
of practice of spirituality of religion and uh and some of them it was
more uh you know clear the nature of this gathering together and some of them
clearly had years of meditation practice behind them and it was the years of
practice somehow that I could feel the the the accumulated combination of their
intentionality their sense of purpose and what they've been doing and for all these years it felt like they're here
they might have had a mind that was overactivated and felt like they weren't getting concentrated but I could feel
that there was something here and in some of them uh the best car way I could
characterize it to myself and one of them to that person was um uh there was
there there was a a contemplative heart contemplative nature inside of them that
of a contemplative I think the person got a little bit scared because they associated that becoming a
monastic but I I reassured her that's not what I meant and um but there's It's a kind of
a um a uh inner sensibility a a kind of
faith a kind of sense of being connected something that's really good onward leading something that feels certainly
pleasant in a certain way but exactly how to characterize it for any maybe
it's very different for different people but something within that's very peaceful maybe or warm or sense of this
is home or this is where some kind of different quality of joy or happiness
well-being exists that's very different than uh the joy of winning the
California lot the lottery that's maybe joyful for a little while but that's
actually the end of that day celebrating you're probably exhausted and um and uh
or crying but um but this deep um and peace
there is something the Buddha called the the greatest happiness is peace so some
sense some hint some feeling quality for something inside that's living there and
I've had uh coming down here thinking about this talk today walking down here I was kind of decided I would try to
remember the different times in my life where I experienced this kind of thing even before I started
meditating and um and so uh you know that I described under the kitchen table
uh I grew up on the water a lot uh next to the water i'm
from Norway and on the coast there and there's uh sometimes being on the fjords
early early in the morning with the water completely still and quiet no wind
somehow that just was like that under the under the rose apple tree experience
um knew where that's where I was supposed to be that's where it was peaceful that was things felt full and
complete and nothing else had to happen the um um when I was 10 uh I there was
something that's happened on this on the public bus coming home from school it
was they had a they had a they had they called it a conductor they had the driver and they had the person who sold the tickets back then this was in Italy
and uh I discovered kind of I'd never thought about it at the time i just kind of did it by instinct but I discovered
that if I sat in a certain seat because I lived at the end of the bus line if I sat at the end of the seat the conductor
would sit in front of me and uh would take out his ledger and
record all the different tickets he sold for that trip you know the round trip one way children old
people you know whatever it was he had a whole bunch and he had to keep a log and I would sit over him but look over his
shoulder and watch him with his pencil and his uh doing his numbers whatever he did and I would just started feeling so
good i just felt and I I wasn't thinking about it i
wasn't like grabbing it or wanting more of it it was just like I knew I should do this and then when I stopped going on
the bus um it never occurred to me to want that again and it was just it was just almost like instinctual just it was
like the sun rises in the morning i would just go sit there and have this good feeling years later when I started
meditating oh that's what I was experiencing that
was a wonderful feeling for me of being being at peace being at ease being in
myself comfortable even though my life around me was quite um you
know I don't know you know I moved around a lot when I was growing up and I
was in a new city new language new country uh didn't know anybody and on an
bus where I don't know you know but so it was you know you know in some ways a
challenging time but but uh that bus ride was a refuge for me and um and so and then I kind of had
begun meditating but then I stopped when I lived with my f friends on their farm
and because I was living there for a while they decided they could take a difficult to acquire vacation because
they had these cows had to be milked every day so now I could do it feed them
feed them milk them and so I was left alone for the first time in my life for five days and didn't see anyone really
for the talk to anyone for those five seven days a week
and I again I had this feeling that welled up being alone that long time in a beautiful Norwegian kind of rural
place with these wonderful girlfriends that I had that I loved so much and caring for
them and and uh and so uh so this wonderful feeling grew up with this time
also with a tremendous clarity of mind like uh it wasn't that I stopped thinking but I started seeing every
thought like a like a diamond it was just like no matter how bad the thought was it was like
wow and um and that also was something I had started in meditation later i
started oh that was kind of a state meditation often people can have on
retreat and uh but this was so important that experience well when my friends
came back I lost it when it disappeared but it was so important for me i thought
this this was really something to guide a life with this is this I have faith in this is a something I'm inspired by so I
had this uh dharma feeling this dharma
inspiration around this experience and so then it became my
dedication uh to uh to figure out how to answer this question and the question was um
how can I be alone with others i didn't want to be a hermit
because that that's what I was alone for this week but uh but I I didn't I wanted to have this experience it felt like
this is how to be alive and maybe it's a strange expression for some people to
hear you me wanting to be alone with others but there was a best way at 20 that I could somehow understand what I
was trying to do i wanted to be with people connected to people involved in the world but I wanted also to be come
from that place of that clarity and that peace inside so this was an example then of an onward
leading in the present moment it was timeless it was to be experienced by someone who was attempting to be
wise on his way and um and so all these
things were behind me to get interested in Buddhism Buddhist practice meditation
it was there as a kind of a reference point or a guide and um and so and then
as we practice this kind of inner uh feeling of uh of what the dharma is what
this religious experience this contemplative experience this spiritual experience this kind of uh can be can
start becoming a clearer reference and a clear sense oh this is important this is
valuable and how do I allow this to grow in my life and develop and flower rather
than just have it be something I occasionally touch in in meditation or occasionally touch in with by going on retreat uh how can we how how do you
live from this deeper sensitivity this deeper feeling this deeper kind of peace
that's possible and and each person each of you will have a different way of describing it there's a lot of different
ways so I I don't want to use my words and get you believe you're supposed to
have it like me but um but uh to have this this uh this
dharma feeling this dharma sensibility this dharma this uh uh
inspiration and uh and sometimes the Buddha was explicit that it can come
from um uh the experience of a variety of things it can come from
uh all of them are considered part of part and parcel of Buddhist practice it
can come from living ethically and there's something about uh
ethical integrity that touch it can touch into this place that you feel that now it isn't
just like you're making ethical choices through your life but there's a feeling that ethics is arising out of some kind
of deeper feeling of what it's like to have a certain kind of ethical integrity the Buddha said it can come
out of generosity there's a way of being generous of being magnanimous being
open-handed uh to people and to others and to the world rather than miserly or clinging or
hoarding that just kind of something about there's a movement of freedom in opening your hand and giving away and um
that in that done well also can give a person someone that dharma feeling that
feeling for what the goal is and it's you can see it can maybe feel a little bit more like that for uh generosity
because generos generosity is a liberation of things it is a letting go of something so it's a it's a kind of
precursor of the deep letting go that uh that uh liberation
is and then uh and then in the letting go uh that we begin experiencing at some
point a very special uh point arises where the letting go that we do that we
experience for ourselves uh gives birth gives rise to a real
clear feeling of the goodness of letting go the peace the the warmth the
happiness of letting go of the heart not being clenched or contracted or hard or
crusted over or armored or something and you could really feel oh look at this this is good um it might be um I mean
one metaphor the Buddha used was a open path in a overgrown jungle have you ever
tried to go through an overgrown jungle but there's no path it can go slow going
you finally find the path you're even lost you you know where is that path and you're lost and you're going around
you're I've done that and ended up all scratched up and bloody because it was so dense and then
finally the open path is there and it just feels like now I'm sailing through it just feels so good like I can just I
know where I'm going I'm finally safe I'm know heading home or something where and but now there's you know it's
unencumbered to go that way so to have that feeling in your heart and to have
it so clear that that that represents this dharma feeling feeling for the
dharma or this inspiration this contemplative feeling this spiritual feeling that we have in Buddhism it's a
little bit hard for people coming out of western religions to understand this can be a form of religious experience and if
uh so much of the religious experience is around a relationship to uh a deity
or some something that's outside of you um But it's it might be very comparable
the kind of deep experience it just has a different kind of object of where it's directed and here in the dharma it's um
directed to an experience we're having that then grows and inspires
us and the reason one of the reasons why this inspiration is so good is that for
the Buddha uh when we kind of really get a feel for it uh it gives rise to
joy a joy that doesn't take us away from the present moment puts us into the
present more fully and so it supports the practice of mindful presence being really here and
it's a joy that begins setting in motion this onward onwardleading nature of a
certain way a joy that leads to happiness a happiness that leads to a
peace a peace that leads to um um No no
it's a it's a gladness that leads to joy a joy that leads to uh tranquility a
tranquility that leads to happiness and a happiness that leads to a deep version
of this samadei a deep deep version of this uh feeling of being under the rose
apple tree and um and
uh so uh it was nice yesterday being here and
feeling that there were people who had were expressing in their how they were sitting how they were talking you could
feel that their kind of sense of very wonderful sense of purpose that they had
for some of them it came from uh ha having something in there that saying
this is the path this is what they're doing they practiced long enough you could see that there was this wonderful
way in which they were giving the practice a chance meditation practice a chance to really um change them and open
them and reshape reshape themselves in some kind of profound way because of how
much they sat and what they dedicated to and what they're allowing to grow and see coming and um so I was inspired and um
my hope was to share that inspiration with you coming here today so maybe you
have a contemplative heart i think everyone does but maybe we shouldn't
maybe there's a better word for you than contemplative heart maybe you have a practice heart and practice orientation maybe you
have a a not a liberated heart but maybe you have a liberating heart a heart that
wants to be liberated maybe it maybe you like prefer the word love maybe you have a love
loving heart and your feeling of what love is it's love that needs nothing
that's so deep maybe that's that's the experience we're talking about here for you
so um so maybe also this is a nice talk
before we celebrate the Buddha's birthday next next uh next week is we're celebrating his
birthday his enlightenment and his death all in the same day it just so it's
really efficient and we can get back to meditation and do it for
ourselves so we have a few minutes and um let's start um by hearing a couple of
comments from some of you or questions you might have and maybe it's nice to hear other voices here in the community
as we start kind of shifting to a more community-based
process anybody want to share
anything good morning Gil thank you so much for today's talk
um Oh sorry thank you so much for today's talk and um my husband and I are
also enjoying the Monday through Friday sitting meditations with you
um and now at this point in my life I'm really enjoying the peace and
calm um but I also wonder I I feel like I have this
struggle but I don't know if it's a struggle my best and favorite memories from
childhood are actions and physical um so not peace
and calm and maybe some of that was because of my family environment but um
the running and jumping off of swing sets and balancing on various things and
tumbling and rolling down hills um and so very much a
physical experience and so I'm trying to figure out what that means to me it
feels like yeah that's being in the moment but it also feels like maybe too
activated and not at peace and not calm
so uh fascinating wonderful that you see that i I'm sure that that freedom you
felt in action can be a wonderful reference point for this practice and
you might try doing walking meditation and seeing if a little bit of it can come alive there and um and yes if it's
too much energy involved there can be a feeling of freedom but it doesn't allow the mind to settle enough to start
touching the deeper places that need to be touched in this practice deeper places where where more and more of this
freedom can be discovered but can only be discovered if if the more activated
actions have gotten quiet but I I wouldn't want to dismiss this or say that it's you know you shouldn't have it
it might be some way to use it uh to connect to something so you know go
tumbling now be before you meditate and then
maybe then do walking meditation with it and then sit down and and maybe let things get quieter and see but uh and
then in the in deepest um in meditation the deepest deepest places you go in meditation um you could you could very
well uh reexperience that level of freedom without any action at all
thank you
when I was in seventh grade in San Francisco at a Catholic school and it was very uh warm and all the windows
were open and the nun was droning on and on for some 50inute lecture like they
used to do but I very distinctly remember I've never told anybody this i
very distinctly remember my
that the feeling of kind of a leaving the room hearing
the outside world come in and then I felt connected to the entire world that
the entire world was humming all at the same time with me and
I kind of left my ego and it was just this collective world m very nice
yeah so so
um so some of you maybe have had experiences like that some of you don't
have any memory like that and what you remember is the opposite that some people have had all kinds of very tragic
experience very difficult experiences growing up and I don't want to belittle or dismiss that or ignore that that's
some people people's experience and for some people that's why they come to
practice and um and I don't know if it's a coincidence
uh the uh the Buddha died when he was a baby the Buddha's mother died when he was a
baby which any kind of lack of loss is huge so that maybe also was in his
psyche as he was kind of finding his way with all this and because he was certainly motivated to try to find an
end to suffering so I can I well imagine that he knew suffering well as
well and um and so both both are very important for the dharma to be honest
about to see to recognize and what the Buddha was trying to teach I believe is
that in order to address suffering well it's it's good to uh create a really
good state of mind and heart um that prepares you to hold it in a good way be
able to hold it in a generous open way without being a victim of your suffering but rather to be a healer of it and find
the freedom in in it and so um the the sense of joy and happiness that uh can
come with practice um is is in the service of addressing the suffering it's
not an escape from it and not some kind of way of just just going around and
just you know just pretending everything is just just you know sweet and
wonderful and and you can just ignore the suffering of the world the
suffering of the world is being addressed but it's with this finding a a different lens a different approach
different way of holding it different capacity to be with it than most people learn on their
own so we have still a few minutes before the usual end so if you're a
willing to stay for a few minutes and uh it'd be nice to have Yes one more person wants to speak okay
thank you so much um I'm Lance and um earlier when you asked us what memory we
have of peace um what came up for me was being in my parents' room when I was
young with my siblings and we're all just like enjoying our time together you know like we were singing sharing pizza
and and that was great and another memory was me hiking alone in the wilderness um and just like looking at
the um the mountains h how does one reconcile the sense of peace amongst
others or within a community and also like in solitude like what what is
between peace in a community like in the family and and what's the other one in the nature yeah like or like um you know
like peace um in solitude like say meditating or hiking alone like h how do
we what is peace I guess sorry that might be a loaded question
so yeah I don't know but [Applause]
uh but whatever but uh but I think I I mean I I appreciate this question a lot
it seems like coming from an important place in you that uh that the that um uh
peace can be experienced is peace is not an issue about who you're with or not with or where you are in the world peace
has to do with the quality and characteristics of your heart and some environments kind of create the
conditions that support the peaceful heart and maybe the quality is a little bit different the characteristics is a
little bit different in different situations but the center of focus is not the external world it's to be
experienced by the wise personally and so to to start discovering some of the
operating principles inside how the mind and body and heart work uh how you lose
the peace how it what supports it so you can begin at finding identifying and
living with it as a companion no matter where you go and you take it with you
thank you so uh the idea is now if you would turn to uh maybe a couple of people next to
you and just look around so that someone's left you're not left alone because everyone turns the other
direction by coincidence and and say hello and introduce yourself and then if
there's anything from this talk that inspired you um uh maybe share it with
uh in a few brief words don't tell a long long story and uh but just you want to hear
from others and just say hello and and I'll ring I'll ring a bell