welcome welcome everybody nice to see you
all I'll just say those of you sitting in the back on the floor you're perfectly welcome to stay there but
you're also welcome to come up here if it's a little bit easier to not be behind chairs so you can do whatever you
please so I'd like to begin tonight by just telling a little story that's uh
captured in the early Buddhist literature and it's the story of a king
who had decided maybe I'll back up and say King sometimes we
can think of them they are lay people they're not monastics and they have a
lot of power of course they do and they have a lot of wealth so they just represent at least in my mind those
individuals have power and wealth so there's this king who uh
decided to renounce being a king and he was going to be a monastic underneath
the Buddha and he took the name badia
badia and so he would do what monastics do at this time of the Buddha they spend
time meditating and so they would be like a group of uh people practicing
together and they could hear him saying something like while he was
meditating and he would be if they listen they could hear he would be saying oh what happen
us oh what Bliss and so it didn't matter where
badia this former King now a monk uh where he was he was often doing this whether he was out underneath a tree
whether he was in some Hut or what just in different places he was uh saying
this What happiness what Bliss oh while he was meditating and so the other monks were
saying you know this guy budy uh clearly he's just he's not really meditating
he's just remembering his former life he must remember like how it was so great
to have all this power and all this wealth that clearly must be what he's uh
doing and they went to talk to the Buddha and say there's this guy budya who keeps on saying and maybe what Suka
I'll just say that word in poly is Suka it's the opposite of Dua Dua is you know
suffering and I'm going like this with my arms because it's encapsulates so such a wide range of things and Suka
also does a wide range gets translated as happiness I'm doing it as happiness and Bliss here we could say Joy some
people could say pleasure you know Suka gets a just you know that family of things family of words to the they go
tell the Buddha and uh and then the Buddha says
well um ask him to come talk to me so badia goes to talk to the Buddha and the Buddha says is it true badia that even
in the wilderness or at the foot of a tree or in an empty dwelling you
frequently Express you're frequently saying Oh What happiness oh what
Bliss Bia says yes and then the Buddha says but why do
you say this and badya the former King says
formerly as the king ruling the land my guard was well organized within and
without the Royal compound without meaning like on the outside and on the inside on the inside and outside of the
royal compound it was well guarded it was well guarded on the
inside and the outside of the City and on the inside and the outside of the country it was well guarded but although
I was guarded and defended in this way I remained
fearful scared suspicious and
nervous but these days even when I'm alone in the wilderness meditating or at
the foot of the tree or an empty dwelling I'm not fearful I'm not scared
I'm not suspicious I'm not nervous I have
relaxed I Live Now unruffled and my heart free as a wild
deer it is for this reason that even I when I might be in the wilderness foot
of the tree or an empty Hut when I'm meditating I'm frequently saying Oh What happiness oh what
Bliss there's a lot that we could unpack in this story there's a lot of things there but I want to
emphasize that it's this movement towards right he had a pretty simple life going from having all this wealth
and power that he had to protect and was feeling anxious right somebody's going to take it or maybe I
have to uh prove that I deserve this kingship and you know fix these problems
there or you know do something so people don't Revolt or whatever it might be I don't really know what Kings do but I'm
sure it's something very important so he we could say that he
just like drastically simplified his life and realize oh this is where the
ease is and often we're not noticing how much like tension there is and this kind
like this protecting in so many different ways and so we could say that
we could maybe simplify some of the teachings in this tradition is pointing into the value of
Simplicity this is not a movement towards you know getting more and more and more not like acquiring more stuff
or not making things more and more complicated or you know getting more and
more uh experiences it's not about that it turns out that
it's there's these Basics that we refer to again and
again they get You Know spoken about in a number of different ways and you know
there's some complications right if you want to you can dig down into the sutas
and learn poly or you know something like this but for those of you who don't know poly
is the language that the early Buddhist literature is preserved
in so there's these Basics with this practice and we could say one being
present for what's actually happening
now not what the mind is saying and making up and fantasizing or remembering
or something like this but what's actually happening right
now turns out to be pretty powerful something that's simple turns out when we start to pay
attention we notice how much we're not actually here but we're elsewhere so we could say that's one
thing that it's a simple a poting to Simplicity we might even say Budd of this King when he was
thinking like oh what happened as what Bliss that he was just feeling into like
oh yeah right now I just have to be here experiencing this
moment I don't have to be worried about whether the kingdom next door is going
to try to throw me o throw it over throw this Kingdom over or something like that
and then we might say a second thing first is maybe just to be present here and a second basic simple thing that we
return to again and again in these teachings is notice what's leading to
more freedom and what's leading to less Freedom what's leading to dooka and what's leading to Suka what's leading
to what words were here fearful scared suspicious nervous like what kind of
leads to that Direction and what leads to well-being and ease peace
freedom Awakening and so part of the practice is to just be sensitive and notice
this and then this gets you know fleshed out in so many different ways but we could kind of boil it down to just this
simpleness we don't have to adopt some beliefs instead there's this invitation
like oh good go figure this out for yourself go experience it for yourself don't don't take what my word or Dharma
teacher's word for what's being said here but maybe what's gets said here what you hear whether it's in drma talks
drma books dma friends test it out for yourself by being present and noticing
what's leads to more ease and what leads to less [Music]
ease so you could say that this practice so much is about letting go of what's
extra letting go of you know some of these complications quote unquote that we like to do and maybe an example could
be something maybe you are um attending a potluck I'm just this example and
let's say that you show up and you forgot to bring something not that this person actually
ever did that no I have I have showed up like oh whoops shoot I was supposed to to bring I left it back at
home so let's say you show up and like oh no I forgot this uh dish that I was
going to bring and I was going to share with others and then the mind we could do
something like oh I can't believe I forgot it I'm forgetting so many things maybe dementia is setting in and yeah
cuz I forgot where my keys were the other day and like maybe what am I going to do about this maybe I should go talk
to that my friend she knows a lot of medical stuff she would know yeah but the last time I talked to her she kind
of looked at me a little bit weird and now I'm not sure that I want to reach out to her and okay well maybe I should
go have therapy because clearly I'm like so messed up and you write the mind right just can go just can go we make
stories there is not a lot of freedom when we get stuck in those stories I don't want to demonize them and say it
wrong it's a human tendency to do this and this practice is how we just
recognize like oh yeah this is the mind's habit we don't have to believe everything it's saying we don't have to
go off and uh let it push us around and do things that uh it's uh trying to tell
us that we have to do precisely then but maybe an alternative when you
realize that you forgot something bring into a potluck is just recognize oh yeah
this this feels uncomfortable yeah I I really wanted to share this
with others now I can't share it yeah and now I'm going to be here and
maybe everybody else bought something and I didn't and I'm going to feel a little bit uncomfortable there it's going to be a little bit
awkward I don't like to feel awkward feels awkward to imagine I'm
going to feel awkward and then maybe there's this way
that uh oh yeah I can maybe when you notice this to you could like oh yeah my mind wants to make me into a terrible
person because I forgot but you know people forget things and I forgot things
I forgot this can that be
okay and then maybe you depends the event go to the host and say and I
apologize you know I really wanted to bring this I was looking forward to sharing this with others and now I'm
showing up empty-handed I I hope that's okay and if it's not okay the host is going
to tell you nope sorry and if it is okay they're going to say oh don't worry about it there's always always so much
food here we're just happy you're here and there you're done right it's
not a big complicated thing it doesn't have to be worrying about our mental health or what things that we should do
or something like this so this idea can we just be with what's happening including feeling the
uncomfortableness of when we forget to bring something when we don't do something we say we're
going to do it's human nature to forget things
it's also human nature to not want to feel uncomfortable but we do we do feel
uncomfortable maybe we could say part of this practice is to feel comfortable with not being feel feeling comfortable
with being uncomfortable
so maybe I can point out that there's this way of pointing to Simplicity of
just being with what's actually happening in this
moment and then this other moment just returning
again planning will happen taking care of things will happen
thinking that we have to figure things out it's going to happen but can we just
be present with feeling the pressure of the chair or the cushion against the
body hearing of this voice this
moment feeling your feet on the
ground this is always available this is always available the
Simplicity of what's Happening Here don't worry you will take care of the
things that need to be taken care of there's a part of us that thinks like oh no no no I have to go figure this out
and a lot of the figuring it out is just a distraction from feeling
uncomfortable so this idea of just simplifying just
simplifying because simplifying really supports a sense of contentment and a sense of well-being
and it's not that this practice is only about chasing contentment and well-being or chasing good
feelings but there's this way in which if we have a certain amount of ease it's much easier
to not get uh it's much easier for the the wisest version of ourselves to show
up and to maybe like see the bigger picture and not get caught up on small
things that are happening that maybe aren't so helpful that turn
out to be extra all of us probably have this sense
of relief uh if there's a let's say for example there's a a drawer in the
house a lot of households have like the junk drawer you open up if you can open
it up like sometimes there just so much stuff in there you open it up and there's like this mess in there and then for whatever reason you feel like okay
you know what there something needs to be done with this and you just clean it up and organize and throw things out and
like oh wow here's this I had thought seen this for a while you know this kind of stuff and then you organize it maybe
you donate some of it maybe you fix the thing that was broken that got shoved in there whatever it is there's a sense of
like ah that feels good right kind of like when there's a little bit of a when
a mess is gets have some semblance of organization to it when it gets kind of
like simplified in some kind of way we all have this experience of what a good feeling it is this relief when things
that seem messy get simplified so this movement towards
making things simpler simpler whether it's our actual experience we make them
simpler by just being with the experience of the moment which I'm
pointing to the body the usually the bodily experiences or the simplification
is It's usually the mind that is uh making things more complicated or maybe there's this way in
which we just find ourselves being busy a lot doing one thing after another it's not uncommon for it to feel
like you know being busy is a spadge of Honor semblance of how important we are and how people need us or something like
this to be busy
so this pointing towards [Music] Simplicity this movement towards
Simplicity because it's supports well-being and
ease but there's also an unhelpful side of
Simplicity there's this way in which it can be really help with tremendous support and then there's a way in which
there a certain type a certain way in which we might do doe Simplicity turns out to not be helpful
at all in fact kind of like take us away from greater peace and
ease and that is when we bring this idea of Simplicity or this wish to make
things less complicated in some way and that uh supports us kind of propels us
into having this dichotomous thinking or this way in which we have
this um just bifurcated thinking okay there's
good and bad there's only two things and if it's not in the good it's
in the bad or if it's in the bad it's certainly not anything good about it
there's this way in which we can have this polarized thing like things are
either you know at the ends of if we wanted to say a spectrum there's nothing
in the middle there's no nuances or gradation it's just good or bad right or wrong yes
or no you know these ways we do this this is a simplification and often humans we like
to do this when sometimes when we're feeling uncomfortable like oh that's
bad they are bad and this over here is good and we
are good this terrible thing that can happen when
we do this this way in which there's like yeah
we know what's right and all those knuckleheads over there I don't know there they clearly don't know what's
right yeah we got it all figured out and you guys I don't know you have some problems clearly right it's this
sense and then as soon as that starts to show up and Us Versus Them me versus the
world versus you then this is where nervousness and
anxiousness and fear and scared comes in in a subtle way in some ways we like to
have this self-righteous feeling like yeah we know what it is but it also requires in a subtle way that we're not
paying attention to there's so much data about this how
humans they will like just um ignore information that doesn't support the
sense that they are the good guys and everybody else is the bad guys they will just like completely ignore and forget
it or they'll make up some Twisted logic to explain away something that doesn't
quite work this simplification is not the way
forward it's never quite like this that we are the good guys and they are the
bad guys how could it be humans we are we
have complexities we have ranges of things in our
life and so ear earlier I was talking
about Dua versus Suka like leading to well-being and not leading to well-being
this also is kind of you could say is a dichotomy and a bifurcation but it's this is pointing to
like what leads to Greater freedom and ease and what doesn't that's different than this
person is a good person that person is a bad person this what leads to Greater ease
is for all of us to discover there doesn't have to be a value judgment on an individual or a group of
individuals but when we start to have like these binary perspectives
about ourselves and others it's a way in which there's
this we kind of like let go of any idea that there things could be new uh the
Nuance of things or we let go of things that are that uh not
extremes and uh there's somebody on YouTube that sometimes says yeah yeah
I'm the alt middle like this feeling right you know just the fact just to be in the middle
is a is to be an alternative inad instead of a on these ends of these political
spectrums and there's something that happened to me uh a number of years ago that had a really big impact uh on me
regarding this and I want to share this little story when I was in graduate
school it's uh common and like in the sciences and probably in other fields
too that uh we would get together and discuss the latest literature you know the latest findings and every week the
the students and the professors would get together and we would choose one paper and we would uh evaluate the
experiments that were done and the data and how they interpreted the data and stuff like this right just to keep a
breast of the field and to learn about what other uh Laboratories are doing so this had such a big impact on
me that I remember this that uh we were looking at the paper that was discussing
preons some of you might remember there was mad cow disease this was uh in the
early uh 90s and I remember in the UK they had to like kill all their cattle or something
like this it was like a it was a really big deal and it was um people were dying humans were dying and the cattle were
dying and people didn't understand and we were looking at this paper that was
talking about prons which is like a novel infectious agent that has this novel mechanism of action not a not a
virus not a bacteria nothing like this it was something completely new that we had never heard of before but all of us
I remember us reading this paper that was published in the most prestigious Journal we were making fun of them we
were laughing at them oh my gosh they did this experiment but they interpreted this way oh my gosh I can't believe it
clearly this data really points to that we just couldn't get our minds around that something new was happening and
right we were all scienti that were had dedicated Our Lives to trying to help cure human diseases smart people that
were just you know trying to work things think about things and work with it but
we had this this bias that here's something new that we hadn't thought of before we hadn't seen before and it
clearly was wrong and we were mean I remember in this we were the people that
weren't in the room but were like oh my gosh I can't believe how did they get this published it blah blah blah
the person won the Nobel Prize a few years later for this right but we were
like so sure of ourselves because I of just something
different and so this made me really realize all these times in which I think like okay I clearly know and all my
friends clearly know too we're all in the same maybe we don't maybe we don't know
maybe we're not so sure so when we get into this dichotomous thinking like okay we're the good guys
and those are the bad guys Maybe not maybe it's not so clear maybe there's
something that we don't know yet or maybe yeah we just don't
know and it's not the way forward it's not the way forward instead in order to
help us support that we're the good guys and they're the bad guys that uh this kind of gross
simplification that and we have to start attributing all kinds of terrible stuff to whenever they do something good and
helpful we have to dismiss it or say oh they only did that because their motives
must have been something terrible or something like this and we have to dismiss when our motives turn out to be
not very good or something like
this so there's a poem that points to this that's not by Rosemary
traumer surpris I'm often citing her poems this uh poem that I I it's a short
poem that I found really powerful really powerful it's by yakuda
amahai I think I'm pronouncing that correctly and it's translated by Byron
Kat's husband Steven Mitchell it's by yahuda amahai and it's
called the place where we are right
from the place where we are right flowers will never grow in the
spring the place where we are right is hard and trampled like a
yard but doubts and loves dig up the
world like a mole a plow and a whisper will be heard in the
place where the ruined house once
stood I'll read it again the place where we are
right from by uh Yuda amahai from the place where we are right
flowers will never grow in the spring the place where we are right is
hard and trampled like a yard but doubts and loves dig up the world
like a mole a plow and a whisper will be heard in the
place where the ruined house once
stood right in this place where we are right implicit in that is there's that
other place where you are wrong if we have we are right this place then there
there's that other place where they are wrong and this creates the conditions
for fear and hatred for those people that are wrong over
there this is not a world we want to live in that's full of fear and hatred and this is what happens when we're
making this uh they're wrong over there I'm not saying that everything they're doing is perfect I'm saying the simplification of
we are right and you are wrong is not the way forward
I love that this line but doubts and loves dig up the world like a mole a
plow so doubts maybe there's like this room for H I'm not so sure it seems like
this right now this is what makes sense to me I think this is I my
understanding I can't see any other way to interpret it but this way this is my current hypothesis but this is very diff
all these things I'm saying are alternatives to I'm right you can say there's when there's doubts there's this
feeling you know this makes sense to me but it's leaving some room for like
well maybe there's some other data I'll have or something else that I'll learn that'll make a
difference and the poet is saying like a mole so moles
are quiet underneath unseen sometimes we think like oh these are
pests and if you're a gardener you might think that they're pests but they also serve a really important function right
they are underneath like breaking up the soil and ating the soil they're important they're an important part of
like the ecosystem but they were underneath kind of like invisible breaking up the soil
and then there's plows that are like on the top of the soil they doing the same thing like breaking them up and this is
like very intentional a farmer or somebody who wants to cultivate a particular plant for example like
intentionally goes in and has a plow also from above so this way that
that place that gets hard and trampled like you know when I think the the poem
the poem has this word um the place where we are right is hard and trampled like a
yard I'm thinking like School yards prison yards you know this place where
there's a lot of uh people trampling maybe behaving in so many
different ways but the ways that they get broken up and
where the trampling doesn't lead to hardness and
stuckness is with things coming from below and things from coming above moles
and plows and it might be that some individuals
maybe in the world out in the world not just in their personal life but out in the world they want
to they feel like yeah there's something that's not right and I want to make a difference maybe they are people who
will be like plows who will in an obvious way break up the soil they will make big
changes and then maybe there will be people who are in the
in the greater world who are just quietly like the moles
underneath just breaking up the soil and air rating and allowing the soil to make
room for flowers where flowers you know something beautiful
and um of course an essential part of plant's life cycle but maybe there's
some happiness or joy and flowers
so whether this we're talking about um we are right and they are
wrong maybe there's something that we feel like oh there's I I don't want to
say that everybody's right and everything is perfectly fine I just don't want us to simplify
things and just slap a label on them and then be dismissive of them but if we feel like oh there's
something that could be better that could be changed that uh maybe needs needs something maybe it's clear to us
what is needed then maybe there's some obvious thing that we can do in the
world or maybe we're the type of person I I happen to be one of these type of
people I'm a little bit more quiet and introverted and I'm a little bit more kind of like underneath trying to like
plant seeds breaking up soil and I kind of view giving dermat talks is this is
my way of like okay maybe this is a way in which can help uh create the conditions in which uh new things can
grow which uh something new can happen so that the yard isn't just hard and
trampled in this place where we are
right because there's a RAC you know there's these um Awakening
factors these uh qualities that have we all have that really support
Awakening investigation is one of them investigation this looking into
getting curious about engaging with we need
that that's different than we are right they are
wrong and today of course is MLK Day
Martin Luther Dr Martin Luther King Jr he was in his way working with uh the
ways that there was just terrible terrible oppression of people it's so so many
terrible things happening and in his own way he was trying to address this let's not just say okay black people are this
way and white people are that way or simplifying things in that
way so as humans we like to simplify things it feels better and sometimes it
feels better in the short term to say like oh they're wrong but it
also kind of creates the conditions in which there's this
um way in which then we have to be always supporting like they are wrong
and I'm right and maybe like this uh King in the beginning of the story he
had this certain amount of anxiety or I'll just say in my own experience as
soon as like I make other people like they're wrong then I'm afraid of them like I feel like I have to get away from
them I don't want to be near
them and then I stop like listening or respecting or caring
about hatred never ends with hatred
this is an ancient law in the dapa and Martin Luther King
said a version of this hatred never ends with hatred how could
it so maybe the complexity of Simplicity it can be simple in terms of coming to
what our experience is not no not getting lost in what's
extra noticing what's extra and but not allowing our to
simplify things into where we are just uh slapping a label on people or
ourselves and then just thinking that's sufficient and not really being present
for what's happening or being Nuance recognizing nuance and complexity that's
there with people
maybe I'll read this poem one more
time the place where we are right by Yehuda
amahai from the place where we are right flowers will never grow in the
spring the place where we are right is hard and trampled like a yard
but doubts and loves dig up the world like a mole a
plow and a whisper will be heard in the place where the ruined house once
stood so I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there are any questions or
comments thank you
any comments or
questions well di yes you're thank you for your talk it reminded me I used to
have a poster in my office that said everything should be made as simple as possible but not
simpler there you go it's by Albert Einstein nice okay there you go there
you go but not
simpler yeah
um I'm not sure I got the last line uh in the meaning is the ruined house the
are destroyed preconceptions yeah this is such a thank you Jay this is a good question and a
whisper will be heard in the place where the ruined house once
stood um you know it's this is how I'm interpreting it it's well actually
should ask you do you have an interpreting that the ruined house is that's where I went meaning like once I give up all that like all my
preconceived notions which is the bad house or if you want to think of it that way then I'll hear the true Inner Voice
come through and that's the whisper that I'm hearing for you know it's always the the true voice is hard to hear so the
whisper from me I'm reading it that way I know if that's yeah yeah I like it I like it I was also thinking that uh the
shouting will have stopped so then you can hear a whisper also right you know people yeah I I I I was like thought
well there's a number of ways I could go with this or I don't know if there's some other ways too probably have you
read his uh his translation of T Chang um you know I read that so many years
ago but it's so it's not in my head now he has one of the best translations for the T JS y y okay thank you Stephen
Mitchell translating the da ching and I apparently he done translates a number
of different languages so I didn't know this any other
comments okay so I'm wishing you all a wonderful evening thank
you and if you'd like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me otherwise have a great week