Hello and welcome to this meditation to this to red to insight meditation center
in Redwood City, California. And welcome to um to this uh uh YouTube community of
people coming together to meditate and to hear the dharma. I appreciate this
opportunity. And the topic for this week has been uh
something that maybe is not automatically welcome to to address, but
this is suffering in all the different forms that it takes. and um from the
mildest stress to the greatest catastrophes of life.
And Buddhism, Buddhist practice, the meditation practice we're doing was
designed to address some of the deepest uh existential issues of our life and
and um to address them directly uh and
um unflinchingly. So um
uh there's many different perspectives, many different uh ways of understanding,
seeing, experiencing what we might call suffering. And as we do this uh practice of
mindfulness, of samadei, of insight, a time comes when uh uh the challenges of
our life, the challenges of our direct experience, challenges of our emotions, emotional life,
uh our physical life uh is experienced,
is seen, is known from from a place of great stillness.
There's a place within. We find a place in awareness
in the heart, in the mind, deep inside, in the belly
or some place that has no location at all.
that there is profound sense of stillness,
something unmoving, something imperturbable.
It might be being inside in a very quiet,
still room,
looking out the window. And sometimes we have the sun and
springtime it's nice to see. And sometimes there's the winter storms with
lots of snow and
um snowstorms and wind and lightning.
And um the um
but we're inside and we're still the movement is outside
and it's cozy, it's nice, it's safe, it's it's uh it's comfortable to watch
the snowstorm. So rather than identifying with
suffering, rather than becoming it, rather than being the the victim of it
or the re receiver of it, the bearer of our challenges, there comes a time with
the deepening of samadei, the deepening of insight that we can gaze upon our challenges
from a place of profound stillness. stillness.
A stillness that's a little bit like the stillness of a vast open space.
Maybe a vast place, open spacious place in nature.
Maybe the vastness of a
large temple or cathedral where everything has certain kind of
stillness to it that holds it all.
So as we sit today, maybe with your imagination, maybe with
your all your senses or particular senses,
maybe you can find some way
of experiencing the present moment as it unfolds
from a place of stillness. Some place inside that doesn't move.
It's not doesn't go towards, doesn't go away. Some place that's so still inside that
is almost like there's nothing there to resist the experiences of life like empty
space. It just goes right through it.
So assuming a meditation posture
and adjusting little bit your positionality, positions
of your body to bring your body into some degree of
stillness. the body. So to to some degree
it moves less than usual.
And maybe it's the larger movements of the body that become still.
And within the wider stillness of the body,
become aware of the movement of the body breathing
and how That
movement of breathing
occurs together with the wider stillness
of the body.
And as you exhale
to relax into whatever stillness
you also feel Here.
There might be stillness of the body
that highlights the movements of the thinking mind,
the energy activation.
As you exhale,
let the activation of a thinking mind,
the edges of it dissolve into the stillness.
And if how you're mindful, how you're aware
also moves from one thing to another. If the mind wander wanders off in
thought and you bring it back, see if instead
you can recognize a way of being aware, being mindful
that doesn't move.
A still quiet knowing
like sitting quietly and very still
on a chair while you look out a window.
And the awareness doesn't move.
You don't move. Even though out the window
there's rain and wind and snow.
Know your direct experience without chasing it,
without going after anything.
without avoiding anything or trying to change anything.
from whatever is the stilllest nonmoving place that you find.
know the movements, the activities,
the experience you're having
where first and foremost you know the movement of breathing,
but you know it with an unme unmoving knowing
Whenever you have a chance, settle back
to the stillness that's here.
Settle back to maybe some core center.
that is unmoving
that maybe has no solidity.
It's more like the unmoving
space in the middle.
of a large peaceful space.
with whatever degree of calm or subtleness you have.
Feel your way. Imagine your way
to the place within that has the most stillness.
a place of unmoving awareness,
attention,
and from that unmoving place,
be aware of anything that fits the word dooka.
suffering stress,
discomfort, unpleasantness
and and gaze upon it from the stillness.
Know it with the unmoving mind
that is not touched, not affected
by the duka.
Gaze upon
What is unpleasant
from the simplicity, the home,
the sacredness of a deep,
imperturbable refuge. image
of unmoving awareness.
Maybe Stillness is like the still air when
there's no wind.
The still air that permeates
every area of space around you.
It's always there in the stillness
of a windless day.
Being aware from that still place
imperturbable.
And as we come to the end of this sitting
with the next few exhales,
relax. Settle back into whatever place of calm,
stillness,
sense of ease that might be here.
And then with your imagination gaze upon the world
kindly.
Be still and gaze upon the world kindly.
Be still and gaze upon the world kindly
with a heart that has the well-wishing of others. close at
close by.
May all beings be happy.
May all beings, be safe.
May all beings be peaceful.
May all beings be free.
And may it be that each of us with our inner stillness
can gaze upon others nonreactively.
And in that non-reactivity, there's a room for people to feel safe,
peaceful, and free
in how we relate to them.
[Music]
Hello and welcome to this continuing series on insight, the insight of
insight meditation. And currently we're looking at the topic
of duka, the poly word for suffering or stress, d-stress.
And uh one of the learnings to be had through meditation, through mindfulness
practice, through samadei practice is that um our experience of ourselves,
our experience of the world, our experience of others is very much contingent upon the state
of mind we have. And uh and if we don't know that then we
assume that whatever way we're experiencing the world ourselves um is how how things are.
But if we begin appreciating the state of our mind, how stable the mind heart
is, how concentrated it is, how calm it is, how open it is, how receptive it is.
Um there's a whole slew of ways how how clear the mindfulness is. The state of
the mind has a big influ im influence in how we know ourselves, how we know
others, how we know the world and how uh and because the state of the mind can
vary quite a bit, the uh how we understand see the world and ourselves
can vary quite a bit too. And this is a radical thing to understand and very
different than how most people I believe go about their day. Uh most people don't
know that there's a huge range of states of minds in which we can live in
and uh and uh and so to not
uh take as authoritative whatever way whatever state whatever view that we
have at any given time. And so the state of mind is fluid and changeable. And it
becomes more so when we uh are a meditator. When we learn how to let go,
we learn to get focused. We learn to get become calm. We're moving through in
between different states of mind. And uh we begin appreciating that whatever
state of mind we in is just the state of mind for now.
And the way in which we see the world becomes a little bit more like a question mark like oh or more like
appreciation. This also is uh not necessarily the absolute truth. This
also is just a byproduct of the state of the mind that we have. And uh I think
the more people meditate the more they come to a profound appreciation that uh
of the role the state of mind has in how we know the world, how we experience the
world. Uh it's a particular state of mind where we see the world as a dangerous place.
Of course, the world is dangerous to some degree, but uh but to constantly
see it through that lens is a is a product of a particular state of mind or
art. to see the world as um as um
a difficult place, to see the world as a beautiful place, to see the world as a
um as a place of belonging. To see the world as a place where we don't belong.
To see the world as as a um ours, see the world as not ours.
to see the world as um uh or to see ourselves as a as a wonderful person,
see ourselves as a difficult person, see ourselves as an inadequate person, uh all those conclusions, all those
things are in part the product of a certain state of mind. And if we're
navigating these views, these ideas about the world and only trying to
readjust, fix, solve the the world, solve ourselves without appreciating the
very way in which we're looking is part of the part of the solution, part of the
what's what's going on. And um and so rather than changing the world,
sometimes we learn to change our mind. And as we learn to change our mind and
go through all kinds of different states of mind, we're all kinds of different ways of seeing and experiencing
ourselves in the world. Then any particular state that we have in any
given moment, we start seeing well that's just how it is now. This is
impermanent. It's changing. It's not fixed. This is not necessarily the absolute eternal truth. This is just
what's real and happening at this moment. And we learn to hold it lightly.
We learn to not make grand conclusions. We learn how not to uh fall into the
delusion of permanence. It's always going to be this way.
And even to this day, I fall into little states of permanence like thinking kind
of almost subconsciously thinking sometimes, oh, this is how it is and I just have to kind of figure out or cope
with it. And um and the particularly way is sometimes when I have a lot of things
I have to do, I feel a little bit maybe harried or a little bit the pressure of my to-do list. And um and at some point
when I feel it's strong enough, I've learned to just stop and sit and meditate for a few minutes. and uh and
my state of mind quiets and I realized that I was the state of mind was one
that was had pressure in it, anxiety in it or or responsibility that was in the
forefront and it had a certain authority and I thought this is how it is. But when I
set meditate, the tension of responsibility, the tension of
the to-do list or wanting or to finish or anxiety dissipates and now I see
things in a very different way. And so this means that when I uh the more I am
aware of this, the freer I can be and the easier it is to move between states.
So it's a long introduction to point out that uh how we see suffering, how we
experience it, how we interpret it, our relationship to it has a lot to do with
the state of mind that we have. And if we're only have one state of mind that
we know that we're trying to address suffering, um it might be,
you know, like the bird that's pecking on the window. it's never going to get into the window. But um but it doesn't
know any better. And so uh the um
so sometimes what we're we want to do is not try to solve the problem in the state of mind in which the problem has
appeared. Sometimes when we want to uh change our state of mind, our ch our our state of
heart by becoming calmer, more centered and more settled to develop a clear
sense of present moment awareness where the present moment awareness is not
caught in the grip of our preoccupations and concerns. And um so as we begin to have this
fluidity, as we meditate, there comes a time when we become uh aware or we the
state of mind is characterized by being um very still, imperturbable,
nonreactive. The state of mind is spacious,
open, receptive. The state of mind is aquatous,
steady, and sometimes feels very broad. It feels
like the state of mind, the awareness maybe feels like it's expands way beyond
the boundaries of the body. Or maybe it feels like there's a quiet still place
deep, deep inside where that's the refuge, that's the home. And we're not
turning away from anything. We're not avoiding anything. We're quite available
for whatever shows up. But uh but we're available from this quiet, peaceful
place. like when I would went I lived for a while with my greatg grandmother
and she lived in a small little apartment in a three-story apartment
building and and I had a little room on the side and um and she doesn't seem
like she's so old now that I'm so old but back then she was in her 80s and and
she would sit in her chair kind of very soft maybe like a rocking chair or something with a blanket over her knees
and and I would go visit her in her small little room, a living room where she was in and
filled with little white lace that she had uh crocheted, I guess, on the table
and different places and um and we wouldn't talk very much and we would
just sit in silence together. She'd be very still and quiet, but it was so
comforting to be with her. I felt like this was peace, this was love, this was
um a wonderful wonderful just to be with her and accompany her and her to
accompany me and um and so this this you know and I'm she went through a lot of
challenges in her life and um and so to her to come to this place of peace and
quiet I think was a refuge for her too and it was certainly a refuge for me. So
to find that come to that place deep inside ourselves to be able to let go of
the ordinary states of mind that sometimes we're attached to in a ways we don't even realize how attached we are
to being in this kind of way in the mind and to let all the tension in the mind
dissipate and quiet and come to a place where we can gaze upon our suffering
quietly. Gaze upon suffering peacefully. Gaze upon suffering without being for
and against it, without trying to fix it, without defining ourselves by it,
without being the victim of suffering. But we gaze upon it with a this
stillness as a a imperturbable
unmoving kind of awareness that maybe is everywhere at the same time or maybe is
at the center of all things or something. But there's a the shifting
states of mind to come to a place where we know that we can be aware of anything
at all and not be affected by it not be
troubled by it. So in relationship to suffering to suffer but not be troubled
by it to feel stress feel discomfort and not be preoccupied be it caught in it
but to kind of be our own great grandmother just peacefully quiet
um present available seeing knowing not shutting anything out
but knowing from an imperturbable able place knowing from a non-reactive place
knowing from a profound stillness within. This isn't easy to do.
But as we go through some the the practice of samadei, the practices of
insight, uh we're going through different states of mind. And at some point we start feeling, sensing,
intuiting um this place of profound stillness
that has space to let everything be just as it is.
Nothing has to change, but we're aware of it in a still way.
And in relationship to suffering, we know suffering, but we're not
troubled by suffering. We know suffering, but we don't suffer
because we're suffering. We just know the discomfort as discomfort. We just know the stress as
the stress, the tension as the tension. And it's not anything that needs to be
fixed or solved because
in that place of stillness in a certain kind of way there are no
problems. It's just what is here. And this is not the absolute state. This
is not the final conclusion. This is not how it's supposed to be what I'm talking about today.
But it's one particular state of mind that we can tap into. And as a dharma
teacher uh when I'm supporting other people in practice, I'm less interested
in the state of mind that people attain or have than I'm interested in the
fluidity, the ease by which people can move between different states of mind.
That's where the freedom is. And as we become more free and relaxed and can move freely between states of mind, then
at some point this idea of the unmoving, imperturbable, still aquamous mind
becomes highlighted and it becomes a gamecher to be able to
understand suffering in this kind of very free way where we're not defined by it or troubled by it. And then we might
that might carry over into our ordinary states of mind where we begin now see how contingent and uh and our reactivity
is and how unnecessary our reactivity is and we can learn to
leave suffering alone and be free.
So I hope this makes sense and um and uh I hope it doesn't trouble you. The idea
is to support you to be untroubled through all this and we'll continue this
uh adventure uh tomorrow. Thank you.