so hello and welcome and here we are in our
meditation
session and one of the Arts of samadi is the
careful orientation towards pleasure
and underneath this or more fundamental is the way that mindfulness
practice Buddhist practice is meant to be a very
realistic understanding seeing acknowledgment of suffering of our
difficulties and to see them clearly one of the ways to care for it
is is not to do so directly but to do it indirectly through
the path of samadi and that should be done carefully and wisely not as a ver aversion to our
difficulties but rather with a a care for them a love for them a love for
ourselves and so the orientation towards pleasure is uh in a way it's done with a
with a gentle message that that you care for yourself you care for the suffering
and this is a way of doing it and then to be modest in the
orientation towards pleasure and when we first sit down it might be to notice just this the relief
of sitting down after maybe a busy day or a lot of activity and just the
Simplicity of just breathing and being and like you have permission to not
accomplish anything not to go through Tod doist but just to be be breathing
and to feel the relief the pleasure the goodness of
that and uh and so then to uh
feel uh is there any sense of pleasure or enjoyment or goodness or rightness in
the body in the mind and
to gently allow it to be there to appreciate it to let it be part of the
meditation sometimes the priorities or the biases towards the difficulties and
the pain and the suffering sometimes the priorities is overdone towards
um uh towards
um towards uh the pleasure and the joy so before we continue I wouldn't be
reassured that uh you are seeing the screen because I had trouble of making
the the the YouTube screen um so it looks like we are seeing
it
um so I wonder if someone could point out
that they are seeing they're that we're connected video is fine great thank
you uh yes to the screen the good okay
good I believe that maybe the wires here at IMC had gotten loose since yesterday
and so when I first logged on I couldn't make it work so
pleasure the pleasure of things working well enough so to begin the
meditation to uh assume a meditation a meditation posture
that gives you the pleasure of being alert the pleasure of being
present through your embodied body so that means not the pleasure of
relaxing in a couch or something but the pleasure of being
somehow with the body in the appropriate way whether it's laying down or sitting or standing
standing some appropriate way where there's an intention expressed through
the body to be
here in a way that has some pleasure to it some it's feels like it's inspiring
or good to be
alert and to gently close close the
eyes and then take time to scan through the
body to recognize where it's Pleasant and comfortable in your body and where
it isn't and a kind of matter of fact simple acknowledgment of how it is in
different parts of the body so that parts that are uncomfortable are at least acknowledged
and
known and maybe continuing this way but taking a few long slow deep
breaths so as you breathe in you're connecting to some part of your body body and as you exhale you're softening
relaxing opening that part of the body
and to let your breathing return to
normal and there's a pleasure or Pleasant feeling that can come with
relaxing so as you breathe in feel the muscles of your
face and as you exhale soften relax the the
face around the eyes the
Jaws feeling this subtle pleasure or goodness that comes with
relaxing on the inhale to feel the shoulder shoulders and the exhale to
relax on the inhale to feel the
belly on the exhale to soften the belly
on the inhale to feel the thinking mind and on the exhale exhale to soften
open expand the thinking mind into the quiet around you
and then on the inhale feeling the body's experience of
breathing in wherever that is Pleasant or connecting
or
appreciated and on the exhale
relaxing the body
breathing breathing in a normal
way feel if there's any pleasure or
pleasantness or sweetness or or
rightness in the direct experience of the body
breathing and to feel
that it can be quite subtle the pleasure
and if you feel some of the pleasure or pleasantness of
breathing can you slightly adjust your
breathing to let there be more
pleasure maybe extending the
exhale extending the inhale Maybe by Maybe by relaxing
something in your torso
maybe the pleasure is not connected directly with breathing but rather the gentle
influence that the movements of breathing have beond the edges of the
movement connecting to the inhale at the beginning of the
inhale connecting to the exhale the beginning of the
exhale and then in a way that feels
Pleasant easeful sustain the attention through the whole
length of the inhale the whole length of the
exhale staying close to the feelings of
pleasure so that it's easier to stay with the
breathing because the mind enjoys a
pleasure
e
for
e e
whatever way you're you're calm
settled peaceful Fe feel the pleasure of
that
e
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to again feel whatever is
Pleasant sweet or pleasurable in our body our hearts our
minds
and to imagine that it's a light the light of pleasure the light of
sweetness that can radiate from us out into the
world that staying close to a feeling of
well-being of being com comtable in our bodies and
Minds allows us to be with other people in ways that can spread good
will spread the sweetness the
goodness the The Joy the
pleasure as we experience meditative
Joy well-being peace and calm may it spread from us in our words
our deeds and our
attitudes may it be that the way that we
practice creates the conditions for us to to go into the world to make the
world a better place for others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank
you e
so to continue this series on samadi that uh as at certain point as
the mind and body get settled collected
unified as it gets stabilized
um the means for the support for entering into the Temple of deep
Samar is to uh is through the doorway of
pleasure not necessarily sensual pleasure but certainly an embodied
pleasure that begins to feel like a sense of well-being joy and
happiness and so you're allowed to take in feel be nourished by
saturated by well-being when you're doing Samari
practice and so to be oriented towards it in just the right way to not be
attached to it expecting it pushing for it um but rather
to be open to it to allow it to acknowledge it when it's there to appreciate it and as it's there to
gently allow it to there be a kind of a feedback loop between the joy the
pleasure to and the meditation and the and the focus on breathing focus on your
primary object and so that uh the joy the pleasure um keeps you
connected and it's a feedback loop where that as you get more St stable more
engaged more fully in the experience of of the breathing of the meditation you
can feel that the well-being shifts and changes gets richer gets
stronger and um so this is not uh it can seem like
you're you know one in or you know clinging or trying to make something
happen it can some people get tense but the IDE is to stay relaxed almost as if
you're not expecting anything to happen but you're allowing it samadi willing so
willing let the let the The Joy the well-being spread and one of the little tools for
this is to uh have a little half smile smile turn up the corners of your mouth
just a little bit until you feel a sense of pleasure there and uh and let that pleasure uh uh
be the support to keep you connected keep you here in the present moment and um some people will shift
then from from the breathing to the pleasure the the physical pleasure of the smile and get absorbed in that but I
recommend that you just use it as a background support as a that as a as a pointer as a
encouragement stay stay with a breath continue stabilizing continue entering
into the world of breathing and as we do this massage of connecting and
sustaining uh it almost it can be in harmony with breathing in and breathing
out where we gently lovingly connect to the beginning of the inhale and that
massage of sustaining is there as the the chest the Torso fills with air we
feel the expansion the movement and the becoming larger and then we connect to the exhale
and and uh and um sustain the attention
feeling the the pleasure of the smoothness the smoothness the release
the softening the settling that can be there in the exhale and sometimes it's nice to feel
the slight pause at the end of the exhale if that's really easy to do uh
and feeling The Emptiness of it the the lack of anything um the relief in a
sense of just being for a moment or two in that pause and because of the pause the call
to breathe in is maybe a little bit stronger so it's a little bit more pleasant to breathe in because the body
somehow wants it we're not holding the breath for a long time there's no holding really just a pause to
accentuate being there with the breath and enjoying it and
um and uh and then part of this then is to that uh this focus on somebody on
breathing and the pleasure of it is meant to be a way to help the thinking
mind become quieter and now the thinking mind is
fueled by focusing on thinking itself the food for discursive thinking
distracted thinking is we lose our attention in the thinking but if the
attention goes somewhere else then the thinking is not being fed so much it might be there in the background but
it's the the preoccupation that being caught in it is not being fed and often
the thinking becomes quieter but it's also possible to participate in quieting
the Mind by relaxing the the thinking muscle to relax the tension uh the
pressure the contraction or round thinking and maybe softening the mind
opening the mind making this feeling the sense of the Mind become expansive and
open um and so sometimes that can happen on the exhale as you exhale let the thoughts
evaporate float away so that there's more space in the
mind the the absence of thoughts is not just a pure absence it's an absence
that'll kind of make room to feel the joy the pleasure it's an absence that
makes makes it you feel it almost with the experience of samadi with the
goodness of it with the breathing with the Sensations with the
pleasure and so there is a kind of Art in in the samade of knowing how to give
yourself fully to the experience without straining of giving yourself fully to it
while we relax and while you uh um you know let
go the first time I ever got instructions in samade specifically for
purpose of samade I was told it was all about letting go and I thought that was a useful
instruction to get because then um I kind of understood not to cling not to
Crave not to be pushing not to be trying to make something happen um but just
keep letting go it's almost letting go into breathing letting go into samade
letting go into uh this uh this uh Nur in
settled enjoyable place within and um and what's uh really
special that can happen is that the pleasure The Joy the well-being of
somebody belongs to a different operating system within us than the operating system of difficult
emotions sadness grief depression distress it's a different operating
system than a physical aching and pains in our body and so because it's a whole
different operating system it can operate beautifully wonderfully
without um um feeling that we're being
somehow disloyal or somehow bypassing or
somehow um that we have to kind of fix the emotional difficulties we have
first so we can get concentrated uh it's more the opposite
that as we can into somebody it puts us in a much better place to meet and
understand and address our suffering and this is one of the great possibilities
from samade enter into samade get really Ed meditation to get really stable and
settled and calm and then when you come out of meditation glance and look at your challenges you
have and see if you can see see it now in different eyes see it from a
different context a different frame of reference and um and uh you might find
yourself living in a kind of different world with a stable quiet settled body
and mind then the world you see when you're spinning in your thoughts and preoccupations spinning in your
suffering so that it's almost like the glasses by which you see are the glasses
of suffering if the glasses you're seeing is the glasses of calm well-being peace
then you can address and understand and have room and capacity to be with your difficulties in a much better
way so the art of samadi includes the art of how of being
attuned to our body heart and Minds capacity City for pleasure for
well-being which moves into joy and happiness and some of the most Sublime
forms of Happiness can come as we dip into into deeper and deeper
samade and um and as uh and if sometimes the Joy or the happiness gets quite
strong be rest assured that there's better things than joy and there's
better things than happiness so these are just was way way points along the way that strong pleasure if there's it
is strong the joy the well-being these are just uh uh means along the way uh
they're not the end so um so for today uh as you go
through your day you might want to see if you can spend more
time appreciating the pleasures that are already here so don't go out and you
know Buy Pleasant pleasurable food so you can have pleasure just as you go
about your daily life check in regularly today to notice the pleasures that are
already here many people are so busy they don't Avail themselves with
pleasure that's already here The Simple Pleasures of Life stay closer to it and
maybe staying closer to the pleasure pleasures of life will also keep you close to being calm in the middle of it
um because it means that with stay giving time for the pleasures means that
you're not fueling and continuing the spinning mind the pressured
mind the tense mind but take time today today you have
permission if I'm allowed to give you permission to spend the day being a
tuned to The Simple Pleasures of of life as they become available and uh see what difference it
makes by the end of the day so thank you very
much and um and I'll continue this samade uh later tomorrow thank you