so good morning everyone and so a couple of announcements so uh first I want to say
I'm so delighted when we do these polux and teas here on Sunday and people who stay and the sense of community that
comes and so you're all welcome to stay the fact that there's not a lot of food
is incidental to what we're doing the real thing is just coming together and and um and uh most of you
can probably if you don't get enough food at this meal
can Pro probably find a little bit more later in the day
somewhere so please stay don't don't be shy and uh and then also um many of you
know we've been doing this fundraising for save the children that was meant to go for about a week but we kept the the
Donate button up and um and so now um uh
we've raised $95,000 it doesn't show that on the save the
save the children um kind of site yet but it it will but that's pretty
impressive and um I guess it's not over officially it's over but things
money keeps being donated so who knows maybe we'll get to 100,000 it's it's
very inspiring to me uh just in general but also at these times that a community
of people can come together in this kind of way and collectively make such a big impression impact and it's almost a
statement uh of of what a community what a society can do at a time when we have
a society that's showing what it can take away what it can stop doing and uh to you know save the children is one of
those uh wonderful organizations that uh uh had a contract with the uh United
States agency of International Development uh to they were count on
money it was promised basically and then suddenly it was taken away and so all these people who were employed by them
all this food that they were bringing in medicine so it's kind of a tragic thing that to have happen the way it happened
and so but to have people step up as communities to I mean we're making only a small difference but it's a I think
it's a beautiful thing and I'm inspired by it and I want to thank you all participated and if you want to make a
donation still maybe we get up to 100,000 um uh it's still on IMCU website
that there's a red banner and on top and um
so um you know I've been thinking this last week just in general more than I
usually do what to teach because of uh National world
affairs and um and I would like to uh make a case that one of the very strong
contributions that Buddhism has to our society our world now and in general is
its emphasis on on ethics on virtue and that uh in ethics and virtue
maybe not is not the Super popular topic but that how what it's popular how it
comes in Buddhism is that it's also an expression a manifestation of what
happens to people when they do Buddhist practice if you do mindfulness well what
comes is a heightened sensitivity to yourself in the world and it's that
heightened sensitivity uh will almost in inevitably lead to what can be called an
ethical sensitivity a heightened ethical sensitivity because we start feeling
intimately in ourselves that um what harms ourselves how we we we kind of violate
ourselves even to use dramatic language uh we harm ourselves we shut ourselves
down we alienate ourselves from ourselves that when it h when we do things that are intentionally harmful
for others to others and um and also where there's a heightened ethical sensitivity to how
harm affects other people the our own way of harming people but also how they're harmed by others in our
society and the Buddha was clearly um uh Champion the idea that when we see harm
being done to others we should speak up that we shouldn't be passive about that
and so that this ethical sensitivity then we become increasingly sensitive to
to how people are being harmed by unethical Behavior by harmful behavior and and uh we do something
really good for ourselves if we know how from this place of ethical sensitivity
to speak up and the question is what is that speaking up look like how is it
different than being angry how's it different than responding from hate how
what what happens when we come from this deeper ethical sensitivity that Dharma practice inspires what does that look
like and one of the things it looks like it looks like it's in the classic Buddhist language it's virtue virtuous
it's ethical uh or even more classical is that um the language in Buddhism
would be that it's beautiful the one of the words words for ethics is beauty it's something
beautiful behavior and another uh word is wholesome and uh and wholesome in
English popularly I think kind of has a connotations of healthy so it's a healthy
response um U but I like the atmology of the word which is that it's uh it's
wholesome as part of the whole and uh and the UNH wholesome is that which is not part of the whole
there's UNH wholesome Behavior um that not beautiful Behavior that's
unethical where we actually make ourselves fragmented we we're responding from only
part of who we are because we can't really be involved in causing harm to
others without losing touch with our whole with our deeper sensitivity and so you know in Buddhism
this idea of being wholesome being um is really a central move movement of
Buddhism to live in a wholesome way to act wholesome from the whole from the beauty that we have and so ethical
sensitivity is also sensitivity from our Beauty and I don't know how many people
how many of you relate to that you that there's something beautiful inside of you but that's kind of the direction
that Buddhist practice is going they discover that there is beauty there's inner beauty there's a kind of a beauty
that we practice in we live in we are inspired by we come from and what does
it what does it mean to respond to and and uh and resist to stand opposed to or
to speak up for Injustice in the world in a way that's
beautiful and most people don't put those two together because it's somehow
when there's Injustice it demands righteous action it demands Fury
it demands somehow we're now getting into the world of conflict and conflict
must mean that there's I don't know aggression assertiveness being upset being
demanding doing something lot a lot of behavior which is not
beautiful and so what does it mean to be beautiful not in a way that
avoids but steps up and does so this emphasis on virtue on
Beauty on ethics um is I think a very important one to consider in the current
climate of things because um uh from all my lifetime until last month
I thought America was based on the rule of law and uh and now we have a president
who says he's Above the Law or he he's not above the law really but he decides the
law if he decides that's a law I mean that's a phenomenal new thing that I've
never would have imagined would have come out of this in this country presidents in this
country and um so but it basically means that uh means one person is above the
law and the rule of law means that everyone is responsible to the
law but uh uh philosophers of or or
political scientists who studied the uh the idea of rule of law have pointed out
that it has a flaw that uh the flaw is that uh it's
too easy to have loopholes it's too easy easy to have gray zones in which uh people kind of
manage to get by breaking the law or not not adhering to the ethics of the law
it's too easy now in a society where there's capitalism and huge corporations
with lots of money it's too easy to shape the laws in your
favor so just a rule of law by itself is not enough and some some people say that
you need something else and what you need is virtue and uh and that that idea goes
back to ancient India even it goes back to the Greeks it goes back to ancient India where they recognize this issue
and in Ancient India before Buddhism I think uh there was the idea that um um
the law was the Dharma and sometimes the word Dharma in certain context in India
Indian text when it translated into English is translated as the law and
that uh even Kings have to adhere to that law the Dharma law the and one of
those laws that uh in Ancient India for a king uh if a person doesn't follow
this particular law they forfeit their right to be king and uh and that was uh
to protect everyone their job is to be protectors and if they don't do that if they're the ones who harm them then they
forfeit their their Authority their right to have that so that's considered an ancient law
and uh and uh that even the king the monarchs had to adhere to and um and
Buddhism also that uh last week or two weeks ago I talked about the ancient myth that the Buddha presented that uh
if a king doesn't follow the Dharma doesn't follow particular caring for the poor that uh then uh society
unravels and um and so this idea and the way it it reels the way it comes back to together
is when people start living ethically so when when the Monarch is
unethical Society falls apart but when the people are ethical they can come back together
again so that means that we all have a role and uh and it's a happy
role I think too often in in uh english- speaking countries I get the sense that
the idea of Ethics is a little bit of a burden it's a little bit like you know
you know oh no and certainly when I you know when I grew up um I actually thought ethics was
kind of like a four-letter word you know I you know it you know it wasn't really
you know I was growing up there was a lot of ideas that there was a lot of hypocrisy ethical hypocrisy in our
society and ethics people who are really ethical kind of were Hypocrites somehow
or that they were superficial or they were just kind of polanish or it wasn't really real and and and so there was a
whole generation of the counterculture that I was part of that was looking for something that was more authentic and
looking for another way of living and so there was a kind of kind of a rejection of Ethics at least for me without being
unethical mostly because I had a lack of imagination and so so but you know so I
was you know it wasn't really doing anything unethical but what was surprised to me and a great source of
joy for me was through buddh practice to discover how wonderful it is to have
this ethical sensitivity ethical sensibility from the inside out I had no
idea that there was a reference inside that of beauty and it was even even a
word that the only word I could describe it to myself which is also a taboo word for
many years was the word purity uh Purity we also represented all
kinds of things that were problematic in the Puritans and things like that but then lo and behold to discover that
there was something that felt really pure inside that was the best word for it sometimes I try to I still try to
slip around using that word uh by calling it clean it feels really clean and cleansed
rather than purified and um but to discover this place inside and that that's a place
where there's a love for for for this Sensibility ility for this way of being
it is love almost and that and that you don't want to violate it it's is it harm and I
remember when I first discovered this on retreat in Thailand that uh I could I
could see that if I had certain thoughts that were you know maybe a little bit unethical that uh I could feel that
immediately was violating this thing inside or kind of diminishing it or harming it and so the idea was to keep
coming back to that and trusting and living in it and it's you know it's always in
navigation negotiation it's always discovering you know how this works in
different different circumstances and um but for the Buddha
when he you know uh emphasized this uh kind of the importance of ethical life
there was a wonderful little teaching it's a place where uh he's he called it
uh kind of this is the teaching this is the teaching of all the Buddhas so that's quite nice you know
not just him but all the Buddhas um it's a it's a three line it's a four-line
verse it goes um don't
do what is Barren don't do what is
deadening engage in what is wholesome purify the
mind this is the teachings of the Buddha the first line is sometimes
translated as evil don't do evil and there's kind of a question of what this
ancient Indian word means but uh but I like the word some
people have tried using Baron or deadening and what I like about that is evil doesn't necessarily point back to
the effect that those behaviors have or where where they come from but Barren or
or um deadening uh indicates where they come from and their effect that they
have on us so to do really harmful things in the world with a evil intent
in a sense um comes from baren place inside comes from a place of that's not
really full and wholesome and alive from that beauty and the effect it has is
kind of deadening on people and um something dies inside as a
result and um so um so that that's kind
of considered that Buddhism in a nutshell don't do what's
Barren do what is wholesome purify the mind or the
heart and um that's it now you know you can go
home and uh but this of the wholesome and one of the first and uh
one of the ways one of the uh classic descriptions of what is wholesome when there's a list of things that are
wholesome begins with not killing not harming so now I want to read this is
the opening you know just some people call it the the beginning of the Buddhist Bible because it's the DAP and
just there's no real like first like the Bible has uh you know in the be you know
beginning there was kind of it has a kind of real real beginning of it of it
a Buddhism kind of like a text that has like the beginning of the Canon but the closest thing maybe is this these these
verses here all
actions are preceded by mind led by mind made by mind speak or act with a
corrupted mind and suffering follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the hoof of the
ox all action is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind speak or act with a
peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never departing Shadow
so so what you how where you act from makes a huge difference so then it goes
on he abused me or let's say it a little differently they abused me
they attacked me they defeated me they robbed me for those carrying on like
this hatred does not end they abused me they attacked me they
defeated me they robbed me for those not carrying on like this hatred
ends hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it end
this is an ancient truth and U many people translate it a little differently it's it's allowed this is a
very literal translation and the alternative is hatred never ends through
hatred by non-hate alone does it end this is an ancient truth
this is uh Martin Luther King Jr a basic fact that characterizes
nonviolence resistance is that it does not seek to defeat or humiliate the
opponent but to opponents but to win over their friendship and
understanding isn't that is that remarkable I would say that's beautiful what a beautiful
thing that's very different than wanting to kill them or
or all kinds of things get rid of
them so that's an example that under the rule of law is
virtue under the rule of law is ethics under rule of law is the Dharma and here
the Dharma of Love of care of respect for
people love is not a weak passive love it is Love In
Action love seeking to preserve and create community so generative love love that
creates Community unity and people and this was a huge part of the Buddhist teaching
also that uh uh when we speak we should speak in a ways that unit people not in
ways that divide people so how do we do that with people that we disagree with
how do we do with people who are even harming us do we do this and um how do
we do this and I want to read another piece from Martin Luther
King here we go hold you have your seat belts
on so I guess uh he's he's quoting uh Mahatma
Gandhi rivers of blood may have to flow before we gain
our freedom rivers of blood may have to flow before we great gain our
freedom but it must be our
blood isn't that quite something so this is the recognition
that these great proponents of non-violent resistance that uh this is not for the
Cowardly it's not for the weak this was for the strong and this had to be done with
great courage great Beauty great dedication something that some deeper value that uh of ethics of of of virtue
of Love of community of unity that um I mean there's plenty of
people who are willing to die for their country if they have a gun in their
hand then people people go to war for that purpose you know they're willing they're you know but how many people are
willing to die without a gun in their hand and I think what they're saying is
that's required too to make a
difference so
um so if you read something like dapada you find there's a kind of a
a beat a rhythm that goes through it that is emphasizing nonviolence
peace better than a thousand meaningless statements is one meaningful word which
having been heard brings peace better than a thousand meaningless
verses is one meaningful verse one line of a verse which having been heard
brings peace everyone trembles at violence all
fear death seeing others as being like yourself do not kill or cause others to
kill all tremble at violence life is there for all seeing others as being
like yourself do not kill or cause others to kill this is one of the
primary rationals that Buddha gives for nonviolence Ence is that just like you don't want to
die you want to live so others want to and so to kind of empathize or
understand this deep source of uh deep wish de deep movement of people's inner
life and respect it see people as
oneself whoever uses violence to harm the nonviolent and
innocent quickly goes to one of 10 conditions intense pain and great loss
bodily injury or Insanity serious illness or vicious slander oppression
from rulers or the loss of relatives houses consumed by fire and wealth
destroyed well we see plenty of examples that that doesn't happen fast enough
so here's this word uh evil that that I translate now as Barren or or
deadening evil is done by oneself Alone by oneself is one
defiled evil is avoided by oneself by oneself alone is one
purified Purity and impurity depend on oneself no one can pure purify
another don't give up your own welfare for the sake of others welfare however
great clearly know your own welfare and be intent on the highest
good some people are really disturbed by this verse because you're supposed to be altruistic your welfare shouldn't count
you should really you know sacrifice yourself for the welfare of others this is not what the Buddha taught because he
taught this deep place of ethical sensitivity which is the beautiful place
is our welfare the highest welfare we can discover inside of ourselves and
from that we can act don't sacrifice that if you act don't sacrifice it if
you're the one who's standing in front of the tanks in kinan square you might be asked to do that
conquer anger with non- anger conquer Wicked wickedness with
goodness conquer stinginess with giving and a liar with
truth so it's not you know go to court this is calling upon this Dharma
this virtue this inner law to who we
are it's easy to see The Faults of others but hard to see one's own
fault when sifts out fults of others like chaff but conceals one's own as a
cheat conceals a bad throw of a
dice one is not just who judges a case
hastily one doesn't fire people justly if you fire them
hastily a wise person considers both what is and isn't right guiding others
without force impartially and in accord with the Dharma one is called a guardian
of the D Dharma intelligent and just so here the Dharma doesn't mean Buddhist
teachings here the Dharma means the law the truth this underlying virtue that we
that kind of built into a deep ethical sensitivity and sometimes d word Dharma
can be translated as Justice guiding others without force
impartially and in accord with the Dharma what is called the guardian of the Dharma intelligent and
just so couple of more from the dapada not by harming living beings is one a
noble one by being harmless to all living beings when is called a noble
one having given up violence towards both towards beings both timid and
strong whoever neither kills nor causes others to kill I call a Brahman
so there's emphasis on nonviolence but that doesn't mean that there's not nonviolent
resistance and I think that would be the way that uh Buddhists
respond but I would like to say there kind of the theme of this talk is not that per se but to rather to say that um
underneath the rule of law there has to be virtue there has to be an understanding of ethics and and whether the society as
a whole can learn that in time we don't know but uh that's the kind of specialty
of what we want to con convey to the world and bring to the world and one of the ways to do it is uh by how we live
and our action and one of the ways we're going to live it some of us I feel is
always this has been true ever since I was young I felt and one of the reasons
I came to Buddhism was so we could be ready for what comes and I was ready
I've been ready for sometimes where I've s seen violence around me I've seen people
fighting uh physically fighting each other in the streets and places and communities and uh
and my instinct I think coming out of this practice was to approach to get to see what I could do
to stop it and sometimes not clear I was successful but
remember the first time I did this really was in the middle of an intersection in San Francisco and this
woman was kind of being attacked by big men she was trying to get away from them
so I stood between her and them but they were bigger than me big and strong so
they took a step towards me so I took a step
back and they took a step towards me you know I was still standing in the
middle but I took a step back so I didn't know what to do who got be stepping back and then this person came
off the sidewalk into the intersection and said to these two big guys
hey uh if I was in the situation of this woman I I hope you would come and help
me they that immediately calmed the whole situation down just that saying that statement wasn't that something he
knew that person figured out what to say or that was just that was enough so
maybe maybe my role was just to you know slow this thing down long enough so he
could show up and then I once um I've told this
story here near my house there was people also F getting ready to fight and
two people in a group of people outside of a house and then I
approached but I approached and stood be it was in the street right so I I carefully stood behind a car I didn't
want to get too close I didn't know what was going to happen there and I said um
I'm a minister can I help and uh technically I'm a
minister legally I'm the minister so sometimes I use that
card and uh and every everything calmed down so and the last time I did
something like this was a believe it or not there were people
playing frisbee golf who were having two different
people with having some huge conflict around frisbe Gulf and they were also
big muscular guys and and uh and they and they started
actually hitting each other and falling on the ground beating each other up so again again they were much bigger and
stronger than me and who am I to go do anything so I didn't know what to do but
I started walking towards them but before any I don't think anybody noticed before I could get to them their friends
pulled them apart that was nice I'm glad
because I don't know what I would have done but um but you know these are all
examples of doing something responding being ready are you ready and whose blood is going to flow
are you ready to have it be your blood what does that mean what kind of Courage is needed what kind of healthy
appropriate understanding would allow for that to happen I'm still very deeply touched by
uh the John Lewis civil rights leader for what he did but the the the
thing that most touches me is a story of U First what had leading up to the story
was he did his uh walk across this bridge in in U
Alabama that um and that police were waiting the other side and they were
marching for civil rights and um and they kept walking and then they were beat up they were with B batons and he
got damaged and hurt and I think he ended up with a concussion and uh uh and then ended up
being a congressman and uh for many years and
then uh something like 40 years later uh oh or he was beat up repeatedly
not just that time but before that he would go and do these protests in in U
in uh bus stations and um and there were these kuk CL people who came and would beat him up
and he was beat a couple of times also would to you know pretty pretty badly and 40 years after one of these
beating UPS the man who beat him up came to his office in congress with his son
to apologize 40
years that's impressive we don't see the good results right away sometimes but
you know he touched someone very deeply
so what what how are we going to touch what are we going to do
so we I don't know I don't know what we should do it's
complicated all these different points of view that go on in our society but there's a very interesting thing that uh
I wonder wondering if there are nonpartisan things nonpartisan seems to be more like bringing Community together
nonpartisan seems more like like maybe something that is uh coming from love or
care and supposedly there's a nonpartisan um thing that's going to happen on Friday on February 28th
there's been economic boycott of the major corporations don't buy and uh and that's very interesting
because it's not exactly political but it's actually addressing
one of the forces in society that are kind of part the law and not part of the
law the major corporations are the ones who can kind of find their ways around it or can buy politicians and do all
kinds of things and um and and corporations they're not really run on
virtue the corporations are run on making money which is a very different
decisions that uh they make and uh and so to make an impression
on them that there are that people have power too people have uh can respond to them and
they're not they're accountable to the the people who provide them the money and to make that impression so that they
maybe think twice what they're doing and be more careful so that's supposed to be a
nonpartisan thing and is that buddhistic is that a way that Buddhists
can uh speak up or do something and act in a way that comes from this deeper
place of beauty and ethical sensibility and Not to cause harm not to create division
but to actually bring people together you'll have to decide I I shouldn't
answer that question for you so um those are my thoughts
today but the core one saying the third time is that Underneath It All one of
the Specialties of Buddhism is to really point to the tremendous importance of
Ethics virt virtuous Beauty beautiful virtue that uh can
come from cultivating a deep ethical sensitivity it doesn't have to come from
a moral requirement should that comes from the outside it really it can emerge
deeply from inside and for maybe each person then it'll emerge in different
ways maybe there's a plurality of what how people live from this deep inner sensitivity but the one thing they all
have in common is they're not going to kill not going to cause harm that way
and that's the fundamental Buddhist ethical principle don't kill don't
harm so those are my thoughts and we have a few minutes before there's the polu and as I like to do in these days
is for you to say hello to each other and maybe you want to say a word or two about this talk if it touched you in
some kind of way or made you reflective of something and so if you would if you're willing to
stay for a few minutes um maybe to maybe to maybe to two people around you two
three people turn around and say hello and share a few words but look around make sure no one's left alone because we
don't want people that sitting there kind of we want to bring people together not create separation so and then I'll
ring a bell in a few minutes and then we can uh maybe have uh have the P luck so
thank you