so welcome it's an interesting thing that
if we uh come and have a meditation practice and we have this intention that
maybe there'll be some calmness that shows up maybe some well-being maybe
some mindfulness maybe some settledness whatever it might be
it's interesting that if we come to meditate and we kind of have this orientation or this direction we're
going it requires that we go through the territory of non-comm
nonmindfulness nonettlness nonwell-being it's part of the
practice and yet so often kind when we sit down and close our eyes perhaps for
meditation we kind of have this idea like well where is it you know where is this uh calmness or well-being that I'm
looking for and forgetting or at least I certainly in the early parts of my practice really kind of forgot that no
it requires it's part of the practice it's inherent in it that we work with
everything that's not what we're uh or oriented
towards so it's not a failing it's not that we're doing something
wrong when there's a lot of agitation or a lot of unease or something like
this there's this u analogy that the Buddha speaks about and I'm going to
tweak it a little bit here that and it's analogy that I like a lot it's this idea
of when it rains up on the mountain and then there's a rivullet that gets
uh made that gets created as the water's going down the mountain and it turns into streams and then it turns into wait
creek and then a streams or you know bigger and bigger whatever words we want to use as it uh goes down eventually to
the ocean but it never just goes straight down boom you know there into the ocean
of course not of course not instead there are boulders there are banks there are trees
there's like all these what we might call obstacles maybe but it's not a
problem i mean the water just comes up against it and goes around it goes over
it or or goes a different direction it's not like there's aren't
ever any of these big boulders or obstructions and it's the same way with
practice and part of the reason why I like this uh analogy there's a few one
is the stream as it coming down this uh water as it's coming down it has
intimate contact with the boulder the tree the bank the river whatever it is
it's not like it sees oh there's a boulder okay I'm going to go around it no it like runs right into it
experiences it in the same way our practices too we experience these
boulders that's how practice is this is a part of
practice the second thing that I like about this idea of this uh analogy metaphor simile whatever way
we want to describe it is that it's not a straight line it's meandering right
and even if we see um streams that are in like in deserts or something they're
never straight right they there's some way in which the hydrodnamics make it uh curve around a
bit that's the way practice is too it's never you know the most uh what we think
might be the most efficient or straightforward way or but it has this quality sometimes of meandering or maybe
sometimes there's rapids and going fast and sometimes it's going slow
think about so much this is how kind of like practice unfolds this could be when I say practice unfolds this could be
over a lifetime or maybe just one meditation sit as well or maybe there's
a lot of boulders and restlessness and and the mind is kind of going all over the place but maybe eventually kind of
like settles down and kind of like uh has some momentum and starts to go towards more and more settling
so there's these ways that uh I mentioned them briefly last week that the Buddha identified thousands of years
ago about what we might call like these there's different ways we could
describe them mind states or maybe just energies or patterns or phenomena
there's like all these kind of like vague words we could use to point to
these five types of experiences that sometimes might be considered boulders
but are really are an integral part of practice and it's actually not possible
to practice without them if you're not experiencing these you're not meditating
or you're not alive I would say probably or you're a completely awakened Buddha
so one or the other so there's something about them
there these are like very human experiences every human has them whether
they are a meditator or not so these uh and I'll describe them in a moment here
but these I'm using this language energies mind states patterns they
affect everybody pretty much almost all the
time like anytime there's been any when you haven't any occasion in which you
haven't just gone straight to do precisely what you wanted there's one of these that are at play so with
meditation we see them because maybe in a more clear way we have this intention
maybe to get settled or calm and then we can notice all the ways in which we are not
calm maybe we don't see them so clearly in our lives but they are there they're
showing up in all aspects of our lives and these are often called these
uh hindrances it's often that neva and how it gets translated as
hindrances we could say they in meditation they hinder some calmness
maybe they hinder some brightness in the mind or maybe they hinder a sense of
well-being in the mind or maybe whatever your uh ex objectives
are for a sitting for a sitting meditation there's a way right which we don't meditation doesn't always turn out
the way we would like and it's because one of these five is showing
up so this list is um there's in a particular order in which they're often
given and one is this uh sensual desire this craving for pleasant experiences in
such a way that it distracts us from our life from our experience
and uh I heard this expression recently that I thought oh maybe this is a modernday way to write about this this
addiction to comfort this way in which like we don't want any discomfort we
don't want to be bored we don't want to wait we don't want any discomfort and uh when I look at my life
like all the things objects I have in my living space you know just to be
comfortable soft blankets things to cook food that I like
in the way that I like refrigerators you know but it's just fascinating how we
just surround ourselves just to try to um assure that we could have comfort but
life is not always comfortable and if we're always chasing
after comfort then we're not uh looking maybe deeply at our life or experiencing
our life deeply instead we're just chasing after the next pleasant experience
so that's the first one it's a commonly said is sensual desire i kind of like
this idea addiction to comfort the second is aversion or ill
will this feeling of hostility or maybe some
resentment or maybe anger but it also can be really subtle it can be like no
thank you nope nope nope no no no and this also can be related to this
addiction to comfort too like no no no i don't want this i don't want this person that's driving in front of me going less
than the speed limit and I'm stuck behind them you know there's this way in which we kind of feel like don't they
know I want to get somewhere or do something so this aversion can be
towards other people it could be towards a situation can be towards oneself you know this inner critic often has this
uh flavor of aversion it's uh it's amazing the types
of things that we say to ourselves that we would never say to anybody else but we say to ourselves so
ill will or aversion is the second one sloth and torper is the common uh translation this was these words were
not in my vocabulary until I started studying this Buddhist practice so this
is a sense of tiredness and we could say the reason why there's two words here sloth and torper is one is kind of like
a dullness or a foggess in the mind kind of like a uh and one is with the body
just feeling just doesn't have energy and in traditional way that we
understand sloth and torper it's not that there isn't any energy it's that
you don't have access to the energy Because when there's sle sloth and torper often what happens is that you
know after the bell rings for example when you're meditating and you maybe during the meditation you're doing a lot
of this you know this kind of thing falling asleep the bell rings you're like oh okay great I made it through now
I got to go do the shopping and I'm going to go pick up this or I'm going to do that I'm going to do this you know then all a sudden the energy just uh shows up again so sloth and torper is
this uh kind of just the energy draining out while meditating this turns out to be really
common and it's one sometimes it's just physical tiredness that wouldn't be
sloth and troper that would just be physical tiredness from lack of sleep but a second is often because uh people
are want to want to avoid something they're trying they're not not ready to experience something and this is a way
in which the mind and the body are avoiding just kind of like tuning out
just shutting down the fourth one is restlessness and
worry it's kind of the opposite it's this oh my gosh when is that bell going to ring i can't wait sometimes when I
have restlessness I feel it in my legs or my arms there's like this feeling like I just want to go and do something
but it also can be uh having this a lot of worry and worry like uh this rumination and um getting stuck going
around and around it again is a part of restlessness and worry as well and then
doubt it's this hesitation uncertainty i'm not sure is this the
right practice should I be doing this do those teachers really know what they're
talking about what is this Buddha guy does he know what he was talking about so just kind of this uncertainty about
it so these five hindrances and as I was pointing to before part of practice is
to actually practice with the hindrances to work with them sometimes when we're
doing mindfulness just uh maybe some in-depth mindfulness we will just be
mindful of the hindrance but there's a way in which that also itself is a way
with working with it thank you Jim so there's this way that meditation
kind of like highlights these hindrances and it can make such a big
difference in our lives so even if we feel like our meditation is just a hindrance attack and it's nothing but
one hindrance after the other but somehow we're gaining some facility or
some a little bit more ease or familiarity with them so that they're not as
problematic we shouldn't underestimate how this trans can transform our
lives really to be able to work with some of these subtle small obstacles as
well as really big obstacles because of course these happen in our lives as
well so there's this way that we don't sometimes uh we might think like okay I
just have to sit it out we just have to wait for it to end but we don't have to
just possibly experience them or maybe even
possibly observe them or witness them there are some ways in which we can work
with them then this I would say is part of the art of practice if you're in
meditating or in daily life and you and I'll talk a little bit more about this in a moment but when you notice like oh
for example like here's restlessness i am so restless sitting in the car can't
wait to get to where you're going and the other cars are driving too slowly or something like
this there's this way in which you know what i just lost my train of
thought that's interesting well I'll say the next thing
so some of you that are familiar with uh Buddhist teachings you'll be familiar
with this idea of these four right efforts right being most helpful not uh
moralistically right but just the most helpful and part of these are
to cultivate what is helpful cultivate what is beautiful cultivate calmness and
mindfulness and loving kindness or whatever your practice is but these
right efforts I'm using the word right that's how I learned them we could think of them maybe as wise
effort also is about abandoning what's not helpful
so we could say working with the hindrances is part of the wise way part
of to apply our energy with a practice is to help abandon these
unhelpful experiences so here's an overview of uh
how we can work with them and then I'll talk about a few in
particular one thing about the hindrances and part of the way why they hinder they're part of their
effectiveness is we don't see them we just think like oh this is just I don't
know it's just how it is and we're just like bouncing off of them or we're getting pushed around by them or
something like this using restlessness again as an example it can be enormously
helpful to just name it oh this is just restlessness
and there's a way to just name it it feels it has less of this compulsion that we have to do something and get up
and make things go faster or run away or whatever it is the restlessness is asking us to do just to name it oh this
is it's just restlessness i've had restlessness before i've felt like this before it's
uncomfortable that's okay i can be with discomfort this kind of
discomfort so one thing that we can do just in general is to just recognize
what's happening we might imagine there's a way like if you're in a maze let's say that
the hedges right are like really tall and you can't see where you're going and you're just trying going here trying to
find your way out of a maze there's a way in which recognizing oh it's just
sloth and torper here just the energy is drained out this feels uncomfortable
it's not the end of the world to just name it is kind of like you know being
up high and looking down on the maze instead of being in the maze where you're trying to just find your way when
we name it it kind of helps us to see big overview doesn't necessarily make it go away that you're no longer in the
maze but now you can see like oh yeah there is there's I can see there's a way
out it's possible instead of just frantically trying to find your way through the doubt or sensual desire
aversion whatever it might be and there actually there's uh when we
do say "Oh this is restlessness this is doubt." There can be
um a a small little like blip of delight
of this recognition because there can be a way in which um there's a certain amount of
frustration or irritation or something building up as we're trying to like find
our way through and then we recognize uh it's just restlessness there can be a little
like oh okay it's just restlessness and there's this little bit
of uplift with this recognition there's a these moment of clarity that can
really uh support us in our practice even though it's subtle and perhaps short-lived we shouldn't uh
underestimate because it interrupts the momentum of I got to figure this out i
got to make this go away it interrupts the momentum
so the first thing recognize what it's happening if you can sensual desire
aversion restlessness and worry sloth and torper and doubt these uh five
hindrances and then can we allow it to be there as best we
can this sometimes is the hardest can we just allow it to be
there don't have to fix it don't have to make it go away it is
uncomfortable but we don't have to all of a sudden you know try to do some I
don't know big giant uh changes to make it go away not only do we not have to make it
go away we don't have to create a story oh my gosh I'm always restless i'm just
a restless person i'll never be able to meditate not like those other people over there that are that I saw on the
internet or here in the room or whatever it is there's amazing how like the stories start getting made and often
there's some comparing mind we compare ourselves to how we were before or how we want to be or how other people and uh
it just lends to more and more dooka more and more suffering more and more discomfort
so can we just recognize it and then just allow it to be there as best we can
i'm saying as best we can because it's not easy this is this isn't easy but is
there a way that we can have can we like dial down some of the story
making some of the self- evvaluation and it's like yeah this shows that I'm human
and that I'm alive and that I'm having this experience it doesn't have to make
a story about your value as a meditator or your aptitude for meditation or your
likelihood for freedom or anything like this it doesn't have to mean that it doesn't mean that at
all
and recognize allow and then how to be with it so
allowing it's not so easy so how can we be with it to um in a way that's more
comfortable and diminishes the discomfort or diminishes the
intensity and allows this hindrance to kind of fade away one is to we could say widen the
field of mindfulness and what one way to think about this is
uh if uh it's an experience of I'm I'm
using this expression of restlessness because I had this uh not too long ago being stuck behind a driver that was
going really slow and I noticed how I had this little like flare up of come on
come on you know this like the speed limit is quite higher than what you're
doing here and you know and I thought oh look at So there's a um there's a way that what
I mean by widen our mindfulness that if you're experiencing it primarily in the
mind thoughts and thinking widen your mindfulness to the body to the bodily
experience if you're experiencing it primarily in the body like this restlessness sometimes like I said I
feel it in my arms and legs this feeling like I really want to move then maybe to uh include the mind
and notice what the mind is doing so to widen the mindfulness to include more
than what you're experiencing because one of the ways that the hindrances how they hinder I would say probably all
difficulties do this is they kind of like collapse our awareness we kind of
like collapse into the whatever is being uncomfortable or difficult there's a way
in which we kind of like forget about everything else as we're trying to find our way out
of the maze or something so this idea to broaden to widen to include more of our
experience is really kind like takes some of the
the compelling nature out of that uh hindrance
so maybe there's a a way that um I'll continue here and say and
then the last thing and sometimes this might not happen during meditation but might happen outside of meditation is to
investigate and so what are there some some of the things to investigate what underlying beliefs do
you have that are supporting this what underlying
beliefs i should be comfortable at all times or if things if I feel discomfort
I'm failing or I will never be happy unless I have perfect meditation sessions or
you know these are exaggerations um but often these underlying beliefs are buried pretty
deep these aren't something that you would hear yourself saying out loud but it can be really fruitful to have some
curiosity like what's driving this what's fueling this what is allowing this hindrance to
persist here like what is the why is it here because there's one way we can
consider them is kind of like seeds that humans have and then when the seeds like
germinate there's a way in which there's hooks on them and the hooks like grab
onto something and I've told this story a number of times it's for me it's a good
example of uh I was uh sitting in a retreat this was some time ago and uh I
noticed how much desire I was having during the meditation just all these things like I was going to buy things
you know and I was just imagining things I was going to buy or that I was I don't remember all the details now exactly but
just a lot of like all these things I wanted I this was a long retreat and I just wanted to be done with it also with
this feeling like I just want to go outside and all this stuff but I felt like okay I could work with that and the
desire kind of uh calmed down and then uh It came up
again for something else i'm like "Oh okay okay i can work with this be mindful experience it in the body and
calm down." And then this was the meditation session uh before lunch so that bell
rang the end i'm like "Oh okay i made it through." Phew and they're like "Okay I did all
right." You know I had all that desire i worked with it and then I went to the lunch line which is a buffet on on
retreats i put so much food on my plate way more than anybody could eat it was
just kind of like showing up like "Oh I want this oh I want that oh wow i should have some of this oh this would be good
for me." You know just put all this stuff on and this is how the hindrances
work is there's kind of like this hook and they attach to things so in this
little story and this was my experience and I'm sure if you look you'll see this experience as well that it's just desire
and then it starts to oh I want this and then this and then this so often with
desire we're focused on the objects and not noticing how there's just this desire that's getting placed on all
kinds of things there's a reason like when you're searching for the internet
when you're like click on this then you click on that and then click on this and click on that often there's a sense of like I want to eat something or I want
something more or there's or you end up buying something is because this uh the
internet often like surfing the internet feeds this sense of a desire and then
the desire just gets placed on different things so there's this way in which can we just
be with the experience can we be with the experience rather than um trying to solve it or
make it go away can we be with it and then investigate what's what's
underneath this what are some of the underlying beliefs or we could also
investigate if I weren't experiencing this hindrance what would I be
experiencing because there's a way in which these things arise to distract us
also there's a way in which the mind and the body don't want to experience
something that there's been a glimpse of and so they make big giant problems as a
something to solve and to kind of like pull our attention away so this could be
a second thing to be curious about to investigate is if I weren't experiencing this what would I be experiencing
so maybe I'll give a little bit of a an example for um working with
aversion if there's a little bit of hostility in the mix we would say aversion is uh ill will and it has this
huge spectrum right just mild irritation to boiling anger
and there's this way in which if there's this boiling anger and maybe it's like some hatred and hostility in there there
can be this way is just this swirl of the story of I can't believe they said this don't they know who I am you know
kind of like the hands on the hips this righteous indignation like it shows up when we're so angry how dare they treat
me that way with so disrespectfully or wait until I I'm going to you know this
type of thing so there's a lot of stuff happening in the mind and it might be when we kind of like this type of anger
it's probably the whole constellation of emotions some hurt maybe some
embarrassment or some frustration or there like there's a whole bunch of things kind of there together that are
like fueling this uh aversion so maybe that's one way we
might experience it just a lot of anger towards
institutions individuals oneself maybe and then there can often just be
this mild aversion to other people some of our
co-workers some of the people that we encounter that we don't really know
there's can be this way in which we're projecting onto them like why are they doing that they're so inconsiderate or
something like this some version of this maybe we're complaining about
uh a coworker that's like just too noisy or talking all the time or uh stealing
your ideas or what whatever it might be whatever it might be but there's this way in which we have
this idea about that person and I don't like that person because of X Y and
Z but the truth is we know so
little about other people in general we don't know what's happening
in their home life for a lot of people some people we do know we live with them we do have a better sense but there's we
don't know some individuals maybe they've gotten some news recently they
have or they have some diagnosis or something or maybe they have a a history
of some terrible awful things happening to them when they were younger and they are still trying to work through it or
find their way or there's all these ways in which people maybe they didn't have an
upbringing in which they felt like they were loved and cared for and they're trying to find their away with
that and so there's all this way that we're maybe like we're quick to jump to
conclusions and to maybe just have this uh ill towards other people thinking
that they're inconsiderate or inadequate in some kind of way
then I will also say this uh aversion also shows up boiling anger towards
other people and I'll just give another example is to our experience it's amazing if you really
wanted to look at it how often there's this slight little no thank you I don't
want that to whatever is arising like can it be better yeah it it should be
more like that we're so long living our life with this really [Music]
subtle this is what that Buddha was pointing to called a dooka the sense of yeah it's just not quite
right and I would say working with this is lifech changing
if we can work with the way that we start we're saying no in so many different
ways and can we say yes to our experience I'm not saying we have to
like it I am not saying we have to be passive I am not saying that there isn't
a lot of awfulness happening there is a lot of awfulness happening but there's a way that if we
can like settle into our experience and maybe tune into or be
attuned to the way in which we're saying no then the no can soften and then there
can be some wisdom or some clarity or some
openness that becomes available that's not available if there's this quiet no
no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no going on and when there's this openness and clarity
and wisdom that arises then we can meet the awfulness in a way that
um is powerful instead of just fueling this uh aversion that we have
so to practice with it with these different types of aversion is maybe to
I'll say specifically recognize oh this is
aversion maybe to like a widen the mindfulness experience is to what does
aversion feel like i notice that when I'm talking about it I'm like doing this with my hands and I'm going forward a
little bit kind of like pushing so there can be a way that's kind of like mentally or even physically there's a
clenching the teeth or like maybe your stance is is uh with your feet planted
and you know that kind of a stance or something like this so just get familiar
what does this aversion not wanting feel like in the mind and in the body and
maybe notice all these different things anger just aversion annoyance frustration with people or just the way
in which we're in a subtle way so often saying no thank you to our
experience and then how does that feel in the body because there's a way in which we are projecting all the problem
on something out there the person the situation
have you tried changing everything in the world have you tried changing everybody doesn't work right it doesn't
work but to be to kind of like bring the attention back here and to be with the
experience there's this way just repeatedly redirecting the experience to the body and mind feeling the
aversion just this repeatedly doing it because the mind you you will not want
to do this i'll just say you will have aversion to aversion and then aversion to the aversion to the aversion but you
will not want to do this but if you can there's this way in which the mind and
the body just start to relax and become a little bit more supple and a little bit
more easeful and there's not the there instead of like this big no there starts
to open up a sense of yes that allows or maybe
um allows understanding things in a new way or a new idea or creativity comes
from this place from this kind of like this place of yes that allows us to solve problems and to show up in the
world in a different way and people notice of course right if we're showing up with
a from a place of no versus a place of
yes and then you can do this a little bit of investigation is that it will
covering something is there frustrated desire is
there boredom is there embarrassment is there like is there
something underneath it that's fueling it and maybe it's serving another
purpose maybe this ill will is serving a purpose is well it's uh um holding up an
identity you have yeah I'm a member of this group and because I'm a member of this group we hate that group over there
so I just have a will i just because you're that group I'm in this group you're in that group and that's why we
just kind of fall into this so there might be a way in which we are doing it because uh we want to be part of an
identity or something or part of a group and or there's so many different ways
that gets uh played out it doesn't have to it doesn't have to get played out
this way so I talked about hindrances all humans have them they
show up in our meditation as well as they show up in our daily life
to work with them and to work with them I would say is such a big part of practice of course it is if we're going
to work towards something we work with whatever is getting in the way whether this is meditation or whether it's our
life and one is to recognize it and I'm using this word like widen or broaden
the mindfulness the awareness of it if it was primarily in the mind bring the
awareness into the body that's usually how entrances show up they're usually a mind thing and then bring them into the
body and then oh I um and to allow them
sorry I missed one and then investigate and maybe investigation happens during meditation or maybe it happens
later is this covering something is there an underlying belief is there a
purpose that this hindrance is serving right now so with that I've talked about one
out of five life hindrances i've talked about other ones in other settings i'll
see if I'll talk about some of the other ones perhaps in later talks but the hindrances are such a integral part of
practice and and maybe I'll just say that for me it was very personally when
it was very helpful personally when um I discovered these like oh these are just
what it means to be a human that's all that's all just what it means to be a
human so thank you thank you and with that I'd like to open it up
and see if there's some questions or comments
yeah we don't have to we don't have to talk
i feel like if I let you out early it's like you get to go you know when you were a kid and you get to go recess
early or something like this why don't we just end a few minutes
early thank you thank you wishing you a wonderful uh rest of
the evening if you'd like to come talk to me here uh afterwards you're welcome to but otherwise uh safe travels home
byebye