so hello and welcome to this 30 minute
meditation and as a continuation of this series on samadei I want to maybe simplify the
whole idea of moving into fuller and
fuller samadei the peace of samadei and that is that uh it's the
progressive uh um releasing of mental
pressure the the uh progressive re uh
light letting up of the ways that we cling to things or get really caught or
preoccupied and we do it kind of from the outside in maybe starting at the the
more uh larger kind of ways in which we cling or get preoccupied caught in things and
we slowly the process of settling relaxing calming
uh we start letting go and we start feeling uh the the place where we're still
holding and then there's a softening letting go of that and then letting go further and further and partly what this
uh uh involves is developing a deep deep
sensitivity to the way in which uh we
think uh about things when there's some pressure there some um tension there uh
in the way that we think so it's not just simply that we're thinking but
there's an added pressure tightness associated thinking and when we have certain
preoccupations certain ideas that we're thinking there could be pressure around those tension grabbing leaning forward
resisting and uh so that that begins to go because we feel that tension and
feeling the tension uh requires No longer being so involved in the content
of our thoughts but rather to feel the experience of thinking and how there's
uh there's um discomfort in that being there's some kind of
disturbance there and that gets let go and then uh the hindrances we get let go
of the hindrances as part of that and then um and then we're able to
kind of now bring our attention much more to the present moment and we're
able to kind of place the attention and sustain the attention this rhythm
massage of just being here the mind kind of drifts a little bit come back drifts a little bit come back and it's quite
lovely as an alternative to that tensions preoccupations with thoughts
emotions intentions feelings and with time we feel that even
that involves some kind of little bit of kind of tension or pressure and there's
a relaxing of that and then there's experiences of joy and happiness that
can come and then with time we see that the joy part of it is kind of coarse or kind
of a little bit too much there's too much uh involvement whereas at first the joy
just seems ecstatic and see feels so fortunate but over time as we get more familiar with it we can feel sense the
way in which there's some holding some pressure some involvement with the joy
and then that tension releases and then we're left with a happiness that deep
sublime kind of feeling of well-being meditative happiness but then at with time we start
sense and feel that even that ever so subtle hard to believe that this sweet
healthy feeling of of happiness has a certain kind of orientation of the mind towards it that's still a little bit of
tension little bit of pressure little bit maybe something holding and uh and so that
releases and then we move into the fourth Janna where uh there's uh really
we don't feel any pressure or tension whatsoever it just feels peaceful the
absence of all pressure all tension all force of the mind caughtness of the
mind and so it's a progressive stilling quieting calming of tension tightness pressure
um um uh that uh we become sensitive to and
then we let go so to assume a meditation
posture and the broadest
beginning of relaxing is as you breathe maybe with
your eyes closed to feel any
tension tightness
pressure in your body and as you breathe to feel
that and as you exhale to relax the
body relaxing into the present moment with your
body as a welcoming place something in your body welcomes
you as the pulling away of tension as the
narrowing in of tension
releases and then to feel the tensions in your
mind pressure contraction
doesn't matter what the tightness is about feel it on the
inhale and soften relax on the exhale
relaxing in a way that allows attention to settle more deeply into the
body where the body welcomes attention welcomes you
as you inhale feel any tension or pressure holding in the heart
area feel it on the inhale soften around it relax around
it on the
exhale letting attention letting you settle more deeply into the torso
maybe deep into the soft belly
noticing if there's any preoccupations major concerns that
you're thinking about don't be concerned about the content the
but rather the felt sense of tension tightness
pressure around this
concern and as you exhale
soften relax
settle and then to
settle into the body
breathing with that gentle massage of connecting to the
breathing and sustaining attention touching into the
breath and riding on the breath for a few moments
a very gentle
massage of breathing massaging it with a
soft very light no pressure
attention breathing in breathing
out maybe feeling the relief or joy gladness
that you're less preoccupied than you
were massaging the breath with awareness letting breathing massage
you breathing in and breathing out
and perhaps some of the more subtle tightening or
pressure can be softened by having a Small half
smile
smiling at the goodness simplicity of breathing in and breathing
out being connected in a in an embodied
way with oneself
and if there is some delight or
joy allow the massage Massage your
breathing to suse that joy through the
body as the mind gets quieter and
stiller the fewer the thoughts The more room there is in
awareness to feel the goodness the
rightness that's part of sitting
quietly attending to the breathing
and then relaxing more relaxing around the joy or the
delight the sense of relief
to feel more deeply deep in your body whatever sense of
well-being might be there even if it's in the cracks of feeling
otherwise feel that kind of well-being a sense of
happiness contentment
letting the mind become quieter so you can better have
room for happiness contentment
and then deeper than happiness deeper than
contentment is peace
the peace of a clear nonreactive
mind nonreactive
awareness letting go of happiness
contentment and becoming centered on that part
of your
being which is a clarity of
attention attention that feels clean
open spacious
that part of awareness the heart of awareness that has no pressure no
tension nothing to do nothing to
be simply
aware as if awareness is a vast open
space undisturbed by
anything he
And as we come to the end of this
sitting to see if you have a clear sensitivity
ity two ways in which there's added pressure or tension
in the mind the heart the
body an activation of
Wanting and not
wanting holding on a stickiness to thoughts and
feelings and even you can let it be the way it
is but appreciate that there is the
possibility of not having any stickiness any pressure any
activation any holding and that
possibility exists together with your holding surrounding it underneath
it as a friendly welcoming
possibility yes you can let
go you can release the pressures on the mind
and that allows you to see the
world with new eyes with clear
eyes without the filter of desires and aversions wanting and not
wanting without the burden of judgments and
interpretations to gaze upon the world
calmly with a friendly
heart a warmhearted attitude to all
beings may all beings
Be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and thereby may all
beings know what it's like to
live without any tension in their mind any pressure any
holding as they come home to themselves may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so good morning and welcome to this series on samadei and I think we're now on
the 57th the 58th talk and u discussing
the fourth janna and to step back to have a little bit of
um um different orientation to
understanding this whole process of samadei is that sometimes it's said to
be a continuous process of letting go that that's what's required in attaining
a deep samadei another way that similar is that
samadei has a lot to do with relaxing or letting up on all the ways in which
attention has been hijacked or uh harnessed into our attachments into
pressure into subtle ways that the mind grabs onto or pushes along um it's
thoughts subtle ways in which we're reacting to our feelings and how we
are the subtle ways maybe not so subtle ways in which we're uh uh in very
involved in with kind of pressure or contraction or tightness or leaning into
uh whatever attention is directed towards and if it's directed towards thinking there can be a lot of it and um
and so that process of becoming sensitive to
that holding that pressure that push that
preoccupation around anything at all the way attention you know zeros in and
sometimes it's innocent enough if uh you've lost your keys
uh then there's some part of the mind you know is kind of now you know intent
on finding the keys looking for the keys and there might be a subtle kind of
tautness intentionality in the mind or there might be fear and anxiety and
desperation that now the mind has really gotten tight really gotten
narrow the holding on there can be a a healthy tautness
healthy kind of engagement that or there can be this all this extra stuff and so
this uh meditation as a place to become very sensitive to the
tension the pressure the strain that we add and sometimes it's pretty uh soft so
in ordinary mind states we don't see the tension but as the mind gets quieter in
meditation we start noticing uh what wasn't noticed before because uh now
we're quiet enough to start feeling more deeply what's happening we're not preoccupied not caught up in in the
thoughts ideas and we start feeling the cost feeling the tightness the tension
the strain and then as we just sometimes with mindfulness just feeling it
carefully is enough for it to begin to soften dissolve and the process of samadei
whether it's feeling the tension letting dissolve or whether it's staying on the breath focusing on the breath uh you
know wholeheartedly so the attention doesn't go into that tension doesn't go
into the preoccupations and they kind of fade away on their own both are happening in samadei and uh and in one
way or the other the tensions of the mind are calming down and
quieting and uh when they quiet down enough that we really feel like we're in the present moment we've arrived and
we're not leaving we're just now at rest at ease it can start feeling like a delight it can be a relief it can be
happiness and so then we go further there can be uh the stages of the the
four stages of the four Janna are a progressive calming of the tensions
activation of the mind and uh and it's some sometimes just enough to feel
recognize the the tension or the disturbance or the activate unnecessary
activation that happens in each state so in each Janna if you hang out long
enough get to know it suse it feel it really be enter into it um then sooner
or later your system you will recognize oh this is where there's still some kind of tension and that releases and we can
move into the next Janna and the next Janna and the third Janna for some
people is the most satisfying in some ways because of the sublime happiness that's
there But even there there's a kind of attention a little bit of something
extra activation that it feels so good to find that which is calmer still more
peaceful which is the fourth Janna and now because the mind is not oriented
towards anything it's not oriented towards the happiness gathered around for the happiness uh there's no very
little sense of the body going on there's no pain and pleasure in the state um and
sometimes uh breathing gets very very quiet some people report that breathing seemingly
stops because there's no we don't experience any breathing in and out and
um and then whether we are still breathing a little bit or whether uh the
need for oxygen is so so diminished that uh there's some kind of you know cycling
of oxygen and carbon dioxide in some kind of way that doesn't quite require active breathing exactly what's going on
we don't know i don't know but um it's it can be
quite the first time it's you know I thought I stopped breathing i was so deeply calm and peaceful and
unpreoccupied by anything until I noticed I wasn't breathing and then I gasped and said to myself I'm going to
die and then I was you know back up in my thinking mind and over time I learned
to trust this and uh and how I wasn't going to die in deep meditation when I
could no longer feel any breath and some of that is that the quiet peaceful mind
that has so little mental activity doesn't need a lot of oxygen that one of the primary consumers of oxygen in the
body is the brain because we're so you know busy there
so um so with the fourth Janna um there
is no real any now involvement with anything outside of the state of awareness itself and uh and so it's
that's kind of described as an aquinomous awareness or a clear mind
clean mind pure mind and if anything there's a kind of a feeling of of this
is what there is and there's a the the unification the one-pointedness
um is just with what's left which is this quantumous clear awareness mind
that we're here and this involves uh no you know the absence of phenomenal
absence of tension activation that's so deeply satisfying
so I wanted to emphasize this today because um uh the the the balance in
practice is some balance between um being focused with attention staying
with like the breathing or the object of attention and relaxing and softening and
um and you can get somewhat concentrated by only focusing but uh there's not a few people
who do that who don't notice the strain by which they're focusing and then their
samadei gets a little bit uh uh out of kilter uh their sami gets a little bit
off in some ways or very much off a lot of a lot of the strain tension builds
kind of energy that's not a healthy energy to have and if we're only focusing on
relaxing and letting go um it might not really allow the kind of unification the
kind of quieting or centering that um that allows for the deeper
submod so where we find the balance is somewhere between the two and uh some
people want to emphasize more the letting go the relaxing some people more the focus different times more one or
the other but ideally they're working together and they're working harmoniously almost as if they're the
same thing and uh and that becomes a protection from the problems that can
happen with samadei if uh we're trying too hard to get into samadei if we're
straining pushing um gung-ho and I've known people who have
been a little bit too idealistic a little bit too striving around somebody and they've
gotten into trouble because uh the tension built so much in their body and their mind and and um they got headaches
for example or strange kind of activation of energies happen in their body
so it's very important to see the process of samati to be a sensitivity to
tension sensitivity to holding to pressure to contraction to clinging uh
in all the many variations that can be there to be sensitive to it so we know
how to let go we know how to relax and this is uh valuable at any stage of mind
of practice um uh if we're in ordinary states of of consciousness of mind then
uh maybe some of that holding is fairly coarse as we get deeper in meditation
it's more and more subtle subtle doesn't mean it's unimportant it becomes uh
what's the next maybe the next doorway to go further and further
so the progressive stilling softening
evaporating of tension clinging holding
pressure and then we come to the fourth Janna and uh when a person has kind of
come to the fourth Janna and is well able established in it then it can be
relatively smooth and quick to move between the Janas the mind becomes
malleable mind becomes workable and sometimes there's a sense of mastery of
just can move in and out of this states because there's no clinging no tension
that interferes with that movement it's just enough it's almost like you blow on a you know you you blow on dust and the
dust kind of floats away so you flow and direction is in these concentration
states and you can kind of move between them because there's so little clinging and the idea is not to necessarily
develop mastery of the Janna but rather how the how the deeper the Janna
the less holding there is to the in the mind less clinging and the more and more
prone we become to a deeper and deeper letting go that the mind does on its
moon and that is a miracle that is a delight when the mind lets go of
itself so thank you and um so we have two more days on this fourth Janna and
um and I appreciate very much this chance to be able to offer you these teachings