so good morning everyone and I hope you hear me okay with
the microphone on my laptop so here I am at Spirit Rock these
wonderful rolling grasslands oak grasslands that uh the retreat center in
Marin County California i'm here teaching a retreat with about a hundred
people with a few wonderful teachers that um my
friends [Music] so welcome to our meditation session
and maybe you hear the birds and we'll
see sometimes when I'm here um animals will walk by yesterday there was a a big
healthy looking beautiful looking coyote uh up here walking up by in the
hills so um I'll offer you an a kind of similly
analogy in our uh in my yard garden at home we
have a um outdoor faucet used for watering the garden and the faucet has a
extension to it that is the shape of a Y so that we can attach two
hoses to the same faucet and then the Y has a valve and
you can move the valve back and forth between um one or the two arms of the Y
depending which hose you want to have water in or you can also put it in the middle
position and it goes some water goes into both hoses so in the same way uh we're and so
whatever part of the garden we want to water uh we turn the valve one way or the
other so in the same way for our meditation uh we have something that's
waterlike and it is um ordinarily I think of it as awareness our
attention and the um and in in the Janna uh it's the
meditative joy and happiness that comes from the practice but it begins with awareness
that awareness attention is a kind of a a water that
waters that feeds that nourishes whatever it flows into so if you're
watering worry worry grows if you're watering
um desires desires grow if you're watering resentment resentment grows it
matters where your attention goes where your focus goes where your involvement mental involvement
goes and it helps if we can turn that valve inside so this wonderful resource
that we have attention awareness can flow to flow and water feed nourish
something that's really wholesome and good and the ancient tradition in
Buddhism is to you do that with meditation mindfulness of
breathing and um and so there's a kind of a non-thinking
awareness that uh we pour into uh the
body settle into the body to and we water with awareness the
goodness of uh of just simply
breathing and as we breathe there's a second
nourishment and that is uh as we get uh
uh absorbed engaged fully giving ourselves over to
uh to the simplicity of breathing then there starts to be the
nourishment of well-being a joy happiness
delight that comes from the absorption that comes from the full engagement in
what we're doing and of course it's a little bit more difficult to do it with something as simple as breathing than it
is to do it with a really good book we're reading or great craft we're doing or sport we're playing but that's the
art and the practice we're doing here is to find that way to take the healthy
nourishment the healthy take awareness and our well-being and let it flow into
our body into the practice to be fully here so to assume a meditation
posture and for today you might want to emphasize a posture that is uh has no as
little discomfort in it as possible so if you normally sit with
knee pain or back pain uh maybe for today assume a posture that um that
lessens that as much as possible
and then gently close your
eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths
beginning to turn the flow of awareness into the
body out of thinking where many people spend much of the day
letting the breathing return to normal
and investigate the body breathing
investigate how breathing is occurring in your body at this moment
what moves in your
body what sensations come into play as you
breathe
what is the nature the quality of your breathing is
it forceful is it easeful is it slow or
fast is it shallow or deep
whatever it is just notice it note it how it is for you
and then as you breathe pause at the end of the
exhale for a comfortable length of time however brief that
is so that you have more valuing more
appreciation of breathing in
the same with the top of the exhale inhale a slight pause so there's a
growing appreciation of how important and valuable it is to breathe
as you exhale softening your
body relaxing sing
as you exhale relax your thinking mind
soften in the mind that
thinks a soft softening that lessens the strong pull
or the strong inclination to think it's okay for a little
while to let thinking recede to the background
and turning your attention now so the the nourishment the food the
water of awareness flows into your body breathing
Almost as if with every breath inb breath and out
breath the water is filling water of awareness is
filling your torso filling your body gently softly Please
and as you're sitting here
breathing aware of the body breathing feel in your
body feel in your breathing
whatever is pleasant whatever is
enjoyable in the sensations the embodiment of
attention where is the pleasure of that
maybe there's a degree of
calm clarity a feeling of
wholeness and into that calm body flows awareness attention
the kind of awareness that has minimal thought in
it a sensing a
feeling and observing
And as you're sitting here sensitive to your inner
experience feel whatever Whatever joy
contentment well-being there is
pleasure that comes from being engaged in the
meditation that comes from not getting lost in
thought but rather being dipping
in flowing into this broad
lake of the
body with an inner
wellspring of maybe subtle wellbeing joy and
happiness and as if the b the body is a welcomes that
joy the clarity and
calm is a welcome container welcome invitation
here let that well-being have space have room in this
body to flow to open up and to
spread with every
breath whatever wellbeing there is spreads through the body
and supports the mind to become quiet
clear without being crowded with
thinking the clear space has more room for wellbeing
that for these minutes is being
prioritized as if it's a kind of nourishment for you
maybe a soft gentle current of
flowing wellness happiness contentment
flowing in the body and with every
breath giving more room for well-being to
flow coziness sweetness to flow through your
body spreading into the arms the legs
There can be a feedback loop or
quiet soft attention to joy and
happiness supports the joy and happiness to grow which in return supports the
interest to stay there with it to breathe with
it slowly gently the absorption in the meditation
the absorption in the pleasure and the pleasure of the joy and
happiness grow together
then as we come to the end of this sitting
to let the boundaries of your body your joy your
well-being flow beyond your body or let the joy and the happiness flow
beyond any sense of boundaries to self like the
breath the air comes into your body and leaves and spreads out into the world
so let your joy your happiness whenever you have
it not be something you hold on to for yourself but something that is the
condition the cause for you to be friendly to
others that you meet people carrying your joy your
well-being that is the medium through which you see people through which you speak with
people those times when you feel happiness let it be something that
spreads into the world may it be
that this practice we're doing together causes each of
us to improve the lives of people around us today with small acts of kindness small
acts of joy of appreciation respect may it be that this meditation we do
serves the world so that all beings may be
happy all beings may be safe all
beings may be peaceful and all
beings may be safe may be happy and free
so thank you i'm sitting here in the hills of Marin County without a
bell so I will bow to all of you and that bow will be the end of the
meditation thank you
so Welcome to this next talk on the samadei series the fourth talk on the fourth
Janna and um some people call Janna just call it Janna some people call it
absorptions some people call it immer immersions um some people have in the
past many years ago they used to call it transes when they didn't quite know what it what it was
and um uh there states of wholeness
uh of unification where we're not divided from with it with with ourselves we're not uh
uh distracted or um our attention is not um
uh pulled in different directions and it's a pleasure to come
together and have all of us here all of ourselves uh engaged in the same thing at the same
time and to really get into it to really be absorbed in it and give ourselves over to it there's a joy that comes i
think human beings and I think animals too can have there's a there's a joy of
certain kind of certain types of completely giving ourselves over to something that's really enjoyable and
pleasant and there's a kind of more than just pleasure there's a kind of happiness and delight and thrill and of
kind of giving ourselves over to it or losing our not losing ourselves but kind of fully giving ourselves over to
something and I think I told the story sometime recently but that um many years
ago I came out of uh out onto the street was raining and um and there was a car
across the street uh where there was a little bird that was sliding down the
windshield of the car the wet windshield in the rain and then flying up to the
top of the windshield and and sliding down again over and over again around and
around and um I could only think that this uh bird was enjoying itself was
absorbed in the delight of sliding so to give ourselves over maybe a little
bit like uh the delight of children uh fully giving themselves over to some
activity that's so much fun so the quality of the second Janna
uh has to do with uh coming into a form of full absorption full engagement in
what we're doing without any stress when there's a a a vast calm
settleness stability uh when there's a vast clarity
uh some people call it clarity and um some people I was going
to say use the word assurance for the poly word the ancient Buddhist word so
to sit with tremendous sense of assurance of of confidence or or
safety or this is really a good good way to
be and um and a unification of all of us
involved and then the art of this is to begin appreciating the joy and the
happiness that's there the some people call it um even rapture because it can
be quite strong and some people call it bliss rapture and bliss because of the
it's qualitatively so much greater sometimes than ordinary happiness and
joy and um and to adhere a situation you ought to give yourself over to it you're
allowed to make room for it and feel it and enjoy it and there's an art in in in
deep meditation to begin not holding on to the joy not that being attached to it
but to um make room for it to uh with the breathing perhaps massaging it more
or allowing it to flow and mostly in the second Janna I think of it of this as as
um just making more room uh letting it flow uh feeling the
current of it feeling the hum feeling the the flow of these uh good feelings
that can be there and not making a lot of them not getting excited uh staying
with the calm but with the calm and the clarity just allowing them to live
allowing them to flow that this is where the the the food of awareness this is what
attention uh supports the growing of the growing of joy the growing of of
happiness and the classic instructions are to let it pervade suse permeate
spread throughout the body and um so sometimes it's actually kind of nice to
kind of feel like you're kind of blowing it or or supporting it to flow into the
arms and the hands and into the legs um into the full
torso um and at times when there doesn't seem to be any boundaries to the body to
just feel like it just just it's just just kind of radiating in all directions front and back and everything
and um so I know that this kind of joy I'm talking about is uh far from or our
ordinary experience and there's a lot of challenges that we have in our lives and
challenges with our external lives challenges with our own minds and hearts
and uh it can be a little bit uh grading or discouraging to hear these descriptions of this kind that pervasive
joy and happiness um so it's uh but it's also
can be inspiring that this is possible for a human being we can put aside the
all the all our ordinary concerns and get refreshed get renewed get
settled so that eventually we can do a deeper work um of really of insight
deeper work of really seeing clearly to the depths of our hearts uh where
suffering is and where freedom is um and that's the overall purpose for this joy
and happiness it's not just for this meditative joy and happiness for his own sake and some people get a little bit
side or quite sidetracked by it by just getting addicted to it and just want to have this over and over again but it's a
it's important to see it as a stepping stone to eventually having very deep
insight there's a purification there's a clarification that goes on with this
there's a healing that goes on by allowing ourselves to feel this kind of joy and
happiness and uh it's good to take take if one drops into these kind of Janna
states it's good to take one's time with it uh ordinarily people will often get
quite excited by these wonderful states and then they pop right out they start thinking how wonderful it is and they
get distracted almost by their excitement but the idea is to become familiar with
them don't be in a hurry to go through them don't be in a hurry to strengthen them but gently get to know them feel
them become familiar with them um and uh and let the joy and the happiness um
nourish you support you guide you uh feel it well this is a time in life in
these states when they when this joy and happiness is there you have complete
permission in meditation to experience up to the point of ecstasy to experience
the joy the happiness and um and maybe even uh you
can you can support that process by making a half smile and or you could
maybe feel that the joy and the happiness wants a half smile And you can
smile with the practice as you do it and then uh if you go into these kind
of deeper states of well-being then um uh you can
um it's valuable to come out of these meditations slowly uh don't be try not
to be in a situation where you have to pop out and get to work or do something quickly but come out slowly and so you
stay closely connected as if you're allowing something to still work you
allowing you're receiving the goodness of it the blessings of it somehow or the
the you're you're reconditioning yourself in a deep way and maybe get up
and start doing simple things in the morning maybe you can get up and make breakfast in a simple relaxed way that
kind of goes along with the general tenor the general feeling of how it felt
in the meditation and um and if you don't feel
this kind of deep happiness and joy uh that's fine mostly meditators don't feel
it um but from time to time they come and I'm hoping that uh you'll have a
greater appreciation and readiness to practice with it uh through these
teachings here so thank you very much and um I'll
be here tomorrow again at Spirit Rock and next week the first three days so
probably I'll be doing it from this place here where the grass lands behind me and uh with a little bit of luck
we'll have sun one day one morning and and uh maybe the wild flowers will start
coming out during this week so uh thank you and I look forward to
uh tomorrow morning thank