good evening Welcome I'm Hillilary and I'm sitting in
for Diana this evening Is there anybody who's here for the first
time oh yes Welcome Welcome
So I'm going to talk tonight about
something which sounds a little strange at first but hopefully by the end of the
talk it will make more sense It's called changing poison into
medicine So Nagarjuna a Mahayana Buddhist teacher
from the 2 century in India likened the Buddha's teachings to
a great physician who can change poison into
medicine So each of us finds our way to the dharma for different reasons
But often it is suffering Is there anybody who came here because you feel some sense of
suffering you just feel free to raise your hand It may not be everyone
Um there's something inside of many of us that keeps us from a a sense of uh
well-being It might be physical emotional or psychological
um pain which we might try to fight
against or tried to get rid of Has anybody tried to fight against their
suffering or get rid of it i got to root that out I have
definitely But unfortunately it only causes more suffering because we're at
war with ourselves Whatever we resist persists
That is a a saying that you'll probably hear in the
dharma So uh so the suffering leads us to the dharma
for medicine So the Buddha went in search of medicine
when he couldn't bear knowing that people became
ill and they grew old and
died So he left his palatial life Um you
would think he would have no suffering but he did And so he he left the palace
and he went out in search of wisdom some
medicine And he started off with practicing very aesthetic practices He
um at one point was eating so little that he
almost starved himself to death They say that you could he could touch the front
of his belly to his back There was nothing in
between And it was not until a young woman Sudata came along and found him
and nourished him with some really uh rich
porridge And he realized ah that's not the way
right to cause more suffering for myself more pain physically right and that
helped to put him on this path of enlightenment this middle way
Um so in this path on this path to
enlightenment he finally sat down underneath the bodhic tree and he
said I'm going to sit here until I achieve enlightenment And then
Mara came along and bombarded him with
all kinds of frightening and tempting things There were demons and uh raging
storms and there were beautiful dancing
girls and he met them all with
equinimity And as these armies let loose a barrage of arrows it is said in the
sutas that they fell all around the Buddhas Buddha like flower
petals So he showed us a path to change poison
into medicine Whatever came at him he
was able to transmute it Whatever pain and sorrow and
fear he transmuted into beautiful qualities of
compassion and patience acceptance kindness wisdom
So the first step in transmuting poison into medicine is to turn towards the
pain Does anybody feel that's counterintuitive it feel it felt like
that to me at first right turning towards the pain really that's going to
help So most of us spend much of our lives until we get to the dharma We
spend our lives running away from ignoring
repressing this this pain and we say "I'm okay." And we get
busy with other things Has anybody said that oh yeah I'm okay
Yeah But if we we just ignore it if we try to repress these these feelings they
don't go away right they just go underground into our
subconscious and they cause unease and they undermine our best intentions
Do you ever feel sometimes that there's this like inner part of you that's always
trying to get in your way or try to
uh just impede your progress and you're like why what what's in there why who is
that why are they why is that part of me doing that
so there's a Tibetan story about Millera
who lived around 1,200 years ago and he was filled with a poisonous
rage Um and he he actually murdered many people out of
revenge for his family's stolen wealth
And after a while eventually comes to the dharma and he begin the message
begins to penetrate and he turned his life around And I'm going to read you a story
about how one day he went into a cave seeking
firewood One day the Tibetan teacher Millera left his cave to gather firewood
When he returned he found that his cave had been taken over by
demons There were demons everywhere His first thought upon seeing
them was "I have got to get rid of them." He lunges towards them chasing
after them trying forcefully to get them out of his cave but the demons are
completely unfaced In fact the more he chases them the more
comfortable and settled in they seem to be Realizing that his efforts to run
them out have failed miserably Millera opts for a new
approach and decides to teach them the dharma If chasing them out won't work then
maybe hearing the teachings will change their minds and get them to
go Seems like a good idea So he takes his seat and begins teaching about
existence and non-existence compassion and kindness the nature of impermanence
After a while he looks around and he realizes that all the demons are still
there They simply stare at him with their huge bulging eyes Not a single one
is leaving At this point Valera lets out a deep breath of
surrender knowing now that these demons will not be manipulated into leaving and
that maybe he has something to learn from them He looks deeply into the eyes of
each demon and bows saying "It looks like we're going to be here together."
I open myself to whatever you have to teach me In that moment all the demons but one
disappear One huge and especially fierce demon with flaring nostrils and dripping
fangs is still there So Millera lets go even
further Stepping over to the largest demon He offers himself completely
holding nothing back Eat me if you wish He places his head in the demon's
mouth And at that moment that largest demon bows low and dissolves into space
So Joseph Campbell was a famous mythologist
and he said "The cave you fear to
enter holds the treasure that you seek."
So the dharma teaches us that whatever we run from pursues us and whatever we turn towards
transforms us So we practice accepting what is true
in the moment and that may be I am in
pain Right i am in anguish I am so sad or I am so
angry Right whatever that is
true for you When we turn towards
it the pain is finally heard It is seen
felt and it can breathe a sigh of relief
Finally someone cares I'm no longer abandoned no longer
alone There's a contemporary poet Naria Wahed writes "Feel
it That thing you don't want to feel feel it and be free."
So the first step in transmuting poison into medicine is to turn towards the
pain Acknowledge that it is here Allow the feeling to be felt seen
and heard And to hold it in loving awareness with compassion And part of what is so
helpful about the teachings of the dharma is to learn that we have inside
of us an awareness that can be aware of the thoughts the feelings that sensations
that arise within us But our awareness is not those things
There's a space that we can create between what we think we feel we sense
and this awareness So that is the first step
turning towards and then the second step is to notice when we're shooting the
second arrow and stop Right so the first arrow is the
pain of whatever might be happening to us that causes us this feeling of
suffering The second and subsequent arrows are the ones we inflict upon
ourselves as we heap on thoughts that are unkind
If we suffer a misfortune we make a mistake we often say hateful things to
ourselves Has anybody done that here said really unkind things to yourself
you would never say to someone else because it would be so devastating And
yet so often we do that all the time within our own minds
So it's these second arrows that are optional We can choose to turn these
arrows into flowers by befriending whatever inner
demons arise within us Khalil Gabbron
wrote "And God said love your enemy and I obeyed and loved
myself." I'm going to read that one more time I think that's so profound God said "Love your
enemy." And I obeyed and loved myself
So like ancient alchemists who endeavor to transmute these base uh elements into
gold that's the alchemy of our practice We turn poison into medicine
by turning pain from suffering into wisdom and
compassion And so how do we do this how do we put our heads inside the
mouth of our demons and transform them so there's an ancient Tibetan
Buddhist practice called Chud that was developed by an 11th
century female Buddhist teacher named Machi Gladron
And chud means to cut through And the philosophy of chud sees
our inner demons our obsessions our fears our
addictions anxieties um sometimes even chronic illness as
energies which can be healed by bringing them into the light by meeting them
getting to know them Rather than seeing them as our enemy and
fighting against them we turn towards them and nurture them by feeding them
what they need So there's a contemporary Buddhist uh Tibetan teacher uh named Sultram
Alioni who teaches a five-step process for doing this based on this ancient
teaching of Chud and she calls it feeding your demons
So in our practice we might substitute uh for for demon we might substitute
suffering So our sufferings may be feelings of deep feelings of uh perhaps
uh anger frustration or inadequacy or feeling unlovable
or feeling uh just deeply grieved or uh any number of of uh
things that can cause us to feel this inner suffering So the practice this five-step practice
that she teaches Sa Malonei is to find in the body where we're holding this
suffering most strongly And usually it's a feeling It's a strong feeling and then allow it to take on a
form so that we can we can visualize it and see it get to know it
And then the third step is discovering what the suffering needs And this is the interesting part
by putting yourself in its place So if there's a deep anger maybe your anger
demon who's feeling rage about lots of things that are
happening you would then in this process and the this step you would then become
that anger Try to see it from inside
out And then the fourth step is you you ask it what does it want what does it
need and then you begin to nourish it to give it what it wants
what it needs and see what happens See if it begins to transform So I've done a similar process
with the kids in the Dharma Sprouts program here using a book called An's
Anger And here it is And this is An and
An's anger demon And so Anne uh he is living with
his grandfather and he knocks over all his blocks and anger and he's sent to
his room to be with his anger And lo and
behold his anger shows up right it's this fuzzy red fang you know
clawed creature and they get to know each other
and they become friends And what we do is we have the kids actually make a
puppet that is their anger And then we have them talk to their
anger like "How are you oh I'm so mad I
want to throw something I want to scream." Right whatever it is let the
anger tell you how it's feeling And then after it's gotten that
out then you say "What do you need?"
And then you listen I need
a I need a hug right or I need to go outside and run
around or whatever it is right this is a lovely way of teaching the kids that
there's this awareness There is anger that is in them and they can have a communication
with the singer This anger is not them Right what do we say sometimes we
say all the time I am angry Right rather than oh there's anger in me right so we
create some space and then we can have a a a communication with this anger and
see what it needs to tell us There's no emotion that is wrong or bad They're all
useful in their own place and time right sometimes we need anger to protect
ourselves So
um we make these puppets and then sometimes the oh in the
book Anne's anger actually begins to transmute itself It goes from this
really ginormous really scary looking creature to this friendly little guy
who's you know there to protect on when needs it right so just imagine having a
relationship with one of your inner demons or one of your inner sufferings
So instead of trying to get rid of it or to fight it or run away from it you turn
towards it and say "How are you feeling how are you feeling
sadness what do you need what do you want?"
Um and so what I like to do is just give us a little sample of what this would be
like And so I'm just going to lead us in this five-step process just for a few
minutes You are welcome to participate in this or you can just tune it out
and and just sit quietly If at any time you feel unease and you don't want to
continue with the the practice then just open your eyes and look around and take
a breath and um and then just uh it we'll we'll be back uh together after a
few minutes So um let me take a sip
here So if you'd like to close your eyes you're welcome to do that if you'd rather just have a soft downward gaze Um
and then just start by taking several slower deeper breaths I like to breathe
in through my nose and a long slow out breath through the
mouth I feel much more letting go when I do that So couple more like that
And then just letting your breath find its natural rhythm And just checking in with
yourself Is there something present here in you that maybe feels like a suffering
maybe it's a a disappointment a
fear sadness
something that feels just hard to be with a little bit Don't pick your
worst worst fear but if you can be with it just
notice where are you feeling it in your body where is that feeling most
strongly often times it can be felt in the chest
or the [Music] belly maybe in the face or the
shoulders the hands See where that suffering lives in
you And then when you feel like you have something in
mind some feeling that feels a little hard to be with then visualize
this this feeling this emotion this suffering Does it have a size a
shape a color
and you don't need to make anything happen It's fine if you don't you can't visualize It's no worries If something
comes to you then just let it happen You don't have to make anything happen Is there a way that holds itself
maybe really upright or hunched over or how does it hold itself
this
suffering and what kind of emotion is it
exuding maybe it makes a sound
And then if you can imagine that this suffering has
eyes and you look into the eyes of the
suffering and ask what do
you What do you
need what is it that you
need and then seeing if you can change places now with that
suffering that
feeling and see what it says from the inside
out Being the suffering what does it need
does it just want to be [Music]
heard does it need to know that you
care does it need a hug
and then imagine switching places again once you've heard from
this suffering And then imagine nourishing it with whatever it
needs Imagine just feeding that to this this demon
and see if anything happens if anything changes anything
shifts maybe just in the way that you feel towards this little demon this
suffering
And then we'll just give another moment of being
with this feeling Seeing what happens when you nourish it with what it
needs And then when you're ready just taking a deeper breath in and out
and then opening your eyes
So rather than trying to fight
with these inner feelings these
inner whatever you like to call them whether you call them demons or parts or
suffering we can make friends with them and become become more
whole The suffering feels seen and heard
and [Music] comforted soothed And so these strong
feelings are no longer afraid of us that we will reject
them we will turn away we will try to repress them or get rid of them
And we are no longer afraid of being with
them The poison becomes the medicine And what we were fighting to
repress can become a friend an ally perhaps a protector when we need
them There's a a poem by Rainor Maria
Rulka Perhaps the dragons in our lives are princesses who are only waiting to
see us act just once with beauty and
courage Perhaps everything that frightens us is in its deepest
essence something helpless that wants our love
So I would like to invite us to um a
just a little conversation about how was that for
you and um are there any questions or
reflections and we can pass the microphone
Um thank you for that uh talk and the exercise was interesting
Um I think initially it's with the imagery of demons it's easy to like
think of it as uh something we're averse to like the
aversions Um I and this may be more of a comment but I
uh I'm not sure if also we could work with things that we have um the opposite like too much desire for and view that
as a demon Yes Do the same exercise So something I'm trying to think of but
yeah absolutely right Sometimes we are so
desirous It could be food or sex or shopping or you know
gambling or something And and often that is something inside of us that is
longing to receive something that we're trying to substitute
for Right and so oftent times what we're
really longing for is connection and love and care and we're not receiving it
from the outside world And so we can actually give that
to ourselves One of the things I do is I teach mindful self-compassion courses
And it's amazing how when we do when we learn to turn our
compassion we have towards others towards ourselves how soothing and comforting it can be even like a simple
touch with an intention of kindness even if we make a mistake and instead of
saying oh I cannot believe I did that oh I'm so awful I can't believe that
instead Oh this hurts I'm so sorry that
this happened and I still love you I still
care You're still a worthy human being Right So thank you for that question
That was really very good
question Anything else coming up for you
is it oh yeah go
ahead Thank you Um I can share my experience through this practice Um it's
very nice So my demon at this time is the sadness emotion and I visualize it
and I ask it what do you need um it didn't speak but I can feel what
it need I really just need that I accept it that I being with her like really
accept it and I try to accept it and I feel fear in my
heart and um yeah and then I also try to you mentioned like we need to nourish it
so like try to give blood to it to nourish it It doesn't want my blood it just want me to accept it
That's so beautiful Thank you It's It's very beautiful Thank you so
much I love it You're welcome Oh I'm getting chills Yeah because so often what happens is
when we're sad we do not want to feel it right that's also true of fear and um we
don't want to feel the sadness because it feels so overwhelming right we're afraid we're
just if we go into it we'll never come back out We've got to be strong right that's what we're taught you know stiff
upper lip Um and yet the sadness is
sad right the sadness is sad The sadness needs to be
comforted right so thank you for that
Is this something that perhaps you could imagine just doing sometime just on your
own and it could be as simple as it doesn't have to be the five steps It
could just be the realization that there's a really overwhelming feeling that is causing
suffering and you are really trying to run away You're trying to repress it You
do not want to feel it And instead can you perhaps turn towards it visualize
it and say I see that you are so
upset Can it be here for you can I actually make space for
you and can I hold you with some compassion can you imagine doing that
that would that be different from what you do now
yeah The thing about self-compassion is that I think a lot of us have been led
to believe that it is a weakness It will make us weak it will
will take away our inner motivation We won't be able to face the world We've
got to be strong But what happens is all of these feelings that we've had and often times
this begins when we're very young I mean how many of us as children
were told when we were crying or upset stop that Did anybody hear that stop it
Go to your room Right And or if you're angry yeah go to your room and you know
when you can you know gather yourself together whatever then you can come out
right so we're taught that all these feelings are not okay So nobody tells us
what to do with them right and so I think we can come to this practice and
realize that there's a lot of these untended feelings You know we've stuffed
inside And I can tell you I've been practicing for 20 years You can keep
stuffing those emotions your whole life and they don't go away They won't go
away until oftenimes what happens in our in this practice is that when we
sit in in silence and we make space for
whatever arises stuff will come up right has
anybody found that out like stuff that you buried starts to come up and you're like "Ah what do I do now?" So this is
something that you can do you can meet what arises without being so
afraid right i mean I I think of all of these feelings as being more like
like kids you know that little child in me that was overwhelmed that didn't get
what I needed And so now whenever I feel some some sadness or fear or frustration
I I just can imagine them as these little these
little people who need my support and my help That is that space between our
awareness and the feelings And sometimes the feelings are really really strong
right they're very frightening And what we can do if we
feel overwhelmed like I cannot deal with you right now we can still be kind right
we can still say to the the fear the sadness the anger you know I see you I
feel you It's you're not bad It's okay that you're here It makes sense for you
to feel this way and I need to go for a walk right now right or I need to go uh
do something else right but I will come back to you I will be back for you So
those feelings don't feel abandoned from from us right and little by little over
time with with practicing this way we can begin to hold more of these feelings
and not be so afraid not feel like we need to run away and then as I said earlier the
feelings then are not afraid of us and we're not so afraid of them and we can
become we can become friends so we can become allies So I hope that this has been
helpful I hope um and if it hasn't been if it's something that is not useful for
you then just completely let it go There's lots of ways to practice This is
one that I use and uh it's very helpful for me so I wanted to share it But if
it's not helpful for you then let it go and uh find find the things that are
really helpful for your practice So I would just like to dedicate the merit of
our time together Um may all beings turn towards their
suffering with kindness and compassion
And may we practice this self-compassion that
will benefit all those that we connect with all those other suffering
beings May we meet them with compassion Thank you so much for being
here Thank you for your practice And I will stay here for a few more minutes if
anybody has anything that they want to share anything they want to ask Thank you for being here
Take good care You're welcome