arato sama
sambasa arhat sama [Music]
sambasa bawat arhat sama
sambasa budd All [Music]
right some of you know the words awesome
tell people there's some more front yeah sure yeah if anybody wants to come
forward they got room up front
and and there are also uh kind of these cushions out out just outside the room
if people wanted to grab
those well I hope everyone experienced that sit as I did as very quiet that was
a very quiet sit uh I think it was partially partially the carpet partially
the carpet uh it's partially all of all of you we're all contributing to silence
together which is rather amazing to have this many people in a room together for half an hour
and basically just be quiet together it's a really unique way that humans
don't usually uh we don't usually interact in this way and I mean I'm not
super woowoo just because I have the the robes but uh I there is you know coming into a
place where this place this hall has been used for meditation and had great
bicku great monk teachers great nun teachers great lay teachers come and and teach in here with all sorts of people
meditating for 25 years or since 2002 2002 okay so this is a great space and
uh I feel really uh happy to be here with everyone uh my name is Ajang Kovilo and I
ordained at a monastery in north of Yukaya uh called Abayiri and I'm
currently starting a monastery uh I became a monk in 200 well came to the monastery in 2006
and I've been a monk since 2010 and currently starting a monastery with my
monk brother Ajaniso up in Seattle it's called Clear Mountain Monastery and
usually we're meditating in a gym gy gym
and uh we call it the triple gym because we're Buddhists and uh it has a disco
ball and hardwood floors and yeah it's rarely it's it's never been this this
quiet uh up there um but yeah my mom actually lives just
uh you know 10 15 minutes down the road in uh Minlo Park so I come to visit her
from time to time and I'm very happy to be making this connection with IMC because I secretly want to convert my
mom to Buddhism and even if she wasn't Buddhist I want her to meditate and this is just
such a great kind of this is a great place this is like her she's not
Buddhist but this is this would be her Buddhism um basically a group of people who are just curious who want to find
inner peace and want to learn specific strategies for settling the mind
so she's come here actually for uh a couple of different events and uh I
think it's not going to be too long it's not going to be too long before I've got her coming on the regular maybe
um but tonight I actually wanted to talk about um SA this SA gem the SA jewel the
SA as refuge and it's a little bit interesting
to talk about in the west I mean you talk about the Buddha as an archetype of these three uh these three gyms these
three refuges the Buddha he was a historical figure satarta Gota he uh
attained enlightenment 2600 or so years ago is you know what we uh believe and
there's lots of history to to back that up uh and budau what we were reciting is
just the principle of wakefulness of being awake so as we recite that just reminding ourselves that we're not here
to fall asleep our eyes are closed but really are trying to stay awake actually
in a way which is balanced in a way which isn't biased towards chasing after the things we like
and running away for the things we don't like so just wakefulness with balance is is the Buddha is the archetype of the
Buddha is the principle of the Buddha is the mantra of Buddha and Dharma his teachings basically the truth the way
things are these are very easy for modern Americans to kind of get behind
why not be awake with compassion why not see the truth it seems like all good
things but then you get to the SA and you got people dressed like me And
you know it's something that most of us didn't grow up with and it can seem a bit foreign it can seem very
institutional um one of the monks in our tradition uh so all of the monks at the monastery
where I ordained were born in America none of them had Buddhist families and
were all basically convert Buddhists and um one of the fathers of one of the
monks you know is kind of lamenting he's very you know secular person he's kind of lamenting to his monk's son he's like
I can't believe maybe atheists grew up atheist and the father is lamenting he's saying I can't believe you would go and
join an organized religion and this monk says "Actually we're not that
organized." So there is this tension and you see somebody wearing a costume like this and
and you think I don't want it you know I've seen Wild Wild Country or whatever
that documentary about Osho is and you think I don't know if I can get within
you know foot you know arms reach of uh somebody in robes like this but yeah I
just thought to uh talk about different types of SA so um roughly speaking I'll
talk about four types of SA and then really honing into the latter two so
roughly speaking you have the word sa uh s n s a n with a dot over it technically
g h a sa it can just mean a group so you have places in the polycanon which is
the teaching basically the Buddhist cannon where you see a group of a mega
sunga which is a group of deer or a kaka sunga which is a group of crows so here
it's just any group of beings you have a dva sunga that's just a group of
celestial beings so that's just the most basic level of of sa just a group of
people the second type of sunga is what is really just uh a beautiful aspect
mostly of IMC or of spirit rock or of IMS berry center uh is the lay sa so you
have a group of people many of whom might not even call themselves Buddhist but all of whom are really looking for
peace looking for ways to train the mind and bring some sense of yeah stillness
and solidity into their into their hearts and it really is beautiful i mean
uh I Gil I was kind of in between monasteries before I had actually
ordained and I Gil didn't know me from anybody else and IMC already existed and
I just found out the Gil's email address or emailed the group email address here
and said I'm kind of struggling uh do I go the path of a monastic or do I stay
the path of like a lay Buddhist because I was really committed by that time to a life of meditation and virtue and didn't
know me never met me but within 3 days he said "Yeah let's go for a walk." And he makes the time to meet me here and I
think I volunteered to paint a door and I painted that door out there i don't know if it's still uh Don't don't look
too closely uh I didn't I don't know if Well a job I did but uh took the time
and basically walked around the block a couple times and yeah great teacher lay
teachers in America are many of them are fabulous um and so this is a lelay sa and but
using the word sa in this context of a specifically le sa is somewhat of a
western usage so you go to Thailand you go to Burma you go to Sri Lanka which are the main uh countries of Terravada
Buddhism which is roughly the Buddhism of of IMC and Spirit Rock and the tradition I came from a Thai a Thai
tradition um and SA is just reserved for the monastic SA so bikus and beunis
people who are uh largely robed in different forms and who've taken on a certain number of precepts that they're
living with for a certain period of time so here in America we've got this lay
sana and it really is such a such a support and there are uh groups uh yeah
some monastic orders who really take exception to that use of sa and say that the word sa really should just refer to
a monastic sa uh it's inappropriate to use SA with within a lay
context but if you've got a a SA of davas a sa of celestial beings a sa of
yeah just any any group I feel it's a very valid use of of the word especially
when in a place like America you don't have that many monastics where you know
hopefully not whatever the opposite of an endangered species is whenever the species is like you
growing and taking over um hopefully that's what the SA is um but yeah you've
got this Lelay SA so that's the second type of SA and I'm so happy for all of you who live near here and can come here
on a regular basis if this is your first time would encourage you to come back because there's a lot of great teachers
who who share the Dharma here and the third type of SA is the monastic SA um
the SA of Bikuz who are ordained monks and Bikunis ordained nuns uh who've
dawned what's called dawned the ochre robe and really dedicated their life to
keeping certain precepts and really keep our emblematic we're basically flags we
are flags for Buddhism we we're always wearing these robes i wear these robes to bed i sleep in some of these robes
and uh we're wearing them all the time we don't take them off when we want to go and break some precepts we're you
know keeping them keeping them all the time wearing them all the time and uh
it's our lives and we have to a large part in our early years in robes we're just figuring out how to wear the robes
and it's it's a good reminder uh because they're not easy this rectangle this outer rectangle is about 9 ft wide by 6
feet tall and we just basically roll ourselves up like a soft shell taco and
it's not so convenient it's not convenient you're walking around and you have to be mindful it's a it's forced
mindfulness is this roll the roll will often times fall off so you're having to
constantly keep some level of bodily mindfulness and really in our tradition
the ajanch cha tradition of Thai Buddhism uh really
meditation gone to the body meditation which is yolked to the body mindfulness
which fills the whole body is really kind of the foundation of our practice and that is inclusive of breath
meditation so we're a symbol the ordained SA for however length of time
in some Buddhist countries like Sri Lanka it is most monks do ordain for
life so uh yeah that's a big commitment in Thailand much less so most monks who
ordain in Thailand will disrobe it's almost always a temporary ordination uh
the tradition in Thailand so up until maybe 15 or 20 years ago uh it was a
practice for males in Thailand to ordain for some period of 3 months so the
majority of Thai men would ordain probably 70 plus% of Thai males have
spent some time in robes in a traditional period of time would be three months but that could even be
these days it's a lot less you do have people ordaining for a weekend it's lame
if there are any Thai people watching it's lame three months it's a good It's a
good period to really just figure spend that first month just figuring out how to wear the robe you know um but we do
have aside from the robes uh we have all these rules that we're keeping and largely uh it is uh variations and
extensions and expansions from what are called the eight precepts so in Buddhism for anyone who doesn't know uh basically
the foundation of Buddhist morality for anyone for someone who's um yeah just
curious to take on another level of ethical training and harmlessness in their lives you got the five precepts
where which are a voluntary training you can say the this formula I undertake the
precept to refrain from taking the life of any living creature i undertake the precept to refrain from taking that
which has not been given i undertake the precept to refrain from sexual misconduct i undertake the precept to
refrain from lying i undertake the precept to refrain from consuming intoxicants intoxicating drinks and
drugs which lead to carelessness so those are the five precepts and they're a great foundation for an ethical
life but in Buddhist countries you will have people taking on three more these
eight precepts which people will take them on lay people will take them on for short periods of time maybe one day a
week or a couple days a month when you just I'm going to up game I'm going to uplevel for this day maybe take on these
extra three and if these first three are moral or first five are moral precepts
especially those first four really do have a bearing on the degree to which
you bring harmlessness into the And the degree to which you're able to give this gift of harmlessness to the
people around you this flag that we wear is a symbol for harmlessness even if
people have no idea what we are they're not afraid of us the deer at a Bayer
they're not afraid of us by there for about almost 30 years now and every 6
years or so there'll be a noticeable closening of the deer population they just get closer and
closer at night time you can get within Yeah from me to Nick of you know uh
several deer you get that close the deer are just not afraid because they know it's a safe place there's no shooting
there's no violence so people take on these eight precepts the next three the renuncient ones are refraining from
eating afternoon seventh one is to refrain from uh beautifification and adorement
specifically from listening to music or playing music or bodily beautifification
and adorement and the last one is refraining from lying on a high or luxurious bed and most of the monk and
nuns rules are expansions of those so we have rules like uh monks do not eat
after noon so and we can't store food
afternoon and food has to be offered to us so if you were to invite us to your
house you wouldn't have to be afraid that we're going to go into your refrigerator and take all your food
because food actually has to be placed into a monk's hand uh or placed into our bowl for us to be able to eat it uh all
your food is safe around monastics
um and yeah this entertainment we consciously refrain from entertainment
when you come to a monastery in our tradition we have an active period of uh
seven years in particular where it's like a forced digital detox there's two
or three different levels of training when you come in first you live just as a normal leg guest everybody keeps the
eight precepts when they're visiting a monastery um and then after that you can request the white robes of a eight
preceptor and you're also wearing robes and you kind of at that phase you give up maybe you give up your devices you
give up your cell phone and any other device you might have then you take sa
after a year which is a novice ordination and then that's when we give up money so renuncience we don't use
money uh literally we don't have a dollar to our name even if we touch
money like if you were to try to if if we're going on alms around this happens most monks even though it is a rule most
monks and nuns around around the world actually do use money but the Ajan cha tradition very strict with this that we
don't even we don't touch money if you tried to touch money to us we'd be like and if we were on alms round and
you tried to put money in our If we were to move from that location
then it would be an offense so we actually very kindly say "Actually we can't take money and could you would you
be willing to uh take the money back?" And uh we can receive food so if you
wanted to make a food offering that's great and we can eat it today before noon um but we can't take money
uh so you take that novice precept and then after a year you take uh the monastic the full uh 227 or 311 rules of
a monastic and we give up entertainment and when you became become a monk you
give up your old email you're given a new email address and uh yeah basically
you don't have any device I myself didn't have a phone for eight years nine
years something like had uh only had my monastery email address and yeah you get
a taste and basically there's no cell signal at the monastery in general it's in a valley and couldn't get it if you
wanted it um so forced digital detox and it's great you just get a period of a
long period of away to just totally reset and see all the ways that we're pulled in different directions by by our
devices and all the notifications so refraining from entertainment from
beautifification and lying on a a high or luxurious sleeping place which is
defined as having you can have legs which are eight finger breaths high but
above that that's high and a little bit luxurious um and you might think what
what is the point of that what is the point of that um but it's fascinating i
mean I haven't I have slept on bit like visiting family my mom thinks it's super
weird if I don't if I lie on the floor so sometimes I'll I'll sleep on a bed when I'm at her place but honestly I
prefer the floor and it's it might seem weird and quickotic it might seem
strange like what is what kind of training is that it just seems arbitrary but it's it's a gateway into more
renunciation so you you start lying on just a you know you don't have to go to
just lying on a you know uh air mattress most of our huts at the monastery just
have an air mattress and the monks will sleep on that but you can have a you know a thick you can sleep on a mattress
on the ground and you just realize that you actually don't need a bed you don't
need a bed a bed takes up so much space in a room it's like all high and what do you even do under there it just collects
dust and you realize that you don't need it and things are simpler without it and
when you're used to just sleeping on the floor it's easier to go camping uh you know you can just there's all sorts of
benefits that are just knock-on effects that you wouldn't have guessed when you take on this this precept and just you
can experiment doing it for uh you know one day a week or one day a month just
today I'm not going to lie on a high bed going to put my mattress on the floor or
experiment not eating afternoon and that does take a while to uh get used to the
body but the body does get used to it i haven't eaten solid food afternoon
for almost 20 years and I'm doing okay
i'm doing okay i got a normal BMI um and yeah so just roughly speaking
these are the value of a renunciate sa and why I bring it up is because you do
have sa who come here monastic sa who come here ajan tenisero does she still
come on a yearly basis sanusa and does she come and teach
here maybe I think she has she
has I think she was in yeah she's got now she has uh there's two of our great
Bikuni sisters who have a a monastery in Sunnyville and also down in the Santa Cruz Mountains where you can go and
visit uh and there's lots of other monastics we have a we have a YouTube channel so after you know eight years of
that detox you know kind of somebody gave me a cell phone and then it all went downhill from then but uh but now
we have a YouTube channel but it's it's great um we interview great monastic teachers and song teachers we've
interviewed Gil um Shila Katherine Joseph Goldstein a lot of great
teachers we've got a Zoom group that we meet with um so this is just an
encouragement to find SA and if you don't have monastics in your neighborhood then drive down to the next
neighborhood and if you live in San Francisco then you can drive down here or if you live wherever you live uh it's
worth it's worth the drive to meet um people who are really trying to give their life to the Buddhist teachings in
a way which is is visible you know we we can't sneak around you know we
don't I don't have I don't own jeans anymore I don't own pants anymore people I couldn't go out and sneak around if I
wanted to um and so it really is and um yeah there
are different sas who hold the rules in different ways um but yeah if you can
find a sanga bus or bunis who really are keeping you can you can kind of get a
feel for someone when you live around them and this person seems like they've got a gravitas to them or they've got
yeah they're just living in a way which is a bit different it's a bit of a mirror for uh for our lives my mom um
yeah when I come to my mom's house we clean up cuz she's like I own so little
i own so little and she owns so much that she just looks at me and she wants to give things away so the last several
times I've come today I spent all morning if you see any dust on me it's because we've been cleaning up her bookshelf all morning and just giving
things away we take you know multiple boxes to the local thrift stores when I
come to visit and so it's just a a good encouragement to and why give away why
give away it's not just to deprive yourself but because there is a happiness there is a nikama suka a
happiness a joy which comes from renunciation from giving things up from being able to thrive with less the
Buddha talked about friends good friends three characteristics of a good friend is that they give what's hard to give
they're able to do what's hard to do and they're able to endure that which is hard to endure and you can make yourself
a good friend in those ways when you kind of Yeah just push yourself beyond
uh a little bit beyond what you think has to be your level of of comfort and
in Buddhism um you know some people think it's a negative religion ajan
Punadama one of our teachers in um in Canada he says people come to me and
they say that Buddhism all you talk about is suffering and he says no we also talk about sorrow lamentation pain
grief and despair what you got this whole spectrum of teachings um and that that is all true
and it is great to have people who don't hopefully are learning to not flinch from yeah the suffering and stress of
life but you can also conceive of the Buddhist path one of my favorite dharmapata verses says that if by
relinquishing renouncing getting rid of letting go of a lesser happiness a coarser happiness you're able to enter
into a more refined happiness a subtler happiness a higher happiness then the wise person will relinquish that lesser
happiness that more coarse happiness the happiness which might entail some level
of suffering to other people a harmful happiness then the wise person will let
go of that lesser happiness having their eyes set on the higher happiness so the whole path is one of letting go of more
and more ajancha our kind of grandfather teacher said when you let go a little
bit you get a little bit of peace and when you let go a lot then you get a lot
of peace and when you let go completely you get complete peace and that might be
a good transition to this fourth type of SA which is the true SA the Arya SA the
noble capital N noble capital SA the Arya SA and this is the SA the group of
not just monastics but lay monastic male female anyone who has
trained their heart to a level of true awakening to a
non backsliding state so in Buddhism we do talk about four levels of enlightenment stream entry once return
non- returnturn our huntship but it is starts off as a belief and then it becomes an experience
of actually being able to through meditation through stillness through practice to be able to permanently let
go of obstructive mental states to permanently let go of doubt about the
path and eventually what an arhant has done they someone who's fully enlightened they've fully let go fully
let go of greed anger and delusion the delusion which
um doesn't know how a human causes themselves suffering and how to let all
of that go so that's the delusion which in our hand has completely transcended they know completely how unhelpful
unhealthy craving leads to suffering and they've just totally dropped that
and yeah it is it starts off as a belief and it is part of what's called mundane
right view so transcendent right view is knowing the four noble truths that there
is suffering there's a cause there's a sessation and there's a path but transcendent right view is these much
more mundane um beliefs about the world so there are
10 of them that the Buddha lists specifically there is what is given what
is offered where is sacrificed that is there is benefit of generosity and yeah
that is that's a belief and all of you hopefully all of us have been gathering
evidence about the effectiveness of generosity when you give your heart grows and you've seen the generous
people in your life and you've seen that their hearts are bright you've seen that they're they tread lightly and the best
givers are really many of the best people that we know but it's a belief there is what's given what's offered
what's sacrificed there is fruit and result of good and bad action so this is
a belief about karma um that when you do
things which bring harm into the world then they'll you'll receive harmful results and when you act in a way which
is harmless is beneficial is um healthy for yourself then you'll receive
healthful results and there is mother and father so there is some kind of
relationship um yeah that is significant between ourselves and our our parents um
and there are there's this world there's the next world there are spontaneously risen beings i won't talk about that
right now um basically just suggesting that what we see isn't the
whole of the picture there are other realms in traditional Buddhism and that's a belief that um yeah there's
evidence for um but won't talk about that tonight don't worry and the final
one is that there are beings there are beings who through their own practice
have realized the path and teach it so it is possible and this is a belief and
this is a belief and if you've never thought about it then I'm going to say it right now and then you're going to
have to think about it and you're going to have to really come down on one side or the other of this because we're all
operating in different moments from different defaults is do you believe is
it possible to abandon unh wholesome states and what the Buddha posits is
that it is possible to abandon unh wholesome mental states and it is possible to cultivate wholesome mental
states and that's a belief and when we're
depressed we just can't get ourselves to believe that it's impossible i'm totally dark my my heart is totally dark and
there's no way I'm just going to be like this till I die there's just depression has sunk my heart and there's no escape
whereas hopefully when we're able to get a bit above the water yeah it is possible to cultivate wholesome mental
states and it is possible to abandon unh wholesome mental states that's at the root of any wholesome habit of any
helpful habit that you take on and at the root of any unh wholesome habit unhealthy habit that you're giving up
and you take a it is a belief and would encourage anybody to Yeah it's just a
nice belief it's a nice belief to have and the next belief is that there are beings it is possible to completely
transcend greed anger and delusion and that might be another step do you believe that there are humans who have
who just no longer have greed and anger coming up in their hearts
and most of us maybe have never met anybody who comes anywhere close to that
but the more you stay around centers like this the more you come to monasteries maybe the more you go to um
traditional Buddhist country where say like a place like Thailand you've got 300,000 monastics you got 30,000
monasteries and yeah I can't know I don't know totally the heart of other
people but I do feel like I've met beings who I've
met Yeah not just one um but I've met beings who I believe have actually
attained this level of the Arya SA who have completely transcended greed anger
and delusion and and that one it's a beautiful belief to have that a human
heart can transcend to that level if you hold the belief healthfully
you don't want to beat yourself up because we're not there yet we are where we are but just yeah maybe a human heart
can come to a place through training of the the mind training of the heart that
these mind states just no longer come up if you've ever given up smoking smoking or any other bad habit and if you've
done it for decades just the thought never comes up anymore and take that
principle to yeah hopefully if you've been meditating for a while the anger that you used to feel so chronically or
used to come up So with so much fire hopefully that just comes up less than
it did 5 years ago 10 years ago 15 years ago 20 years ago and just extend that
principle that maybe if I keep walking this path that I myself can become part
of this noble this noble sa and it's a it's a cool belief it's
not just a healthy and a happy it's a it's a it's a cool belief to have and
yeah hopefully I hope all of you get to meet someone who inspires the faith um
living closely with these people or just meeting them you might be able to see like a a radiance or even having met
people like this the image of you know in Christian iconography the image of a a halo it
just makes sense you meet people who seem to have like a a bright there's some kind of brightness to them or you
might there's one teacher who I do feel has this attainment um and it would be
like on multiple occasions I get within 20 ft of them and I might not even know
that they're you know 20 ft away and automatically like my heart just drops down into this deep place of of
mindfulness just knowing if it's a a meditation object like Buddh just buddo the Buddho kind of inner mantra just it
just goes on like you know motor hall and um yeah wow that's interesting I
wasn't like that you know 10 seconds ago um so yeah those are the four types of
sa and yeah all of us right now this is definitely we've gone beyond just being
a herd of deer or a group of crows we're all definitely in this um level of of
lea and And I totally encourage you just having community the value of community
especially these days when this uh you know pandemic or this pandemic of
isolation so many people are isolated finding a place like this where you can find community is great that third level
of monastic sa finding the monastics near you especially the inspiring ones and the uninspiring
ones I figure out how to deal with them as well um but the inspiring ones draw
close and then the noble sa yeah just just look for them and yeah
see if your heart can believe in something like that so we'll end the formal talk there and just open things
up for for questions we've got just 10 minutes i was hoping we'd have a bit more time than that but um if anybody
had any questions or things to to share um yeah please
hang on a second i'll bring a microphone thank you
it's kind of harder to stay put like initially there is excitement for example you joined in 2006 so you're
trying to be part of the practice there's initial excitement there is like a feeling that there's something great
going to happen there is some I'm just kidding like nirvana or like or there's
like a lot of people talk about lot of things you could achieve or something but what happens is after 2 three years
sometimes people how did you endure it because you you might feel you're not making enough progress you're not there
or what people are saying is not what you are experiencing and so on yeah you know it's a great it's a great question
and um yeah I think this is very common
there's a a phrase which comes up in the the canon about the dharma which says that the dharma the dharma the Buddhist
teachings are beautiful in the beginning beautiful in the middle and beautiful in the end and that's great and hopefully
you'll keep finding ways that the dharma is inspiring but I was reflecting a few days ago that the SA the SA starts off
sometimes if your if your heart is kind of open to it the SA starts off it's beautiful in the beginning you see these
monastics and they wear their robes slightly well and you know they know a lot of polywords and you go to a
monastery and everybody's bowing at the same time and it's it's inspiring beautiful in the beginning but then you live with these
guys and the smells and the all the other human the humanness of the sauna
so it's a little bit less than beautiful in the middle in the middle in the middle you don't know how long that's
going to last and many people do disrobe and part of our training and the Buddha laid this out is for your first 5 years
as a monk there's a principle in Christian monasticism called stability
you stay at the same monastery or you stay with your teacher for the first 5 years but after that you do you can move
around a bit more um but yeah hopefully um yeah you you realize that the SA we
are still human most of us the vast vast majority of us have not yet attained to
this level of the noble sa yeah we do act out of our greed anger
and delusion and those things they're ugly it's ugly whether it's a lay person a monk seeing greed and seeing anger is
ugly but it seems a little bit especially ugly if you see someone who's wearing this robe act out of that so you
come to a monastery it's easy to get uninspired but if you can stick through that and say they're a human and they're
going through whatever they're going through but the robe is still beautiful and us we bow we bow so much we bow so
much at a monastery and um yeah it's a good thing to be able to bow to the robe
to be be able to bow to the archetype um rather than the individual cuz individual the Buddha said himself like
you shouldn't place faith necessarily in any one teacher but
in the SA institution as a whole those beings who the possibility for
transcendence so if you can kind of separate mentally in your mind the robes the ideal of both
the monastic sa and the arry sa the noble sa in your mind then you can keep hopefully come back to a place where it
is beautiful in the end and yeah you can come back and they're
flawed humans um but they're still if they're sinc if they're sincere and
there are sincere monastics in the world and even if a whole monastery is a bunch of you know lazy and whatever monastics
there are still practicing bikus and bikunis who are practicing rightly in the world so coming back and finding
that beauty and yeah so yeah you're welcome yeah
please oh yeah fun I just wanted to respond can you
hear me I just wanted to respond to him that uh as a college instructor I just
trying to connect the situation question which he asked so I started semester with 150 students
right and right now I might have 100 or maybe 90 so not everybody graduates
right so same with um any I think if you compare this to monastics so many of
them might start but some of them will drop and it's okay they might come back later or maybe they won't come it's not
for them right yeah so just seeing that not trying to uh finding some perfection
in beings is the path that we all have flaws we all are learning and then one
day is different than another we might drop today come back tomorrow and maybe
day after or maybe never and that's a a lifelong journey and not only this life so many lifetimes we've been here
walking this path thank you Vana yeah and would just put a plug i mean we
really do have a vibrant SA we don't yet have land in Seattle but we do have a vibrant online SA um we have weekly Zoom
meetings every Sunday night we go through the Maji Minikaya the middle- length Discourses of the Buddha we're on
36 we're doing one a week so that's 152 sutas about 3 years we're on 36 and you
can start next week and it's great we've got a group of about 50 people who join every Sunday night and we put out a a
video at 5:00 p.m and you can watch and it kind of summarizes the suta and you get on and you know people like Vonda
and I are there and Wednesday evenings we also have a zoom session after an interview um so yeah just join and this
is fantastic how CM sa clear mountain sa is growing it's like I joined them I
think in 22 but then now we see so many and they don't even have a monastery yet
so it's just the power of the dharma and coming through those two beautiful monastics feel like everybody connects
with them that's what my personal feeling is and Deborah and the other people who are here we know them right
and I don't have any money so I didn't pay her to say that so she volunteered
thank you and this might be the last question but
uh thank you for an amazing talk it's always inspirational to see people who've uh renounced so much
um my question is I often find myself thinking about um how much to renounce
um you know like I in in my own life I've noticed cravings that are
definitely unhealthy and good to let go of but then there are some cravings like craving for music that I really enjoy
and I was very struck when you said that you gave up music for eight years um so
I guess my question is did did the Buddha think that it's necessary to enter into the monastic lifestyle to
transcend um greed hatred and delusion um yeah to become part of this noble sa
um you don't have to become a monastic uh there yeah time of the Buddha you
know hundreds of thousands I think the report goes of of lay people who've attained some level of the path and the
final level of or the second to last and the last um you do one finally does
transcend sensual desire or lust so basically it's almost default
monasticism but yeah monastics it's not just the first seven or eight years but we basically have given up music and we
do have quite a few former musicians but it's definitely I'd say take so there's
a great term in in educational studies called the zone of proximal development and if you're on this end of the zone
like if something's too easy for you if you're in fifth grade and somebody gives you you know kindergarten math you're
just not learning at all and if you're in fifth grade and somebody gives you advanced calculus for college student
that's way beyond you you're just flailing whereas you got this zone of proximal development where you're cutting your teeth and you're really
learning and I'd say just experiment you don't want to give so much that life is unnecessarily dooka you're not trying to
do it to to elicit depression you know you're you're doing it to make the heart
brighter and to realize that you actually need less you can be happy with less um so taking that that measure of
of well-being um as a measure for how much you're you're giving up and yeah
you can do it just temporarily for a day oh maybe today I can experiment with not listening to music or not eating
afternoon or lying on a a mat for the night and see how it goes and if it's inspiring then yeah maybe you can do it
again and if it's helpful one of the reasons we give up music is just because we meditate a lot and sometimes you get
it like I have if a thought Yeah songs can get in our heads for like a long time a long time yeah
well that might be the end of the session and it's really lovely to meet all of you um I brought two sets of
books which we published at Clear Mountain which they look almost exactly the same but they are different and um
the backs look different but this is every time in the cannon when the Buddha said thus you should train yourself so
all of these trainings that someone can take on if you're experimenting with
that kind of thing and the second one is all about pamoa which it can be translated as well-being
so the Buddha talked about you've heard of Samupata or dependent origination which is the causality of suffering
whereas this is the causality of happiness you do certain things and the Buddha gives this image of it's like a
cloud a raincloud raining down on the top of a mountain which the rain then fills up the pools up here which then
fill over and fill up the pools down here pools pools pools all the way to the great ocean and so too the Buddha
said you do things the various clouds are like being generous having a sense
of ethics like uh the precepts um listening to dhamma um these are all
what water the pools of pomoa of well-being you do this and the Buddha says it's natural you just be generous
and it's natural that you have a sense of well-being from well-being it's just natural that that will lead to when the
pool fills up it will fill over into the next pool of py or joy which then fills
over to pati which is bodily tranquility which fills up and leads to suka or
happiness or pleasure which fills up and leads to samadei which leads to concentration to a collected mind a
naturally collected mind which then fills up leads to seeing things as they are to dispassion sessation
nibbana and it's interesting to note there that people often think once I get
my samadei or concentration together once If I learn how to meditate then I'll be happy whereas in this
progression you see the Buddha said it's the other way around it's once you get your happiness together then your
meditation will fall together it'll fall into place and you'll be able to actually sit and you think about your
day i just did a bunch of good stuff i helped my clean bookshelves with my mom and you know whatever it was even though
it was filthy you know just joking mom it was it was it was uh dusty um so yeah
there there are these books outside and um also have stickers poly stickers
anybody who likes the poly language we've got dooka on there if you want to put And we do have a club of people up
in Clear Mountain who actually take the dooka sticker and put it on the front of their phones are you Are you up to the
challenge yeah and you can actually scroll through it so but but yeah um
yeah would love to give those out to anybody and would just say it's it's
been really lovely sitting with all of you and come join Clear Mountain anytime
both online and if you ever visit Seattle we do meet in person once a week
um on Saturday mornings and then in person all we eat 5 days a week is the
food that we're given on alms so you can come and if you're in Seattle you can offer alms Pike Place Starbucks for
Starbucks and offer alms to one of the monastics that's there and uh yeah would
love to see you all up there in person or down here again when I'm staying with my mom so thank you all
okay thank you Ajan Killo yeah Jen yeah