hello and welcome back to IMC those of you who
are with me especially to Spirit Rock and
uh I think it would be nice if I could broadcast every day from a place like Spirit Rock outdoors and
uh it's not so convenient to find a place that's quiet for that purpose but
uh this works to be here
so we're continuing in this practice of
samadei and there is a variety of happinesses
joys that are elicited in the in the practice of
samadei and beginning to appreciate the different kinds of
well-being that come along ong it helps the process clinging to it striving for
happiness is not so useful but recognizing it or allowing it and um
valuing it when it happens is helpful so in the beginning of um the practice
of going into the Janna there is the happiness of
um the joy the h kind of happiness of uh for the time
being at least during the time you're meditating the the kind of
happiness of being ethical here and now in this
state in this body we're not going to cause any harm and so that's
there there's a happiness that's a contentment that just for now we have
enough we have enough to be sitting quietly and closing our eyes to meditate
we have enough shelter enough clothes we have enough food just maybe just
enough and uh and it to have a contentment rather than a feeling of
lack and then there's the happiness of no longer being caught up in
preoccupations no longer being caught up in the concerns for you know our challenges in the world
not to put those challenges away or deny them or repress them but for now they
are left outside the meditation
hall so the happiness of not being preoccupied and then there's the
happiness of seclusion of having left things outside the metaphorical meditation hall now
we're in this kind of different zone sacred zone contemplative
zone now we can really and and kind of uh
legally put aside our concerns for the world our uh
responsibilities we've left we've kind of checked them at the door we've kind of now we're kind of here and we can
focus internally to this body and mind to this time here and there's a happiness of
seclusion happiness of no longer being preoccupied with the world no longer
living in the world uh rattled by or pushed this way and
that way by what happens that can be for later but for now the happiness of being in this space
of meditation there's the happiness of then being able to give oneselves over
wholeheartedly to um sincerely to the process of meditation
through just giving ourselves over in a unified way gathering
ourselves together being complete feeling whole feeling here grounded
feeling somehow solid feeling settled this is good this is a kind of
happiness and then there comes the happiness of uh the mind being equist
and non-reactive the happiness that's a happiness of the
body and I like to think of it as the happy body the body is a field of
well-being maybe very difficult to imagine for some people
but now we get to dip into the lake of
well-being the wake of happiness some people call it the wake of bliss
so assuming a meditation
posture and giving some loving care to your
posture caring for how the posture for
meditation can help you feel solid
alert here rooted
perhaps to whatever surface is holding you from
falling by the pull of gravity
here on this spot and gently softly closing your
eyes and with the assumption that one way or the other even in the smallest
corners of your body there is well-being
there is some feel form of well-being
happiness perhaps it's simply pleasure that is not because of
anything but it just because it arises out of being settled
being alive the sensations of being alive that
appear here and now maybe some of them are pleasant
enjoyable maybe qualifies as being symptoms of happiness to be
here and then as you breathe maybe breathing more deeply
fully breathe into and with whatever that sense of pleasure or
happiness is giving it permission to be
there and giving yourself permission to feel it as you
breathe as if you breathe through it and with
it and as you exhale to relax let
go and if it's possible to have a momentary pause at the end of the
exhale so you can feel the goodness or
sweetness of simply being here here and
now letting your breathing return to normal
but continuing for a little while to have that little pause at the end of the
exhale as a way of feeling whatever is good or comfortable
settled enjoyable in just being here and now
independent of the world independent of obligations
preoccupations sometimes it can be nice to make a small half
smile especially if that triggers a little bit feelings of joy or delight
and whatever good feelings that come from the small half
smile orient your meditation your efforts your how you see
things through the lens of that well-being that joy
breathing in
joy breathing out relaxing
and as you relax below the joy
below can you find the happy body the happiness of the
body a contentment a sweetness
a vitality that feels
pleasant and this should not be feared
breathing with the happy
body and all other things can be known within the field of
happiness the lotuses in the
lake gently
breathing in the vast
space of happiness
contentment allowing the thinking mind to get quieter
letting go of thoughts as you
exhale so there's more space to feel the happy body
as you meditate trust the
well-being of meditation of being present
present with every
breath breathing the body breathing in joy the body breathing in
happiness trusting the physical embodied
well-being more than you trust whatever you're thinking about
relax the thinking mind so you can
feel the well-being of your body
and as we come to the end of this sitting to feel into your
body to see if there's any greater feeling of calm physical
calm settleness
Any greater sense of contented
aliveness in the present moment just
here just in the nowness the
hearness is there any greater sense of
well-being sense of happiness however small it might
be take in whatever is good in your
body as we come to the end of the
meditation breathe it in
maybe drink it in let it fill you spread in you
as if the world asks you
please be in touch with your happiness your
well-being as if the world says we need more people who know
this who trust this as if the whole
world asks Please don't
add to distress to fear to anger in this
world there is more than enough of it not enough people
know how to be at peace with themselves
please feel that peace
and come into the world carrying that with
you as medicine for the world may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may your you stay close to your own
well-being stay close to a peaceful happy body as if you're
medicine walking through the world
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to the next talk in this series on
samadei and uh in the week of the third Janna and uh the instructions in
meditation that's given for fir first the third Janna is very simple
uh the actual things that we do um it says that one enters and
abides and experiences happiness in the body
so one enters and abides in this deep state and one then experiences the
happiness of the body that's the instruction the most active instructions
experience the happiness or almost the most act active and then it goes on to say give this
instructions so this if you want to do something if you're a doer this is what you actually do in the third
janna you would pervade saturate ate and permeate this
body with a with happiness so no part of the body is not
touched i mean it's kind of remarkable instructions to spread to happiness
around the body so that the whole body feels happy
now whether the word should translate it from poly into English should be happy or happiness is a person dependent
each of us will have a different relationship with different words and different inner states so it's in the
family of happiness states so maybe it's contentment maybe it's a sweetness maybe
it's a deep sense of being cozy and comforted
maybe it's a kind of ting warm glowing sense of
aliveness maybe it's a kind of glowing happy feeling of peace in the body
so you know the idea is to here is not to take
um some impersonal idea of what these words are but to make the words personal
so the word happiness find a way it can become your word with what you recognize
and can feel inside for yourself and eventually we come into what I call the
happy body the happiness body many of us walk around with a fear
body and the whole body is tensed in a certain way and and hyper vigilant
because it's just filled courarssing with fear some people are in the sadness body
that depressed body the grief body some people might be in the volcanic
anger body rage body and so the whole experience of the
body shifts and change what's going on there's the ecstatic uh body of
something really fantastic happening maybe you think winning the lottery for
millions billions of dollars is a good thing and you're just like your whole body is just kind of firing all the
neurons is fire firing with excitement and there's the excitement
body uh there's the uh nurturing tender
uh caring body of maybe caring for a injured bird
or maybe holding a newborn baby and uh the whole body shifts and
changes so in a sense we have different bodies and uh and the happiness body is
another one and one and that's part of the movement in meditation in samadei
practice is to move into these really healthy and healing bodies and one of the ways to do that is
to have a kind of a good meditation posture good means
maybe dignified maybe upright maybe um or maybe it's better to define it by
what it's not it's not collapsing it's not recoiling it's not
shutting down it's not reaching for and trying to make something happen
um and so uh we're not we're not being the the posture
itself is not under the sway of what's happening in the world
and what's happening with our emotional life inside terms of the posture so the
posture becomes kind of like the monastery the posture becomes a meditation hall the posture becomes the
source that can the container that can hold everything and we begin to
experience and recognize how much we in fact are being swayed this way and that
way by what's happening in the world what's happening with our relationships what's happening with work and family
and home that our moods and emotions are so dependent so uh influenced we're so
influencable by all the things that's happening around us we're constantly
reacting this way and this way and that way and uh
samadei is the practice of beingcoming so fully present and home and stable
here in the moment that the posture is no longer being
uh under the influence of emotions the world the events of the
times and then slowly the inner life the inner the heart the the yoni the deep
place inside um begins to come alive the inner life becomes
alive independent of what's happening in the world
and this is a revolution for some people revolution for the heart to feel a sense
of well-being to feel a sense of aliveness uh uh contentment peace
uh happiness that's not dependent on what is happening in the
world and this is not a betrayal of the world betrayal of our
relationships it's actually putting ourselves in a really healthy way that
we can go into the world into our relationships in an infinitely better
way where we offer it our clarity offer it our fullness offer our um
peace offer our respect our attention that can't be offered if part
of what we are is reacting to the present moment caught up in our desires
caught up in the feelings emotions about and desires and aversions that have to do with the present moment and what's
happening we don't bring the fullness the best of us when we're being swayed
this way and that way so the training in samadei is a fantastic training for daily
life and knowing that might make it easier for your mind body heart to be
willing to put aside the world put aside your
relationships put aside your preoccupations because you'll be coming back to them after the
meditation and you're putting aside long enough to be
transformed be changed into a kind of deeper settleness deeper fullness of
being so that and so in the third Janna it's having a sense of a happiness
body and um and to feel that happiness body to feel kind of cozy
delighted contented that we carry with us into the
world and that's medicine for the world if we go into the world angry that's not
medicine if we go into the world distressed that's not medicine there's
enough anger enough distress in the world do we really want to add
more because we're angry maybe and because we're distressed because we care
in that caring make yourself the medicine that
the world needs make yourself the medicine that you need
that's the function of deep samadei that's the function of deeply settling
and going into this deep deep place it's not an escape from the world it's a it's
an ability to be become whole complete with the best that we have available as
a human being and with that comes a
profound aspiration to live for the welfare and happiness of this world
without sacrificing our own well-being it's much easier said than
done but that's the principle of this practice it is possible to learn that
and it's a worthwhile skill to learn and
so I'll read the the description of the third Janna one more
time furthermore with the fading of
joy a practitioner abides at quantamus
aware with clear recognition experiencing happiness with
the body the practitioner enters and abides in
the third Janna which the noble ones declare a economous and aware one abides
in happiness the practitioner pervades saturates and permeates this body with
happiness freed of joy so that no part of the body is not touched
i celebrate this description what a great
phenomenal pointing to a human potential that we have that you
have it is possible we can This is a potential we
all carry within us
so may you be your own
medicine may you be the medicine for the world thank you