so good day to everyone I always love looking in the chat and seeing
um the greetings coming in very much appreciate that some of you know each
other we really have quite a sa here don't we so let's go ahead and get started
with our sitting together closing the eyes if that's okay
for you and settling in to a meditation posture knowing that you're sitting with
a large group of people from around the world many of whom have expressed their
happiness for being here and being together and just feel the nice feeling
from all of that connection of the
Dharma maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths and on the
breath softening into the body arriving in the
body maybe there's kind of an energetic
feeling as you let the body awaken letting the energy flow into the
[Music] cells permeating through the way water
would permeate soil it doesn't always feel like this
but that's the invitation to invite sense of opening to the body's
energy and [Music]
aliveness you may notice as you do so that the body
naturally settles into a position that is upright and also
relaxed that has some dignity and straightness to
it but is soft somewhat
flexible and so too in the mind inviting the mind to be
present alert and also
receptive willing to receive what is happening in the body the heart the
environment around us
we may not always appreciate what an unusual stance that is in the world
actually to be alert receptive calm and yet
engaged and we don't always pull it off of
course but even the intention toward that is quite special in the world
a gift of the human body and mind to do
that perhaps sensing the breath coming in going
out tuning in to that natural life activity breathing
inviting the mind to rest with that
flow and even if there's some busyness or
tiredness or emotions going on we can breathe through that and still
sense the breath and allow that to be there in the
background or bubbling away but we're still breathing
and gently allowing the attention to settle toward
the the heart area down into the chest the upper
torso could be a broad area could be smaller
just sensing Into the Heart Center how is
it it's fine if there's some aching or
tension it may feel open may feel warm you may not feel anything
but I'll be inviting some instructions in meta practice loving kindness Good
Will which you invited to participate in as it feels right for
you also okay to do your regular
meditation so allowing the breath to move through the heart
area some people like to imagine the breath directly coming in and out of the
front of the chest or if that imagination doesn't
quite make sense you can note how the air flowing into the
lungs naturally flows around the
heart so breathing in and out through that area of the body
softening and we'll be doing a form of meta
practice it is a a radiating practice
rather than saying phrases so we begin by
evoking an image or a sense of a being for whom it's very easy to feel meta
feel Goodwill feel friendliness
well-wishing a really good choice is a pet an animal that you have a simple
happy relationship with or it could be an animal you see
outside the window a bird a squirrel or maybe a
baby a being For Whom the relationship is
simple and the Heart naturally uplifts just on seeing or sensing this
being
and you just bring in this image or
feeling and allow it to evoke some sense of friendliness in the
heart doesn't have to be anything
big just tune into that feeling that it brings
and then with the breath just the way the breath brings in
oxygen that circulates throughout the body imagine this feeling of
friendliness warmth Warth being infused through the body by
the
breath it stays centered in the heart
area but there's a feeling that it can spread a bit
and make sure you let it spread to the back side of the body and the
sides not just through the front where most of our attention tends to go
and now imagining a little further that on the in
breath this feeling of friendliness meta grows brighter and stronger as if
it were a light in the
chest like the way when you blow on a spark it gets brighter on the INB
breath and then on the out breath we feel that spreading or
shining of the meta
breathing in it gets brighter stronger Fuller breathing
out it's spreads
outward and as you get the hang of this you're welcome to just drop the image or
sense of the particular being and put all your attention on the feeling of the
meta that's the
object for me there's sometimes a feeling of gathering myself
around this intention or feeling toward
meta sometimes I imagine the way the the dust out in outer space gets kind of
gathered up and when it's dense enough like a star it begins to
shine so we have this star in the middle of the
chest breathing in the parts of ourselves are gathered together toward this feeling of goodness
friendliness and they shine and then on the out breath we just let that
radiate as far as it wants to go there's no sense that
we're pushing the meta out or trying to stretch
it to reach somewhere that's not what a light does a
light just [Music] shines might be a little candle might be
something larger however it is now is
[Music] fine the radiation of this sensor of
good
will maybe it just gets to the surface of your
body maybe it gets a little bit out into the
room it can be quite
modest keeping the attention on that feeling
the radiation of meta is said to be boundless without
boundry and that doesn't necessarily mean that it goes all the way out to
Infinity that's a lot but instead we would see
boundlessness as being that we don't place any bounds on it we don't limit it
in any way and one way that we embody that in
the practice bring it about in the practice so that we
imagine removing any boundaries that might be
there so the imagination is that there's maybe a a
curtain around the heart that's obscuring a little bit this
radiation and now if you would imagine drawing aside a curtain to the
front so suddenly the radiation is spilling
out to the front of your body completely unbounded doesn't matter
how far it goes but it's been freed by having the curtain drawn aside
it spreads
forward and now drawing a curtain aside to the right side of your
body so that the radiation spreads out shoots out farther to the right
drawing the curtain back now to the back
side and the meta radiates out
unbounded to the front the right and the
back see if you can imagine it radiating backwards it's not often that we put our
attention that way but it's
unbounded to the back
and now to the left side also we draw aside this
curtain radiation unbounded out to the front right back and
left boundless meta
we further imagine it spreading
upwards and downwards meta is now blocked by the
floor the Earth can radiate all
around freely as far as it goes
and even if you're not feeling much meta is not so available to
you it's actually still helpful just to have directed the attention in all of
these directions to have some sense of awareness all around the body
even without meta that groundless allaround awareness is
beneficial and if you're feeling meta perhaps there's a sense of warmth or
radiation in addition
so see if you can soften the effort at this point and just
rest in whatever sense you have in the heart
area this is not meant to be a strong
doing more like we're being this allaround awareness or
radiation of
meta in a very soft easy
way and you may notice that if it starts from the heart
area and expands outward it must pass through every cell
of your body before it gets
out you are naturally the first recipient of your
meta and just resting
and now letting go of the feeling of
meta it may linger a bit but just releasing that
intention and just sitting with simple
mindfulness of the body of the mind or you can return to the breath if
that feels natural just letting go and letting
experience flow
for
e
e e
and as we move toward the end of this sitting
i' just like to invite a reflection on the
way this heart quality can have a kind of a penetrating
feeling through our whole
body we don't have to necessarily direct our love and care and good will toward
particular beings or categories of being we can imagine instead that
there's also a way it can just um become part of our cellular
structure so that it's kind of there in the background and that this can inform our
way of being in the world I don't think we need to imagine
an ideal like will will always be a loving kind
warm perfectly socially attuned [Music]
person ideals are not always so
supportive but nonetheless having a a sense of General Goodwill especially
toward oursel can greatly inform
our way of being in the world such that we're a little more
resilient in how we can meet our own difficult states of mind or
challenges in the world and also it informs us to be able
to see what is easeful and good and beautiful if we're caught up in concerns
and habitually in a negative mind State we may not respond to the simple moments of joy
that come a beam of sunlight coming through the
window a cup of tea somebody giving us a compliment in
the grocery store we may Rush past simple moments like
that and if we have this General background or permeation
of good will will'll catch more of those so
there's a great enrichment of our life through tuning in to the positive
abilities in the heart and that's a small bit of what we've done
today so I hope this will carry forward for you today and perhaps in other
[Music] days as a a support in your way of being
in the world that benefits not only you but can spread out
to others also sometimes in unexpected ways may it be so
so it's a week of talking about letting go and
cultivation in the spirit of these New Year intentions that many people are
drawn to make but also just in the spirit of walking the path skillfully in
our life on Monday we named the three wise
intentions that are taught by the Buddha which are renunciation non-ill will and non
cruelty and the second of and third of those are essentially about
non-harming and sometimes they're made into a positive form by calling them a
loving kindness and compassion I think that's okay um but today I so I want to
address those today you know these these cultivations that we that we bring in
but I want to talk not just about kind of abstract cultivation of them like we would do on the cushion but also kind of
an integrated C cultivation you know how would we bring the heart more fully into
all aspects of our life and I want to start with a just an
anecdote um so I was driving along a
country road one day after a morning of hiking and I I came around a corner and
I suddenly saw an oncoming car in the other lane flashing its headlights and
my mind said w oh what's going on why are they doing that and you while I was
I didn't see a obvious reason while I was trying to figure it out the car went by but then I saw it I saw that there
was a deer crossing the road that the other driver must have seen also and I
had plenty of time to stop um but I I reflected that you know the flashing of the lights did help you know it brought
me to attention maybe I wouldn't have had time if if they hadn't given me that signal
and then I felt really happy I thought about how the other driver you know
wasn't they didn't have time to think carefully about what they were doing there was the deer there was my car
coming around the corner there was the concern to prevent harm and so somehow
they just decided to flash their headlights quick give a signal to that other person and probably all of that
happened faster than ordinary thought so I don't know the actual mind
state of that other driver but it did remind me of what I like to call
Integrated care in action so the way in our finer moments um acts like that come
forth naturally we we just do something because that's what you do because
that's how uh we would care for the world around us and for the situation that we're
in and of course we know that sometimes those inte grad care in action doesn't
come forth right we remember painful moments where it didn't come forth so I felt really happy to have
been kind of part of that in that moment in Dharma practice we don't have
to leave that kind of uh integrated care in action up to chance we can cultivate
certain wholesome qualities so that they are more likely to come forth when needed
they become a more integral part of our life and you know many of the good
qualities that we would want to cultivate and integrate are in this realm of non-harming things like meta or
Compassion or patience or care um friendliness Good
Will so many of us do learn meta practice first in the form of saying
phrases of well-wishing for various categories of beings ourself a benefactor a friend a neutral person a
difficult person and that kind of formal practice is very good it can establish
and strengthen this intention of Good Will and it can also stretch it into new
territory as we start including beings that we might not want to include at
first and there's also this radiation that we did which is also a very good way I find that to be a very effective
effective way of cultivating meta but I would say that there's yet another level to practicing meta or
Compassion or any other kind of non-harming if we want it to more fully
integrate into our action and speech and thought then we can kind of we have to take it on maybe as a training not just
a technique that we're doing So Meta is one of a set of character traits that
are called parami that apply to a person who is walking the path to Freedom
someone who is walking the eight-fold path and they're they're meant to become you know character traits actually part
of how we are in the world in a sense and luckily long before we've completely
mastered this um you know like maybe the Buddha had long before that our mind can
call them forth reliably in our actions in in many cases and they get expressed
through how we are in the world we have kind of a general tendency toward being
kind or considerate or helpful so at the appropriate moment we might say
something helpful or not say something right or maybe flash our headlights to
alert alert another driver of a of a deer so I want to read um a quote from
aan suito in a book that he wrote about the about the parami these character
traits he says when we make the resolution of kindness not just toward
kittens on a nice day but even toward cockroaches on a bad day when we include
dictators and brutal Maniacs as well as all aspects of ourselves then we're making meta into a
Perfection a vast and transfiguring way of life so it's not just kittens on a nice
day but even people whose actions are clearly harmful and even harder than that might
be to include all aspects of ourselves we all have aspects of ourselves that
make us cringe um and they come forth sometimes and that's you know then we
feel bad about that but we're meant to really include all of that all of it if we want to make meta nonharming into an
actual way of life um then we we try to be more and more inclusive even of those
parts that are that are still suffering within us and the promise of doing that is
quite amazing it's a potential to transform how we live in the world we don't need to start though we
don't need to start with the grandio ideas we tend to start more right here and right now with the ordinary aspects
of our life so if you're interested in in this idea of cultivating meta as
something that's a a character trait or that pervades our way of being even amid
the ups and downs we can actually start pretty much with what we've got so for
example um there's my neighbor my neighbor feeds the squirrels
he's a very nice fellow but he likes to feed the squirrels and it's kind of sweet in a way but we have this shared
entryway and sometimes when I come out the door there's a s hovering there um
and I feel they're quite bold and I feel like they're just close enough that if they wanted to they could bite me so I
have a little bit of nervousness around that sometimes and um also there's uh
you know there's a tendency since they're all there is that there's some urine stains accumulating on the
concrete also right so there's this um you know kind of mundane aspect of life
but I've learned to f focus on my neighbor's generosity and appreciate the the very real Delight that he takes in
in giving the squirrels treats so um this practical cultivation of meta
uh helps it become more integrated in us and it comes um it comes through in
various actions of speech and body and mind that we do and if you want to uh consider you
know how do I actually tune into that in a practical sense I would recommend
using the energetic Sensations in the body so the way our emotions and thoughts manifest in bodily Sensations I
know not everyone can feel the body so easily but it's well worth tuning into
that uh and developing that a bit if you can so when we develop meta on the
cushion for example instead of just focusing on the phrases we can feel it directly as sensation that's what I was
inviting in the meditation this morning uh sometimes we'll feel warmth or
softness or uprightness a certain kind of dignified strength that comes in and
then as we do that on the cushion that begins to translate into daily life because we also have access to
sensations of the body maybe you know less finely when we're out in everyday world but nonetheless it's like the echo
of it from the cushion is there so we can have sensations of energy or warmth or
contraction we're tightening up and we can as we learn to manage those and feel
those in the body then we'll have a sense of when the mind can be oriented
toward meta and when it's starting to orient toward ill will or some form of U
harming essentially so the thought for example of my neighbor and his squirrel
feeding habit it might bring in a tightening of the throat or a sense of
judgment you shouldn't be doing that something like that but I can also
notice if I notice the discomfort of those somewhat ill will related thoughts
there's something in the heart that wants to release that and not get caught up in that and so then the Mind tries to
find a way to soften focus on something different expand awareness into the
bigger picture so that I can be a little more relaxed about this one little instance of something that's happening
so sensing tension and the release of tension is a great tool for learning to
relate well to both our internal mind States and to other people in the world
I think this was what aan sucho is referring to when he calls meta a way of life um meeting our own anger our own
sadness or agitation with Clarity with kindness neither resisting and judging
them uh nor believing them and collapsing into them but being able to
be with them we talked little earlier also about capacity having the capacity
to be with all the different aspects of our self one could say that's part of
what meta is part of what friendliness and goodwi is and maybe it will
translate also into meeting other people even those whose values differ from ours
um we can have some degree of flexibility or Grace in meeting them
seeing them in a bigger picture being able to treat them as the human being that they are even if we don't agree
with some of what they what they believe so if we do this if we take this
on as a training there's a part of the heart sometimes that objects a little bit and says well if I really commit to
kind Ness and Good Will and compassion as a character trait probably I'll
become a doormat and I'll I'll just start agreeing with everything I won't have empathy I won't have enough empathy
for the injustices of the world I'll just think it's all okay I haven't found
that to be true on my own as far as I've been able to go so far on this
cultivation it seems that we do still have the ability to differentiate what is helpful and what is harmful to
clearly name dictators and brutal Maniacs for instance to choose a phrase
for majan such chito's quote in fact I would say that ability even gets
sharper um but nonetheless we're at the same time broadening and softening our
mind to be able to Encompass the fullness of experience and how the world
really is out there aano goes further in this book um
about the part me to say that when nonharming becomes mature in a person's
heart he writes the result is a mind that is grounded in wisdom and
compassion and which easily opens to the Peace of nibana so that's Freedom
Awakening so may that be so I think that I think that is the potential is that if
we really allow uh meta Goodwill sense of friend less and care you know the
intention of non-harming to permeate our being we become more able to stand in
the world be clear about what's skillful and unskillful and yet to have the
bigger picture that the suffering doesn't penetrate our heart and so we're able to act and respond even better so
may that be the case and I encourage this um somehow with within this set of
you know New Year orientations of the mind that we tend to bring at this time of year I hope it will include the
cultivation of these traits of non-harming as is uh implied by the
second and third of the wise intentions non-il will and non cruelty or goodwi
and compassion so may it be so for all of us
for this world that needs it so much thank you