hello and welcome to this Friday meditation session and
um to say a few words preparing us for the
meditation um the the phrase for today is that
samadi is sweetness that samadi has a kind of
sweet quality to it and maybe in case the word sweetness doesn't have such
positive associations with you as it does for me the uh there are other words that uh
speak to the goodness that comes with somebody it can be um there can be a
feeling of beauty and um feelings of beauty that come with it
more classically people talk about there being Joy
gladness um happiness sometimes Bliss a more simple and maybe a little
more humble way of saying the same words is there can be pleasure that somebody is uh involves
pleasure that something starts becoming very pleasant as the state of Som begins
to develop and at first it might be something very specific
like um uh there might be a a feeling of pleasure and that seems to radiate or
come with the experience of breathing sometimes the experience of breathing can feel like it's just
beautiful there's a beauty to it it could be that there's a tingling
and warmth and joy may be kind of similar to what happened if you uh had a
half smile and a little bit of you know turned up the corners of your
mouth there might be a little bit of H kind of delight that physical Delight that appears maybe in the eyes or
the the cheeks or someplace so this idea of I'm calling
its sweetness today and that sweetness can start to be pervasive and the
sweetness becomes a um feedback loop where we feel the sweetness of somadi
and and allowing yourself to feel that and we're allowed to feel it we're allowed to feel the pleasure the joy
that comes with somebody and we're allowed to feel it and uh and it becomes kind of a biof
feedback uh uh that goes on where we feel it and it going to be there to to
help us to stay focused keep doing what we're doing so we can keep growing and
developing uh the um and then the second thing to say we
start now in the Chinese when they when Buddhism arrived in China and they had
to translate indic Buddhist text into Chinese uh the way that they
translated uh uh samata vipasana samadi
vipasana is concentration the word they use the word stop and for vipasana
insight they use the word c so together the practice of samata vasana is to stop
and see so there's something about about samadi that does involve a kind of a
stopping and a stopping which is a relief a stopping which is Pleasant this
feels good oh I'm here I don't have to do anything anymore
I don't have to keep accomplishing or proving myself or I don't have to I don't have to finish my to-do list I
don't have to you know for these minutes of meditation of samadi it's a it's a
radically alternative way of being alive Fully Alive
here without needing to accomplish anything just to be here let everything
all the accomplishing doing activities stop so with
that to assume a meditation
posture that is in in a way the beginning of
stopping a clear sense that now we're not going to be doing the activities of
daily life it's a time for a sacred
pause for something that's more important invaluable and it's a maybe you can feel
the relief of stopping to just
be in this
posture and for these minutes in meditation the only person who is going
to be talking is me so there for all of
you you can you can stop the ordinary maybe activity of
talking and so something gets quiet maybe it feels like a
relief or maybe not
and there can be appreciating stopping of needing to think about things and solve
things and to feel the relief that now nothing needs to be
accomplished including accomplishing
meditation and to feel the relief the goodness of just being alive As You Are
and is there somewhere inside some sweetness some
goodness some maybe very subtle
pleasure somewhere for just simply being alive
and awake and
present and and
gently breathing in in a deeper way to feel your body more
fully and as you exhale to
relax relaxing the body
and relaxing is more a stopping of something than a
doing of something it's the stopping of being
tense of holding the muscles
tight and as you relax the
body if there's any kind of anything that approaches pleasure in that
relaxing in the midst of the relaxing feel that pleasure or feel that
goodness letting your breathing return to normal
and as you breathe in feel some place in your body that's
tight the muscles are tense little and gently on the
exhale soften relax if it doesn't relax soften around
it make space for it
and if there's any subtle pleasure in that or relief in that
just feel that
and if there is now any feeling of sweetness or goodness relief or
pleasure just sitting here without needing to accomplish
anything just being here
allow your breathing to be in the middle of that
sweetness breathing with it through it
and in a way that you stay with a natural enough enough
breathing if there's any small tiny ways you can adjust your
breathing so that it's more pleasant there's more pleasure in any part of the
breathing or if there's already some pleasure in
breathing feel
it some people will feel certain pleasure goodness or
relief during the
exhale some people in the inhale
some people in the pause if there is a pause
at the end of the exhale
as you breathe breathe with whatever pleasure
sweetness there might be here maybe one that's very
closely related to doing almost
nothing the relief the pleasure of just being
just being with something so simple and fundamental as breathing
for some people the pleasure might come from the gentle rhythm of breathing in
and breathing out maybe like being
comforted gently rocking in a rocking chair
and sometimes the sweetness related to breathing
is just beyond the edges of the sensations of breathing so in the
body maybe almost like radiating from
breathing the influence that breathing has in the areas close in
around what is moving as you breathe
the area of space
spaciousness maybe the spaciousness that's
here as a kind of pleasure or relief has space for joy
and if you need to let go of your thinking and relax your thinking
mind let go so that awareness drops into the
sweetness in your body connected to
the
meditation Relax The Thinking mind to feel the
pleasure of
relaxing letting the thinking mind be quiet so that you can better
feel the sweetness of being present here and
now breathing one breath at a
time
for
e
e e
and if there's anything that resembles sweetness
pleasure contentment as you're sitting Med as you're
meditating let that be an
encouragement for the mind to be
quieter and the body to be more open
to the experience of breathing and the experience of
sweetness however
subtle
e
for
e for
there's an art to feeling the sweetness the
goodness that's here and within
it allowing whatever is not sweet not pleasant
to float to be there in the background to
not zero in or fixate on what is
difficult but allow it to float in a wider
ocean of the sweetness of meditation
that's gently massaged or by the breathing
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to you begin to feel
whatever sweetness goodness calm
relief pleasure contentment
wellbeing however small to sense and feel into how it is
right now for you and your body your heart your
mind maybe having some sense that it can radiate out into the spaciousness the
space around you even if it's just an inch beyond
your
body that somehow imagine that your goodness your
sweetness is something that you can transmit to
others not what you say not what you do but how you
are to share the sweet feelings you have letting it radiate out into the
world and imagine that's your gift today to the world
whatever goodness whatever pleasure
well-being that comes from meditation comes from being Mindful and
present may that be a gift that somehow is
transmitted [Music] somehow
radiated out into the world for the people that you'll
encounter may it be that how you are
today is for the welfare and happiness of others and for your
own may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peace peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you
e
so welcome to this 15th talk on samadi this ongoing
samadi series and uh one of the things that
this week perhaps you would have noticed is how seldom I use the word
concentration and uh and in the kind of phrase that I use for each day this
week the quality that's being emphasized is not concentration so samadi
is uh Simplicity somebody is
subtleness somebody is steadiness sadii is
spaciousness and today samadi is sweet
and um and so maybe the closest thing to concentration in those five is
steadiness but you you know to be steady with your presence Be steady in your uh
in your awareness To Be steady here with the practice and these uh five
qualities uh don't have to be separate they can be part of the same state that
we're in we can be sitting in a state of Simplicity where meditation is not
something complicated it's not an engineering feat it's not a complicated thing to do it's uh almost like an
undoing a not doing more than it is a doing and that it is
um settling a settling into something and not a concentrating
on something and it might be that the consequence of settling is that we
settle so fully in a relaxed full way that the world around the place we
settle um kind of Falls away or recedes into the diff distance and it's almost
as if we're concentrating on the subtle place but rather than poking it with
from the control tower it's more like we've settled into it like we would settle in into um you know a nice soft
mattress or on top of a mattress but it's a nice comforter that we lay down
in it just feels so good to settle into that and we're fully completely here in
that small little world where the body touches the comforter in the bed and the
rest of the world Falls away you could say we're concentrated there but um but
the to con concentrate on that experience for some people immediately gets us tense to strain or gets us in
the control tower but to settle into it becomes something that becomes embodied
something that's includes all the whole body it's the fullness of it this steadiness holding
steady um there's something in us that I think loves being steady it's kind of
like a commitment or a devotion or a or Simplicity of being just
this because when we're steady something can relax into it settle into it um I
love to go hiking and there's H sometimes as we go hiking used to be this when I went run used to run if I
just keep walking steadily at some point um kind of something settles in me I I
arrive and I'm just there in the walking steady in the walking but I have to walk steadily for the Gathering of my all the
different parts of myself where the the distracted mind concerns of the day fall away and I'm just steady it's kind of
like the steadiness allows something to gather around
it spaciousness is such an important quality for somebody because to have a
sense of being spacious open lots of openness makes room for the sweetness
that can arise in somebody and maybe some of you don't care for the
word sweetness but in somadi they uh there is a pleasure there
is um uh there is a sense of
well-being there is uh for me one of the most wonderful words for the state of
Som is beauty there's a feeling of a beautiful state that kind of radiates
out or the breathing has gotten quite beautiful and it kind of radiates a sense of beauty into the
body um the most classic uh way of talking about it is uh there's joy and
happiness some people add the word gladness so it's kind of like each of those is a deeper and Fuller
experience uh that's more and more satisfying and some people use the word
satisfy and there's a feeling of satisfaction at this it's really good here and um and some people may be like
the word goodness this feels good sometimes I've like the word
health because the settling into a good state of Sade feels like an embodiment
of Health even at times when I've been sick uh if I could settle into samadi
Sadi state it just feels like I'm there's this healing energy that courses
through the body just feel so good the healthiness the health of it so
um um so I'm not saying that this is easy
and I'm not saying that it should happen today or tomorrow but this is one of the characteristics of
samadi and so as we and so as we settle into it the practice it's good to start
becoming uh sensitive aware when some of these good feelings to be terrorise
these are these are good feelings which are symptoms of
samadi and um and one of the reason one of the interesting things in the teachings of the Buddha is that uh he
puts uh uh happiness as a precursor for
somebody and uh you know it's a little bit odd to say that because many people
are suffering a lot and they're meditating in order to not suffer so
much or to be free of their suffering to work through it and now to have somebody you have to be be happy to begin with um
but um we always have the mindfulness practice to fall back to and you know
for five years now on YouTube the primary practice I've been teaching is mindfulness so for those of you been
following you can always uh the recourse is to go back to just being mindful of the experience until something settles
and you feel like you're able to be present with what's happening in a simpler way and then you can develop uh
this quality of samadi this primary focus and a lot of sbody has to do with
having a primary focus of attention a primary place to
settle a primary place to um be uh at
home and to be to relax and to to um to um and and is
this kind of being being absorb the idea is moving into kind of to be absorbed in the
experience and maybe you could have as a reference point uh something you do in your life that you get absorbed enough
into that you feel a kind of well-being in doing it all the the difficult
thoughts and difficult feelings that in life have fallen away as we do this simple thing that we get absorbed in
doing for some people it's reading a book some people it's doing a craft or
playing an instrument some people it's feels really just going into a
shower um lets everything else fall away and just nice to be in the shower and
some people start singing in the shower uh it might be being with a
friend that uh does that and may walk in the park or um listening to music for
some people can do it so there's might be something that you already do that gives you a sense of what it's like to
have these uh qualities of this week of um Simplicity becoming simple just to
listen to the music just to do this one thing uh where there's a a subtleness in
it where're we're not preoccupied and agitated by other things just here with this where there's a steadiness and
absorption like this here and that uh there is a spaciousness
around it because we're not limited ourselves in kind a tight way but we're relaxing into think something something
opens as we get and sometimes with somebody things will get smaller and
more more narrow first before the spaciousness opens up so don't look for
spaciousness too early just when it starts becoming available and then um partly I'm
choosing the word sweetness because it has an s in it to be complete for the week I think that um if I wasn't for
the wanting to stay with 's uh I probably would have chosen Beauty for
myself so um
um so uh these are some of the characteristics
of somadi and not necessarily easy to tap into or
touch into but they can be very subtle and if we have it already a disposition
in the mind to orient ourselves to what's difficult Orient ourselves around our problems Orient ourselves
around the the pain we have or something sometimes inadvertedly
that's actually where the samama is going that's where the concentration is going to those things and if we go
concentrate on things this way where there's a fear or aversion or um
something that is not so healthy um that focus on the problems actually can make
the difficulty feel worse not to ignore it but it's possible to with some to sh
shift the primary focus to breathing to the settling place to settle to keep
settling and until uh and knowing that you're not betraying the difficulties
you have but you're placing them in a different context and uh and it's a really a
delight to be able to sit in a state of some state of goodness state of health
where the difficulties we have might be just they're just like um um jellyfish
floating in the vast ocean they aren't the ocean and um and uh so they're there
and they're recognized but they're being held by the goodness of
somebody so uh so finally I'd like to say that um for next week I won't be
here and I think Kim Allen will come and uh and uh I think it's Kim will come and
um and teach for you we have these wonderful teachers at IMC that can be my
substitutes and um and uh the
um I should probably be sure about this so that uh just out of respect for my
co-teachers that I have it right here we go
um oh no no I'm sorry uh next week it's Liz Liz Powell and a wonderful teacher
it lives in Colorado now and delighted that she's going to be here with you all so
um so in the meantime um if uh the beginning of the week I
encourage you to count your breathing because that supports that can support the
steadiness and it can support all these qualities provided you find a really
nice way for the mind to do the counting gentle soft beautiful settled spacious
see if you can find a way to count and um and there are different ways of counting as I describ
um but if you find yourself being able to settle into the counting you might
see if counting from 1 to 10 and then Starting Over Again begins to uh support
this settling in the steadiness um that really brings you
getting starting getting absorbed in this experience of um breathing of
sama and I'll be back the following week and um I look forward to this quite a
bit to continue this and um now those of you who would
like uh we're going to uh have a zoom meeting for the for our community and
um and what that means is that uh I'll put a zoom link into
the into the I'm G to try to put a zoom Link in
let's see if I can um and
uh see it's a little
bit here we go
um I'm having a little bit trouble figuring out how to man oh to put it put
it in the chat I don't know why that's a challenge today um somehow my YouTube channel is
not showing it if someone could go and get the the uh the link the zoom link
from uh the calendar what's new and put it in the chat I would appreciate it a lot and it'll take me a minute or two to
be able to make it to uh the zoom room myself and if you need it you need a
pass to get into it and the password is um me is meta poly word for loving
kindness so M TTA me TTA and um so um and I'll be there
shortly thank you
and those of you who'd like to stay in the zoom don't want to go to those uh stay in the YouTube can stay here I
won't turn it off and uh then you can um um just you can listen and be part of
it and if we do a break group I can kind of be looking at your chat a little bit
and so I don't see anyone putting the YouTube uh Link in the chat oh there it
is thank you Cindy so now it's there and uh I'll be there shortly thank
you for
sh
[Music]
okay
okay so let me see can um there's a lot of people who
I so it's the best so can you hear
me yes wonderful oh so
I'm oh I know what I have to do I the technology of all
this okay no that's not what I want to do and I want to go this okay
okay so so you can hear me
again so I left the YouTube on and so on my computer so the YouTube channel
was volume was on so I was hearing myself and uh so now we're just regular
zoom and the people on who are stayed on YouTube should be able to hear and and
watch me at least so it's best I think given uh so many
people that we you keep your uh yourself muted unless you're going to speak and
um so I think what we'll do today is uh I'll take some questions hear from all
the some of you and uh we'll do a breakout group and at some point there
maybe be before we do the breakout group I have some announcements to be make to make and uh that's relevant for us and
then um then we'll do the breakout group and and maybe time for more
questions and the the function of the breakout groups is just uh for a chance
maybe somewhat random but the chance for some of you to meet each other and uh have some personal conversations uh some
of you have been chatting um daily sometimes with uh on YouTube and it's
been lovely to see the warmth and the friendship and the care that goes into some of those chats as you communicate
with each other so um happy to have you here all
of you and uh is anyone who'd like to ask a question or make a comment and
ideally they'd be somewhat brief and um so we can have more chance for more
people to speak and uh the easiest way to do this I think is if you if you could raise
your Zoom hand because there's more tiles I won't be able to see everyone's um physical hand going up but if you
could do your uh you know the uh raise your hand and if you don't
know how to do that um some some some Zoom uh uh accounts have a on the on the
menu at the bottom of it there says raise hand sometimes you have to go to the reaction bar and find it I think so
uh oh Captain how nice delighted to see you
so let's see uh I can't oh no I have to try saying it again um can you hear me
yes yes I well thank you to Kil to you and to
everybody else um I live in the middle of the woods so this is a very uh special Community uh for me to feel
connected um I will try to keep it brief uh when I first got got back into
meditating um like a year and a half or so ago um I often felt more relaxed and
calm by the end um which was a lovely feeling um and now I noticed that a lot
of the time first of all it's much harder for me to settle um but also by
the end of it I often find that I'm experiencing more of uh the hindrance of
restlessness and wor rather than less like it sort of amps up over the session
and I feel like there must be something that I'm doing to sort of engage it
during the sit but I haven't been able to figure out what so I was wondering
just if you had any thoughts or any suggestions or anything like that yes
thank you Captain the the the the general way that I view these things is
that uh many people when they start meditating uh there's often beginner's
luck there's a kind of excitement there's more Focus because it's new and exciting and
um and uh and so uh people will um
uh let me hang on here um people will will get uh um you know
so people can get pulled in a little bit quickly the other thing that can happen is that uh we're practicing well enough
that we're dropping into a deeper layer level of the Mind in our psychology and
now it's time that something has to be addressed uh the analogy I use is uh if
you go into you know you go you move into a house that people who lived there before you never cleaned for
decades and uh and so the first thing you do is you can manage to in order to get in there you have to clean the the
entry hallway and you have you get it really clean it's nice it's easy to walk through and say oh this is good and then
you open the door to the living room and oh my this is like oh this is I'm G to
this is terrible how could it be so much to to be done um but actually you're making progress you've taken care of one
thing now you have to take care of the next room and many of us have a number of rooms that have been unattended and a
little bit messy that as we settle we're coming to that next next so that maybe
makes it a little bit easier to have a more positive view of the challenge you have sooner or later everyone who
meditates will be up against some challenge where they think they're going backwards and um and it's not you never
be I like to think we never go backwards and then the question is how do you how do you address this and meet
this and one way is to uh not be so concerned about the issue you had the
way you described it but rather uh what is your relationship to the issue and that might be the key thing to
focus on uh that you know there's all kinds of secondary um uh arrows we add to it that
that's more important to look at than the actual issue itself and um and in and if the second
Arrow stop then it might be fine to sit there with the challenge you know not so
troubled by it it um and then maybe you can see it more clearly the other thing
is you call it a hindrance and we have these five hindrances that uh we do and
so you might want to go through carefully the five hindrance and see which one of them seems to be operating
or which ones some people have multiple hindrance attacks so you might have to kind of see
the number of ones but the first thing that occurred to me as you described what you there might be some degree of
Doubt playing itself out and so doubt is one of the hindrances and um and so if you want to
learn more about the hindrances you know in my teachings I have this book called unhindered that goes through them and I
did do I think I did Doh five days a week on the hindrances in December and
maybe it was a preparation for this uh this uh series on
somebody so is that okay for now Captain give you something yes yes thank you so much and actually I just got your book
uh for the holidays excited to read it thank you very much thank you and then
feather hi can you hear me yes great thank you and it's so wonderful to see
all these faces around the world so um Gil I love how at the end of every
meditation you invite us um to send Goodwill to all people and all beings
and that no one is excluded and that really really helps me settle and I find
that in my loving kindness meta it's quite easy for me to do that when I'm
sitting to send care to everyone yet at the same time I'm finding it really
difficult these days to witness suffering um in humans and in animals
when when what I perceive is Injustice and what's everything that's happening in
the world and I'm super sensitive and I get activated so easily by hurt and so
I'm finding myself asking friends to not talk to me about politics and to stay
away from news and TV and social media and basically just be with my horse and
be in this community and just shut it all out so I'm wondering if you can
maybe say a word or two about how to practice with that yeah with that sensitivity to the world thank you yeah
thank you so um I think the first thing to do is
to be very caring and respectful for how you are with all this without starting
there it's there not going to be much and so you know the uh so what is it in
since you started with the way I do the dedication at the end of the sitting to say that
um um uh what is it that you given this challenge you're
describing uh what in you needs loving kindness and
compassion and um you know maybe it's premature to do it for all beings
something in you needs to be attended to First and the chances are there's
something unresolved in you that needs to be recog recognized met loved cared
for understood because what you're describing I I don't know you except for this description you gave but I've seen
very very many times that when people have this level of
difficulty this level of difficulty let me see um if someone if if people don't
have their uh their microphone on mute I put it on speaker speaker phone on
speaker view when uh when someone's asking a question and then I lose them if someone has a the
microphone on yeah so no okay so
um uh so this when UNR so someone has something unre unresolved deep inside
then the suffering of the world uh touches that unresolved
place and uh and it kind it's kind of like putting a magnifying glass on
something a magnifying glass on the suffering of the world or a magnifying glass on our own heart the unresolved
emotional issues that are there and so they need to be cared for loved attended to in a wise caring way and sometimes uh
just sitting in meditation and being really present for these unresolved places of suffering uh is a way forward
to kind of work with it but sometimes that's a slow process and maybe not
what's needed is to get some kind of uh ongoing support from some a loving
caring person who can really attend and support you and accompany you into this
territory and generally in the modern world it would mean uh some some form of
therapy whether it's um you know a regular therapist I put a lot of value
on somatic therapy because us generally somatic therapy is a way that that use
the body to be present for the diff these unresolved things that um is very akin to what we do in in mindfulness
practice um and sometimes it's not necessarily a therapist it might be a pastoral counselor that uh maybe feels a
little bit more if you have a spiritual orientation kind of makes a different context for the work so those are my
thoughts does that uh you want to ask anything more or say more so that I can
I can understand better it's it's touching a deep place so I
appreciate that I mean I I I and I wonder if many people do do therapy I
just actually stopped because this format here is just touching me in such
a deeper way uh great so maybe lot maybe maybe stick stick to this process now
and um maybe um uh you know give it a chance for a while and see how it
develops and uh and what I told Captain might be relevant for you too that uh
maybe there's something deep really deeper in you that you're going to be get in touch with that might be
difficult for you as you move into this new room that you haven't attended to and so the first thing you might to look
at in this practice mindfulness practice is not the difficulty there but rather
how you're relating to it do you recoil from it do you blame someone do you get
afraid and closed down you know my my one of my uh kind of if I'm if I'm
feeling one a interesting question is uh when you're tired hungry overwhelmed and
you have no wisdom how do you react to your challenges and uh so for me uh uh I
think my go-to kind of strategy and those kind of circumstance is the ostrich
approach I try I just like want to put my my head in the sand and just kind of pretend nothing is there for a while so
so what's yours you know how do you relate to it then so so this is super helpful and I'll just one last thing
I'll say is I one thing that's comforting is I don't maybe the way I react is different but I don't feel
alone in the world with the political situation all this that's going on around us that I'm struggling so that
feels good to feel belonging and not alone so thank you and at some point uh
uh what we can develop and grow it in this practice here is um not a polanish
view of difficulties and Injustice we want to be able to address them and see them and feel them but we feel more
comfortable with feeling the discomfort of it all we're more at ease we find a certain freedom in being present to feel
it it doesn't have to uh it doesn't have to cause us distress it just has it just allows it
just breaks our hearts and motivates us but it doesn't have to be a problem
for us personally and but it's also not denying it it's not you know it's not
you know ignoring it and and but it's a way of being we're developing our capacity to be fully present for the
challenges in the world so we can make a difference uh without being
overwhelmed okay thank you so well there's two more people with their hands up we'll take those uh hear from those
two people and then we'll uh do a breakout group those who' like to do that so um
Wendy hi Gils thank you um I want to um
incorporate more forgiveness in my practice I heard um the Dharma talks on
forgiveness and I've done the Forgiveness meditations but what I'm looking for
is Maybe more um or just other ways to forgive
others and myself and even those you
know who don't know that they've done something when you know and I'm holding
a grudge uhuh what what to do maybe more um you know
um I guess what I'm looking for is more of a action related meditation you know
like when I'm you know work you know when I'm watching my thoughts what to do great
well you well this is a a it's a very welcome question you're asking I I I put
a tremendous amount of appreciation value for this desire to address the
challenges of our life with forgiveness so I want to appreciate that first and
I'd like to uh uh you know ra rather than answering your question directly
which maybe would be the thing to do I'd like to offer you the more classic
Buddhist response to the same situation because generally in Buddhism in ear
Indian Buddhism the kind of Buddhism that I based my teachings on uh there's not really an emphasis on forgiveness
the way that it's understood in the in in the West in the western
culture where forgiveness is deeply embedded comes out of
uh theistic religions and relationships to God and religion and the need for
forgiveness that uh Indian religion doesn't have the same world
view so when the the challenges you're describing what what Buddhism offers
might look like forgiveness might have the same effect but it doesn't involve
forgiveness what it involves is um letting go of one's own
anger resentment that's one and the other is
to cultivate loving kindness Good Will and those two things have do almost
the same thing as forgiveness except we're not actually um uh
forgiving condoning uh uh what someone has
done uh we let that be their karma and we're just telling them we're no longer
going to hold it against you with my anger resentment I'm going to meet you with Good Will and but you're
responsible for your actions and the consequences and I I'm just I'll hold you and support you or just be with you
in a kind way but uh I I'm not here to say that what you did can be now that
you're exonerated from from The Challenge you did but I'm just simply
not going to hold it against you and I'll meet you with Good Will so that that's for some people that makes the
whole idea of forgiveness a lot easier uh to to switch the orientation
so I don't know if this satisfy you since I'm not answering your question Wendy but um can that give you something
to think about that was perfect thank you great thank
you so then Charlie hi Gail thank you so much for
your um your online meditations they um help my life very much and um I hope to
meet you someday I live in Colorado and I've been um trying to get to one of those Retreats they're kind of hard to
get to um my my question would be about somat
really appreciate the recent samati teachings and
um there's there's two things that I've learn to fold into my meditation over
the years that helped me to settle and expand my awareness and they're both not
the breathing um and so I just wonder about your comment on them
um one is that I I use sound what I
he um it feel it feels like it's less in inside me and I'm more connected with
the world when I use sound as the object of meditation instead of the breathing and I'm i' I've I've been using the
breathing for a really long time and so that's there too just automatically um habitually it's part of
the meditation but I tend to um use sound as my as my focus and and that
sometimes can be distracting um I sit in my living room in front of a big picture window I looks out to the
street um and um but I find that that it helps me to
feel more present by being connected with the here and now when I'm um with
the sound and the other thing is meta over the uh o over the years I've realized that just being with the
breathing sometimes um I I just um
it's there's a boredom or like a lack of purpose or something um the me when when
I start meditation with meta or include an aspect of that just not necessarily
one of the contemplations but something really light just like connection the purpose My bodhak Vow and
and bring that into my meditation and use that to settle my mind um those two
things I are or what I tend to do great and and so
um I know it's kind sometimes it feels like there's I have all these options and I and I have and it's a little much
and I know the breath is so simple and sometimes I come back to just that okay
but um that's how I tend to settle and work with somebody and those two things seem to work better for me so I just
wonder about your your your guidance on on working with those things great thank you so first fir f first I'd like to say
that um uh yes there are people for whom uh there are better uh objects or
focuses of meditation than breathing and especially if you've done one for a long
time uh you're welcome to continue with that and as we go go further with the
zadi practice I'll keep referring to breathing but you could welcome to translate it into these other practices
you're doing I think that you can probably without much effort translated in you know every time I say breath say
sound for example or meta and um and one
way to one way to uh uh one one one approaches is to uh do these means that
you have for de developing your concentration being settled and when you're feeling really settled then
switch don't start with the with breath but uh pick it up once you're really
settled and then you might find that it actually supports you to go further into the samade than what you're already
doing in the n in about 20 years ago or so there was a trend where Insight
Meditation teachers spend a lot would always begin when they they guided meditations on Retreats and stuff always
begin with doing listening meditation like you're doing and some people find it very helpful because you can't
interfere with the sound You Can't Make a Better Sound you can't react to it uh you can't you don't you don't get
entangled with it in the way some people do with their breathing so it's a way of being
spacious and allowing just and uh and very open so it can be very nice there
was a time when we emphasize that a lot and meta is a classic one in our tradition for developing concentration
and and uh some people will start every meditation with 5 10 minutes of meta to
in order to get somewhat settled and concentrated and to create a good atmosphere in the mind good attitude for
doing the practice so um um but I I still have an Orient
myself into an orientation to something like breathing because some point or other uh uh the orientation to listen to
sounds um uh it the sounds begin receding away and you want to be able to
keep staying focused on something that's more basic and breathing in the body tends to remain as we go into samade
sounds can usually disappear entirely at some point in deeper samade and meta
becomes you know depends how you're doing meta but certainly if you're using meta phrases um they become at some
point become a little bit too coarse and the phrases have to go away as well and
then you're dropping into the body to feel the radiance of the meta rather than the mental side of it so there is a
there is a way of working with all of this so I hope my words kind of re uh address your
questions well enough yes great thank you so much
great thank you so so I'd like to make an announcement just because I think some of you won't stay for the breakout
groups and that is that um some of you might remember about two three years ago
at the at the beginning of the Ukraine War uh we we did a fundraising drive for
uh save the children uh one of the preeminent nonprofits doing humanitarian
work that um in order to support their effort to work with the the children
affected by the Ukrainian War at the beginning of that war and uh it was the main thing we had
at IMC back then because it was during the pandemic was um the you you the
YouTube YouTube Community and it was very successful very inspiring we raised some like
$70,000 to give to uh to the save the children and now we would like to
um uh at the time I thought we should do this once a year for something but now we're i' like to be able to do it again
for save the children and they have an emergency uh Children's Fund that goes
to places in the world with highest level of emergency for life and death issues um that uh I thought would be
really good to support and right now the two highest highest level places they're concerned about is now that um uh is
Gaza and uh and also uh Sudan and so we would I would like us to
I'd like to put open up another one IMC fundraising drive we what we do is we
spend a week where we try to encourage that and and so we're going to do that I think in the middle of October of
February in a couple of weeks and I'll say more but I wanted to just use this
community meeting as a chance to uh to um kind of talk a little bit about the
history of this how we've done this before the good effect it have had and and really speak well about save the
children there they're a non-political group they've been involved in the some of the greatest crisises in the world
for the last some like 70 years or more and um they know what they're doing and
and um and uh it's a I think it's a wonderful group to U support and we've been in
touch with them directly about this uh uh drive this idea so we you know we
talking to them on we've had phone calls with them about it about how we can participate and how to make sure that it
works well for our community that we feel good about so so little bit more information about that but I wanted to
let you all know so what we're going to do is take um I I'll make groups of uh five
and we'll take about uh maybe 12 minutes for those groups of five and um then we
come back here for a little bit more more and um and what I'd like to ask you
in as you go into your group is um uh maybe just talk a little bit about uh
what it's been like for you to participate in this
YouTube uh uh community and practice uh the time you have and maybe with a
little emphasis on what it's been like with now with this samade series but what I'd like to ask is you don't say
much make make one point um so that other people can speak
and uh and the idea is there ideally um you're able to go around your group of
five kind of um multiple times so it becomes more of
a listening exercise than a speaking exercise many people have a strong need to speak and want to say everything they
could possibly say uh which there's that has a lot of value too an occasion but
for this format I think what has the most value is to really have a chance to listen and hear and sense Everyone by
saying something relatively brief and then going around and one advantage of
these kinds of brief statements where it goes around and round is there's a mar can be a marvelous way where as we hear
other people statements it affects us and after a while we find ourselves we're Changed by it and new things come
out of us when we speak then we could never have imagined speaking if we just kind
of explained everything about ourselves that we already know so hopefully that uh works and if
you don't want to be in a breakout group um I would ask you to uh leave YouTube and if you want to come back in 12
minutes or 10 minutes or 5 minutes you're welcome to come back uh to the
zoom room but to to leave the zoom now because the reason for that is that otherwise you get assigned to a room and
then the rooms get kind of skewed with how many people are there so um
okay so I'm going to make
um no that's not right that should
be okay so it'll probably be
okay so see how this goes
um okay so and the timing is 12 minutes and and here it goes
this
so if any of you are there behind your tiles if you want me to help you to go to a group I I'll try to do that um but
um it looks like
um if you're if you want to try to go yes some of you going maybe and if you
go to the bottom menu and see breakout groups maybe you'll find an invitation there to
join and I'm going to go to YouTube
now to so there I am at YouTube so those of you is there anybody
on YouTube watching let me see we
have 93 people watching now so so hello so we have about 12 minutes
so if uh if some of you would like to uh say something in the chat there's
about a 15 minute delay between um what happens here at IMC and and it appears
on on YouTube it's not instantaneous so if you put a chat and it'll take a few
seconds for me to see it um
and um ni it's nice to see the names I see
there
there we go okay so so I guess
so I've been wanting to inquire about any reference material that may be recommended to support samadi
practice Yeah a good question
um um there are books about samadi uh if you want a General survey of samadi in
in uh kind of our Buddhist tradition and some of the different uh ways it's
taught uh there's a book by Richard shankman called the experience of samat
that there's a nice survey of it all how it is in the teachings of the Buddha and elsewhere and um so that might be you
know kind of a nice General place to begin
um
and so hello I don't know where the zoom link
is thank you for yeah so the zoom list
so so nice to see the names they're
there Kathy and Lorena Pat and Jean nice to see your
name Jean and your greeting
so we have five more minutes for the breakout
groups and
late
[Music]
so so those of you on YouTube um then I think let's see there we go
can you talk about Flow versus samade a second
flow is um can be part of samama and um and inly in Buddhism the
flow part of somebody is a relatively um um intermediate step of somebody
where there's a strong sense of flow moving through us that classic metaphor
the Buddha gives for that is a um Mountain Lake in which there's no water
coming in from any River into it and there's no rain entering the but the water that comes into the lake is from
an underground spring from deep in the lake and the and the water's flowing up
like a fountain that is spreading this refreshing water throughout the lake and
so it can that way there's no input from the five senses coming in from the world
around us but the whole sense of flow movement in meditation is well up from
within of a nice flow of energy of joy of delight of well-being that moves but
then as concentration gets stronger some gets deeper or Fuller then
it um it uh it um the sense of movement
stops itself is no longer there there's no sense of FL it's really really still
and um and uh so samade is a general term for the these States and within
suat there's different stages or different uh ways and it's experience
and it tends to be a progressive a deepening of somadi and flow is there
first and then there's a deeper uh Stillness that
happens so let's see we have uh three minutes left
in with the you with the zoom room I'll come back now to
Great your comment about everyone feeling feeling as if they're going
backwards at some point was very important to me because that's exactly how I was feeling thank you that's
nice yeah there I've learned uh that both from my own practice and being a teacher supporting many people in this
practice that um the key element is to is the sincerity of our practice trust
the practice and keep doing especially mindfulness practice just keep showing up for it keep practicing it and um and
just trust the practice uh no matter what the ups and downs are and any
spiritual practice that's uh worthwhile to do will have ups and downs and so the
image I have for the ups and downs is it's a path that has um that has uh you
know got up ups and down but you're still moving along the path um it's not
that going you're going up a hill and then sliding down up a hill and sliding down you are moving ahead even if it
seems like you're going backwards but that's just natural part of it and the way to keep going is to trust the
mindfulness trust the practice keep doing it um and if you're if you find
that something persists for a long time that really seems like a challenge then you should probably find a teacher to
ask questions of and help the teacher explore it help you know help the teacher help
you explore it are there any plan changes the format
or teachers for the 7 a.m. sessions there's uh the only no there's no plan
for any change uh the only thing would be that when I'm not here then I have uh
substitute teachers who come and we have a big set of uh wonderful teach here at IMC so who will step in when they
they're able to and um and the only only change might be if
for some reason I cannot come but cannot find a substitute uh one option would be to
like for one day if something happens and I can't come for for some reason I can
pre-record that day and and broadcast it which would allow it to continue another
would be that um um so may maybe some some I might on
short notice not be able to find a teacher substitute for me and and then
maybe the plan is to uh uh for the YouTube is to play an old recording kind
of do a rerun in a sense so with the time is this time is still happening and people can come and join and participate
but it won't be live but that's only in case there's an issue but otherwise they're planning to continue uh this
uh perhaps an odd question during practice earlier feeling rather embodied settled I shifted to sweetness and sense
this question where is sweetness or where is that feeling located seems like
a good question I I wouldn't having the question is wonderful searching for the answer it
might not be NE necessary sometimes it's just nice to have these Dharma questions
arise and um and uh and it's part of the deeper
process of something unfolding to have the question there and just having the question might be enough for something
to appear or something to continue so I'm going to close the um
breakout groups they have 60 seconds in the zoom
room and
let's see all
right so now they have 60
Seconds
for for
so I think we're back everyone and
um so so welcome back and uh hope that was
nice for you and so what uh else would anybody like to bring up any anything
you'd like to discuss or anything questions or uh maybe mention how that
was was to be in the breakout group or the floor's open the idea is to continue
until 8:45 so another 7 minutes or so so
Lou well yes hi Gil and thank you and we were all very grateful that you have
been online now for four or five years and available to us I just wanted to mention what we have formed here in
Nevada City Nevada um northern California that is there are about 10 of
us locally who follow you and have been doing that for years uh and we have
formed our own s we meet weekly we discuss your teachings and it's provided
an opportunity for us to share at a deeper level and also form a community
that supports one another in times of need um and also just uh to provide a an
opportunity to listen and learn from one another and your teachings have been the basis for U our gathering and so thank
you very much but also it's an example I think of what others could possibly do
at the local level given enough interest wow Lou thank you that was
wonderful to hear it's very gratifying to hear that kind of uh initiative getting together in benefit yes I know a
few other people who meet together around these YouTubes and have discussions and and share it with each
other so uh some people are lucky enough to be close by some people
um people who don't have anybody nearby uh we do have uh through IMC a Sunday uh
after the Sunday morning talk there's a Sunday morning song of the meets on on zoom and so it's not the same as the
YouTube exactly but there's a lot of overlap and uh you could probably sign up you know I think it's the link is
there on the IMC calendar for the Sunday morning um group
that meets thank you so someone
else anything else that uh yes yeah so Debbie it helps if you I
don't see all the all the tiles because there's three windows but I see Debbie so please G I just I you know how I feel
about this group and everything that you offer at IMC um after I fell last week this week
a friend said oh tant Tata what is
that yeah it's a it's a word that sometimes translated as
equinity but it it means more like balance it's like stand it literally
means something like in the middle of it all uh so it means some like standing in
the middle of it all and uh and be able to hold your balance in all the you know
the the difficult challenges of daily life and uh and so it's it's equinity has
more to do with wisdom uh uh we see we see equinity
means to have an overview literally means to have an overview of the situation that's wise so we're not going to be reactive to it but and tatra Ma
Tata means more that we have an inner strength to be able to stand there be
present but we're not reactive because there's a strength of of like standing
there like standing on a rocking boat and you have the strength to stay balanced you don't have any wisdom but
you have strength and balance yeah wow thank you thank you and love deep love
for you and all of you and the breakout groups are super wonderful thank you
Debbie thank you and
Karissa um first I just want to say thank you so so much Gil um that was
really really beautiful and I saw in the chat um someone mentioning about doing it
once a month or something and I just that would I second that um but I just
wanted to share that um in our group to
feel the common Humanity of the suffering that has brought us all here
um was very beautiful um and I felt so connected and
um it felt like a it it felt like a place where all of our tiny little
squares like we all there's so much life in each one um
and this is just a I don't know a silly little example of something that I do um
to like feel common Humanity when I'm feeling like I'm really
suffering um is that I imagine this person that I've named Lucy who lives in
senagal um and when I'm hurting and when I'm feeling pain and when it becomes
suffering I imagine that she this imaginary person is feeling the exact
same way and for her own situation and that um we're both in this suffering
together and we realize that there's common Humanity with us and we both send our
spirit energy our meta to each other and it kisses over the Atlantic it comes
back to us um and that's what I feel here like I feel that you know we're all
suffering and have we all have this pain in different ways and it may become suffering and as we connect and you know
then it can go back to each one of us because of this support in the S and so I just I really felt that in in the
breakout rooms and I'm just I am really really grateful so thank you so so much
Carissa that was wonderful to hear all of what you said it was very meaningful and and uh to hear it and know that this
orientation this understanding is happening here in this community and thank you very
much so thank you and this idea of doing it once a month I have this idea to do
it more often and U my schedule is so full it's it's a little hard but I will
um uh I've been thinking about it and just hearing the request gives me a little bit more momentum to to look for
when it it's possible to do it and um and the other thing I was
thinking about this morning was um maybe for one week if I can find a time in my
schedule where my week allows for it and we're doing the samade uh series I think
sitting twice a day as I've been encouraging you to do is really useful when the the focus is on somebody that I
thought that maybe we uh I I could host a um a YouTube sitting at uh in
California at 4:30 in California time for half an hour for one week like five
days and uh just have one week get the experience of coming together in community to do two sittings a
day so I'll look for my schedule and see if I can find that and um and hopefully
dur during the series there'll be a time so thank you very very much uh yes
Cindy yeah Gil I just wanted to say um when Matthew was teaching for a week um
we had some uh a lot of discussion about grief and and loss um and so he did a
zoom meeting for us which is really great and maybe some of the substitute teachers could you know do do a because
I think this is that's really meaningful to this group to see each other and have the exchange that's a great idea I will
uh recommend it to them thank
you okay so until next time and uh you'll have Liz next week and I'll be
back the following week thank you bye bye and bye everyone thank you yeah
unmute love you s thank you dude thank you so much everybody in G
bye everyone goodbye [Music]
everyone great seeing you all yeah bye thank you
bye good healing Debbie yeah thank you bye be well Debbie bye everyone
blessings blessings to you I'm glad I got to see you Deborah
it's my hometown Portland
okay bye everyone
hey and for those of you on YouTube that was uh thank you for being part of this
and I hope it was nice for you to uh to be part of this indirectly and hope
you didn't feel left out and uh put a link in save the children fund you we'll
do that uh when the time comes in a couple of weeks we'll have a clear link and and uh that's IMC specific that uh
to to save the children so that's coming uh probably the week of something like
the um the 14th I think um so middle of
February thanks bye-bye