good morning or good day everyone
welcome and as we come here begin our
meditation one of the very valuable approaches to
meditation is to when you begin to do so deliberate
ately deliberately intentionally purposefully clearly this is what you're
doing it's invaluable to sit down to meditate and it's invaluable to sit down
to concentrate the Mind such a way that it enters into a degree of
somebody the Buddha said that to see things as they are in this
world cultivate somadi and to be able to see things as
they are in ourselves to be able to see things in the wider world it's as valuable to clear
the eyes in meditation as it is to get a good night's
sleep or to have the basic needs of food and and water cared
for so that there can be the subtleness and the clarity and the to be able to be
in this difficult World in a useful way so in the same way for somebody to
see things as they are and one of the ways to do this is um to be actually quite
deliberate that you are entering into a new situation if you're going to go to
sleep to do so deliberately just go to bed and people who are sometimes tempted to
bring with them their devices maybe have a hard time falling
asleep if you're going to clean yourself in the
shower don't do it casually and walk in with all your clothes do it deliberately and prepare
yourself and so when I started uh meditation regular meditation it was in
Zen tradition and every time we would sit down the practice was to bow to your
meditation seat and then to Bow away from the meditation seat which was
understood at least I understood it to be bowing to the whole world as we sat
down and and z and that I sat then we would sit facing a wall so in a sense you were
turning your back to the world and now but before doing so you would bow to the world you're not
abandoning it you're not leaving it behind and so this bowing made a clear
transition to really sit down into a new location New time this is what we're
doing if we go into meditation too casually we can bring along with us the thoughts
and concerns preoccupations of the day and uh and they kind of we're
swimming in those as we begin there's something very wonderful and clean and
appropriate that when we start doing some activities for example going into a
sacred Temple uh we're leaving behind for a few
minutes the The Ordinary World not to abandon it but to actually enter into
the world in a deeper way that we can if we still swimming in ordinary daily
preoccupations so we can see more clearly so that's the theme of this
meditation today the idea of starting the meditation
deliberately so to with a certain kind of purpose
purposefulness or deliberateness to care for your
meditation posture and you might sway
backwards and and forward side to side is a way of kind of
really feeling the center of gravity feeling the Pivot Point with your sitting
bones so you can find a way that if you're sitting upright that the weight
of the body is balanced aligned through the whole body
centered if you're lying down maybe there's a way of also
twisting or a little bit or adjusting the spine the shoulders
there's a way of having the shoulders roll back a little bit so they can the shoulder blades are
a little bit more tucked underneath the back allowing the chest to open and and
maybe the small uh straightening out of the
spine between the shoulder blades some people find laying down that
uh bringing their legs up up towards their bod so the knees are bent and
upright makes for more deliberate we have here I
am so the soles of the feet are you know flat on the
surface and then to close the eyes and spend a little bit more time
with the posture now from the inside out feeling is there any ways in which the
body want wants to be adjusted any ways that you've
overdoing a casualness or relaxation in the
body comforting yourself in a comfortable posture on a couch it's
possible to overdo that and it's possible to do it too
little and to adjust the posture so that it's an intentional
posture there's a sense that the whole posture is now is going to participate in the
meditation it isn't that you park your body in a comfortable position so you
can forget about the body and meditation is mostly
mental Samari is a full participation form of meditation
it has to be because it involves a unification of all of who we
are so a deliberate intentional way of having the
body generally it means to sit a little bit more upright
like if you heard a fascinating sound that you don't recognize
nearby some people would sit up straighten up to what is
that to not with tension not with fear maybe there can be an attitude of
delight in this intentional purposeful way of being here in the
body and this posture this purposeful inclusion of the
body provides a grounding in the present
moment in the present location
and then with the eyes closed almost as if it's a ritual of
beginning of putting aside The Wider World in whatever reasonable way that's
possible to be here for the purpose of meditating not
for the purpose of solving problem problems to take to assume to offer
yourself a few deeper breaths comfortably deeper Fuller
inhale and a longer exhale than usual
that's part of this deliberate coming to hear to meditate you could say to yourself as
you breathe in deeply
here and as you exhale a longer exhale
now letting those words invite you into here and
now and then letting your breathing return to normal maybe for some few more breaths
to use the words here and now but as you say
now for the exhale
gently without ambition relax your body
relax your body into
now so that it's a choice at least for a moment to
deliberately Orient yourself to
now and as you inhale
here deliberate orienting yourself to hear
maybe with the inhale also kind of settling into
here letting the words hear now maybe become quieter or fall
away but with the attitude behind those
words gently breathing in
here breathing out [Music]
now and as you breathe out to relax the thinking
mind Relax The Thinking
muscles
for for
and then with a gentle relaxed
determination here as you breathe in can be a here just with this
inhale now as you exhale just now with this
exhale not pushing anything away but letting
breathing the sensations the experience of breathing here and
now be at the center of all things
with a certainty maybe a provisional
certainty that breathing mindfully breathing with attention breathing just
breathing is invaluable
this is all you need to do so that you can
purposefully dedicating
L be centered on breathing in and breathing
out
wa
for
e
e for
gently gently with a certain purposefulness
be here and
now as if just fully here is the most important thing
and can you [Music] feel some healthy appropriate
difference between being just casually here or not really here
with drifting off in thoughts versus being here with a gentle
deliberateness maybe arising from deep inside a sense of intentionality
embodied intent to
inhabit Here and Now
and and as we come to the end of this
meditation is there a way of being
deliberately rooted Here and Now centered in your meditation
posture that provides its own important valuable way to turn your attention out
into the world to see things as they
are without losing a rootedness a centeredness
here gazing upon this suffering
World gazing upon this compassionate world of people
caring for each other suffering
gazing upon this world where people do feel fulfilled and feel Joy
too rooted here to gaze upon it
all and to wish well to gaze upon the
world and wish it well may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may all beings know that there are others who care for
them even from a great
distance let's not exclude anyone from the circle of our care
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this fourth talk on
samadi and um as follows the this is still part of the in
introduction to this topic of samadi more will be revealed slowly as
we go along and so it began with the emphasis on
Discovery this is why mindfulness is invaluable is to really know oneself as
well as possible to know all the parts of oneself so
that when we when then the work of samadi begins all that begins to be
gathered together in a certain kind of way in which the inner life gets organized or
oriented and then to create the attentional space intentional context
for this Gathering together it's helpful to have
a a form of attention to what's happening in the present that has a
lightness to it or openness to it or non straining non
forcefulness at the same time as not being casual or laxidasical
and then yesterday the emphasis that samade is um really a stepping away from
life as it's ordinary lived ORD ordinary concerns thoughts and activities and
even feelings not to push anything away but as deliberately stepping away
as uh you know as is going into the into
a shower to clean oneself or going to the bathroom or going to your bedroom to sleep at night or there's probably all
kinds of activities where you go and you really put things aside maybe a nicer me
reference point for this was uh still very fond memories of visiting my son's
preschool and we could visit anytime we wanted to it was a very wonderful special place and um and somehow being
there when all the all the children were napping and uh and so that's a time when
when you don't want to wake up a little preschool kid did um and uh so
entering into the space was to put aside everything else to just be there quietly
and it was a very clear way to be somehow now or in a different place so
somadi as being entering willing us to enter into kind of a different realm
almost and we'll talk more about this as we go along but the and then today I
want to make the emphasis said this uh that uh if the focus is going to be on
somadi uh it's really helpful it's as helpful when we do mindfulness but even
more uh Central to sit down and do so to meditate in a deliberate
way to be deliberate purposeful intentional like now this is what I'm
doing it's all too easy to bring with us uh uh the our life our consern our
preoccupation the habits the momentums of our mind and be a little bit too
casual laxidasical and just kind of sit down in a casual way or an habitual way
and and we sit down and we're just continuing to Roll Along in the how we
were thinking and how we're feeling from before and not to push anything away or deny any of it but um this this
deliberateness of now I'm going to do something different this is a time for
this Sacred Space that now is a time for this uh to really be centered here and
if you feel like you're abandoning or the your world yourself you know
what's going on um to understand that the the purpose for samadi is not for
its own sake for the pleasures of samadi the purpose is in fact to be able
to see things clearly and and so it's a it's a approach to shift the
orientation of where the mind the concerns are
temporarily to create the the the conditions in the mind the heart the
body to be able to then later see the world more
clearly and um and so this is different than how sometimes mindfulness is taught
mind mindfulness is thought um that everything is practice everything is something to be mindful
of and um and there's not a turning away or deliberateness and saying now this is
the time to do just be centered in the breathing for
example uh it's uh uh samade is a kind of gathering inward to a particular kind
of focal point or center around which We Gather ourselves whereas mindfulness
sometimes is thought as uh don't do that but rather stay completely open and just
know be aware of whatever arises in your experience this is also a very effective
way of practicing though sometimes it leads to
uh to just uh letting our mind Roll Along like it
usually does I've known people whose idea of mindfulness is letting things be
just being aware of it to just let their thinking think what it wants to do and just kind of casually kind of just
follow along and um that's not really mindfulness if we're just kind of
letting you know the train of associated thought just kind of um think what it
wants to think um mindfulness is not stopping that but it's stepping away to
no longer participate in that to see it so clearly that some kind of participation and fueling of it stops
some part of our mind becomes quiet so so mindfulness is much more of
an open awareness usually samadi is more of a of a
centered awareness where uh there it's a different
orientation and we'll talk more about this but these two don't have to be opposed they're actually can be partners
with each other and um and that's how I like to teach mindfulness is that it's
partnered with somadi but for now for this uh weeks we're focusing more on
just some by itself and the integration with mindfulness will come and so for
this purpose when it's somei to understand it's not letting uh the Mind
continue as it usually is it's really choosing to step into a different
approach a different way it's a deliberateness and it begins by uh how
in meditation you you enter into your meditation posture to think of that
posture as almost like a ritual of deliberateness of purposefulness of now I'm going to do
this almost as if as a transition to go from one space to
another um and um and uh
uh you know there are playtimes in our world where we Mark the transition from one situation to
another and um sometimes in certain situations there's a minute of
Silence uh to prepare people for what's coming and
um so this deliberateness here I am and um
so uh so as you practice meditation you might experiment with for you uh what is a
good way to bring a quality of deliberateness purp
purposefulness intentionality to your meditation when you sit
down and to discover how to do that so it's not a strain it's not a stress it's
not uh uh an expectation that uh things now have to be different and you have to
kind of you know and your hold things at Bay but rather
a settling a a um
a a rootedness here and now now it's time to
do this now is not the time to compose shopping lists or not the time to review
the conversations from yesterday or um now this is the time to do
this and um so uh so part of
subma uh involves a Clarity of
purpose and the simplest way of saying that maybe is a Clarity that
now I'm going to Center myself root myself on uh something that's going to
be at the center of everything and so rather than I think
now there's a laser focus on something it's a centering on or settling on for example
the breathing and that's the reference point we'll use for this these weeks on samade some people it's another uh thing
they Center themselves it's a loving kindness and there's loving kindness is understood to be a Samar
practice some sometimes it's a mantra um so there's a variety of things
but uh but for now it's breathing and this idea of centering yourself on the breath rather than focusing on the
breath um is offered as a way to appreciate that we're gathering together
we're not we're not creating a a separation with a mind that's
looking and zeroing in and focusing we're not um excluding things
uh we're not um but we're uh going into having something be at the center of all
things and at that Center we settle into it more and more we we we relax into it
we open into it we allow it to fill us and everything else either gathers
together to support that or it simply Falls away temporarily because it's not
really needed in this this uh centered way of um of living in the course of
meditation and this approach to living a deliberate life in how we are present
for things how we're rooted here and now uh you might want to experiment with that through your daily life as well uh
there might be all kinds of situations where uh you just end up doing it casually as you go through the day but
what would be like to do the things you do with a gentle clear deliberateness
now I'm doing this I'm giving myself centering myself on this if you're uh
washing dishes or filling the dishwasher to just Center yourself and do that
fully not casually cooking in the kitchen cleaning the house um walking
from your car car in a parking a lot to wherever you're going in store or work
or something is to do that in a deliberate way root it so
you're rooted here in the walking so uh what happens how's your
life differently if you at you insert an intentionality a purposefulness
deliberateness to really do what you're already doing but to really do it and
not to do it um you know as if it's
a not really what your life is about that moment what you're really about is
the proliferation of thoughts and concerns in the mind so may you live may you
benefit may you find a freedom in living
deliberately so thank you