so the topic for today is equinimity and over the years people have come to
me when times are challenging either locally in certain area or in nationally
or internationally said Gil please give a talk on equinimity
it's like the go-to thing that people are requesting and um and uh when I discovered
equinimity for myself uh it was in on retreat
and I was quite surprised to discover it and to understand how both sweet it is
the that it's really sweet that it's really involves a tremendous clarity
and it's powerful it's an amazing thing and I had no idea until then that
equinimity was like a thing it's a particular state that we can experience
particular way the mind operates that can be known that operates if anything
if I when I thought about equinimity before I thought it was like a
admonition like some like stay calm you know don't be reactive now or
something some a little little bit you know like you had to do something okay I got to be a quantumist
but to discover on retreat as the mind got very settled and peaceful that there
arose this particular state of mind or particular activity of the mind in a
sense that is known as equinimity and how beautiful was it that was a great um
you know a great source of joy for me so um so the word for equinimity in Pali
in the ancient language is upeka and uh it uh is a word that means
something like to watch over to have an overview of something and so to get to
have the big picture of something and it's not a few times that if we have the
bigger picture of what's happening that uh we're going to be much more forgiving in the situation much less reactive
uh you know if someone you know is being unnecessar unnecessarily
snappy irrit irritated and irritable and just like what is going on here you
know this is my friend or this is my colleague I've known for a long time and and it's easy maybe to get
self-righteous or upset or critical this person's doing me wrong but then uh
someone tells you you know so and so um just lost a very close relative and they
have all this personal challenges right now to kind of and oh now you have the
bigger picture they understand more why the person is emotionally challenged so okay let's let's give this person lots
of permission let's just hold this person with care and kindness and not take it so personal that the person is
attacking me by being snappy so there's lots of situations like this where where we do this maybe or we don't
do it because we don't have the overview maybe you're in this in the market you
know checkout and you you're going to the checkout and there's lots of lines and you see one place where the line is
kind of short and it's clear that you're the you have the right you're they're right there ready to move into the be
the next person in line and someone slips right in front of you like how could they do that they they could have
seen me and how could they possibly this is offensive and then they see me and so
many times people don't see me and and I should give this person a piece of my mind and this is not how good people
operate but then somehow maybe you start a conversation with a
person something happens and you discover that the person's been kind of
seriously critically ill for a year and this is the first time out and it's
challenging it's the person's exhausted and tired and just barely able to kind of manage to get their their food and
get out of there and they don't really see what's going on around them they just saw the line and they were like in
a trying to cope and so they just saw this kind of gap and stepped into it
without they didn't have the bigger picture but when you hear the story about this person's challenges oh please
of course you could have be in front of me no problem and so there there as soon as you know something you have the you
know the bigger picture of what it is and one of the remarkable things that
happened to me many years ago was that I did a retreat with Steven Levine who was
one of the premier kind of pioneers for the modern hospice movement and he wrote
a very impactful book at the time called who dies about death and dying and so I
did a weekend workshop with him and brilliant man very insightful and
attuned to people and and it was a death and dying workshop and and um it was up in Marin at maybe
the community college there or some place like that and before the event was going to start all these people were
milling around outside in the courtyard and um and um
I don't know exactly exact you know I don't know exactly how to describe how I was viewing everyone but I think I was a
little bit at the minimum um I had this view that these were just
everyday ordinary people it might have been a little worse than that
but I if I could tell if I could remember it properly I would tell you but but you know some people like these
are ordinary everyday kind of people and then we went into the workshop for the weekend and the primary way in which
Steven line worked was he invited people to come up and speak about their challenges around death and dying and
then he would engage them in a transformative way very quickly it was remarkable what the two days were like
and the people who spoke who were these ordinary everyday people
had these dramatic difficult challenging experiences i mean
some of them were literally um you know dying while they were there some people
had just lost their child young child or baby or something some people they're all in accidents and this and that that
uh war zones it was ordinary people everyday people with this huge
painful difficult time and I thought Gil you just kind of
viewed all of them as ordinary everyday people who don't have any suffering kind of or something
and I said wow I take people for granted who knows when I'm walking down the street what suffering what background
what challenges these people have maybe everyone has some kind of serious
challenge background and let's not take people for granted anymore let's not kind of assume that everyone is I don't
know what everyday ordinary folks everyone has an emotional depth and
background and conditions that I don't know and so that provides an overview
kind of a different attitude to how to be with people that lends itself to not
being immediately reactive judgmental uh operating on pref preferences
u bias and uh so this idea of an overview an equinimity from an overview from seeing
a bigger picture seeing in a different way the other word that's used for
equinimity is a very ordinary three words that are
strung together into a compound that sounds like a sophisticated word if you don't know poly
it's it's the words um um
kind of like this middle standing
in the middle of all this so uh it's kind of more of a sense rather than an
overview it's more like having a balance being in a balanced standing position be
able to take a stand and not be pushed around and this comes a little bit from
from being somehow emotionally or spiritually or psychologically strong
there's some kind of inner stability inner balance that if someone comes and
says something unkind to you or if someone praises you
that uh that's not going to kind of hit anything inside it's not going to tip you over one way or the other you kind
of you're you're you're kind of rooted in a certain way that that rootedness means that you're not prone to being
pushed around by what's called the winds of the world the praise and blame success and failures and things like
that so these are the two kind of primary forms of what what background
for equinimity and what they both do is they protect us
from a reactive mind they protect us from somehow and reactive in my
vocabulary is uh a action a response in
the mind which is on automatic pilot that happens before we've decided it
decided anything or come to conclusion we just automatically kind of react to a
situation rather than respond response can be more thoughtful more
considerate more kind of balanced more coming from a deeper place reactivity is
kind of like a surface reaction that uh that you know after it happens
we realize that we've done it and so uh equinimity balance protects us
from this reactivity which keeps the mind calm calmer one of the natures of
reactivity is that it agitates the mind and an agitated mind is more likely to
be reactive which keeps it going and some people unfortunately seem to live
in reactivity and sometimes what people are reacting to and I've certainly seen
this in myself um I'm reacting to myself
i have a thought I have an idea I have something and like that that just like you know gets me agitated you know
automatically and then that agitation then another one another one and it goes
on and on and so equinimity is to come to a place where we're not prone to be reactive we
might have all kinds of feelings and responses that arise but all those feelings and responses are held in kind
of a wider field uh rather than generating an automatic
uh uh response so how is equinimity
brought about how do we find ourselves to be a quantumous someone tells you be a quantumous what do you do uh there was
a time when some I kind of indicated at the beginning where someone if someone told me Gail be a quantamus
I would have reacted to that
and and one reaction is no the other reaction would be okay I got
to get to work you know somehow you know this is something to do
but I think that reactiv um equinimity is not something we do but something
that we we build something that we create the conditions for so that it's
there to support us it's not a not a doing if it's a doing it probably is not
going to work if if we try too much to be a quantum it's probably not equinimity but equinimity is almost like
a byproduct of a way of living a way of practicing a way of being that we want
to put in place that we can do um and so
uh in doing them then equinimity can become stronger and stronger
so there are seven things that I think of that are the conditions for
the
seven conditions for the arising the appearance the establishing of equinimity
the first is uh and this some of this kind of follows a very common uh a kind
of progression of practice described in the in the Buddha's teachings the first
is um to live an ethical life and an ethical life in the Buddhist
vocab Buddhist teachings is a life that does not involve any intentional harming
of anybody else that's the that's the criteria for it and if there's no
intentional wanting to harm someone through our body speech and mind then
that gives birth according to the Buddha to uh the joy or the bliss of
blamelessness that no one has anything to blame you people can't blame you uh uh based on
what you've actually done of course people will blame you anyway
but you know that your inner life was clean you know that you dedicated to
nonharming and you were not intending to harm someone even though uh inadvertently maybe you did cause harm
to someone or offend someone and then you maybe try to take care of that but
at least you have the equinimity the balance that you have nothing to apologize for
uh you don't have to be or worry that someone's going to uh find out what you did because you had unkind thoughts or
you did something unethical and so a tremendous value of living
harmlessly dedicated to harmless harmlessness uh that's based on no hostility living a
life without hostility and um and to take refuge in that to
value that to realize how important that is so that if someone does blame you so
that if something you do something that the byproduct somehow accidentally is that it causes some harm or pain for
someone uh you at least don't have to worry about your intention you don't
have to worry about you know the motivations you have in your inner life you you can you kind of kind of kind of
feel good about yourself on the inside you might not feel good about the consequences of what you did and you
might want to try to do something to alleviate the problem that was caused but there's some balance or some
non-reactivity there's nothing in there you have that causes you to feel like
you did something wrong that you were just somehow were off in your way that
you went through the world so this uh sometimes it's called the bliss of blamelessness the well-being of
knowing that you you have nothing you've done nothing that deserves blame from someone else
the second support for equinimity is um uh it's often in English called
faith sada in Pali uh I like the word confidence
confidence in the practice confidence in the dharma confidence in these teachings confidence in the purpose of this
practice that when there's a confidence about how to live confidence about a
practice we have to engage with this life that we have if that is strong then
we have we know we have inner resources and an inner direction inner orientation
that will support us in any circumstance we find ourselves and so even though we
don't understand what to do in a in a situation we know that the practice is always there i can't tell you how many
times I've been in a situation where I did not know what to do
but uh I've come to trust that in those circumstances I can always be mindful
and if I'm mindful somehow things seems to work out that I couldn't have
predicted if I had not been mindful I would have been caught up in my reactivity my fears
my trying to figure things out my kind of agitated mind but with a faith and
confidence and mindfulness I can stay somehow balanced and calm non-reactive
and realize okay we have time here let's just be present uh let's talk about
what's actually happening here what we can recognize and know let me stay close to how I'm feeling and somehow uh
through that things work out so I've learned I have a tremendous faith in
mindfulness i have a tremendous confidence in uh uh cultivating calm
cultivating um non-attachment cultivating a certain kind of uh inner
freedom i'm not always those ways but have confidence in it and that carrying
that with me means that I'm much more likely to be non-reactive it supports
equinimity the third is uh a sense of is a
well-developed mind or develop developed heart the our inner life
uh you don't have to put I was going to say put up with but maybe that's not nice um you don't have to uh just uh be
stuck with the inner life that you have your inner life is malleable your inner
life can change and grow for the better or your inner life can can grow and
develop in ways that are kind of harmful to you and the world it can go oh uh it
can go to be kind of beautiful inner life or it could be a fairly ugly inner life when there's full of hostility and
hatred and and uh greed in a way that um you know is not kind to the people
around us and so uh to develop a good inner life a
strong wellbalanced inner life um to cultivate mindfulness so the mindfulness
becomes strong to cultivate uh concentration and calm and stability
so those become strong so that not that they have to be strongly mindful
strongly concentrated or calm all the time but so that
those are available to turn on when they're needed
turn them on kind of or or or turn up the volume or or bring up the greater
clarity so there's sometimes I'm in a situation where um this situation feels
like okay now I got to really be mindful really be present for this and I can
kind of turn on the mindfulness muscle and uh it's kind of like pulling the
curtains from the mind and so I'm not so caught up in my thoughts and my
fantasies ideas myself but now I'm really seeing knowing
recognizing noting uh tuning in to the details of the present the details of
what's happening inside of me and this is invaluable to have this heightened
kind of capacity to be mindful there's a lot of circumstances where because of my
role my my role as a teacher where I'm meeting one-on-one with people and it's really important that I kind of turn
this on so that um I'm really attuned to what's happening in me and the other
person really present and um I don't really I'm not thinking about the past
and the future too much uh I'm not even trying to remember what people say i'm
just really trying to turn on and be present be mindful be clear what's and
track what's going on here um there's you know and it's not not
always appropriate thing to do in all circumstances uh I shouldn't do this too much at home
you know in with my family my kids you know um you know it's a little bit you
know too much for them but um but they uh but they have the ability when something is difficult to turn on the
mindfulness and really know it's there it's a strength we have or to turn on the calm or stability to be able to kind
of know how to kind of become embodied how to relax be settled be here in an
embodied kind of way that's soft relax calm to breathe calmly this is a great
skill to have both of these to turn on a higher degree of strength of mindfulness
a higher strength of stability calm help then this non-reactivity to be there
we're less likely to react because we have this balance this support
the fourth factor is a well-developed uh happiness well-being
to have to become happy and this is one of the goals that is inherent or or
explicit in the Buddhist path to liberation that the the on the way of
this path is to become happier to have more joy to have an inner life that uh
is is you're glad to have you're delighted to have there's delight in it there's joy there's happiness and this
is of course a little bit challenging to hear for some people there's a lot of people who their life is not like that
where they're quite challenged quite sad grieving depressed angry hurt
uh you know it's there's a lot a lot of people that way the dharma though is
here to support them with this practice to hold it and be with it in a wise and
compassionate way but in the process it is supposed to kind of slowly help
people to develop an inner capacity for happiness well-being so their inner life
has the ability to feel when it's appropriate uh a friendly and welcoming
a place to be in a sense we're be we're in the dharma we're supposed to become our own friend
so that our mind rather than being an enemy is our you know our best friend we're happy to be company our mind or
have our mind along because it's a happy place to be so uh one of the ways that's developed
is to begin recognizing more often than we normally would when
we have moments of well-being when we have moments of pleasure and delight
i'm quite capable of leaving my house in a hurry i'm late to come and teach the
dharma and so I I don't even know that it's a beautiful blue sky and recognize the
clarity of the light in the early morning uh because I have important places to go
or we can take the few extra seconds few extra minutes to start enjoying and
appreciating the simple joys of life the simple pleasures of life not to be
hedonistic but in order to begin uh conditioning ourselves acculturating
ourselves that it is possible to create the conditions for inner well-being
one of the functions of of samadei practice is in fact to cultivate greater
sense of well-being one of the functions of some of mindfulness practice is in fact to
discover how to put in the conditions of mindfulness so that a natural capacity
for well-being wells up one of the great surprises one of the great pleasures
treasures of dharma practice is discover that there's well-being their sense of
joy and happiness that can arise for no good reason
most of us you know we need reasons win the lottery we get a good date we get someone praises us all kinds of things
that uh that uh you know conditions in the world have to be a certain way and
some people are chasing the world chasing conditions in the world trying to reorganize things and make things
happen so that they get the condition so they get things happen that make them happy
in the dharma we discover that we don't have to f our happiness doesn't have to depend on the world the world being a
particular way getting what we want uh there can be the the harmonious
working of the inner life itself produces happiness and well-being
and it's really a delight to just feel this carry with you an inner happiness
not dependent on the world and that's one of the lessons of this practice
the next one is so that's four so uh ethical integrity
faith well-developed mind a sense of well-being
and then the the fifth is um wisdom to have some uh some good understanding
street smarts of what's goes on in this world so I I attained acquired some
wisdom from the Steven Levine workshop and um it wasn't so much about my own
relationship to death and dying from that weekend but rather was a much deeper understanding appreciation wisdom
about the challenges that human beings have that when I was young was quite kind of eyeopening to see and so that
that gave me the wisdom to not take people for granted to be ready to understand that people are suffering And
that wisdom gives me more ability to hold people with equinimity with care
a very uh somewhat typical I think advice that hospice workers will give to
family of someone who's dying if they're dying slowly and uh is to kind of warn
the family that sometimes I don't know what exactly how it is 3 or 4 days
before they die the last week sometimes um sometimes more uh people will go
through a kind of maybe it's a physiological changes maybe it's hormonal changes in their you know in
their body who knows what it is why but uh they they the dying person will be
become very hostile and angry to the people that they have loved the most in
their life their family or spouses and it could be deeply distressing for the
family to suddenly have this anger being directed at them from the one person they love but hospice workers will often
forewarn people and say this is a known phase of people that are dying you don't
have to take it personally and so then when then when it happens oh okay we know why why it's here this is
not this is not the culmination of our relationship for 40 years this is just
chemicals maybe operating in their in their system and so now we have the have
a wisdom of how this works we might have wisdom about how our
reactivity works maybe we've learned the lesson from many
years experience slowly gained that when we react we re
react we get a headache when we react we feel uh stress and tension when we react
we tend to make a lot of mistakes and um and so uh to begin slowly to
learn our our delusions our reactivity our beliefs that are operating that that
keep us from being aquatous that's wisdom the um um I mean a few things that I I
had I learned myself through these years of practice that was slowly gained
because maybe sometimes I'm a very slow learner and u but it slowly dawned on me that my
success rate at predicting the future was abysmal
and I had you know I would I would have all these fear about the future plan I would try set everything up to be just
perfect so it' all be good and I was just planning ahead and anxious and wondering or expecting it to be a
certain way and over and over and over again it the event that happened was
different than how I could have expected it to be and so slowly slowly I learned
that Gil the chances are pretty high that your predictions of the future your idea of
what's coming is not going to be right and that created more that wisdom
created more equinimity for me the um
I have delusions and so that was also slow slow to to recognize so I've maybe mentioned this
recently but one delusion that I'm still operating under is uh I do a lot of
writing little essays and different things and uh as soon as I finish
writing at the first draft it's done it's ready to be sent out or something
and uh and I'm then or I'm eager to send it to someone to help edit it or something but it's done you know I've
done my piece and occasionally I've uh you know had that idea in the evening
and then in the morning I wake up and I have new ideas you know no or I read it
two days later it's a wait this is not ready so I don't know what it is and why I'm
built in this kind of way that I come to these conclusions maybe I think to I don't know what I don't I'm not going to
guess but I have a delusion and that delusion was against there slowly
learned to see it and now I see it when it's there and and so I don't bite I
don't give into it there's equinimity and things are much easier for me with my writing because I just now give it
the time that it needs or much of what it needs
so wisdom the the the sixth is um
is um the wisdom of non-clinging
to not cling or to have the wisdom to recognize when you do cling and to know
how to let go to recognize we lean in oh I'm angry with someone and to them I'm
leaning in to hold on to that anger it's a you You know it's it's a very different to be angry and hold on to it
tight versus being angry and not picking it up just letting it move through us we
don't have to justify anger necessarily we don't have to condemn anger necessarily
if uh if we're not clinging to it then we may be more balanced with it
equinimously angry meaning we're quantimous about being angry look at that there's anger
well let's see how this goes rather than you know immediately getting on the angry bandwagon
to have a desire desires are dime a dozen but uh but
again when we cling to desires that's where we might make problems for ourselves or that's where we lose our
equinimity and so to learn to not hold on to desires to hold them lightly
and um you know rather than holding it in a fist we hold them with an open hand so we can see them clearly and we might
then better be able to assess is this a good desire or not a good desire useful
or not useful so to learn something about clinging
uh it gives a lot of uh contributes a lot of capacity for equinimity because
most loss of equinimity most reactivity involves some some clinging to something
and then finally the seventh support for equinimity
is um the absence of clinging
the absence of holding on to some fixed ideas about life ourselves fixed ideas
about our who we are who we're supposed to be who we shouldn't be fixed ideas of
what is right and wrong so that when something happens in the
world it doesn't hit some attachment we have it doesn't hit
something we're holding on for dear life so you know the the example that's given
uh in this in the teachings of the Buddha is that uh conceit is apparently
like a um the the the
flag the banner that an army you know
troop carries with it into into b into battle announcing it's there and then
everyone can attack but without the flag of conceit uh
nothing can be attacked so it's kind of like if some if you hold up you know something uh you know if you and you
throw something at it it can hit it and hurt it and then there's a reaction but
if there's nothing there then some things go right through it's like an a a
closed window the neighbor's baseball will break it open window it goes
through and lands on the living room floor floor hopefully and causes no causes no damage
and uh so so there's this there's a a a
deep letting go that is possible that the dharma teaches and that deep letting go then means that
we're not holding up panes of glass that the world can strike
and and and and uh and then we react accordingly we just things just go right
through in a sense things can arise and oh
so you know if uh if one of you said to me that you know dharma teachers who
wear gray shirts you know they're a sorry state
you know you know there I don't know I think that would just like
that would have no that wouldn't touch me at Oh I might
wonder about you
maybe you need equinimity so equinimity
so uh one of the principles here that I'm trying to convey is that it's not
something we do because then it's probably not equinimity but it's rather
a condition that we have supported and grown and come to appreciate come to value
come to see that equinimity is really for our own best
equinimity makes room in the heart and the mind for the best qualities inside
of us to come to the forefront equinimity is a kind of a condition that
allows for the goodness we have inside us to grow and part of what we're doing
in dharma practice is growing our inside our inner life so that it becomes a
beautiful inner life it becomes a valuable inner life it becomes an inner life that um
is here to support the well-being and happiness of all
so those are my thoughts on equinimity so um
what are your thoughts we have about five minutes before the end do you have any questions about that or thoughts or
did it did it did you lose your equinimity in some way hearing it
can you hear me so I've been thinking about equinimity
uh in the context of what's going on right now in the world
and particularly the news that we got last night that we seem to be
starting yet another war you know our country that I'm a citizen
of and I came into this very troubled by that and I listen to your talk and
everything you said is is correct it makes sense and yet
I'm struggling a little bit with how I can reconcile a deep sense of compassion
and a feeling of wanting to
alleviate the suffering that we seem to be on the brink of
with this all the stuff you just talked about maybe could you could you give some guidance on on how to hold this so
I don't know your inner life to know whether I can speak of speak for it but
first I want to say I appreciate very much your compassion and desire to alleviate suffering in the world that's
a beautiful quality and um I think that uh
to have that I hope people will act on that I hope you will act on that in some way
i hope you have the wisdom to know what's appropriate for you to do uh sometimes we can't we can't uh address
directly address the big things in the world that are happening we read in the things we read in the newspaper but we
can be changed by it so that uh we can uh put more energy or effort into
what where we can make a difference it might be that um if you offer your care
support for a neighboring child
you might be preventing World War II World War I who knows how
this kid's going to grow up but it's possible that the one person was really kind and supportive changed the whole
direction of that person's life you think that's ridiculous but there's a lot of small ways
acupuncture points of change in this world that are operating that are not
you know but and but then but to go and stand on a street corner with a sign saying you know no war that might be
nice but it might not that might not be the acupuncture point that makes a difference and um and you're so so but
to but to do figure out what to do absolutely but the more interesting uh reflection
of what you're saying is that what's the complex ecology in you
uh when you have this uh the it's one thing to be aimous
it's another thing to have no equinimity to be caught in fear distress anger
confusion but to be caught in the grip of that
the desire to be do good in the world to be compassionate and alleviate suffering takes a very different shape depending
which of those two ways your mind is and so the chances are the way you the
tone of voice the way you said this and the way your face and everything looked uh there's a lot of extra going on here
for you that's not needed not needed and so to not to not let that be unconscious
so that it creates a power a strength of distress and pushing like something needs to happen here that's being pushed
by fear distress anger uh that uh that's what the dharma practice that's what
deep equinimity helps us to find and then we find that
and maybe settle those things heal those things and then maybe that when we do
engage in compassionate care for the world we do it in a way that's more
effective and one of the ways it can be more effective is we become the example
of what we want the world world to have how does that sound to you does that
address your concern or is it easier said than done
[Music] but that's I'll try that's why we have a
practice and in some way one response to these kinds of the big challenges of the world
the sufferings of the world one very powerful response of what we can do is
we can practice and some people actually will will throw
themselves dedicate themselves to a life of practice because they this is this is
the deepest response that we can do some people feel that's not for them
that response or that seems like it's avoiding the problem but uh in a sense uh in a real sense I
saw the huge challenges of the world and when I was young
the distress of the world and that's what I decided I decided to take the
route of the dharma and the practice and um and so now when I teach I've
tried to teach in such a way that that um support people in their suffering and
freedom from suffering But I I'm also teaching because I want all of us I want
everyone to to become agents of change to make this world a better place not
just to sit and meditate but to whether it's the local children or whether it's
you know in capitals of the world or that we try to make this world a better
place but uh so that's a response to you that that uh dedicating yourself to practice
is not a escape it's a way of really getting to the bottom of who of
ourselves bottom of our reactivity our attachments and clinging so that uh we
can be much more effective and happier in how we deal
with the suffering of the world so maybe if you if you think it can be a
short answer can we can you pass it there because we the time is up now i'll
try to be quick with my answer now let's see if I can be quick with my
and and economous my question i just remain confused and I may be
saying the same thing that the gentleman just did but it it seems like
with practice that compassion is essential or where I want to where I
want to go and so is equinimity and that I need to just keep finding a balance
between those when I find I've gone so much with compassion that I'm overwhelmed then I need to go back work
more on being equinimity but yeah I think I I went through a I'm
not being short am I i went through uh about 15 years of being part of the
Friends meeting the Quakers and it seemed like both of those were something that was being worked toward not always
with ease and the other day I Let me let me let me respond since people I want to
may I okay the the so equinimity and compassion maybe both of them are uh uh
expressions of something deeper that we develop and so we what we're doing in the dharma practice we're trying to get
back to the roots that are deeper deeper down and so we don't want to be too
quick to call upon equinimity as the response to the world too quick call on
compassion we might not be quite ready so we want to develop a strong practice
which uh creates the inner stability the inner quiet the inner mindfulness so
that we can actually start seeing the roots of deep what's deeper inside it's those roots that have to be somehow
trans transformed without knowing ourselves down to the depths uh we're
just rearranging the deck chairs and the Titanic
i don't know i I just I drove by a church the other day and there was a big banner that said um immigrants and
refugees welcomed here and it seemed like it wasn't a wild action uh that it
was a loving action and if we're very committed to ethics and compassion yeah
sometimes I just really feel like in a very calm loving way it would just seem
like a group that I really love that's devoted to those would Yeah very nice i
love the Quakers and and I love the Quakers and different churches that are involved in social action that's their
mission is to be involved in social action and I think it's fantastic
okay thank you all very much