so good morning and welcome or good
day and um so the theme overall for these beginning of the year is
samadi the practice of samadi the experience of
somebody and um this first week setting the
foundation for exploring this and for this fifth day last day of
the week as a foundation or background or context for practicing
somebody is Compassion Care anampa
karuna meta mudita that all the different care
giving care feeling feelings that we are capable of
is the context for samadi that the purpose of samadi is not
for its own sake is not to have some wonderful good experience uh just for
its own purpose certainly it's invaluable to some of the experience of samadi that can occur but uh the purpose
of samadi is not for its own experiences but rather to
be able to meet the suffering of the world our own suffering and care for it in a profound
and effective way to care for it not with our reactivity but to care for it uh where
we meet it with um the place deep inside
where the heart can be open enough to hold the whole
world the place of stability and steadiness where love can gaze
Upon Our Own Suffering The Suffering of others and care about it to offer it a k
a tender love to offer it um um The Gaze upon it as something that
deserves our respect our care our love
our just like if you encountered a child
who was injured maybe a very young child or an animal or a friend or an
elder you would offer your heart to them you would
stop and and uh care and maybe at first you
wouldn't do anything uh you just let them know that there's someone here who cares and is holding them and holding
the context of their challenge to accompany them they're not
not alone so we have this profound
capacity in our hearts maybe deeper than our hearts within us
to have a care for the world and a care for
ourselves and samadi the context for that for samadi is to practice
somebody out of that care with that care for the purpose of that care
and uh and to not lose sight of that is um uh will make the whole
practice of zadi more meaningful more satisfying more
inspiring and more transformative so as we sit
today to experiment with what it's like to sit
with a kind of deep care for yourself where you are
accompanying yourself with love accompanying yourself with compassion
kindness friendliness and all these words can be a high high standard to measure Yourself
by maybe you can meet yourself with respect samadi is a i is a
sacred in a sense it's a area of reverence at least for me and so can be your experience of
yourself the attitude toward yourself that a certain reverence and
respect a sacredness of holding all of who you
are including whatever is challenging so this is a context for
somat so to begin this meditation practice to gently close your eyes or
lower the Gaze if you want to keep them
open and to appreciate that however you are in this
present moment in your body in your mind in your
heart with the challenges of your life
that here in meditation that you've come to hold it in
care to accompany it with
care to begin by not trying to fix it or judge it or be overwhelmed by it if
possible but rather to assume that a deliberate posture of care
attention of accompanyment and for some
people the deliberate posture of meditation helps us to step out of
our normal states of mind so we can better accompany what is
here
and the same with breathing to begin maybe if you hav't a
shift of attitude where the Deep taking a deeper
few breaths is done in a way that you care for
yourself you want well for yourself as you supply
fly oxygen
presence and relaxation
calm into your system taking some long slow deeper
breaths and relaxing with the exhale
and then returning to a normal
breathing and if there's some very simple ways you can adjust your normal
breath so it's more comfortable or
Pleasant so it's more sensitive to your Deeper
Life maybe you can exhale little just a little longer
than usual Maybe by letting go
maybe there's a greater stability in breathing if you relax your belly
maybe there's a feeling of welcoming the inhale
and then relaxing whatever is agitated or tense
in your body mind or heart
and whatever way that you're sitting here in meditation whatever Way You Are
can you imagine that there's a
wide field around you of care love
compassion that you're the radiance of your
care spreads wide enough so all of who you are occurs within it
and then then the center of it all Center of that Radiance of love or
care the center of your thoughts and your imagination of
love the center of it all for there to be breathing
and with the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out is what massages care and compassion and love
is what
spreads a tenderness and a gentleness of
love into your meditation
and you might once in every cycle of breathing in and breathing out ever so
softly say to yourself a word of
care love or compassion
kindness or the word care itself say these words as a reminder her
to touch in to these feelings these
attitudes as you sit here with whatever is
happening
e
for
for for
if you are a little calmer or more subtle than at the beginning of the
sitting see if you can find on the edges of your
calm edges of your subtleness
embodiment attitude or feeling of Compassion
Care a tender kindness
and then breathe into those edges breathe into those
attitudes maybe allowing it to be the flavor or the weather of
attention
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a two or three breaths
to gaze upon yourself in
appreciation no matter how challenging
or easy or meditation has been for
you it's a profound offer of care gift that you give
yourself to give yourself an attitude of respect an attitude of valuing
yourself enough to do this
practice and to gaze now out upon the
world to Value everyone
to offer a degree of respect and
appreciation for the life force capacity for attention and
connection relationships success and fulfillment
that everyone has a capacity to experience and which many people don't
and to offer them a whole world our compassion our
care with an attitude of respect and [Applause] reverence where people are
accompanied and supported in how they're finding their
way may the way that we live our lives support the welfare and happiness of
everyone and may we wish and may we act in ways
that is for the happiness of
everyone May our Good Will and how we
live support the safety of
everyone May are well-wishing and how we contribute to
this world contribute to everyone feeling
peace being at
peace and may we wish and offer whatever way we
can freedom for everyone's Hearts may all beings be happy and
safe peaceful and free and may that be our heart's wish
[Music]
thank
you e
so welcome now to this fifth talk introductory talk to the
topic of Samari and and um this
uh experience the dedication the practice of
Samar lies at the heart of Buddhist Meditation practice and it's a integral to
both uh the development of deep concentration and to the development of
uh mindfulness itself Bas itself that uh um mindfulness and basana are not the
same thing mindfulness is a practice and vasana is a consequence of that practice
the word vipasa refers to the Deep insights liberating insights that can come when the practice of
mindfulness is conjoined is united with a strong stable
steady focused uh still attention when it's mind with
samadi and um so in the way the Buddha taught
samadi it's always um uh there's always preparation for it there's not a direct
frontal assault on somebody and um not a few people maybe
highly idealistic or will learn about meditation learn about samat and say by
golly I'm going to do this um there's a story of the kind of a
fable of a very capable young man who
success successful at school successful in sports successful in many different
areas of life very capable who for some reason decides to
address his suffering by going to a monastery to practice and he asked asks the Abbot
abbis you know it explains the abbis you know I'm quite dedicated I learn quickly
I'm skilled in uh in many things and I can really apply myself I have a a
dedication I have discipline and um if I come to the monastery to live here to practice how
long um will it take to um become enlightened and the abis says well
probably 10 years and that seems pretty long for him and he says no you don't understand I I can really give myself
wholeheartedly to it and apply all of myself to this and really do it fulltime
and how long will it take if all my capacities are engaged and she said oh in that case
it'll take 20 years so to uh have the wrong attitude
of dedic of of uh willfulness with some body which is not uncommon for people uh
is not the preparation that's needed and so uh this week has been
about some of the things we can do to prepare ourselves and they're all kind of a set
together and they kind of support each other these five qualities and
um so they don't they don't necessarily have to be in order but the first that
we gave was discovery that uh and this is why mindfulness is so
helpful that it it's so invaluable necessary for somebody to
know yourself well I've known people who have practiced concentration maybe
sometimes not even practicing it I've known people as uh young children who have had very very difficult lives maybe
with a lot of suffering maybe a lot of violence and the only the relief they could find was by somehow separating
themselves detaching um disassociating themselves from their ordinary life their ordinary
mind and had the ability to go into very deep states of
concentration and uh it gave them safety it gave them a place to go that was away from all the the challenges of their
ordinary daily life sometimes at home um and uh but they had never really
opened up to really experience and be associated with themselves be connected
and healed what was there and um and they come these kind
people who have this deep quick ability concentrated is often a sign that um
they don't they don't know themselves very well and for sombody not just
concentration somebody to really be effective the idea is that it needs to include everything and so discovering
who we are knowing who we are and as we practice new things will appear and
about ourselves and to welcome that oh this too needs to be included this too needs to be
known the second thing we talked I talked about was the very awareness the attention
that discovers and is present for things is to experiment so that attention is
not there's no strain in it there's no forceful in it or willfulness to it that
there has a lightness to it that there's a feeling that attention is open maybe
receptive maybe accepting may be um available and non-c
contentious um that there's a light touch and of course that light
touch lightness of attention um makes it easier for thoughts to hijack attention
and to mind to wander away and so the art of of meditation practice is how to
have a deliberateness and attention uh inent
intentness for being attentive without having strain and that takes a while to learn
and one of the ways to learn it is to understand that we are when we're doing suade practice we are not consciously
bringing all of our life with us even though we want to include all of who we are in it uh there's a a samade practice
is to enter into a Sacred Space a special
time where um uh you know you might go into a sacred place in nature a place a
Grove of trees where things are really peaceful and still meaningful uh feels like you you can
really relax and be whole and feel like you belong now to the world and there's
a quiet and peacefulness and you've left the World Behind but in that peacefulness all of
you can be there that's still there and so you can feel yourself and know yourself in a deeper and Fuller way that
if it bring with you all your preoccupations concerns desires fears
into samade so to have this light touch that doesn't wander off into thought there
has to be an appreciation that this is is a distinct time and place and now to
be here in a different kind of sacred environment that is
meditation and to be somewhat deliberate about that so some people will bow some
people will light a candle light incense some people will put on a Shaw
meditation Shaw or some people have robes um some people uh close the door
lower lower the light or do something or some people like to meditate outdoors
and go someplace Outdoors under a tree do something that's intentional
that feels like now I'm going into a different time and place it's very valuable to go meditate
in the same place every day so the association with the place has to do with meditation so that deliberateness
that Association that familiarity kicks in when you're there
and then today to have compassion care
love and the whole uh uh family of
caregiving emotions that we have um is a
pallet that we can choose from some people uh experiences love different
ways some people for compassion is what's close at hand some people it's
friendliness and kindness some people it's a very simple feeling of care that
uh maybe wouldn't be called love but has a gentleness and a tenderness to it or a
warmth to it some people it is just the feeling of warmth loving
warmth all of them what they have in common is care is appreciation is a
valuing and a respect for the object of that love that care and in
Samaria practice that can be for ourselves and to sit and have and create
an atmosphere and part of the intentional deliberateness of entering into the
world of somi that supports the lightness of awareness is to somehow
Infuse or connect that lightness of attention with something that's tender
and soft and warm that feels like maybe uh dropping into a
warm bath or uh on a cold day sitting in front of
a warm fire with a blanket over you something that kind of uh and there might be other examples
rather than mine that helps you feel like this is a special time for care for
love for warmth so that that when we're
practicing samadi there's not a lot of greed and force there is not a lot of
disappointment and discouragement that it's not going well like we're not getting
concentrated um that's to get concentrated with samadi uh happens can happen without
concentrating in the normal kind of way it there can be a settling into a
center rather than focusing on a central point and sometimes um the movement
toward somebody is best approached kind of from the sides or
from the back not this frontal kind of this is what I'm going to do now and be
determined some people that works for very well but what I'm trying to
emphasize this week is to is to deliberately uh and if it this idea
works for you ritualistically like a ritual with a ritual to create the
conditions to focus on putting them into place and um and for today the last one
is to have compassion as part of it and that can be the overall
motivation for samadi practice that um subar practice as I've been saying is
not for its own sake but really the purpose that Buddha offered samadi is so
that we can see things as they are clearly with care with love with
compassion um so we can become free of our suffering so that we can enter the world
live this world um free of suffering free of clinging free of distress free
of anxiety we can live stable
strong settled peaceful with a Clarity of
purpose that we can meet the suffering of the world we can live a meaningful
life so um so the purpose of
samadi uh points back to how useful it is to
prepare for samadi if the purpose of somadi is to be free of suffering and to
awaken a care for the world then the preparation for it is uh
to begin with care to begin with compassion as a context for doing this
practice so thank you very much and uh we'll continue this for number of
weeks that I'm here and so next week I'll be back and we'll continue thank you