so hello and good Monday to all of you hello to
this beginning of the week and there is a art in dhma
practice to [Music] appreciate
Beginnings to appreciate that in some way every moment is a beginning
that every moment we come to a fork where we can
choose a healthy wholesome good way of being present that supports us that nourishes
us or we can maybe go maybe down another Fork where we get
Den nourished so here we are in Beginnings
every moment is an ending and a beginning and the glory of Dharma practice is to
really appreciate the newness of these beginnings and there's a wonderful art
wonderful way of leas in
meditation to put aside the past you don't have to forget it
forever put aside the future future there's lots of time in the future to think about the
future to be here and allow every moment to be a new
beginning where we step into it with attention with
awareness and with samadi practice that stepping into this
moment over and over again to this newness of
now is stepping into or being to a Simplicity of
being sometimes I think of the definition of samade I've different
definitions that that I like to play with I'll probably offer different ones
as we go along here but the one that I would like to emphasize
today is samadi is
Simplicity a radical Simplicity simple way of being with one
thing and what we're going to be with here what I recommend is the experience of
breathing and to enter into that experience of
breathing so it's uh we are simply aware of
breathing we're simply becoming
breathing we're simply giving ourselves over giving attention over to experience
breathing fully but the language we use like
awareness awareness awar be being aware of it fully concentrating on the breath
it's all too easy for that to engage s a tension or a tightness in the
focus that kind of getting serious and buckling
down the Simplicity of samadi without
tension just here in a simple way
so I'll offer a few things today for practicing with
breathing but one of the key practices
techniques that supports a Simplicity of being with something Simplicity of being
with the breath is counting the breath it's a
ancient concentration technique and I'd like to offer that there's
different ways of doing it and the idea is to keep this very
simple and I recommend that for today you count the
breathings some from somewhere up to one or up to
three and if you lose count just start again at
one and sometimes just just counting up to one is enough and then do it again
and again the count is at this point less important than how the count allows your
gives your thinking mind something very simple to do that's directed towards the
experience of breathing and so the thinking mind is engaged in this process of being simply
with the breathing and being simply with the
breathing kind of bringing together our
experience so we can over time experience the different aspects of
breathing all in the purpose of sh sheering
awareness into a simple
relaxed attending to this moment here with the
breathing and they can become very pleasant pleasurable very
satisfying if we can become very simple with the breathing with no pull to other
things no no judgments about it or anything else just breathing so to count you can just one
way to do this is on the inhale count
one and on the exhale count two inhale
three and then let the uh exhale go without a count just just follow it
peacefully and then Begin Again 1 2 3 there's many ways of counting if you
prefer just do one on the inhale one on the exhale just over and over again that's
okay and the idea is for the count to be very
gentle it's just like a 2% of what them think of what the attention is doing
very light kind of the lightest possible count and then don't you the check list
check checking it off kind of approach one then you're done your job
but rather see in your m in your silent thinking mind you can say the word one or the the
number kind of through the length of the inhale and two through the length of the
exhale so it would be
one or it might say the the count a couple of times gently
softly one one
one however long the inhale is and then two
two so you're really there so assuming meditation
posture and gently closing your eyes and taking some now some
gently but long longer inhales and
exhales as a way of familiarizing yourself to the body's experience or
breathing
and then as you exhale relaxing your
body as you exhale relaxing the breath body the part of the
body that does the breathing for
and letting the breathing return to
normal and for a few breaths perhaps relaxing as you
exhale and gently putting the
awareness on top top of the physical experience of breathing like you'd put a leaf on the
top of a flowing
Creek and then the Bela would gently flow down with the
creek so put the awareness on the flow of breathing
and with that very light touch of awareness
and flow along all the way to the end of the exhale to that settling
Point deep in your body that you can touch at the end of
exhaling and then on the inhale
feeling how it arises from that settling Point supported by
it expanding through the body
awareness is lifted by the rising tide of the water
and then gently softly to stay with the flow of in
breath and out
breath let there be a soft
count that keeps you there floating on the
breath so you're not fixating attention straining
attention it's almost like peripheral awareness is resting on the experience of
breathing and the count helps you to
settle helps you to be simple helps you let go of your
thoughts counting the inhales and
exhales and if you lose count without any
commentary judgment start again
for
e
for for
with each count being like a dial that quiets the
mind quiets the thinking mind in favor
of a simple
soft attention
resting an inhale and
exhale
for
e
e e
and as we come to the end of this sitting
to see if you can find in your m in your mind the quietest
whispery place to have thoughts as if you're in a very quiet
location and you're whispering to someone whispering to yourself
here here in this body and
mind with care with
love here in this body and
mind with care and kindness
here in this body and
mind with
appreciation and
joy and here in this [Music]
world with care and and
love for the
world here in this
world with care and kindness for
others here in this
world with the appreciation and
joy for others and may it
be that what radiates from us what spreads from us may it be that our
contribution maybe our small contribution to this
world is a spreading of good will
out from us may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may may that be what we contribute rute to this world
today may we benefit the
world through living
[Music]
today thank you
for e
so so welcome to this 11th talk on samadi
and the the main point I'd like to make is that
is almost an equivalence with somari and simplicity samadi is
Simplicity and um
to and one of the things that we can do when we practice samadi is to notice how
we are not simple and that's important very important to see the complexity in which
we live how we get pulled into thoughts and feelings ideas
plans and appreciate that this is what the Mind does it's not a
crime and there's a homecoming that we can do
there's a way in which too much thought Keeps Us alienated Keeps Us separate from
ourselves unless we think who who we are is our
thinking but we are so much more than that something deeper and so homecoming into the
Simplicity and the more simple we can be with breathing the more there's something
marvelous that can begin to appear and part of that marvelousness is
that um it can feel very settled
very sweet very simple just to be alive here with the
breathing and it's almost like we're entering into the deep place of
home so that uh we can turn ourselves inside out
to allow some deep capacity for peace and subtleness
to animate how we live our life
so uh there's many ways in which people develop samade and but one of the ancient
techniques is counting Counting the breath and of course the breath isn't
suitable as an object for everybody so there are other ways of
developing samadi and uh in our tradition one of the
um one of the alternative common alternative suggestion is to develop
somebody with saying the phrases of loving kindness and just to find a way of
saying that that's settling that's simplifying that gets us absorbed in the
the activity of offering good will but the reference point I'll be doing is
breathing counting the breath and that'll also be the focus for this week
and um the um and you can certainly stop
counting uh if you don't want to but if you've never done much counting or even if you have there's something to be
learned about spending a week doing it that might be invaluable uh not a few people certainly
me have thought I was getting settled and concentrated but really was drifting
off often thought and it was only when in a very pleasant way perhaps it was
only when I started to count that uh I I saw oh I'm more involved in my thoughts
I didn't realize how strong the pull of thoughts were and um because I only got
to the count of one and or half a count or I int there have been times where
I've intended to count and never got around to it because the thinking mind was so strong
or and so if you can get to 10 then that's pretty good um if you can't get
to 10 you if you get to one only and and then you get pulled into thought then
you know thinking is really strong if you get to Seven then maybe thinking mind is not that strong and that's kind
of nice to know so you get to see something what's going on with you the counting is also a way of of
including the thinking mind in the Gathering the unification the bringing
together of all of who we are into the Simplicity of this moment with the
breathing and so rather than having a thinking mind be idle an idle mind gets
in trouble uh rather than the idle to think whatever it wants uh you're
actually giving the thinking mind something to do that is supportive of
the effort being done and sometimes the thinking mind is H really happy to have
a task happy to be included happy to be supportive of something that is so
incredibly profound and useful as developing somebody it has a purpose it
has a meaning for the thinking mind and sometimes that's what it wants and if you don't give it then it
goes off and looks for something else and so to offer the thinking mind
the simple thing to do that um might just involve one syllable at the count
of one two three and um and i i s i s when I was
taught doing this I was taught to count to 10 and then start over
again and uh or if you lost count to start over again and um and the way I did
it uh how I was understood it was I only counted the exhale and I filled the
exhale with count I've since then learned that it can be valuable to count both the inhale
and the exhale and what I'm offering today is that um to keep it really simple and
that is to count you can from some choose to count somewhere between
between one and three and to count both the inhale and exhale and I don't want to confuse you
with too many options but maybe you can land on one that just seems intuitively
what's right for you rather than kind of struggling around it some people find it
helpful to give the same count for the inhale as the exhale so one one 2 two 3
three and then start since I'm going to I'm going to keep it really simple here today start over again then at
one some people find it helpful to change to just count the inhale one and
the exhale gets two two and then three and when I un done I've done this up to
three uh counting both the inhale and exhale gets the part of the count I find
it really helpful to not count four but so breathe in
one breathe out two breathe in three and then let it be
quiet in the mind just ride the exhale in The Quiet Mind and then start again
and um and one of the things that does it stops the counting become going on to automatic pilot it also allows for some
kind of quieter thing to stay there so you're you're you're referencing quiet
subtleness for how you're going to say the count I've sometimes counted harshly
and you know and hard and you know staccato like the idea is to do it gently
softly with just enough uh just enough effort to count that you can um that
just just enough to have it the mind make that thought and sometimes what
I've done to make it really light for myself is to imagine I'm
counting and um and somehow in I this idea this exercise of imagining I'm
counting it becomes almost like a wispy or silent or um there's almost no
effort going into it no physical energy going into no strain no pushing just it
just kind of floats up and then and then but you don't want
to make the count the primary thing you do you want the primary thing to do is a
kind of resting settling um entering into the world they're breathing and the count is a
little bit like a pointer like a reminder oh oh stay there stay
there and um and it and the focus is not as laser focus on the breathing uh
sometimes I've thought of it there's all these metaphors for it and one metaphor that I've liked for myself is
um someone coming from behind someone I I trust and and uh and care for and they
gently put their hand on my back just letting me know I'm the there and they're there with me just reminder I'm
here I'm here to support you and um and so it's kind of that way we approach the
breathing the body breathing and just gently the count is here I'm here with you I'm supporting you I'm being here
with you and um and so um in doing so uh the
surface Mind of a lot of agitated thoughts and concerns hopefully can
understand it's okay it's safe to become quiet it's okay to you don't have to
quiet you don't have to actively get rid of that thinking mind but as the energy
of attention goes into breathing into accounting um something begins to soften
and relax in the body and the mind that that begins um decreasing the tension or
pressure that perpetuates agitated
thinking so that pressure quiets so to count your
breathing and I'll talk more about it this week but this was kind of introduction to this topic and
um and um so what I'd like to um
suggest uh this week that if you're able to in your life
if you have uh the capacity and hopefully the interest that um meditate
a second time today you've done it now with us here do it again so and it can
maybe 20 minutes is enough and uh in order to kind of
continue uh the momentum of this kind of practice um the uh I do talk a lot in
the guided meditations because of trying to teach this here and um
and ideally uh you then would practice it on your own so you can do this in silence and develop kind of a momentum
behind it so if you can manage to sit another 20 minutes each day uh I think
that will support this uh amazing process of samade that we're going to go through
slowly so thank you very very much and
um um and may your ability to be simple and
present and attentive may it enable you to enter the
world with Good Will May this practice support the spreading of Good Will
wherever you go thank you