so hello my friends and welcome and welcome to this
meditation and one of the ways of beginning meditation is to think that what we're
doing is gathering ourselves together there's ways in which
we become fragmented or spinning out or disconnected from parts of ourselves
because we overemphasize other parts and to begin sit down in order to
gather ourselves and so a
posture and sometimes if in in ordinary life if someone who knows nothing about meditation and they're really
anxious spinning out and some friend comes along and in a
very kind way says friend gather yourself together we have to we have to do
something we have to go help the children
uh you know get out of the burning house gather yourself together and so
the person then stands a little bit straighter and taller with feet kind of both firmly on
the ground and maybe takes a deep breath and and takes a posture and a breath
that is to kind of gather together bring everything back in so that they can take care of the
important thing that needs to be done so we're here to gather ourselves
together and perhaps starting with your posture
a posture that includes as much of your parts of your body as
possible so you're caring for the whole body in whatever posture you're in
standing sitting lying down you are
consciously adjusting placing considering the different parts of your body so that
they begin to be aligned or they begin to can begin to in a sense
work together come
together and [Music] to take some deeper breaths so on the
exhale you're gather gaing yourself
together not racing off in thoughts and
desires not resisting
anything not holding on to anything or clinging to
anything so that you become disconnected from the
hole and you don't have to necessarily stop thinking or stop feeling or
whatever you're feeling whatever your emotions are but to relate to it
all so that it's all begins to become together as part of the whole
nothing is selected out so we become
fragmented separated from the rest
awareness starts Gathering ourselves together into a hole
with the eyes closed letting the breath return to
normal and with your attention with a relaxed easygoing way
do a grand tour of your body with the idea of bringing
in all different parts of your body into the hole gather Gathering it
together kind of like you have
a a messy room you start walking going around the
room and placing things in their place placing them in Harmony and so the room
begins to feel like it's orderly or clean
or that the whole becomes has a nice feeling so a tour of your
body bringing it all together placing it together
seeing that with awareness with attention to your
body you can feel or sense a subtle
movement to bringing the body part of the body into
harmony into relationship to each other contributing to a
whole here and
now and then whatever you're feeling whatever ever emotions you
have do a tour of those recognize what's here maybe feel the emotions in your
body feel where parts of the body they're activated or energized or have
Sensations connected to how you're feeling and gather that into the
hole so you're not over overemphasizing your emotions you're not
underemphasizing it but rather you're welcoming it into the
hole
here also in
harmony with with the whole
and then to also a grand tour of the mind and
thinking and wanting and not
wanting not to resist anything not to hold on to anything but simply to know and
recognize and gather your mind into the
hole so that too is not over
prioritized but becomes part of the whole here together with the body
and then to do a tour of how you're aware
are you aware with a lot of effort and strain or you
aware casually and
unenthusiastically are you aware by feeling and sensing what's
here are you aware by knowing and recognizing what is
here are you aware with the kind of Mind's Eye as if you're
almost observing gazing upon what's
here and whatever way you're aware of the present
moment can that be clear and
relaxed [Music]
calm and gently engaged as part of the
whole not overemphasizing awareness or under emphasizing
it but having your way you're aware be in harmony with the
whole with being in
harmony with welcoming a deeper connection
to your lived experience
now with breathing at the
center for
gently but clearly gently but
committedly hanging out with the breathing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out while at the same time being aware of
whatever broad sense there is of the body
the peripheral
awareness of the body of the presence of attention maybe being
cozy
here as if the broad awareness with all things gathered
together is like being lovingly wrapped in a blanket soft
warm comfortable
so that how you're
aware has a contentment to it content to just be here and the lived
experience of the body
awareness that's supported by what is Pleasant
cozy
for
for e
letting go of desires so that there's more room in
awareness to calmly be aware of the present moment
calming the thinking
mind so you can be more
sensitive to the onward leading
movement of
some of being connected here
here gathered to together
here
for
for for
what would you adjust what would you change
or allow if meditation is to is to sit in
harmony with all of who we
are to hold it all together in some wider field
of Harmony
care
love no part left out no part pushed away
no part held on to all of who we are is set
free to be part of the
whole
for
e
e for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting evoking your imagination to imagine yourself doing
what you're doing right now have an image in your mind or have thoughts in your
mind of yourself sitting in
meditation imagine yourself in harmony with
yourself and somehow in harmony or at peace with the immediate space around
you and imagine yourself in harmony and in
peace with the neighborhood around
you and imagine that your sense of peace and
Harmony not resisting anything not holding on to anything is the most important medicine
for this world and that you imagine that here
sitting meditating you're spreading that field of Harmony of
Peace of the way that you hold and relate and are present for this whole
world as if this whole world can
settle in the field of your peace
and of course this is just an imagination but with that imagination
now let your good will have thoughts of Good Will and care and
love for all the lack of Harmony there is in this world all the struggle and all the
suffering that exists and imagine that your good will
can travel out through that field of peace to touch
everyone may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may it be that when each of you goes out into the world and meets other
people that this Good Will is remembered this idea of being in harmony
with the people around you is remembered
and may you contribute to the Peace of those immediately around you that you
encounter today may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so good morning everyone and or hello and welcome to this now fifth
talk on the approach to
samadi and so now done I think we've done maybe six weeks now on this topic
of Samar and uh this the kind of the last
kind of piece of of approaching or moving into
somebody is um what's called the approach approach somebody or access
somebody and uh I'd like to evoke the idea that it involves some kind of
Harmony that we're Gathering ourselves together together a unification of of
ourselves uh we're not every single thing that we are we know we are is included but everything that's present
in meditation is included that uh whatever we can be aware of here and now
as we're settling into the present moment um feels like it's all gathers
together into one large hole one large
um um uh harmonious whole and so to to find a way to to live
in this harmony so in the ancient world samade is sometimes associated with
Harmony or a evenness where all things are held
together in a kind of even uh way harmonious
way sometimes there's a word the word that's used is beauty that there starts to be a kind of beauty
and we begin to live in kind of a beauty we meditate in Beauty and I love this
expression Beauty because of um it's not something we can appropriate for ourselves we can't kind of claim it to
be our ourselves or who we are but it's kind of like the atmosphere or the
context in which we're operating we're operating context of beauty uh walk in
Beauty talk in Beauty medita in Beauty so the world that we live in
begins to change when we are uh in
um in um when we're when we start entering into deeper
samade and um so
um uh it's not easy to do most of the time when people meditate they're not in
some Mi it's still amazingly beneficial to practice mindfulness meditation well
short of entering into a state of being that's known as samadi or recognized as
samadi or we can say that samadi is many different types and for people who do
practice uh practice mindfulness there is a kind of samade that has to do with
how we enter into any single thing we do if you're washing dishes there's a Som
of washing dishes is where you're really there in harmony with that activity you're not trying to do it quickly to
get on to other things you're not doing it while doing a second or third thing at the same time you're just there in
that and so this idea of just being present for this activity fully in harmony or attuned to this activity is
sometimes called samade in daily life and the more we do that it supports doing that then in meditation as well
so this uh Sade the approach Sade uh I'd like to
use an analogy uh say that you've never ridden
a bicycle before and that you want to uh try ride you know and so you never plan
to ride a bicycle it's the last thing you want to do and um and so you um you
are um um but then there's a friend of yours
who um maybe many miles away is uh is
really in need of some medicine it's really important the person has the medicine and so then uh
you um but you can't get there fast enough you don't have a car you don't have any
public meanss of Transportation but there's a bicycle and uh but you never ridden in
bicycle before and um but someone says well if you ride the bicycle you can get
the medicine there in time but if you have to walk you won't be there in time but I've never ridden a bicycle well
it's up to you so you said okay well I might as well try so you begin getting
on the bicycle and it's really difficult the first few times you try to get on you fall off you pedal a little bit and
you kind of fall to the side you get back on it's so important to keep keep trying because of your friend and so you
keep trying you keep moving on and uh slowly you can pedal more than
a few pedals uh on the without falling off and then finally you seem to be able
to pedal and stay on but it's very wobbly and shaky and difficult and and uh you feel like you're ready to give up
because why bother when it's so difficult and um maybe have one big spill and then you're really ready to
stop but you remember your friend and so you get back on again no matter what even with scraped knees or whatever you
have and then you keep pedaling and after a while you get the hang of it after a while you can pedal and it's a
long flat stretch and you're pedaling along and after a while you feel like you're in the groove and um you feel
tired so you stop pedaling but then the bike stops and it's a little hard to start again because you still wobbly but
it's wobbly maybe you fall again and finally get going again and then you realize I just have to keep pedaling
because when I have some momentum it seems like it's easier and so you keep doing it and
doing it and then the way the terrain is set up to where your friend is you know
you're going to get there in plenty of time because with the bicycle but you as the terrain goes it slowly begins to
slant down the road a slow grade and at first it's so slight you don't even
notice then you notice well it's a little bit easier to pedal and then then you feel it's
getting easier to pedal and easier at some point you feel the momentum the pull of gravity and you realize you
don't have to pedal anymore you're being carried you're being pulled you can just
Glide down um it's uh you're now in this place where you're approaching your friend's
home that's down that hill and it's not a real steep hill but all you have to do
is to stay on the bicycle and feel that momentum stay with the momentum of
gravity that pulls you and you get pulled all the way down to your friend's house with the medicine and and then
your medicine is Happy Ever After your your friend is Happy Ever After so someity practicing meditation
can be like that the beginning can can be wobbly and difficult and we fall off and we get discouraged and and the point
is to always just get back on again and back on again and and the regularity and familiar it with this something starts
developing and we gets easier and easier and at some point as we keep practicing
and keep pedaling uh there's almost like there's begins to be that uh slope that
um begins now we're beginning you know this there's a directionality there's an onward lead leading just like on the
bicycle if it it's on a grade going downhill if you're keeping your balance
in the bike it's onward leading now to some place and so you some point you can
you're really all there it's all smooth all in bicy is All In Harmony biking is
in harmony everything is Flowing with your you have the balance and now you're in that you're in
this approach stage and at some point you have to learn to just let go of the
pedaling and um and uh and then uh go allow the momentum the onward leading
nature to kind of pull you along and um and that's a takes a lot of uh
Harmony it means to be in harmony with all things it means not to be resisting
not to be wanting not to be ahead of yourself or behind yourself but to be
centered here in yourself and um so to be in to bring
everything into harmony so um so we're here now at this
approach stage of somebody and um and this seems like a good place uh to
pause uh because um the um I'm going to
um uh I'm going off to IRC for a couple of weeks to our Retreat Center so uh
we'll have wonderful guest teachers who come to teach while I'm away and um and
in and in the meantime um and then I'll come back and uh we'll continue the somati uh Series
in March and how would I think I think on March 10th I come back and on on that
day uh we will um uh we'll do one more week on this kind of approach stage to
samade um kind of to warm up again get back into the groove of it and because
uh it's a kind of very refined State and uh becoming more familiar with some of
the challenges that can happen in this in this approach state will help you kind of maybe understand better what
it's all about and um and maybe easier to kind of maybe
follow along when we go to the next uh step with it all and um so
um um so may Elliot will be here next week
and Diana Clark will be here the following week and they're both wonderful
teachers and I look forward to um our return to continue on this and if some
of you would like to kind of stay a little bit more in the flow in this samade uh series uh you might want to uh
relisten to some of the previous um talks or guided meditations of this series um maybe even going back
to the beginning to kind of uh kind of stay in the flow and and so some of the
earlier teachings can be more familiar for you and supportive as we go forward here so thank you and then I also want
to uh just uh offer a big thanks and final report about the fundraising we did for save the children and um we
exceeded our goal and uh on the on that little
thermometer kind of circle that we have it shows we've now raised uh over
$73,000 plus there's another some a little more than $10,000 who's come in directly to IMC that we're sending to
save the children so uh we're getting close to $85,000 not quite and so if any
of you would like to offer more it's still available but I want to thank all of you who did and um and um I'm very
happy that uh very happy and very grateful that our community could come together this way so thank you and I
look forward to seeing you all and or being with you again in um in a couple of weeks