here we go excellent so hello everyone hello again ah so lovely to be with you um In
This Moment In Time In This Moment In Time so so the theme I like to invite us
to um practice together um is is a sense
of meta for this moment in time you know we've done practices in happy hour with
the past present past future f pre past
selves metaphor younger versions of ourselves and actually we haven't done
future selves I realized that would be fun maybe we'll explore that tonight meta for our future selves if there are
any that's that's uh you know meta for different arcs of Our Lives as well as
meta loving kindness friendliness for for who we are in this moment in time
and if we consider the Arc of Our Lives of course not knowing how long it
might be but but the Arc of our lives whatever it is as this hologram in time
as this hologram in time as if um we could have this hologram stretch and we
could see this hologram in time and and often we
don't consider this moment in time as as it's going along we sometimes look back
at our history at when we were younger at another version of
ourselves and yet we don't often have this appreciation as we're going through
life that this is a moment in life that is going to become past that we don't
have this you know we're so in our head sometimes not embodied and perhaps
compassion and meta is not so available thinking about oh this is a part of my path this we don't step out of ourselves
to to see this being who is me um as um
as as going through this this life path and this moment being part of this Arc
the challenges difficulties that we have the the intentions the good will the
beauty that we have so so um we're going to be playing around with that and if
all of this sounded a little too heavy you can let it all go you can let it all go and I'll unpack it and oh I forgot to
also thank um Neil for putting information about happy hour Google Groups and uh um the happy hour breakout
uh guidelines so just to acknowledge that so all right so now let's let's
just sit together and I'll guide us wherever this might go let's let's uh be
open as always we're going to sit just arrive in our
bodies arriving in our our bodies in our heart with some silence some silence
Landing Landing with the
breath Landing arriving with the breath
and can we relax and receive the breath not so much focusing on the breath but
can we relax the body and receiving the
breath relaxing and receiving relaxing and receiving this
breath in this moment as it presents itself however it's presenting itself
and can we relax
around receiving the breath relaxing the
shoulders relaxing our neck relaxing our heart our heart
center relaxing our back our
belly relaxing our sit bones sit bones into the cushion into the
chair softening our legs upper legs knees and lower legs and
feet and arms and and
softening offering the whole weight of the body to the Earth Landing
[Music] landing and allowing the breath to be
received just as it is deep shallow doesn't matter and
notice I'm not inviting us to focus on the breath or to breathe because it all
happens on its own simply receiving what is already here simply relaxing and receiving the
breath it's so simple simple don't need to make it
complicated relax and receive and let the breath
be as it is and can there be just a little bit of enjoying of this breath
just a little bit enjoying this breath
and taking some time to land in our bodies allowing the body
to envelop the breath the body enveloping the breath
the breath enveloping the body with
ease
e
e e
can we allow this breath to
be nourishing
nourishing and soothing calming [Music]
settling as if we're tuning into the quality of the breath
the same way that we would tune to a particular [Music]
station on the radio is tuning into
this the quality of calming soothing
settling there could be also the energizing quality that we could to into at times
and different qualities but right now tuning Our dial the settling quality of the breath
nourishing what does that mean for for me for each of
us and don't let it be effortful but no it's already here the same way that
the radio waves are already there it's just a matter of tuning into them ever
so subtly it's already here we don't have to create it and if it's not accessible
to tune into it no problem no worries
can we then be with the whole frequency range whatever is present whatever is
present it's all okay it's all
okay
e e
spending it just a few more breaths feeling feeling the body feeling embodied the breath within the frame of
the body
feeling the breath in our toes our feet our
hands our belly our
chest now I'd like to invite invite us to
consider as if we were feeling this
body feeling this body body and yet as if we were watching the movie of our
lives and then not a movie in time you know movies you can only watch
one particular point of a movie right but as if it was a hologram this this
hologram extended hologram and were saying the our birth our
childhood young adulthood seeing this moment then
perhaps future moments of [Music]
Aging this Arc of our lives and with at the beginning of this meditation
I like to invite us to bring some emphasis as this moment in time as as an unfolding of of this Arc this Arc of Our
Lives this being who was
born whom we identify as this being was born he grown up has had challenges
difficulties Joys lots of Joys Ambitions
hopes happinesses pain sorrow and not in a way of getting
involved in the stories this is not a time to think of the stories but just as if you're looking from a distance a
hologram hologram and this moment in time is part
of this Arc ongoing Arc of this being doing their best with
what they have been given and of course this being will
continue to agent
and get older and and and die at some point and that's a part of the Arc of life as
well and bringing awareness and appreciation to this moment in the ark
of this life this moment in the ark of this
life as if you were watching the Ark of the life of your best friend someone you really care
about best friend or or sibling or a
dear being a dear being in your
life you are your own beloved other appreciating whatever this moment
is in this Arc of this life whether they're challenges they're always challenges one type or another and
they're always blessings always
and watching watching this being that is you with eyes of friendliness
Goodwill as if you're looking at a [Music]
friend with interest curiosity support
and more than anything else
friendliness and perhaps there phrases of Goodwill friendliness
meta I wish you well I wish you well
directing the Good Will to this moment in time to the being who is you shifting
perspectives I wish you well and maybe allowing yourself maybe
shifting perspectives again if it's available to receive it as if you're
receiving this Good Will from your wiser self this wiser inner wisdom
the inner buha that sees the Ark of your life sees the whole Ark and it's wishing
you well in this moment Blessings In This
Moment goodwi In This Moment see if you can if it's possible
to open up to it and soak it up soak up your own good
will this good willll that's showered upon you which ins some ways it is yours
and in some ways it's as if coming from a wiser being that sees the whole
Arc with spaciousness with
gratitude e
does it feel like to receive what does it feel like to receive the The Good [Music]
Will in this
moment chose to soak it up you don't have to do anything to
deserve it just because you're a human being you live you die it's it's hard
enough to be human e
and to allow ourselves to receive this Good
Will with no strings attached nothing that we have to do to deserve it or earn
it
friendliness Goodwill with no strings
attached
e
e e
and as we bring this meditation to a close
together appreciating appreciating our
practice that we're planting seeds we're planting seeds of friendliness
[Music] Goodwill and planting seeds even one
seed of Goodwill and kindness It's infinitely better than no seeds at all
and we don't know when the seeds are going to flower and appreciating our
practice of cultivating Goodwill friendliness for ourselves and for others as we're more
friendly to ourselves we become more friendly with the
world starts with
ourselves and may our practice be of benefit to all beings everywhere in ways
that we cannot comprehend and foresee may all beings be well may all beings be happy
be including ourselves I don't have my bell with me
right now so it's going to be a verbal Bell ding
ding ding thanks everyone thanks for your
practice [Music] so so thank you so much for your
practice for for coming to together in this way cultivating good willll
kindness and just a few words about this practice so we
um started with inviting the breath to be received
not to focus on the breath but to receive to relax and receive the breath and to also tune into how the breath can
be nourishing and calming that frequency of the breath as
I invited you and then um we explored this this idea of
seeing the Ark of Our Lives the moments of our lives past present future and
then seeing this moment as part of many many moments because usually again when
we're in the midst of Our Lives we we tend to lose track of of this that this
is one moment that is going to become the the past moment very soon as soon as
it's experienced um and can we can we imbue this moment of our lives with Goodwill
with meta with friendliness so that was an invitation to really try shifting these
perspectives uh looking at ourselves as if a beloved other as as if a dear friend then also receiving our own good
will I'm doing the best I can in this moment um and if this didn't work for you it
didn't quite click that's okay no problem there might be some other aspects of it that
worked so um yeah that was the invitation for this exploration and um
yeah we often don't think of ourselves in this moment as this is seeing as if
there's this moment is part of the arcs of Our Lives we're always either future oriented planning there there or
thinking about the past regretting but there's just a different way that we can relate to
ourselves um so that was the invitation and I hope something something opened
up so um i' like to invite us to um to
um now shift to another way of practicing which is when the practice
from sitting perhaps with our eyes Clos silently on the cushion uh now meeting
others meeting the world this becomes the practice of meta Goodwill in um in
real time meeting another couple of practitioners um and and sharing so so
in the invitation that I have for you actually in this practice um well I'm
going to put the guidelines in chat as we've been doing so these are the happy hour breakout um
room guidelines um so practicing meta in the
small groups M standing for mindfully listening and speaking e embracing
compassion t for staying on topic and the topic I want to give um tonight the
the invitation the question is this
um is um what is not wrong in this moment like as you think of this Arc of
your life right as you think of this Arc of your life what is not wrong in this
moment so and this is the way you'll answer it and you'll go around and round uh
answering this question what is not wrong so so um what is not instead of
what is right like oh I'm okay you know I'm healthy so this is a different
question you're going to answer it what is not wrong well uh my ankle is not hurting right now my back is not hurting
right now I don't have uh acid reflux right now I don't have a headache right
now I don't have a u i don't have hunger right now I don't have impatience right
now I'm not angry right now right just all the things that are not wrong right now does that make sense it's it's it's
a kind a little bit of a mind twister I am not uh exhausted right now I'm not um
I'm not drowned in a crowd right now I I don't have earache right now like whatever what is not wrong right now
okay does that make sense where we're going with this yeah okay just play along play along and you'll see how this
goes so in this moment in time especially because we've done this practice now with The Arc of our lives
like what is not wrong well I'm not in grief right now I'm not in whatever it is so so play along see see how this and
we're going to go around and around so we're going to go uh with alphabetical order which is the next t wait take a
turn turns briefly so the first person whose first name starts the first uh
closest to a will say well um I don't my
finger my ring finger doesn't hurt right now or whatever you want to say I don't have a toothache right now okay the next
person like this this is what's not wrong right now they'll offer another
sentence and then the third person then you go around and round a few rounds um
and and it's it's a way to really appreciate this moment in time and um
and then to tie U to tie it in with the sense of Goodwill maybe actually do this
for maybe maybe five six rounds when you feel yeah do this for five six rounds
and then maybe switch for a uh a if if you are a beloved other of yourself like
if you're stepping out of yourself doing that thing the things that are not wrong right now what what are the good what is
the what are the blessings or what what is the Good Will so it could be either a
statement of gratitude or statement of Goodwill for for your own self so I'm
giving you a lot of R latitude in the next round so it could be a statement of Goodwill for yourself you know I
preciate that I'm um yeah I'm going with the flow there challenges but you you
know she's doing the best she can right now or I'm grateful for XYZ so the next
rounds after you do what's not wrong right now then is is either statement of
gratitude or statement of appreciation for yourself how's that play this is improv we're just throwing spaghetti so
there's you don't have to get it right it's just uh so all right so I'm going to
create a uh create the small groups oh and then did I already go through the
yes TTA and avoid cross talk giving advice and all that so I put um all of
that in in chat so so I'm going to create the breakout
groups here we go and again please be kind to yourselves be kind to one
another and um and yeah if if gets messy it's okay it's it's all
right the the instructions do the best you can um
so all right I'm going to open the rooms have fun I think that's the most important part have fun here we
go hey welcome back everyone we're back from the rooms and I see some smiles and
uh yeah would love to hear what uh how that went for you I'm very curious so
please do share for the benefit of all beings uh the S and you know how how did
that go what did you discover and please raise your Zoom hand otherwise I may not see you uh you can also put your
Reflections in chat if you like I'm going to open chat and you can either um type them to everyone if if it's public
or just type them to me chat them to me and I will read your reflection but not your name if it's just written to me and
I see Peter's hand just shut up so hi
Peter thank you Nick that that was a whole lot of fun it was uh I had trepidation going in it was
unlike anything before ever um but we we we had a lot of fun and it seemed very
productive thank you oh neat that that that makes me happy any other um any
more Nuance you want to offer yeah I'm delighted to hear was fun and productive can you say little it require it
required a very different way of thinking to do that um and so I think it
allowed to go deeper in what's happening for us nice oh nice that's just great
that's just great thank you thank you for that Peter yeah great Mima
please what I found it was it was a lot of fun but it it really helped me focus
on the blessings just today about what was happening with me so it kind of Drew
my attention to my brother called me and I saw his beautiful face when he smiled at me when he saw me on FaceTime and
little things that were happened throughout the day that I it would have gotten by me if we wouldn't have practiced this tonight so thank you for
this practice thank you ah sweet thank you so much Mima that's lovely Nicholas
good to see you uh yeah um so like like Peter said I
I found um it almost like as an exercise of improvisation where um you you don't
realize how many things are going well they're just they're so ubiquitous that it can be hard to um draw them up um
whereas like we we focus so much on what is not well that um yeah it's just a
it's a a warped perspective in in that regard but um it eventually it became
easier to acknowledge what is um what well in this moment nice nice That's
great yeah thank you yeah we it's we yeah we it's all of us right we tend to focus
on what's wrong what's not going well and and yet you know what's not wrong wait what what what's not going wrong
what's not wrong today yeah yeah very cool thank you Claire I see your
hand yes thank you it's good to see you Nikki um I did out to what everyone else
has said so far but one of the curious things in our we we had a three-man team
and it turned out it was we didn't ask it just was revealed that we were all writers we all had the same common
allocations or passions so that was really very lovely to be in a you know
like-minded group of people was fun sweet yeah thanks for sharing that yeah
I love that sweet and um I see Amy says um there was a swet meta magic in our
break room that's sweet meta magic I love that and Lakshmi says it was very
sweet to connect with people and feel happy for their good fortunes ah isn't
that sweet yeah and Bruce is asking how do you bring up the hand okay so Bruce
um I I see you so I'm going to ask you to unmute you've brought up your hand by sending the message so
please oh I was just curious um I mean I we didn't we were
top heavy so we we answered the first question a lot get around to the second
that's all good how did that go how did that go for you how did it went fine I mean we um how did it feel I think um I
think as we went along it started to get more difficult and um started to go a little deeper I think nice um so you
know that was good great that's the purpose of these questions usually is first we get to the we answer the
surface things and then yeah it it be it becomes deeper which is beautiful yeah
great thank you and and the way you would turn uh rise your hand later if uh
different systems if if you go if you click on react um there's a raise hand function
under react for on many systems Vicky hello
Vicki so great to see you Nikki thank you the same and you know it was just
interesting to think of what the difference is in what's not wrong and what I have gratitude for you know
because starting out that way you think well there's so much wrong in the world
but then you realize how much there really is that's going
right and so that that was a really curious way to get to what's right
thanks nice love it exactly there's so much that is going right in the world
right yeah there there many things that are not but there's so much that is going right in the world yeah awesome
well said Thank You Vicki thank you so great yeah any other Reflections
um anything else anyone else either in chat or in person anything also about
the meditation anything you want to share about the meditation of some something that worked something
that didn't any questions objections it's all
welcome Audrey hi Nikki thank you I just wanted
to say thank you so much for doing the body scan at the beginning of the meditation that um especially uh I
enjoyed at the end of the day when I'm a little bit more hyped up and it helps me
to get into my body so I wanted to thank you for that a thank you it's you know
body scan is such a great practice right calming soothing settling and so
beautiful yeah thank you for giving it a shout out and highlighting how how um supportive it was I love body
scans oh yeah thank you Audrey beautiful so oh Diana you get the last
word here in the meditation I just love it's back
to the body scale especially breathing into the different parts of the body and
letting each one receive uh but the idea of of the body and the breath um
enveloping each other you use the word envelop and I had a wonderful image of
the one enveloping the the breath and back and forth and whatever it was that
was very nice and um settling and peaceful for me so thank
you yeah thanks Santa I appreciate you reflecting back the that phrase that I had never used before it's the first
time the breath enveloping the body and the body enveloping the breath and yeah there is like oh yeah it's kind of fun
right this this this play of the breath and the body and um this was inspired by
a quote I um read a few days ago by um I
forget his name but Ralph is his last name this is the person who came up with Rolfing this which is a style of massage
ralfing and he said something like the body is uh how did he say it my
interpretation was my paraphrase is that that that the body is kind of solid matter that wraps itself around the
breath that that kind of like enveloping the body enveloping the breath and I just love that image of oh yeah kind of
it helps me land into my body more and my breath so so thank you dear ones
thank you so much for your practice thank you for coming and planting seeds
of kindness wholesomeness goodness for our own sake and the sake of all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including ourselves yeah and at
this time