hello everyone and welcome and I suppose the background hasn't
changed so much from yesterday it's um but uh I'm actually now back at IMC
yesterday I was at IRC our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz and so here I have
welcome you to welcome you to Redwood City and um delighted to be here with
you and to be able to share this time and
um so the topic for this beginning of the year is
samadi and when it's con when it's translated as
concentration uh sometimes um uh we limit ourselves
dramatically by F focusing on focusing we limit ourselves to a
particular channel of attention that sometimes is a kind of a one-pointed
laser focus or an attempt to do this and
um and uh samadi is a practice that uh
awakens or utilizes all our attentional
faculties so it's something that is holistic or in
inclusive of um the the wide range of ways which we we can be present here and
now in fact in some ways there's a way in which there's a gathering of all our
capacities for attention into one way and then uh with that we are as the
the uh the objects of attention the what we're aware of become simpler and
simpler because uh we're not preoccupied or not
the mind is not chasing different things or fragmented and going off into different
directions the mind the heart gets more settled more at ease and peaceful in
itself and so there is no
um um uh there's very little uh
multitracking going on uh but without the without narrowing the
expense of the open awareness and all the different faculties of attention so this is one of the reasons it's called
Uh Gathering Together unification process and that's my favorite way of thinking of samade or translating it as
a unification so it is using our attentional
faculties and so mindfulness is very important because that is one of that
that is also using our attentional faculties and the um and one of the
things that mindfulness can teach us is uh is to have a very light
touch with with awareness uh that to allow the awareness
to be unburdened or uninfluenced by stress by
pressure by weight by force uh where awareness has the is
lighter maybe I was going to say lighter than air but maybe then it floats away maybe this you know the same weight as
air that awareness uh has the same
clarity as a really clean window or maybe better a Clarity of an
open window where there's no glass even in the way or it has
um uh it uh where awareness has no shape in a certain kind of way sometimes
it feels like awareness has no location or Center but whatever it is there's a
lightness to it or a softness to it or a um non assertiveness to it or non-
hesitation to it sometimes it's uh people will describe it as being
accepting re but even those are too much of a doing
though they get get the we get the hang of it from that and
um and uh so to learn that kind of attention and to learn to do it so the
mind doesn't Drift Away uh and that's the the art and that's one of the ways that
concentration helps is to help the mind not Drift Away into other things and
other plac is so yesterday I emphasized the importance of
Discovery and uh getting to know yourself better knowing what your mind
is like your body is like what your heart your feelings are like and i' like to continue that process of discovery
but today uh with an emphasis on
uh uh an emphasis on um
uh experimenting with how you're aware of
whatever you discover is happening now so it's not this is not a practice today still of making any kind of change
trying to get yourself concentrated to get yourself maybe even undistracted it's not trying to make anything happen
anything go away or fix anything but it's a simple process of discovery of
what your what's happening what what are the elements what who are you what's going on for
you um because that those all the different parts of who you are is what
is needed to gather the mind in this
unification and and and then how you do this with the mind the awareness with
which you do it that's also key so see if your awareness of whatever is happening can have no Force no weight no
tension in it it just very light almost like you're awareness is like an open
Palm that's going to that holds uh where where there lands a butterfly or lands
even more lighter than that might be a an a dandelion um uh you know those uh
flowers that they're floating through the air with the seeds and you just land there and just just there it is that
kind of weight so to assume a meditation
posture and to gently close your
eyes and without doing anything else to prepare yourself for
meditation discover how you are right now
almost like you're stepping back to be the
Observer almost as if you're observing something that you don't
identify yourself with but you
are kindly attentive how's your body
the kind attention that allows your body to be as it is even if it's some
challenge but for a few moments just discover the
body and see what kind of simple
awareness a way of feeling sensing
a simple knowing of how the body
is where these forms of attention have no force in
them no expectation no reaction no judgment
and then notice also in your body how you're feeling what's your mood
or emotional state to
discover maybe it's a bit of a kaleidoscope of Shifting feelings
and see if how you know it can be light and open
receptive allowing
maybe it helps to back off from not to disconnect
or not be aware of but to back off from your
emotions so you're not riding them too closely allowing them to be
there discovering them like a
naturalist and then how are you in your mind your thinking mind
without opposition or contention with
anything can you experiment with the lightest Touch of
awareness that is present without any pressure or Force
and now with the lightest of
Touches for your awareness your feeling sensing
knowing to be aware of
breathing if awareness is light enough to float on the
ocean maybe the image of awareness floating on
the waves of breathing in and breathing out gentle waves moving through the
ocean with awareness riding on them
a light
awareness and so the awareness doesn't float away across the
ocean imagine there's a gentle
soft rope where awareness is anchored to the
bottom of the
ocean staying in more or less one place as it goes up and
down floating on the surface of breathing in and breathing
out rooted with an anchor deep in your
body for
for
for for
if you're aware right now how is it to be
aware what are the characteristics of being
attentive just to what's happening in the
present and is there some way to relax any unnecessary
tension associated with being aware or judging what it's like to be aware or
not aware
letting awareness be like an open door that welcomes in the
breathing the body is experience a breathing appears
freely in a light
open awareness
that's
anchored deep under the surface of the waves of breathing in and breathing
out
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a few more breaths to rise on the
breathing floats up and down with inhale and
exhale and as you exhale to relax your
body soften
as you exhale Relax The Thinking mind soften any tension or
pressure associated with thinking
and if there is any pressure or tension contraction associated with how
you're feeling see if you can soften
relax that tension
and then as if body mind and
heart or one [Music] whole as you
exhale relax your whole being
as if the edges of your being can soften
open and
then in the Comfort or security or safety
of your meditation
posture to let your attention now your thoughts now
wonderand out into the world to the people in your
life friends family [Music]
neighbors neighbors known and
unknown colleagues at
work people you encounter in stores mail carriers that might come to
your
mailbox see if you can relax your whole
being in including others into your heart into your
mind and to allow the possibility
that the practice of meditation is for the benefit and happiness of everyone including
yourself may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful May all beings be
free and may those four
wishes flow out of the goodness of your heart out into the world
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this second talk on
samadi this uh probably be a longer
series and it's such an important topic in Buddhism in Buddhist practice samade
or concentration and uh it's part of the
key Foundation stones cornerstones for Buddhist
practice mindfulness is another one ethics being ethical is a third one and
kindness and generosity or maybe the
fourth and but it's it's tremendously valuable and it can lead to a lot of
stress and a lot of confusion uh I certainly have tried to develop concentration and meditation and
ended up with u a headache because of the way in which I was trying to develop
somebody it was it was too willful it was too um forceful it was with a lot of
tension and with a lot of expectation and a lot of uh um degree of conceit you
know I'm the one who's going to get concentrated so it's I think of samadi
as an art and uh sometimes as an art uh that we develop or craft that we develop
over time sometimes I think of it as Grace uh that uh when samade arises it's
like a gift that's been given and I don't necessarily feel responsible for developing
somebody but um I have to put the conditions into place so one of the ways of
understanding the unification of all of Who We Are a as part of samade practice
um and why it's so important to discover all the different aspects of who who we are um to do so without any judgments
without any uh criticisms without any reactivity to it but just to discover is
to think of ourselves all the parts of who we are as the new members of a soccer team or
new members of a of a dance team and um not everyone is uh completely
skilled in dancing or playing soccer and the team doesn't know each other and so
at first as they practice it's awkward and difficult and uh even the coach
doesn't understand the different skills and abilities and uh how to uh how to uh
give people different parts or and how those different uh players of the team
can uh work together and so of course that's the way it is in the beginning of
course it's awkward of course it's um it takes time for uh to discover the
skills the abilities the the how to be inclusive and how to put all the
different pieces together so in the beginning the coach is involved is
discovering uh the players and then as we discover them we learn how to begin
bringing them together to work together to support each other to have the same
purpose and uh to be a uh a team that is Unified so the desperate parts of
ourselves we want to First discover what they are understand what they are and then uh we want to start understanding
how to bring them together and so that the unification doesn't have any stress in it it doesn't
have any uh UNH wholesome qualities to it that it actually feels like a
welcoming com together a delightful coming together and uh kind of um uh
coming into a kind of fullness or a holistic Vitality or
liveness so we begin with the discovery process and we discover a lot of things we discover how distracted we are how
little concentration we have we discover that we have expectations of wanting it
to be different we have judgments about what's happening and this if only this
wasn't happening then I could get concentrated and so there's you know pushing away certain things or judging
certain things um we might be we might have a lot of conceit involved that
maybe you've been very successful in doing various uh things in your life and
you think that the meditation should be the same you just apply yourself you learn what the steps meditation by the
numbers and you can just do it and and um and that conceit sometimes of being
the doer the successful person uh gets in the way and the important thing here is just
discover the whole thing without judging it getting ready
uh for the Real Performance the real game later but for now just kind of
getting used to each other and seeing what's there and one of the things to discover is the different ways in which
uh awareness operates because samadi is a unification of not only of all of who
we are but all the different ways in which we can be aware
attentive and um and so there's three in particular that are useful for Saadi and
for mindfulness as well there is um our ability to know what is happening so
that's a cognitive uh function of the Mind recognizing and
it's a very it's not judging or having commentary not that kind of knowing but
the simplest possible knowing there's a sound uh we don't uh hear a big bang
like I just did and um begin thinking of oh was that an accident was that someone
at hammering what was someone doing banging this early in the morning and so
my mind Braes off off it's just like oh sound bang that
simple and um so the simple Act of knowing knowing the INB breath knowing
the out breath knowing oh there's thinking happening and keeping it very very
simple and so that's one way the cognitive functioning of uh recognition
of knowing the second kind of awareness is uh somatic it's how we can feel and
sense things through our body uh so you might know there's an inhale but you can
feel the expansion of the chest you can feel the movement of the chest you can feel the smoothness or the choppiness of
the way the the inhal moves out um and but that can be felt from the
inside out it's the I like to say as many of you know um to uh to notice how
the body experiences breathing how the body experiences itself so how does the
body experience the breathing so this experiential aspect of it which is somatic and uh
sensory is another piece another way in which we're aware a Third Way emphasized
by the Buddha that uh in his teaching at least usually waits until people are
pretty settled in meditation and that is to observe and this is uh to Simply uh see
why watch observe what's happening not NE without necessarily having to know
what it is without interfering with it because when you see something you don't
interfere with what you see that comes a different way and um and we're not
necessarily directly feeling it there's feeling and sensing experiencing can be
have a wonderful intimacy um and but observing can have a
much more peaceful much more equanimous it's not aloof uh can be very
important but uh there's a quiting of all kinds of activities including the
activity of sensing and feeling so there's knowing feeling and
um and watching and observing there's also hearing and tasting and smelling
there's proor perception there's all these different ways in which we um can
experience the inner life through the different nerve endings that we have and um and it's useful to recognize
what is our strength as part of the team the soccer team the dance troop uh what
is our strength are we we the person who's more easier with with the sematic
experiencing are we the one who's more has greater ease with um recognition and
knowing and that's how we anchor ourselves in the present or we more like we we kind of settle back and observe
and and that's our strength and um and so um uh and then
there's the ways in which attention can be very open taking in everything and as it arises and occurs and sometimes
attention is very um uh centered somewhere so that it's not it's not so
large maybe chaotic and confusing that so much is going on at once we're just kind of narrowing the attention to one
little place um so like if you're in a crowded restaurant sometimes it's really
nice to open the awareness the hearing and just take in all the amazing sounds of people eating and clanking their
spoon against their plates um and they just can that can be very relaxing and
spacious or it can be confusing and it can be agitating just like too much
input and and for some people they prefer to just kind of just be with their own plate their own food and let
their attention be centered there and it can be very relaxing and quieting to just be have this intimacy with your own
food and everything else Falls away so how is it for you what kind of
awareness is useful for you um uh is it important part of this discovery process
that uh of bringing together um the team s
the um the the dance troop the samade dance troop and so um uh this principle
of Discovery and knowing yourself uh is is invaluable for the preparation for you
know uh moving into samade itself and um so I've said a lot
today but you might want to as you go through um the day today uh
notice discover how you're aware and uh some people are very aware
through the the lens of their thinking their bias their preconceived
ideas and that's not quite the kind of attention the Buddha focused on but it's
important to see that that you're doing that and then as you know anything at
all about yourself the experiment the core experiment of today is can you know it lightly can you
know it without judgment can you know without tension and pressure and
um and uh how light how soft
how uh uncontracted how
untight can you simply know simply feel simply observe
what's happening with you so um in this slow way that we're going
to go into samade this is the second step of how to we're going to move into
it and um so thank you very much and I look forward to continuing tomorrow