hello everyone and welcome to our meditation and as we go into the least
least uh evoking or exploring considering the second Janna
uh one of the features of it is that uh characteristics of it oops is hello
everyone is a feeling of uh experience
of unity or unification the word is
ecody which uh loosely can be
uh described as uh weaving into one bringing everything into a oneness
of sorts and um and so it's a feeling that uh of
inclusion that everything is included in such a way that we're not apart from
anything and nothing is apart from us everything in a certain way becomes
subject there's no object for the experience and what's operating here is the word
inexperience logic understanding common sense can give us a subject object
distinction there are things we focus on which are objects and that's part of normal
consciousness but we experience the world very differently in very deep meditation
and it's not meant to be a metaphysical uh statement or provide us with
philosophical truths about stuff it's just a nature of
experience and um if uh you're absorbed in reading a
good book or uh you be you could say you become one with it there you're it's all you're
just so fully in it that you're not you're not really this there's not the book is not the object the letters are
not the object out there you're in the story there's a unification with the
story in a sense so this kind of not holding
ourselves apart from anything not resisting anything not judging it not um
trying to make something happen that's different than what's happening uh a kind of a kind of becoming one a
kind of becoming I like I like the word whole quite a bit and uh a feeling of
subjective sense of wholeness where nothing is
excluded and so it's uh quieting the m mind enough that the activity of the
mind that objectifies the activity the thinking the way of the mind operates that has a
there and a here that has that and this that has me and
mine has you know my breath versus
um just being breathing my body is a objectification
of the body just being the body closer to just being it's all
subject now this is not something we have to do as an objective thing it's
something that we settle into we relax into as we get more and more absorbed
immersed centered settled in our present moment
experience centered here so this is the world that we swim
in in the second Janna and the world I use the word swim
intentionally because
floating is the metaphor for the second Janna
so to assume a meditation posture and
to gently close your
eyes and to give some care with your Eyes
closed to your posture not as an objective thing
from the mind thinking about what the good posture is but from a subjective sense of being
inside the posture to feel what would be
nice what would be a nice adjustment almost as if what does the
body want it might be very different than the
ideal the instructions you've had what posture does your body want to
have in order to be centered
alert in the meditation
the body in a sense wants to breathe will breathe without
your thinking about it directing it the body just breathes
can you now sense and
feel the way that the body wants to
breathe whatever way that
is putting aside ideals how it should
be just allow the breathing to breathe
itself in whatever way it happens to be
breathing and within the experience of
breathing what is it in that experiences those sensations
that wants to be known wants wants to be
felt what is it in breathing that reveals
itself to a mind which is present and clear
experiencing your breathing within the wider
field of your body body
sensations and is there anything in your body that wants to relax as you
exhale and don't do relaxing but let there be a open
allowing for relaxing or softening
and might there be somewhere in the body the experience
of breathing a center point for breathing
center of gravity the beginning point of the
inhale and in that center point of
breathing is there any feeling of calm however weak however
brief let yourself touch into the calmness of breathing
and as if the calmness of breathing is like a soft pillow for your
head allow your thinking mind to relax and settle
into whatever inner tranquility there
is no need to be
thinking the gift to the mind is to let the thinking mind rest
and together with a calmness that's
here might there be some experience of clarity
the clarity however brief however
small clarity of
awareness that's in between your thoughts beyond the edges of your
thoughts
may be at the center of your
mind that makes more room to receive experience the breathing
do I have this sense of yourself as the experiencer the
subject of objects of experience
is to hold yourself apart there's a little bit of work
effort in the mind to create the subject object
distinction that interferes with everything being
subject interferes with a oneness a unity a wholeness
and whatever sense of wholeness there might
be could it be permeated with tranquility with
calm
could the very atmosphere in which it exists be clear
and breathing intimately
part intimately continuous with calm
clarity and unity breathing
in and breathing out
relaxing the mind the thinking mind and relaxing into the
middle of your experience
becoming your experience of
breathing becoming the calm the clarity
like someone floating on the surface of a
lake forgetting all concerns and becoming one with the lake
unified in the floating relaxed tranquil clear
we can be floating in the middle of our
experience and be so absorbed in it so centered in
it on one hand we're not aware
of the world beyond our
body on the other
hand we're completely
open to the wider world
the experience of unity
wholeness where the boundaries of our body boundaries of our sense of self
dissolve so all things are included in our
hearts a heart which is relaxed
tranquil clear
whole
undisturbed radiating out warmth and kindness care and love
like a heater that's undisturbed by the cold
around it but which radiates out warmth out
into the wider world without
reservation without a boundary to that warmth
so may our kindness our love our compassion our heart's care for this
world radiate from us peacefully
calmly letting everything exist within a calm home
so that the deeper
non-anxious the deeper nonself
preoccupied attitudes of love and care and
goodwill can flow from us into the world
may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free and may we experience each of these things for ourselves
so that we can better wish it for others may all beings be
happy thank you
so so welcome to this third talk on the second
Janna and it takes a lot of settleness it
takes a lot of capacity to be at ease to have let go of so much of our
preoccupations and agitation takes so much healing and
settling to come into the wholeness that allows for the second
Janna and um and
so but one of the things that can get in the way of it is a mistrust of
it somehow a feeling that it's uh uh that if we drop into these deep states
of meditation that we won't it's a betrayal of the world around us we won't
um we won't be able to take care of this world others somehow we won't be able to
take care of ourselves and sometimes what happens is that people are quick to judge these
deep meditation states uh in a particular way and that is they
judge them as if this is the true way of being like once I go into this I have to
be this way all the time that somehow I tap into this I won't be able to
function in my ordinary life and so there's a resistance there's a reluctance there's a um fear that uh I
won't be able to you know be an acceptable person or a caring person or um responsible
person and this is um you know if that's the case it's a little
unfortunate and But what it helps to understand is that these are temporary states that are cleansing that clean us
that provide us a sense of deep sense of wholeness satisfaction peace
well-being and it isn't that we come back into the world with all the
qualities characteristics of this these deep states but we are we do come back uh
refreshed we do come back more connected more grounded more calm we do come back
more able to connect to people and to our responsibilities in a wise way in a
good way rather than being anxious rather than being uh ambitious or full
of our preoccupations and so it's not a betrayal of life to go into these deep
states um and any any any bit more than it's a betrayal of life to um you know
sit down to have a glass of water when you're thirsty when you're just drinking
water you are you know you're not talking you're not caring for someone else you're not doing other things for
people you're not uh taking care of your worldly
responsibilities you're allowed to sit there and just drink your water and doing so makes you so much better able
to engage in the world in a good way uh you know if we're parched uh you know
things don't go so well so um so so to be able to trust this
processes and when people finally come into the second Janna there's a kind of
confidence and trust in it partly because it just feels so right so good
and there's so little required from us in the first genre there's still something required from us this ongoing
movement of uh applying and sustaining the attention the needing the massaging
of attention and their experience and the breathing just be there come back stay
uh but in the second Janna that those kind of the intentional efforts to be
and stay to come back and stay here kind of the um it comes to a rest and um so
you you can you know if the analogy of the scooter makes sense for you that
I've used a few times you know in flat ground you might need to um you know
push on the scooter every once in a while to keep the momentum going on a push scooter but if
um and uh and you can and if it's a little bit of a slope you're going down
maybe you don't have to push uh kick off so often um but when the slope gets a
little bit steeper you don't have to push off anymore now we can just rest
and and keep yourself centered keep yourself focused on you know staying
going down the hill but you don't have to the legs don't have to work the legs can rest and both legs can be on the
platform of the scooter so in the second Janna we're kind of like in now we don't
have to make any effort anymore and so there's a deep feeling of ah I'm arrived
I'm at rest I'm just here and um and one of the uh
characteristics of this is a sense of unity or unification or wholeness
there's a variety of words that come into play with samadei that uh can mean
unification some people will say that even the word samadei means to gather together to unify uh eagata a word
that's sometimes translated as one pointedness um also can mean a a coming into one and
then this echo also has the word eka in it meaning one um many years ago I read
that it meant something like the the odi of ecody uh can mean to weave i love the idea of
weaving together weaving into one into a hole and um sometimes when I've
meditated I've imagined that the breathing are like is like the the warp and weft of a of a of a
weaving and uh and some is just gently with you know the weft i guess the weft
is the the the what puts puts go the the the warp I think um I used to weave but
I don't so long ago 50 years ago and so uh just I've imagined kind of
uh moving through the strings of the warp and and you know weaving things together with the breath and that's kept
me nicely engaged um because a sometimes a little bit of an image a little bit of a imagination of what adds a little bit
of kind of engagement or interest help me sometimes to get concentrated and
then some point I let go of the imagination because it's no longer needed for that
so weaving together into a hole and um so this quality of wholeness
uh I I I love the word wholeness more than uh unity or
unification um because uh um just somehow unity or unification seems a
little bit more complicated in my mind but wholeness just seems to hold all everything it's like you know there's
a it's all things included in a harmonious way it's all things have a
space everything no no outside and one of the things I've come
to appreciate as being for me one of the most sacred things is uh the awareness
that is whole the awareness that has no outside uh there's nothing which uh is
intentionally excluded or treated as unacceptable in the wholeness of
awareness and um and this inclusion of everything the good bad and the ugly is not a
condoning or approval of anything except the idea
that it's possible to hold everything in a tranquil clear and unified heart mind
and in doing so we're not making the situation worse
from the point of view of deep meditation to to start living in the world where
there's an an object and a subject you know that thought is
unacceptable I don't like that thought that thought has to go even like I have to let go of that thought all that is uh
the mind is activated it's oddly enough the the it's work for the mind to have
those thoughts in ordinary minds means it doesn't feel like work it just seems
like what's happened but in deep meditation we start seeing that that
kind of activity is a work or strain it has a kind of coarseness to it
it's kind of unsatisfying for the mind to be involved in kind of this making a subject and object distinction there's
something out there and and the alternative is um everything becomes
subject or everything becomes um some people would say everything becomes object and there's no subject um
but maybe these two things comes to the same
um and uh and so the um
um and so it allows the mind to become quieter and more settled all this so
there are these five different characteristics that are primary in the
second Janna there is uh a
calm and this now this calm is a calm that has no boundaries no edges it's
kind of it feels a little bit more like it it's the atmosphere there is a a clarity uh the
mind is clear the heart's clear there's a clarity within which all things are
occurring and there is inner clarity it's called and then there's a a oneness or a
wholeness or unity that uh is experienced with it all without this
subject object distinction those are the first three and then the last two which
we'll talk about a little bit more tomorrow is um uh the joy and happiness
born from concentration so even though there's not exactly a subject object there's still
in a way please forgive me there's the object of of uh concentration there's
the the center there's a place where the whole is centered on and if it's the
breathing which is the object then that's the um um that's the place where
um uh we're kind of um um the scooter is h or the or you
you're happily rolling down the slope and
there's a kind of a a thrill and a happiness contentment
uh a sense of happiness goodness uh with
being on that slope being in that space being with the breathing at the center
of all things and um so I know I'm contradicting with this word object
but I don't know how else to talk about it that in this state that there's all
subject and the the heart of the subject is the the center of the meditation the
centering place of the meditation um in uh in this case the offerings mostly
these days is the breathing itself but then with that can come this joy and
happiness this pity and suka sometimes rapture and bliss that can come on and
uh and that also that is part of this wholeness that's also kind of saturates
everything but it does it has a sense of movement to it especially the pity especially the the thrill or the joy way
it has a cleansing uh sense of being of um of movement or a
showering through us or a flowing through us or a tingling or a vibrating
or a sparking um or we can feel like waves moving through us in a nice way and um and
maybe with every breath there's kind of a wave it's kind of a rhythm of this great pleasure that can be there
and um so those are the five kata qualities that are mainly there in the
that highlighted in the second Janna so there's calm clarity unity joy and
happiness and that can't be too bad and um not only is it not too bad it's
actually quite healing it's uh provides a reconditioning to us that uh many of
us are conditioned growing up and through life with a lot of challenges and um and this is a very wholesome
conditioning that now that can can really shift things in a very very deep
way more than a lot of other ways that we try to change ourselves so to drop into this calm
clarity unity joy and happiness and allow it
to help us grow so thank you and um this afternoon
I'm driving up to the Spared Rock Meditation Center up in the countryside north of here and um I will uh do the uh
continue with the YouTube uh this uh 7:00 a.m from up there so you'll see me
sitting in a different place hopefully outside uh and um and that'll be the
through next Wednesday and um so I look forward to being with you from this wonderful
meditation center at Spirit Rock thank you