so we'll go ahead and get started all right welcome my name is May Elliot good morning good afternoon good
evening wherever you are in whatever time zone uh my name is May uh and today
we'll start with a simple meditation on the breath uh the idea is that we're
doing a practice that helps to settle and collect and stabilize the mind and
this this practice of settling and collecting the mind by focusing on a
simple object like the breath um it's a supportive condition for insight and
insight will be the focus of the teachings this week so uh go ahead and find a
comfortable posture I'll offer a very light instruction
today so maybe finding a position that is um both uh upright and relaxed
maybe connecting with three deep breaths
taking a moment to relax just soften the forehead and the
[Music] temples release the
jaw relaxing the shoulders
softening the
belly and allowing any extra tension to flow on out through the legs and the
feet
for the rest of the meditation I'll offer a guidance on following the breath if you know that the breath doesn't work
for you if there's a better Anchor for you maybe the soundscape or a global sense of the body
sitting uh feel free to do that instead and you can translate the instructions
for
yourself for those connecting to the
breath finding your home
base connecting with the breath where you feel it most easily most
predominantly maybe in the nose or the rise and fall of the
chest maybe in the belly
receiving the sensations of breathing
putting aside thoughts of the past or the future putting aside any judgments or
interpretations of what's Happening
Now and instead dropping into the felt sense of what's
Happening Now
and you feel the full length of an inhale and a full length of an
exhale
e
e e
settling and stabilizing [Music]
electing the mind which is so often
fragmented reecting and
settling
e
e e
you allow the breath to be in the foreground and anything that arises that
isn't the breath maybe a sound an
emotion a thought can you allow these to be in the background
keeping the breath in the
foreground
e
e e
receiving each breath remembering that each is [Music]
unique that this breath has never come before and won't come again
feeling the breaths from inside the
body
e
e e
though our primary focus is on the breathing here and there you might check
the attitude how are you relating to the
breath is there straining or striving
boredom
judgment if so can you invite kindness
and
curiosity can you invite an attitude of okayness with whatever is arising
remembering that we're not trying to make anything happen here just training in how to meet our
life more fully how to be more free in our
life this Begins by training the mind
training and being
here
e
e e
and for these last minutes seeing if you can maintain some continuity with the
breath almost like you're polishing the breath with your attention maintaining
contact with the
breath
e
e e
welcome again my name is May Elliot for those who are just
arriving and this series is coming to you from Insight Meditation Center uh if
you're someone who Tunes in fre L you probably know by now that what we're
doing here is often called Insight Meditation or vasana and the word vasana is a poly
word poly being the uh the original language the Buddha's teachings were
recorded in uh and the theana in vasana means to
see the V is an amplifier so Vasa could be translated as uh like really seeing
um but more commonly it's translated as clear seeing theana is translated as
clear seeing uh so this of course leads to a question what are we clearly seeing now
if this is called Insight Meditation what exactly are we having
insight into so this week uh we'll be answering these questions uh and more uh but by
discussing The Three core insights of the Buddha also known as the three
characteristics uh or the three marks uh and these three core insights they
include uh impermanence also known as
inconstancy uh suffering or unsatisfactoriness and lastly not self
so this week we'll spend a day exploring each of these um and we'll also talk about why
these insights are significant for our practice you why why do they matter um
and namely um they're important because they facilitate letting go um and this
Letting Go it releases craving and it frees us of the causes of suffering so
it's insight into the three characteristics that facilitates the end of suffering the end of
duka um and what we're letting go of by the way uh is our greed hatred and
delusion um when these these sources of suffering are released um then beautiful
qualities of mind can come forth um you qualities like kindness
compassion uh joy happiness patience equinity these sorts of states can arise
uh more easily so the Buddha said that um this freedom is available for all of
us um and he gave us practices to realize this possibility for
ourselves so this week we'll talk about um one of the practices for how to get there um and one of the ways we can put
uh conditions in place that support Insight that support Awakening so we'll talk about the ways that
samadi collected and stable mind can support Insight um and I just want to um rewind
for a second there because mentioned um putting supportive conditions in place
and this uh this point is of particular interest to me um because many of us
don't realize that our daily meditation practice is a condition for awakening as
a supportive condition for awakening um many of us have received meditation instruction um maybe to pay
attention to the breath how we did in our meditation today um but not everyone has an understanding of how uh how that
simple practice can lead to Insight uh it's not always clear how following the
breath can result in a heart and mind that's uh completely free from stress and discontent so during this series
we'll explore how uh this very simple practice of collecting and stabilizing
the Mind by following the breath provides an important condition for
insight um and in doing so my hope is to provide you with a like a mini Arc of
practice showing how our basic daily meditation practice when done more
intensively can open um can open into insight into the three characteristics
and how this Insight can facilitate Freedom um so I'd like to begin uh by
discussing what Insight is and how it functions um so to begin uh an Insight
is a non-conceptual experience of you're seeing uh sometimes people think about
an insight as being sort of an aha moment an aha moment um where it's like
oh like I'm really seeing the true nature of things like I'm I'm seeing the
way things really are um and this clear seeeing provides growth in
wisdom so many people associate Insight with like a flash of clarity almost like
a strike of lightning or something like that um and sure Insight can definitely
um come about as a distinct profound Moment of clarity um but it took quite a
while for me to learn that our insights into the three characteristics don't always happen like
that um and because most people associate Insight with a distinctive aha
moment um I'd like to offer another way that Insight can show up and this other
way it's a little quieter um a little less dramatic a little less obvious so
this less obvious form of insight uh comes simply through the way we're seeing the world Once the mind has
stabilized um Once the mind is more still and settled and collected so once
there's some concentration in the mind when some is present um so when uh the
mind is still uh for example uh it's easier to see arising and
passing um to see things coming and going so when the mind is stable we might just be able to see impermanence
um things are rising and passing over and over and over again so we might see you sights and sounds and smells and
tastes and emotions thoughts Etc all arising and passing arising and passing
um it's kind of like when we're wearing the lens of impermanence uh we begin to see the changing nature of everything
kind of like if we put on rose-colored glasses we'd start seeing everything
with a rose toonee um so if we see impermanence for long enough from the vantage point of a very steady stable
mind we begin to understand per impermanence much more deeply and it might not seem like a big aha moment um
we're just seeing things coming and going um but this begins to shift our understanding we're shifting from
perceiving phenomena as permanence permanent and fixed and changing to
being in flux uh and when we have the wisdom that everything changes we're
much less likely to cling to it we're much less likely to take refuge in it uh
we're much less likely to relate to it as uh I me or
M all to say um an Insight can be very obvious and traumatic but it doesn't
have to be it can be very uh subtle um it and it can R uh gradually
just simply through our way of seeing when uh the mind is
collected uh there's a quote from Suzuki roshi where he's he's talking about
progress in practice um he's not talking about Insight per se um but I think the
quote actually applies nicely to how Insight functions so uh he's talking about
progress on the path and he says um it's not like progress on the path it's not like going out in a shower as in like a
rain shower uh in which you know when you get wet in a fog you do not know
when you're getting wet but as you keep walking you get wet little by
little so sometimes um an Insight is like stepping out in a downpour and we
do have a dramatic experience of being soaked by insight and we very much know it when it happens but sometimes our
sites are a little more like walking in the Mist like walking in the fog um much
more subtle we're just seeing a rising and passing doesn't seem particularly special but over time it shifts our
understanding it doesn't feel like it's raining out um we don't know we're getting wet but if we're walking in the
Mist little by little the mind's being transformed um and over time if we walk
in the Mist long enough we're drenched so insights can happen in both ways um
both in more obvious ways and in more subtle ways where we might not even realize we're being
transformed so as we Embark in a few days of talking about these core insights of the Buddha um you don't need
to strain or strive to make something special happen um some people think if
they strive hard enough and insight will pop out or something like that so um uh
so don't do that to yourself um really efforting to make something happen
uh more often than not it can be aggravate aggravating and um and
disappointing and I don't want you to fall victim to this uh so I'd like to offer something that can help temper the
tendency to turn your meditation into a project sometimes when people learn about the three characteristics um their
meditation becomes a project and that's not so useful um so uh I'd like to say
something about conditionality um our our practice it has a lot to do with
putting certain conditions in place when the conditions are there then the path
of practice unfolds so the primary insights of Insight Meditation are
revealed when we put the appropriate conditions in place um and there are many conditions
that are supportive and I EMP emphasize this so it's clear that we can't force
Insight with our will uh we can't command it we can't muscle it to be here
um we're we're in a process with our practice we're in a process of allowing
the Dharma to grow in our heart um if we're growing a plant for example we
can't pull on the stem to make it grow faster instead what we can do is provide
supportive conditions for a plant to grow so if we're growing a plant supportive conditions are things like um
Sunshine water good soil and likewise in our meditation practice uh we can
provide supportive conditions like uh Faith uh contentment uh somat or
stability um and we can supply these conditions but we don't control when our
seeds germinate in the same way we don't control when Insight arises so Insight
it happens naturally on its own time uh when we put the appropriate conditions in place so tomorrow uh I'll be talking
about one of the primary conditions for insight uh the condition of stability or
somat and I'll also be talking about conditions that support somebody uh
itself uh so in addition to kind of exploring how to cultivate sombody or
concentration um we'll talk about how it functions to support clear seeing how it
how it functions to support Insight um so I hope this has given you a lay of
the land uh for what's to come and provided you with an introdu an
introduction to the topic of insight um I look forward to seeing you tomorrow
for an exploration of samadi have a wonderful day thank you for prioritizing
your practice and being here take care