good morning so um yeah
so this being this closest Sunday to Earth Day I thought it would be a good
day to celebrate it with a uh Earth talk day uh talk Earth Day talk
and um this is very kind of a topic that's very dear to me because of what I
feel is a very intimate and close connection to the earth to the natural
world that I kind of grew up with and continued to be part of in different parts of my life that it seems that um
who I am as a person is almost inseparable from what the earth is what
the natural world is and the representative Um this little story that I like for
that is when I was uh going to college at um Central Valley in California in
town of Davis uh they had some magnificent oak trees
in the courtyards of the campus uh old massive majestic oak trees and um
somehow they had survived from being cutting cutting down and I think there was a time when these massive great
majestic oak trees were spread out across the valley uh the earliest
records of Europeans coming to the peninsula which was uh Admiral Vancouver
in something like 1780 or something no yeah i think something like that uh he
describes that there was like an English park along from here right lit l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l l literally where we are with massive oak trees and
I think he came in the springs grasslands and and so in Davis on the campus they
have uh some of these big oak trees and I was studying botany I took a bot
class and uh in the beginning of that quarter they talked about the cycle
of oxygen and carbon dioxide and how it you We breathe out carbon dioxide the
the the trees breathe that in and convert it through to oxygen and that
the oxygen that we breathe is uh coming from the plants around us and
um and uh so I was quite absorbed in this whole can the
biochemical description of how this works on the big blackboard in the very big campus hall and so I got probably
got somewhat you know absorbed in that topic and mind got kind of quiet and uh the
class was over and I walked out and I was came into the courtyard
stunned as I stood there i kind of froze in my tracks and looked at uh these
majestic oak trees and the thoughts that went through my mind was I need these
trees to produce oxygen for me the plants not just the trees of course but
um more than I need both my kidneys more there's parts of my body I don't need as
much as some kind of thing outside of me that's producing the oxygen and um and so I had this question
where do I start where do where do I end where
does a tree start where does a tree end i mean where where who are we uh if I
need the tree more than I need my left hand kid left kidney or something where
do I begin where do I end what is this connection and and I remember my mind got so still and quiet and feeling of a
kind of vast kind of sacred uh space just being with this these
massive oak trees and um the uh now this is the third year I'm
going to do a pilgrimage uh in Marin County it's a walking pilgrimage tonight this time about 5 six
days we're going to leave the Spirit Rock Meditation Center and walk over the Marin Headlands over Mount Tam um and uh
some of the places we go uh have um have old growth forests old old
growth redwood forests and maybe you've been there we go to Mir Mir Woods early
in the morning before everyone comes and it's uh very very quiet there and peaceful and these trees are
magnificent and uh for me maybe for a fair amount of people get quiet being
there in those groves and in fact one of the groves is called a cathedral grove
so the sense of the sacredness the specialness of it and the reverence that's there and there's a kind of maybe
a kind of healthy humility that comes with being a human being in the presence of these massive ancient trees some of
them probably easily a thousand years old if not more and
um and um and it kind of for me it changes my
relationship with all these places of me and the world i feel like now I feel like I'm in a reverent relationship to
the natural world to the world i feel like uh I feel I don't feel like I'm
dominating someone who's going to dominate the world i feel I'm a small little member of this family of life on
this planet uh and feel a kind of uh I feel more alive in this humil
humbleness or reverence in the relationship to these groves than I do
uh watching Netflix surfing the web or something
working on my computer and um and uh and I' I've reflected one of these pilgrimages about
um the native people of that area when this there were a time before they were
logged things were cut down uh freeways put in that uh I think there were many
places that uh had this massive trees and redwoods and you know you walk along
the coast there it's spectacular the the marine coastline and
um and uh I'm sure that there was plenty of situations where there was a very
different relationship for who we are in relationship to the natural world by having it that way imagine I I've
imagined myself here on the peninsula before there were any uh of
these square buildings that uh we have here now and
what it would be what it would have been like walking 300 years ago 400 years ago
here in the peninsula and uh with these great massive oak trees there was one on
Pulgus one of the streets here nearby a massive old one and when the city
decided it it needed to be cut down because it was it was in danger of falling
um and it was relatively close to a school and you know falling on cars or whatever uh there was all these people
protested and they tried to stop it but they no success and uh so then they did
the uh the ceremony around the tree and all the see all these kids stuff that they put kids local neighborhood kids
came and kind of honored the tree and said goodbye to it and so this way in which our
relationship to the natural world can shift and change depending how we're in
touch with it what we live in it in it um and uh and how we participate in it
so this pilgrimage that we do it changes my relationship to the land by spending five days walking across it and um and
we walk usually in the morning in silence uh we do some ceremony as we go
along and um the um
um so the sense of be this greater humility um and then for me a kind of a
renewed promise I make to try to walk on this world gently try to walk on this
world without having such a big impact on it the Buddha when he was
enlightened before he was enlightened um and we have in the statue we have the
statue depicts the moment if you see his uh right hand drapes over his knee and
it's him reaching forward to touch the earth and uh the
the as was the custom back then but in what had now for me becomes a
phenomenally powerful symbolic value the Buddha uh
the stories say was born under a tree outdoors he was enlightened outdoors
under a tree his first teachings were done outdoors under a tree he died
outdoors laying on the ground between two trees they say the trees were flowering so it was kind of a special
time and uh and on the on the night of his
awakening um they say that this kind of
particular evil trickster kind of character showed up called Mara to try
to prevent him from becoming enlightened and uh and and came to him and said you
don't deserve to be enlightened who do you think you are to do that i mean isn't this you know you know you you're
not worthy of this and um and so the Buddha did didn't reply directly exactly but what he did
was he uh he put his hand and touched at the earth the earth touching gesture and
called upon the earth to be his witness for his right to be awakened to be free
to be free now no longer caught in the in the traps that Mara the tempter uh uh
was setting up to trap him in and uh the primary thing that Mara how traps people
is with sensual desires occasionally probably you've been caught by
that and so the you know so he so but and and he the last thing Mara wants is
someone who escapes his his realm of sensual desire so he
really wanted to stop the Buddha and so the Buddha touched the earth and they they say the earth then had uh
shook bearing witness of all the compassionate things the Buddha had done
through his many lifetimes all his practices he done that yes he was worthy
of it and um and I love this that uh we
call on nature for to witness we call on the earth um to be our
witness so if you're meditating or if you're walking on the earth what does
the earth what what can the earth earth be a witness for you what does the earth
say about you what is it there to show you about
yourself and uh and I'll leave that question now for now to hanging
there um the
um um but one of the things is that
um we live on the earth and it's so easy to forget it
we live with the earth and in the case of the Buddha touching the earth it was
rep they had this idea that there was the earth goddess so mother earth some people like
to say historically they nowadays may be the parent earth but this kind of parental the source of life that the
earth has been for all of us and um it wasn't so many years
ago in the scale of time that apparently there was no life
on this earth there's been more period of time with no life on this earth than there has been life on this earth
so
um and then if we think about how long humans have been on this earth it's much
shorter period of time and I've read I don't know I don't know the latest research on this but uh I read some time
ago some idea when they do genetic testings of human beings and now they
can kind of look back in time through the genetic evidence that
survives they think that all humans are descended from a small group of people
tribe there were probably just a few hundred large somewhere on the plains of
Africa at some time a few thousand 100 thousand years
ago or something and I love this idea that we have we all have common
ancestors it makes us all kin it makes us all family and to call on that that we're
all family in some ways we all have shared ancestors if we could trace it
back we would be able to all walk up maybe to the same little group of people and say
"Hi I'm the result of what you started thank
you for my life." And we'd all kind of be gathering around the same group of people to thank them
maybe there's a story that's told in the Jatica tales that also goes back many
many millennia thousands hundred thousand millions of years billions of years
uh which tells stories of the Buddha in his previous life before he was the Buddha and some of these are like uh
Asop's fables and the fable here is that of the the Buddha was a um deer he was
the king of a of a herd of deer very large herd of deer and he was called the
banyan uh king the banyan deer banyan
being the buddhi tree and um and the story goes that
there was a new king in the land and this king loved to hunt and so he took a
um the royal forest very large forest that had lots and lots of her herds of
deer and uh he put a large fence around all of it to keep them all there and
then once a day he wanted to go hunting he wanted to kill one one deer a day so
he could have food and so he can kind of enjoy his sport of
hunting but his hunting that way uh he would come with his entourage and
soldiers and elephants and it was a big to-do when he came hunting and the deer
would get afraid and they would start rushing often all this way and that way
to get away but they were trapped inside this large area and so that made them
panic even more and so he was successful in you know killing one deer a day but a
lot of deer got injured in the process us they would trip over each other trip
over logs they you know those who had antlers would run into people others you
know stab them and things so it was kind of a mess and so one day the king of the
banyan after the the king had hunted one of the deer went up to the king and said
"Excuse me sir uh you have to realize what you're doing here you're injuring a lot of the
deer you're harming them there more are dying than need to die because the way you're doing this hunting and I'm here
to ask you to please try to to do an act of harm reduction and um he wasn't asking him to
not kill because maybe that was asking too much but uh
as intermediate was to ask for harm reduction and the harm reduction was um
we will provide you with uh we'll have a lot we'll have uh what was it called um
we'll we'll we'll choose someone to have a lottery or what call you know where um
not a lottery but what do you call when you pull pull uh straw
and what choose letter choosing lots yeah yeah anybody see who
you know would has to uh present themselves to the king to be killed every day and that'll create uh won't
create all this other harm the people running and trying to chase the runaway and so that's what they did and
these uh you know compassionate deer who wanted to
prevent uh so much harm being done were willing to sacrifice their lives to for the greater good in a sense
then one day uh it came upon a pregnant dough to be the one to offer herself her
sacrifice but she was pregnant so she went to the king and said "Please can I not do it until after my dough is
born." And uh but the king said "Well I can't really ask someone else to do it
in yourstead but uh don't worry don't you don't have to do it." And so the
when the when the king came to hunt that day the king offered
himself as in order to save the the dough and the
pregnant child and uh but the king uh that the deer the king deer was kind of
very majestic very you know had a strong presence and stood there in all his
dignity ready to be killed but this got the king's attention
and the king said "I can't kill another king you know in this kind
of majesty." And so he said "What are you doing here?" Right and u and the
deer said to the king the story about the the pregnant dough and that he was
taking her place so to save the dough and the child and the king was so moved by the
compassion the care and the sacrifice that the deer king was willing to make
that he was this changed his heart dramatically and he said "Okay from now
on I'm going to stop killing any of the deer." And the king deer said "Dear king
that's not enough can you make a vow not to kill any
animals and the king said yes so in that realm from then on no animals were ever
killed so it's a fable and um the
um and it said or I'll say that when the moment the
king said promised yes he would no longer kill any animals that's when the
forest started to heal itself we've harmed so many places in
our world in the natural world when are they going to heal some of them maybe never will
heal i was uh when I was in high school I went to hear a talk by Richard Leaky
some of you might remember him uh he was one of the first not first but a really important anthropologist of ancient
humans and I think he was the found was found at the time remains of the oldest human uh in Africa the skull of an
oldest human and so that was a big deal so he knew a lot about you know how
evolution and you know and he in this big auditorium explained that what he
had seen is that a species that oversp
specialcialize die out and he used the example of some like great uh like um
um what do they call those um those elephants with big tusks that no longer
mammoth woolly mammoths they apparently they their tusks got so big they couldn't function very well anymore
defend themselves very well and so um then they were easy to hunt and so they
died out because they over specialized this big so he was saying that back this was 1960s late60s that if we over
specialized as humans that we were going to have the same fate but in some ways we already have we've had civilizations
come and go over the millennia and I saw some of that uh growing up in Europe i
grew up a little one of the places I grew up was in the Adriatic coast and um
and in you know my eyes there were some really beautiful islands that uh we would visit and go vacation
on uh we would go sailing sometimes along these islands and part of their
beauty was their starkness uh of just being rock just these but
they weren't always just rock they were had been a time when they were filled
with olive and grape orchards and uh you could still find
back then in the 60s if we went diving into the water uh in these little bays you could find um uh clay vases that had
fallen over the boats and and uh find a lot of pottery shards left over from that time and when they came the ships
came the Roman ships came to get the olives and the grapes or the grape juice whatever they made
wine and uh and then they overfarmed and uh all the soil washed
away and the islands can no longer uh bear a lot of vegetation because all the
soil walked away and so the people who were surviving and lived off the land had to move because they could no longer
survive and that's happened to whole civilizations in Mesopotamia where they over farmed overused the water and then
um um you know the civilization collapsed so it's what Richard Leaky said if you over specialize do too much
things collapse and um I grew up partly also in Los Angeles in the 60s and uh I remember
still very well the amazing amount of smog that LA used to have back then and
we would get sore throats just by breathing the air back then and uh runny eyes and remember
sometimes flying back to Los Angeles from being in Europe and going out of
the airplane and the smell of this thick smog was quite
something and um and
uh the direction it was going i don't know if anybody would have survived in Los Angeles but that's one of the good
relatively good stories of uh of cleaning the air and um the catalyst
catalytic converters all kinds of things happened that cleaned up the air enough so it's not as bad as it used to be i
don't think people get sore throats anymore in LA from the smug
so um what kind of harm reduction do we we
do we in do we do can we do are we the king who goes around killing the
metaphoric deer by how we live in our lives how much dies how much is killed
how much is killed uh and destroyed inadvertently by the lifestyles that we
have and how many you know there's a spill over what's the equivalent of of
uh the king hunting and um and then the secondary effect of all the other deer
dying what happens to us what do we do here what are we
destroying the um so one of the uh kind of dramatic
I think very clear teachings of the Buddha is that he distinguished between
the natural world and he didn't use this word but the synthetic world world he
made a very strong distinction between the natural world and the humanly
constructed world uh what we can build and make and think
that doesn't exist in the natural world itself it's not natural in the sense
that um uh it doesn't not produced by the natural world and it doesn't have
the na doesn't participate in the natural process of regeneration of
self-healing doesn't selfreplication and um and I saw that
when I went to spirit rock last week a little bit representing of it for me was
uh so great to be at spirit rock this meditation center in Marin County It's designed to be outdoors between
anytime you go between different buildings there and uh you really feel like you're part of on the land in a
nice way and uh I've been there going there for over 35 years now be even
before there were any buildings there and in about
1993 the person who started IMC before I got involved in IMC a man named Howard
Noodleman who started it him and his wife Ingred in
1986 in Menllo Park and then when I got here was had moved to Palo
Alto uh he died and so to and he had been president of the Spirit Rock board
and so when he died we we went and bought uh three oak trees and planted
them uh near Sir Francis Boulevard as you go into Spirit Rock uh in his honor
well those three trees are still there and they're just look like they're more grand every year I go to Spirit Rock
they're growing developing and and now they've been you know over 30 years they've been growing
there in 1998 they opened the medit the big
residential meditation home which uh you know 27 years ago was
shiny new i remember what it was like i was like "Wow
this time when I was there I looked around wow it's aging it's beginning to
rot the wood in the side of the building and rust here and there and you know
this is not going to this is not going to last so well for another 27 years but
those trees are doing just great
we build things that uh that don't exist in the natural world and not don't participate
in the natural process of life because they don't replicate they don't reproduce they don't they're not and
some of those things that we create that are not natural the synthetic things uh
cause a lot of harm and so now we have all these microplastics that are we're finding
deeply embedded in um you know in our body in our brain that end up and I
think I read this last couple of days that they're finding something microp in the fallopial tubes it's not going to be
long before we find microplastics in the embryos is that what we want to have in our
life and um so we have to be very careful about the synthetic world that
we're creating and for forever chemicals so the Buddha had this he
didn't know about all the things that we create synthetically now but he made a made a very clear distinction between
what's constructed and in his mind it was really the things we construct in the mind that don't exist in the natural
world a lot of the concepts ideas and that we live in ideas about me myself
and mine uh greed hate and delusion um
that we construct on that these constructions these ideas these worlds that we move into that we our fantasies
create can create so much harm and um and the Buddha wanted to
kept pointing us back to the natural world in ourselves and he used metaphors
of the natural world outside to as a representation of how the natural world
works so we can find it in ourselves and uh and I think the most
dramatic uh use of this kinds of metaphors that uh using part of the
natural world that's in us to represent the natural world that's in us you know in terms of spiritual practice in life
was um he referred to something which uh um something profound within us that
arises from something that he called the yo the yoni yoni is the source of life
for humans it means the womb the the profound attention profound
contemplation the profound engagement with life that's womblike coming from
this deep place within it's a generative place the Buddha talked about spiritual life is a
life we're growing and um and I want to
um say something i've said that a few times
um we um
uh in in uh English Buddhism we use the word practice a lot to describe what we
do we practice meditation for example and a lot of people who practice meditation so the common question in the
Buddhist circles in the west is what is your practice and then people usually reply
with a technique i practice mindfulness i practice loving kindness i practice
zen i practice this and that um and that's nice but it's usually describing
it by technique the ancient from the time of the Buddha the equivalent word to the
word practice that kind of fits in the same kind of context um that word um
what it it means is um uh to grow to cultivate to develop something
but it can mean to grow so what happens if you were asked not what you pra what
are you practicing but instead you're asked what are you growing what would you answer
then if you say what you're practicing I think there's easy to say well I'm practicing something else you're
practicing that I'm practicing this and I'm practicing the better thing but what are you
growing now we're talking about the natural world within and uh and something we all have
we all have inner growth we all have this natural world inside that can grow we all are
nature it's hard to imagine that they'll ever have a human being who's not born in a
womb will they ever be able to incubate or gestate a in a lab a human being is
that possible i hope not it's amazing what's what our natural
world is like that which is in it within us the natural world within us that can
think that can feel that can heal to some degree that can replicate all kinds
of things that arose out of this earth came from this
earth that is part of the earth's natural processes we're sharing this in a profound
way that makes us kin makes us family with all life on this planet
um that uh it's not just
like you know the earth is all the things we see in the natural world are not just
decoration for our pleasure it's participating it's a
participatory natural world that we participate in it participates in us it
provides us with oxygen it provides us with food provides us with so much in order to be able to alive we need the
natural world and we then our naturalenness has
a chance to grow and and for the Buddha we have to t
we're learning to tap into to support to generate to care for to preserve the
natural world in ourselves so we don't get caught up in the constructed synthetic
world that uh humans have been very clever in creating over these last
centuries the the Buddha also saw the constructed world of ideas of
self and um ideas of status ideas of
dominance ideas of right and wrong and good and bad that
there is they're causing so much harm in this world
um so the idea we're all kin we all belong to this
world and um and what
the and what the redwood trees remember what the deer
remember we're just we need to re-reme remember re-remember reconnect to that
how much we're part of this natural world how the earth cares for us and if the earth cares for us
shouldn't we care for it should we can we walk on this world
lightly and what would that look like at least in terms of harm
reduction the idea of stopping causing harm might not be natural
just as I saw a um there's a at Spirit Rock last week
there's a a white egret has kind of taken up residence at Spirit Rock and
now it doesn't seem to be very afraid of people you can't get too close but you can get 10 feet away from it and it's
been there for about a year and so it's kind of cool to see this white secret they named it
pole and um but one day I was standing 10 ft away and it was doing what it does
and and uh suddenly it just kind of snapped at the ground and in its in its
bill was a lizard that had it caught and I was told there's very few lizards around Spirit Rock right now because of
this this one egret and on one hand at first I thought
"Wow this is like an amazing natural thing to watch." But then I thought about the
lizard and I felt for the lizard but you know some of that it's not going to stop
that's going to continue but can we at least do harm harm reduction for ourselves
um so we don't hold ourselves above nature that we are
nature may we be like the king of the deer may our compassion spread out into
the world so that we everyone is cared for everyone's respected and valued
may we have forests that are sanctuaries cathedrals sacred places
that we go there to to remember who we are in some deep way that we can't
remember so well so easily on the freeways in the Bay
Area in rush hour traffic
and perhaps this earth is not something to be saved maybe it's something to come home
to and if we come home to it and live with it as our home then maybe it will
save us
the natural process of this natural world the regeneration the self-healing
of the natural world has the ability to heal us save
us if we allow it to if we connect to it in such a
way and the earth I think will always continue maybe you know life as we know
it will be radically different maybe the human race will
disappear but for a long you know the earth will be here life will probably be here in some
form or other so we're capable
but it looks like we're we know now and since the 20th century that we're quite capable of destroying this world as we
know it and if we do that we destroy
ourselves but if we say but if we come home to this world and touch the earth let the earth be the
witness to our own naturalness maybe the earth will save us
that's my hope on this Earth care week
2025 so thank you and uh we have a few minutes maybe we can take five minutes
if anyone have any comments or questions you'd like to ask and
Maybe that means you're all eager to go out to the Edgewood Park
or go out for you know walk on the trails here in the peninsula that would be nice to
believe oh yeah morgan
I think so down uh hi my name is Morgan and I wanted to
just mention that there is a a cemetery in Santa Cruz that uh for ecology they
they sell the redwood trees for burial and so if you have loved ones that you
want to have a family tree you can buy a tree and you can bury them in the
redwoods in Santa Cruz and it'll be there for as long as redwoods last great
thank you it's a beautiful uh I didn't call better a better forest that's what it's called yeah thank you i didn't know
there was such a thing in Santa Cruz but there's a number of places now that have green burials where sometimes they plant
trees as part of it and and um and we're going to maybe walk by it when we do the
pilgrimage this year it's in Tennessee Valley in Marine County
there so thank you may you love this earth