okay so why don't we go ahead and start as people are continuing to
trickle in and I while people were arriving I
commented on how long it's been somebody wrote it's been since April 2020 so
that's right around the beginning of the pandemic i think it's nice now and then to
reflect on the value of connecting with other people in our practice and the
support that we gain from meditating together in a group even if we're not
physically in the same room i think for some that's been a real discovery maybe
some weren't surprised by that the dharma doesn't really have a place and a time but nonetheless it does
matter so carrying that with us let's begin our
meditation together closing the eyes if that's comfortable
for you and finding a posture for sitting or you could be lying down or
standing
maybe taking a long slow deep breath
and on the outreath just softening in a bit to the position
that you're in whatever posture your body feels is good for you today for
this sit
and inviting some ease in the body which is always possible even if there's
pain or illness we can invite just a sense of being at
home so perhaps
bringing attention into the face and just softening the expression on the
face softening the eyes and the eye sockets
sensing into the head area and just inviting some
calming some easing any thinking that might be going on
not that there's anything wrong with thinking but just making it softer
down through the jaw and the neck
bringing some attention to the shoulder area maybe letting the shoulder blades slide
down the back
releasing the arms
letting the chest area and all the way down into the belly
just letting that be itself
how we do this right now
softening the low back area
sensing where the hips and seat are resting
you're in the sitting posture and then down through the legs softening
any bracing that might be there
in a way we're just trusting the body to be as it is
by touching it with the attention we let it know that we're here
we see it
and that begins to bring into the mind the simple awareness that we call
mindfulness
knowing things clearly without demanding that they be a certain
way
knowing them as they are
and then for the process of meditation it is helpful to
intentionally choose something to orient around often people use the breath
but if that isn't so right for you you can use body sensations or sounds
these are present moment objects
and I find that when I use the breath for example
it's kind of just a touchstone and I can still sense the flow of thoughts
emotions [Music] i do still hear sounds
but I'm breathing along with all of those things
mindfulness isn't really exclusive
but it is a way of orienting so we're not just following anything that happens
so the invitation the invitation in this sit
is to have a simple intention of being simple is that when the mind
gets complicated It gets lost in its thoughts or
fantasies memories and we notice that we simply return
and the support for that also an invitation is to bring in a brief acknowledgement
that we are all doing this together there are actually hundreds of people
around the globe doing this sit
so without adding any complexity just remembering
that we're doing this together and see how that goes with simple mindfulness
gently present with our own experience
and yet a small part of awareness attuned to
being part of this larger group
how does that feel as we continue to stay with the flow of our own experience
the instructions for mindfulness meditation are actually quite simple
and they've worked for countless people
over millennia
we are not an exception to this rule
these lines are from the dharmapata
think not lightly of good saying it will not come to me
drop by drop is the water pot filled
likewise the wise one gathering it little by little
fills oneself with good
breath by breath moment by moment
the mind gathers goodness clarity
strength from doing this practice that so many have done and so many are doing
together right now
[Music]
and moving toward the end of our sit together
we can begin to bring the mind
toward thinking about our life out in the world
and really there it's the same mind
we can continue with the simple trust in
mindfulness and wholesomeness
this kind of trust is not about blindly following instructions or rules or
creating algorithms that might not be so wise
but we know that we can trust in the eight-fold path because we've seen for
oursel that it's beneficial
to whatever degree you've practiced and everyone here has now practiced at
least 30 minutes of mindfulness
we can see that there's something beneficial there that's the basis
for trusting in mindfulness and wholesomeness
so that means doing actions like wise speech
living in mindfully having intentions of harmlessness
and appropriate kinds of letting go as a way of being in the world
we may find then that by knowing just internally knowing that we have a path
we can relax a bit as we go through our life in the world
we don't always know what to do or how to deal with certain things but we have
a path it'll be good to approach with
mindfulness and wholesomeness and that's enough
and even that small amount of ease that we have from knowing internally that we have a path
can support others they can feel our own ease and that helps them too
so may it be that we walk through the world clearly knowing
that mindfulness and wholesomeness are beneficial for all
[Music]
so this week we are using animal simileies to discuss the journey
that the mind takes from not being wise to being wiser or even free
and there's a dharma instruction in each of these cases that comes forth as we use
each of these animals so with the quail it was about getting to safety you know
if you stray into mindlessness come back to the body or the feeling
tone or the mood of the mind or some aspect of the dharma you know just
coming back to the present and then with the monkey yesterday there
was a little bit more so monkeys also stray out of mindfulness but then we were also asked to notice
the various patterns that are taking the mind into distraction so monkey mind as
it's called is to be investigated to understand how it is that we get caught
up so that's the beginning of insight practice and then once the mind is protected by
mindfulness and has a sense of how to investigate its own activity we could say that we're engaged in what
this tradition calls crossing the flood it means that we're learning to navigate
this mind and body while living our life here with other people in the flood is
kind of a word for distractions like greed hatred and delusion and other
challenges that come into the mind wanting to have certain identities
wanting to grasp on to things those are all the floods that can overwhelm us but
once we have the tools we can begin to cross over that uh toward having some
freedom from these forces in our mind and sometimes freedom is called the
other shore you know as if we're we're going to that place
although it's not really a place it's right here but today for our animal we are moving
on to the cow now there are a lot of cows in the sutas
it was an agricultural society at the time of the Buddha so everybody knew about cows if you said cow everybody had
a an image of what that was it may be less obvious for us but I think I think
you'll get the point um there so there's a wide range of cow analogies but the
majority are in the realm that we're going to talk about today so cows are herd animals and they tend
to follow a leader and this is actually an important aspect of our path
there's a suta about cows crossing a river under the guidance of a cow herd
and in the suta the Buddha first talks about the cow herd so in in one case
there's an unwise cow herd who doesn't look carefully to understand the
nearshore and the far shore and then she drives her cows across the Ganges River
where there isn't a ford so there's kind of no understanding of what's going on
and this doesn't turn out very well for the cows but then there's a wise cow herd who
understands both the nearshore and the far shore and drives her cows across the
river at a place that has a ford and so she's also further wise about which cows
can swim better than others and she chooses to send them across in a wise
order so uh first the cow herd drives across the
the bulls um the kind of strong leaders of the of
the herd and it says in the suta they breasted the stream of the Ganges and
safely reached the far shore so you imagine these bulls having no trouble
crossing a river and then after that she drives across the what are called the
strong intractable cows and they too breast the stream of the Ganges and
safely reach the far shore and then she drives across the bulocks and the heers
the younger cows and they all breast the stream and reach the far shore and then
finally the calves and the weak cattle the ones maybe who are sick or otherwise
weakened and they too can get across and get safely to the far shore and then it
adds this little line that said "Once it happened that a baby calf had just been
born urged on by its mother's loing even it managed to breast the stream of the
Ganges and safely reach the far shore." So it's a nice image of these cows and
then there's a you know an analogy created so the bulls are likened to
arahants to people who are fully awakened and then the other groups of cows are likened to people who are not
fully awakened but do have various degrees of wisdom so this is a smart way
to do it right so that when the smaller or the weaker or younger cows see the
other ones before them getting across the river and reaching the far shore safely they feel confident in entering
the river also so some cows are not very strong swimmers but even they can get across
even the tiny calf is inspired when cheered on by the loing of its mother
so I like to say that what we see here is the value of having a teacher on our
path and having real guidance you know having good meditation instructions and
also having some kind of a group that we're working with like a SA we do need
this in some way along our path you know that might be being with a literal
in-person group but not everybody has that it can also be an online group like
this one for example or it could be taking guidance from a teacher in some other way but somehow getting um clear
instructions and a sense that we're uh doing this in line with the tradition
and in line with other people it helps a lot and then the Buddha is likened to
the cow herd so he claims to fully understand the human condition that's the nearshore and the farshore and also
to know that there is a ford so he knows that the teachings he's offering really
will work and that we you know we can get across the river of difficulties in
our life and in our mind if we do mindfulness practice and follow the various kinds of instructions that are
found in the Buddhist teachings there are also lots of sudas that use this image of crossing the flood uh to
talk about the journey to freedom so it isn't just this one with the cows and we can even do all of this now in
this modern world where we don't have a living Buddha notice that the cows were
following the stronger cows uh it's good enough to watch older dharma students
and to listen to a modern-day dharma teacher by whom you feel inspired like
the calf listening to its mother for example i remember uh when I went on my first
residential retreat it was it was a nine night retreat and I had only done a
dayong before that that was the longest I had ever meditated and I was going on this nine- night retreat and it was very
helpful for me when I was there to see the more experienced practitioners
what were they doing sitting walking sitting walking following the schedule
sitting still in the hall and so I just did that too i figured that was what you
did on retreat and it worked great and I fell in love with retreats right away
so yeah I was listening to the dharma talks and instructions also of course but the teachers aren't in the hall all
the time so it was really important that I could watch people who had been on
more retreats than me so maybe it's worth some time of
reflection what is your inspiration what keeps you going are there ways in which
you have observed others and gained confidence on the path in some way
and it's also worth pointing out that this is not a static process if that
makes sense um if we want to get all the way across the
river and not say stop in the middle we're going to need to move forward in
some appropriate way so for example if you started meditation
by listening to guided meditations that is great and it's great for a while it
may keep you on the cushion it keeps your mind coming back to have prompts coming uh through your ears but at some
point it's also important to learn how to guide yourself in meditation and not
have to listen to a guided meditation or if you like listening to dharma talks
that's great i listen to dharma talks from time to time but also you may want
to try some study to directly learn the teachings um this has effects at levels
that we can't even see to study the sutas or to learn the structure of the
of the dharma if you have a regular sitting practice where you find you know a time to sit
every day that's really great that's not easy for everyone to do but then how
about trying a dayong you know set aside a whole day where all you do is sit and
walk and listen to the dharma and probably eventually uh most of us
will benefit from some kind of extended retreat time if we're able to manage
that get the conditions in our life that can take longer to arrange but you know keep keep going keep going
across the river keep looking to those who are farther along and at the same
time keep listening to that within you that wants to cross the flood
sometimes and maybe eventually more and more of the time the guidance that we
take the cow herd and even the other cows seem to come from inside as well as
outside this is again a a way of talking
about our ongoing insight journey so in the cow I see an element of
humility we do need help crossing um that's not about self-deprecation or
making ourselves small that's different from from real humility in a sense
it's just the reality that we won't go as far on our path if we try to walk
completely alone so I have a certain fondness for the the
humble cow and um maybe we could say that the cow
is about sa and trust in just continuing
the work of going step by step across the river and we can do it we can cross
this blood so continuing on we'll have another animal
tomorrow and thank you very much be well