so continuing with this series on
Samar so one of the important approaches to meditation has a
lot to do with how you approach meditation how you approach how
you utilize your capacity for attention for
for awareness and for
mindfulness for knowing what's happening in the present moment for feeling what is happening in
the moment for observing what's happening in the moment and I use all these words not
to confuse you with too much to do but for you to appreciate that we have these
different attentional capacities and different people are oriented towards different
ones and they're all good they're all useful for helping us be here in the
present moment but how we engage it is
important the idea is not to engage it with
strain not to engage it with uh
uh pushing or force
or expectation or strong desire for something to happen or not to be
there there's a a lightess of being and if we if you're willing to go
along with kind of this almost a metaphor that our ability to be
aware has no weight the ability to have to hear a
sound the hearing has no weight to see with your eyes the seeing
has no weight the cognitive capacity to Simply know
and recognize what's happening has no weight some of it can occur
without even any intention any wanting to do it
so much of the attention we have that's operating through the day happens without
self-referencing without trying and there's plenty of trying to
be aware strain there's a straining of the eyes to stare at
something there straining to hear straining to understand straining to be
mindful and uh um there can be a lot of willpower involved or
self and the idea is to feel your way into
Where Your Capacity your way of being
aware can return to where it has no weight where it's almost like the weight
of air or the weight of a butterfly that lands on
a flower where you almost are not doing
it but rather you're allowing
it almost like you're holding your hand open so the butterfly can
land or you're pulling the curtains so that your eyes can see what's outside
without needing to look so this simple light way of being
aware and then but there is a kind of deliberateness there is a kind of a
devotion maybe for some people it could be called play for some people it could be called
a loving commitment for some people maybe it's a
a preference and I like to call it an orientation we Orient
ourselves to something which is the primary home for
awareness maybe we can call it the nest if awareness is a very light
[Music] bird that can float on the
updrafts the bird keeps returning to its nest and maybe at night gets cozy there
doesn't leave and so breathing can be that Nest
The Body Sensations of breathing may be in the resting place
the nesting Place deep inside so there's a preference to stay there and so
exactly how much how that how to sustain that
through time without any tension is the art but there's a
sustaining entering into the nest staying there so for this meditation I'd like to
propose this idea of applied and sustained attention vaka and
vichara be used in the cycle of
breathing that when the in inhale begins you you connect apply you the
butterfly lands on the flower of breathing or you settle into the
nest of bre of the body sensation of breathing in the resting spot the
grounding spot where it's all
rooted and then stay lightly
softly ride the inhale stay all the way through the
exhale sustain without
tension without pressure but really stay there Orient
yourself organize yourself to be right
there there's a settle settling and then do it
again with the inhale begin and Ride The
Wave in next inhale connect and be maybe like
a like a butterfly
that's Gathering the the nectar from the [Music]
flower throughout the breath and then it goes to the next flower for the next
beginning of the inhale so to assume a meditation
posture and gently closing your
eyes maybe so the eyelids are soft and relax floating over
the curve of the eyes and the eyeballs are resting in
their sockets maybe imagining your eyes are
looking backwards and down not not looking out words at
all the eyes take a rest from
looking and no matter
how much weight you feel in your body is there a place where the you feel
lightness in your body
maybe the lightness of your
fingers maybe some lightness somewhere in the Torso
softness then as you exhale to relax into the the base of
your breathing
body maybe softening your belly as you do
so as you exhale without trying a lot just almost
like you're allowing it to happen and as you exhale let there be a softening through
your body not an ambitious
relaxing just a almost like letting the body
soften together with any tension and holding there might be it's all okay
with the exhale maybe a wave of calmness through the mind and
body a wave of calmness through whatever is not come it's
okay and then at the end of the exhale maybe deep in the Torso wherever
You' come to the grounding place the settling place of
breathing at the end of the exhale pause for half a
moment to allow room for relaxing
settling as settling around around the end of the
exhale and then with the lightest possible
way connect to the inhale as it
begins and sustain the
attention continuously through the full
inhale and riding the exhale all the way to the end
we're connecting and sustaining the
attention it's not so much happening in the control
tower but it's a very very nature
very working of the body breathing
itself breathing feeling itself the breathing body
experiencing the lightness of
attention breathing in and breathing
out
e
for for
and as you feel the inhales and exhales as you know
it as you sustain attention if there's
any Pleasant Sensations pleasure
in the breathing in the sensations of breathing in and breathing
out let that be the nectar of
sweetness that you feel and sense that you take
in
for
e
e e
the weight of a awareness
resting on the sensations of
breathing and as you
exhale letting the thinking mind become
quieter so there's space in the
mind to share with a pleasure of
breathing
e
for
e e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate or
feel whatever way awareness attention
has no weight has no strain in
it a sound arises and it's no effort to hear
it some Sensations arise in the body and there's no
effort for it to be known
some thoughts arise and maybe it's effortless to know
the thought is there there might be added strain or
reaction but in the beginning it's just effortless
light and to stay in the lightess of
awareness to stay stay close to the lightess of
being and to then open your awareness open your
imagination to the world that you'll encounter after the
meditation maybe locally the room you're in the building you're in the
neighborhood
and to understand that it's a gift you give to the world around
you the gift of the lightness of your being the lightness of
awareness that knows what's happening without reactivity without
tension without an automatic call to
action giving room to All
Things allowing each person the space to be who they
are so perhaps your response to the world can
come from a deeper
place where love
kindness can arise with the same lightness as a lightness of
awareness may we enter the world
offering it the gift of a light awareness a light
kindness the lightness of Good Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may the lightess of our our awareness give space give room give
time for others to be happy
safe peaceful and free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this now 30 second talk on samadi
and um this week the orientation is a little
bit of a review and part of the way of presenting this is that uh
when you're practicing meditation especially samade but
anything it's really valuable to always think of yourself as starting over as a
beginner don't come with a lot of expectations that you know what to do you know how to meditate and you're
going to just sit down and do your thing uh it better not come with any expectations of and maybe realize that
we're often just beginning again and that we're all beginners and sometimes uh it's the
beginning steps of meditation that we have to repeat over and over again and
it's invaluable to do that uh we're actually transforming ourselves changing
ourselves in the background by just starting over and over again it's like getting a massage something's being
worked and relaxing and opening and uh and learn to be
gracious learning to be relaxed and and uh willing to be a beginner over and
over again is how uh we can be an experienced
beginner and one of the little secrets of an experienced beginner is that that
uh is expressed in this little saying that the fastest way from a to be
is to be fully at a and um and so just to really be
willing to be here with how you are is away and it turns out that we're not
going anywhere in meditation we're it just we're going from a to
a um but we're really going almost like we're going deeper into a
we're just really being here and um and um and so we start where we are
and allow that deeper settling to happen so part of very important part
of the kind of beginning of really starting to enter into the world of
somebody is that the attention starts to be
continuous in the present moment and with with some kind of a place that it's
the nest it's the home base it's the primary place where we really stay
connected and uh classically that's the breathing there can be other objects um
practicing loving kindness and the feelings of love that come up can be
another alternative one and um but with breathing the idea is is to um to have a
uh to be able to sustain attention over time and to expect you can't really just
kind of lock in um you know as we start from the beginning the idea is that
there's a gentleness where we persist we sustain the attention there and
um and then to um um and part of that is
this massage this rhythm of connect Ing
and sustaining connecting and sustaining and um the
um and uh maybe it's like a bird that maybe only has to flap its Lings Wings
once to catch the updraft and it Soares and then does it again and Soares um maybe it's like a um a
u you know a a a a bee that lands in a flower and it just
walks around looking for where the nectar is kind of there's this the
classic metaphor is that of taking a cloth to polish a bowl and you connect
the cloth to the bowl and then you gently kind of there rubbing it and then you do it again in different
part and um so this sustaining this connecting and
sustaining and I've offered you in that meditation a lot of different metaphors
for that I apologize if the metaphors are too many uh but the idea hopefully
is that one of those will work well for you and uh sometimes a metaphor in
imagination um helps the imagination helps us be connected more to the practice the Buddha used a lot of
metaphors um to help that uh the mind kind of really feel or sense how to
enter into the world of meditation and um and then the idea is to
sustain and uh and I suggested in the meditation that uh connecting with the
beginning of the inhale and then sustaining it through the whole cycle of breathing in and breathing
out sometimes that's too long sometimes what works better is to connect to the
inhale ride it really stay there sustaining the attention however long it
is the inhale and then um and then do it again connecting to the
beginning of the exhale and riding all that all the way out uh one way that uh an interesting
way to uh help this sustaining and connecting connecting and sustaining with the breathing is um and you have to
do this very gingerly very carefully gently um just enough not too much maybe
slightly you know less than and that is to um the end of the
exhale let there be a a little pause that allows the exhale to maybe relax
further or the whole body to relax into the experience and because you're
pausing at the end of the exhale it there's a little bit in the body that gets interested like where is the next
inhale I should be breathing but not with any distress just a gentle kind of
oh I'm waking up almost okay relax it the pause allows to
something to relax to let go that maybe it wouldn't do that if we
go immediately to the inhale and then um also you could do
that sometimes at the uh at the end of the inhale is just pause and let there
be a relaxing and opening and then release into the
exhale and uh so this is like the massage this is kind of the working need
the classic the metaphor is kneading kneading a kind of powder with water making it moist um so we're working the
we're working the breath in a very light soft relaxed way no strain in the
attention but just enough um uh there's
in the muscles there's difference between tense muscles and taut muscles
the tautness of a muscle and the many of the muscles are taught that's what their nature is to be taught the muscles
holding up the back for example and um and so but they relaxed enough and so
kind of a simple tness or uh commitment or interest just stay
interested um or love or a inspiration
something stay there stay with the whole flow if you sit down to meditate
sometimes the breathing can be quite fast and it's just really quick breathing in and out and that idea of
sustaining is not really you're not really ready for it but as we settle and get calmer and calmer and the breathing
begins slowing down and the inhale and exhale are become longer that's when it
starts to work better and better to just stay with the whole thing and
um and uh so sometimes it's the awareness that's connecting and
sustaining and sometimes you can turn it around and um and uh and feel it's the
breathing that's doing the work of meditation that the breathing is connecting to um
awareness and sustaining it that this the sensations of breathing and the
sensing of those Sensations are one and the same thing so whether
you're the one who's staying there sensing or whether it's a sens
Sensations that are coming into the sensing it's just a kind of it's It's a
you know you can it doesn't a little bit hard to separate them out so you can say it either way so sometimes the attitude
of that the breathing is coming into awareness um uh the breathing is what's
connecting and sustaining can make it lighter can take kind of the the the
habit of being the doer and the one who's trying something to H make something happen U take a
rest so Thea is play with it play with your attention find the lightness find
the sustaining and connecting uh really kind of settle in
and then to feel feel the pleasure of it if there's any even the slightest sense that it's Pleasant to take that in as
well and once you start feeling some of the pleasantness the sweetness that comes with meditation
then it might be easier to let go of your thinking so that the there's more
relaxed the thinking mind and let go of the thoughts so that the the Mind itself
the space in the mind becomes larger and can somehow receive or take in or share
in some of the pleasure of the meditation a quieter
mind is a is a mind that can feel more
pleasant so I hope these uh all this uh gives some of you
some some uh all the ideas of today are too but maybe there's just few of them
that really help you be an experienced beginner here and um as I said yesterday
um if at all you're able to meditate a second time today um even 10 20 minutes um I think
that uh and then maybe without guided meditation try and do some of this on
your own and be very accepting of however you are and
however easy or difficult it is um assuming just sitting and meditating is
enough don't be too uh measuring how
well you're doing so thank you and um look forward
to being here tomorrow