so good morning and um this morning I wanted to
um talk about um a relationship the relationship between the eight worldly
winds and or intentions uh the intentions that we kind of live throughout the day
with um they're called the eight worldly winds because they tend to uh toss us
around like strong winds um and um you know they can even
um uh um U you know kind of batter us around quite a bit you know like it
reminds me in New Zealand you know the wind sometimes in in Wellington gets so
bad that they actually have uh places to hold on to at the street corners when
the winds come and it's not that unusual uh but you know that's a lot a lot of time that's really what's
happening in our minds and um a lot of what keeps our minds from being at peace
in our lives um and you know no matter how um
you know how carefully we set up our lives how hard we work to always get the
winds we want uh it doesn't happen it doesn't work you know so we're always
kind of chasing these winds um you know trying to um trying to get the good ones
and avoid the bad ones um so just so very simple you know
the the they they're four pairs and the first two are kind of the personal ones
um they're Pleasure and Pain you know my Pleasure and Pain uh their uh gain or
loss you know things you gain or lose in your life um and the other two can be
more interrelational um so praise and blame I mean we can praise and blame ourselves
right we some of us are very familiar with that and uh but there also something unh happens in the in the
bigger world and the other one is uh the last one is Fame and
disrepute um now a lot of us who oh I don't want fame but but there's something very related to fame called
status and so fame or status which sometimes can be as simple as being um
I'm a good artist you know um that that just that little bit of wanting to be seen as a good something um so these are
all the things things you know these very common human things that Force us to drive
us um so um soly changing gears a little bit um
you know the first time um I saw a living statue and
anybody does everybody know what a living statue is you know so I I was in San Francisco and a living statue is a
performer they usually Street performers who they'll perform at fairs and they
basically what they do is they get in a costume and they paint themselves and
the first one I saw was just like a silvery white you know and they're in costume their faces painted everything's
silvery white and they just don't move they're just like a living statue and I
remember you know the time I was a yoga student you know and I really struggled
five minutes holding still standing up all I was just standing up Tre POS they
called it you know just standing 5 minutes and I was like you know really hard and this person you know I kind of
went for a walk came back an hour later they're still standing yeah it's quite
Quite a feat and um so now moving up to some
years later um there's an artist um her uh a musician performer um kind of an
unusual musician performer her name is Amanda Palmer and you know maybe you've heard of her maybe you haven't you know
um but um before she made it in music um
she was a um living statue and she did it for seven years and this how she made
a living and um her her gig was called
uh the 8-foot bride and so she would stand on a pedest Crystal and um she'
paint herself white dressed in a wedding gown you know with a veil and um and
holding a bouquet of flowers of real flowers and she would basically stand there for you know usually they do like
an hour and a half at a time per set and um and there'd be a little um basket you
know at the floor people could leave a donation and um when she reflected on it
you know she happened to be a student you know as Zen and yoga student and she
said that um she said yeah yeah I'm really not a disciplined person you know
um but but you know when I thought of doing this I thought I can do one thing at a time and that's just like just
stand still that's all I have to do just stand still you know and then she qualified it stand still and love
whoever shows up um and so she um so this is what she
did for seven years as the way of making a living um and so people would come up to
her you know and and look her deep in the eyes and she would be really connecting with each person you know
this is like her practice you know to really show up fully for each person and
um and you know and then if they chose to give a donation um she would move surpris them
by moving and handing them a flower and um so it's just very very
sweet you know but but it really struck me was just the way um she you know her
intention was just to do one thing she wasn't going to do a lot of things but just this one beautiful thing of
lovingly standing still
um you know but a living statue is also affected by the eight worldly
winds and um and so just you know to tell on them now you know that uh and
really maybe connecting yourself you know as as you uh con reflect on them um
you know like Pleasure and Pain you know where um it can refer to the really
small little pleasures you know like sipping a cup of warm tea or the really
big pleasure you know maybe reconnecting with a long lost friend and just feel
all this intense pleasure and joy um so can be physical can be
emotional you know and same thing on the other side you know the the uh the little aches you know of of uh standing
in line too long or um or the really strong ones of when we're ill or um or
heartbroken or uh you so all it can range Pleasure and Pain can be just this
huge realm and um um and you know so all of you here I
I think you all experienced a little bit of one of those in the last sit right anybody feel a little little
discomfort at some point um you know anybody felt a little bit of Peace a
little bit of of Happiness pleasure um you know so maybe some
actually felt a lot of pain right some of us have a different conditions in our life um and so the the art is is is how
do we relate to those when they arise and if Our
intention is to always feel good it means that we're in conflict
with probably half of what happens to us and um and what happens when we
always want to feel good that means that we start grabbing it and oh don't go away that good feeling let me have my
third cookie I know I'm full but I want a little more pleasure right you know so we're always chasing after it not
wanting to Let It Go
um you know um the example that I I often go to with this is um um you know
I used to you know I moved away from my mother so I didn't see her that often you know and you know but whenever I
would come to see her you know she'd open the door and her eyes would just light up with joy to see me she'd just
be so happy so delighted but before I even got through the door she'd say how long are you
staying and uh and you know what whatever I said wasn't enough it didn't
only if I moved back in would be enough but but this is what we do we you
know we keep chasing after those good feelings those Pleasures
um so what's the alternative instead of being um you know seeking to be
comfortable all the time you know seeking to be at peace with whatever shows up could be an
alternative what kind of intention can we bring to our lives so that we are
present for whatever shows up and we're at peace with whatever shows up it
doesn't mean that if we notice that um oh wow I'm I'm really sitting crooked
maybe you know I'll be a little more comfortable if I sit a little straigh you we might still rearrange and be a
little more comfortable there's nothing wrong with being a little more comfortable but it's how we hold that
you know we might not be able to get more comfortable you know so how do we uh still find a sense of happiness or at
least a sense of Peace So having an attitude an intention
of Good Will towards ourselves or of kindness toward situation uh what can be your intentions
in the moment and intention of Letting Go you know in Buddhism we teach the
three wise intentions you know Good Will nonharming and letting go or
renunciation you know so those are the three kind of three sides to of the
qualities that really allow us to be present with whatever shows up and have a heart that's at peace when these
worldly winds you know can arise and Fall Away
so with gain and loss you know and and you know you think about the living statue I am positive she had plenty of
of um you know little Cool Wind feeling really sweet and probably quite a bit of
wow this hurts and and learning to meet that you
know um I mean at one point she said you know I have the best job in the world I
have the best job in the world um so gain and loss so um you know
we all have we all get things right we get things we want all the time you know might be something simple you know we go
to the store we buy dinner materials or we buy um or we get you know the bigger
things in life we might get a relationship a friendship we might get a career family all the different things
that we um you know skills you know uh learn how to play music learn how to work with
wood um you know Sports you know learn how to play tennis uh so you know maybe
we travel we get all these a nice place to live we have all these different um
things we gain we can gain in life and we can lose all of them right you know
we can um you know people who've been Master pianists have have uh injured
their hands and and lost that skill right so every everything we have you
know people get divorced um children move away you know
so um you know we all have losses in these lives this life is made of of both
all these great things we want might be minor you know uh that that we get and
and they might be major and we have all sorts of losses in this life and um one teacher said um
spiritual growth is a constant state of loss which is kind of interesting
interesting thing you know because we are actually constantly letting go of everything every moment otherwise how
when we show up um and um you know and some people give
such importance to some things you know I mean uh that's one thing that's always amazed me you know and and you know I'm
just culturally not in tune with this is that people get devastated when their team loses in
sports yeah I mean incredibly devastated you know and uh so we give
things a lot of meaning you know a lot of meaning you know I guess the meaning must be this is really important they
win it my life depends on it you know at least some people act that way you
know um you know I remember you know um it was her first newer car you know and
it looked perfect you know it looked perfect and you know somebody came Buy in a bicycle and just keyed every car
down the street you know and I remember um you know doing you know thinking you know
just um we're actually standing outside uh IMC at the time you know it's like when I first started coming it was like
back in um Palo Alto and um and and it was like right after Dharma talk you
know so it's was a pretty equanimous place and I said you know next time my car I'll do that right
away I'll keep my car right away then I don't have to worry about it
anymore um but gain and loss right
um you know and you know and we lose everything right we you know eventually
you know we lose our health our abilities our capacities and we lose our lives we lose everything everyone we've
ever loved everything in our lives we eventually lose and Suzuki roshi said it
beautifully he said life is going to see in a boat you know will
sink you know I love that you know because you know that's that's the reality of it that's the reality of
it and you know there's nothing wrong with wanting healthy relationships and working towards these wonderful things
in our lives it's how much the heart is at peace it's like sometimes people you
know become Workaholics you know they're working in their career but they're so tight you know we actually have a name
for them type A personalities people that give themselves you know headaches high blood pressure from being so
contracted instead of working out of Joy instead of working in a peaceful
way um you know I remember when I used to um
work in a different you know um realm you know I used to you know I I I loved
what I did you know and I felt at the end of the day I wasn't exhausted by it you know I was kind of uh inspired by it
you know because I was just able to just do it full-heartedly
um you know one of the things you know that we get attached to you know in in
um um you was a yoga student you know and um um and I was really feeling good
you know it's like I'd been practicing for a while and I was really strong and
flexible and so I just felt really good for the first time in my life my body felt really alive and really really
strong and um and I injured myself and I had a really bad bad injury um and I
couldn't you know my whole leg was kind of messed up a bit and and um and I
remember talking to my friend who's a yoga teacher and um and I said oh I can't do
yoga now you know it's going to be months and months of of rehabilitating this before I can do yoga she said no no
no no yoga is about what you can do not what you can't do and so I found ways of doing yoga
with what I could do and um it brought a lot of ease to my body it brought a lot
of ease to my mind you know maybe I couldn't do um you know Lotus anymore you know but I could still
um you know stretch my upper body and I could still uh be really present in my
body you know so uh and this is a little this is really the practice you know we
see you know we're meditating and the mind is just like restless and chaotic we this is what we can do we can
show up for it we can show up for it with with peaceful attitude it doesn't have to be fixed it
doesn't have to be changed just by having a peaceful attitude towards this chaotic mind uh already transforms it
it's already something that we can observe we can be mindful of
so praise and blame now we're getting into the relation Rel relational part
where um you know as I said we can often blame ourselves or praise ourselves oh I
did really great didn't I you know or or blame yourself you know I used to play racketball with this guy and and every
time he used to a ball he would hit himself in the head and say God idiot
idiot you know and you know it was kind of unpleasant to to play with him you
know to I thought we were playing a game you know um that um you know who you know
who knows who we blame ourselves for um you know I I remember when I first start
really paying attention to my mind and meditation every time I got distracted I
would blame myself you screwed up you there' be this little mean little voice that would blame me you know you know
and it's amazing how consistent that was you know I would failed you failed you blew it you know and and of course you
know you do that a 100 times a minute you know in you know especially in the beginning you know and you know maybe
only 50 in the advanced you know
um you know and the thing about failure is um failures are the building
blocks of learning right you know if you watch a little kid learn to walk what do they do
they fall down right and how many times they fall down they don't oops I blew it
I didn't get it perfect never trying again you know um you know they just fall down fall down learn to get up get
up and that's how they learn to walk they learn to figure it out they learn to strengthen their
muscles um and that's how we learn any skill you know playing piano you keep hitting you hit the wrong note okay now
you hit it right you've got the wrong Rhythm okay now you've got it right you know and this is how you learn but you
have to have you have to fail to learn and so to have a relationship with the
natural failures of life um the um a
wholesome relationship um the quote I really like
from Neil bore you know he was a noble price physicist um he said an expert is
someone who has made all the mistakes that can be made in a very narrow
field but I love that I love that that's the expert is the one who screws up the
most you know and so let's make lots of mistakes you know it's okay um this is
how we learn we learn more we try more we're more adventurous we're more willing to talk to a stranger you know
more willing to make fools of ourselves um
you know Amanda you know the the eight-foot bride you know she would get
um you know uh people who would sit her oh God you're awesome you're awesome you're great thank you she get all this
wonderful praise and you know she she she noticed she would feel herself kind of puffing up with a
praise and then people come by and say get a job you know and you know she said her mind
would would come to defense say I have a job this is my job you know and and eventually she was like oh
okay praise blame you know and just allowing them to course through her yeah
because when you're just doing one thing being still you see pretty clearly eventually you see these things you see
these movements of the Mind grasping um and you know again that's a
you know what what are we doing in meditation we're living statues right you know
um the Buddha said they blame those who remain
silent they blame those who speak much they blame those who speak
little there's none in the world who is not
blamed you know and uh you know how much energy do we put forth trying not to be
blamed you know so um and you know the thing about praise
is that um um you know for me I I I like being
praised but I didn't like being told you I'd like to hear about it from somebody else you know but when somebody would
praise me to my face I always felt uncomfortable took me a long time to find my way to say oh thank you a simple
thank you um so we have all sorts of different relationships of praise um you
know and and then um you know we can take praise and as I mentioned like get
Conceited from Praise You know you're really good at something and people are always telling you how great you are and
you get conceited by it or you know people you know like it it always um um
it would always bother me to see people praising kids for being pretty you know
especially your little girls for being pretty oh you're so pretty you're so pretty you're so pretty you know and and
then you you know you get old and you're so ugly you're so ugly you're so
ugly um you know praise some blame PR some blame they come and
go you know the motivation to get praise disconnects us from
people you know because we want something from them right you know we want them we want them to like us we
want them to we're wanting wanting you know um or not wanting to be blamed
you know so so you kind of tiptoe around
things you know we when we connect with our Good Will towards
others uh towards our kindness towards others we become interested in
them when we're wanting to be praised we're interested in ourselves you know we're want in you
know and and so that's where the connection Rises and even if Our intention is to connect with others
those winds arise in us you know if we're not you know we may not be
purified of wanting to be liked wanting to be praised you know wanting to be
seen as successful you know those things can arise in us and they can arise in a
bigger field we don't have to keep feeding them or being run by them them
and and chasing them we can have in a bigger field of of oh yeah this is my
intention is to show up and be here and to love you know and to uh connect um to
be to hold my life in a peaceful
way you if we didn't cling we wouldn't be practicing there'd be no need for
practice you know so clinging is not a mistake you know this is uh I mean you
know it's unnecessary unhelpful makes us suffer but this is what we do as human
beings you know or the whole human civilization is just filled with clinging all the suffering in humanity
is just filled with clinging this is The Human Condition
it's not for personal failure yeah which we often um look at
those things as personal
failures so the the last pair the status um or fame and then
disrepute um this is about our image or how we are seen in society how we are um
uh or place in society uh how other people see us you know um you know some
people like to brag about everything they accomplish you know make sure everybody knows I think you know you may
have done that or maybe you've seen other people do that you know I I remember kind of looking for places and
conversations where I could um kind of weave in my accomplishments you know
uh the little ways that the ego wants to get its little perks yeah um and I've I've also been where um
you know we're talk you know um I had an idea it was a really good idea and you
know shared it with a group and then somebody's sharing my idea you know and and you know and everybody's like really
liking the idea it's like I want to make sure they know it's my idea you know it's mine you know and you know so these
little pieces of of this is the status the the wanting to be seen you know I'm
the one who did that you know I found the best restaurant the best one you know it's me who found it you know not I
want to share this really good food with you but no no I'm the one who found it you know I found
it um you know one of the things that always used to strike me you know even
though I had all these same feelings um but God this is so blatant you know people would have a bumper sticker that
said a proud parent of an honor student it's like you know um and maybe it was
like totally had had didn't have this flavor but for me that was like wow
that's like showing how much ego you have you know um so
um yeah and then you see the the other side of it you know you see like Olympic athletes right who are just incredible
incredible athletes and people who get the bronze and feel like complete
failures you know it's like we we attach these things to status you know the
things that give us status and the bronze for to them was
failure um you know we see it in you really see it in school you know when you're in you
know grade school high school you know you're either popular or unpopular
you're in this click or that click you know and then you see you know it reverse right you see some of the nerds
who are now had these huge companies and you know and they're the successful ones
and the other ones have the the lesser jobs and you know and and it just kind of goes on this whole status game you
know that people play um but it's not so much fun it's not a it's not a fun
game um you we create a lot of suffering for ourselves so we're motivated by wanting
to be liked or by wanting to get approval by wanting to be
admired um you know an example you know that you know I've often um used to some
students you know um is um let's say we're making lunch for a friend you know
and their initial idea is like oh well we'll get to spend time talking I'll make them some good food and I'll make
something really nice for them and we were kind of happy about it and then you sit down to planet and you start
worrying you know oh are they going to like that are they going to like that and then you've got to clean the house
and you get you know it's like oh it's not clean enough and and you know you go through this whole Rick andaro of being
very tense about this um you know not you know this is just uh some people
have this this particular Quirk and um uh and so instead of just
being with your friend and being a fun thing it becomes this uh and maybe at
some point you enjoy the company once you've gone through the hell of getting there yeah uh but all of that all of
that can be done with a different intention because the reason that it's so painful when we do it that way is
that we're trying to be liked we're trying to get it perfect you know we're trying to be give a good impression we
want to be you know seen a certain way you know oh she makes great food oh she
she's uh she keeps a great house she you know whatever it is that that um
that we're wanting how we want to be seen But when the focus instead is like
to love her oh I'm going to make something to love her okay she doesn't e gluten okay I'll do something
gluten-free but it's coming from a very different place and the whole thing we
can appreciate the process of cleaning um and it doesn't have to be perfect we
don't have to hold it so tightly and if the meal fails you know um we had an
epic failure once with a meal you know it was uh um it was New Year's Eve and I
think we were supposed to go out but the the with some friends they were coming over driving from long distance and we
had plans but somehow the uh place we were supposed to became um
unavailable and so we didn't have food in the house but we found one package of
pasta and so you know we put up the pasta and then put on some good me music and we're having fun and we're talking
and we're talking and we're talking and never hear the timer and you know show up and there's
this big green congealed mass of spinach pasta you know or well we couldn't call
it past anymore um and you know we all just start laughing you know it's just
so so classic you know and and it's okay we survived not having dinner on New
Year's Eve um and um you know un fortunately you
know the state we were in we're having such a good time I didn't feel um personally like a personal
failure um but easily could have been easily could have gone the other
way um so
um so I want to tell you about um and maybe some of you have heard this is um Zen story uh about sudong PO he was
um um uh a Chinese 10th Century uh poet
artist Statesman um and um he was a good he had
a good friend who was a zen master and I always forget the name zen master F Yin
and you know who he would often discuss Buddhism with you know and he was a very they're both very um uh Sudo is a very
serious Buddhist student he took it very really took it to heart and so um you
know they would often discuss this and they lived kind of across a river from each other so you had to kind of take a
raft to get across you know and uh one day suong po was very inspired by his
meditation and he wrote a poem and um this is a it's just four
lines okay so um um I bow my head to the heaven within
Heavens okay rays of a light Illuminating the universe the eight winds cannot move
me sitting still upon the Golden
Lotus so he was impressed with himself and um he sent a servant to meet
hand carry the poem to um to F yin and
you know took the raft across the water and brought him the poem and um and um
you know and so F Yin looked at the poem and um he smiled and he wrote one word
on it and sent it back and the one word on it was fart
and um so Sudan po gets the manuscript back and um you know he's like you know
assuming that he's going to get praise and you know and um so he he sees that
and he is outraged he is you know what the hell that blousy old monk you know
who does he think he is you know and he gets you know dress goes across the river you know uh rafts over and and and
but the door's closed and there's a note on it for him
and it says the eight winds cannot move me one fart blows me across the water
[Applause]
[Laughter]
but this is what we do right this is how we are these little insults the little
insults so
um you know um as Amanda Palmer said as a statue all
she needed to do was to be still and love that's
it and um you know that's what the practice leads us to it shows us to show up for each
moment with a certain amount of Stillness and with a heart full with a
heart open a heart ready
um you know regardless of what Winds of Change have shown up you know what pleasures and pain what
gains and losses we just keep showing up for um you know with an open heart to
whatever shows up um you know in
Zen um they very much stress the benefit of doing one thing at a time you know
and kind of you know you kind of hear a little bit of a put down on multitasking not being quite a Zen thing to do and um
you know there was a z student you know who heard that this teaching regularly you know when drinking tea just drink
tea right you know and that one day he sees his teacher um drinking tea and
reading the newspaper you know and of course he goes up to him you know and he says um you
know he's he's kind of shocked you know it's like you know I thought I thought you said when drinking tea you're
supposed to just drink tea and you know the teacher says when drinking tea and reading the newspaper just drink the tea
and read the [Laughter]
newspaper we don't need to be perfect we don't need to be
rigid we we we don't we can just be you know these winds are there or
attachments are there uh and how do we hold or attachments you know how do we how do we
relate to um getting cut up by by craving how do we relate to that can we
hold them with just oh yeah you know being attached to that but being attached with an open hand can we be
attached to something and yet give it room for it to be seen to be healed
in its own time um you know we can aim to show up
for whatever is is in our lives whatever comes next with this at open-handed
attitude um you know towards any Wind of Change that shows up you know just be
completely just open-handed whatever arises can arise including or most
ridiculous egos sometimes you know sometimes just the ego has these you
know things that you don't want everybody to see right you know it just it wants a certain way you know it just
this little yeah oh that's what showed up that's what showed up okay you know
the moment that we can meet that with uh an open-handed uh acceptance it transforms
it it's no longer I am that ego it it's ah that arose and that went away it has
room to change it has room to um do both you know
um uh drink or tea and read the newspaper it has room for
both so um so thank you thank you