Good evening. Welcome. Welcome. Nice to see you all.
It's nice to practice together.
So, tonight I'm going to start with this bold statement that earthworms are often
underappreciated. that they do this work of you like
airrating the soil and creating little tunnels that allow
air and water to move through as well as they eat some of the organic
material and essentially recycle it as uh leaving behind some castings and
but the interesting thing is that you know earthworms of course they're underground but we don't see them
they're doing this work and proving the quality quality of the soil. Probably,
you know, this planet wouldn't work as as it does if we didn't have these
things under underneath the ground that we didn't see and that we often just simply don't appreciate.
And Ajan Chawa, who's uh one of the he was, for those of you who know, Jack
Kornfield, was one of the elders in this tradition, and he practiced with Ajan
Chawa in Burma, in Thailand. sorry in Thailand and uh
Ajan talked about this earthworm wisdom this idea of doing practices that really
can make a benefit in your life but often goes unnoticed is often like
underground you know not so obvious and not seen and yet what a difference it
makes I myself don't work with soil I don't have earthworms so but I this is my
understanding is that you know What a difference they make in terms of the quality of the soil.
So, what is meant by this this idea of earthworm wisdom? I just like that expression. I think it's kind of fun.
Well, part of it, there's a lot we could say that fits under this uh banner or
this uh moniker, this uh statement. But
what about this idea of just simply caring for ourselves?
Because there's this way in which sometimes we come to Buddhist practice or maybe any spiritual practice with
this sense that things should be different that somehow we are
lacking that we are something's wrong with us something is uh broken or I
don't know we have all these uh sense of that's inadequate or insufficient in
some kind of way and then we come to practice with with this idea we have to fix it.
We're a problem or there's a part of us that's a problem that has to be fixed.
And this uh kind of what's fueling this what's underneath this a little bit is this sense of
not enough. Something's wrong. I wish it weren't this way. Dang it. And
everything would be so much better if it weren't like this. If I didn't have this quality. I didn't have this behavior or
whatever it is. So, there's this little flavor. It's subtle or maybe it's
obvious. It can be obvious or subtle. This sense of Yeah, it's a little bit of aversion like
wishing to undo some of some part of ourselves maybe to excise
or remove or get rid of or somehow transform or change. There's this little
slight feeling of uggh. I wish this could be different. Why
isn't it why is it like this? And so perhaps we undertake meditation.
Maybe I'll just say for those people that I see that are putting on warmer clothing
that uh this is the uh air conditioning comes out of these vents right here. So
there's these microclimates. So under the stage is the warmest place when the
air conditioning is on. And so just uh just I don't know state maybe uh what's
always thank you Jim for changing the temperature there.
So there's this inner climate sometimes that shows up of of wanting to get rid of things. And I could say some of this
earthworm wisdom is instead of this idea we have to get rid of and change and fix
because there's something wrong or inadequate or insufficient. What if it's uh there's a sense of care
that's born out of uh a respect and honor of our experience
because we care about ourselves. Let's have some maybe some warmth. This
doesn't have to be obvious or giant or big um self uh arandisement or something
like this, but instead just how what if it were just uh because we have some
respect for ourselves and that's what's fueling some of this practice like yeah maybe I'm going to
work on this because I care about myself and I anticipate that my life will
unfold in a way that brings more and more happiness. if I do this that I'll be able to bring more and more good into
the world. I'll be able to support more people. What if that's what's underneath? What's fueling our practice
instead of this self-improvement project instead of it's a care and respect for
ourselves and for others. I'm not going to sit here and say that I
didn't start my practice with uh with this idea of care and respect. It definitely was a self-improvement
project. So I think it's most often we bring us to practice but just this
recognition that there can be this shift this uh tilting in the way and what fuels our practice especially the more
the longer that we have a meditation practice.
And so what is something that can support this can support this shift away
from a self-improvement project and something towards that's born out of a care and respect and and honoring of
ourselves and some of that there's a number of ways which we can do this one thing I
want to talk about tonight is this idea of meta practice many of you will be
familiar with this word meta is often translated as loving kindness or I I
often think of it as warmheartedness or goodwill or benevolence, care. These are some of
the other words that we could use for it. And I'll just say briefly in kind of
like a a big broad brush. Um, maybe before I say that, I'll say for
those of you who don't know that on IMC, Monday through Friday, so 5 days a week, uh, 6:00 p.m. to 7:00 p.m., there's what
we call happy hour. That's uh, on Zoom and sometimes it's on YouTube, not so often, but and uh, it's all about
cultivating this. And for years, I taught this a couple of times a week, this uh, warm-heartedness, this uh,
loving kindness. Um, and it's and there's people that
have been going like every day, five days a week since the pandemic. So, what is that almost five years now? Five
years. And they talk about how their lives are different and transformed and changed from just this uh just regularly
showing up for one hour on the week nights. So, what is this kind of practice that
we're doing at happy hour? is this uh loving kindness practice, mental
practice. We could say again this is a big broad brush is there's three elements to this practice. One is to
bring to mind uh an individual. We start with an individual that um we wish to
extend uh goodwill. We always start where it's the easiest.
So often uh start with a lovable being in which there's already a sense of care
for this lovable being. Some people use kittens or puppies or grandchildren or
babies or I know somebody who does squirrels you know for whatever it doesn't matter
what it is. So there's the maybe an object or an image of of an individual
and then there's this felt sense of maybe this connection that you feel with this lovable being might be really
subtle and it might not even be there and it's perfectly fine whatever it is.
Then the third aspect is to say phrases that we repeat in the mind. So just like
with mindfulness practice we like have mindfulness of the breath for example and then the mind wanders and then we
come back to the breath with loving kindness practice we use the phrases as a way like I have a phrase the mind
wanders and we come back to the phrases as a way to stay with this connection
with this warm-heartedness this goodwill this uh benevolence this care that we
have for others. So this practice of loving kindness is
not about convincing ourselves of anything. It's not an effort to pretend
or plead or I don't know something like or demand maybe even that uh that
there's this warm-hearted feeling. Instead it's just creating the conditions for that which is already
inside of us to arise. Sometimes it does and sometimes it doesn't. And that's
okay. In fact, that's what's expected. It's more just the intention of
inclining the mind and the heart again and again towards connection and warm-heartedness with others.
It's quite amazing. It's quite amazing. It's a beautiful practice.
So, it's about tapping into something that's already inside of us. We're not
denying or pretending that there's a lot of awfulness in the world. We are not just putting on rosy glasses and you
know hanging out with unicorns and uh butterflies or something like that. It's
more it's just this practice of this continue orientation towards some goodwill towards others.
So it's more than just a feeling though when we do this practice. It's not like
we're trying to cultivate something that feels ooey gooey or
that's I'll just use that as a technical term. Instead, it's often what can
happen is this sense of openness and spaciousness and ease and warmth.
As I've said, it doesn't it's not doesn't always there. But when we're practicing it, it's not
it doesn't matter. so much whe what exact uh uh emotion we're having. It's
more like we're planting seeds. We're just you know neuroplasticity just
bringing the mind back again and again and again towards this uh goodwill this
uh wishing well for others.
And there's this way I talked about it as being warm and maybe spacious and uh
open but it also can have a quality when this warm-heartedness this meta arises
can have a quality of being a little bit bubbly like a little bit uh energetic
like like an uplift in the heart. It can be soothing in this way. It can be
calming. It can be very gentle and it can also be like wow shazam. It
can be a little bit of kind of that thing too. It's beautiful how there can be just such a big wide range of it.
And so some of the phrases that we offer with uh loving kindness, some of the classical traditional ones and there's
nothing magic about these particular words. These are just uh what the
tradition uses. And so you'll find often variations of this. In fact, you're encouraged to find variations that maybe
speak to your heart or resonate more is uh why we're have a start for the
lovable being for example. And the phrase that we would say is like may you
be safe, may you be happy,
may you be healthy, may you live with ease.
So, it's just this way for us to connect and this uh
encourage this warm-heartedness. As I said, this is not a uh it's not so
much a prayer. We're not it's not an invocation to any other being. It's just this uh
wish. It's just a wish, an invitation for others.
So this idea of loving kindness
is that it expands out out into all beings and importantly it includes our yourself
having loving kindness for oursel turns out this is often not so easy. A
lot of people uh will tell me when I'm teaching a mentor retreat or have done some uh with happiness like okay I can
like do it for all kinds of people all these beings all these situations yeah but for myself not so it's not so easy
and then they just kind of ignore it and I'm just like doing for everybody else
but this idea that care for oneself is pretty important it's this uh
foundational practice I would say that allows us to meet the world with some
warm-heartedness as opposed to trying to get something
from other people all the time to feel fill uh holes that we feel in our hearts
and minds in some kind of way.
So there's this part of uh not having uh loving kindness
for oneself. There's some resistance to it. This sense that
that feels selfish. I I should have loving kindness for other people, not for myself.
Or maybe there's this sense that yeah, if people really knew some of the
thoughts that I've had or some of the uh exper things that I've done, they they
they wouldn't think that I'm worthy of loving kindness or care. So somehow they feel like they're not deserving or
something. So they there's some resistance to this.
I just want to say that we often have resistance to so many experiences uh that we're having not only resistance
to loving kindness for ourselves but just there's this way in which we are
maybe in a subtle or obvious way saying no no I don't want this experience.
No make this go away. No, I this isn't what I wanted. I didn't meditate wanting
this experience. Make it be different. Dang it. You know, is this often this thing that uh can
show up? So, this idea of resistance, it's a natural response to uncomfortable
experiences and it just stems from our wish to avoid discomfort.
of course this so it's this urge to push away or deny or minimize the experience
and resistance I'm using this word it says no but it can also just show up as
distraction this way in which we are creating stories or narratives getting lost in
fantasy with things that we're remembering maybe there's even ideas like oh I can't
handle this and off we go into something else. Off we go with our minds or or
sometimes even we just literally get up and uh do some different activity
in order to distract ourselves from whatever is being uh experienced that's uncomfortable.
So it's this fascinating thing that I appreciate so much about Buddhist
practice. We often can have this idea and I know I did for such a long time and it wasn't
until I was helping Gil with his book on uh the hindrances that I really start to
understand this differently and that is we often have this idea.
Okay, I'll get to the practice as soon as this bothersome thing goes away. As
soon as you know my irritation with my neighbor, my frustration with not being
able to find a parking spot or whatever it might be, as soon as that gets taken care of, okay, then I'll come
back uh to the to the practice.
But it's actually is the practice to be with the resistance. It turns out that's
exactly the way to practice is with uh the
resistance that we're experiencing. I like the simile that we find in the sutas
where the Buddha describes that uh there's um up in there's rain up in the
mountains and then the little uh
trickles of water start to trickle down and then they kind of join and become little streamlets
that become uh streams that become rivers that eventually find their way to the ocean. Right? So there's rain here
that just comes together and finds its way to the ocean.
And of course it's not in a straight line.
And of course it's not that it doesn't meet like you know the big boulders or
big uh obstructions. Instead this water just touches the obstructions and goes
around and keeps on continuing. So it's the same way with our practice is that
we meet these obstructions and part of the practice is to like have contact with them. It's not to just see them in
the distance and then go around them. So resistance, how do we work with this
is to recognize it and to not resist the resistance.
Just to notice, oh yeah, this is uncomfortable. I wish it weren't here.
And then just to feel into that wish for it to not be here.
That's the practice. Feel into recognize,
oh yeah, I'm I'm irritated. I have this aversion. I want this to go away.
So instead of fighting the resistance, instead of resisting the resistance, can we welcome it? Can we recognize yeah
this is a natural part of the process. It's a I would say a required part of
the process. If it's uh just perfectly easy all the
time then that's where there's not a learning there isn't a expanding of our
capacities. It's just maybe a I don't know going down a water slide in the summer
like that. It's just entertainment or fun. Not to say that practice can't be
fantastic and lovely and all those kinds of things, but sometimes it isn't.
And so by acknowledging the resistance, we create space for it to be felt and to
be recognized. Maybe in the same way that the earthworms under the soil are making
space for air and water that uh for you know something beautiful to be grown
from the soil to make this soil fertile and um able to support a lot of growth.
So I'd like to introduce a poem here. I'm on this kick of uh doing poems. Uh,
sometimes I I pulled together a talk and I feel like, oh, that doesn't feel quite
enough. There's got to be a poem somewhere that's going to make this better. So, here we are. Here's uh
Diana's attempt making something a little bit more relatable. And I always like poems that
have a little bit of whimsy, you know, a little bit of course are relevant to what we're what the topic is, but have
some playfulness or fun or or at least uh or have some imagery. So this poem is
called How by Rosemary Tramer. Simple title, How by Rosemary Tummer.
Not the tick. No, surely it is not sacred. Do not try to tell me so. These
rep repulsive tiny blood suckers. I do not wish to be impressed by their
survival. Do not want to respect how they have thrived since the first flowering plants arrived on Earth over
100 million years ago. I do not want to praise their hard
protective shells, nor how efficiently they swell, nor the ease with which they
sense moisture, heat, vibration. Rather to vilify what disgusts me,
repulsive little carriers of sickness, vile little vectors of disease.
What joy is there in knowing a tick is so effective and good at doing what a
tick was made to do? Could it be greater than the perverse
joy I get from my hatred? It is clear my repulsion does not affect
the tick. Oh clenched heart, oh clenched fist,
where is the line between what I love and what I resist?
Is it true there is holiness and everything?
How do I wound myself when my heart and hand are closed?
Let my prayer not be to fall in love, but to open to the prayer I do not yet
know.
know. this idea that okay we want to love
everything like you want to hate these things love these things and I
appreciate so much right Rosemary Tummer she's really a highlighting like how much we just like ticks
and she's saying but I don't wish for love so like to transform this but to be
open to something new open to something else
open to the prayer I do not yet know. And I would say that is what care for
ourselves allows is allows us to be open to something new
to greater peace, greater freedom, greater ease.
this way in which um we it stops being me versus the world or us versus them.
Instead to be open to a different way of experiencing
our practice, experiencing the world, experiencing each other.
And so this practice of ma
We can bring this to resistance in a maybe radical this is not the uh
most conventional way that I described it uh earlier but rampa he describes
this way that I think it's very provocative and very interesting this idea of why don't we bring meta this
wish for others usually we think of it as wish for others to be happy, safe,
healthy, and living with ease. What if we were to do that to just all
phenomena? So, this is not a uh practice for
beginners. This is in terms of meta practice. I would say this is something to do if you've already started with
meta practice or maybe not. Actually, I haven't tried this as a beginner. So,
maybe maybe it works great. I don't know actually. But there's this way in which what I'm
about to say can feel a little contrived. It can feel a little like wait what
if we employ the thinking mind too much. But there's this way in which it can
touch the heart and maybe allow this something different to arise.
allow something different than love or hate or resistance or
non-resistance. Instead, it uh allows for something different
and that is to radiate goodwill towards all
experiences, towards all phenomena,
to what is seen, to what is heard.
to thoughts. Those are the three more obvious ones. And then of course uh to aromomas and tastes.
So an advantage of like why this might be helpful is because it like uh reduces our tendency to resist our experiences.
If we are actively sending them goodwill, our experiences, then we're
not actively resisting them. May maybe there's a little me mixture there before
the meta takes hold. But there's a way in which even to have a shift in our
relationship to our experiences really opens up possibilities.
It's also a shift away from our personal preferences. If we're going to have this meta
practice for our experiences, whatever they are, that really starts to highlight how, oh, yep, I don't like
that. I do like this, I don't like that, I don't like that, I don't like that, I do like this. You know, just how our whole lives are end up being about our
preferences. And this is, oh, how can we just meet what life is bringing us?
And this is uh this is the type of care that can really be transformative.
So an example would be and I'm as I said this is not the
conventional way of doing this and if we think too much about it maybe it just starts to feel too artificial. So the
invitation here is just to allow the mind maybe to take the back seat and the
heart to take the front the driver's seat or something like that. So we could say phrases like
may this sensation feel welcomed
maybe you know allowing the space to simply exist instead of the way in which we're always trying to
push away or change or shove or manufacture manipulate engineer create
you know our experiences. Instead, the experiences that are already here,
already being experienced. Could we say, "May this experience feel
welcomed." Wow, what a shift that is.
Or, "May this sensation be allowed?"
Really highlights all the way in which we're not allowing it.
Or may this sensation feel cared for
like this way of treating our experiences with respect and care. Kind
of like honoring what's actually happening. So often we're lost in our head with our
expectations. This isn't what I wanted. I thought it was going to be like this and it should be like that. You know,
this is often what the mind is doing. And this is like a radical way to say
May may this experience, may this sensation be welcomed,
may it be allowed, may it be cared. And then maybe this idea, may it feel at
ease because there's this way feeling at ease allows maybe it to arise and pass away
and be released. Because this is what sensations do. This
is their nature to arise and pass away and be released. It's only when we are get tangled up in
them and the tangling up often shows up as resistance.
This way in which we are often saying well I want it to be a little bit different here.
So this is kind of a different idea. It's like may this sensation feel welcomed.
May this sensation be allowed. May this sensation feel cared for.
May this sensation be at ease. So then it kind of rise and pass away
which is you know the natural course it things are arising and passing away all the time. Of course they are. But there
is truth to this statement that what we resist persists.
So there's a way in which the we could direct this towards uh maybe even more
practically towards the hindrances. Some of you might be familiar with this this uh
perennial list of five ways in which resistance shows up or obstructions
shows up. One is desire
like this way in which we like uh scrolling scrolling scrolling looking for something or shopping for something
or maybe there's a way that we're looking at our social media like the craving for some connection.
Can we have some care for that experience?
And maybe we can recognize that maybe all that desire is just wanting to really feel met and seen.
And there's this way if we say, "May this experience be welcomed. May this
experience be allowed. May this experience be cared for. May this
experience feel at ease." is the way in which we are meeting ourselves
instead of waiting for something out there to meet us.
Or maybe there's this way in which we have this aversion or ill will resistance to a person, a situation, a
institution, anything, right? It's endless. We can have aversion to anything and everything. But there's
this way that it kind of like tightens the heart kind like there's this constriction whenever there's there.
Maybe having some meta for this experience can uncoil that tightness can
bring some spaciousness and ease into the heart.
Or maybe there's this way that's one of the the uh entrances about sloth and
torper. this uh feeling like practice is slogging through molasses. Like
slow and heavy and sticky. Maybe something like this.
And can we have some meta? Can we direct meta towards that experience?
Or maybe there's this restlessness. Maybe there's a way in which you sit here and then you're just going through
the to-do list. Okay, as soon as I leave here, I got to stop by the grocery store. Remember to pick that up because I'm going to do this tomorrow. And oh
yeah, when am I going to get the oil changed in the car? You know, there's all this kind of stuff that we might be doing when we sit down to meditate. That
sense of restlessness or maybe we just want to leave like, oh, just get me out of here.
Can we bring Can that experience be welcomed? Can that experience be
allowed? Can that experience be cared for? Can that experience
have ease?
And then the uh traditional list of uh the five hindrances, the last one is doubt. And
that might be is this even helping whatever practice we find ourselves
doing, whether it's uh loving kindness or mindfulness.
And is there this way that meta can meet the doubter?
Maybe there's uh this tightness or hesitation or vacasillation that we feel
in the heart. Can that experience be welcomed,
allowed, cared for and have some ease?
So this idea of meeting resistance uh with loving kindness
as a way to help create the conditions that maybe fertilize the soil in which
something really beautiful can grow. Something that's different than the me
against the world or our incessant trying to just get everything right out
there in the external world.
So, let's see here. I I had this phrase that I wanted to say, welcoming what we wish
away. Often what we're trying to push away, can we welcome it instead? And meta
practice can be a way that we can do that. So, I'll end there and open it up to see
if there's some questions or comments. Thank you.
Does anybody have something they'd uh like to say or comment on?
I can read the tick poem again. I like to read poems twice because some,
you know, you have to read them a few times, right? So, maybe I'll read it here. I have to get my
find all the pages that have it here.
This is how by Rosemary Tmer. Not the tick. No, surely it is not sacred. Do
not try to tell me so. Repulsive tiny blood suckers.
It's funny. That's I don't know why it's hard for me to have a straight face when I say that.
I do not wish to be impressed by their survival. Do not want to respect how they have been how they have thrived
since the first flowering plants arrived on Earth over 100 million years ago. I
do not want to praise their hard protective shells, nor how efficiently they swell, nor the ease with which they
sense moisture, heat, vibration. Rather to vilify what disgusts me,
repulsive little carriers of sickness, vile little vectors of disease.
What joy is there in knowing a tick is so effective and good at doing what a tick was made to do?
Could it be greater than the perverse joy I get from my hatred?
It is clear my repulsion does not affect the tick.
Oh clenched heart. Oh clenched fist.
Where is the line between what I love and what I resist?
Is it true there is holiness in everything?
How do I wound myself when my heart and hand are closed?
Let my prayer not be to fall in love, but to open to the prayer I do not yet
know.
How by Rosemary Tummer?
Is this on? Yes. Okay. Thank you very much. That was really interesting and helpful. I've
been um doing a lot of studying on about mindful self-compassion and your talk
feels very similar. Um but one thing that I've took to heart
is, you know, in in self-compassion work, it's often about really, you know, sending kindness to yourself simply
because you're suffering. And you're talking about sending kindness to the ex specifics of the
experiences of suffering. So it's like breaking down self-compassion even
further it seems. Yeah.
Is there a question or do you want me more of a comment? Yeah. So this uh mindful self-compassion
is really powerful practice and can really make a lot of difference in people's lives especially because it's
amazing how much uh inner critic and how harsh we can be to ourselves.
And this breaking it down towards experience is less about the self which
the self-compassion is about and it's more about you know just what's arising.
Um both of them are beautiful practices. There's just uh yeah, as you pointed a
different emphasis and maybe self-compassion um allows us maybe to just settle down
and start to feel more whole and collected and steady in some kind of way
that then makes it easier to um send meta to different experiences or or
resistance I would say. So I is that helpful maybe to say that? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Great. Thank you. Thank you. Back here.
So let's say we start off and we start practicing meta and we accomplish what
you're guiding us toward. Maybe is it wrong to think of that as a
self-improvement? Do you have a sense of what would be the
disadvantages of self-improvement? Um, I think it depends how how you define it
because it could be you could use it in a way that is very counterproductive, but you could also maybe use in a way that is helpful. But I'm wondering like
so the Buddha he was a Brahman and he left the palace and wandered around tried all these different things and
then under the Buddha sure he woke up to enlightenment out of Mara. Is it wrong to think of that as that he improved
himself? So technically I would say it's not ex
yeah it um it's not so much that he improved himself it's that he saw
clearly that there is no permanent self no abiding self to which all
experiences happen. So it's was a radical shift in uh perspective and
understanding rather than like just getting better better just becoming a better and better version of himself. He
like transformed into something different. But Matt, I understand what you're pointing to. Um maybe one thing
I'll say is this. What's implicit in this idea of a self-improvement project
is that a that there's a self, but maybe b that uh there's something wrong with
me and it just kind of sets that there's something wrong with me and it seems
like there's no end to the improvement that can be done, right? There's self-help industry is, you know, huge,
right? If you go to the bookstore, right? Those aisles where the self-help books are big. So, so it's not wrong so
much. It's just think of it of a self-improvement project, but there's maybe some nuances or different ways to
think about it. So, you mean that there just a better way of expressing that path, the
spiritual path and saying self-improvement? The last thing you said is so there's a
better way of expressing the spiritual path itself than just saying it's I'm improving myself like
Yeah. Yeah. It's more my my hesitation is more about
it's just focusing it tends to be focusing on what's wrong
and I'm not saying that everything's perfect and that but it's just the it's the orientation or what's implicit in
that. Thank you. Thank you Matt.
Maybe we'll end there. So, thank you all for your attention.
I wish you safe travels home and a wonderful rest of the evening. Thank
you. And if you'd like, you're welcome to come up here and uh talk to me.
Otherwise, uh have a good evening.