welcome to all of you it's great to be here again my name is May Elliot and
today we'll continue our study of the three characteristics with a focus on
the second Char characteristic uh Dua or uh
unsatisfactoriness suffering so yesterday we looked through the lens of
anicha impermanence and when observing
impermanence um it's pretty clear that we're observing change right the arising
and passing of phenomena but when we consider insight into Dua um we might think that the
practice is just to sit around and uh think about the ways that our life
sucks which is obviously not the case that's not what we're doing with this practice so I just want to be overt
about the fact that contemplating Dua is not about uh dwelling in or uh
ruminating on our difficulties um and it's also not to cement a view or a
belief that life is suffering rather um we're learning to
clearly see the source of suffering which is craving we know this from the
second Noble Truth so the source of suffering is craving that's what we're interested in seeing when We crave and
claim we suffer um and of course the other side of the coin of craving is
aversion so when craving or aversion are present when wanting or not wanting are present we
suffer so during the meditation today uh we'll be noticing if and when uh craving
or aversion are present or we'll be noticing the absence of craving or
aversion so if and when we identify desire wanting not wanting uh during the
practice today we'll meet it by using a practice called raft raft is an acronym
developed by T Weiser frequently taught by Gil um R A
ft so the r stands for recognize a for allow or accept f for feel and T for
te's um so the r recognize we're just really clearly recognizing when desire
or aversion are present we allow um a for allow we don't try to get rid
of them this would just be more aversion sneaking in through the back door so we're we're um letting them be present
and then F we feel it in the body uh desire and aversion they often include
uh like tension or contraction so we're learning what it what it feels like and
where um really getting to know it when we can get to know um these manifestations really really well we're
much less to uh less likely to be um consumed by them to be hijacked by
them and then lastly tease though this is the last letter in the acronym
actually kind of doing this one first um so we're teasing apart the object of
Desire say the desire for a cup of coffee so the coffee would be the object
from the desire itself so rather than just uh fixating on getting the cup of
coffee as the typical human does um we look a little closer and
notice if there's some desire in relationship to the coffee uh so we're
we're teasing apart the object from the desire just so we can see that there's two things that are present um we're
usually so absorbed in getting what we want that all we see is the object all we see is what we're trying to get not
the wanting in relationship to it so um so in This Acronym um we'll put that
that is really going to need to be this teasing apart is going to need to be upfront um so that we can really clearly
see oh there's desire here and te that teasing apart will allow us to R
recognize once we've re recognized it we can a allow and F
feel uh so this is this is one way that we can deliberately explore Dua in our
own experience um but as I've I said yesterday uh there are many many ways to
explore the Insight themes you don't need to go directly looking for them even um uh but it can help to be
intentional about it from time to time to learn how to develop the capacity to see desire and aversion clearly um
really helpful so um so for our meditation today uh as with yesterday uh
we'll start by by cultivating the supportive conditions for insight
um so uh we'll um you know we'll connect with any contentment that might be
available um we'll let allow the mind to settle a little bit and then we'll shift to exploring uh wanting and not wanting
U more directly so that's what you can expect today and so let's let's start our
meditation go ahead and connect with a posture that supports you to
be um both uh awake alert and
relaxed maybe taking a deep breath to support you in landing
maybe starting by sensing what's here for you physically has the
body how's the heart how is the
mind just a brief check-in at a
glance whatever you find um can you me it with
contentment even if there's a 99% discontent
dissatisfaction maybe there can be uh 1%
okayness maybe just being content uh that it's possible to know things as
they are the beauty of knowing things as they are what a gift
and when you're ready connecting with the breath or with your primary
anchor and inviting the mind to settle and relax
if it's supportive for you to connect with vaka and
vichara as we talked about on the second morning of this series you might try
that making contact with the moment a breath starts and then sustaining that
contact like a bird flapping its wings and gliding
that little bit of effort to touch in to connect with the felt sense of breathing
you're using an object besides the breath ITA and vichara can be practiced
there as well whatever the object this connecting and
sustaining contact aim and
sustain
e
e e
V taka connecting connecting with the
breath and vcha is sustaining contact with the
breath making contact and sustaining contact
as you practice with the breath at
times it's likely that thoughts and emotions will
arise and when you notice thinking rather than jerking the Mind
back to the breath take a moment to recognize where
you were what landscape were you in when you
were thinking were you planning maybe
planning dinner or your next vacation were you regretting
or replaying a
memory are you fantasizing or rehearsing an upcoming
conversation or maybe
fixing so if you notice that thinking is occurring rather than get lost in the
story line uh notice thinking almost as if you were
an onlooker not in the thought but observing the
thought
e e
as you practice you might notice recurring themes recurring thoughts that seem to
keep coming
back often these thoughts are fueled by unseen desire and
aversion so if you notice thinking is Aur ing during your
meditation see if you can recognize if there's any wanting or not wanting in
relationship to the content of the
thought if you're regretting there may be aversion [Music]
present if you're fantasizing there may be desire
present if you're trying to fix or change something maybe
both we're just opening to the field of the mind to notice our attitude to
notice any want wanting or not wanting in relationship to our experience
as you do this as you check the mind for desire or
aversion uh you might notice an absence of desire and aversion which is
also valuable to notice
so continuing with the breath and just checking the Mind here
and there see if there's desire or aversion maybe in relationship to the
thinking mind or maybe in relationship to some
other aspect effect of
experience e
if you notice desire or aversion wanting or not wanting
can you recognize
it nearly seeing
it can you allow it not pushing it
away not getting rid of
it you feel it in the
body what's it feel like to Crave to cling to
want or to push away experience to reject experience
maybe there's contraction or tightness some aspect of discomfort
if there's an absence of wanting or not
wanting you might feel what that's like what's that like in the body
maybe the body is relaxed or soft
[Music]
open p in your own time now practicing with the breath and when
it feels right turning to check the
attitude checking for wanting or not
wanting
e
e e
welcome welcome back again my name is May
Elliot and today we'll be continuing our study of the three
characteristics uh with our Focus today on Dua or
suffering sometimes translated as unsatisfactoriness uh
stress dissatisfaction so Dua covers the full
range of difficulty uh it can be the slight
discontent of uh wearing a sweater that's too tight uh the pain of a
sprained ankle you know to the Heartbreak of losing loved one so this full spectrum of of
difficulty uh so yesterday we talked about how all conditioned things are
impermanent the characteristic of Dua is sometimes phrased all conditioned things are
unsatisfactory so this isn't saying that all condition things that all things are
unpleasant now we know that many things are Pleasant um rather it's saying uh
that they can't lead to Lasting H happiness um to say all condition things
are unsatisfactory is pointing to the fact that they can't lead to the forever
fulfillment that we're seeking that we're investing into
them uh so having just talked about insight into impermanence
yesterday uh we can see the relationship ship between that insight and this one
uh impermanence and unsatisfactoriness um and here's how um because all things are of the
nature to change of the nature to pass away uh that means that all objects and
experiences are unstable refuges as in any object or experience
that we might try to get or have it can't provide deep lasting
satisfaction um so this is really important information um because it it
guides us on our path to happiness which is really what the Buddhist teaching is all about you know it helps us discern
where happiness is and where it isn't if all objects and experiences pass away um
why would we try so hard to get them why crave and cling to them you know if we
know um uh that it's not going to work that in the long run it's not going to
work and that's not to say that um you know we don't uh you know we don't turn
on the heat in our house when it's below freezing or um that we don't share love
with those that we care about or you know there's uh uh ways to skillfully
engage with objects and experiences um but what we find is that the clinging to
them is not so useful um so uh one of the key insights
into suffering um as we we talked about before the meditation uh is seeing that
the source of suffering is craving um so typically um as the Buddha
would say an untrained worldling um thinks that they're suffering because of their circumstances so um I'm suffering
because my socks are too itchy or because I I
feel insecure after that conversation with my partner or I'm suffering because
the food is too salty or uh because my coworker is incompetent or I'm
incompetent um or you know I'd be happy if I only had a better uh relationship
or job or house or family so if we could just arrange our circumstances is then
we wouldn't experience Dua then we wouldn't experience suffering but what we don't tend to
realize is that the Dua isn't from the objects or
experiences it's from the craving and aversion itself it's not because of the
socks or the crummy job uh our suffering comes from the wanting and not
wanting so it was um it was striking from me to see this uh for the first
time in relationship to physical pain and I have a a disability so I live
with um some Associated chronic pain conditions and uh this was particularly
pronounced during my time training as a monk at uh tasahara Zen Center in the
Venta Wilderness so it's very rustic conditions there uh it especially cold
in the winter and get up in the morning maybe 3:45 a.m.
um sit meditation till noon work a few hours and then go back to the Zeno um so
it was one of the during one of these long days of practice um in the first
thing in the morning I had a few sips of tea and uh and it set off a multi-hour
spell of uh this chronic pain a digestive pain and so for much of the morning uh
this the physical Sensations I had were uh quite unpleasant um so uh there's maybe
contraction tightness pressure um but the Mind wasn't agitated
it was it was relaxed around the object like it was it was fine it was just unpleasant unpleasant
Sensations um but a few hours into the sitting a
thought arose and the thought was something like wow I can't believe this
pain is still happening and with that thought there was this kind this sense like it
shouldn't be this way I felt kind of incredulous that uh that much pain would
come from such a minor stimulus and that seeing you know it shouldn't be this way
you can probably hear in it it was just like dripping with aversion there was so much not wanting with that and that
feeling it just cut me like a knife and sudden I was consumed in Dua was filled
uh with suffering so here's what's
interesting nothing changed with the level of pain but I went from very
peaceful and at ease uh into the throws of suffering uh in an instant so what
happened there what happened um so this was such a
noteworthy the Insight um because it showed me where the suffering
was it wasn't the sense object that caused the Dua as in it wasn't the stomach pain it wasn't the
unpleasantness of the pain I was able to be with that without suffering right
with you know an easeful mind but rather it was the craving for it to be otherwise it was the aversion of it
shouldn't be this way so I was just fine until that feeling came along
aan suito says uh first we think we need to get out of the
predicament of this predicament then we realize we are the
predicament so the predicament it wasn't the pain uh it wasn't the chronic
illness it was my own mind the predicament was my own
aversion so how are you relating to your own
Dua in any given moment uh most of us aren't even aware that we're suffering
when we're suffering so our first step is just knowing recognizing like oh this is suffering and can you be aware um
that suffering or stress is happening when it is and if so that's actually great it's great to be able to know
that's happening um most of us don't feel excited when we recognize suffering is present but that's actually a really
um important thing to see because if duka is present that means craving or
aversion are present um so you can see that if youve teased apart that object or circumstance
from your own reactivity you're seeing the difference between the circumstance say uh fixating on how your roommate
doesn't take out the trash and you're teasing that apart from your own aversion that's the t is the T the te in
raft that I talked about before the meditation um so we're able to see the difference
between the object the thing that we don't want and the the aversion itself
so our once we see oh yeah aversion is here um then we can practice um R A
those first letters of raft that I talked about earlier we can you know clearly recognize
it we can allow it to be present not judging oursel for it uh not going to
war with our aversion or our wanting and then we can f feel it in the
body feel it in the heart and mind so for me the often there's a lot of
tightness in the chest or the belly you know point of contraction somewhere in the body maybe in the throat uh in the
forehead the temples the jaw um so see what you recognize or see
what you feel um what we often find is is that desire and aversion are actually
uncomfortable um they're kind of painful in a sense and when we can see this
really clearly and we can see this with mindfulness it starts to train the mind
heart that like ouch desire and aversion are painful like I don't want to keep
creating this this um aspect of the mind this quality of mind and it begins that
wisdom that clear seeing begins to let go of the pattern the pattern of
constantly craving constantly rejecting experience so when we um when we look at
our craving and we see we see that it's painful um and this is uh in part
because at its core um craving is an expression of um of discontent um of a a
lack of contentment so we could say you know desire it wears a thousand different
costumes you know it masquerades in all of these different ways in our life so that we barely recognize it um but
within all of the different facades um it always carries the secret message
this moment isn't quite right this moment is not
enough and this is a message of dis dissatisfaction this is you know that
the the core of duka you know like this isn't right this just isn't right um but what happens is when
we see the source of suffering in the mind that it's in the mind and not in all of the external objects There's an
opportunity for transformation um because we can train the mind so as some people say uh the
Dharma may not solve our problems um but it has the capacity to dissolve our
problems s right it can dissolve our problems when we can let go of our
craving and our
resistance so over time uh as we encounter Dua again and again and again
um we begin to see um that it's not bad news uh that it's actually the seed of
our Awakening it's it's the foundation of the pth so one of the Buddha's teachings is
called liberative dependent arising and it consists of 12 mental
states that uh that condition the mind for enlightenment um for complete freedom
from suffering and the reason I mention it is because of the first step and this
is what I find that so extraordinary about this particular teaching the very
first link the very first necessary condition in this list of 12 that ends
in Liberation is suffering suffering suffering is step
one on the path to Liberation so if we don't
suffer we don't see a reason to practice and we need to practice in
order to wake up Tibetan Monks actually have a a
prayer that they chant where they're they're actually praying for suffering
so they can have something to practice with so often we think that something's going wrong when we suffer uh but what
would it be like to meet suffering um saying oh wonderful like I'm right on
track can we meet our suffering with that sort of like oh great I have something to practice with so this is
this is our task in life in our practice in transforming uh obstacles into the way
you allowing our suffering to inspire our practice so let your suffering fuel
your practice uh as the Insight teacher Joseph Goldstein says don't waste your
suffering don't waste your suffering so remember uh as we explore
insight into Dua uh remember that the role of the three characteristics fundamentally is to teach us to let go
to let go of craving and aversion wanting and not
wanting the Thai Forest Master aan cha he used to say
um if you let go a little you will find a little peace if you let go a lot you
will find a lot of Peace if you let go absolutely you will find absolute peace
and tranquility now elsewhere in aach Cha's teaching he
also said 70 to 80% of spiritual Life Is
Knowing we're cing and not being able to let
go so that's why Insight is really helpful because it cultivates the wisdom
needed to let go of what we can't release on our own so often and we see um we see we're
clinging and we can't let go you know the heart just won't let go um we know that's what needs to happen and it's not
happening so it's it's insight into the three characteristics that provides the
wisdom to let go of what we can't let go on our own that's 70 to 80% aan cha
talks about and when uh wisdom lets go of cleaning we let go of suffering so
this is where the path takes us uh to complete peace complete
Liberation so today as you practice don't waste your suffering
allow it to inspire you to be mindful uh you know recognize your suffering see if
craving and aversion are present and if so allow it to be there uh feel it in
the body there's uh there's a sacred visitor that comes to teach all of us
this visitor is Dua and and our job is to get to know our
guest so may you notice your Dua with Clarity and kindness thank you very much
have a lovely day