yeah so I'm here at IRC the our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz California and um
I'm here for a two-day program that I'm helping to teach with Andrea fella and um 15 people we training to
be inside teachers then uh we're coming to the end of the four-year training and
it's been quite special to be here and special to be here with the volunteers
the residents and it's a really a special place to be in some of you maybe
have been here some of you maybe will think of coming on Retreat
here so so welcome and happy New
Year and here at the beginning of the year uh I'll start a extended series on
samadi on it's a kind of provisionally we it's called
concentration practice concentration states of concentration and um I almost prefer not
to use that word because it often associations with it are very different
than what is being cultivated when we cultivate Samar and then uh so there'll be what
we'll do in the med the meditations and the 15minute talks will kind of very
slowly um kind of build up the foundation foundational element ments for
somebody and um and uh whether you get
concentrated in the way that we call samade or not I'm hoping that in the process of this you'll learn a lot about
uh your capacity of attention and how to harness attention uh for yourself rather
than having it uh hijacked by all the different forces growing forces in our
society that um that are trying to uh keep your your attention hostage keep
it busy keep it activated um there's a whole attention economy now that I never would have
imagined could have existed so for the meditation this
morning uh as a beginning for this whole Adventure in
samade uh meditation a good way of beginning all meditation uh and then um you know
getting a foundation for meditation and mindfulness meditation and concentration is first to uh take a
little bit of of uh Initiative for the state the way that
you are not to just go along uh captivated by whatever state you're in
and one way to do that is to uh relax a bit to begin a meditation with uh and
it's not just the the value of relaxing but it's also the value of
lovingly um uh um kind of uh engaging or taking
control or being responsible for how you are rather than the forces of the world
dictating uh or the forces of your of uh of a unsettled mind dictating how you're
going to be so to begin harnessing your capacity sa your attention by
relaxing and that's a standard way in which I teach meditation is to relax the
body the mind the heart and then for the rest of the
meditation as a as a kind of a be a very important beginning for these weeks
we're going to be exploring somadi that uh the focus today will be on Discovery
not after the initial relaxation not being so focused on trying to do
anything yet uh getting but to really just spend the time discovering how you
are discovering State and quality of the Mind the heart the body with a
willingness to stay that simple to only oh it's like this now it's like this now
with no need to oh it's like this now and I have to fix it I have to stop it I have to be different this is not right
all that to put that aside for now so it's a process of
discovery what you might discover is you have all those kinds of ideas it
shouldn't be this way I have to make it different I'm not doing it right it should and um but in the process of
discovery it's like oh and here again you're beginning to take a certain um
initiative or certain control or certain overview of yourself without getting caught in anything and
just to discover oh it's like this now it's like this now it's like this now
and what you discover about yourself then will be the foundation that you use
for uh developing samadi and without that Discovery uh you won't have the raw
material that's needed to gather together for uh these concentrated
States so to begin then uh to assume a
meditation posture and uh and maybe there's a way
of having a somewhat alert posture that allows a deeper
relaxation than if you start with a relaxed posture if you have already taken put
yourself into the most relaxed posture you can be uh that might be nice sometimes but for
the purposes of samade and Discovery you want to have also some modum of being
alert and so to adjust your body in some way whether you're sitting on a chair
the floor lying down um that there's a kind of a an
intent intention intentional body to be yes
here now and then gently closing your eyes or if
you want to keep them open to gently clo lower your
gaze and then to take a few long and slow gentle
deep breaths and deeper breaths
expansion of the chest maybe expansion of the
belly maybe a certain kind of lifting around your shoulders as you breathe
in allows for a longer
exhale and that longer exhale
to
relax or soften in the body
and then allowing your breathing to return to normal and to continue
relaxing continuing to take a certain degree of initiative or control even
over your experience in this very simple way of continuing to relax
soften the Buddha didn't use the word relax though he used the word
calm calming of the
body in with the exhale let there be a calming a away of come through your
body that might allow the shoulders to soften
relax the belly to soften
and perhaps there can be a calming of the face a loosening relaxing of the muscles
of the face with every exhale for
maybe a softening around the eyes if the eyes feel engaged even with
the eyes closed letting the eyeballs rest in
their sockets maybe even by imagining that you're looking backwards and down
into your
body and then your
mind you don't have to go along with how the mind is
completely you can also begin softening relaxing the
mind the thinking mind the thinking
muscle maybe with a loving reassuring
attention maybe with the attitude it's okay with the exhale let the thinking
mind settle soften
relax almost as if as you exhale you're allowing the gentle pull
of gravity to settle quiet the thinking mind
[Music]
and for the final relaxation if notice that there's
somewhere in your body mind heart that is activated by whatever
emotional state you have whatever mood you're in
and not necessarily to go to try to stop being the way you
are but also not to go 100% along with how you
are but to engage in a certain degree of
sovereignty over how you
feel by relaxing any way that you're activated by how you
feel any place where there it's energized or
agitated as you exhale softening relaxing a
bit without ambition to do it a lot just a gentle
softening calming of how you are are emotionally
and then for the remainder of the meditation have this period be a time of
Discovery put aside any ideas of what you're supposed to experience as a
meditator or make happen as a meditator with every inhale
will discover recognize what's happening for you how you are in your
mind your body your heart whatever shows itself to
you and with every exhale very simple
discovery that does not involve stories explanations
reasons and causes just a simple Discovery like
you're a naturalist of your own inner life sitting
quietly noticing whatever way you
are and naturist who watches the animals in the wild without disturbing them
allowing them to be as they are to sit quietly naturalist of your
own inner life discovering seeing
recognizing without any other idea that of what meditation
is
e
for
e e
one way to practice this discovery is simply to discover where
your attention
goes almost as if you're following
attention now it goes to a sound now to thinking now to a feeling now to a body
sensation back to thinking
discover the pulls and pushes on attention and where it
goes
for
e for
e e
that
can you discover the difference
between discovering what's happening and being lost in what's
happening
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting I would like to mention that this process of
discovery of Buddhist practice is to discover that we we have
a treasure within
invaluable goodness possibilities for invaluable
Treasures of peace and happiness that can be found
within not only ourselves but they can be found in
others everyone contains Treasure of goodness
the spark of Life on which it's possible to
settle be at peace free of
unsettling and as we end this sitting May our process of
discovery help us appreciate the treasure that's found in everyone we
meet everyone is precious everyone is sacred everyone has the
capacity for an inner peace and freedom
happiness and may we live in such a way that we shine a
light on the goodness in everyone even those for whom their their public
display is not that of goodness let us discover and see what's
good in everyone so that is what grows in our
world may we see everyone's capacity to be
happy so everyone grows in happiness
may we see everyone's ability to feel at
ease safe so that they may feel at ease and
safe may we see everyone's capacity for
peace so we can support the capacity for peace
and may we appreciate everyone's ability to discover an inner
freedom and may we live in such a way to
support the growth of that inner Fe Freedom may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so hello on this uh first Monday of 2020
and happy New Year to all of you and welcome to this new series that uh I'll
be doing on titled samadi and the last few years I've been
doing a long series some of them 50 60 um sessions
long on different uh basic meditation practices that
uh our Buddhism offers I I've done it in anapanasati mindfulness of breathing the
four foundations of mindfulness and so today this year I'm going to do uh a whole series on basic
instructions and practice of samade the word samade is generally translated into English as
concentration and um it's not uncommon for people to not be very satisfied
calling it concentration because it it limits it too much and Narrows the scope
of what somebody is and also sometimes it suggests a kind of laser focus and
kind of a intensity that's a little bit intense to really um stay focused and
one pointedly focused whereas the uh samade is not a particular way of
focusing the mind it's a whole state of being it's a whole qualitatively uh uh
state of being like if you felt deeply at peace and uh the peace wouldn't be a
particular you know activity of the mind it would be something that would be integrated into your whole sense of
being your body your heart your mind so in the same way some is something that's integrated and complete and whole and
all of who we are it's a state and to call it kind of a laser
focus of the Mind actually interferes with the relaxing opening to this
General whole state and um so today it's a little bit to make some introductory remarks about
uh somat and this series we're doing and then um and then we'll just continue and
and one of the introductory marks to say is that um is that samadi is a very important uh uh uh state for deepening
Buddhist practice uh and it's very important for mindfulness practice ice
that uh the depths of mindfulness practice the full potential of it actually um requires uh a degree of
samade and the way that I understand teachings of the Buddha that uh
mindfulness practice and Samari practice Sati and Samari practice are practicing
and in integrated together as being not really two distinct practices but uh
they come along sometimes we might emphas excise more uh
the the Sade aspects of the mind sometimes more the attentional aspects
of the mind of it of mindfulness but they're both going together and they need each other and um they're both
accompanying each other um maybe not any maybe not if there the best analogy but
um the left and right foot when you're walking sometimes you step with the left
foot sometimes with the right foot and you need them both both in order to walk um if you have an inj I've had an injury
in my foot and um and it was very hard to walk um with the you know with the
one of my one of my legs so it was like I could bring the back leg when the the
the injured leg leg uh up to where my uninjured leg was but the stepping
forward always happened with you know the the uninjured leg and it was very awkward and slow to walk that way but to
walk in a fully integrated easeful way was to be able to go back and forth between the two so
um so both are needed both you both use the other and um in sod and
mindfulness so I don't want to set up a sharp dichotomy or distinction between them but for this series it's going to
be focusing on the samade mostly but a lot of mindfulness will be needed in order to engage in the samade activities
that we'll be we'll be exploring um and as we go through this
uh the plan is to do this very gradually in very very small steps some of you are
already fairly familiar with meditation practice with concentration practice and
I'm hoping that if that's the case that uh the slow steps we make putting down
the real simple elements that add up to the whole um it will be informative to
some of you who maybe never kind of never really tracked this so carefully what it took to be to enter into somat
you understand much better the Dynamics the different elements and pieces that come into
play some people have Minds that can naturally drop into deep
somat and uh and some people have Minds that are more oriented towards mindfulness and never really kind of
appreciate both of them if it's easy one or the other might not appreciate some some of the different Dynamics in the
mind and the heart that come into play that uh maybe you take for granted and
so to go through this very slowly those of you who are new to all this the slow slow steady pace of little drops of
pieces of instructions at a time maybe will allow you to follow and go along at
some point as we do this uh you might not follow the instructions but maybe
then you use your imagination to get a sense a feel for what talking about so that uh you you have a general sense of
what's going on and some point in the future this will become relevant for
you so um the um the word
samadi uh is U literally the atmology of it uh in
Sanskrit and P means more a a collecting a gathering together
a um a settling together and there are uh words that are variations of samama
that uh specifically means um collecting um sometimes uh collecting
fire wood to make a fire you're collecting that sometimes these uh uh
related words you know just grammatical variations uh can also mean uh to
settle uh to steady and so there's a settling a steadiness of the Mind a gathering of the mind and
the idea of gathering is probably one of the most important aspects of samade is
that it's not an exclusion of uh uh as it is a is
inclusion there's a feeling that all of who we are uh is now
included uh but not in a way that's fragmented not in a way that's um uh
going off in different directions but rather it's gathering together to work
together and be coordinated uh doing the same for the same purpose the same intention everything is here and
present but the um uh it's a it's a huge process to man to to settle in to steady
in to gather in everything and part of the reason a big pro project is that uh
It Go so much against uh the grain U of how Minds often work even in time of the
Buddha it was hard for people to develop samade because their minds was uh he used the word monkey mind that just the
mind was constantly uh the idea of a monkey mind is that um it's like a
monkey that's swinging from the trees that uh as soon as it grabs one branch it's already reaching for the next
branch and so it's the mind as soon as soon as it's one place it's reaching for the next
place and um so even the time of the Buddha that was true and I imagine it's
even more true now in the last 20 years with the Advent of uh te these these
smartphones and screens that were on tablets and um that have in some ways
unsettled the mind that have activated the mind so it's always searching always surfing the web the next thing the next
thing and uh many people have pointed out that the modern mind has lost its
capacity it's lost its span of attention the attention span has decreased get bored more there's more
like an Impulse like what's next you what's else is there and and rather than settled on one thing and just doing that
one thing it's like what's next next next and um and uh it's now there's been all
kinds of studies and research done on uh the economics of attention the the
attention economy that uh there's people who are paid a lot of money to plan and
organize and create a Content that will
get you to click get you to look get you to move on um to keep your attention to
have you return to look again what's happening what's happening and um you
know I've noticed and myself I'm sure some of you as well have this issue that uh um there's an idle moment and to grab
for the phone to see is there an email is there a news or something they're constantly being stimulated by what's on
a screen and the idea that of sitting and doing nothing and being quiet which
uh I think human beings had much greater capacity to do in outside of these
modern technological worlds that many of us live in is becoming a uh unavailable
State and so somi is uh is a return to a deep natural
state of wholeness of subtleness of an open attention which is not being driven
by a thirst for more thirst for thirst for content thirs for experiences thirds
for search for um serot rush or dopamin rush or something that you get get get
discover discover discover want want want and I like to think of it as a
process of being turned inside out uh it's a challenge to turn the the the
stream the flow of the Mind from wanting and attention going and moving and being
outwardly directed or directed towards fantasy and thoughts and anxieties to
turn it around around and inside out almost to settle deeply into ourselves
and to discover that we get turned inside out and there's a whole new way
to live in the world a way where the mind's anxiety the mind's reactivity the
mind's overactivity uh is completely settled and quiet and the source of our life
arises for some deeper place of peace and well-being and wholeness Within in
and the mind is now a vehicle of support a ve a channel for this deep settled
peace and happiness that we're capable of rather than the mind being what drives us so maybe the analogy could
be uh rather than having what's on our smartphone
screen be where we live uh uh we actually
live settled in a very deep steadied way in our inner life in our hearts and our
bellies and our mind here and that's what drives that's where the engine
that's where the source of Vitality comes from that's where we find our peace and
well-being and to make the transition from a scattered activated
agitated um fragmented mind to a mind that's steadied
stable uh gathered and whole uh can be a slow process and a sometimes a very
challenging POS process but it's a really worthwhile process and so we'll
go through this and maybe discover um some you'll discover something more about what I like to call the Natural
State a healthy state that many of us have lost tract with that uh is
invaluable for living a wise life so this will be the focus
Sadi uh the Gathering Together the healing of the fragmented self into the
whole self for the purpos of a deep
peace so thank you and um tomorrow I'll be back at IMC and um and I'm happy to
be with you on this beginning of the year