good morning good day good evening this is the fourth of five talks and
meditations on the five elements or five qualities or properties of embodied
experience as they can support insight and today we'll be covering air
so um the main focus for our meditation today will be
on breathing
the invitation is to take a step back
mentally and feel into this body
maybe take a couple of longer slower breaths
noticing the feeling of air on your skin
and allowing your attention to move inward downward
exhaling tension and inhaling a sense of awareness
then allowing the breathing to be natural
normal
and noticing however your breath is for you today
is there warmth or cool in the air as it comes through the nostrils
it's on the throat
noticing a sense of motion in the chest and rib cage
noticing especially movement of your life's breath
in your diaphragm and abdomen
the flow of inb breath and out breath
noting perhaps gently in the mind
rising as the chest or abdomen rise
falling as the exhale happens
[Music]
noticing moisture or dryness of the air as it becomes breath
feeling
your body rooted grounded in the moment
and especially attuning
to the language of the body the vibrancy
maybe a sense of stretching or pulling on the inb breath
releasing relaxation from the outreath
noticing the very beginning of the inb breath
the different changes in the abdomen diaphragm and chest
through the whole inhale rising expanding
tuning into the feeling of fullness at the top of the inb breath
and then that feeling of release softening
falling chest falling abdomen
warmth of air being breathed out
allowing any thoughts of future or past
to be known acknowledged with kindness and to fade to the periphery
inviting awareness mindfulness to the forefront of attention
this breath this moment of breath
this moment of warmth or cool motion or stillness
heaviness or lightness
immersed in the momentum
if perhaps the attention is here just a little more
the invitation is to really dedicate the mind the meditation to the details
of moving movement and air
noticing the difference between the beginning of the inb breath
a few pulses in as the abdomen or chest rise
all of the different sensations of expansion
as the lungs fill
tiny moment of transition where the inb breath ends and the
outreath begins
and noticing perhaps even noting the falling of the chest and belly
back down through the entire life cycle of the
outreath
resting when it occurs in that small still point
at the end of the outreath
softening allowing
the cycle of movement the cycle of life to continue
in the last moments of our meditation together
the invitation is to feel into all of your experience
movement and stillness warmth and cool groundedness
or lightness
moisture or dryness and open to the heart and mind
how you are in this moment
especially attuning to any benefits peacefulness
attention calm kindness
and soaking in them letting them percolate through your system
nourish your heart
and from that place
casting your internal gaze outwards towards all the others your
life touches directly and indirectly
wishing that they may be happy healthy
safe peaceful at ease and free
may all beings benefit from our practice here together
and may our practice be a cause and condition for greater love
liberation and peace in the world
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
so welcome to this fourth of five talks
on the five elements or five um qualities properties that we're
covering this week in direct experience and more metaphorically inspirationally
to support insight so so far we've covered earth water and
fire and today we are on air or wind
and um here we're starting to move into territory where the the um translation
of datu the poly to element starts not to make quite so much sense of course
air element you could think of it as air molecules that makes total sense and it
can also be more of a property a potential indirect experience
the ancient teachings describe the direct experience of air being movement
pushing pulling stretching expanding contracting
just like I read that meditation where the chest the belly or the diaphragm might expand contract rise or fall
the function according to the ancient teachings is to convey that air or wind conveys
which makes sense if you think about kites for example or birds kiting soaring
more fancifully if we combine the air element with the heat element
fire element we might get the conveyance of a hot air balloon or a blimp
so how it shows up in meditation is that movement of breath movement of
the chest or abdomen or belly and also in feeling the contact of the breath on
the inside of your nose or your throat your lungs
and air is of course the literal experience of breath and in stiller
moments of practice very quiet moments it's actually possible to feel the
transpiration of the air without any movement of
breathing at all it's kind of cool
there's also um in the ancient discourses different kinds of sensations
and different kinds of feeling to inve great and not pleasant unpleasant neither are likened to winds from the
north south east and west that all kinds of different feelings can be associated
with those winds and speaking of wind internal and
external contemplation can be particularly evocative for practice with this element
playing with the exploration when does the air around you become breath
and when does that internal breath return to air not an intellectual answer
to that or a conceptual answer but a felt sense when does it happen
in your own experience
external wind a breeze on our face or wind all around
us if we're in a windy or gusty area meditating outside or just sitting outside
that can be a very powerful meditation object
there's this inconstancy of the touch of wind on our skin or even the in the sort
of indirect feeling of it through clothes or a jacket that
is a direct experience teacher of ana
and constancy
and not a few practitioners that I've known including myself have meditated in
the breeze and the wind and then when the wind stops there's a very interesting process that
can happen in your own meditation that constant contact stopping can allow
a powerful dropping away of body
and then a little bit more shall we say an emotional or mental
exploration of this is notice for yourself
differences and how your heart how your mind how your body respond
to breezes or wind based on conditions they could be conditions of warmth or
cool or humidity or dryness dustiness or clean clarity sweet breezes with perfume
of flowers or they could be more internal conditions
the same wind one day might feel bracing invigorating
and another day feel overwhelming or like too much
so this brings us to other air and wind simileies that the Buddha used
the eight worldly winds is a very famous teaching also translated as the eight
worldly vicissitudes which are pleasure and pain loss and
gain praise and blame and status and
disrepute or fame and disrepute it's sometimes glossed
so I don't know about you but many many people in my life and at many points in
my life those have been quite consequential for me in terms of emotional life responses
general attitude and then as practice begins to deepen
as wisdom begins to gather as maturity begins to happen
those vicissitudes those winds don't blow us around quite so much
but instead there's a stability mindfulness can be like the ballast
to hold us steady in fact the Buddha talked about a wise person being like a
large boulder in the wind unmoved by praise or blame
or the other eight worldly winds for that matter a steady friend is also talked about
this way a true spiritual friend who doesn't abandon you in bad times or
flatter you and try to snuggle up close just because times are good and there's something to gain
a fully awakened person in a hot is described as completely unruffled by the
worldly winds or any wind for that matter
so we see that wind air element
is associated with more than just the sensations of pushing pulling movement
conveying it's also about pushing and pulling
forces of life and the way we move the way we convey ourselves navigate through
the physical and metaphorical winds
and there's wind power so the Buddha advised his son Rahula
to make his meditation like air like wind if you make your meditation like wind
sun agreeable and disagreeable contacts will not invade your heart and mind and
remain and he goes on to say if disgusting or
unwanted things are thrown at the air or wind
they don't stay they don't stick
but instead
there's no response so this ties into another teaching of
the Buddha to practitioners in daily life about wind and air
and that is not to respond
not to take it personally to allow the wind just to blow through it said that
wind is not trapped by a net and we can consider that the net of our
opinions the net of our views the net of the way we want things to be
and instead the wind just untrapped
so we can be free like the wind
so we'll close with a poem from Rosemary
Watla Tramer wonderful um indigenous American poet
and this ties together um some of the elements the properties we've been
talking about this week you'll see
she writes "Sometimes a person wakes believing they are a storm
it's hard to deny it what with all the rain pouring out of the gutters of the mind all the gusts blowing through all
the squalls all the gray but by afternoon it seems obvious they
are a garden about to sprout by night it's clear they are a moon
luminous radiant faithful
that's the danger I suppose of believing any frame
let me believe then in curiosity in wonder in change
let me trust how essential it is to stumble into the trough of the unknown
and marvel how trough becomes wings becomes faith becomes math
let me trust and certainty is a sacred path
so thank you SA for your attention and your assignments should you choose
to accept them in the next 24 hours is are to notice
how does including awareness of the sensations of motion show up for you in
your daily life and notice what what helps you weather the
vicissitudes the changing winds even the storms of life
so thank you may your practice sustain you through
all weather