uh thank you to all of you for being here um so my name is Lean Shut my
pronouns are she and they anyone new today tmc all right special welcome to
both of you all right i don't know about you all but um
I've been really tired lately and uh yesterday I took a nap it was a
little late it was like after 3:00 so my girlfriend and I thought okay we take what we like to call a nano nap just a
short nap you know because we want we don't sleep that well but we we know we shouldn't nap so we could sleep better
but we were so tired um and I will say that um when I
lived at the monastery I trained myself to take nano naps um uh because we didn't have a lot of
time um but it was very hot and tiring so I uh lie on my back when I want to
take a nano nap and then when I hear myself have a little snore then I wake
up and usually it's like 8 to 10 minutes and um I noticed yesterday I was so
tired that I did it three times and each time I woke up I realized I had so much
anxiety so much anxiety in my chest and uh a real pressure
and just tightness and I know that um you know
for the conditions of the world and uh to me and the and the nation and I
would say to me having lived in Egypt the stuff in
the Middle East is especially hard right now and um so
um I've done my share also of um destruction distraction to from the
unease from the worry from the anxiety and
um I like to do jigsaw puzzles
um as a wholesome way of distraction so I'm going to talk to you
about jigsaw puzzles uh this could be found in suta
number No I'm [Laughter] kidding no uh a very thick uh tome in my
life but uh not not this who does um so you know my my um I I'm adopted and my
father used to love to do puzzles so we we did it kind of was the only family thing that we did that um in retrospect
didn't have a lot of um right and wrong good or bad and uh
it's we you know we do have a form though right and um I love doing puzzles and um when I go to do a puzzle I get
actually I love doing puzzles during the pandemic it was so great right do you
guys have exchange of puzzles during the pandemic your family knowing other people yeah so whenever I get a box I'm
really very excited and um you know you you dump out the boxes the pieces and
it's a little tedious that part where you turn it all you know up so that you can see the the picture um and then
um you want that because you need to see what the picture is right um and then um
there's a lot of sorting and evaluating a lot of discriminating and discerning that's
needed right uh in my family we gather the edge pieces separately and you put
that together first right that's that's how we go about it and um and
um there's a certain amount of um excitement and then confidence because
you start to see pieces right that you're like "Oh I know where that one's going to go." and um and and I really
have a sense of I'm going to be able to do this a lot of confidence this is going to be so easy it's going to be so
fun and um so for me it's a really
uh exciting and fun time and I actually even because I like
it so much and uh I even start to imagine when it's finished when I even
when I'm opening it up I'm like in that last piece is always so satisfying isn't it so already that's there and uh so I'm
working towards that satisfaction now um as I just shared in
in my family we mostly just sort the edge pieces and then the other pieces and then we put together the edge right
away and um this um puzzle that I got um
which I got at Goodwill um was a puzzle of birds with birch
branches um and some you know branches coming out i'm
not I don't know birds or trees very well so there were six birds and I'll
just say there was a cardinal i could identify a cardinal um and then a a blue
J um and then I don't know what the other four
birds were but there were some black ones with stripes and uh yellow ones
right um so uh someone was also doing the puzzle
with me and I'll just say their name is Jane just to use a name and uh uh she
was saying that her family you know when they sorted after they finished they also then put it into bags so then you
don't have to go searching for the edge pieces again and I thought "Oh that's a good idea right that's a good idea." Um
and so uh as I sorted them into categories um I put the red ones in a pile right
the yellow ones in a pile what looks like maybe you see little eyes or you
see the beak and you start to put them into piles like that and that's that's how we do it and um so as we go we need
to differentiate and and actually we start to see more and more of the complexity
of what just you know is a cardo or a j or yellow bird um or birds um and um
sometimes some of the pieces seem very clear and some of the pieces are really
um blurry and you also start to see the subtlety of what makes up you know the
feathers like a a yellow bird can also have some ochre some uh darker color
brighter colors right so and at first that's kind of the fun
part and then as you start to put together it's some point it becomes anx
it's so fun at the beginning when you're doing it and then two you see two pieces and you just know you just know they go
together and you click them together and it's so satisfying and so you start to put the
bird together um but then at a certain point it isn't so easy
and as we're looking for different ways to um put the picture together
um we have different ways right at one point Jane said to me "I need a piece
with two heads and three arms you know and I give her a piece."
And she said "No no I want you know the two heads to be this way and the two
arms to be like this." and you gave me you know two heads this way and you know so that's not the right one and I said
well I you know I like to go by color more than you know the shape of it but I
thought okay all right that's different way now also started to realize um how
is it that we go looking for the pieces uh do we go looking for the
missing piece so here's this cardinal and I go looking for the piece piece that I think is
missing is it from a sense of the the energy that goes to look for that
because I could get really obsessive like I have to find this piece do you do that with a puzzle or not yeah you just
get obsessed in this one little corner or one image and so is there a sense
then that is there a sense of lack until that missing piece is found
is a way to go looking for the piece that fits about that click the
connection that happens is it going to look for the
right piece that's the wrong piece which is the right piece which is
the perfect piece so you start to I start to realize that
there's an attitude to what I'm doing it's not just
a matter of the task or the doing itself i mean besides the excitement obviously
that one was easy is a attitude of doing this puzzle
one of sharing is it competitive
is it taking over or is it being too helpful oh here's a piece here's a piece
right am I offering too many pieces to someone because often time you know you
say "Okay I'll take this bird and you take that bird i'll do this corner."
Right and then there's also you know I like to do like a thousand pieces right
so it takes more than one day i I have to admit that sometimes I've been I give
myself a whole day and I can do a puzzle a thousand pieces in a day those are such great days for me um
but in general uh they take several days you know and when you do it with other people
um you know people start to say I'm doing this one and I'm doing that one and um uh someone was doing the cardinal
and um they weren't there some of the time so I found a piece and I put it in
there and then I found another piece and I put it in there and I thought "Oh wait
wait maybe I shouldn't be working on this because again is this being too helpful is this doing something to the
point in which um I'm taking
over?" And then there's also um you know when you start to think it goes to one
bird but you realize that it starts to go with other birds especially when a
lot of puzzles they you know for the most part unless you choose like a 100 piece or 300 piece they they want to
make it a my idea I am not a puzzle maker I they want to make it kind of hard for you so right so even though you
think you can tell the distinction they start to blend so oftent time you have in this case like I had three birds
working at once and um uh the other person was
doing a bird that of a similar color and uh so I offered them one and they were like no no that's your puzzle there you
should keep on doing that right and so where's the sense of who's whose whose
part is which so how is it that we're engaging
with this um and and then when they said your puzzle they they walked away and I
thought well what what happened what happened here um where is it that when
we're engaging with something and it starts to be not so easy the pieces
aren't clicking together what you think is this bird is in this bird um when is
it or how is it that we um stop
engaging in the activity or is it that sometimes you
know you think oh especially on days in which it's um you know you're spending
time with someone and of course my my girlfriend and I are very busy these
days and um we're both essentially gig workers right we go where we're offer
work uh or you know teachings in my case and so we have very little time but
sometimes when we have time together you know it's very hard to go what do you want to do you know what do you want to
do what do you want to do and so sometimes you know she'll do a puzzle
because she knows I want to but then at some point it feels like is she engaging
just to like you know give in and So sometimes when she
starts to go off I have a feeling like oh maybe maybe I'm kind of not forcing
her by any mean but am I is there a way in
which the interest in doing this is you know not being um that's not hers
and so what at what point does it become um staying against not really against
your will you know we're talking about jigsaw puzzle but when is it that it isn't feel so smooth right and so what
is it that um when is it that we walk away and start to do something right maybe to go get something to eat maybe
to um you know some of it's just maybe you're hungry but but also that
awareness of when is it that I need to I divert my attention
from what's here we're moving
away sometimes though the moving is to get a different perspective you know I
generally like to do my puzzle from you know if the picture is of trees going
this way I want to be here so I see the whole picture but sometimes it helpful to go from a different angle isn't it to
look at the picture so that you can have a different sense of what might might go there what pieces might
fit from a different perspective
and then there's the um you know the way in which sometimes I'm so frustrated
that I will walk away for sure and then of course again if a puzzle is quite
quite many pieces we we're not doing it the whole time so um a lot of time we uh
you know go away and we come back and then I find myself just looking at the puzzle and uh looking and finding a
piece that's been missing you know oftent time when we do the edge we can't find all the edge pieces and you just
keep looking but you just cannot see them and then you go away and then you come back and you find one and you're
like ah that's it and when you find one then you have that energy or I have that energy in which I go okay I found that
one so there are more here I will find more and then again you find yourself
obsessive so I go away and then it becomes this this sense of ooh maybe
it's lucky to like go away and then come back so this sense of when is it that
I'm this is my doing and when is it that I let go in
some sense you know it became kind of a joke like it's lucky we we should just go away and then we come back it is it
just fresh eyes I don't know do you know but and we I know my girlfriend and I sometime we impute the sense of luck is
it really luck I don't know but it feels that
way then there's also you know when I uh doing this blue
J i had all the blue pieces in front of me and I'm putting together and they
don't fit you know keep on doing then they're pretty limited number of pieces
and so then I go to the you know those piles where you're not quite sure where any what what is and I keep looking for
pieces that I know go to the blue jay so I just keep looking and keep looking
and yet all the pieces are in front of
me all the pieces are in front of me
right so maybe you already got it but what I'm
trying to point here is that there are
patterns of thinking and perceiving
uh condition ways of processing and being with information and being with situations
i mostly think I go to do a a jigsaw puzzle because of the content right
there's a picture you get it you know jigsaw puzzle has a picture it's a very clear what the end result is and so and
it's about putting it together it's a task and yet the process of how that
picture comes together how you engage with it
is shows itself in the doing now I want to be really
clear right what did I list some is it looking for a missing piece a sense of
lack is it about being competitive is it about being you know mine and
yours right now I want to be very clear that um noticing these habitual patterns of
either perceiving or thinking um one is not better than the
other right noticing them is the key right
there is something in Buddhism called uh personality view right
sakayai so how is it that when you you make contact with something and
then all your habitual thinking around it
your poncha you could say your grouping of stories that go with it and then you
solidify it into a sense of identity and sometimes when we
recognize a habitual pattern then we go I'm a competitive person oh no I'm
greedy right oh no I'm so right and wrong or of course you're doing it to
the other people that you're doing the puzzle with
so I would like to say that practice isn't so much of figuring out whether
I'm a greedy person or a competitive person it isn't so much um to
solidify against a sense of self right uh it's more about being
aware and open in that moment of perceiving a
pattern and maybe not rush so much to interpret what it
means can we stay there and see and
investigate what what is right there what happens right there do I
contract do I shame be it self or
other do I um what is the movement of both heart and mind at that moment
you know I know that um with practice I think that
um a dharmic moment a time in which I am practicing well is when I'm
compassionate and open very classically we could say without hate greed or
delusion um and yet mostly in practice I find I hate greed and delude a
lot right and so to me that's a dharmic
moment that's the opportunity
that's the fun
really in some ways our practice isn't actually it's great it's great to
come to a dharma talk or a meditation or a
chant or service but a dharmic moment is when
we wake up Right we have a sense of what is
happening a clarity of knowing and we we rush to figure out
what we should do about
that and I'm not even telling you that this is what you should do i'm suggesting I'm suggesting that that
moment is a moment can you just stay open and noticing what happens right
then very much in sensation very much in the quality of
feelings by that I mean emotions very much in the quality
of thinking
And there is also a sense of a choice in
that moment it isn't purely a moment of
awareness it's important and in that moment you have a choice of how you
interact with what you're aware of and how do you keep on interact with
what you're aware of right even I know when I think well what
happens right then I think of a whole process right I need to figure out the
pattern I need to go need to go like this right and sometimes we see that as we practice but the and the practice
isn't to necessarily look for that all the time right so it's actually what is here then
what is here then what is here then what is
here i don't know about you but in the meditation obviously I'm giving a dharma
talk so I think about the dharma talk then I go what is
here i think about you know I'm having lunch with someone afterwards so I
brought lunch but it's in the fridge and lunch I want to remember the lunch you
know so I worry about that and then I go oh what's
here what's this moment of you know there's a practice of
going ah anxiety when I go lunch right certainly and in some ways I'm saying
that that you know is part of this puzzle thing and there's Also what is
right here what is right here what is right
here so it's the same heart and it's the same
mind doing a cross word puzzle sorry a jigsaw puzzle and the sitting
down to do the jigsaw puzzle and the doing of the jigsaw puzzle and the
getting up from the jigsaw puzzle and the
interaction about what you do with the cross jigsaw puzzle obviously I have
crossword puzzle in my mind so every
moment is an opportunity to be
aware and not a task there's no having to finish in some
way the puzzle i mean in some ways you know it's a
um it's a way I you know I'm also aware that doing a jigsaw puzzle is a way of
not really control i haven't maybe I'm just waking up to that part of myself
around a jigsaw puzzle that is about control well I'm just noticing that right now because I was going to say you
know to do a jigsaw puzzle um you buy the picture you already know you already
know what's what's the end result maybe it's also about what which ones you find
interesting to put together you know my father loved those ones that are like
this in the 80s so remember all right there was one of the stairs going to he liked those kind
enough and then also people like to give him puzzle you know you know how dads are the very limited things you feel you
can give them so you know one time we got you know a black cat with two yellow eyes was big
square one so much black so much black
I've just I do not like those kind of puzzles I I'll confess actually I wasn't
I was going to add this part but I'll confess because you my favorite kind of
puzzles are so busy so busy like a yard sale puzzle you know those yard sale
puzzles or the garage that's just filled with things and I know I like it because
hey there are many little things I can put together and then they're done right
and so that's fun to me to go from thing to things right so obviously my mind is inclined towards
certain ways of being with conditions right and
that's okay when I'm doing a jigsaw puzzle at least when I do it's for fun it's it's
not it's not a challenge in the sense of you know I have to do something
hard and is it is it that wanting to know what is going to be the end result
again that last piece is so
satisfying so how we do a jigsaw puzzle or how I do a jigsaw puzzle is really
about engaging in the
pieces in the heart and the mind as I am doing that and with others
the thing is also puzzles come to you even if you go to buy one unless you you
know buy the wrapped one like you go to Goodwill and even it has tape around it
or saran wrap you can get home and there are pieces
missing what happens then so maybe maybe we
think maybe you already have a jigsaw picture of your rest of your day
that you're going to go and find the pieces to put in and who you're going to do it
with and maybe you have a jigsaw puzzle view of the
world and how the image that you would like it to
be and that's okay you already have
it might as well be okay with it
and how it comes together
is and how you respond as you interpret how it comes
together to me is practice which actually isn't
different from living
maybe the difference as a practitioner is there is there an
awareness of what is here what is the hearts and mind
response what is the hearts and mind allowing
for input and what is the heart and mind as it
negotiates the view we have
chosen and the mirrored things that come forth and reveal themselves to
us thank you for
listening all right are there any pieces you'd like to share with
[Music] me and I always invite people maybe a
little shy maybe you wouldn't be the first one to talk to so give it a try but it's not
it's a it's a choice
actually Lean um your talk really moved me um particularly because um my brother
got Alzheimer's and he at the beginning of Alzheimer's he was very very good at jigsaw puzzles he could do ones that I
couldn't do and then of course as the disease progressed he had to do simpler
and simpler ones and eventually he couldn't do them at all in fact I
remember a moment when we had the edge pieces there and he took one out and put
it in the middle and I thought "Oh dear." Okay it's not about
completing the puzzle it's about being together and um eventually he got to a
point where he couldn't put uh words together in a sentence but he would say the pieces the pieces and uh so it's
just your your talk is making me think of my brother in very fond ways and
thank you thank you Martha i feel it in my heart that story thank you
hi um tell me your name please oh I'm my name is Ken hi Ken and uh thank you for
the talk you know in in part of your talk you'd mentioned the decisions or making a
choice can you expand on that in in terms
of like you know you're you're going through and doing the jigsaw puzzle and
uh you you find a piece and you decide what you're going to do with it
and how that relates to the dharma talk and
well that's a lot to be said about choice um let let me see if I can frame it in a way that
maybe resonates for what what your question is in some ways I
know that um I see the world as like a
jigsaw puzzle sure sometimes I think oh I choose an image
And um and then I say "Oh I've made a choice to work in this section." And I
think it's useful because there's so much here right especially when um in some ways I go to do a jigsaw
puzzle because things feel overwhelming maybe now now I'm getting my control thing in a little bit here
right because this is something I can do something about right and I actually can
for myself can have fun doing it but noticing when it doesn't become fun as
part of a moment of choice but it so at first we approach things by saying do I
have a choice or not and then for many of us we think oh I don't have a choice here right even
though we've picked the p the picture and we say I'm going to work on this
section part of practice is realizing when does that section that you made the
choice when does it that you think you don't have a choice anymore it doesn't work it doesn't fit i
can't put this together and then you start to What do you do then right do you go off to do
another piece and you know that's not bad like in a jigsaw puzzle we can say oh that's just I'm going off to do over
here and in some way our practice is that we say there's certain things that you focus on
right in my family we focus on the border right first so there are some
parameters of how we can view and certainly you know Buddhism will give
you a view the the fornable truth is the view of Buddhism right they're suffering
their origins are suffering uffering there or causes right and then there's the end of suffering and then the
eightful path so in some ways we're we can be given a view but Buddhism isn't actually um that's just the map but the
ter the and the the the doing the traveling is where you start to see
oh how do I relate to the view of the world right and with
practice there's there's several ways of talking about you could say I need to keep on until I understand if I have
chosen this view of the world right i keep on meeting it with
the teaching of how to view buddhism gives you a teaching of how to view
right but the and the practice is not that there there's skillful ways and
unskillful ways for sure and hopefully it has less greed hate and delusion that would
be the main thing in Buddhism right if when we have a choice we go
towards non- greed or renunciation uh I hate greed um so greed
is renunciation hate is um meta right so towards goodwill instead of ill will and
then towards karuna or compassion instead of cruelty right so yes in some way that's it but the the
doing or the understanding that you always have a choice right because what
is renunciation i could I could tell you what the sut says with some notes you
know like what is what is renunciation but until you go and practice it and
realize what kind of choice you make and pay attention to what might be the
result that might be the other thing so don't forget the first no truth is really the the eight-fold path to
understand sorry the the way to understand the first of the eight-fold
path is skillful understanding or skillful view of the world which is what
the four noble truths and and this is the part that people forget
karma karma is the big view the big big
big view and the big big view that's dependent upon causes and
conditions right so and causes and
condition is dependent upon choice volion karma means action
volitional action actually so it's not just passive action we might think that things come to us and we're we're
passively receive them but in each moment we have a choice about what we do about it hatred certainly can come our
way and we can be taught hatred without a doubt we're all taught hatred we're
all taught hatred i have not met a person who has not been taught hatred
whether they become enlightened from that something else but we're all taught hatred what do we do at that moment what
do we do sure there's teaching to help us but and in that moment we have a
choice and yes we have teachings to help us know how to make better choices or
the choices towards nonharming and some of that has to do with really having a sense of what is the motivation
which is a second part of the eight-fold path right skillful thinking which is
act the wisdom part which is actually thinking is not passive in Buddhism thinking is always purposive because our
thinking becomes beliefs which then goes into the sila section of the A-fold path
which is the interactive skillful speech skillful action and skillful livelihood or living I like to say so that our
thinking is really more um per um I like to say motivation because it your
thinking drives you that's why I like the word motivation it gives you both the aspiration and it gives you both the
drive to do it gil likes attitude attitude to me I like attitude but to me
that feels a little bit more big you know I have an you know I have a attitude which which I can become
certainly i like motivation because I feel like oh there's a little bit more wiggle room right uh attitude feels a
little bit like a little tight you know but then it can get that for sure does that answer your question i'm
I'm in in many ways yes okay yeah it was very you know choice is so big right
choice is so big there is free will in
Buddhism for sure thank you so Lean I don't know if you'll
be able to stick around and talk to people afterwards sure for a little bit before lunch yes okay which I need to
remember thank you so much thank you thank you
everyone do we dedicate the merit or
Okay let's dedicate the merit all right
uh for any merit we are crew this morning we dedicate to
ourselves let nonharming love and
compassion center us and guide us as we meet the conditions of our lives
be it in a jigsaw puzzle or the rest of the
world this we wish for all beings and the 10 directions and the three
times thank you very much have a beautiful day