so hello and good morning having been away for a couple of weeks
that Overlook some of the different settings that have to be created for this YouTube
broadcast I'm very happy to be back here and be with you and to continue with
this series on samade and it does feel like a bit of a
gap between over these two weeks so it might be good to kind
of um maybe review or start slowly again
this week and um from the very beginning of
the Samar series I emphasize the that the foundation of it is to First
discover first realize or notice how we are that we're not trying to override
ourselves we're not trying to bypass ourselves with somebody but in a sense in a certain
kind of way to go through US ourselves and so to discover what's here
in our body mind and heart but that that how we discover it
is almost more important than what we discover the how is to be at ease to not
judge to not react to have a lightness in the knowing and the Discover
Discovery and the checking it out not trying to make anything happen
or just just see and the how we are mindful the how
we are
focusing is so important for somadi if we if we Overlook if we don't
notice how we are the how actually makes it can make it either harder or easier
to become deeply settled and by discovering how we
are two things are possible one is that we can we can
start um we can calm bring a sense of
calmness Tranquility to how we are so that the
natural process of coming to equilibrium natural process of healing
of settling has a chance somebody has a lot to do with um allowing a natural process
of settling to work its way through
us and the other is to um uh to discover
the process of discovery is one of one of the ways to come into a fullness of
being that Samar again is not a bypass but it's you want to really have a
fullness atten Global awareness as if all of who we are is included and comes
into harmony as we meditate so to assume a meditation
posture and to
either lower your gaze relaxing your
eyes or closing your eyes and softening the eyes and the eye
sockets and to begin the process of discovery
just notice how you are whatever way that appears for
you but being careful for how you discover how you
notice can you notice in an open
way can you notice in a way that doesn't make anything a problem
as if what you notice can benefit from the Simplicity of how you
know
it and if you kind of step back in a sense to have a global
awareness of yourself what do you notice how are
you and can you be aware of it kindly gently
openly the how we're aware so important
allowing that part of you that is silent that part of you that's not
involved in a lot of thinking and judging to be gently aware globally
aware of yourself
and then
to gently take a few longer and deeper
breaths not too much but enough to feel it kind of more
full connection to your torso your rib cage
your
belly and as you exhale to relax the
body to calm to let there be a calming effect through your whole system
letting your breathing return to
normal and continue on the exhale to soften
relax while on the inhale you discover you know more
fully something about how you
are for
and then again to have a global awareness of your
body in whatever way that's easy for you either your attention can just
wander around or is as if you have an overview
of the whole thing
including an overview of how your mind is your thinking mind as if the thinking mind is part of
the whole not pulled away or separated
and as you exhale to let there be a calming of the
thinking
mind for
and then finding your
way to the end of your
exhale as if with the
exhale you're being led to the last place deep
inside where the exhale you feel the
exhale maybe down to the grounding place the settling
place from where then the inhale begins
in the middle of your whole
being let let yourself come to rest at the end of the
exhale maybe even having a moment pause before you breathe
in half a moment
allowing the inhale to begin rise out of the grounding
place the settling place
deep within your
torso e
for
for for
at the end of the exhale a slight
pause and then as you breathe
in
feel a growing fullness of your body as you breathe in
as if your whole body is participating in the
inhale and your whole body is relaxing
settling on the
exhale
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to feel again your Global being
become aware of a global sense of being here in your
body and to discover how it's different now than at
the beginning
and to expand that Global sense of attention beyond your body into the room
you're in location you're in out into the wider
world and in the middle of it all continue with breathing
as if the breathing begins at that subtle spot grounding place
within and expand and the world expands from
there and returns there on the
exhale and between the exhale and
inhale maybe a momentary
Stillness and from that Stillness as the breathing inhale
expands so expanding Circles of gazing upon the world
kindly Be Be Still inwardly
Still and gaze Upon This World
kindly how we're aware of the world is as important or more
important than what were aware
of to be aware of the world
kindly may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may all beings be touched by
kindness and may our our kindness spread
out into the world
[Music]
[Music] thank
you e
so hello everyone and welcome to this uh ongoing series on
Som we had a two two we break as I was
mostly at our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz during this time and
um and now I'm happy to be back and it's a bit of a gap so I'd like
to just a little bit um kind of kind of start
over uh with meditation in general but also with especially with samade there's
something invaluable about always feeling like you're starting over so that you're not measuring or
looking for something or trying to tap into something too
quickly so that you sit down to just be with yourself as you are to discover how
you are because it's very easy in a life
busy life full life scared life angry
life to view ourselves our world
partially to only be connected to part of who we are and to enter into
somadi really want to be connected to all of who we are because samadi is a
process of unification it's a process of gathering us elv together so that all parts of who
we are can be working together in harmony and um and so in the beginning
of this series I talked about somadi being a temple and that we're entering the
temple and uh we want to bring all of ourselves along and uh and we want to do it
carefully with respect with kindness with a certain kind of of uh humility
or we're not
storming a fortress we're not storming and aggressively trying to attain
something we're going with respect and care and almost as if Dharma willing the
doors of the temple will open and we're bringing all of ourselves
along uh just like if you go to a literal to a sacred place all of you goes with you
and some sacred places some places that have tremendous Tranquility or peace or
sense of inspiration to be there it can actually kind of our whole body kind of
can kind of be awakened or tingle or feel inspired and feel included feel the
calm of the place and so this ability to feel our whole
body to calm our whole body to settle ourselves the Buddha's instructions
for um first foundational instructions beginning instructions in mindfulness
and in anapanasati mindfulness of breathing is to
um breathe mindfully be present for your breathing feel the whole body
and then relax the body calm the body and when we feel the whole body
part of what we're feeling is the reactivity the tensions in the body the holding patterns the effect of our
karmic actions and um and uh the challenging aspects of our
body one for the Buddha is recommendation is to bring a sense of
calm to it let it bring Tranquility hold it calm it settle it like you would if
someone is really agitated dangerously so you might do things that are calming
for them so to to uh discover what's here to
enter in a calm way into the temple with all of ourselves and to um not be assertive and
not be expecting or wanting or pushing to make
something happen we have to be diligent in practicing somebody we have to be
deliberate there's a deliberateness like this I'm going to be here it's not too
casual it's not like oh I'll get around to it I'll just sit here and let something kind of settle by
itself um there is a deliberateness this is what I'm here to do
and then you might Begin by not trying too hard there is a kind of natural
settling that some people can experience if we don't try too much at the beginning maybe for 5 minutes 10 minutes
and then as we go further then the deliberateness comes into play more and
more okay here I am if we try to early we might be stressing ourselves or being
tense and deliberateness is uh um is to kind of Define this is the
territory here and now to be here with this experience
now and um and then to um steady
oneself to steady oneself stabilize oneself in a kind of inner Stillness
steady oneself in a kind of still way with the whole full breath coming and
going coming and going not fixating on the breath but as
if the breath is at the center of the global body the whole body and we're
resting there with the breath we're riding the breath we're surfing the breath we're coasting on the
breath so we practice and one of the things that can begin happening for some
people is that you feel the benefit of it in your daily
life be to to interrupt the normal patterns of thinking and reacting in the
mind the loops we're in around fear or
distress or anger with the world and how it is takes a break and we can
experience ourselves in a different way and uh that's more calm more centered
and not so easily caught in preoccupations and needs and all this
and that can make a world of difference and um when the world is in a a
difficult state samade is one of the great Protectors of us not to escape it
but to be able to be grounded and centered in ourselves so that we can go
into the world in a more effective way somadi is a um is a great support for
living our life and uh maybe we can live more calmly less reactively maybe from the
platform or that from the vantage point of being settled and unified and calm uh
we can go into the world more kindly and be more friendly less contentious less ready to
argue less ready to see conflict wherever we go
but to see wherever we go an opportunity for connection an opportunity for the
unification the unity the Gathering Together the connecting uh more and more fully
wherever we go whereas samadi is a unification of
body and mind right speech for the Buddha a
speech which unifies people that overcomes divisiveness between people
and so we see here this parallel between unifying and harmonizing all of who we
are when we sit in meditation to not be contentious not
be um opposed or not be pushing away any
part of ourselves uh with uh how we live in our world to enter the world world to unify
to find connection to see if we could have a
warmhearted connection with someone uh rather than a contentious
one so Sadi is a great help for how we live our life and how we um go about and
for sombody to have its greatest benefit uh it probably it helps to be able to
practice every day so I hope that this uh our 7 a.m. sitting here in YouTube uh
allows some of you to have that continuity of every day and as we do this series on somat
and we get back in the swing a it or at least I get back in the swing of it
um that um this might be a good time to start meditating twice a day if you can
and even if it's just 10 minutes the second time or 20 minutes the second time time to have uh one sitting here on
YouTube that's guided and but one sitting a day where you really don't
it's not guided you're just left with yourself and practicing in silence to whatever comes up and whatever you see
so you're developing it's kind of like taking the training wheels off and now you're getting to starting to see for
yourself what the experience is what's happening and some of you certainly can
practice more than 20 minutes or 10 minutes but maybe you don't and
um and uh so maybe you can figure out to
um you know to at least add a second sitting of some length that works for you and while as we as we continue for
some weeks more on this theme of samade and um to kind of re you know
remind you we're kind of uh in the reach the approach stage what's called access
concentration approaching a deeper Som so I want to kind of review a little bit and for a
few days and to get us warmed up again and then uh we'll kind of uh at least
talk about and point you to the possibility of deeper states of
concentration and um some of you it'll just be um informative some of you might
be familiar and recognize uh these states for yourself s and um and uh it's
part of the temple the Temple of samade so thank you very much and
um and I look forward to being with you again tomorrow