morning good morning welcome welcome and even if it's not morning where you
are just happy to be here practicing with you all you can see from the title that was
posted there on YouTube that um I'm going to do a week of poetry here done
this a few times before there's a way in which I like to do poetry as a to point to there's a
different way in which we can engage with the teachings than the memorization of the list or trying to remember all
the sequence of practices or something that we've learned that's tremendously
valuable and I love the list I teach them sometimes but I think it's a trap
if we think that the only way to practice is that we have to figure something out and we have to understand
it all and get it just right right the less right or something like
that as an alternative to that poetry points to something that's in the
heart something that we feel our way into or open up to or um allow ourselves
to experience and know in a different kind of way than all the lists and the
instructions we need both I would say and it's so easy when uh doing a Dr talk
to feel like here are the instructions here's something to do extremely useful not the only way to
practice in fact I would say but we need a combination
so we I'll say that uh part of uh practicing with poetry is allowing the
language to touch us in a different way maybe in this way that rather than
consuming information maybe a little bit more passively it's a way to allow
language to touch us maybe touch our hearts or or maybe allowing language to
nourish us instead of telling us uh what we should be
doing so well that is a little introduction about this idea of poetry
of practice but will guide us into
dropping into an certain amount of settledness whatever amount of settledness is
available to you this time and then I'll drop in a poem and then there'll be some
silence and then uh for the little daret I'll unpack the poem in the way that uh
we might use it as a way to support us in our practice and certainly in our
life okay
so taking a moment to settle
in with our meditation
posture connecting to the sitting surface
whatever that might be whether it's a chair cushion bed
pouch wherever it might
be if you're using a back rest feeling the sensations on the back as it
contacts the back rest
for all of us feeling the contact with the buttocks as we are
sitting we're laying
down we're connected
supported the back of the legs
the feet resting our awareness and an easy
relaxed manner to feel connected grounded
we're
here it can be helpful to do a little bit more of a body scan
to help the body find some ease and
let go of whatever tension tightness can be readily let go
of without making it a
project checking in around the eyes
the
mouth the shoulders allowing them to drop away
from the ears
the chest sometimes we bring a certain
amount of armoring to our
experience can we allow it to soften and open
and the
belly allowing that to soften
then bringing an aliveness of
attention to the sensations of
breathing feeling into the experience of breathing
bealing the sensations more than thinking about
them maybe there are no words with the
sensations e
tuning into the
experience of breathing
allowing the attention to settle or organize
around the
breath e
and we set the sense of direction as one of
welcoming whatever is arising it's already
here can we align with the reality of the
moment
e
e e
there's a poem I'd like to drop into our
meditation it's entitled prescription for the
disillusioned by Becca Del
Rio prescription for the disillusioned by Rebecca Del
Rio come new to this day remove the rigid Overcoat of
experience the notion of knowing the beliefs that CL your
vision leave behind the stories of your life spit out this sour taste of unmet
expectation let this stale scent of what ifs waft back into the swamp of your
useless fears arrive curious
without the armor of certainty the plans and planned results of the life you've
imagined live the life that chooses you new every
breath every blink of your astonished eyes
I'll read it again prescription for the
disillusion by Rebecca Del Rio
come new to this day remove the rigid Overcoat of
experience the notion of knowing the beliefs that cloud your
vision leave behind the stories of your life spit out the sour taste of unmet
expectation let this stale scent of what if left back into into the swamp of your
useless fears arrive
curious without the armor of certainty the plans and planned results
of the life you've imagined live the life that chooses
you new every breath every blink of your astonished
eyes
e
e e
what would it be like to arrive
curious to this
moment
e
e e
[Music]