so uh so welcome folks welcome to you all
um yeah uh good to uh good to be with you
i trust you all have some way of practicing and are not relying on my
instructions for that purpose you know I'm sort of like ornamental you know on
the base layer of your practice should have said that like 15 years
ago but um let us uh let us sit
So relaxing uh whatever can be relaxed everything that
can be relaxed we relax whatever tension
remains we give a complete blessing to remain yeah
and if anything's tight or hurts in your
body just remaining in the flow of meditation but uh go ahead and
uh gently massage wherever there's tightness pain
sense the way that uh
kindness it's manifest in that
gesture certain expression of uh loving kindness
i'm just feeling the transmission of that uh
care perhaps from your hand to your body
find oursel in this uh lineage of love and care
same gesture of
kindness manifested a million ways a million
times over uh millennia
the wish to be free of suffering is the kind of
uh animating theme of history it's just that
uh generally people don't understand happiness well
enough that we're learning here on our cushions our
seats our
beds learning about our nervous system and about uh this realm of
experience some
sorrow learning about what's worthy of our reverence and
protection where we can let go
our worries will not stop until we stop
so we sense into the flow of breathing but something in
us stops
instinctively we place so much
hope to a Future that never exactly comes
So we renounce
the protection and acquisitiveness
ownership the control
we refine our relationship with
helplessness and in this way cultivate our power
our attention is usually a kind of appendage
of our wanting and our fear
but we can't uh fool mother nature
we have to let
go to uh receive this moment
and when it um those times it doesn't work maybe
nothing
works actually get to uh see what we were trying to
do and
manufacture it's okay
maybe we can say in any given moment insight
into one of the four noble truths is on offer
we just do our best not to miss it
[Music]
okay it's good to uh to sit with
you um so uh no
um no class next week i'll be away but
um back on the
23rd so
uh several several years ago uh following a kind of you know episode of
some some harm you know kind of like unethical leadership uh some insight teachers were asked to
say something about CILA ethical conduct and
um uh to write a short thing and um uh
Kitty Sarro um was uh also known as Tanniser's husband
it's not all he is meditation teacher road scholar whatnot anyway but also
Tannisra's husband um wrote this and I I condensed it slightly but um uh has
stayed with me over these years so um wrote um after a meal on it was
this is in the you know 70s uh late 70s or early 80s I believe and
um as a as a monk in the Thai forest tradition so he says after a meal
offering in rural northeast Thailand I was sitting with Ajin Sha and a group of
young western monks from several different countries he told us that one day we'd all be
teachers bringing the dharma back to our own countries he warned us quote "Don't be
the kind of teacher that gets so puffed up you can't get through the door don't
go around thinking I'm a teacher." Always remember you're a
practitioner if a situation arises that calls for teaching let teaching happen
it comes and goes in your heart you are a practitioner mindful and
empty ajenta was warning us about the dangers of being inflated and
intoxicated by the power and prestige of
the leadership position we are regularly reminded that the
blessings do not belong to us that we are riding on the perfection and power
of the awakened one as our practice of the path deepens we'll naturally grow in
personal power cultivating sila samadei pa plugging into the measureless merit
of the triple gem we potentize our actions for good or for ill it's vital
to be interested in and sensitive to our impact on the world and those around
us we must regularly ask ourselves are we doing harm because we have ignorance
we must open ourselves to the feedback uh using the SA to help us see where we
do unconscious harm to our community being a dharma teacher or a dedicated
Buddhist practitioner we are waving the banner of the awakened one representing that
extraordinary heritage partaking of that trustworthy
power and prestige when one has power one's
wholesome actions are amplified but so are the unh wholesome ones everything we do has more impact we
have the potential to do great good and also great harm
so just the image of that uh that scene kind of touched me you know Ajent Sha
this kind of revered figure back then revered and kind of legacy only grown
but sitting around and Ajin Sha foreseeing the spread of the dharma
uh and I'm very curious who was there what people were there uh Jack Kornfield
over overlapped I believe for some years there and uh I'm curious where they went
and what goodness their lives have
brought and it's likely that my life
somehow is tied to that moment after that meal offering maybe 50
years ago and that means of course in some way
you're you know tied to that moment too and that moves me you know the ways
that goodness ripples ripples in in a manner that's
hard to anticipate and imagine to be feeling the blessings just
kind of reverberating down through the uh decades
it says if a situation arises that calls for teaching let teaching happen it comes and
goes you know it's like identification with our roles imagining that we are
actors not roles it's insidious the ego is
insidious not an enemy but insidious
and especially when there are things that we love at stake have to be very
awake in the Thai forest tradition um a a a dhamma talk must be requested i
think it's usually a very junior you know monastic sometimes anagorica something like uh asking
formally for the talk meaning that a talk is only ever a
response to a need not a product
it means that the dharma is
always shared
consensually that the teacher only exists because a student exists
otherwise she would not exist and this ensures that the teacher speaks
into a kind of field of sincerity that the dharma is transmitted
from warm hand to warm hand
the blessings of the path um do not belong to us and
uh you cannot own goodness the dharma just like a
people is un unpossessible you know
and ownership is really a kind of core egoic
fantasy and part of a dharma life of living a dharma centric life is living a
life amidst the kind of felt sense of
unpossessibility because um the ego is always trying to exert
power we talk often about surrender the dissolution of willfulness we talk about
vulnerability and softening and suppleness yeah that's all necessary
we don't talk about it in this lineage but I had a mentor in the in the Tibetan
lineage and um they're always talking about
power the path cultivates power wisdom
is power love is power cultivating sila samadei pa
plugging into the measureless merit of the triple gem we potentize our
actions actions become more potent more good more
ill and the more powerful one becomes on this path the more force one is
marshalling and that cuts both ways the power to heal and to harm right that's
sometimes like saying in medicine like anything potent enough to heal is potent
enough to to harm to have side effects right and as practitioners we become
interested in acrewing power in so far as it helps us alleviate
suffering our own that of others
and the more powerful I become through my own practice through my own
maturation the more seriously you will take me when I say something
like be kind with yourself or it's safe to let go or a
million other things
but there's another part of me that doesn't want power or attention at all
like once the student is gone the teacher
dissolves and Kisara goes on to to speak about
sila sila as a protection we do our best to follow the principles
of nonharming but we in a sense can never
have a completely lucid view of ourselves there's some measure of
unconsciousness and so we rely on others to harmonize our
understanding of our intentions and our effects our
impacts and we we become more and more
calibrated you know our intentions impacts those are kind of like more
tightly coupled but we can never be sure and the
open loops of feedback are essential for communal safety that's how SA stays
well we're waving the banner of the awakened
one representing that extraordinary heritage partaking in the
trustworthy power prestige that's big those are big words
i like those words um yeah partaking partaking in the the
trustworthy power and prestige we want to be worthy of that
banner and we do our best to it's not emulating something we do
our best to be ourselves and represent that heritage
that the prestige of that you kind of like can't
perform the dharma you know you can't partake in that power and prestige
through performance you you're becoming the dharma and in
becoming it you are also becoming yourself and that that experience of
becoming dharma becoming oneself
um that that evolves on our
path and so power and reverence cultivating Power means it's even more
important to cultivate the safety of sila and we see when power and love
diverge there's tremendous damage and so we
um must be powerful and must be safe insight
into emptiness gives us power and deep self-standing
uh makes us more and more
safe and our life becomes a kind of trace of of
goodness you know less and less
debris more and more kind of just quiet trace of goodness
and so uh so this this week this week um how will you cultivate and uh use
your power and how um can you serve as
uh making your heart serve as a refuge making your heart a refuge for all
beings can you do this it's our um maybe our
homework okay folks lots of uh love wish you well