so once again good evening I'm Maria Strotman and I am here for
Diana who could not make it tonight And what I would like to talk to you
about is a spiritual life
Does talking about a spiritual life make you uncomfortable does it not really what you think of
when you're doing your practice does it make you feel like you're at
home oh yeah Great Now I'm going to know just what it is
I'm going to have all the answers So
let all of that evaporate because none of that's going to happen
So today the IMC newsletter came out and Gil had a really lovely essay essay in
there opening up that newsletter uh about his own spiritual journey which I highly recommend that you read If
you're not on the email list which is where I saw the newsletter you can find it on the website and just see what he
has to say about what it was like these last 50 years that he's pursued
meditation and and this way of life So
what I want to talk about because I've been contemplating my own spiritual journey its twists and turns
and its missteps and its blossoming and a kind of assessing
I remember setting out on my journey and saying you know I've ignored my spiritual life for some time
I think it was a therapist who asked me what my spiritual life was and I said hm
maybe I better go find out And this despite the fact when I was young I I had every intention of
becoming a nun I was going to be a nun I was quite determined and uh
uh I there are three primary uh vows poverty chastity and obedience And I had
a lot of trouble with the obedience one I just didn't want people telling me what to do
So I'm not going to tell you what to do because I'm really opposed to that
And also as I've reflected on this and the thing I want to emphasize tonight is
the efing trap the trap of of efforting in your spiritual path in your examining
of how am I in the world and what does it mean
the wanting to be something better than you are different than you are have
certain characteristics If I was just like this then my practice would be perfect and I would know just what to do
Because the one thing I am most clear about is that a spiritual path begins
right here right now with conditions just as they are
Right here right now just this
The only thing I have to work with is this imperfect being that I am
And this is my spiritual path not to become a better person although I
have aspirations like everyone else But what's become really clear to me
is to the effort that goes into trying to be something other than I am
is not the spiritual path
Over the weekend I attended a uh an art show
a ceramics art show at Palo Alto Art Center which is a very good show by the
way And one of the exhibits was 100
small cups like teacups that you might find in an oriental tea set
100 cups in two shadow boxes a pair of shadow boxes on the wall And uh each of
these cups was different It had a different glaze or a slightly different shape or you know some were round some
were very pyramat pyramid like pyramids
Some of them were had extra clay around them They were all different
100 of these And
in the what I want to read you is the uh the accompanying statement The artist's
name is Kina Yang And here's what she said As a hobbyist ceramicist these 100
cups made over the course of three weeks represent more work than I had ever made
up to this point I chose this quantity of cups within
this time frame to release myself from my own expectations of how perfect a
piece needs to be to share it with someone else
I chose this quantity of cups within this time frame 100 cups in three weeks
to release myself from my own expectations of how perfect a piece needs to be to share it with someone So
there are kind of two ideas in here that struck me as relevant One of them is um
that she was able to abandon her expectations of perfection
She was willing to just see what happened if she didn't have to have each one exactly right She could have chosen
to do just one piece and have it truly exquisite And I'm sure some some of the
pieces that she made as she was going along had to be discarded Maybe not
She was fairly skilled These were nice looking cups She
probably had some missteps Not all of them were perfect
The idea of what happens if I give up the need to be perfect
can I what kind of art do I present then and am I willing to present myself am I
willing to make myself vulnerable to doing this and that this idea of
presenting oneself is really relevant
This is the part where we say a spiritual path is about showing up and
you have to show up for yourself You have to I'm here
just warts and all here I am
meeting this moment meeting this day meeting this time
with these conditions As I was sitting here
I I felt my knee sitting here and I realized that this morning I had a
treatment of my knee and that the doctor had said to me "Now no big exercises I
don't want you bending that knee you know no bridges." And I'm thinking here I am sitting in this no bridges
I thought well this is the way it is because this is how it feels for me to
sit in meditation He would not approve
This is how it is Life is not something that we set up and
our spiritual path is not something that we set up only when conditions are
perfect This is it This is the whole thing Alan
Watts wrote a book called This Is It And I used to have it on my shelf And I I
would just look at the title of it and say "hm this is it This is it This life
right now this moment this is what we have to work with
This is a place of being in with just what arises
Whatever the clay decides to do in our hands at this moment I'm here for this
and I have to enter into this moment with whatever is here It's really about
entering into this moment It's not about achieving something or being somebody different or
attaining some magical state of perfection or
ecstatic joy Not that these things don't happen
but it is the very act of showing up with the intention of seeing what is
here How is it to actually experience
what you're experiencing you know when I first started meditating I think probably about week four
five something like that I remember driving down the freeway and thinking
about what I was doing I was mindful of driving I was mindful of my hands I was paying attention to all of this stuff
And I said you know I am inhabiting more moments of my life
than I ever have And what a realization that was for me
that mindfulness is not something you do instead of living
Mindfulness is totally inhabiting your life
being totally engaged with what's coming up Okay so if that's the case face it
it's not all going to be roses You may not even like roses especially
yellow ones Life is just as it is
And the trick is somehow to enter into the experience without constantly wishing it was otherwise
That constantly wishing it was otherwise is suffering
So last week I had uh I had a plan and I
wanted to get people together in a kind of a well it was family I wanted to get
I wanted to merge some family things And so that was my primary intention in in
getting things together But you know what it wasn't anybody else's primary intention
Their primary intention was to have a good time
And after a while I realized how tense I was becoming about
people wanting to go off on their own No no no no no We have to be here together
And I realized that that however wonderful the intention was it was
creating suffering for me and everybody else because I was so stuck on it
I was so stuck on what it would be like if we were all happy together
And so I had to walk away I walked away right before I said something really
hurtful to my sister So it's a good thing I walked away
and totally unnecessary
And as I walked away I could feel the energy ebbing
ebbing ebbing ebbing Okay letting go of having it a certain way allowed me to
just go back It was okay Then
the secret to a a rich spiritual life is not perfection
It's how you deal with imperfection
How you're willing to meet it How you're willing to enter into it
How you enter into the experience of life
The other day I was I I went to my husband and I said 'You know I'm I'm sorry I'm just feeling distressed And he
said "What can I do to make it better?" Sound doesn't that sound great it's very
generous And I said "Well maybe you just need to listen about why
I'm distressed." Now I didn't say that to him I just said
"Okay you're right I don't need to feel this way." And then after a while when I just
allowed myself to be distressed I didn't roll around in the floor on it
I just said "Okay distress is here but I'm going to do this thing with my husband."
I was able to I was able to just see okay I'm distressed Distress is here And
I cried a little and I watched the energy fall out of that
And then I noticed what a beautiful day it was and how nice the food was that we were
eating And I was still I still knew the distress It was still there The things
that were causing me distress were still true
But it didn't define me It didn't define the day
It's constantly changing
What I'm talking about is not so much saying anything that is distressful is
okay I'm really not saying we have to accept life as it is I'm simply saying
we have to see life as it is and say and now what
and now what it's not the effort that says I'm never going to get angry I'm
never going to be upset I'm never going to be too attached to my views I'm never No no no no That's a lot of extra stuff
The comparison comparing myself to this person or that person
is extra stuff Not needed not important
Not needed not important No expectations of the moment but a
curiosity about what's true here what's happening here
What this does is allow what is arising to to be there It's it's it's oh this is
what's happening Oh
now now when I see clearly I can see oh I don't want to be doing that That was
that I don't want to be doing that That just makes me unhappy
This is what happens as we practice It isn't so much that we be that we set
out to become better people But when we see oh this behavior is making me sad
and you sad and then we stop doing that And when we see ah this sitting in
silence and just breathing
is opening Oh
that's kind of nice I'm going to do more of that
I'm going to be more with that
One of the great problems that we have in our society is that we're all very
conditioned toward goals I'm going to do this I know how to do this I'm going to set my goals and I'm going to I'm going
to accomplish this and then I'm going to accomplish that and then I'm going to do this other thing and and the result of
all that is you know the payoff It's extremely difficult to step away
from that It's extremely difficult because we're
kind of we're kind of geared at that You know this is what I want to do so I'm going to do all this stuff to make it
happen
One of the consequences of that is that we we begin to harden ourselves with
resolve and we harden ourselves to an approach and we become rigid and
unyielding and the heart becomes rigid and unyielding
with ourselves with others and we can't get past that
But if we allow the vulnerability to slip in and say
well so what what happens if I allow my heart to soften a little bit
if we take the example of my my telling my husband that I was distressed
I could have said about his his technique by the way is you got to fix
that distress And my technique is okay it's here
Now there could be a clash there because he likes to fix things that are
wrong And so if I noticed that I am resistant to his efforts or resistant to
the distress or resistance to how I feel about something I'm beginning to
feel a kind of pushing away of the experience Now I'm not engaging in the experience I'm rejecting the experience
and I'm aversive to the experience When I see that I can say "Oh you're
trying so hard and I can feel the softening in my
heart." Now a soft heart can be seen as something
that is very uh diff uh risky
Can be seen as risky but it isn't
It isn't because what it does is open up for you the possibilities of seeing
things in a way that produces a different outcome So when I was walking
with my husband this afternoon I talked him into going for a walk because he was very stressed And so he said "Well okay
I'll go for a walk cuz I'll feel better afterward." And I said "How about just feeling better how about just going for a walk without expecting the walk to
make you feel better?" What happens then how about just changing and dropping the
attitude of I've got to do something responsible better but simply
abandoning that stress that efforting
and saying this is what needs to happen now What needs to happen now is I need to abandon
that just for now This is what we do when we meditate is
we sit and follow our breath and say just for now I'm not going to tell myself stories Just for now I'm going to
let go of that Just for now I'm just going to sit here
This is practicing the letting go of expectations and needing things to be a certain way
And what can arise in that moment if you're open to it is something else in
addition to whatever you brought into the moment that you can see something else
But when you're rigid oh it's like tunnel vision You can't you
can't see it It's not available to you
It's not the same thing as doing nothing and saying everything is okay That's a different kind of trap you know That's
that's a delusion trap It's got I'm going to pretend it's not there Doesn't work either You have to you know it's
here Whatever it is it's here We don't want to fix barriers against
the experience Go ahead and inhabit the experience
just inhabit it Okay this is this is what's happening How you respond to this moment is enough
It doesn't have to be better It's just here Here I am And I'm willing
to trust myself to present myself in this moment
and see what happens
we can just be good enough
We want to get away from the idea that life has to be
life is a life experience is a requirement and we want life experience to be an
unfolding just a an unfolding
I'm going to end my comments with a poem by uh
Jane Hersshfield In this poem there's a a reference to a place called Hyarpasa Station which I
think is in Istanbul It's a train station It's certainly in that part of the world So here it is The name of the
poem is 10 t i n I studied much and remembered little But
the world is generous It kept offering figs and cheeses Never mind that soon I'll have to give
it all back The world the figs To be a train station of existence
is no small matter It doesn't need to be Grand Central or
Haidapasa Station The engine shed could be low windowed with cold dust under a
slat shingled roof It could be tin Another mystery bandaged with rivets and
rubies leaking cold and heat in both directions as the earth does
I studied much and remembered little But the world is generous They kept offering figs and cheeses Never mind that soon
I'll have to give it all back The world the figs to be a train station of
existence is no small matter It doesn't need to be the Grand Central
or Hyasa station The engine shed could be low windowed with cold dust under a
slat singled roof It could be tin Another mystery bandaged with rivets and
rubies leaking cold and heat in both directions as the earth does
Our experiences allow us to be a train station of existence
which is no small matter Your existence in this world
just as it is is no small matter Treat it with joy and respect
and that's what you'll get back Thank you
So does anybody have any comments or suggestions as I straighten out my leg
difference dr Wall will be very happy
Does it make sense i I' I've really been struggling with how to
to uh explain the idea of of not having a a
predetermined approach to life That the spiritual p the spiritual path is really
an unfolding and not a direction or a a series of steps that you take that that
guarantee that you get somewhere else that that really the freedom
that we seek the freedom from suffering can only arise
by just being in this experience this one
as you are whatever you are experiencing
and not needing it to be anything else You know I would just assume my knee
didn't hurt but it's just a knee It's just a painful knee
It's not more than that It doesn't have meaning It doesn't have weight
And I can act on it or not act on it
the engaging with life just just this experience and seeing it
just as it is not how I would like it to be or how I thought it would be
This is the route to freedom The freedom that says I don't have to be
other than I am The world doesn't have to be other than it is for me to
experience ease in the moment
It's not the ease of everything's okay It's the ease of ah I'm here
with this Does that make any sense definitely
Whether it's distressful or happy be there
Be there
And if something is painful you can move I was going to say something Um
Thank you for your talk Yeah it's time for me to shut up Wh when you were um
talking about the spiritual life I remember I can't remember if I read it or I heard um Sharon Saltzburg talking
about how to when she was um a beginner in in meditation
She said she would do walking meditation and but she was never noting anything
because she said "I'm just waiting for something spiritual to happen." Yeah Right like well you know okay I'm
meditating and I'm walking but now when is something spiritual going to happen and I I think about that sometimes when
I'm uh I don't know just
maybe having sort of a blah meditation or walking you know it's just
like no nothing's happening you know and then it's like huh
what what's that about right Great That's great That's great Thank you You
know I I remember being in meditation one time and and thinking I was about to fall asleep
and I had been meditating for a couple of weeks so I was very concentrated and
still And here I was I was just about to fall asleep And I thought well maybe I
need to sleep Or maybe I just need to know what it's like to be falling asleep Or how what is it like to be falling
asleep and I felt myself walking on this edge you know like if I fell off a cliff
I could just fall off this cliff into sleep But I'm right on this edge There
was just enough alertness to notice being on the edge of falling asleep And
how exciting that was how really thrilling it was to be on
that edge which is you know I was just falling asleep
And and I I think that's that's the same idea that that a spiritual life is not
about something else It's not about something else It's it's really
um Yeah that's that's the best I can do
Yes Well here I empathize I empathize so much with you
about the knees Okay Because I've been able to sit on a Zafu most of my career
sitting and this is a beginner question Um
when your knees are hurting so much then what story do you tell yourself you tell
yourself well I'm doing this practice this looking at this pain and and um
where's that going or I have to give myself a reason for doing it or something bigger than myself or I
because it sometimes it's so extreme It's so hard to just stay with the pain
and just try to you know deal with it You know even especially on a long
retreat when you're doing it day after day after day on a long retreat I don't
spend all retreat with sitting cross-legged on the floor I spend a lot of time in a chair Even though there's
there's a certain energy that comes from this the triangulation and sitting this
way on the floor that feels feels right for meditating
I I can't do that because I'm too distracted by pain That's right That's what So there's no point There's no
point to that The object is not to meditate a certain way It's to
be still and see what arises That doesn't require me to sit a certain
way Even if I'm more comfortable if I think I'm more comfortable that way
because if if the if all I'm doing is focusing on pain
I'm just focusing on pain It's just one big struggle So sometimes it seems like
just remembering to be present in your daily life for five
minutes or 10 minutes or some small
something through the day than it does to sit through all that
Well I don't want to I don't want to quantitate it right but it's very important to notice during the day where
am I how am I what's happening here what's my attitude what's the energy level It's a primary part of my practice
Thank you very much Once you become addicted to mindfulness it's pretty hard to get away from it
Some people can do that I've spent 50 years trying to do that
I'm sure you're I'm sure you are more mindful than you give yourself credit for possibly sometimes
But we're not we're not measuring You see it it isn't about measuring Just celebrate every moment that you notice
you're standing on the ground Celebrating being here tonight All right
There we go I'm very happy I'll celebrate with you
Anybody else um I I love that the phrase train
station of existence That's perfect And I think I have Grand Central
because it's exactly like that And what a me when I'm mindful is how much actually is going on in there at one
time The sensations the impulses the worries the fears the tensions um plans
all these things all like at one time This cacophony If I'm understand you correctly that's
fine Yes Okay
Sometimes Sometimes it's busy Yeah Yeah Okay Sometimes it's busy Yeah Or or a
lot of the time but you know No you uh to to be fair it's busier sometimes more than others Yeah Um but it it can very
much be that way It's like you can watch it go by like a parade Yeah Yeah And and what's what's uh what
might be useful is when when you notice all of that cacophony
and how do I feel about that and what am I what how am I responding
to that and what's the energy like is it does that caca
cause jitteriness or excitement or aversion just notice what whatever is
happening just that's what's happening Yeah Well it's kind of like that I think the mindfulness helps because it used to
be if I wasn't aware of it I'd just be distracted or all over right and it's like okay there's all this stuff floating on there What do you need to
focus on now yeah You know yeah Um Oh see that's a that So I spent some time
today thinking about priorities that we're always trying to set priorities right and this has a higher value than
that So that has a higher priority And that that whole valuing our experiences
can really get in the way that this is more valuable experience
than that you know Yeah Well I meant like eating I mean you have to eat right
something like that But no no I I I totally get what you mean Uh you can get yourself more worked up for sure Um
making kind of priority list and thinking I got to do this first or that So but um I I don't have that too much
but I do have the train station existence I'm never going to forget that That's perfect That's a great It's a
great phrase I love that Jane Hersshfield said that Yeah
Excuse me The problem arises of the desire to just have a moment
of nothing emptiness or quiet or something
And you just can't you can't you can't arrange that It just happens No you
can't But the desire is always there So it's hard So so you notice the desire
Notice that and and just remind yourself what you're doing is wishing things were other than they are That's right And
then and then of course you say "Oh no I'm not going to do that." Right Right And then you can feel your heart
softening Say "Oh." And in that moment you can
feel the ease too And it is that very moment
Ah thank you Don't miss it
Very helpful image So else
does anybody else have comments or suggestions
so I am thinking
that this has been delightful Thank you
Good night everyone