okay folks yeah welcome I appreciate
um being together tonight so
um that's uh that's uh that's it I'm my you know my talks I plan out my
talks carefully do not plan out the guided
meditation at all but um we just see what happens yeah
and I I sort of presume you have something some way one at least one way
of practicing that feels native to your heart and
um it can just lapse into that uh if I
do anything bad
okay on that inspiring note let us uh let us dwell in the dama together
let us uh take good care the uh Karma of the
day or the the week or the
life it's all come to this
the heart made so
vast that everything has its place
there no more sorting out what we want and what we don't
want e
just putting down the melodrama of
self the gridlock of I
amness e
we pour our awareness
into the
senses e
just each moment uh becoming more
alive how alive can you be in this
moment e
maybe pick up your
breath is a way of refreshing aliveness in each moment
the more we hold on to the moment less alive we become
don't even look for
ground e
this moment doesn't exactly care about this
life we learn to tolerate at not caring
we come to trust that
taking good care of this
moment uh leads to a rich
life
e
e e
poem wrote something like um that's what the minute said to the hour without me
you are
nothing that's what the the moment set to the
life
e
for
e e
to uh be fully Alive we have to put
in a sense put down our
life sticky melodrama of self and
project this includes uh
aliveness
for e
don't hang on to all the familiar reference points
that's not what keeps us safe anyway
just come to trust that
um there's safety in the
falling the
groundlessness
e
e e
all phenomena remind us of our
freedom
e
e e
[Music]
e
okay good to sit with
you so a quote I saw this week from uh arent
aito uh as it is based upon dispassion and
cooling the realization of nibana cannot arise from getting heated up about the
host of Mara or from denying its existence comes from replacing the
compulsive movements of craving and ignorance with mindful energy and
insight niana is the experience of space in the Mind where
previously everything was densely stuck together in regenerative
congestion in that congestion a self is imagined that now and then longs to
escape from the oppressive host of inner voices feelings doubts and
desires so to one who practices Insight the idea that nibana is a selfish goal
doesn't make sense because the Mira The Mirage of self
evaporates as the fires cool and the means of bringing this
about is the selfless eight-fold path as a practice this means
cultivating a purer and wiser response to faults and attachments than the Counterattack or
defense moods adopted by the self view rather than fight the host or get
away from them you have to liberate the host from Mara the embodiment of
suffering Mara have to liberate the host of Mara from all
delusion from all the hatred and fear and belief that binds them with self
view so aent s of course is a u as a monk
uh but you get a sense of how profound the path turns
inwards and this is a a path that's really not about helping my life
along and the whole notion of my life is a symptom rather than the
centerpiece and the austerity and devotion of of that spirit
is um kind of startling and I see a quote like that
and I have to reflect okay do I do I want that I would say I have some some
ambivalence um sometimes I feel like I I kind of want
the middle path between nibana and some Sara
right and uh like that you know from the
confessions like give me Chastity but not yet Lord give me Chastity but not
yet maybe and I think we lay practitioners
are still in very early stages of translating the the
kind of radical gesture of relinquishment for Lay
life so the host of Mara that is an interesting
phrase the host of Mara me my project My Views ideas this
is the host of Mara and Mara visits and our so-called life
becomes the host and in like biology a host you know
uh provides the kind of nourishment for the visiting
organism and uh how how do I provide
nourishment for Mara philosopher Mets singer says um
biological evolution is not something to be glorified it's unknowing driven by
chance and has no mercy it's a process that exploits and
sacrifices individuals for millions of years Mother Nature has talked to us
through our reward system and through the emotional layers
of our self model our phenomenal self model um we have to learn to take a
critical stance towards this process to view our experience as a
direct result of it we have to stop glorifying our own
neurophenomenological status quo face the facts and find the courage to think
about Alternatives in a rational
way so much of my life you know is
essentially the ruthlessness of my evolutionary
conditioning just kind of bullying me mother nature speaking through my reward
system speaking through sakya DTI the self
model denying Mara is one of Mara's tricks you
know so we practice radical openness to the truth of this
moment failing to listen to Mara means that we will obey
Mara we have to see and hear Mara respectfully
respectfully for not to host them
generative congestion that's that's like the opposite of you know you
just cramped cramped the opposite of space gridlock you know and congestion
is a metaphor but it's also not in a way like suffering often seems to involve um you
know energy and by that I mean like you you know very subtle layers of feeling
experience um involves energy not flowing somehow
contracted whirl pools like you know
hyperintensities the whirl pools where things feel stuck
regenerative congestion compulsivity always feels dense you know like if we were like
Imaging our spiritual body or something like that compulsivity would be like uh
would show up on the image you know kind of
density and compulsivity and
ignorance aito says ignorance we we
forget we forget the dhma we forget our wisdom and suffering in a in an
important sense is a kind of forgetting and it may be worthwhile to
ask what do you forget uh when you
suffer that word nibana gets used different in different different ways in
different Moments by different Traditions different teachers um and uh here uh uh as as the
experience of space in the mind and how how vast can the mind be
how empty and open unfixed you
know and um the movement in you know towards more well-being in this life is
um I don't think it can be fully characterized as a move from contraction
to spaciousness but that captures a lot of the heart's
movement and suffering and space tend to
be inversely correlated you know suffering is a kind of
claustrophobia the vastness um is
uded and so dispassion and cooling aan
says so much of suffering clinging involves a
certain kind of you know psychological terms like
hyperarousal maybe maybe all of craving is a kind of hyper arousal a kind of
heat right the the eyes are burning the ears are burning everything's
burning heat the Heat of
clinging and Tranquility is not numbness Tranquility is not numbness it's alive
it's the aliveness that I was alluding to in the sit but without the kind of whirlpools that capture the
attention I says a lot in that paragraph So the ego the ego sense of of um self
it's almost the ego is almost endlessly Innovative crystallizing around anything
like a kind of amoeba including spiritual practice you
know and the word nibbana or Enlightenment is sort of catnip for the
ego but this is not a story about the self getting
better that's just more congestion and the idea that freedom
freedom is a selfish goal doesn't make sense The Mirage of self evaporates as the fire is
cool the whole notion of the self as
kind of like possessing something some attainment that it it it possesses that
becomes kind of um just silly absurd
um vudi Maga s today is like I am not
anything belonging to anyone
anywhere and we could say nothing could ever belong to Freedom or own
freedom freedom is so often kind of envisioned as adding something like a
kind of autant of the self but it's
subtraction a profound state of non-
territoriality and so liberating um from
all the hatred and fear and belief that that binds binds them with self View
um the sense of self sometimes I have this image of the sense of
self as like uh as like a hologram you know like uh the creation of
um you know some figure by like arranging light in a particular way and
the lights creating the impression of self are made you know of of of you know
fear clinging and
so uh the dissolution of self if it's
genuine can only lead us to Care
More and when the self system is no longer the sight of endless
curation what's left is the rest of life very
open and the self re arises but we
know a little more deeply how innocent it
is it's not a host for Mara in question the same
way so I offer this for your consideration and uh please pick up
what's useful and leave the rest
behind Okay so thanks
folks um see um it's uh uh this week uh IMC is
uh supporting uh save the children at or
money going I believe primarily to Gaza Dar for for um to B to protect
children uh so I put the link there in the um the YouTube video and also um I put a
link to a form to um uh uh
um submit questions um so that's uh let
me see I can get it here too
um okay there it is also in the chat but it's in the description and um yeah submit some
questions and uh it's helpful for me to uh to know what's on your mind and get
inspired by your uh curiosity so um see you um see you next
uh next time and uh yeah wish you uh wish you all well okay