okay so uh so welcome folks uh good to good to be with you
um yeah I don't have anything to say let's um let's practice together for
maybe a few uh deeper breaths just to uh land
here maybe deeper than any other breath
today for
and maybe we uh make a kind of promise to our worries and
preoccupations the the Loose Ends of uh any human
life kind of make a promise that
um I'll get back to you I won't neglect you
forever we're just queuing to uh the Deep
Mind that is it's uh okay
to put down the ordinary defenses
okay to stand
defenseless just to offer up our heart to this
moment
e e
whatever you think your life
is lay it
down the sense of the the project of your life
all the metrics we have just lay it
down
e e
and we're practicing knowing uh
experience very simply what would it be to
breathe without elaboration
every moment is so ripe with a potential energy like it
can go so many ways and we feel so compelled
to elaborate on
experience keep our reference points
here we just uh are a body breathing
simple
intimate
e
e e
and practice can feel hard instructions can feel
like a cruel
joke tension squirly tired or wired or both
but we often only a
few mindful breaths away from something
shifting and we just uh attune to this subtlety that shift
appreciate
it keep going
e
e e
even the Assumption I'm a I'm a human can Cloud The View
we get more quiet we become more sensitive to the ways
we construct the the Avatar of
self the little bits of sense data that go
unnoticed and become the ground of
self
e
e e
what if uh you were never seen
like you were never an object in the mind of another
likewise no mirrors no never uh an object in your own mind
just empty phenomena rolling
on
e
e e
okay so a
question um that was uh sent to me uh person writes as I get deeper in
meditation composed and almost concentrated fear pops up flips the
ejector seat and out I bounce I
see the fear in my body uh there it is and have begun to acknowledge and even
try to welcome met in response it's it insists uh louder and harder that it's
irresponsible for me to surrender not just on the macro level like with all
the horrors going on in the world in the US right now but also on some very deep
intuitive level it's dangerous for me I suspect this partly
stems from growing up in a chaotic and unsafe household being alert and aware
felt necessary for survival partly two it might be a culturally
female thing I am meant to be perpetually attentive to others moods
needs wishes and not tune out until after I've I've assured that everyone
else is fine anyway don't know if this warrants a darat but I would be grateful for any
teachings on working with this fear
Instinct so so let's start with the easy
part the the of my response not the easy part
but the easy part of my response around the gendered pressures of being a um
caretaker and what I thought of when I was we were
out to dinner with my parents last you know a few days ago and um our the
waitress had kind of large hoop earrings with some script uh written and um my mom sort of
caught caught her eye and um she asked the waitress you know what what your
what the script in your earrings says and uh waitress said smash the
patriarchy and uh my dad was like okay okay fair
enough so Dharma pleasure that's
your Birthright as much as anyone
and it's not a kind of indulgence and your growing spiritual
power maybe uh you know is perhaps kind of doesn't feel Justified or is
intimidating to some but it's it's a good force in the
world and so okay fear yeah some part of
our mind to you know Stillness sadei surrender all of that is
dangerous you know anicha uncertainty means that we we don't know
and not knowing is um a very precarious position for an
animal not knowing is precarious because how could
we defend or manage or control that which is not
known and the priority as I often say in all virtually all moments is ensuring
more moments it's about Safety and Security and
security is about the future and a deep abiding preoccupation of what now means
for my future and so letting go as you suggest
does not come naturally to us it does not feel safe and when the Dharma teacher said
says casually just like oh just let go let go you know some part of us is like
really you're not actually serious that this is what you're asking like or maybe
it's different for you but that that's not safe clinging is what feels safe
thinking is what feels safe worrying is what feels safe pinging to
all of our familiar reference points is what feels
safe and you know our our Consciousness our
knowing is infused with this fear and
this vigilance and it's it's almost that's
what I was alluding to in those strange meditation instructions I'm not trying to be self-deprecating but they were
strange um what I was alluding to with the kind of
like potential energy of each moment the sense of like needs to be elaborated
upon need to know which way this can go and um and so that that infuses our
Consciousness and at different gateways to um like a deeper Stillness or Letting
Go it um it can feel like it's our job to do
more to do something to make something happen and um I'll Circle back to the
fear but that that at that Gateway it feels like okay I have to I got to do something now but doing something that
sense of willfulness is actually just more static
in these Realms you know when we get quiet in that way trying to do something
which is trying to be somebody that's more
static and many of these kind of like you know these gateways to into some
deeper intimacy deeper surrender deeper states of practice they're highly
attenuated self States know like the
ordinary sense of the control tower of preferences of judgments of agendas like
all of that is is thinned out otherwise we're not granted access to any kind of
Stillness and the sense of of Free Will of me like orchestrating this
thing me entering into something me um
you know choreographing my practice sense of of that control even
of the free sense of free will that gets thinned out and the pressure to uh to make
something happen is just more
contraction okay so the arising
of spirit ual vertigo
um sometimes comes when we're so accustomed to the somethingness of the
self the solidity of the self it's like um we've just grown so
accustomed to reiterating the the kind of story of
me that uh these attenuated self States they they are jarring right it feels
like it's like um we're standing at some kind of abyss and it's almost like I can't
really see where I fit in there that's
scary and sometimes at that Gateway that kind of doorway there might be fear yeah
but there is also craving and engine in and the craving needs to be
known clearly in Awareness
relas nothing actually needs to happen you know it feels like um I think
I think it was Jesse Vega fry who said like you know was describing a long retreat he said he was like had this
sense of like like being right on the cusp of something you know he said like that's the worst you know on the cusp
you know but we do get to the cusp of some
things and um but the way we kind of enter is
um is by releasing the the need for anything to
happen the goodness unfolds from not needing anything to happen
sometimes when the fear comes up we we make the fear an object of practice as
as you're implying you know and so we're deconstructing the experience
of fear like okay what is this why do I call it fear I'm not disputing that but
why do I call it that what is its signature Body Mind
how can we know it as impermanent you know how do we know
it uh you know soothe it soothe it with
love sometimes we we simply need to go through that we need to like many times
we have to actually habituate so that the fear is kind of like old hat you know it's like oh yeah
yeah familiar with this get quiet then
Mara me whatever you want to however you want to language it there's the
fear sometimes uh you know once the fear is Arisen it's it's just it's already
too late you know uh that's okay too that's okay too
we're practicing such that spiritual vertigo is less likely to
arise and yeah I mean sometimes in the kind of
hyper plastic you know modes of deep
practice some of the the sort of most congealed self States rise up to meet
the kind of precipice of a Nat of not self that's that's that's uh that really
does happen you know it's like the Stillness and the quiet it makes love
much more accessible but also everything else much more accessible seems weird
you know but yeah Stillness can make hate more accessible make the most dense self
States more accessible these are much more fluid Realms of
being okay so we're we this is sometimes there's something to do in the moment
sometimes it's this gradual training we don't have to perfectly heal
no one has perfect psychological health no one has no
scars but we're working so that our past is De electrif
ified and the pain of the past the pain of our life can it might still hurt but it can
no longer Ambush us ainus is no there no monsters
lurking sometimes the monster is uh mortality the the changing of all things
the grief at the center of all things and so we let our heart acclimatize to that fact you
know um the fact that we we already know how every story
ends not always so Suzuki Ros she
said and so we we focus sometimes on the pleasant so
much feels uh really good and you know we just
marinate in that we get on a kind of positive feedback loop ah yeah very
pleasant bake that into your circuits feels good to be tranquil this is safe
this is a safe kind of pleasure this is a safe kind of
surrender and then um sometimes the the the only thing we
can entrust ourselves to is faith faith that the
darkness will not harm me faith that something
love will catch me and the sense that I'll be you know
I'll be harmed by this silence it's almost like the last breath of the
thawing self we surrender to dhma trust in the
lineage and uh know that you are not uh the exception to the
Buddhist rule so let
welcome uh the uh silence beckons you
okay thank you uh thank you all yeah uh appreciate your
attention and uh I'll um won't have class next week but uh
back on uh 26 we'll keep going I'll I'll
post the uh link to submit any questions I obviously can't answer all but they um
help uh um structure my thinking and understand
some of you all right you um take good care good to uh good to be with you