good morning and warm greetings This is a sound
check also an invitation to let me know if um you're
on the chat or to silently reflect what you noticed yesterday in
your practice what you noticed about staying in your seat connecting to
the
moment Great Thank you for the sound feedback
So this today we will be um on the fourth of fifth fourth of
five inspirations for insight this week's
series and
um invitation is to find a meditation
posture that helps connect you to the moment after you've finished whatever last bits of settling in need to
happen Perhaps taking a couple of longer slower deeper
breaths Inviting the attention
inwards relaxing
softening allowing the breath to connect you with your core
and then allowing the breathing to be
natural and settling in Noticing the sensations of being
alive warmth or cool a feeling of
await And feelings of lightness
Noticing motion vibrancy in the
body inviting attunement to that
vibrancy the language of sensation
Allowing attention to settle on the process of breathing
Setting aside concerns of there or
then to tune in to the natural [Music]
rhythm of your body
Attending with care kindness to any thoughts
emotions distractions that come up Noticing them allowing them to
persist and reconnecting with this
breath This moment
noticing whatever arises with simplicity
Allowing the mind the
heart to rest in
Contact with whatever is soothing whatever is [Music]
connecting in embodied experience at this moment
And as you settle into this meditation
practice noticing anything that contracts the heart and mind
that brings up more
tension Seeing if it's possible to soften around
it Perhaps take a step back Allow space for it to move through
And noticing any sensations or feelings of
ease comfort pleasant sensations
and appreciating those without hanging
on allowing them resting in them
In these last minutes of meditation together
Noticing how it feels in this moment in the body heart and mind
Taking a moment to reflect
back if there were any moments of challenge or
difficulty Meeting them with
compassion And if there are any moments of goodness of
benefit kindness [Music]
calm steadiness
awareness appreciating those noticing
them Perhaps reflecting on what fed or supported [Music]
them Allowing them to soak through your own
system Nourish your
practice And then from that place perhaps with an internal gesture
of generosity offering the benefits of this
practice outwards to the others in your life the others in this
world
May they be safe
happy healthy May they be
peaceful at ease and
free May the goodness of this practice ripple out
through our own minds and hearts and lives to all of the lives we
touch and all of the lives they touch outwards and
outwards May all beings be safe happy
peaceful and free And may this
practice be a cause and condition for the growth of love and liberation and
peace in our world
Thank you for the sincerity of your practice
So warm greetings
SA Today as I mentioned earlier is the fourth of fifth five um talks in a
series on inspirations for insight These are stories from the time of the
Buddha and soaking some of the wisdom out of them together in ways that
support the arising of insight in our practice So today
uh when we left off yesterday the Buddha had just awakened We're fast forwarding
some time now and it's a story that happened not
long after his young son Rahula joined the order ordained and um this particular
story happens when Rahula is about 7 years old and it starts in mid
conversation and it's clear from the first question the Buddha asks
um that young Rahula had told a lie A
lie which was later discovered So we can all relate to this having been kids and
maybe having lied since then The Buddha gently shows his son using a
bowl that um a lying progressively lying in the can
have a negative effect on spiritual practice He
describes um a bowl being almost empty as empty as of water as being as empty
as a person becomes in the spiritual life if they repeatedly lie And then he
kind of dramatically turns the bowl over and then turns it back upright to show
no water left And that that is the effect over time And we can imagine that his young
son became sharply attentive in this moment So it wasn't a shaming
conversation or a blaming conversation but it was direct And the Buddha rather than um
sort of castigating him or finger wagging then provides a teaching a kind
of a pathy teaching to guide him in kind of a compass for behavior in the future
A compass to empathize with others and to recognize the impact of his actions
on himself and others And the teaching starts out with
the Buddha asking "What is the purpose of a mirror son?" And Rahula says "Well for
reflection sir." And the Buddha then says "Just
like that you should reflect before each action of body speech and
mind Will it cause affliction suffering in myself the other person myself and
the other And if so don't do it And then the Buddha goes on and I'm
paraphrasing here because it's actually quite long I'm summarizing You should reflect during
each action of body speech and mind Will this cause affliction or harm And if so
stop doing it Right Then and then reflecting after each
action of body speech or mind Will this has this caused affliction or harm in
myself in the other person or people or in all concerned And if so make a resolve not
to repeat that So on the other hand the Buddha says if
you reflect before during and after each action of body speech and mind and
discover oh this action led to benefit to goodness for myself the other person
or all involved then it is fine to do to continue the action to repeat it
So again the image of a mirror reflecting on inward and outward
actions It's another way of talking about karma kama action and
result It's also a teaching on conditionality cause and effect and
empathy Powerful guide to behavior Simple enough for a
seven-year-old And we're not talking here about absolute standards of right
and wrong Instead what's offered is a simple way
to use self-reflection as a compass for all of the actions of life Is it harmful
or beneficial Is it afflictive or conducive to healing to peace to care
So I found this teaching supports insight both directly and indirectly As a direct support for
insight reflect on my own mind on your own mind And with mindful awareness it's
possible to observe one's own internal speech and actions of thought to assess
which are afflictive to oneself or others and to refrain from giving them
any energy or excess energy Well for most people it's usually
easiest to start this by reflecting after meditation maybe right at the end
of a meditation as we did at the end of this meditation preceding my
talk With practice what this repeated reflection does is help a
spontaneous wordless understanding to arise during meditation during an act of
me mental speech during an act of
thinking So using this kind of reflection is not an invitation to fight the difficult forces in your own mind
Rather it's an invitation to meet them with softness
care and understanding of their conditioned nature and to notice Notice the
impact Notice the impact
Eventually through this process that which causes suffering
dissolves it softens or is transformed
into wisdom Arrows into flowers We learn from our own
duka Lama Surya Das Um I was at a talk of his once and um he was asked if any
of his neurosis had disappeared over his many many years decades of meditation
And I was so struck by his answer He kind of laughed and he said "Nothing's gone away but it's so light now that I
don't pay any attention to it It has no affliction for me It's just the mind
doing its thing." I'm paraphrasing there So eventually the suffering is
transformed either into wisdom or into something that we can just shrug smile
say "Okay nature of the mind The system our systems learn through
this process that for example generosity feels better than
stinginess That kindness has a much more beneficial effect than
harshness That simplicity simplicity is more easeful
than complication And another thing I take from this story
is that mindfulness mindful awareness is a form of honesty
You'll notice this in your own practice that the understanding and capacity to
see one's own mental activity can get sharper keener subtler more
conducive to insight Especially if we get interested in
this reflection before and after affliction harm benefit ease that begins
to invite more discernment into the mind And this simple teaching invites us
to turn our life energy and attention to cultivating those internal mental
actions that are beneficial whole making
simplifying gradually there's more contentment and space ease and
lightness then there's an indirect support for insight by reflecting on our actions of
body and speech in the world not incidentally this also serves as a
compass for navigating life harmoniously reflecting outwardly if if there well
inwardly on the outward process has there been benefit or harm to
another this is another way of talking about ethical conduct sila it's also a way of continuing to
learn and grow from reflection on actions many centuries after the
Buddhist time the field of clinical chap Chapy training evolved and I was a
chaplain for a while I went through that training at first not with the idea of becoming a
professional which I did but with the idea of it deepening my practice and in
particular there was a model in that training of action reflection
action priceless opportunity because we learned from each other Those of us that
were embedded in the hospital or wherever the people are embedded we learned our impact on each
other through honest reflective conversations for the purpose of being
as safe for others as skillful and as self-aware as
possible And a lot of time would be spent writing and reflection on our own
interactions with others So this process actually in some ways
echoes the Buddha's last piece of advice to his son If he discovered Rahula
discovered that he'd done something that caused affliction or harm the Buddha
advised him to tell someone that he respected and
trusted And this itself was not for the purpose of being again
punished but for the purpose of learning changing
adapting It's a growth mindset It's helpful to work through these
things It's said that the purpose of a spiritual teacher a spiritual friend is
to hold a mirror up to the back of our heads
to help us see what we can't see Now just like in meditation the vast
majority of us learn this kind of reflection by noticing the impact of an
action afterwards If this is you you're in good company The Buddha presents this
teaching in chronological order but most of us experience it in
reverse Reflecting on the effect of thought speech and action
afterwards and even dur during can be more of a
contemplation And Naomi Shabnai the poet glosses the word contemplation as a long
loving look a long loving
look So gradually with this kind of honesty
care love compassion mindfulness awareness ethical
sensitivity increase and we notice actions and their veilance that I've
been discussing here during and even
beforehand It's a gradual cultivation of wisdom and compassion and it gradually
leads to more confidence strength lightness and joy
So dear Sana my invitation to you for the next
24 hours your homework should you choose to do it is to
reflect either during or after or before
one action of body one action of speech and one action of mind What do you notice
harm or benefit affliction or lightness and how are you able to be with
that The most important thing is to hold whatever you discover in
kindness Thank you for your kind attention