hello everyone and aware that for some people it's good
morning some afternoon some good
evening hello around the globe that are
listening and to continue now with this kind of
series is on samadi I want to mention that often when
we sit down to meditate a very common maybe almost
daily uh guidance in meditation is to relax the body to settle the
body and it is a kind of bring the body into kind of a
homeostasis the kind of balance for it to relax today I'd like to do the same for
the mind it's possible to bring the mind to
a kind of homeostasis that kind of
balance and more important that it's possible to uh for the thinking mind the Mind
itself to uh not be tense not be contracted and
there's no pressure in it the Mind itself becomes settled in a very nice
way and um and in becoming settled uh becoming a healthy mind becoming a
stable mind becoming a a unified
mind so to assume a meditation
posture and to think of the medit
assuming the posture is a ritual of becoming
present a ritual of connecting to your
body and grounding yourself in the
body so that if you lower your gaze or close your
eyes you you're ready to sense and feel
the body not from the control tower in terms of thinking about
it but more feeling it from the
inside the sensations of the body taking some moments to become more
familiar what it feels like the sensations of your legs your feet and your legs
legs what are the sensations associated with your sitting bones
or the contact against some surface that's holding you
up what are the sensations dancing
in your lower
torso and what are the sensations alive for you in your upper
torso the area of the chest the back rib cage
and what are the sensations in your hands and
arms is there any way to adjust the positioning of your hands so it's more comfortable and
balanced less tension
what are the sensations of your shoulders and if there is tension in the
shoulders as you exhale to relax and soften
what are Sensations in the
neck and where the spine joins the
skull and is there any small little adjustments of the positioning of the
head that feel good for you feel relieving or
opening or perhaps give you a little confidence as you sit
here and what are the sensations in your face
and if there is tension in your face as you exhale to let there be a
softening softening without ambition expectation that things actually
soften maybe it's more of an opening to it an allowing
and what are the sensations in your thinking mind the mind that thinks or
visualizes is there any pressure contraction tightness
is there any
agitation are there the sensations of any emotions
underlying your thinking
process and take a few couple of minutes now to
discover without needing to change or relax the mind to become more familiar with how
this thinking mind is for you almost like you're giving yourself a
guided tour of the thinking mind just to get to know it not to change it not to judge it
and in particular the sensations the
feelings the direct experience associated with the thinking mind what
is it like for you
a calm process of
discovery and the Mind as a whole is more more than just a thinking
mind is there some way that you can feel or
sense the larger process of mentality that's more than just
thinking a larger process which within which thinking is one component part
maybe part of this larger process of
mentality is some sense of Silent awareness itself
maybe there's a sense of the Mind in its
fullness has no edges to it awareness has no edges
it spreads out into the space all around the
mind all beyond the head
and now as you exhale to relax the thinking
mind letting the thinking
mind settle settle into this wider space of mind
as you exhale a gentle calming of the thinking
mind so that any pressure tightness agitation
quiets settles moves to a Stillness
and to stay connected to the present moment you
might feel the rhythm of the body
breathing with the sense that you're breathing with the
Mind breathing with with any calmness or settling in the
mind for
and as we
continue please see if you can
discover what happens to the quality of your
mind when you get absorbed in
thinking sometimes there's a disconnect you're no longer aware of of the Mind as
a whole maybe not even aware of the
body sometimes we're thinking the
mind kind of goes out like a light going
out things get
darker or there's a contraction or a narrowing the mind gets
small the stronger the thinking the more there's a physical
location from where thinking
occurs notice what it's like how the quality of the Mind changes if you get
caught in thinking and after exploring that a
bit return to breathing with the breathing
accompanying a connection to the mind
companying the best quality of mind that's
available
for
for for
for e
to breathe with the Mind breathe feeling and sensing the
thinking mind to breathe and feel the tensions in
the mind and as you
exhale to relax the Mind soften
calming the mind so the Mind
settles maybe any sense of the weight of the Mind feels a gentle tug of
gravity so it settles comes to
rest
for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate our capacity to know the
mind to know what we're thinking what we're wanting what we don't
want to know our motivations and impulses before we
act and then how learning about ourselves learning about the mind the
heart through this practice can show us that we have choice
of what we say and do choice about what we refrain from doing and refrain from
saying and this choice is
invaluable because it allow us to to choose that which is beneficial for
ourselves and for others to avoid causing
harm to avoid void making situations worse and may it be that
the that our capacity for
mindfulness is used to for to use for the sake of benefiting ourselves and
others for the sake of the common
good for the sake of support supporting and caring for
others may this practice we're doing be for the welfare and happiness
of everyone may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank [Music]
you
e e
so hello and welcome to this now this seventh talk on this samade
series and um a lot of uh our success in being able
to cultivate somebody the unified state of being
has a a lot to do with how well we know ourselves that if we know ourselves
well entering into these states of concentration absorption don't have to
doesn't have to be an act of will doesn't have something that we force oursel into
or uh strain to enter into but rather it's a profound settling in it's a
profound kind of entering into to a new mode of being but the the the it really requires
understanding ourselves well and one of the things to understand is what happens
to our mind our me our thinking mind or mind when we get
distracted when we get pulled into obsessive thinking and I began this uh week with
the discussion about the first two hindrances desire and aversion
and today I'll continue with that with the second uh the the third and fourth
hindrances which is U usually called sloth and toror as the third and
restlessness and remorse or restlessness and agitation
worry as the fourth and um and what all
these hindrances have in common and and partly why they they're so hindering for us is they they
involve uh mental preoccupation they involve this thinking
which may be borders on a being obsessive that we get pulled into the world of rumination of daydreaming of
commentary of story making and and it's the in the and that
in the strength of this thinking we get absorbed in the content of the thought and we don't see we don't even see
what's happening we don't even know we're thinking and uh but one of the
consequences is that we're thinking about things which are not that wholesome or healthy for us to be
thinking if we there are certainly healthy ways of having desire and thinking about what we want but as a
hindrance there's an obsessive quality and often times we're thinking in ways
and With Attitudes that are not healthy that are full of of maybe greed or
strain or conceit or aversion or hatred and it's
the power of these UNH wholesome ways that gives uh strength through our
preoccupation to be lost in thought or keep getting pulled into it and even if we're not lost in it we know we're doing
it it's they're compulsive and we can't quite know how to stop them and it can
be quite discouraging the force of these kinds of uh thinking is um
uh very significant because they have a conditioning effect they there's a
feedback loop with when we're thinking in ways that are UNH wholesome uh that
creates uh more UNH wholesomeness within us it makes us feel kind of lousy or not so good and this is particularly true
with the third and fourth hindrances the third um is anything that
that kind of drains us that depletes us so the energy is not there in a full way
sometimes there's a numbing effect that goes on uh by how we think or what we're concerned with sometimes there's a
shutting down sometimes there's a freezing like a flight or freeze there's
a freezing because we things are so difficult for us sometimes there's a profound
discouragement or a or a shutting down going to sleep because we're resisting something or we're
overwhelmed but those can come with some kind of attitude udes or thinking or
beliefs that are operating maybe even subliminally that we're pulled into and we don't even know how much we don't
even realize how much they've affected us and with agitation and remorse and
worry regrets um there too uh there is um
something we're thinking about uh we're thinking about something that agitates us and we're energized we're activated
in a way that it doesn't really feel Pleasant it feels like you know agitation Restless or uh so we're
thinking about something it's a or or remorse or regrets or worry all have to
do with things we're thinking about and so what the the thinking mind is activated so in in both of these
third and fourth hindrances it's certainly possible to feel the effect that those being and those hindrances
have on the body but more important for this what I'm going to talk about today the effect
it has on the mind the effect it has on being
aware um and um when we're caught in thoughts uh there's usually physical
Sensations think a lot there are physical s Sensations that come along with the thinking there can be a
location for thinking that is contracted or tight or as pressure there is a
narrowing of attention to a small little domain of the mind there is
um uh tightness there is uh maybe uh maybe I
said pressure and um maybe some people have reported when they get caught in
the world that uh it's almost like the light went out things got dark and when they wake up it's like the light comes
back on and so what effect does it have on the mind what does effect it have on the
awareness can you feel how there's a compulsion in it maybe even a sense that
the we're wearing blinders and we only see what we're concerned with we don't see the bigger picture we don't see the
fullness the wholeness of what's going on and um like like if we have a verion
with someone else we don't see their goodness if um we
are discouraged by something we're not in the and we shut down we get depleted
then we don't feel that uh we don't have the wherewithal to see where is the choice
where is the inspiration where can we make a difference in a way that does make it better uh even if we can't get
what we want or something is limiting us dramatically um we don't have to be defined by
it and so um so how is it affecting the mind and the reason why this is
important for somat is that samade is a
healing of the mind so it's not fragmented so it's not uh uh so we're
not uh it's not limited we're not caught in a small little domain the hindrances have a way of
limiting the Mind narrowing the mind uh blocking the mind not allowing the
fullness of the mind to be there and uh and for somebody to occur there's a the
mind gets reorganized so it's not fragmented or it's not narrow it's not uh limited and
so first we have to see the effect that our thinking the hindrances have on the mind to appreciate that it's how how
limited has become how fragmented it's become how small it's become or
contracted it's become or or um uh or maybe a sense of weight and
heaviness that feels like a burden on the mind and um and so it might be
discouraging to feel these qualities of the mind that can be there when we're caught in the hindrances OR caught in
thought but the um what we're doing here is seeing getting discovering how the
mind is like so that the the the ways in which awareness can support us to heal
it to knit it back together again to bring us back into the wholeness of the
Mind where all the capacities of the mind can work in a kind of homeostasis or work together for the same
purpose so um so part of the task for
somebody is become a mind Whisperer to become someone who begins to sense and
feel and know and recognize the quality of the Mind not just what you're
thinking about in fact what you're thinking about might be important but
for you what's more important is the quality
of the mind is the is the uh aliveness of the
Mind the goodness of the mind and with Sloth and torper the quality of the mind
kind of becomes deflated with agitation and worry the quality of the mind gets agitated and gets uh uh um you know um
gets overactivated and um both of them are not so useful for us but we if we can
see that and know how the mind has shifted under the force of these two states that's the beginning of being
able to open up or to allow something to settle the settling of the mind or the
calming of the mind or the opening of the mind or the expanding of the Mind
Over time for meditators there's all this Rich world of the mind that we
begin to sense and feel that's so much greater than what we are thinking about
and we begin to appreciate that um is um that there's
more the mind is bigger awareness is bigger than any of the particular things
we're focusing on so if we're agitated chances are there's something it might
be subconscious something that worries us or concerns us or or uh we're we're
troubled by and um and can we feel that sense of
agitation troubling of the mind can we care for it can we hold it in the simple
rhythm of breathing um a lot of what samadi is about and mindfulness itself is not
about fixing things it's not about judging things and but rather it's about
healing things settling things in meditation we don't solve
anything we dissolve our problems problems are not solved they're
dissolved in the in the larger uh scope of intelligence
that is not even personal when the mind is full and the mind is Unified and
whole so the part that I'm hoping that you'll understand from this talk the
most is uh the value of becoming familiar with the quality of your mind
the characteristics of your mind in different situations that you're in a different during different mental
activities and particular how some mental activi some forms of thinking some some forms of wanting and
not wanting some forms of discouragement and some forms of worry that they create
a particular kind of mind that is much more limited the full capacity of the
mind is not really available and to start feeling and sensing what this is like uh in in
preparation for how some will help this to settle help this to quiet to calm and
the mind becomes whole or unified so to the degree to which you
might understand what I've said today i' encourage you so during this next period
until for the next 24 hours when you're awake that you might um uh take time
through the day maybe even put a timer on that goes off every 15 minutes or 30
minutes or something and then to remind you what's the quality of the Mind how
is the thinking I'm involved in the activity I'm doing how has this affected the quality of the
mind and in what way is the mind now become limited and narrow and tight and
and um and is it possible to open it again so um
thank you very much and um and as I've said now a few times we're going to go
through we're laying down a slow foundation for somat and we're going to
go over these weeks uh into some of the deeper states of Som but it's really
important to lay the foundation for it in a slow maybe systematic way so that
you're getting more more and more familiar with the territory
and um so may you study your mind today thank you