good morning friends good morning good afternoon good
evening whatever time zone you might be in this moment in
time i am in the European time zone um and I'm zooming in youtubing in um from
Tuscanyany in Italy you hear the the church bells and there was a bit of a
hiccup with internet um so started the YouTube a bit late but right now we're
right on time 7:00 a.m california time 4:00 p.m italian time so it's wonderful
to see you wonderful to sit with you i'm excited to be teaching uh this week
supporting Gail in being your way supporting the SA and um I'm excited
about the theme this week and the theme
is the theme of concord and harmony and uh
we'll flow this week uh with teachings about uh friendship kalyana
uh how are we a good friend for others friendship those aspects of harmony
harmony in community in friendships in relationships uh the relational aspect I
know that Gil has been teaching uh for many weeks now on samadei very dear to
my heart and when he comes back he'll teach about vapasana and here now we're we're we'll I figured we'll bring in
some of the relational aspects um of of practice this week
together because they're very very important as the as the Buddha said
spiritual friendship is not half of the holy life i'll talk about this more it's
not half of the spiritual life it's the entire it's 100% of of spiritual life of this
practice so I'll say a lot more of course well 15
minutes worth of dharmat but let's uh let's land together let's arrive
together to your sa dear community coming in coming together from so many
different places in the world it's lovely to see all the hellos coming in
warms my heart especially as I mentioned I'm far away from home um so it's very
sweet to connect to sa in this way it's the first time I'm teaching while I'm away internationally so so with that I
want to invite all of us to feel to feel our connection feel our
connection to feel our connection to one another
we belong to one another and we belong to this
earth and inviting ourselves to arrive and to
settle settle in our
body to feel the connection of our
feet if we're sitting in a chair to feel the connection of our feet with the
earth I'm here on this
earth wherever I am on this earth I am home
i belong
earth feeling the sense of connection allowing your body to
relax to
land to feel the land wherever you are to feel the
air it's nourishing your lungs wherever you
are inviting ourselves to land to
settle with each inbreath and each outreath more fully more fully into the
body to the earth earth on earth this body earth element
on earth
whatever is arising in this moment in the mind in the
heart can we gently lay it down just for a moment
allow ourselves to be nourished simply by being simply by being
alive by being
breathed can this be enough more than enough
plenty simply to be alive in the midst of the full
catastrophe
yeah release release release what is not needed
release what is not needed or so much that is not needed
we'll settle for a few more minutes with the body sense of the body and the
breath before I invite the reflection let's keep settling
continuing to settle to release release any tension in
the body
release thoughts preoccupations that are just not needed right now thank you i'll
come back to you
later dropping in to the heart to the
body to the earth
feeling the deliciousness of just being
here the joy of presence
so simple
feeling our belly our
sitbones our feet our
hands our breath in our belly
hey now I would like to invite us
way to brighten our heart and mind to drop in this reflection into our
heart into our belly our abdomen as if dropping a pebble in a
pond in a body of water into our heads this is not a heady reflection but drop
it in see what happens not to think about this
reflection but drop it in let yourself be silent let it
resonate and the reflection is
this bringing to heart a
friend or a benefactor who has been there for you at
some point in your life
who has supported you through their presence their [Music]
kindness their guidance
perhaps if you're considering a benefactor they've protected and guide
guided you or if a good
friend the kalana I'll say more about that later a
good friend they've been there for you with their heart with their full
presence with kindness reflecting reflecting your own goodness
dropping this reflection into your heart and listening for what
arises just sitting with what arises not making stories not thinking but just
sitting sitting with the goodness with the gladness with the
gratitude of what arises with this connection
let the goodness of this being this
person at that point in your life to brighten your heart the
nourishment of friendship of
connection simply this and sit with this brightness with your breath
breathing in breathing out grounded in the body in the
heart breathing in the goodness of this being breathing out with joy sharing the
goodness of this being as if you're spreading this gladness of the heart
with the world as if you're silently shouting
through your breath "Dear world what a beautiful human
being what a beautiful connection."
And if your heart has a tendency to go towards
negative bring it back you can do this bring it back stay
stay with relishing the good not all the ways that people have
failed etc stay with the good there is lots of good always
notice if the goodness of this connection this gratitude this
brightness of this heart this heart-to-heart connection can spread can
be felt throughout your body be patient
if you notice different friends want to come into your heart
space that's okay but spend time with each friend good in a good
while not jumping from one to the next to the next spend time with them in your heart
to welcome them appreciate their goodness sit sit in their goodness their
brightness their kindness their generosity their
care and if your heart starts to close oh I don't deserve this yes you do we
all do it's hard enough being human don't get in your own way
then as we turn to bring this sit to a close
together appreciating Appreciating
Whoever came up to in your heart as good friend or good friends
benefactor benefactors appreciating the
connection the goodness goodness in this world that
you've been privy to you've been a part of you've been a recipient you've been
a co-creator
receiving kindness giving kindness presence resting in this goodness
whatever arose for another beat and also
appreciating whatever arose even if the opposite arose it's okay it's exactly
what it what needed to arise in this moment can I be okay can I release can I
relax around how things have come to be in this moment not fighting not
resisting embracing opening my heart wide to embrace whatever is whatever has
come to be born of causes and conditions can there be goodness in this
moment appreciating being in community sitting
in community in this moment and appreciating yourself for
having showed up having been a good friend to yourself a benefactor to yourself to
have brought yourself here to this practice
period so much goodness
kalana so much goodness kusala so much goodness beauty
wholesomeness appreciating yourself appreciating one
another appreciating appreciation
may all beings benefit from the fruit of my practice in ways I cannot
fathom may all beings be well may all beings be
free and since I don't have Oh wow here is a
bell okay there's the church bell for the very end of our practice how perfect is
that i don't know if that came through or if it got or if it got cut but
ding ding
ding so I'm going to pause the recording for a moment and switch
oh hello hello hello friends from around the
world and if you joined us late or very late welcome welcome welcome and as I
mentioned I'm in Tuscanyany now i'm in Italy it's in the
afternoon and had some challenges with internet earlier and hopefully it's
smooth now you haven't lost me i haven't lost you yay so much gratitude this is
good so so for today's theme I'd like to um
I'd like to speak a bit i'd like to expand on the power of spiritual
friendship kalyana mita
so in in the Buddha's dispensation and
the sassana the cultivation of virtue and wisdom is inseparable from nurturing
of wise companionship and spiritual friendship
is not merely support but it's the entire holy life it's the entirety of
this path it's the entirety of this path and as this beautiful story goes
um Ananda who was the Buddha's attendant and
cousin uh one day he approaches the Buddha and remarks "Admirable friendship
is half of the holy life." And the Buddha corrects them and says "Not so Ananda not
so." This is the entire holy life when a practitioner has admirable
friends companions and comrades it is to be expected that they
will develop and cultivate the noble eight-fold
path and it makes sense right it it's not it's so beautiful i love the way
Ananda comes and says "Oh it's half of it right it's 50 person." It's like "No no no it's the entire thing it's
spiritual friendship it's good friendship it's it's wholesomeness of whom we associate with." And modern
research psychological research aligns with this and
um the there's a long longitudinal longitudinal study uh that shows that
social connection is the most powerful um predictor of of mental health of even
mortality much more than success and fame
and various other aspects so um so there's there's a wholesomeness to
to connection to good connection and right companionship isn't
just helpful it is vital for our life even for survival for us to live um and
and the study by the way also talks about mortality that that those with without
um lack of of uh connections social connections also
it's it's a um it correlates with with
shorter lifespan not as not as much health etc and it makes sense we know
this we we don't need research to tell us this but yet it's so interesting for
me also how the teachings um of the Buddha about how important connection is
how important is you know because in practice we we we go towards meditation
silent meditation oh yes silent meditation yeah yeah that's of course silent meditation is so important in the
context of connection spiritual friendships they are not just 50% of the
path they're 100% of the path
wow so kalana mita uh kalana the word kalana means
beautiful virtuous and mitata means friendship so kalana mita beautiful
virtuous friendship it in it it's um this this beautiful
term that you might have heard uh in in the teachings it's an elevated bond
that's that's not just friendship of oh let's go for a walk though walks are nice but
it it really it's elevated this kind of friendship is elevated to foster ethical
and spiritual growth and and again in in studies show
that there is emotional co-regulation that that we unconsciously
regulate um our emotional state through trusted relationships there is mutual
attunement that calms our nervous system and strengthens our resilience so this
attunement that uh that this emotion deep emotional attunement is part of the
gift of kalana mita of this rich beautiful virtuous friendship
friendships and so so in Buddhist terms one can say
that spiritual friends buffer us from afflicted emotions and steady our minds
on the path isn't that beautiful to consider that there are many benefits
that spiritual friendships offer we'll talk more about it this week and of
course our role in it too we'll talk about that too to consider that it's a
buffer from afflictive emotions that that good friends good virtuous ethical
friends support us bring us back bring us back they inspire us they they they
support us through modeling through their presence through their own
goodness and and there is this what's called the soil principle we grow in
accordance to our environment we grow we're like these seeds that we grow in
accordance to our environment just as a plant needs fertile soil and good
conditions to flourish a practitioner also needs an environment of virtue
wisdom and kindness in Majima Manikaya 95 in the Changi Suta
it highlights the importance of proximity to the
wise so the Buddha says when one approaches associates with and attends
upon the wise one gains faith or
trust energy mindfulness concentration and wisdom isn't that beautiful
i'll read it again when one approaches associates with and attends upon the
wise one gains trust energy mindfulness
concentration and wisdom
and similarly modern research supports that social contagion research on social
contagion reveals that our attitudes our behaviors and emotional states spread
through the network even unconsciously wow right so much
responsibility so again social contagion and this study
is by Fowler and Triakis in 2008 the title of it is dynamic spread of
happiness in a large social network it's a longitudinal study over 20 years but
then they found that happiness and unhappiness spreads through social
groups up to three degrees of separation and if they they could only test up to
three degrees of separation so your friends your friends friends so if you became happier if your you became uh if
your happiness level your your emotional state shifted not just your friends but
your friends and their friends three degrees out there was impact so there's
emotional contagion three levels out and if they could have measured further out
they I bet I'm willing to bet they would have seen they would have seen um
influence on the social contagion which is why you know when we at the end of
the practice when we dedicate the merit to the well-being of all beings
everywhere in ways we cannot fathom in ways we cannot imagine it's not just
those three levels out but it's the contagion many many layers out when we are
cultivating [Music] kindness [Music]
peacefulness care stability [Music]
equinimity wisdom it it ripples it ripples through the
network and the the um see how much time do I
have maybe I'll share this as well and then the Buddha offers this this
metaphor of milk and water the image of blending harmoniously
in in uh Angutar Nikaya 854 the Buddha praises two monks and says just as milk
and water when poured together blend insepar
inseparably so too they dwell blending like milk and water regarding each other
with kindly eyes i love that regarding each other with kindly
eyes regarding each other with kindly eyes so there are other other places in
the sutras when the simile is not mixing like uh water and oil but this is milk
and water and they they mix um beautifully
so and and also again in in psychological
um research there is studies that there's interpersonal synchrony such as
shared joy shared laughter coordinated movements emotional resonance that that
foster profound feelings of unity and trust profound feelings of unity and
trust so like milk and water as the Buddha talks
about so just as milk and water blend seamlessly harmonious sa life can arise
when hearts and action move in resonance and we see ourselves and each other with kindly eyes and there's a lot more to
say about this which I'd like to unpack over the next few days there's a lot
more to say about this so I want to leave us with a few reflective questions
given that we have about a minute
so who has been milk to your water blending seamlessly with kindness
offering stability and protection i invited us to to bring an image of our
uh benefactor uh or good friend and allow their presence to really uh their
their goodness to bring gratitude to bring uh the light to our hearts and I
was enjoying this meditation so much myself i so needed it it's just so lovely to sit in that brightness of
goodness of another being's kindness and generosity here's another couple of reflections how
has the association with virtue v virtuous friends kalana mita open the
path of dharma for me how has association with virtuous friends opened
the path of dharma for me and here's the last one the bells are
coming again i think you can hear them you can let me know i don't know how much um uh the noise cancellation takes
that out but you can put it in chat they're really coming now here's the last reflection in what ways can I offer
the qualities of kalana mita to others today in what ways can I offer the
qualities of good friendship virtuous kind beneficient friendship to others
today so that's my invitation for today thank you so much dear Sana for
joining from all around oh yeah you cannot hear the bells oh okay that's a
pity i tell you what maybe what I'll do is just for the fun of it can I No bells
okay hold on let's see just for the fun of it I can I can turn off Here we go
now you can hear it [Music]
i just turned on the musician original sound so I think you can hear some bells
now anyway thank you all thank you so much for joining may you be well may you be happy
may you be a good friend kalana mita to yourself and to others today be well see
you tomorrow at the same time