good evening good evening welcome
welcome nice to see you all I was just uh reflecting at the as
Jim rang the bell like it's so nice to sit together I I appreciate it very much so if nothing else thank you for uh
sitting with me for this uh 30 minutes it's there's something lovely about that it's different than when you're
home alone right so I was um earlier ear a number of days
ago I was uh reading some of the sutas and preparation for a class I'm going to
teach with some of my friends in a few weeks and reading something that I've
read many times before and looking at it again and like oh H I hadn't really
noticed this before this is often how it is I think with the suit does and so
many things we look at him again and again and there's always some richness or some depth or some novelty or
something new that shows up it's partly why I like to uh look at them and study
them and practice with them but uh one thing that I had just
overlooked before was this whole notion that was in this one little tiny passage
not the main thrust of the suta but just this one little passage this mention of
purific ification they're like I don't really like this word like
purification right it kind of like implies that we're impure and I don't know it just feels heavy-handed and
oppressive and I don't know I just I almost kind of you know ignore it and in
my teachings I don't talk about uh this process as one of
purification but some of you that might be familiar with this tradition you'll know that there's some lineages not this
one but there's some lineages who put more emphasis on this idea of purification and partly because they are
using as a text um something to be authoritative and this book that was written composed
maybe about like a thousand years after the Buddha but that's still 1,500 years
ago right so it's still a long time ago but certainly sometime after that
Buddha and this book is called the vudi Maga maybe you've heard this kind of gets batted around sometimes vasim
Maga this book translated means path of purification and it's a big thick book
and purports like how to uh get oneself purified and so it it talks about uh
this entire path of practice in this context of uh purification
it doesn't talk so much about purification it has a lot to do in there about meditation so this idea of purification
it certainly isn't um unheard of in this tradition but in the this particular
lineage it's not emphasized and maybe I'll just not to go on and on and on about this I could give
a whole lecture about this right but that's not what we want um this whole
notion of purification shows up in the later parts of Buddhism the closer you get to the Buddha as best we can tell
there's not that much about purification so it's something that kind of um came a little bit later and there's a whole
reason about that that I won't go into purification I'm not so keen on this
idea just because it implies that we're impure and I don't know that just doesn't feel very good so I thought well
why don't I look this up in the PO English dictionary maybe there's another way to understand
this maybe there's another way in and you know how like when you look things in the dictionary often like the
first definition is the most common and then there's a second and third and as
it goes down the list right it becomes more and more obscure well here so the word is vudi
that's getting translated as Purity or purification the first definition
brightness like oh the path of brightness or brightening oh I like this and then
the second definition Splendor oh I like this a path of Splendor of Awakening
Splendor allowing splendor splendor rizing we can make a new word out of this path of Splendor
rising or Excellency is the third definition path of Excellence of
becoming excellent or discovering Excellence or having Excellence around r or something like
this the fourth definition is purification so it's interesting that as
translators are taking what's the fourth definition and kind of using that as the definitive one so I'm going to use
brightness I like this idea of brightness and this idea that this is a
path of brightness or brightening and I what does that mean
even this idea of uh brightening there's a few ways we might
understand this but one could be like to see things clearly you know like if there's a certain brightness then you
can see things clearly they're they're not uh behind some Veil or they're not
obscured with Darkness or something like this if there's some brightness you can see things
clearly and that's so much what this path of practice is about is being able
to see things in a way that is closer to maybe what's actually happening when
we're not overlaying on top of all our ideas or our Notions about how things
should be or what we want or what's mine and yours and all these extra things
that we put on them and I'll talk a little bit more about that in a moment but this idea of brightening is to see
things clearly to no longer have illusion to no
longer be obscured so another way we might think about brightening is like when somebody
has a sense of brightness we might say that they have this sense of aliveness or a sense of
Vitality or a sense of uh I don't know Joy or maybe Joy is too strong of a word
but this not a sense of you know kind of closed down but you know bright is like
meeting the world just looking clearly okay what's out there and this sense of brightness a
sense of uh not being stuck some kind of
way so this path of practice is a path of having some aliveness and enthusiasm
maybe we might say or there's a way in which brightness
also can have this sense of creativity this sense of like oh yeah it
a new way seeing things clearly and having some aliveness often brings
creativity so seeing things in a new way not just the usual way our habits our
reactions that our patterns that are we become so accustomed to that sometimes
are not so helpful but we're stuck in them so maybe this way of brightness is
of the create creativity like oh to see things from a different perspective or
maybe combine things in a new way they had thought of before or something like
this and then maybe there's this way that I also say some brightness we might
think about this as some a certain amount of resilience a certain amount of not you
know collapsing in the any um sense of difficulty
arising but instead with there's seeing clearly and having a sense of Vitality
and maybe some creativity then there's this way in which difficulties don't
push us around as much or Bowl us over or cause us to collapse or if they do if
it's a big difficulty then if there's some brightness then there's a way that
we can find our way out of them or not be uh have the setback quote unquote
that lasts as long so this is a this is not a canonical list this is a list that I
made up talking about brightness but this is some of the ways that I think about brightness and I also think about
uh this path of practice as one of that helps support these
things and so I also want to say just a few words about this whole idea of
dullness what what if if brightness or these things well what is dullness like what's the opposite if we don't have
this path of brightness path of brightening
I think there's this way in which dullness can have this uh like we're not
quite present there's like this uh um overlay like you're not quite meeting
what's there this dullness has a maybe there's a veil in some kind of way
between you and experience or you and um other people or there's this not quite I
mean there you're there it's not that you're somewhere else but there's this maybe be kind of like a a hesitation or
a stepping back or something like this dullness right there's this way of maybe just going through the motions or
something like this there's also this way maybe some of you have heard this uh that we talk
about in this tradition about the sword of wisdom you know the sword that can
just cut through delusion when you uh after the sword goes you can see like oh
I see now clearly and dullness right we think that things have not been sharp so this sword
of wisdom not being able to show up kind of in a way that could provide some clarity or help us see things in a new
way so I've been talking about this definition of brightness and this
definition of dullness but maybe more specifically what is it that's getting
brightened if we're talking about this uh path of
brightening I'll say that one thing that's getting brightened or purified if
we want to use that kind of language is our capacity to
notice with this mindfulness practice with this practice that we're inside
practice and maybe some concentration practice is our ability to notice
and chances are all of you have had this experience that uh when you started a meditation practice a mindfulness
practice this is not uncommon and it was certainly the case for me like wow I had
no idea how my mind was like all over the place doing everything except to
being like on the breath like how I wanted it to be like this was kind like the first big Insight that people often
have like wow I had no idea that my mind was doing this we just hadn't noticed
and then when we start to like set the intention okay I'm going to do sitting
meditation on the breath we we start to kind of like hone that skill of coming
back to those sensations of breathing and then we just start to notice all the things that our mind does the planning
the fantasizing the uh reminiscing you know
these types of things but it's not only on the cushion
that are noticing kind of like takes up a a notch if often that we can um just
start to notice how impatient we get sometimes when we're standing in line at
the grocery store and it's a really long line or how we start to get irritated
with drivers on the road that are going too slow that are going way below the
speed limit or maybe they're not paying attention and swerving around and maybe
they're texting while they're supposed to be driving or something and in the past we wouldn't have just noticed our
irritation or our impatience we would have just thought well of course I'm irritated or impatient that's the
natural order of things but as we start to do this practice we start to notice like oh yeah
okay I'm actually irritated and it's possible to not be
irritated we start to feel like there's more more of a that things don't have to be that the
way that they are that they can be other ways too we're not we don't fall into the Trap of the usual
way so maybe that's one of the thing that gets brightened is our
noticing and I uh well uh this I had had an experience and I'll say that my
experience was not uncommon many people have reported this to me when I'm a teaching a retreat and uh people are
coming in for a practice discussion but I don't know why for some reason this particular Retreat uh these experiences
really stick in my mind I don't remember how far in in the retreat it
was near the beginning and just going out for a walk doing some walking meditation and
uh wanting to go find like the perfect spot for walking meditation and just noticing like oh
look there's flowers here wow I never noticed them oh they're so beautiful
taking a few steps wow look at these little plant those little round Le oh
that is so great wow I didn't noticed and then taking a few steps oh wow look at this just you know the usual things
we see all the time just the plants or the flowers or whatever it is all of a sudden everything like just had a
certain Beauty to it a certain maybe they themselves had a certain braak
briess so there's this way that are not only do we notice things that we don't
notice otherwise but there's also a way in which there can be a like a the
beauty of things shine through including things that are not conventionally
thought of aesthetically beautiful like the little candy candy
bar wrapper like wow that red is really shiny next to the green right these types of
things so this brightening of what we notice of what
gets noticed because otherwise you know our La our life is passing Us by as
we're not really paying attention instead just being on automatic
pilot there's this uh Rob Walker he wrote this book that's um the art of
noticing he's not a Buddhist practitioner but uh he's a uh I think a
professor of design and he has all these great ideas of how to pay attention and it's so much
fun I know to think about this and um he has a blog or website or I'm not exactly
sure how this gets communicated but uh he has like the saor of the month so like things to
notice Shadows like for a month just just noticing Shadows um security
cameras so like spend a month when you're out for a walk just notice like oh wow there's more of these than I
thought or uh small flowers you know so he just identifies just things just to
notice as a way to keep us engaged with our life and some you know
provide from his point of view it provides uh a sense of Vitality and aliveness and creativity to kind of like
keep sharp our uh a capacity to
notice but here's something else that's getting brightened which we might say is
really important the art the the capacity to notice can then get applied
to all kinds of things whether we intentionally apply it or not it'll just naturally get
applied and to one particular area can really lead to more and more freedom
more and more ease more and more peace and well-being and that is this
brightening of our capacity to notice the view we have of
ourselves The View we have of our I'm saying
ourselves um but it's a little bit different than that way there's
this but maybe I'll I'll talk about about it this way we might notice that
there's uh different ways to consider I'll just say the self one is just our personality self or
our the ways in which we um the roles that we
have for example right now I'm in the role of the Dharma teacher I was just visiting my mother it
wouldn't go so well if I just showed up to my mom at her house and said okay I'm the
Dharma teacher and gave her darhat talks right this that's just not going to work you know so just this idea that we just
take on roles and then we put them down right when they're not needed and sometime we're identified
with this like the being a Dharma teacher is an obvious role but sometimes there might
be subtle ways in the family I'm the one who's the Troublemaker or I'm the one who fixes things or I'm the one who
supports everybody else or I'm the one that keeps the glue of the family together or I'm the baby that's always
complaining and the world has to take care of me or something like
this so part of this brightening is starting to notice some of the subtle
ways in which we are identifying ourself some of the subtle labels that we have
on ourselves I just gave a whole list of things they don't show up specifically as those
words they're thing that we kind of feel into and just notice oh yeah there's a
theme Here of the way I'm meeting the world or the way that what's difficult
for me and a lot of it is because we are holding on to or clinging onto some
fixed views about ourselves who we are and who we're not
so this is part of what gets brightening is maybe we just start to notice oh there's all kinds of different views
that I have about myself which one is the right one which one is the true one which one
is the real one I'm the one that difficulties following Maps I'm the one that's the
youngest I'm the one that uh knows how to do algebra I don't know I'm just
making these things up right so there's this way in which we
often we have this sense that there's this entity in the center that's like
this constant to which things happen and if that's true well what is
it in the center which view of the self which one
you might say well di di no no no it doesn't work that way it's not one I'm like all of these things like
okay well then maybe is there a um like mental
patterns or maybe habits or something that you do that's uh makes up
yourself this thing that feels like it's in the center of everything and then I could ask the same
question well which one which pattern which thing that you do often
and then you might say well wait don't bother me with that I just feels like there's a self in the center
here and so so much about this maybe this brightening we could say this
brightening we start to see oh yeah we're not the [Music] roles and we're not some of the ideas
that we have about our ourselves but maybe something that I can
uh say here and I've done this uh during a Dharma talk here before but just to
just to ask you let's say that um you could by some magical means let's say
that you could have the creativity or
intellect of anybody else living or dead
or maybe even in the future if you can think that way like if you could have like some of the creativity of some of
these brilliant artists and all these mediums or the intellect of somebody who can just solve problems like this or get
things done who would it be just take a moment who would it
be and then for a second person if you could have the physical
capabilities or the physique of any individual living or dead you could have
like the B bodily capacities or body of anybody who would it
be is there somebody you would choose just take a
moment so this is a trick question
because implicit in even imagining this is the idea like that you could be
yourself with a different mind but how would that
work like that's like if if there was a different mind it wouldn't be you right
but somehow you feel like there's something inside that with a different mind could still be you or same with the
body that some if a body had a different capacity or looked different or in some kind of
way that would still be you so there's often this way and it's subtle that we
are identifying with either our mental capacity or the body and so this
brightening is to start to see oh yeah we're not even that there's there's not even that
subtle sense of this constant thing at the
center every everything is due to causes and conditions everything I mean there
aren't exceptions well I shouldn't say it that way I should say all of our experiences
right are just arising and passing away due to causes and conditions so where would that self
be it's just this collection of experiences so this brightening is
starting to like um maybe like peel away or um help shine through some of this
idea of this causes and conditions is what's uh being experienced not these
different ways in which we are uh having this view of this self and then after I
say this I feel like I often want to say this is not a belief that you have to adopt this is not something like oh all
the Buddhists talk about this not self thing okay I guess so this is more just
have some curiosity and to plant a seed and you might have some you might
start to see more and more in your experience like oh yeah this is always changing how could that be this H self
that's at the center or something like
this what else is brightening this path I would say our
hearts they showing a little bit brighter we see this people have this
practice maybe you've experienced this St I certainly have as there starts to
be we start to notice more and we start to loosen up some of our grip on this view of who we are and how terrible we
are or how great we are whatever it might be we start to see how oh yeah I'm
not so different than everybody else actually they're struggling
too they have uh ups and downs just like I
do and there's this way we start to feel connected and there's much less of a US versus them me versus you and more more
of a sense of this common Humanity like oh yeah this being a human not so easy
sometimes and it's not unique to me not unique to you this idea that there's
difficulties and there's joy and there's love and when we start to see just this
common Humanity when it just starts to become evident it the heart can't help
but care care about
others want there want for there to be less suffering in the world want there to be more ease and
peace in the world it's just natural just happens and this is uh often um also
when I'm like doing practice discussions people in Retreat are often talking about this like wow I didn't realize
like there's so much warmth and love and this type of thing here and again don't
take my word for this don't just believe this because I said it just maybe I'm planting a seed and maybe you might
notice to see if your heart is like opening or softening in some kind of way
maybe a little bit less irritation and ill will and maybe some more
Goodwill so this idea of the path of brightening maybe we might say another
way to say this is like Awakening Brilliance you know just Brilliance with
things that are shining and just allow it allowing it to
arise we're not making it arise we're not forcing it to arise it's what
naturally happens as we start to just pay attention to our experience which is what mindfulness
practice is about and maybe there's Sometimes some inquiry some like what is this or is
this true or is this just something my thoughts are making up so maybe some mindfulness and some
inquiry can really open up just what uh
experience is about and what life is about so Awakening
Brilliance and if I have a poem here that I'm going to close with it's by
Rosemary traumer of course it is what would I do without Rosemary's trummer's
poems those you don't know I'm often quoting her poems I think she's a
fabulous poet so this poem is called a change in
the light and it was written March in the beginning of March
2020 right the beginning of the pandemic before we really knew what was happening
right right at the beginning we none of us had any idea predicted right what was going to happen
but uh here's uh here's this poem a change in the light by Rosemary
traumer now while the Moon is hiding behind the clouds now when the rain is falling
midwinter and now that they've told us not to hug or kiss each other for fear
of Contracting and spreading disease yes now is the time to find
whatever light we have been hiding inside
us whatever measure of Brilliance we've managed to conceal from each other from
ourselves now is the time to bring forth that luminescence and offer it freely to
the world now now when light matters
most I'll read this again this is a change in the
light by Rosemary traumer now while the Moon is hiding
behind the clouds now when the rain is falling
midwinter and now that they've told us not to hug or kiss each other for fear of Contracting and spreading
disease yes now is the time to find whatever light we have been hiding
inside us whatever measure of Brilliance we've managed to conceal from each other from
ourselves now is the time to bring forth that luminescence and offer it freely to the
world now when light matters
most light always matters this luminescence this
Brilliance this uh light always matters especially when
things feel dark especially when it feels like we can't see clearly and there isn't a way
forward there's a kind of dark often has its way of kind of like closing
down now is when we need light and Brilliance from the heart and from the
mind and I'd like to suggest that this practice can support that can support
this Brilliance this luminescence this
brightness I appreciate that in this poem Rose Mar Traer the poet she offers a number of different Nows Moon behind
the clouds when it's raining they've told us not to hug or
kiss but I was thinking like there's so many times in which it feels like it can be
dark terrible news from the doctor's office just terrible
news fires all kinds of
things and there's a way in which we might want to just like okay not look
and uh just keep it in darkness and there can be some wisdom sometimes to
like you know not allow ourselves to get overwhelmed or to not uh get feel too
agitated right that's the job of the media to get you agitated that they get paid to do this absolutely right this is
their job if you're the more agitated you are the more clicking you'll
do but now is a time for some Brilliance for some light some illumination I would
say light always matters and so maybe this can be a I'm
going to call it instead of the path of purification the path of brightening
and with that I think I'll close and open it up to see if there's some comments or questions thank you
what to go back to the original word purification what I thought of when you said that is like a 12-step group so you
want to meditate but you drink a lot right so another probably you would probably have to do something about that
drinking issue to really be able to really to really meditate right so I
mean doesn't matter what called brightness illumination purification but I just thought of a 12-step group when
you said that like if something is really getting in the way you kind of have to you have to do
something about it right or you can't you can't meditate you know if you're an alcoholic so I don't know if I don't
know maybe alcoholic could meditate but you're absolutely right though that there's the things that we have in our lives that don't really surve us I'm
sure and I'll commit yeah I'll take it back but I mean there's certain things that that we have that that we do that
really do get in the way of our you know our Clarity and I just thought of a 12-step group when you when you say this
thank you thank you for saying that yeah yeah this is just maybe a Diana ISM I
just don't like this word purification because I don't like this I don't know I just don't like
it than um yeah I had kind of a similar
point I guess like uh not with alcoholism specifically but even just
like any other obstacles in life like being really busy at work or in a relationship or anything like that um
you know suffering from the fires as many are these days like I think there's always going to be a lot of things that
are getting in in your way of you know focusing on Shining that that light that
you spoke about um and something I personally realize from being here today cuz probably unlike many of you I I
haven't been in a while and I I feel kind of bad about that cuz i' wanted to but like it's just very hard to make the
time and and from being here I've realized like the value of making the time like you just have to make the time
you know like I kind of tried to convince myself that like by getting into meditation in the past you know I
I've been enlightened or whatever and like oh now now I think about things better but like it's just not that way
you just need to make the time and put down the phone and carve out time from from your work or you know solve your
other problems and life and and just um you know really allow yourself the peace
to I guess look within and and you can't really short circuit that's that's just something that I kind of realized
from I guess making the time today I think it's good that everyone else did too yeah nice nice thank you yeah yeah
but it can be also a trap because it can feel this oppressive like oh I have to go to IMC and then there it weighs
heavily on us and then I feel like oh all this story I'm a bad person I'm a bad meditator or something like this and
that that itself can just turn into one more thing that's uh oppressing Us in
some kind of way so yeah it's not so easy right to maintain things that are
supportive and let go of things that aren't so supportive yeah just recognizing that but I'm glad you're
here anybody else have a comment or something I'd like to
say so maybe I'll close by reading this poem one more time just because I like this poem I think
it's now while the Moon is hiding behind the clouds now when the rain is falling
midwinter and now that they've told us not to hug or kiss each other for fear of Contracting and spreading
disease yes now is the time to find whatever light we have been hiding
inside us whatever measure of Brilliance we've managed to conceal from each other from
ourselves now is the time to bring forth that luminescence and offer it freely to the
world now when light Matters Most thank
you and wishing you all a bright uh rest of the evening and um if you'd like
you're welcome to come up and uh talk to me and ask me a question so otherwise wishing you safe travels home good night