so welcome and good day good morning or afternoon or
evening wherever you are and
uh i welcome you to this fourth day of a brief exploration of the six sense
spheres the avenues for our experience of everything that happens in our in our
lives and i'm hoping that looking at each of them in turn this week um will kind of
emphasize how important it is to be aware of our mind's relationship to each
of the physical senses and to investigate that relationship as part of our path it's really useful are we tied
you know to the experiences of seeing hearing tasting smelling sensing in ways
that limit us you know in ways that keep us uh stuck keep us bound is this six sense the the mind is
it relating to the physical um sense contact in a in a wholesome helpful way
or is it reactive is it grasping is it pushing away it's in the relationship of
the mind to what happens that goals arise in our you know in our
lives in our minds in our practice in our relationship to the world and when
that relationship is free of greed and aversion and delusion then uh that's
where freedom is found so it's
essential and today the focus is going to be on the sense of uh touch you know
that is what we call the the tactile sense you know the way the the whole body and all its individual parts sense
touch from the most subtle uh sense of air you know moving against
the skin to the strongest sensations of pleasure and pain so
sensation on the surface of the body and also sensation generated from within the
body and you know we often just use this shorthand sensation for this uh this
kind of sensing although all the all the senses uh experience some kind of a sensation
literally but um i think the fact that we use the word sensation for uh for the
tactile sense maybe points to how much space it kind of it takes up in in the
world of the senses
and i have the sense meaning something different by sense here you know i have
the view kind of that the sensations of the body and the activities um of the
mind are probably also the area of physical experience where we're most
likely to attach a sense of self i think it's um it's probably easier to
recognize seeing hearing taste smell as processes that go on kind of
automatically to see the ways that the mind takes possession of them in a way
and then to kind of parse it out to separate the appearances from the recognition the nama from the rupa in
those other four physical senses maybe it's just my own perception but it
seems like the mind is more likely to take the tactile sensations in the body
uh personally you know they belong to me they're my sensations we don't usually
speak about my sights or my sounds or tastes or smells but but what we see and
what we see and we and here we don't we don't think of as defining us in some
way but uh the relationship between the body and the sensations that occur in it and
to it they're kind of harder to uh to separate i think it's really easy to
conflate a pain in our in our back with a uh with a sense of self you know i am
a person with back pain i'm a person whose back hurts i'm it's me it's about
me and if that's the case you know it makes sense to uh to really make a lot of
effort uh significant effort to to recognize the distinction between what's
happening in the physical body the actual sensations and uh and the and the and
the body that's that it arises in noticing the sensations knowing it's the
body that's feeling the sensations and uh and then maybe we can see the
feathers the knots the attachments that arise and dependence on the two including that
sense of possession and identification with both the pains and the pleasures of
the body sensations arise in the body
they are not the body itself and the body is not
me so in our meditation today you know i'll just i'll invite you to um attend
to sensations in the body as they arise you know noticing how they appear and
after a while they disappear um in meditation with our with our eyes closed
and our focused inward we can tune in to bodily sensations more closely than when
we're kind of in the midst of you know daily interaction with with other people
this river of experience you know the flow of experience that is our lives it
can become quite simple a flow of sensation and uh often accompanied by
mental activity of course so let's uh let's begin the
meditation by as always uh taking a a
comfortable meditation posture with that balance of uh
alertness uprightness and uh and ease no
straining
awake and at ease it's ready to receive what arises
in the body and in the mind ready to be present
just feeling into uh what it's like to be sitting or lying down right
now the sense of the shape that the body is taking how the limbs are
arrayed in space kind of a global sense of what it
feels like to be just in the in the posture that you're in right
now the contact with the whatever your whatever your body is resting on whether
it's a chair or a couch or a bed or floor cushion
you're probably in a familiar posture you know maybe the same posture you take
every every time you meditate
just kind of settling into that and being aware of how it feels what the
sensations are what the kind of overall the sort of gestalt the overall feeling
of what is it like to be in this posture
and as usual if there's tension somewhere in the
body might take a few deep breaths and just let the inb breath move into
the area of of tightness or tension and and let the outreath just calm the
body just let the tension flow out with the
with the
breath just a few breaths like that
finding some ease in the body you know just being here in a very very simple
way
and spending a little bit of time with the the sensations of breathing
just invite you to follow the sensations from where the cool air enters the
nostrils right down through the soft pallet the back of the throat down the
windpipe into the lungs you know inflating the lungs expanding them
pushing the rib cage out a little bit as the breath goes all the way down
to the bottom of the lungs and the belly
expands feeling that and then the sensations of the
breath as it leaves the body noticing how the belly contracts and the
chest falls and that sense of warmth as the air that's been warmed by the
body comes up the windpipe and back out the the
nostrils it's a cycle it happens so many times every
day and there are sensations all along the pathway
and then now i just invite you to open your awareness to receive all the other
sensations that are arising in the body as as we sit here
maybe sensations on the outside of the body coolness of the skin or warmth
depending on what the temperature of the air is sense of clothing touching the skin
in different places maybe tingling or
pulsation in your hands or other areas your arms your face your
lips maybe there's discomfort somewhere
maybe there's pleasant sensation arising just due to
the to being in
meditation sensations are arising in the body all the time and and we can we can
know them they can be known receptively very
simply very
simply and of course there can be mental activity
accompanying the sensations maybe there's just a simple
knowing this is tingling this is warmth this isn't aching this is the breath
this is an itch just simple or maybe there is some
kind of hook a feather wanting the breath to be more
even pushing away an ache wanting me to be
quiet wanting something to happen some deepening some somebody to to
develop just notice how the mind
relates the
sensations does it try to make them my sensations
sensations that say something about
me just notice and and see if you can just let that
go just let it go
whatever is arising in the body and whatever the mental
relationship is to it just just know it for now just as simply as
possible if there's a hook just know it
don't need to try to let go of it just know it these
simple sensing what's
arising sensations mental
activity knowing them directly
so now take any ease and
uh sense of peace and calm um that has uh developed has that you've cultivated
during this this period of meditation and
uh offer it
outward to others all the others who are
joining the sit today and all all
the others who aren't everywhere throughout the
world with a wish that all beings
everywhere have the the strength and balance to uh to meet their lives
um in a wise
hey that they be safe that they be
happy and healthy and that one day all beings all
beings everywhere may be free
[Music]
so welcome again and
uh this week we're looking at um all the ways that our relationship to uh six
sense spheres our world can um either get in
the way of the deep clear seeing that's needed for
insight or can actually support the cultivation of that deep clear seeing
and today i'm going to talk about the fifth uh sense in this list the the body
itself and the tactile sense the sense of touch the body you know there's so many
complex processes that are going on constantly all the time the body is a
kind a vast field of uh uh of sensations arising all the time and we can have an
itch in an arm and a pain in the knee and a delightful tingly sensation in our chest
all at the same time sensations can be vague they can be precise they can be
easy to locate or they can feel kind of diffuse hard to pin down
there are the subtle sensations of uh breathing that we spend a lot of time uh
many of us do anyways attending to in our practice and then the many grosser
sensations of movement that we feel as we move through the
world as we act and all the ways that we receive uh
tactile sensations give rise to slightly different sensations in different areas
and they're all accompanied by some kind of mental activity recognizing defining approving
enjoying resenting ignoring wanting more of wishing would stop etc etc it goes on
and the instruction in the texts is to notice is there a fetter
here is there something in the relationship between the sensation and
the sensing that is pulling us toward more craving and clinging or in the
opposite direction toward more wholesome states so the fedters uh it's not a
feder if it's pulling us in the opposite direction it's just a mind an activity
of mind that's that's not fettering us not tying us down so the feeds that
arise are uh they're just as varied and numerous as the as the possible kinds of
sensations there's so many flavors of uh you know of aversion ill will uh greed
desire there's so many so many flavors and um and there is that sense
of taking possession of a of a self you know um and so which you know which
kinds of sensations do we uh do we experience that that are most likely to
lead that kind of lead to that kind of attachment to uh taking a self and i
think pain is definitely one physical pain especially if it's um if it's a
kind of uh constant chronic um we can question
the sense you know my pain my pain that can arise when we feel uh pain
especially ongoing pain what if it is just instead just pain just pain just
pain simply what's arising in the same way as the touch of our clothing you
know the touch of wind on our skin there's no meaning attached to it no no
taking possession of it you know mbsr mindfulness-based stress
reduction was really initially invented for just this kind of uh situation to
learn a new relationship to physical pain and when we're able to sense
different uh different sensations whether they're painful or pleasurable without reactivity without creating
stories about what they mean about making them mine you know we can find
more balance with them we can be present with them without adding uh any kind of
unnecessary stress without giving rise to
dooka and of course at the opposite end of this the sensation spectrum there is
uh uh pleasure you know um maybe the
kind of pleasure that comes from the exhilaration of of physical exercise or the the texture of a food we really like
the touch of someone we love sexual pleasure no strong pleasure is also an
area where the mind likes to uh create meaning and to take possession where the
attachment to the pleasure as as mine there's something that defines me that
can show up really easily in that uh in that kind of situation
craving for pleasure is one of the most powerful fetterss that uh that arise in
us i think it's um you know can pleasure just be pleasure something
enjoyed recognized as transient you know coming due to conditions passing away
when conditions change even the desire for simple comfort can be a fetter you know it can
keep our choices narrow confined making us
overcautious it's good to explore is to inquire and there are of course you know
sensations of either both difficult and uh and pleasurable that kind of um ask
us to act especially on the difficult side you know sensations that tell us that we're too close to a fire or a hot
stove the example that's often used or that our nose is in danger of freezing you know if we're somewhere that it's
really cold we act to protect the body's integrity the sensations that are su uh
symptomatic of some kind of uh illness um health change
uh or a an uh uh some kind of an injury
we need to use our minds to discern you know is this something that needs further exploration or um is it just a
passing experience but we can also relate to uh these kinds
of sensations in unskillful ways of course you know even if there is something that needs to we need to take
action about we can catastrophize we can move into paralysis unrealistic fear
denial all those things are fedters you know they add mental stress to what is
already difficult painful
and the craving for bodily pleasure of course is something that human beings have been driven by for as long as we've
existed you know there's a biological imperative behind some of our sense desires related to the
body and we can know we do know that the mental states that arise in dependence
uh on desire for bodily pleasure um uh they can really get us into
trouble they can cloud our vision i think every human being who
is older than 20 has been a teenager just by definition dragged
around uh often by sense desires related to the body and many uh many people have
experienced the dooka of addiction you know craving physical craving for pleasure so strong that uh that we seem
powerless in its presence often based on the on that on that physical craving
some particular sensations that we want to have arise as well as cravings for tastes and
aromas which i spoke of yesterday and the the buddha gave
teachings that can help us get more clarity when we're in the grip of some desire that has arisen along with bodily
sensation or with the desire for some particular bodily sensation to arise he
described his own practice um uh with the six sense
bases when he experienced um uh pleasure as a result of any sense contact seeing
hearing feeling whatever sense contact it was he investigated it in terms of
its gratification danger and escape maybe you've heard this teaching
before the gratification of course can be the the pleasantness of the sensation
itself or it can be the mental activity that that arises in dependence on the
sensations and then the danger is what the pleasure can lead to clinging to this pleasure clinging to
something that is impermanent that cannot provide lasting satisfaction
knowing that okay this is the danger of this this is not going to last craving
to bring it back again when it goes that's a feder and the escape comes with letting
go of the attachment to the pleasure the buddha stated that he had to be really
clear about the gratification and the danger in order to have the escape
that's it's really important to keep that in mind it takes time to get clear
about what is it we actually are you know feeling gratification in in this uh
situation and what's the danger it takes time but when we use our discernment to
see what it is that hooks us in the realm of the senses then we are gaining wisdom we're moving in the direction of
the escape so i'm going to share a story
about myself here um as a teenager i began smoking cigarettes and my parents both smoked um
i'm not blaming them but the fact that they did was a condition for curiosity
in me for the desire to experiment it was kind of a familiar thing and it
wasn't too long after i started before i was addicted to uh to smoking and i
smoked for about 10 years quitting a couple times during that period but
always pulled back by the desire to feel a particular kind of pleasure in the
back of my throat as i inhaled the smoke i can still remember that sense that the
feeling of that pleasure and then i saw this little paperback book i i can't
remember the title but it was about giving up bad habits in general
and the technique that it described was right in line with the buddhist teachings about the gratification the
danger and the escape and of course i didn't know that at the time the idea was to make a list of all the things
that you didn't like about your bad habit the danger and i made a very long
list about things of things that i didn't like about smoking and the
instruction was to read that every day every time you were tempted to uh engage
in the bad habit and i did that i noticed that if i just hung with
the desire for a cigarette without giving into it it would pass that was a
a revelation the craving was impermanent you know not that i defined it in that
way then of course as time went on the sense of danger grew in me and the
desire gradually ebbed i never smoked again after going through that practice
except in my dreams sometimes and i would wake up feeling guilty but i had made a final escape from the craving to
uh to smoke and i think that technique can be a really useful way of working
with uh with strong desires that we know are obstructing our ease getting in the
way of seeing clearly listing all the ways the desire doesn't serve us all the dangers that
are in uh that are in the uh in the habit all the ways that it disturbs our
peace and gives rise to dooka when the obstacles in our minds and
hearts to moving in a in a a healthy direction are strong then we need to
remind ourselves you know often again and again of the danger before we're
really going to believe it really take it on but when it's very clear i really
believe escape will come and first we have to know the
gratification so you know in our
uh in our practice of meditation um as samadei develops there can be really
beautiful delightful sensations in the body filling the entire body and they're
a really beautiful part of the path a lovely part wholesome arising due to the practice
itself and we can enjoy those we can encourage their continuation their
onward leading but if we begin to cling to them that clinging it becomes a
fetter it is a fetter as meditation deepens further you
know as samadei really deepens the equinimity that arises isn't characterized by pleasant bodily feeling
it's sublimely peaceful but the bodily experience is neutral so clinging to the
pleasure of samadei can actually create a kind of a road block obstructing our progress towards the the deep uh
equinimity that leads to to insight
so these five physical senses are ways that we perceive uh the world and the
the final sense the mind and act and its activity is where the conceiving
happening happens and that's the that's the biggie and uh remember in any moment
there are only two things happening there is what is happening and there's how we relate to what's happening and
the activities of the mind are how we relate to what's happening so uh that will be our topic
for tomorrow um the place where the fedters really get going
so i hope you have a lovely day and i look forward to seeing you tomorrow
thank you for your attention