so so welcome to you all nice to um see some uh some names
there um so yeah good to good to be back with you it's uh sometimes a week away
feels like not so long this time felt like a long a long time and
um yeah thank you uh for for the questions you've you've submitted um
I'll answer more of those at some point and and let those inform uh the topics that I uh try to
address one question I I saw that I thought maybe should just very briefly
address was um something like why certain Wednesdays isn't just plain Wednesdays like in the suggestion very
reasonable to get substitute teachers uh on weeks that I'm uh away and I get
that and um partially it's just to be
you know gets more stressful administratively to do so some of it's my
laziness and um but there's also a kind of fire hose of online Dharma you know
and that's mostly a great thing and um
and it has also perhaps driven down the kind of value placed on offerings too and so
anybody I could potentially get to sub has a wealth of online stuff
already and um and that kind of Market effect that kind of that logic of the
marketplace of um yeah just the kind of hyper availability I think is is
generally great but it's also so
complicated and the Dharma really only works under the assumption of certain
you know preciousness or Rarity maybe and uh and so that was on my mind
too and then uh and then also just like subbing subbing is a bad gig for the sub
you know generally like when there's an established teacher who is a effectively
driven away all the people that they annoy I have driven away at this point
most maybe not all most of the people I annoy uh and then you have like a very
idiosyncratic crew that's left namely you all um the experience of kind of
stepping into that and subbing it is kind of jangly sometimes
so I'm sensitive to that so anyway that hopefully that uh sounds okay but just
uh wanted to uh explain that seemed worthy of
explanation and um we'll uh we'll sit
um sit in a a moment but just wanted to uh share
something um came up maybe a couple weeks ago this book I I just just finished uh Agnes
callard's uh open Socrates and um it's a book about uh the
necessity the necessity of others and growing our wisdom and uh we cannot see the back of
our own head and Socratic dialogue is a way to help
us pursue truth right where the goal is as much to
be um convinced by others as to convince
others the goal in other words is to lose debates as much as win
them and this not a Dharma book but it struck me oh yeah Dharma
practice is about losing debates so callard writes um we are
unable to think about the most important things on our own and we habitually
Shield ourselves from this terrifying fact all of us even professional philosophers that's what she is walk
around with a conceit of knowledge separating us from other people our feeling of basic mental
competence of having the answers on which the living of Our Lives depend
keeps us from connecting uh to others in ways that benefit us
most ignorance of ignorance leads us to think that we are to figure out these
important questions for ourselves ignorance of ignorance prevents us from
thinking alongside of another person about what neither of us
knows ignorance of ignorance is the barrier between us
Socrates dismantled that barrier
and Strikes me Sanka dismantles that
barrier spiritual friendship dismantles that barrier and that's part of what we do in
our practice this is the jewel of s not lesser than Buddha
dama and even here on video
with our little chat and my little talks and the many ongoing relationships
you have amongst each other we have with each other uh we're we're attempting to
um to dismantle that barrier and uh to
think and practice alongside one another to wake up together that feels
especially important these days and so maybe we begin to sit just
um feeling the the goodness of our uh Collective
practice allowing your eyes to
close e
now
we cannot wake up on our own we
depend on so much and so many
we uh stand on so many
shoulders and we uh offer our shoulders to so
many for
and because we cannot distinguish between our wisdom
and our delusion we uh need each other quite
deeply
Jewel of
sa and so just um let the kind of
this network of um good will mutuality let it uh
soften your heart as we uh begin practice this evening
breathing
e
e e
we are in a sense only aware of what our self model permits us
to
see deep assumptions about
uh who we are what life is
what the world
is and so what we know is mediated
by self self View
in this sense it's a kind of blessing when another person clanks into
our self View
we begin to make what um had been transparent
opaque begin to look at that which we're accustomed to merely looking through
the Avatar of
self the way that awareness
tastes like
self
e
for
e e
we begin to notice the ways
that we uh model
our life model this moment e
way we model a kind of vantage point
you practice noticing letting go disidentifying
e
e e
become awake to uh all the subtle feeling and words and images
that when unnoticed
become the center of gravity of I
amness when noticed
become
empty
e
e e
[Music]
okay it's good to uh sit with
you
so before we we even begin Dharma practice um we have uh a lot of love
tremendous um depth of care and um s member was was was speaking about
generosity she talked about I think it was her very young nephew who
loves cheese yogurt and blueberries just eating it ravenously
delightedly and then uh all mashed up together and then very proudly
presents that mashup to his aunt you
know and uh because she's trying to be a good ant
gratefully takes it right but that uh these deep
impulses evident from very early on and they don't go
away and then you start um
start practicing and the love grows and yeah it's it's
hard uh practice is hard but there is only love and that
which has not yet been loved and the practice begins to free up
a lot of energy a lot of energy a lot of understanding of insight
and the face of insight s is love its manifestation in our
lives is is primarily love and we start to care more deeply
about so much the the circle of empathy uh widens begins to include the
nameless and the named those will never meet those not
yet born and uh the love begins to to
animate our our life our action in the world how we relate to one another how
we vote how we engage
um but as the uh the line in the song goes um there's a thin line between love
and Heath and our moral
commitments um what we care about our love gets yolked together with rage and
the urge to uh to punish and and the question is like how
does that happen how do love and hate become
entangled and uh um trying to address
this because I've been feeling sense of
moral something like moral outrage and I don't
know exactly what to do with it or what if anything to trust about
it don't feel uh I want to dismiss it out of hand if
it motivates some action wholesome engagement perhaps
that's useful um but is it is it possible to
harness kind of moral revulsion in a way that doesn't corrode one's heart and
is genuinely productive that reduces
suffering and uh Ruth King said um said anger is
initiatory not transformative we can
begin perhaps with um outrage or anger
but never end there and through all the different Cycles in
my own life in my own mind I I am left with the sense that
love it has to have the last
word and we we tend to think that our clinging is what makes us persuasive but
it's our letting go that actually gives us our power that
makes us persuasive and we think the volume of
our hatred is what signifies the depth of our care of our love but our hatred is a kind
of distorted expression of our care some kind of
alienated expression of our care and we are purifying our
love untangling it from hate even
even as one articulates a very
forceful no Hannah Chapman she says um disgust
plays an important role in Mor morality the commonality between
physical and moral disgust illustrates the elegant pragmatism of brain design whereby a new
set of abstract social triggers is attached to an ancient motivational
system system or originating in the rejection of aversive and potentially poisonous
tastes the co-option may be driven by the association between disgust and
withdrawal motivation which could have been a valuable addition to the behavioral
repertoire of our highly social
species rotting food disgusts us we wouldn't eat it we wouldn't let a loved
one eat it and ugly ethical conduct discuss us
we want to uh to punish
it but disgust and hate
probably live in the same
neighborhood and the intensity of our feeling seems like it must be matched by the
intensity of our view our stated
position maybe not what is uh unbearable needs an
object of hate right
no and I'm trying to learn to surf the kind kind of intensity
of my moral emotions without acquiescing to the
kesas to greeting delusion and Dharma practice involves
the purifying the nature of our love refining out the
ancient evolutionary entanglements disgust and hate and
vengefulness and the the kind of cruel irony that
that which we most want to change tends to be that which we most hate and yet
hatred is often the worst way to get someone to
change so it's not really that there's a thin line between love and hate but there's a very thin line between
clinging and hate there's a thin line between fear and
hate and so we we begin with uh the
imperfection of some sort of like gets better gets worse gets better gets
worse that matters but always
imperfect and we open our heart to
that I feel a need to take uh we need take good care of
fear need to take good care of our fear that's not to say there's nothing to fear but we need to take good care of
it and we investigate the ways that um our love
becomes uh entangled with with a kind of egoic
tribalism our moral commitments are about love but but they're often entangled with
suity you know with self view our moral commitments and become
sort of egoic badges but our
love is not about self our love is not a badge it's
not an accessory of uh
ego and we want to [Music] be careful not
to impute an agent a self to processes
that in the end are empty
and cells are just linguistic channels into which
hatred can
flow we take some characteristic and make that the center of their being
their identity and then try to hang or hatred on that that uh Center piece
we will not keep our moral sanity through hatred but U but through
love and that might
mean less hate but more grief that's
possible and I don't really I don't know but I I don't
think grief can be reduced further can be
deconstructed more I think it's the the Quark level or whatever whatever the
next level is you know but I think uh the grief is kind of like yeah
that's that's um just going to be the
burden of those who love deeply and so let us let us bear that
well and let um our tears be the kind of
source of our
motivation and uh none of this means I won't be in the
streets I have been and will be but uh
I'll try to remember you all and what I'm saying
now so offer this for your
consideration please pick up what's useful leave the rest behind