hello and welcome and this week the idea is
to say less at the beginning of the meditation so we can have a longer
meditation so to assume a meditation
posture and [Music] to find a nice
balance on the sitting bones and your spine line a nice way in which maybe the spine
straightens a bit regardless of whether you're lying down or sitting
up maybe allowing the chest to be a little bit
broader and maybe more room in the belly for the belly to
relax and to gently close your
eyes and often in these beginning minutes of the meditation I emphasize
relaxing today I'd like to encourage not relaxing but
releasing releasing that's almost like allowing whatever tension or holding
there is whatever tightness attachments there
are to allow them what they want deep inside they want to be
released and that samade has a lot to do with releasing
thoroughly repeatedly just releasing anything the mind is holding on
to and releasing into
the very center of the meditation which have been emphasizing
is the experience of breathing the body's experience of
breathing wherever that is the easiest to
follow and imagine that the
breathing is like a river that's flowing
and your awareness is like a raft
canoe that stays right on the surface of the river but gets picked up and Carri it
along floating along so release yourself
into the body breathing Release Yourself In into the
current of breathing in and breathing
out some points during the exhale or the inhale it might the current might be
faster maybe in transition from breathing out to breathing in the
current has slowed considerably but but if float along be
carried along stay close stay intimate with the sensations the river
of sensations of breathing as if and if when the mind
wanders off when anything gets any preoccupations come
release release back into
breathing and the word release points to something a little bit different than Letting
Go Letting Go has a little bit more to do with something it's more with we
do it's fine to relax it's fine to let go but for entering into
submod there's also this allowing for the release maybe you do a little bit of it
but some of it is also just the the medit meditation releasing
itself following the
breath maybe following when it comes
on the pleasure The Joy sometimes even the the
thrill of being carried along by the current of the river the river of
breathing one breath at a
time
e for
for for
for
remember to release with a
quiet deep deeper sensitivity to whatever way you're
caught preoccupied
tense release and release
settle your awareness into the onward
leading experience of
breathing where awareness
rides the sensations of
breathing as the only
thing that is important during during these
minutes
for
for for
staying with your breathing and remembering to release to
let go
and in deeper meditation
release comes with joy comes
with a delight or well-being comes with a
yes it's okay in these minutes of meditation
to take the chance take the risk of letting go of
everything and letting go into the stream of
breathing release whatever you're holding on to or
whatever is holding on to you let
go let go let go into the Simplicity of
breathing
for
e
for for
the deeper the Letting Go the deeper the
release the better we can meet the next
moment clearly
freshly and as we come to the end of this
sitting to let go and release
enough to be renewed in our vision and how we see see the
world see others for a few moments at least
without prejudice without bias without preferences just
see where what we see has been
released from the hold of our attachments and preferences
desires we give freedom to each
thing and may it be as we return to this our usual world of people and
activities may it be that we see with
wisdom how to release release
others from our attachments so we see them freshly
freely so that the way that we see others makes it easier for
them to feel free peaceful safe and happy
may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may the very way that we walk in the world support this possibility
[Music]
thank [Music]
you e
so welcome to this next talk on some
and um tadi is the Buddhist word for being deeply
immersed in the meditation deeply immersed in anything that we're
doing where that immersion there is no holding back
there's no resistance there's no self-consciousness in a kind of uh
attached way there's a giving ourselves
over to the meditation to the attention to
the present moment and a lot of that has to do with letting go and I think I mentioned some
time ago that one of the first instructions that I received uh about
going into suadi was in Thailand when first went there to practice and um I
met a monk who said that um he was a little bit dismissive I think of samadi
and he said that samadi just it just involves letting go just let go let go
let go and um but I don't think we need to be dismissive of it it's kind of
remarkable that if you place yourself in a nice meditative posture and then let go that this
natural process occurs that is a kind of a releasing a freeing a deepening a
sense of well-being that Wells up that almost as if it's almost as if the a natural state
of being immersed in activity brings Joy uh without there be any worldly reason
for that joy to be there except for the complete immersion in the activity that
we're doing with the meditation we're doing and so this deeper release into
the meditation um uh we're releasing a lot of things but one of the things we're
releasing is any strain or expectation around the meditation any pushing trying to make
something happen um uh any thinking anything that the the the thinking mind
is doing trying to do um in this kind of
the in the in this kind of um superficial way uh coarser way it all
gets let go let go let go and but don't just let go let go
into the object of meditation a release into the the the body breathing so that
you're really like the idea is you're you're finding a way to immerse yourself in it and that immersion is kind of also
then becomes the the totality where everything that we are is
Unified with it and um so then you know the analogy I gave yesterday was someone
in the edge of a maybe it's a hot day and there's a nice cool wonderfully cool
Lake person sits there being very hot and thinks about Lake thinks about going into an air conditioned room thinks
about getting a fan thinks about all kinds of things sitting there being hot
and um and the mind is just busy thinking planning wanting and while the lake is right
there all the person has to do is immerse themselves in the lake and
um and uh and then there's a immersive feeling of the water the coolness the
sensations of it it's clear that we're immersed in something that's wonderful now and all those thoughts planning
Thoughts by going someplace where it was cool follow way because they're clearly
not needed anymore and maybe for a little while there's no need to think of anything it's just so good to be
immersed in that cool refreshing pool of
water so we're sitting in the edge of a wonderful refreshing or if you prefer
the different metaphor of warm nurturing a pool of
somadi and uh don't think about it don't be involved in planning and wanting and expecting um release let go into
it and um and with and don't let go too
hard don't let go too quickly or too often because that itself then it's just
more of the same kind of attachment and trying to manipulate and make make
something happen uh in a just let go in a relaxed open way almost like you don't you're
not trying to make something happen because any holding any tension in and
of itself there's a desire there's a yearning there's a a momentum to let go
just like any ball that's put on a slope um will start rolling downhill we could
say the ball wants to that's what what wants to do the pull of gravity is its desire there's in the midst of any
clinging any holding any attachment to self or to outcome or to pleasure is a
kind of um holding the ball Against Gravity and if we release the ball it
will R downhill we will there an onward leading nature of going into the experience more
and more fully um entering the experience fully is the direction that our whole system
is designed to do if we El go of everything else and there can be this a
surface kind of preoccupations and attachments and but as those get quieter
we can start feeling there's something a deeper movement a deeper desire deeper a
thing that wants to happen that is not really associated with our usual self
our usual desires it's more like a it's as if it's kind of a natural or deeper
or or um Freer kind of movement desire approach that places
us right there in the in the breathing
and um and so to think of the breathing breathing in and breathing out like a
river it's flowing and we place Awareness on the surface of that
River an awareness can maybe think of it as a raft or a canoe and we keep it that
close is floating on top and then the the bodus is carried by the current and
flows along the ups and downs the the twists and turns
of the river as it flows with the in breath and out breath all the different changing Sensations just right there and
to get really intimate um I find it useful to remember
that any Sensation that we experience the sensing of it is nondual with this
uh sensation or what I mean by that is that you cannot separate out as two different
things sensing in the moment and the sensations that are being sensed these
two occur together and uh that's there's an intimacy and a closeness we're sensing
as a little bit more what the Mind does maybe the nervous system does and
sensation is what what is being triggered by some event some some someplace but those things arise
together and that intimacy to be right there to awareness to sense and to feel for feeling to be abiding in that place
where sensing and Sensations Ur together to really stay with that with the breathing the sensations of breathing
wherever they might be and um and to
release and there's an art to Letting Go releasing
into uh the river of breathing that recognizes also that you're releasing
into whatever pleasure whatever Joy whatever thing that's feeling oh yes
whenever yes this is good so we're the refreshing part the sweet part the the
some people refer to as a beautiful experience that goes on yes we're into
this the relief of it the the the the
pleasure of it the goodness of it the healthiness of it yes and you can't make
this happen you can't um you know if you're uh if you don't feel that or know
that as a lived experience uh you don't have to can't be can't argue to someone
that the experience is Pleasant or wonderful it either is or isn't but when it is um in whatever way
it is yes let go into that goodness let go into feel that be it and some point
with this approach stage of meditation it becomes uh easier to stay with the
breathing than it is to go away you must still go away but it's almost like where
you want to be is with the breath there's a desire there's a goodness yes here's where I want to be and uh and so
the that you don't if the mind wanders off um it almost like will come back by
itself uh I used to have this sense the the feeling like there there was a
rubber band attached to my thoughts and I would start my thoughts would start wandering away and when it got the the
rubber band got taught enough it would bring back the thoughts into the present moment bring myself back it was not me
doing it so much it was like here stay here be here flow
along and uh so this approach stage the important part of it is that uh that
it's not so much work anymore to stay present it's not like continually coming back and being here coming back and
being here it's not continually relaxing softening it's it's um it's now we're
here and it feels like it's uh this feels like the right place to be and uh certainly there are plenty of
times where where even experienced meditators uh are beginners and it uh
it's just manual labor just uh we come back and out of confidence and Trust in the process and and just kind of do the
manual work of coming back from thinking Letting Go Starting Over Again starting
over again so we need to be gracious and appreciate that this is an important
part of meditation it's on a regular basis to be feel feeling like a
beginner but then at some point uh when the meditation the samade
begins to kind of uh there's a there's kind of a shift a kind of a um something
either it can be a gradual shift or a sudden shift that now it's it's uh it's the it's like the
the right place to be is with the breathing the right place to be is to be immersed this is good the system wants
to be here anything else just is not not so satisfying anymore and this Bel this
this starts to become the the approach stage of samama uh that we're
approaching a um a u pivotal pivotal moment where the samade is going to um
we're going to drop into a deeper samade that um so that'll be coming but uh this
approach stage where it's a this is good this is good and i i to describe all this to you so
that uh you can recognize when you're there and recognizing that this is also
part of meditation so at the right time you have a sense that this is possible
you're allowed to do this you're allowed to start releasing into it you're allowed to immerse yourself you're
allowed to immerse yourself in the joy and the pleasure and the goodness the rightness you Orient yourself towards it
so the mind is getting organized oriented stable
steady at ease here to
flow on the surface of the river of breathing go breathing in breathing out
just staying there and uh being massaged by it
being being nourished by it just there
so I hope that what I'm saying makes um enough sense for you either intuitively
or with your imagination or maybe even your experience sometimes that um you
can kind of like file it away and remember this so that uh and inspire you
that no matter what stage of meditation you're at uh this is an inspiring um process to be part of it's
inspiring very natural process that's kind of built into our whole psychophysical system to have this
ability and it's kind of uh brings a lot of faith a lot of awe a lot of
inspiration to know yes yes this is
possible so thank you very much and um we'll continue with this approach
approach tomorrow