so I'm very happy to be with you this week and to continue with the beautiful
practice that Gil's been coaching Us in of developing
somat step by step so this week I'd like to support
that practice by offering the opportunity to continue to grow our independent ability
to cultivate some so one way we'll do this this is to
use the morning session to have a little more time independently to explore the
practice we may sit for a little longer each day and I'll offer the mornings
with a little more silence and a little less guidance uh Gil has given us such
beautiful guided meditations and they're so helpful in
giving us a good sense of the practice and how to go about it and with these
guided meditations you really get a feel for what you're doing in the practice but then it's very important to do it
independent of the guidance uh to really understand how
it's working in your own mind heart and body so by allowing more time this week
to experiment with what Gil has already taught us we'll discover what supports
for some work for us one form of support I'd like to offer was based on a request
I heard in Friday's community meeting so there will be a second 20 minute silent
sitting each afternoon at 4:00 Pacific time that will be on zoom and so you'll
check the IMC calendar for the zoom link and the password and uh that way you'll get that
extra time to explore in Silence the
practice uh by spending a little more time this week on our
own uh another support will get to discover often this comes up more when
you're not listening to a guided meditation and that is what kinds of things surface in the mind those might
be helpful things that you know kind of self- coaching little soft ways you
Encourage Yourself they might be some of the hindrances that Gil mentioned last week that fragment our
attention and so we'll find ways to support ourselves with
that uh Gil suggested on Friday that we next try counting to 10 with the breath
so we'll do the guided meditation this morning with that remaining very closely attuned to
the breathing in the foreground and then staying with it from the very beginning of the in
breath feeling it staying with it throughout the course of the in breath to the very end being with perhaps any
pause that's between the inhalation and the exhalation and then staying with the
entire out breath until the end and perhaps returning each time to the still
quiet place from which the breath arises and
passes so keeping the cycle of breathing in the foreground and keeping the
counting in the background or kind of in the periphery it's just a way to keep
the Mind present so with that we'll start with
the guided meditation
briefly settling in
taking your
time perhaps a few longer slower deeper breaths
allowing yourself the time to breathe into and out of any areas of tension or
preoccupation and releasing any tension that can be released
allowing what cannot be released but perhaps softening a little
around any chronic areas of tension or any preoccupation that's remaining
here allowing breathing to provide alertness and
relaxation a balance
and gradually turning the attention to being present with the
breathing feeling the sensations of the
inhalation as the body Rises or
expands as the breath comes into the
body and following the
exhalation perhaps the body has a slight falling
or comes back inward as we release the breath
following each breath with fresh attention
and while keeping breathing in the foreground of
awareness we can introduce very soft
quiet counting in the
mind counting from one to 10 with each
breath so as you begin the inhalation softly in the background the
count of
one and with the next breath two
counting each breath up to
10 and then beginning again at
one and this is simply a way to keep the mind focused on the breathing in the
foreground so the primary attention is is on the sensations of the
breathing the inhalation from the very
start and in the background of
one being with a pause if there's a pause between the inhalation and the
exhalation and then releasing the breath and following the sensations as it
leaves the
body staying with this practice and giving it a chance throughout this
meditation it takes time take taking the
time to settle into it to notice what's happening with
it a very light touch of attention a relax relaxed state of
attention to the
breathing e
if the mind starts to drift and awareness returns
noticing that it's drifting compassionately come alongside
of where it had drifted for a few
moments and gently turning the awareness back towards the sensations of
breathing and resuming very soft counting in the
background if counting one two up to 10 for each breath is not
enough to maintain the awareness on the breathing you might try one with the INB
breath and two with the out
breath three with the next in
breath four with the out breath and so on up to
e
e e
softly noticing any shifts that naturally occur as you
continue if you need to start again it's always fine to start again
with one brething
in respecting what's
happening
e
e e
so hello everybody I'm very happy to be with you today and extremely happy for
the beautiful volunteers at IMC who support
the technology and who helped overcome the tech glitches multiple Tech glitches
this morning so happy to be with you this
week this process of cultivating Sade is supported by spending time
independently discovering how it works for you so we're taking the time this week
to more deeply cultivate what Gil was teaching us last week
ease with thinking if it arises Simplicity through
counting settling steadying with the
breath and opening to spaciousness
this idea of spending extra time meditating in silence each day is one of
the very important supports for samade so for anyone who didn't hear this
earlier I'm offering a second sitting on Zoom at 4M Pacific each day this week
you can find the zoom link and the password on the calendar on the IMC
calendar on the home page page just by clicking on 4 pm and please
know it is not on YouTube it's only on Zoom so it'll be a silent sitting again
to give us more time and of course if you can't make 4M you can do this on your
own so that's one support a very important support for
what happens on the cushion with somadi is what happens during the rest of the
day both Sati and samadi both mindfulness and this settledness
collectedness work hand in hand they're very important strengths to cultivate
together and you can support Zade this week by watching what happens during
daily life as much as possible of course we're using
mindfulness as well in maintaining Awareness on the breathing as we do the
meditation with samade but in this development in daily
life one of the things that Gil mentioned to us early on was that we could start to
recognize how we're getting in our own way how we're fragmenting our
attention how we're uh not whole somebody we're trying to come to
wholeness to a settled alignment of everything right here and now
within and by applying mindfulness in daily life and also on the cushion we can see
ways that we fragment our attention become distracted become uh
preoccupied and one of the ways we do this is the hindrances that Gil
mentioned so we can uh uh see that in meditation and in our daily lives for
example we might notice the habit of mind that clings to wanting things to be
the way we want them to be the way that's Pleasant ideal the way
we think things should be rather than the way they are in this
moment so keeping in mind that the hindrances are very common and human
strategies that are trying to bring us to happiness and to a good life but
they're just strates that we find out over time don't work so when we find
ourselves wanting things in meditation or in daily life to be the way we want not the way they
are we can take a few breaths relax and soften with compassion
wow look at that look at what my mind's doing of course I want the way I want but here's how they are right
now or we could be uh wanting things to be to go away to not be the way they are
we want to push them away avoid them not have it happening even though it's happening so
this aversion is another thing that we can greet with a pause a breath and some compassion wow
look at how much energy it's taking me to push this away to resist what's
actually happening instead of responding a third hindrance that can
happen that you might notice on the cushion or in daily life is when lethargy comes up you had a full
night's sleep but for some reason as you're working on a particular task you keep getting drowsy or you're falling
asleep while meditating and it's not from lack of sleep if it's from lack of sleep you can
just get more sleep but lethargy can arise again approaching it with
compassion same with restlessness the fourth hindrance that can arise we can get caught in the idea that
um we can control things if only we worry about them enough if only we uh
make things be a certain way if we work really hard at it if we do do do uh then
we can conquer life and and be happy but again
bringing some compassion to that it just doesn't work it keeps us tied up in knots it keeps us exhausting
ourselves perhaps releasing some of the tension that arises in restlessness with
a whole series of out breaths using the breath breath
throughout as our Ally in this practice and then of course doubt can
come up and it's very useful during meditation if it comes up to say very
quietly say I see you doubt and you're not going to stop me in daily life you
could write down what your questions are or you can if it's about yourself you can practice the exercise of doubting
the doubt writing down all the reasons that you can uh imagine that the doubt is not
true so as we work the with these hindrances and they get more and more subtle we start to benefit by seeing
that what's coming up is just phenomenon rolling through experience rolling
through it it's not ours it doesn't have to be about me it's just what's happening so this
opportunity during daily life to strengthen mindfulness will support the ability to settle the
mind when we notice the mind getting caught in a hindrance or distracted or in some way preoccupied during the day
and mindfulness arises awareness arises we can notice the impact that it's having on us we can learn the truth of
what the Buddha is quoted as saying in the middle length discourse
19 which Tanis biku translates as two kinds kind of thinking here's his
translation with slight alteration in gender whatever one keeps pursuing with
one's thinking and pondering that becomes the inclination of one's
awareness this is so important have you noticed the impact of
what you frequently think about during the day of what you're frequently occupied
with if you can check in from time to time during the day whenever mindfulness
arises and you realize oh let me see what the mind is doing right
now we can see how what we're pondering thinking any hindrances present is
shaping what's happening with our attention and our awareness and that has everything to do then with how settled
we can become on the cushion when we're meditating or whether we're caught in
the preoccupations the concerns the
hindrances so the invitation today and this week is to check in frequently as
frequently as you can remember to S Sati also is translated as
remembering remembering to be mindful and checking in with what are you preoccupied with what are you engaged
with mentally is it in the direction of more agitation more activity
is in the direction of peacefulness calm
responsiveness so see what happens if you take maybe two minutes five minutes
during the day uh from time to time as well to check in with the
breath come back to this still settled
place all of these things that happen during the day will support the
cultivation of somadi so thank you for being patient with our Tech attack today with my
lightness and I hope that these are of use to you of support and I'll look
forward to seeing you all in the zoom or seeing as many of you as can make it to
the zoom this afternoon at 4 o'clock
Pacific be well