hello everyone and welcome and for this uh morning's
meditation um to repeat that for this week we
are engaged in the aspect of samadi which is not
considered samadi quite yet but is approaching
somebody and uh and um it's a fairly
common to think of samadi as a state of absorption uh another uh word that maybe
works better for some people a state of immersion and uh I think since ancient
times and uh sometime times in the modern world I listen to people talk
about their meditation it seems like people come up with this metaphor spontaneously on their own without
knowing the anything about the tradition that sometimes immersion in
somat can feel a little bit like uh taking a comfortable safe dip uh
under water in a maybe a cool refreshing or warm pool of
water and kind of floating and then sinking a little bit and getting
completely saturated and absorbed immersed and then coming out of somebody
is kind of like rising up and the head comes out of it and um and so right now
we're approaching and um and uh and um slowly they approach we
get closer and closer and so uh one of the aspects of
the approach is uh to begin Gathering Together so that we're really involved
with the meditation practice uh more than anything else that uh the strong Tendencies to be
distracted the strong Tendencies to be U preoccupied um the strong tendenci is to
be reactive and be involved in for and against experience in some reactive way
has abated has quieted for a time being so that we're fully absorbed like we
would if we were completely absorbed in reading a wonderful book or uh watching
some wonderful uh show or activity or or if we're involved in some kind of
uh game or sport or um craft or
musical playing music in some way that uh it somehow it pulls our attention so
completely that other things in the world fall away and we're just here for this and so uh and so it's harder to do
this with meditation because we're not doing you know obviously something that
normally we would consider interesting and the breath doesn't seem like it would be so
interesting what's interesting is not the breath in and of itself but rather
uh what begins to happen in the Gathering the centering of attention the comment of attention the the the um
intimacy of attention uh the the lightness and ease of attention
and there's a feedback system where the more that we're uh gathered around something like
the breathing and absorbed in it it has an influence on the rest of us it has
influence that where think things get gathered and settled and calmed and um
absorbed and it can feel really good and a relief to not be pulled away and
fragmented by thoughts and so this starting to recognize this process this
feedback loop of this gathering this influence that uh being focused has
being centered has that uh and using that as an encouragement to keep
Gathering keep Gathering so that's the approach part
and um and um and the hindrances might still be at
play but now we know there's another game in town we know there's something
with the as we get into the approach it's kind of like maybe we see where we're going or we have a clear sense or
feeling for there's something really good here and so there's a a more easier
way like let's stay let's come back let's keep in a flow let's keep uh
massaging it and staying here and here and here and
um so um so uh yesterday talked about this
connecting and sustaining attention and um and then last week was
pleasure and to bring these together that uh as we uh looking for the signs
of somat the symptoms the feedback loop the pleasure begins to feel little bit
like Joy Delight a gladness a
um a sense of kind of not just pleasure but a sense of
well-being and so I'll offer you some guidance and maybe this can be the
orientation as we um continue exploring these
different uh inner capacities we have that are get getting gathered and
organized and oriented towards somebody and uh we're organizing the
mind we're organizing our mental life our heart life we're organizing it so it's really here in this loving way um
immersed in some immersed in love
maybe so to assume a meditation Pro posture
and to gently close the
eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths and relaxing on the exhale
and then letting the breathing return to normal begin now to sit here
quietly without
meditating to to sit here quietly and do
nothing and if you do anything if you start thinking about things or reacting
to things or reacting to this instructions that's doing
something how simple can you allow yourself to
be if doing anything in might be
relaxing the tendency to do to think to
react and one of the characteristics one of the things that arise is when we get
simpler and simpler doing less and less and less is a natural capacity to be
aware to be present here and now is left
there not an active intentional
attention but a receptive quiet almost
natural way of knowing sensing being aware
in a way that we're kind of capacity for attention is always there when we're
awake and it can stand out in the Highlight if we do
nothing letting go just being
and doing this not doing
is as it works for you don't have a high standard but notice as you do nothing do
little very little some way in which awareness it can be present without you
doing awareness present moment
awareness maybe an awareness which is very
light maybe an awareness which is little bit more spacious little
spacious open receptive that
and then as you exhale to settle the
awareness into the settling spot of
breathing to allow the centering spot of breathing
to be in the middle of this very light open
awareness and as you breathe and as you just be doing very
little feel feel your way into your body to
feel whatever pleasure whatever rightness or
relief there is in this Simplicity of just sitting here in
meditation maybe the awareness a simple non-doing awareness can have a global
reach to feel in the body where there's
pleasure or contentment or
Comfort or a feeling of calm or suling
and without doing much just a little bit more than doing
nothing let there be a gentle massage with awareness gentle returning and entering
and being in the middle of it all
breathing connecting awareness to the
inhale connecting awareness to the
exhale e
connecting and sustaining with the inhale as if maybe the inhale
touches the ability to sense and feel
inhale and this exhale is a touching into
awareness rather than you doing the
awareness awareness is quiet it's more like
the breathing touches awareness and you stay
open to experience the whole
inhale sustaining the whole exhale
centered or breathing the peripheral
awareness can receive whatever pleasure calm
contentment there might be with sitting
here with your breathing sitting here aware
alert enough to the experience of breathing that you're likely to notice
if the Mind begins to think and wonder
off and if it does use that as a reminder
to connect to breathing stay with the
breathing e
you might allow there to be a little
smile add a little bit of joy joy to the
pleasure a gentle
yes to settling in
here to breathing at the center
surrounded by some feeling of pleasure or
Joy however small that
is e
maybe the inhale is a connecting to the process of
breathing and the exhale is sustaining the whole length of the exale
exhale while you relax into a wider feeling of
well-being associated with the Simplicity of
being here
meditating
e
for
e for
and as you're sitting meditating can you do Le less can you
relax let go of anything not needed for
meditation let go of anything not about
meditation soften relax anything that keeps
you at a distance from being settled here in your
body breathing
a calming of the Mind and
Body a feeling of contentment or calm or
simple pleasure that's here as we come to the
end of the
meditation maybe as be as we started to do almost
nothing just just enough awareness to be centered
here in the experience of
breathing and to feel as with the end of the
meditation whatever is Pleasant whatever you enjoy
and maybe you can appreciate that you may took this time
to practice to sit here and appreciate it with a small
smile turning up the corners of your mouth just a little
bit with an attitude of yes here
and if it's easy enough allowing some joy to
arise the joy of
practicing being a little bit more connected a little calmer
settled allowing you to yourself to feel Joy or Del
light or
appreciation a kind of appreciation that brings a smile at least to the
heart and as we come to the end May It Be
that we gaze upon the world with a smile in our
eyes a sparkle
delight and then we see other people with
appreciation many people do not often are not often seen
with appreciation with Delight with
joy and it's a gift we can give others is to not be in a hurry to speak
or to get what you want or to make something happen but to use the ability to be
present quietly to appreciate others
to gaze upon others with a simple
joy the joy of at least having our hearts
open and caring for everyone we meet
we're so lucky when we have care and appreciation
and compassion for others
love and may it be that this practice we
do supports the welfare and happiness of Others May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank
you e
so continuing this series
on uh samadi the topic I want to talk about
now is joy and with that in mind I want to express my joy and my appreciation my gratitude
for all the people who made donations to our save the children fundraising drive and
um the uh the little meter on the save the children's
page for IMC shows us uh more than 90% there to those somewhat arbitrary goal
that we set and um so I'm quite inspired and delighted and happy that uh this
community came forward so much and to offer so it's close to $70,000 there and
uh we're actually raised more because of a donation that came in uh indirectly
not to the through that particular page on Save the window save save the
children so um and some of you if you would still like to make a donation it's
a a donation well well offered and and inspiring to have done it together and
kind of the some total of what we're doing here is quite impressive it's um
it makes a kind of a loud statement for some of us of what a community can do is when we come together to do good things
in the world so thank you so you'll find information about it on the IMCA
website and then so um joy joy as part of
meditation um now it's not so easy to feel Joy I mean it's uh uh when people
come to meditation they often will begin because of some challenge they have
maybe the suffering they have um difficulty they have that um they can't
just sit down and smile and feel Joy um but at some point as the as we
learn mindfulness learn how to be present for our experience uh it's phenomenal that we have a practice that
can meet our suffering and that can meet our sadness our grief our anger and we could do it that practice of mindfulness
does it effectively and it's a very significant way of not being caught by
the emotions while at the same time developing the capacity to hold them in
a beneficial way we're not being driven around or controlled by emot our
emotions but we're also not uh avoiding them so this whole process of
mindfulness is such a good foundation um and as mindfulness develops then at some point um the
capacity to be present grows and it becomes a time maybe to begin
appreciating that mindfulness can partner with some with a a kind of a
steady stable calm Focus uh really staying here in the
present moment some people call call a certain kind of
concentration um um suade uh momentary suade where we're really here Moment by
moment and you can really feel a shift sometimes when we feel now I'm really
here and um I'm not being pulled off this way and that way anymore now the
whole system is is uh um settled enough clicked in enough that um
that uh I'm I'm just going to be in the flow of the present moment um and that
can bring so much delight and joy especially if it's been a long time coming that we've been working with the
reactivity and the strong preoccupation of the mind and bringing the Mind back and waking up again and again at some
point it doesn't become so much work to be present anymore we're here
and even the most experienced meditators have to begin again at the beginning even the experienced meditators will sit
down and their mind will be preoccupied and it feels like they're beginners again and um the difference between in a
sense I like to think that we're all beginners uh just some of us are experienced beginners and the difference
between a a raw beginner and experienced beginner is that um experienced beginner
kind of knows the Terr knows to recognize what's important to recognize what to be present
for and um and someone who's a noest to meditation might not know that yet and
so when we start kind of bringing in samade as a partner to mindfulness uh we're going further into
recognizing what is important what is useful to notice in the present moment so it's not a complete random uh uh kind
of uh choicelessness about what we're being present for um the um uh there is a uh
a because if we do that then the old habits in mind actually gives priority to certain things it's not we're not
really choiceless but when we really settle deep uh and uh then at some point
um the um um the we start noticing
that it feels good to meditate there's a more calm there's more subtleness the mind is not so much in out of
control and um and as we developed a sama want to started recognizing some of
the good factors that began growing and developing and one of those is the
ability to stay present and uh and one of those forms for somat is what I
talked about yesterday this connecting attention and sustaining that there's a gentle kind of um stay there stay there
there so we're not ready yet to really click into the present moment but we're we're there close enough we just stay
there stay there and it can be kind of delightful it can be very pleasant um
almost as it's Pleasant to get a massage it's Pleasant to massage the mind the attention the present moment uh stay
there be here be here and then um as we as uh the
meditation develops uh part of the landscape we want to become familiar with is that
whatever kind of pleasure there is uh with it and uh and the word pleasure as
I said last week involves a wide range of of Good Feelings uh sometimes it's a
feel kind of a sense of beauty a sweetness that's present sometimes it's
more clear physical kind of strong flow of pleasure meure of tingling of delight
that moves through some parts of the body and um and one of the and some of
it has a little more of an emotional quality and one of the things that becomes invaluable as we're approaching
the immersion samade approach approaching and getting immersed in the world of
samade is to feel Joy and the poly word is pi which is a p i TI
and um and it's um I've seen sometimes that it's uh
translated as a thrill there's a kind of little bit of little bit kind of a
joyful excitement uh that's there and um and uh
so it's represented by a smile uh sometimes with a smile there's
kind of a little bit of energy there awakens and and becomes strong maybe
kind of Sparkle in the eyes and maybe the cheeks and the in the head uh
there's a kind of a kind of a feeling of delight and kind of energized Delight
kind of an enthusiasm yes um we're here to practice uh there's
um in that enthusias that yes that delight and joy can be kind of soft and
sweet and it it could also be kind of quite uh strong at
times uh it's kind of like the the u a
um the the connecting and sustaining staying there with experience becomes a
little bit like blowing on a fire and the Fire gets stronger and stronger that staying there staying there with the
with the breathing the focus of attention this uh
connecting applying attention and then sustaining it um is a gentle kind of blowing that lets
that Joy arise the The Joy This Joy is considered
to be in the tradition to be a little bit more mental in contrast to another
form of well-being that uh comes into play when we go into samade which is uh
I call happiness and um it's one that's not it's it's more
Sublime it's more settled and so often It's associated being a little more physical but it's because the little bit
of mental excitement thrill that involves joy quiets down becomes quieter
and then we feel a kind of a settle calm peaceful kind of happiness that feels
very still uh the joy has a little bit of movement or excitement in it that um
this deeper happiness doesn't have and these two can coexist but these are
kind of elements of this Gathering Together the we're Gathering Together
these good qualities and now emotionally we're Gathering our emotional life the good good the goodness that's there with
our inspiration and practice the goodness of the intention of why we're
practicing the goodness of the purpose the goodness of our how we offer ourselves in the practice the
self-respect the care maybe the love for ourselves that grows as we do this practice there's all this kind of
gathering of goodness that's here that is being collected to be present in a
very simple way to be present almost as if we're doing very close to nothing but
we're engaged we're fully here and um and at some point this fully here this
engagement begins having a life of its own and um and sometimes the effort to
practice doesn't does not feel like we're doing nothing but it feels like I'm not doing it now the practice is
carrying me now the practice is flowing and we're here connecting sustaining and
this Joy uh of practice the pleasure of practice begins carrying us begins move
flowing us it's kind of like we've we've stepped onto the the moving sidewalk and
uh and we're walking walking and it's getting and then we suddenly step onto that moving you know conveyor belt and
um and and we can stop walking because now we're being carried Along by it and
so at some point uh the uh as we gather as we feel allow ourselves to connect to
all this it clicks in and we're we're being being practiced rather than doing the practice and for this to happen
there is this uh uh organizing Gathering um of ourselves unifying of it
of those things that we know are part of this process of samade so there is a a a
selectivity not to push anything away not to deny and put blinders on zat is
the opposite it's the releasing of blinders but then also of beginning to
take in the the pleasure the goodness of the practice here and
now we're allowed to feel Joy in this practice not only we allowed that the
joy itself is uh uh and then happiness these
qualities is what begins to allow it's it's part of the approach to the wonderful sweet uh Lake
that we're going to go dipping into that immerse ourselves in um these are the
qualities that come into play if we chase them if we try to engineer them
then uh we get in the way if we have a strong expectation we're forcing it it
gets in the way it's the pleasure of not forcing anything the pleasure of not
chasing the that's part of the pleasure of this samama it allows us to settle in
allows something to come into play and uh puts us on the conveyor belt that uh
that um maybe in the airport where the San
Francisco airport has see all these you know moving sidewalks we can stand on it takes us to the plane so we're going
this and then we'll at some point there some we're in the plane so I hope this makes sense and um
and I certainly hope that for those of you who your direct experience isn't the same of what I'm talking about that you
don't lose heart that um uh that the great joy of this
practice is that the practice puts us in the middle of our life as it is uh and
then we find our way with that with mindfulness and and um I've had a lot of
joy in the practice by oddly enough by having a practice that connects me in a
useful significant way to my personal difficulties so um so even there we we
can find a certain kind of pleasure so thank you very much so uh
you might today as you go through your day um uh see if you can find more
joy uh Avail yourself of the joy that's here there's more probably more
opportunities to feel Joy if you slow down look around then you usually allow
yourself to feel see what happens if you spend a day allowing yourself
to feel the simple joys of life here and now thank you