so I start again welcoming you all here and to say that the journey the
meditation Journey um is a lot easier if you understand it as a journey that's
leading to a profound capacity to be in the world in a new way and it's a it's a
journey that takes us inward in a certain way um deep inward almost like we could
imagine to the the source and there we in a sense turn
ourselves inside out and then we can return to the world in a new
way and um and one way we return is it's as if
the world begins with ourselves begins in our hearts begins deep inside and how we are
as we come out of our depths shapes the world certainly the world that we see
but in a certain profound way shapes the world around us and we want to have that
shaping that remaking of the world come from a place of profound goodness
profound Health profound love or care a
care for everyone no one left out of our hearts
but to do this we have to kind of be to know that that's the journey and then to be able
to uh put aside for the time being the preoccupations we have about
the world the future the past what's happening now not to ignore it or
abandon it but to be able to come back in a better way and um and so
willingness to suspend the usual preoccupation of the mind for a better
cause for a really good thing and
um and so for today the so Monday I said samadi is
Simplicity and then samadi is subtleness then samadi is
steadiness today I'd like to contribute to this list that samadi is
spaciousness that we're going in word in a sense and for those of you who
following along here to use the breathing as the primary anchor or
settling movement that settles us inside to the settling place as we do that at the same time uh
we're opening up to a spaciousness that's the context that's the
atmosphere that's the uh that uh surrounds the experience
of breathing and so and this opening to a
spaciousness it's almost like the peripheral awareness isare aware of the space and the primary focus is aware of
um this um settle place within with the breathing and it is being involved in
two things at once but we do this often in our life that uh we go through a
space that's either crowded or a space that's very open and we're primarily doing our task walking perhaps but we're
very aware that uh the that it's crowded with people are very aware that there's
space to walk in and it either one it affects us and we might not be doing it
so consciously that the focusing on the people or the space but it sets the mood
it sets kind of a condition for how we're going to follow our way so in meditation also we can be attuned to to
the spaces around the breathing and that contributes to a
sense eventually that um the mind doesn't move when we
meditate uh when there's a lot of thinking going on uh and a lot of
concerns and preoccupations it's very reasonable people say their mind moves I lo my mind wandered away it got it uh
got distracted it got caught up in um something and then we bring it back we
bring it back um but as the mind gets more and more settled the idea of bringing the Mind back the idea that
mind goes anywhere is just a metaphor the mind never goes anywhere and as we
settle and feel the spaciousness it gives us the kind of the relief oh the mind doesn't have to work so
much and the awareness seems to be to
be arising out of the spaciousness or penetrate or or kind of in the
spaciousness itself having qualities of spaciousness light open almost
insubstantial so to assume a meditation uh
practice and um assume meditation
posture gently close your eyes
and to settle into here you might Begin by taking some long
slow deep breaths
relaxing in the body as you
exhale relaxing in a settling way so you're
settling your body
in letting the breathing return to normal and continue for a few
breaths to feel your body on you inhale and relax the body on the exhale
maybe relaxing different parts of the body in different
breaths and similarly as you exhale to soften the
thinking mind if you can feel the sensations
associated with thinking mind some pressure
tightness weight
contraction or some agitation activation of some part of
your head as you think G gently softly soften the
thinking mind as if you are
[Music] allowing the waves on a lake to settle
and quiet down or if you drop a pebble into a lake
waves Ripple out but further they go the smaller they become until they
disappear letting the mind the waves of the Mind Ripple
out and
quiet and then to settle
in to your breathing and if you have found a
settling Place deep in the experience of
breathing at the end of the exhale where the inhale begins
a place from which the breathing arises in breath arises and
expands and where the sensations of breathing end the end of the
exhale and not searching for that or feeling for that from the control
tower almost like having your mind deep in your
torso where awareness arises together with the
inhale together with the exhale
settling and then having a steadiness through the
inhale a steady companionship for the whole
length of the
inhale and a continuous
attending to the exhale from the beginning to end
and here's where you might steady your
mind steady your
attention so you can continuously follow one inhale one
exhale
and as You Follow the
inhale notice how it arises it appears it
begins grows and comes to its end
and the exhale begins
continues and comes to an
end and as the exhale comes to an end allow your thinking to become
quiet and into whatever quiet there is allow the inhale to arise
a gentle steadiness with the
breathing then become aware with your peripheral awareness any sense of
spaciousness any sense
of just be on the edges of breathing the edges of how you experience
breathing is the beginning of a kind of space or
openness or maybe a kind of quiet or that kind of
Stillness to whatever degree you can be aware of spaciousness
Stillness while you're with your breathing
it's almost as if the weather is
spaciousness through which breathing
travels e
and whatever feeling of spaciousness you have around the sensations of
breathing will support
you to not fixate on the
breathing but have a softness an openness
that more like allows yourself to be aware breathing in and breathing
out
e
for for
if you sense space around the breathing around
you if thoughts arise
don't be troubled by them or involved in them let them Drift Away into the
space and
you settled on breathing that's in the middle of all
things
for
e
for for
perhaps rather than trying to be aware
you're more like not trying and
allowing there's an R to not
trying that brings forth a deep awareness spacious
awareness almost as if it's always there waiting for you
and that breathing is at the center of
it
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting any idea of beginning an
end exists in the midst of a wide field of
spaciousness openness Beyond the Edge es of the word
and Beyond the edges of any word any
idea in the space and the quiet between one sentence in the mind and the
next between one image and the next
there can be a silence a
Stillness a
spaciousness that can exist together with the noise in the
mind the activities of the Mind
and perhaps to sense and
feel the breathing room that spaciousness provides breathing room for
all things can be left alone just to
be and as we end this sitting perhaps we can do that that to
other for other people give them space
give them breathing room so they can just be as they are
without our judgments and desires wants
expectations the gift of allowing people space to be
themselves maybe so they can see it more clearly Maybe maybe so there can be a
different way of responding may it be that this practice
that we
do helps us to contribute a respectful space attention
awareness for all the people we see in our
lives as spaciousness may all
beings be happy may all [Music]
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free and may are holding people in spacious
in his spaciousness support that
[Music]
possibility e
so hello and welcome to this next talk on
samadi and um one of the things to appreciate is samadi is not a practice per se it's a
state the practice as we do of of um
steuding the Mind focusing the mind being attentive to breathing letting go
of thoughts there's a lot of things we might be doing but that
um uh that's not the samade that's the practice to enter into samade and samade
is a state it's actually a variety of different kinds of states of Mind of
Heart of body the wholeness that we can experience and um uh and then it's
important to appreciate that the practice the instructions for
meditation uh it can be State specific there's a strong orientation
for people to um um use as their reference point Me
Myself and mind how I am now what how this is benefiting me what's how it's good for me or if I like this or not or
if this works for me or not and there's a value in that to some degree but we
can get stuck in that kind of orientation as well and uh meditation
practice is meant to be something that helps kind of step out of that excessive
self-orientation self- referencing and one way to do that is to
appreciate that we have to when we practice Sadi
practice meditation we have to adjust of our um our
um our practice according to the states that we're in and as we go through these this
teachings about somebody uh in a way uh as we get further and further
along um it's I'll be talking about things that probably are not immediately
relevant for many of you um and uh and it's appropriate for
you if you're aware of yourself to practice in an earlier phase of the instructions here uh and often uh we're
we you know the the right place to be is as a beginner or you have your own
practice of how to get settled and and uh get started started in meditation you're welcome to go back and use that
as well um because we're often it's it's kind of like a pyramid as we practice
and we spend a lot of time at the creating the foundation and even very
experienced meditators uh start at the beginning laying on the foundation and
then slowly over time the building of that pyramid maybe goes faster and
faster um or quicker or something but um but we don't spend a lot of time in the
higher states of somat but so just be aware that you have to adapt yourself to how I'm teaching
here and um but also to participate with your
imagination if it's not directly what you're experiencing uh maybe it's evocative
enough for evocative enough for you to imagine uh in a sense because what
you're what be offering is um the landmarks that will become available as
we keep practicing and you might be able to better see the landmarks in the distance having receiving these
teachings you're familiar with what's coming you're ready to recognize what is useful to take in and where the path is
rather than just being in a big territory not knowing not seeing the path um and just kind of wandering
around even though it might be beautiful terrain you're still maybe wondering
maybe wondering in circles so today uh I was
offering opening up to something I think very important for the deepening of somebody or the expand expansion of
somebody and that is spaciousness and um and uh I'll try to
explain this a little bit better the um that um we have an amazing
capacity as human beings for space IAL awareness and I'm sure that there's a
range of how much that capacity exists in different people to some degree it's
a capacity that can be developed and um and some people haven't spent much time developing it but it's
possible for examp for example to close one's eyes when we're in a room and then
with the uh imagination imagine
the the size of the room imagine the distance to the walls or if you're
sitting Outdoors you can imagine the close your eyes you imagine how
expansive the outdoors is if you're standing sitting on top of a hill or a mountain and close your eyes you can
still remember something about how expansive the whole Vista is and um in
the mind and um and um so um so this idea of the mind
has spatial awareness we have a sense of what's to the left to the right maybe even behind us a little bit uh we can
have a sense of distance between us and other people some of that is a deep functioning of the mind if you're going
to toss a bean bag to a friend um some calculation goes on deep in the mind of
how of of how strongly to throw that bean bag how
high to throw it how fast how you know the angle the Direction all this uh is
incorporating a sense of the space and distance and and uh things that goes
into into our spatial awareness and so sometimes we can close
our eyes and have a sense of some kind of spaciousness around us in very
meditation sometimes people have this the sense of uh Infinite Space that
they're uh that the space that they're sitting in has no edges has no limits uh
because edges are uh a concept the Mind makes of this kind of thing of space and
so you can sit and be aware of you know with the eyes closed Imagining the room
you're in and there's a limit to that the walls but if you're sitting on top of a a mountain uh the limit of it it
maybe there is no limit going upwards out into space and so that sense of
limitlessness is um sometimes is breathtaking or inspiring or it just
kind of opens something up wide if we're in a claustrophobic space it tends to
support kind of a claustrophobic kind of preoccupation with ourselves our thoughts our
concerns and um so in sitting with medit ation with the eyes closed when we're
settled enough when we're still enough when we're um steady enough uh simple
enough there might be a time when we can start feeling the space spaciousness in
the mind spaciousness in the body a sense of kind of like there's there's a room for things and um because the mind
is not filled with thinking it's not because thinking and desires and verion
according to the Buddha is what creates the limitations and the the smallness of
the mind and the mind becomes uh expansive the mind of
awareness uh without those limitations of thoughts and concerns and preoccupations desires and
aversions so as we get more settled to begin to become aware of the spaciousness that's here uh
so that we're not not riding riding the breath uh like latching on or kind of
zeroing in in a tight laser focus but rather uh there's the awareness itself
starts becoming um uh um integrated or
integral to that spaciousness and the mind itself now the
awareness itself feels as part of the spaciousness almost and so as the
breathing comes and goes sensations of breathing come and go it feels like they're coming and going within the
atmosphere the weather the context of
spaciousness and the kind of awareness this uh uh one way of understanding this
kind of spacious awareness it's not something you can fixate your mind on if you look at the
space in the room you're in if you're in a room or Outdoors um and try to really you know
like stare down uh the space in the room like really focus and really zero in at the
heart of it and you're really going to you know let the space know that you see
it that kind of one point of focus um that you would have maybe for someone
you're angry with and you're just letting them know through your stare it doesn't work with um with the
space around you that it's almost like you're better off not trying to look at
the space as a point as a for the central focus of the eyes you more like
you have to relax some people when they're looking at the space in in any place at all the
natural tendency of the mind is to the eyes Roam and in the roaming the movement
gentle soft moving this is where we have some kind of inner sense with peripheral
awareness maybe of the space in the room so rather than having a central
Focus we have this peripheral focus of awareness and like the like eyesight
there's uh kind of central focus and the peripheral awareness and the peripheral
awareness is always there but it it's hard to focus on it in the way we can
when we zero in on the central Focus so the same thing as we sit and meditate
the kind of the center of attention could be the breathing but the same time we're aware
of this peripheral space around it both are going on at the same time there's
two different almost systems of awareness operating and they both can be mutually supportive operating at the
same time but in order to do this the mind has to be quiet enough still enough
settled enough and that's the work of getting
developing the subtleness and that allows the spaciousness to start to come
the Buddha sometimes called this an expansive mind Maha the expansive uh because the mind
itself feels like it's starting to lots of room for the Mind rather the Mind caught and preoccupied by something the
mind the mind that's not caught opens up and relaxes and expensive and this spacious awareness
peripheral awareness as we do subtle and steady on the breathing uh makes
possible uh the state of some that are going to arise and that's will be the
focus for to oh not that exactly thing but tomorrow I'll talk a little bit
about um what begins to become possible with uh this settling and focus on
breathing that becomes possible as we begin opening to the spacious
in the meantime until tomorrow I'd encourage you uh to look
for occasions where you can settle back to appreciate the spaciousness the space
the wide space around you probably it works better Outdoors U but you know some places like
here at IMC there's a really high ceiling and uh and that and so just looking up toward the space you're
ceiling that itself does something to the Mind see if you can appreciate take
time have tea look around open to the spaciousness if you're lucky enough to live in a place where it's wide open
space of some maybe a city park or a
Hilltop or something uh spend the day
specializing on on uh becoming aware of open space
all around you so that that might help you to find that in meditation as
well so thank you very much and um we'll continue tomorrow and tomorrow we'll do
the um community meeting uh for um you know our YouTube community on zoom and
uh I'll keep the YouTube channel open so those of you who don't want to go on Zoom can attend but and uh that way but
for those of you who want to attend it on Zo zoom and ask questions and go into breakout groups to meet each other um
that will um be at 7:45 and we will
um um and the already the zoom link is in the what's new on imc's website it's
also in the IMC calendar and I'll put it here in the chat tomorrow and the password you'll need is the poly word
for loving kindness which uh is meta m t
ETA so um thank you all very much and um look forward to tomorrow