okay so why don't we go ahead and get started it's very nice to see everyone and nice
to have a chance to be back again with you this week
I know that Gil has started his insight series Who knows how long that one will
be right after the samadei series and Shelley talked last week about the
sense bases as kind of a support for doing insight practice Well
so this week we're going to take up a series of simileies uh that help shine a light on how the
mind transforms from being timid and distracted to being strong and clear in
some way So in a very broad way you could think of it as a journey of what
happens to the mind as it gradually gains more insight and becomes able
eventually to walk the path on its own And how are we going to talk about that
this week uh we'll look at a series of animal simileies So I'm smiling because
I'm kind of delighted by this um prospect that there's a lot of animal similes in the sutas uh the teachings of
the Buddha and so uh we'll be going through some of them kind of as a as simileies for this process of the mind
So I'll say more about that after we sit So on that why don't we go ahead and
meditate together So allowing yourself to come into
a comfortable posture one where you can be upright and also
relaxed or if you're lying down where you feel generally straight and balanced
And if you're comfortable doing so I invite you to close your eyes
Maybe take a long slow deep breath and really fill the lungs
And then on the exhale just allow the body to settle a little bit more into
the posture letting any imbalances or tensions that
are easy to soften just relax out
And then it's helpful to connect in with the body at the beginning of a sit So
just noticing the sensations in your face and
softening the expression on the face maybe around the eyes
jaw muscles
Softening the eyes and the eye sockets
and down into the shoulders
inviting some release
I sometimes imagine my shoulder blades sliding down the back
down through the arms and the hands
And as the shoulders soften a bit you may be able to feel the head kind of
uplift The neck gets released somehow
That provides a nice kind of upward feeling to the spine
softening in the chest and the heart area
Gently extending down into the belly
Inviting the belly to be soft Maybe just one or two layers of it
Even feeling down into the low back
letting that soften a bit
And as the belly and the low back both soften the spine which is in between
them we really have a chance to feel how balanced that is
Seeing if we can find that simple place
where it's easy to be upright
and softening through the hip joints
down into the legs
all the way to the feet
And if there were parts of the body that are they're just in pain today or
they're chronically uncomfortable or if there are tensions or even areas
of the body that you couldn't feel very well that's all fine
Actually the body is fine as it is or just inviting a connection to it
Then opening the attention back to the body in general feeling the
posture you're in sitting or lying down Maybe some of you
are even standing
And sensing our simple presence mindfulness
to be here
And one of the simplest and most easeful ways to sit is
to have what's called an anchor
And I'll invite a choice of three different possibilities
Many people sit with the breath as the anchor The sensations of in-n-out
breathing That's a great choice
It's also possible to use more generally the sensations of the body as a anchor
Sometimes I sit with the um the feeling of where I'm sitting So all the sort of
all the contact points my seat against the cushion and my feet against the
floor wherever my hands are resting those touch points make a very nice meditation
object
Or if you prefer you can use sound if the body is not
a good choice for you or or not today Just the simple natural sounds that
you're hearing coming and going can be a very restful place to put the mind
So don't try all three but um choose the breath the body or sounds as a simple
anchor
And just see if the mind can naturally tune in
All of these objects are gently changing So that can be easy for the mind to
find its way to resting with it Little bit of gentle movement feels nice
It's very natural that the mind will fall away from the object or become
caught up in some way If you've meditated for more than five
minutes you'll know this And I know some of you have meditated for quite a while
But when we notice that of course the mindfulness is already returned
And the invitation for this sit is to notice explicitly the feeling of
groundedness in being present
It actually feels more easeful more
anchored in some way to be present than to be wandering off thinking about
tomorrow or what that person said yesterday
We might miss the advantages of being present if we
don't look for them So it may be subtle at first but notice
the clarity the groundedness of mindfulness
And I'll also offer a second invitation
in addition to perceiving mindfulness as having clarity and groundedness
Maybe try out perceiving this feeling as a as an aspect of safety
So when the mind and the body are together in the present moment
there's an extra dimension of safety that is not present
when the mind is caught up the mind is following its distractions
When the mind is spread out or distracted
it's kind of like when we're when we're carrying
a fragile bowl and we've got it in one hand and our
hand is wet and we're walking quickly and then
we remember oh this is I should be careful with this bowl And so we hold it
with both hands close to the body and we walk slowly
and it feels so different
So when the mind and the body are together just being mindful of experience
we're holding that bowl safely carefully
Can we sense That
When we perceive mindfulness as a form of safety
we may naturally enjoy being present
Even if what we're present for is a difficult mind state or pain in the body
Still there's this sense of yeah but I'm here for it This is the
place where I can meet it most skillfully
So you may also notice the natural simple
ease and enjoyment of being fully with experience
safely
And as we move toward the end of this sitting
we can notice that mindfulness with its accompanying sense
of safety clarity grounded goodness
is a way of taking care Taking care with our experience
And in a similar way when we are mindful going about our
daily life or interacting with other people
there's also an element of care that comes when we bring our clear
attention to that
If we go through life distracted moving quickly
with an attitude of let's just get it done or I wish I weren't having to do
this right now or I don't want to interact with this person
All of those things actually endanger us in certain ways
We're more likely to say something we didn't want to say or that is not
helpful We're more likely to
get injured drop something on our foot We're more likely just to not enjoy the
time not feel a sense of well-being or ease
It's not that everything we do we're going to enjoy naturally or that we're
every interaction is going to be easy or friendly necessarily But if we're fully
present again we're adding that
doing it carefully doing it as wisely and as compassionately as is possible in
that moment So again there's safety and being present and being willing to stay with
things So the invitation is to try that out today and see if if it's the case
that there's a sense of refuge
safety in being present whether it's pleasant or whether it's unpleasant
Serving ourselves and others in a caring way
[Music]
Okay we'll be talking about a series of
animal simileies this week and I've chosen them such that they are meant to
represent different stages of the mind's journey from being reactive and caught
up to being more wise and strong And
this is a a journey that we go on as we undertake mindfulness practice as we
develop samati some gathering of the mind and as we have genuine insights not
only into our own life but into the nature of suffering and the end of
suffering And so that means that we'll generally go from
weaker animals to stronger animals if you will Don't take it too literally Um
we're not insulting the animals that are early in the week Um these simileies
that are given by the Buddha are meant to be figurative They're meant to help
us reflect on our own minds and our own lives And they also offer teachings in
how to practice well and how to understand some of the important aspects
of the dharma So today we're going to start with the
quail The quail So uh when I was at IRC one
spring I frequently saw a quail pair with their chicks and it was quite
amazing to me because they had something like 17 of them I couldn't actually
quite count them all when they were going by um but I tried and I got close
to 17 So I thought about um also about how well protected they would be if they
were to stay inside of IRC's fence IRC has a fence a deer fence all the way
around it So if they stayed inside there would be no threat from coyotes or foxes
or things like that I mean there would still be IRC's cats um maybe hawks but
IRC has a lot of forest So you know overall the sense was that
quailes don't really fly all that well and they do look kind of vulnerable um
moving around with a big cluster of tiny chicks So I realized that this um image that's
given in the sutas is pretty accurate then which is that the first of all the
quail is portrayed as um physically weak So this is a quote from a a suta
Suppose a quail was tied with a vine and was waiting there to be injured caged or
killed Would it be right to say that for that quail that vine is weak feeble
rotten and insubstantial the Buddha asks this question and the monks say "No no
for that quail the vine is a strong firm and stout bond a tie that has not rotted
and a heavy yolk." So for a quail even a vine is can be quite a substantial bond
And then the analogy is extended um from physical weakness to represent also a
certain kind of um lack of mental fortitude Not that we would have that
all the time but you know we have our moments right So it goes on to um liken
the quail to a person who wants to practice in a sense or even wants to um
ordain Uh but we could just say for lay people to to practice more seriously to
have a regular practice but they find that they're not able to give up even things that aren't serving them very
well So again um from the suta and I have to apologize a little bit for the
um literal language that's used but I'm trusting we since we're on a whole week of simileies we can make that
translation in our minds So it says suppose there was a poor man with few
possessions and little wealth He had a single broken down hut open to the crows
not the best sort And a single broken down couch not the best sort and a
single pot for storing grain not the best sort And his relationships were
also not the best sort And then he would see a person practicing uh sitting in
meditation in the cool shade their hands and feet well washed after eating an
alms meal And he would think "Oh the life of practice looks so very pleasant
The life looks very healthy If only," and now it uses the monastic image If
only I could shave off my hair and beard dress in ochre robes and go forth into
this life of practice But he is not able to give up his broken
down hut broken down couch his pot or his poor relationships none of which are
the best sort in order to go forth Would it be right to say that for that man
those bonds are weak feeble rotten and insubstantial and of course the monks reply "Oh no for that man even those we
those not of the best sort things are strong firm and stout bonds."
So even if we have possessions or life
situations that are not serving us well maybe they're not even healthy for us
if we can't give them up or change them They are real fedters and burdens and
bonds for us So as an extreme example you know people who have addictions of
various kinds their bodies are being damaged They're using up their money
their relationships are not healthy and yet the nature of addiction is that it's very hard to give up even those things
that are that are making life difficult And then you know we may see in
ourselves reflections of this Maybe we're stuck in a job that is uh very
stressful for us or a living situation that is not easy And sometimes we may
even be given a chance to change but we waffle and we hesitate because we're not
sure about giving up even this harmful situation just because we have it It
happens all the time And this is this is where we start actually in our practice is that we
we're clinging to things that are not even supportive for us
So we can notice that the English verb to quail
means to give way to falter to collapse to cower It's not a very common verb but
it is um it is I think the quail was chosen partly because of its resonance
with that English verb You know the the translation of the bird and just saying
it's a quail But hang on I've set us up that that we
can now provide some hope There is some hope for the quail given in another suta
There's there are other quail sutas and it starts out with the quail getting in
trouble But hang on So this is now from a different suta It's a story The Buddha
is actually telling a story And he says "Once in the past a hawk suddenly swooped down and seized a quail And then
while the quail was being carried off by the hawk he lamented h we were so
unlucky of so little merit We strayed out of our own resort and into the
domain of others if we had stayed in our own resort today in our own ancestral
domain This hawk wouldn't have stood a chance against me in a fight So the
quail gets caught by the hawk when it's straying from its ancestral domain is
actually what the text says And then um the story goes on with the hawk uh kind
of mocking the quail a little bit and saying "Well what is your ancestral domain?" And the the quail says "It's a
freshly plowed field covered with clouds of soil." And so the hawk is a little
bit arrogant and lets the quail go and um the quail goes back to the field that
is his own ancestral domain And then um
the the hawk actually gets a little overconfident and tries to attack the
quail there and ends up um injuring itself and not able to to get the the
quail So all that's a little violent sounding but again there's an analogy
given where um the quail gets in trouble when it's gone outside the field and the
hawk gets in trouble trying to attack the quail in the field Each one has the realm where it kind of belongs
And so the Buddha uses this as an analogy for our mind He says if if you
don't if you let your mind stray into areas that are not helpful for it He
uses the term mara Mara will gain access to those who stray outside their own
resort Mara being the name for the forces of distraction of um unh
wholesomeness in the mind And so um
so the the Buddha then goes on to say well what is our own ancestral domain you know where can our mind be safe and
he says the four establishments of mindfulness So he says here monks a monk dwells or a
practitioner dwells contemplating the body in the body ardent clearly aware
and mindful having removed covousness covetousness and displeasure in regard
to the world A meditator dwells contemplating feelings and feelings mind
in mind dharmas and dharmas hardened clearly comprehending and mindful having
removed covetousness and displeasure in regard to the world So we belong in the four foundations of
mindfulness and the domain of others is in the realm of distraction in the realm
of getting attached to what he actually says the Buddha says is the five chords of sensual pleasure forms cognizable by
the eye that are desirable lovely agreeable pleasing and tantalizing And
the same for sounds and smells and tastes and sensations
Um so this is a little bit what Shelley talked about last week is when we get caught up in our sense world in a way
that is not helpful ways that it's either attached to it grabbing after it
or pushing it away Then we are easily subject to forces in the mind that are
uncomfortable for us that get us in trouble that by which we say things that are not helpful for relationships
Whereas if we stay mindful we stay with our body we stay with the feeling tone
we understand what's happening in our internal world it's so much easier to
interact well with our life with ourselves with others And so we have the
the quail Um the story of the quail is that uh he was smart enough to realize
oh I strayed outside um and I got caught by the hawk but if I
had stayed in the field it would have been fine And sure enough the you know he gets detested right because the hawk
lets him go into the field and and can't get hold of him So in the same way if we
realize oops I was caught up I was caught up in wanting and not wanting and distraction Soon as we realize that if
we return to mindfulness we can feel actually how maybe we're still kind of
irritated but it's just irritation We just observe oh the mind's irritated right now and we've pulled back into
this realm of safety just knowing that Mara's there but we're not caught by
Mara So it's good news for us as practitioners
Um even if we're new practitioners or if we're not so wise yet uh we're protected
by mindfulness practice the Buddha's instructions to keep our attention in these particular realms is really good
advice And by the way it doesn't change later when we become more experienced is
always just the four foundations of mindfulness all the way through So the quail generally depicted as weak
physically mentally prone to being attacked in various ways But if the quail remembers to come back into the
ancestral domain of the four foundations of mindfulness then immediately safety
is available and we can use this in our everyday life and in our practice on the
cushion So this is our foundation for the week is that the quail um when our
mo when our mind has moments of being like the quail there is safety available
always So I wish you well in your mindfulness practice and we'll go on with another
animal tomorrow Thank you