good evening welcome welcome especially if this is your first
time here at IMC a warm welcome so I'll just say briefly that uh
on Thursday nights Tanya Weiser teaches here it's a little bit different style a little bit more
interactive a little bit more guidance I think with the meditation and then on Sunday mornings
is skill from stall the founder and on Wednesday mornings often
is also Gil too so these we and then there's a lot if you look at our
calendar there's a lot of stuff happening here and you're welcome to all of them there's a few things that are
happening that are like year-long courses that are we're in the middle of them and I think those aren't on the
calendar so so if it's on the calendar you're welcome to come
and then I feel like I should say happy new year right happy New Year
everybody it's uh I was thinking about this is it is this whole idea maybe
you've had this thought too of New Year is kind of funny it's a little bit arbitrary like okay Tuesday and then
Wednesday but all of a sudden it's a different year and this you know these Concepts
these ideas that we put on certain things for me today feels like the new
year right the first Monday in January kind of feels like oh this is the beginning of the new
year but you know calendars are handy having names for years weeks months days
is Handy it's helpful so we use them it's very useful but I think many of us recognize
that these are just Concepts right I mean if you you were
to write 2024 on a date for something the experience is exactly the
same right whether you're writing 225 2025 or 2024 right like the
experience is the same of when you're actually doing it maybe in the same way
that when we have three-day weekends sometimes like Tuesdays feel like Wednesdays or maybe Wednesdays feel like
Tuesdays whatever The Experience doesn't change if all day
long you thought it was Tuesday but it was really Wednesday you still felt hungry at noon you still felt like you
should take the dog out for a walk at a certain time or you know whatever the experiences are the
same but it's just these Concepts that we put on top which are useful and
helpful and and so much about meditation is actually to help us see this
distinction in a particular way maybe in a deeper
way this distinction between experiences and Concepts
and I brought along some props I don't often do this but I don't
know I just felt like somehow doing this okay so here we are we have a very
helpful office supply a binder clip this humble binder clip very
helpful it's nice we use these I use these sometimes when I have I still use paper for a lot of things I like paper
you know I I grew up using paper so uh I like paper okay this is a modest binder
clip and then here's a pen it's just a
ordinary pen ballpoint pen we could say the pen is bigger than
the binder clip there's no trick question about this this is very straightforward there's
nothing uh uh tricky about this this one's bigger the pen the binder clip is
smaller we're just looking at size just physical size one's big one small big
small no nothing tricky here until we do this little magic trick
Tada what was big is no longer big when it's compared we have six scissors here
which are bigger so now what we were was calling big is now maybe middle
sized you're like Diana we're not in kindergarten what are you
doing these Concepts that we add they're not inherent to the thing there's
nothing about this pen that is inherently big it's just big when it's compared to
something smaller and it's middle ized when it's compared to something
bigger but how often do we think that the concepts that we appli to something
is inherent to this thing to this
person to this group of people them over there those are the
people that are bad or good or something like this there's not concepts are something
that we adding on top of a red skinny thing that makes a
clicky sound and has a ink on the one end of
it we're calling this a pen it could also be a two toy if a person wear a dog
or or if somebody for a dog I should say if uh it could also if I were to throw
this at somebody maybe it could be a means to get their attention
it's no longer served as a ped right or if um I was trying to describe what the
color red was this could just be something else right there's nothing inherent into these labels I was saying
the label big that wasn't inherent the label pen isn't inherent in this there
are so many ways in which we're using words and Concepts which are so useful
we need them and it's not the same the map is not the
territory we've heard this expression the words that we're using
the language that we're using isn't the same as the
experience isn't the same as what the objects
are so in the simplest terms we can say a concept is maybe like a label
that we put on to something and and
makes it feel and we might mistake or conflate that label with the actual
object in some places this makes perfect sense like if I were to say like uh for
example Insight Meditation Center is a a concept right what is Insight Meditation
Center is it uh is it this spell is it this statue is it this uh building
but then what about like the ebels that go out or you know the people that uh
practice here or whatever it is like Insight Meditation Center is kind of like a concept very
useful so that in some ways these labels are
extra and we don't realize how we often we're moving
through life with these ideas conceptions preconceptions
projections thoughts beliefs and these beliefs about
ourselves about life about other people and these are just Concepts and ideas
they're not what's they're not real they're they're not the actual
experience so for some examples or we might have some ideas about
ourselves that um I can't do
that that that this I'm never angry dang it don't tell me
that which I actually said apparently at one time somebody did say to me Diana
you this was a meditation teacher that told me this quite some time ago early in my practice apparently I proclaimed I
was never angry and then a few years later this person saw me and I was really
angry right we have ideas about ourselves right and then we try to uh like re
interpret our experiences in order to map these ideas but the same ways we might have
ideas about other people because they live in that part of
the world that part of the continent whatever it might be that part of the planet that part of the city that part
of the county that part of the street whatever it might be we might just have ideas like oh yeah there's those people
over there and we might think that they're great we might think that they're
terrible but there's this way that we're kind of like diminishing their humanity and not recognizing maybe maybe they're
tremendously generous to their Community to their family maybe they are fantastic
caretakers for their loved ones or for others maybe they're fantastic
caretakers for themselves maybe they have a terrible disease but they are meeting it as best they can with taking
good care of themselves instead of you know trying to deny and pretend it's not
happening I had this a experience where this was a number of years ago I
had to have some medical test I don't remember what they were testing for so it must have been negative whatever the
results were but um it required that they were going to put some uh something in my
veins and stick me in some type of a scanner and um I'm like okay well you
know this is what's going to happen and and uh so they hook me up with something
I don't like to look so I don't know exactly what it was but you know something in my uh arm so that they could insert whatever it was they were
inserting dye presumably and uh the technician the
person that was doing this uh said okay you're going to feel a warm sensation
after um I injected this and it's going to feel like you're peeing your pants
you're not in your head you maybe you've had this I'm like okay
whatever I was all interested like wow there's a big machine and I'm going to go in there and you know all this kind
of stuff and um they uh injected it and
said okay you're going to feel like you're pee your pants I felt like I was peeing my pants it was quite something
and there was a reassuring me you are not peeing your pants there's like this warm feeling
like it just felt like okay this is what it would feel like if one peed their pants and so can you imagine that if I
had had that uh experience and assigned this meaning I'm peeing my pants then
there would have been some maybe some humiliation or embarrassment or shame I
don't know what I would have said or done I don't know what I would have done but it would have been a completely
different experience than the one that the concept have been giving me it's going to feel like this
the exact same physical experience could be interpreted as oh they just put
something in my veins that makes this sensation arise or oh my gosh I'm supposed to be an adult and uh this is
happening here and there's these all these people around here too I don't think I can hide this so right the exact
same experience exact same experience can have different interpretations based
on what concepts we're using how how often does this happen in our
lives I can't believe you're late you're always late it means you don't respect
me I've had this experience too where I was thinking like I can't believe she's late and you know why I'm this person is
always late and don't they recognize you know that I had to go out of my way to be here on time and now I'm having to
wait and you know then to hear like um sorry I'm late I actually got a ticket
was I was speeding to get there on time but then I got pulled over and so you know it's not because they were
disrespectful I had this whole story right about why this person was late but no it was something completely
different so we have these ideas we have these
Notions about our
experiences sometimes they're accurate sometimes they're not how do we
know how do we know whether they're accurate or not does it
matter whether they're accurate or not is it
necessary what if I was feeling a little bit irritated that uh this person
was late in meeting me and I just know noticed oh yeah I feel some uh
restlessness uh a little bit of agitation thoughts are going a lot
pretty fast and a lot of story making is happening and um I'm feeling agitated in
my body a little bit it could have just been that instead of having to attribute a whole story to
my friend I could have just been with my experience and then I would have been present for what is actually happening
noticing the agitation maybe I could have just said oh yeah feeling agitated feels like this my for me I I don't know
why I feel agitation often in my arms and in my legs maybe like there's a feeling of like movement wants to happen
or something restlessness feels like that and that could have been a moment
of just being with my experience and I could have felt grounded in my experience restlessness
would be happening but there's a way in which just to be present with that experience
without making stories and attributing meaning to it to my friends who happen
to get a speeding ticket on the way to see me to meet
me so in the same way when I'm I'm doing guided meditations when
I'm leading the meditation I like to use the Expression
like notice or be with or rest the attention on the sensations of
breathing I like to use this expression the sensations of breathing as opposed
to the breath be mindful of the breath be mindful of the sensations of breathing
the breath what is a breath really diaphragm can contracts there's a
little bit more space in the plural cavity the lung cavity and the lungs
expand so air goes in that's an inhale but what is the
breath is it the movement of the lungs is it the movement of the diaphragm is
it the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide is it the feeling of air going
in like what is it the sensations of breathing is more like
getting out of Concepts and ideas and more to the
experience I'm also ofer often offering three different ways to notice the
sensations you could feel the air going in and out of the nose noticing how
often it's cool when it goes in we don't feel it as much when it goes
out because it's the same temperature as the body or we could feel like the ribs or the
chest area expanding a little bit maybe the feeling the chest the stretch and then the release of the
stretch or maybe the movement of the belly areas it kind of like moves uh
this direction and then another Direction that's the feeling the actual
Sensations is where mindfulness can really help us to make a distinction
between the concepts and ideas that we have and what's actually happening and
what's actually happening and so the the Mind likes to
this is part of its job it likes to make stories and as ascribe meaning this is
helpful we need this in our daily life but meditation is a time in which we can
put aside or put on the back burner all those things that uh all the spinning
that the Mind likes to do and just be with what is and so mindfulness practice is to
just be with the experience and the way that I described for example with the breath but it's
also to notice how our thoughts about our
experience is not the same as the experience or the label is not the same
as the experience the breath that word the breath is not the same as has a stretching feeling in the
ribs and you might wonder well who cares does it
matter that there's a that we notice the difference about
this well I could say in some ways maybe it doesn't matter in many ways I would say it m it
can make a giant difference sometimes we hear this
expression that but uh in the in Buddhist uh circles or Buddhist uh
scenes actually I've heard it outside in kind of in the secular um area as well
this idea that uh pain is inevitable suffering is
optional they're appointing to this exact thing that I'm talking about that okay there might be this
terrible throbbing in the knee maybe it's like this pounding it
feels uh hot and it's kind of this in this vague area it's in the left knee
but there's this sense of throbbing with heat that's different than saying
there's pain pain is a label is a concept that we're putting on top of it but wow soon as we hear the word pain I
can't be in pain at this I can't sit like this I have to move my body I'm
going to damage myself I need to uh uh go to the doctors
after this and make sure that my knee is okay or maybe we hear this word pain and think like oh this is terrible I can't
do this and there was that time that I was in terrible pain when I had that
accident when I fell off my bike when I was a kid or F fell skiing when I was an adult or you know whatever it might be
whenever this word pain we have so many associations with it of course we do
nobody wants to be in pain but when we talk about a throbbing
experience that's not it's kind of in a diffuse area on the left knee near the
top of the knee then maybe there's a little bit of curiosity with
it and we can say wow this is uncomfortable but is it is it getting
worse is it getting better is it moving or is it just in the same
place can can I shift my posture can I move move my knee like this is it still
there right so then we're when we are describing the experience just being
with experience there may still be pain but there isn't the suffering that
starts to go with oh my gosh this reminds me of this and I have to avoid that and I knew I should have never come
to a meditation center they're going to make me being paid or something like this I don't know
we have all these stories we add to
things turns out they're extra turns out the stories are
extra and so much about this meditation practice is to help us to kind of like
tease apart the experience from the
stories often the stories is asso assciated with suffering
not always but often there's a way in which the label the concept the that we
slap onto our experience often is constricting it's just pain and then
that just becomes this black box that we don't want to go near and feels like we
have to avoid and I just there's so much stuff let so
say like with those types of uh without word in
particular now I lost my train of
thought maybe mindfulness helps us distinguish between these between the
thoughts and oh I know where I was going to go here whereas Sensations
are just Sensations some of them are uncomfortable some of them are
comfortable most of them are completely neutral but there's a way in which if we
can like Focus or tend to Incline towards the sensations then there can be
some curiosity that comes oh wow what is this what's happening like I was
describing with this knee or is it is are the sensations getting
worse are they getting are they moving around or is it just in one small area
is it kind of a diffuse area then there's possibility right when we are um
being with the experience the sensation then there's a sense of can be onward leading and um something different
arising and something new as opposed to pain I have to avoid it this is
terrible so when we're with our experience just with the experience and recog we will we will want to assign uh
meaning and labels to them this is what the mind likes to do can we just notice oh yeah that's a
label it's provisional this is my current understanding this is what I'm
thinking it is without like putting so I have it maybe be more like a Post-It
note more than something that's written in a permanent marker you know the label that we're doing it's just like a
Post-It note on it something like this because
there's this way that um when we start to make this distinction
between Concepts and and
experiences then there's this way in which we can recognize that there's more freedom
is available with Sensations we can be with Sensations Concepts often we can
get stuck in them if we use them to Def Define ourselves or to Define others or
there's a way in which things get constricted and we have to um manipulate our experiences in order to cram into
the ideas we have like you're a bad person but I just saw you do a kind thing oh well you only did that kind
thing because uh you must have some malicious intent or something like that or I'm a good person and actually I was
just mean to that customer service agent I was yelling at them because they
couldn't answer my question oh but they deserved it you know we make up some story of why we want to preserve the
sense no I'm a nice person well we'll just ignore that I was yelling mean things to that customer service
person but here's some other things that can happen if we are with our experiences rather than these
Concepts we can be more generous with our assumptions if we're just using
Post-it notes I think I think it's like this it's uncomfortable
sensation I'm not quite sure about the people that live over there I don't know anybody who lives over
there we can be more generous about our assumptions our assumptions about ourselves what we can and cannot
handle whether we are a good person or not whether it's important for us to be right all the time sometimes we have
these ideas these Concepts about ourselves but if we hold those more Loosely then
we can make we can maybe like shift some of these assumptions we have about how we should be how other people should be
what their motives are what they should be doing we can be more generous in our
assumptions and wow life just unfolds better if we are generous in our
assumptions about others and about ourselves we can have this sense of
expansive aliveness if we're tuned into our
experience while waiting for a friend who is late just being tuned in like oh wow restlessness is happening and some
agitation and it feels like this that's our sense of aliveness
there some there's some vitality and like okay this is what it means to be a human who's experiencing some
irritation as opposed to you I can't believe she doesn't respect me you know
that's kind of like a it's a limiting and uh
constricting as opposed to wow okay so I guess this is what agitation feels like
right now this has possibility and it's a this is it's uh inhabiting our
life there's also this way if we are paying attention into our
experiences or the sensations that we're having the the sights The Sounds the
what's being touched what we hear and taste if we're tuning into the actual
Sensations then there's this way that it's easier to start to embrace
uncertainty because we start to see that experiences are changing all the
time that's just their nature they're always changing the things that don't
change are our Concepts it's just ideas that don't
change experiences are changing all the time all the time right this moment
you're having bunch of different sounds or you're experiencing your body is
experiencing different things as you're moving adjusting your posture maybe of course your thoughts are having lots of
different experiences like lots of things are changing so when we start to pay attention to our
Sensations rather than just uh Concepts then we just start to see oh yeah things
are not certain they change and turns out to be
okay because we're noticing it in a small um scale like what's happening one
moment to the next moment there's so many different experiences being had
and then we start to realize oh things really are not as certain as we think
they are they just aren't they never
were but we want them to be we want to feel like we can control things of course we do of course we want to feel
comfortable of course we want the people that we love and care about to be safe and healthy and happy of course we
do but we don't get to control nearly what we think we can
control have you noticed trying to control somebody else
how did that [Laughter] go I was driving with a friend of
mine uh not too long ago uh at her car and uh she has uh a
um like a GPS that's giving instructions you know want the next light turn right
but this one is extra I don't know what it is it says at the next uh light you know turn right and notice the feeling
of spaciousness as you tune into something like this and I found myself getting angry at this think like what
don't tell me what to do I felt like this you know this computer AI thing was trying to control
my experience you know it it's kind of funny it doesn't we can't control others
they get annoyed I get annoyed when people try to control me even when AI is trying to control
me right it doesn't work it just
doesn't we need to guide children of course we do I'm not saying just allow anything and everything to happen I am
saying just notice that we don't control nearly as much as we think we do
we don't even control ourselves how many of us are exercising the exact right amount we think we should how many of us
are eating precisely what we think we should how many of us are meditating
precisely the amount we think we should you know all these things right we don't even control ourselves in the way that
we wish that we could or think that we should it just doesn't happen there
might be this idealized I what we have about how things should be but those are just
Concepts there's just ideas what we have instead are this
experience these Sensations right
now so learning to like distinguish the difference between the concepts and
Sensations and choosing to hang out with Sensations which is what mindfulness practice really is
about really can support us really in our lives in some ways that uh maybe
aren't w't obvious initially when we think about it or when maybe we took up
meditation just thinking we wanted to have some more ease or some uh a little bit more
relaxation but there's maybe something El I'll say that be able
to maybe like separate or recognize the difference between the extra labels and
um Concepts that we're adding on top of our Sensations I'm not saying we don't
need Concepts we do need them sometimes we can completely discard
them though but what would it be like to use Post-it notes instead of permanent
marker noticing this helps us to understand how we might
unknowingly be creating the conditions for our increased
suffering increased difficulties in our lives
saying to ourselves you shouldn't do that all I can't believe you did it you're such a fill in the blank the
inner critic that often arises and it's so mean this inner critic can be so mean
right that's extra that's extra but often we don't even know that's extra we
don't even we just think it's the truth we just think that because it's familiar perhaps we've heard it a lot that no
this is the way things are
so recognizing the difference between Concepts ideas that we're putting on top
of our experiences maybe helps us to understand in some of the ways in
which the ideas or the concepts that we are using Create the conditions for our
discomfort or suffering or difficulties and it turns out that
learning this and looking at look learning this the difference between Concepts and
Sensations and choosing to use posted notes for Concepts and tune into
Sensations turns out to be much more reasonable than trying to get the entire
world to behave properly so that you can finally be happy so that you can finally
have what you want has anybody tried to uh get the
world just be different than how it is
right it doesn't work in the way that we wish it would doesn't mean that we you know shouldn't behave ethically and take
care of others and take care of ourselves it doesn't mean
that so New Years Happy New Years New Years is a concept it's how helpful
useful and meditation is a way in which we can really start to get to know what
concepts are we using what labels are we using that are extra and not
needed or is there a way that we are just living our life in the mind I
certainly did my early life I was very much disconnected I didn't inhabit the body at
all somehow I thought you know well I got rewarded professionally academically
for being in my head right chances are many of you did
too but mindfulness practice this invitation to just explore
the difference between these two and to tune into the sensations the
experiences I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there's some questions
or comments thank you
um I guess this is more of a comment or personal experience I notice sometimes
The more I've noticed my thinking I see patterns where I uh am a little
obsessive about situations I can't control
and now that I've noticed this more I I do the thing where I go okay so how how
does this feel in my body when I'm doing you know and it's like banging my head
against the wall it's not going to change with what I'm doing so that's been helpful to kind of go go
into the body nice and um and tell myself it's okay to not
think about you know to put it aside what's here what's here right now in the
room with me and my physical experience nice nice it's I hadn't really thought
about this until more recently but in some ways it's kind of fascinating how
we have this idea if I have some internal experience thoughts like
ruminating or just getting a little bit uh compulsive or I think the obsessive was the word that you used in our
thinking somehow we think that our having some interior inner experience is
going to change something that's happening not there it's fascinating right how we have this idea so illogical
it's does it's so illogical right but we do it okay if I just worry enough then
they'll be safe right or if I get angry enough then
uh they will change their behavior but you know it's just us that's getting angry or something so thank you very
much for pointing that out yeah thank you very human right I think all of us do this
yeah anybody else have a comment or question or something they'd like to
share okay with that I wish you all a Happy New Year and uh it's nice to see
you all and maybe I'll see you next week thank you