so good morning everyone and welcome to IMC and um what's on my mind this last
few days is the topic of patience so that'll be the subject of this
talk and as a way of kind of maybe opening the door to patients
and maybe why it should be interesting can be interesting there's a teaching of
the Buddha that goes some something like this of all the goals accomplished of
all the things accomplished you'll find nothing more
beautiful than patience and how many of you associate
patience with beauty but uh can patience be
beautiful and uh and that's the call that's the possibility and how is it
beautiful is um maybe the what this talk will kind of point
to the part of the reason why I'm focusing on patience is that I'm also
focusing on a larger list called the 10 parames where 10 Perfections where
patients precedes TR truth the Perfection of Truth the ability to be
present and see the truth clearly and um and so there's something
about patience that allows us to do one of the most important tasks of Buddhism
which is to see things as they are to see the truth and the truth is not often
easy to see sometimes it's difficult to see it in ourselves and some people even
don't even want to admit some of the things they see in themselves it takes a long time to finally say okay well I guess it's true that I'm selfish or it's
true that I'm angry or it's true that something in my life is not working and I was trying to pretend it
was it uh it is uh sometimes it has to do with the the world that we live in
and I've heard a lot of people now who uh in the last few months for whatever
the reasons are who
knows uh have decided not to uh read the news as as much as they used
to and um because it's too difficult or too
something and uh but maybe being able to see the world as it is is really
important for Buddhists to stay informed to not turn away because it's difficult
um uh not that not turn away because it's difficult is maybe not the reason
and there's good there's good reason I think why people are turning away because uh the impact the news can have
on them is so difficult they don't want to have this difficulty but uh that's why patience is
needed this thing that's called patience in English so um the it's possible that uh
patience is not the best word uh to translate the ancient Buddhist word
canti in Sanskrit it's aanti and
um and know I've seen repeatedly that there are very important words in
Buddhism that where the indic word the word as it's came was used in India has
very strong associations with something that's very special something sacred with something spiritual or something
kind of really kind of uh wonderful in human life that when you translate these
words into English we lose that and and the way that kti I think in the
original context of Indian Buddhism and maybe India in general uh it was one of
those words that had very strong kind of uh um welcoming
associations that it was really this is really a good thing and inspiring thing
whereas patients you know in English uh sometimes it's often associated with
enduring and um and uh it might see a little bit that in the very atmology of
the word patience in English where it comes from the Latin root Pati which means a
suffer so sometimes patients is understood to be suffering with something you well patient that is going
to suffer with it that's that's the that's what life is going
along and um but the but the um the Indian Buddhist word canti has very
different Association ations to it besides being kind of a sacred word uh
it also has the uh the one of the the one of the close associations to what it
is is it's often taught together with or mentioned together with the word meta
which means kindness or loving kindness and there's a famous I it's not
famous but at least locally in me
uh teaching of the the it's called the acrobat suta and in there there's um um
uh there's four things listed there's listed patience non-harming loving kindness and uh um
and empathic care and uh these four things are kind
of a little family so to put patience together with non-harming which is
wonderfully powerful inspiring kind of Topic in India uh Central to some
religions of India and with loving kindness friendliness and with this
empathic care for others uh puts patience in a very good family the tribe
is really a good tribe to be part of and um and we get little bit of sense
maybe a very different Association what patience can mean when you realize that the Sanskrit you
see it more clearly in Sanskrit that the there the eological root of the word
Isam which means Earth so rather than the root coming from the idea of suffering it comes from
the idea of Earth and Earth is something that um is stable or can hold or has
certain kind of equinity or space can hold all kinds of things and there's this teaching the Buddha gave that's um
that kind of speaks to this where when he was giving u meditation instructions to his
son um the Buddha said this to
him cultivate your practice like the Earth by cultivating a practice like the
Earth pleasing and unpleasing context pleasing and unpleasing experiences will
not take hold of your mind and remain there suppose a clean suppose clean and
unclean things are thrown on the earth so I don't know which of these is clean which of these is unclean but like
feces urine spit pus and blood the Earth isn't troubled worried
or repelled because of this in the same way meditate like the Earth when you
cultivate a practice like the Earth pleasing and unpleasing contexts will not take hold of your mind and
remain so this idea of knowing how to be
present for things which are Pleasant and unpleasant pleasing and unpleasing um and have the mind have
this SP spaciousness or stability or largess that um that we're not triggered
easily we're not upset we don't get uh we don't get caught up in it and lost in
the reactivity to it is part of what patience is about this CTI so maybe
there's another word in English besides patience that would capture this better I don't know what that would
be but or we have to kind of learn the Buddhist word for meaning of patience
but in the context of of uh wider Buddhism um PTI and especially these
thing called the perfe sections um we have to also understand
what gives rise to patience what gives rise to this earthlike ability to to hold in a beautiful way the life that we
have to hold in a beautiful way what is unpleasing what is difficult and that is
that to understand something about what the Buddhist notion of wholesomeness and um and the idea is
that so I like to translate patience as not by a single different single
different word than patience kti but um but rather to call it wholesome patience
and then maybe you get a sense of that maybe it could be beautiful if it's
wholesome and um so one of the functions of wisdom in Buddhism and Buddhism is
often seen as a wisdom tradition is uh not to read an
encyclopedia about Buddhist philosophy and then become wise but rather for you
to take a deep look in yourself to really not be present for yourself to be
able to see feel observe within you yourself what feels healthy for you and
what is unhealthy what feels um like it
diminishes you and what kind of opens you you know inspires you to feel what
nourishes you versus what uh Den nourishes you to feel what uh gives you good energy
and what drains it away and uh and all those ideas are some
are kind of held within this Co concept of wholesomeness and UNH wholesomeness which uh I kind of like
because it u means uh part of part of the whole or not part of the whole the
UNH wholesome is what takes us away from the whole what hole I don't know the whole of who you
are the whole of what this world is like that we want to be be in it in the whole
as as it is not partial not selective not with blinders on him and um and there's something about
uh uh clinging resisting assertiveness
conceit something about even anxiety and fear sometimes that become kind of like
blinders it's kind of like we diminish ourselves we we're we're cutting we're it's a selectivity process that takes us
out of the hole and so to return to the whole to
the whole experience of the present moment the Buddha often talked about the whole body being mindful of the whole
body as we meditate uh being mindful of the whole mind not the divided mind but the Mind
as a unified whole phenomenon that as we do that what we start having
is in a clear and clearer sense of what feels healthy for us and what
doesn't and um and one of the areas of of feeling that and really getting to
know for ourselves is how we use our awareness how we use attention the very
thing that we have to that is's a the means by which we navigate through our world the very medium it's kind of like
the if the medium for fish to get through their world is water the medium
for humans to get through our world is our awareness our attention everything
that we experience in the world goes through that filter and so how are you
aware how are you attending to the world how are you observing how are you seeing
it and is that wholesome or UNH wholesome
is it beautiful or is it not so beautiful how you see it and um and so awareness itself
sometimes are why we attend to the world can be full of greed can be full of
hatred can be full of delusion it could be full of anxiety
restlessness it can be filled with preoccupations and doubt it can be
filled with interpretations and bias through which we see the experience of the the world and so this focus on what
is healthy and not healthy um is not to interpret these things but to feel what
we're doing and feel oh when I'm seeing the world through my hatred this this is
unhealthy for me this doesn't feel good it's there's tension here there's stress
here when I have seeing the world through my greed there's tension here it
diminishes me it takes me out of that the hole when I caught up in my anxiety you know
if I really you know it's hard with anxiety because anxiety is so concerned with
what it's anxious about that we don't see the effect anxiety has on us it just seems like
it's true but if we turn all these ways we turn the attention around
180° to really look at the effect that our Behavior has has the effect of how
we're relating to things we can feel wow this is actually no wonder I'm exhausted
by the end to day I'm just constantly reacting against everything I'm constantly afraid of everything and
trying to you know establish my place or I'm constantly wanting something and um constantly disappointed
constantly world's not living up to where I wanted to be and so and so we see that and say is
there another way is there a way that's not stressful that's not what's the opposite
of stress not just the absence of stress but it's some kind of wonderful Vitality
wonderful relaxed open Vitality in which we live our life so the wisdom factor in Buddhism
the mindfulness practice in Buddhism is here partly for us to be able to become
to read ourselves well that's the encyclopedia we want to study don't get
to book the book you want to read is your own heart you wanted have have a very
acute sensitivity to what goes on in your heart in your mind in your body in your
speech so that it stops being un wholesome it stops being starts being
wholesome it stops being I don't know if I want to say ugly
but I just did um and uh instead we wanted to be
beautiful can we make it beautiful what we do and how we live is that wise is that
useful well if what you want to do is get wealthy really
fast maybe not so don't bother you can go you can go now
but what if you want if you want freedom if you want to find not just be
distressed and be calm but to find this higher capacity for living a life that's
beautiful the qualities of heart and mind that come forth in you are satisfying deeply deeply satisfying for
you you feel like ah I'm home because I know inside of me now this feels good we
become our own friend our inner life is our friend ah this is beautiful this is
nice so wisdom begins helping us discern the difference between what's healthy
and not healthy for us wholesome and not wholesome and one of the things that teaches us then is where to put our
energy how to apply our energy and uh and so we have to make
choices and so as we have better better sense of what is wholesome and UNH
wholesome we canit wise or choices about where we take this wonderful human
capacity of Vitality that we have energy we have and use it to uh to awake awaken
a healthy kind of energy and and kind of stop doing things
which are kind of energy that is exhausting that's agitating that's stressful that's that's um you know
exhausting for us and it's one of the Great lights Delights of Buddhist practice to start
feeling this wonderful engagement with the world and things that we do engagement with
practice that feels like it has a vitality and a and aliveness to it that
feels good and healthy it brings us brings us joy uh when I was before I was a
Buddhist practitioner if someone had told me you know you know we have to go do some gardening or we have to do some
work soon as they say work it's like oh no I mean work is like a four-letter
word it used to be for me and and now if someone says Gil we have this work to
do I'm just delighted the first first thing okay what is it I'm ready it isn't because of
the activity but because I've learned something about how to offer myself to
the activity which is healthy and wholesome that I feel feels really nice
and one of the big things I had to learn to do in this process when I was in the Buddhist monasteries and we had to work and was
um when I still had this resistance to it I didn't know I had resistance I had
to be able to start looking at the resistance I had how I held myself back
how I collapsed how I um became so
tired oh work but but I'm exhausted you know I'm
kind of tired today and that wasn't real exhaustion and tiredness that was a
strategy to get out of the work that was you know expression of disappointment and and you know had
better things to do and and um and so in the monastery I got
the the monastery was set up to keep coming back study the book of yourself
and I got to see that uh how I applied energy how I in got I got to did what I
did could be healthy and unhealthy and I learned something about healthy
engagement and that made a world of difference and what that can do is then
the healthy engagement the healthy application of energy doing healthy
things for us that uh increases what's healthy it increases the
holesome as that happens the ability of wisdom to distinguish what is wholesome
and UNH wholesome increases the more we learn about this the more we apply and develop ourselves
the more sensitive we become to more and more uh refined versions of health and
healthy and unhealthy the more we discover the more subtle we become
meditation subtle we become in our life the more at ease the more peaceful we are that gives us a better vantage point
to notice when we when we are doing something unhealthy something that's
stressful I saw in myself that still see it sometimes if I get in a flurry of
activity doing a lot of different things I have a long to-do list I'm rushing around to do things
um uh I'm too scattered or too busy or too engaged
too involved to notice that the next thing I do is I'm
doing in a stressful way I'm so stress stressed out already it's like you know
it's like a they say in Buddhism it's like a if you have a a very clean cloth
maybe a white cloth that where any stain is highlighted and um but if it's if it's
only stained just like full of you use it for cleaning your car and changing the oil and it just you know and you
just never clean it and it's just full of stains and one more stain is not going to be
noticed but if you bleach it and it's completely clean and white uh the
slightest little drop in it is going to be oh no it was clean and now it's not
so it turns out the more we get settled the more we get at ease the more we find this more healthy way of
being the the the sooner we'll notice the slightest little way that's
stressful that is not Catches Us
so the application of energy supports this whole process of deeper sensitivity and now we come to
patience something happens and you leave IMC
today and if you drove here you have a flat tire maybe two tires are
flat so your spare tire is not really going to do that much good for you and
you have important places to go so you stand there looking at it and
because of the nature of this talk which I'm sure will penetrate deeply in and you'll remember when you go out
there to see your flat tire you'll say now what's the beautiful thing to do
here what's the healthy thing to do now should I get real then you'll think
about it you'll reflect you know should I really now get really angry
at the world for flat tires is that the best use of my energy and time should I
now get despair should I now get really get worked up and desperately try to fix
this problem as fast as I can and get myself all tense maybe you'll say
yes because the lawyers of the Mind are very convincing
maybe but is that really necessary is that really the best way to live your
life is that really do you want to do the healthy thing if what you want to do
is apply Buddhist practice integrate they call people ask often how do I integrate my practice into daily
life this is an example you would stand there looking at your two your two flat
tires and you would not just get right involved with the issue with the tires you would be tracking how you are You'
use your wisdom how am I right now how am I taking this in what has been
triggered what is the healthy thing to do now I think the healthy thing to do right now is to walk around the block
and cool down let's let's see maybe the healthy thing to do is to call the people I'm
supposed to go see and explained what's happened and saying I have two flat tires I'll come as soon as I can but
just let me it might take a while then you walk around the block to cool down and then you come back and you look
at that and you say to yourself now the tires are on top of the
Earth make your mind like the Earth that Earth doesn't seem to mind flat tires
the Earth can make space for that can I make space for that so I can be so then
when I address the flat tires I do it with spaciousness I do it with
ease you know do do it with patience patience am I supposed to endure this
too no you're supposed to turn this into something
beautiful CTI is beautiful how do you make this beautiful
how do you make this nourishing how do you make this so that by the time you're done with this
you feel like you're a better person maybe if you have a AAA card you
call AA a and you're always so worked up about it and so the per time the person comes
they're like five minutes late and you're ready to yell at them and be all upset and going to you know you know
hang over them like do it fast that's one way the other way is say
thank you for coming and the person says yeah I came
as soon as I could and here's my tires oh let me help and in the process of
helping and maybe you learn something from this person maybe the person's phenomenally friendly and kind and
compassionate maybe they're generous who knows how they are because youve made
space for it because you were beautiful and how you were there with this difficult
challenge Something Beautiful could come out of the person who came to take care
of your tires that could not not have come out of that person if you were in your whole
kind of worked up mode and you're better person because if
you the better part of that person was shared with you who knows what'll
happen so the um so the the beautiful thing so the Buddha gave talked about
the tradition talks about three different areas uh to practice kti this
wholesome patience this beautiful patience uh one is in in the efforts we
make and it's and sometimes it's called gentle perseverance sometimes it's hard to
persevere when there's challenges hard to keep going if there's a lot of things that are offering resistance or
obstacles sometimes it's hard to do it when in practicing to practice meditation for example when there's so
many things to see on Netflix and so to persist no matter what's going
on but a gentle persistence a beautiful persistence and uh this is one of the
real keys of doing Buddhist practice like like meditation practice keep doing
it steadily in all the ups and downs of your life if you only do it when you
feel good you see only part of your life if you only do it when things are difficult you only see part of your life
the idea is to have have the practice address your whole life so you want to keep it going a thread through your life
so it provides a vantage point a reference point for all of who you are
and so this gentle persistence no matter what just keep going that's a form of kti
patience the next one that's emphasized is patience under
insult and patience when things are offensive when and that is that uh the
world you know there was a kind of an insult that those tires should be flat
you know I'm supposed to be a good driver or I don't know what but uh but
more seriously I think sometimes we live in a world of a lot of conflict and people do offend each other people do uh
insult each other people do kind of take advantage of each other people do
terrible things and um and the idea is not to
condone it not to accept it that's not what patience is but uh but to uh to
maintain this beautiful patience this beautiful CTI this Wholesome Way of
being as we try to address it as we meet it and what it explicitly what it means
don't succumb to hostility whatever is happening don't
don't succumb to hostility that's a core meaning of patient patience under
insult the and the third one is um is um acceptance of
Truth and kind of what I started this this topic with and that is that uh
seeing the truth can be quite difficult so as I said earlier seeing the truth of oneself is quite hard and many people
are trying to avoid it or some people are even using uh spiritual practice as a means of avoiding
it and uh and Buddhist practice is all about like especially if you do
mindfulness sooner or later you have to be honest oh this is how it is in me and
so the ability to be honest the ability to see clearly uh in Buddhist practice uh as
mindfulness practice gets strong and especially on Retreat the comes a time
when the usual references points by how we make ourselves feel ourselves safe in the world begin falling away so there
comes a time when uh in meditation not before and after but in meditation
uh um holding on to Identity holding on to clear definitions of who I am holding
on to clear senses of who I am and it just feels too stressful it's
too too much work to keep it up and so that begins to drop but that can be very
frightening because the very way that people have made themselves safe is to become and be a certain kind of
person uh we start seeing uh suffering unsatisfactoriness how many our Pursuits
are not really that wholesome and healthy and when our whole life is kind of based on these
Pursuits then um it can be frightening and disorienting
sometimes um uh the the fact that the world is uh the desire for some people
uh really want things to be stable have a constancy to it so that things can be
reliable and there that's reasonable in many ways but in deep meditation uh the world becomes
inconstant our experience of everything is constantly shifting and changing like we've entered into the stream of life
the River of Life where everything's always flowing everything's changing and so there's nothing there in that stream
in that River that's constant that's solid that's stable and they get stable enough when
you come out of meditation so it's not like you know that um is but for some
people that gets disorienting and difficult and so this is a one of the functions of patients kti is to give us
that wholesome quality of attention that beautiful quality of attention that something can hold all this something
has this has the generosity to be with this willingness to be with his Tom and
I've seen that the people have the most challenges with deep Buddhist Meditation practice are people who've gone too
quickly into concentrated deep states without having built up and developed
this wholesome um repertoire this Wholesome Way of being in the world
who've learned how to develop joy and happiness who've learned how to um be
generous and kind who've learned metha who who kind of developed this kind of
their inner life is a friendly Place their inner life is a happy place then when when things are when
there's no self to be found where the everything is changing where everything
is um somehow unsatisfactory it's more okay because
the very awareness that knows that has become beautiful has become wholesome so then it's easier to have
this wholesome patience patience with truth so in this
way maybe kti either we choose a different word
for kti than patience or we redefine
it and make it into a new meaning it's not suffering and uh
enduring it's not stiffening up
and and just kind of you know tough toughing ourself through something it's
the opposite it's the opposite kind of toughing you know stealing ourself or
something it's softening ourselves as we go through it so that's my idea of CTI
patience so what are your thoughts now do you have thoughts or questions or
maybe you want to offer a different word than patience for kti after this presentation
um is that now can you hear me okay um so this is not um this is
when you talk about reality um I have been going and this may not be very
Buddha of me but I've been going to protests at protests
[Laughter] prot um and uh you know I've been trying
to come up with um uh because I I don't know what else to do so I go to these
protest because I you know I'm I um have aversion to the what's going on I guess
and um you know there are signs that you hold up and some of them are not very
Buddha I mean some of them are very so can you is first of all is that
a skillful thing to do or is there another way and how would you what what
protest sign would you
have I think with anything at all uh it's the
consequence of what you're doing that's measures whether it's wholesome or non wholesome the consequence can be in
yourself as you do it so if you do it with hate that's unhealthy for you if
you do it with uh animosity and hostility for someone or anyone that's
unhealthy for you if you're doing it out of greed if you're doing it out of um
you know if you do it doing something out of fear might be healthy and appropriate but to do something out of
anxiety is a very different animal very different phenomena and then what is the impact
you're having are you doing something and then doing it you feel justified in
doing it but the consequence is is that there's more divisiveness more hostility
in the world or you're doing it in a way that actually heals the divisiveness in
the world is there a way of not creating more hostility but to create goodwi
across all kinds of uh divisions that we have so the the Buddhist question is how
do we do this is there a wholesome way to do it and what is the Wholesome Way
and so in this regard um I kind of almost prefer that Buddhists don't do
protests they demonstrate because that because that
gives us a chance to demonstrate a different way we might go we might be in the same place we might be this doing
the same you know for this trying to do the same impact on the world but we're there to demonstrate an alternative
we're there to make it show a different way in how we do it and so the signs
that are there maybe are very important what they write and um and uh so that's my take is
so the answer to the question is not for me but rather uh your way of reading
yourself what is wholesome what is healthy for you and what's health and what comes out of you is healthy for for
the world around you and uh and I don't want to be in the position to answer that question for
you my question Gil is uh re uh around reactivity I can find
myself sometimes being very reactive and coming out with hostility or or huge
disappointment whatever so can you give some thoughts around how to relate to
that and how to respond to my own reactivity for myself how do I respond to this so you you know it's happening
while it's happening uh I sometimes I do but uh oftentimes I
don't think I do know it's just boom you know so what do you need so that's so
first thing you need to do is to catch it so what what has to
change what what what has to change for you how do you how do you change your
behavior in such a way you'll catch your activity when it happens well before I respond to that
can you say what you mean by catch it notice it recognize it that it's
happening well if I've already if I'm already reacting and saying something
or excuse me or you know um looking disgusted or something to the other
person it's already happened so I I guess what I'm asking
is if if it's already happened I can then I can be aware of it but how do I
be aware of it before it happens yeah that's that's what I'm asking oh also but what what I'm what I'm offering to
you is uh you know you you've been tracking this for a long time you're
aware of this for a long time and you have a lot of data and or you can maybe you need to
start collecting the data and then answer you have to answer the
question how do you physically behaviorally change how you live your
life so you can catch it earlier is that all
it's a joke and because if if if you expect that you can just Barrel a barrel
ahead in the life that you're living and somehow those magic formulas is going to be there to help you see this is not
going to work you have to actually reflect on your
life and and see what what do you have to change about your life in such a way
that you you're you're there and present for what you do as you go through the day that you catch it earlier uh so
early that it doesn't come out of your mouth or maybe it doesn't come out of your your Grimace or something and um
and so what does that take so I don't know your life well enough some people find it makes a world of difference to
meditate every day maybe maybe what really needs to happen for someone like
you is maybe it needs to be an at least an at least an hour a day
I don't know how long you meditate but uh but you know if uh if you've been
coming to IMC for a long time that tells me that this practice is important for you and maybe this is a time to do more
of it and and maybe it's temporary maybe for it's three months that you meditate for an hour two hours a
day you know an hour in the morning around in the afternoon it's it's crazy in the life people live here right
that's so filled with doing doing doing but if this is is important enough for you if the question is being asked
because this is really important for you then maybe you have to do something that really allows you
to and maybe meditating more maybe it's doing less another neurotic thing that
goes on in our culture there are so many opportunities so many things to do that
more here more in the modern world than probably anywhere in life certainly more than time of the Buddha uh you know
there's so much available to to us so there's a way in which people are trying to have to do so much and catch every
stay up on everything and get all the movies get all the books get all the recreational activities get you know do
do do do and um and some of it's because they have to work and people are working
long hours and that's where it all at but um
uh if you want to answer that question for yourself maybe you need to look at
what you spend your time doing every day maybe need to create more space in the day maybe everything that everything you
do that takes um uh it takes maybe 45
minutes to do uh whatever how long something it takes you always add 10% more time to it
so there's space between things you don't kind of out of breath and then you off to do the next thing so you have to
decide what kind of change you want to do in your life and otherwise I don't see any way to answer your
question thank you I see a hand here oh that's
say hello um I just want to share something can if you hold it uh
horizontal like like this yeah uh I just want to share something that might be
helpful uh helpful for me um um like
when I come home I will park in a garage and meditate for 10 minutes before I
enter the house and that has really been helpful fantastic for my interaction
yeah uh with my family and same thing when I go to work I will also sit in the
car and meditate for 10 minutes before I go to the office and that really also
has been very helpful fall fantastic I love it I used to do that uh Park about
300 yards from my house uh before I went home into my house because we had these
little babies at home and I and I had to get ready for was coming it was it was often like I'd
open the door it's your turn and so those those those few
minutes of set getting settled from the day got ready for the my last
one um thank you Gil you know um I really appreciate your love of language
because using the way you're using patience in this talk um is kind of
really opened a new dimension uh for me and um
I was reflecting on it in the context of what happened to me in the
past 12 hours um I I had a
beautiful dinner uh last night and um I got home Angry Angry yes and it was like
out of nowhere and I remember looking at the mirror and seeing my anger and I was
just too tired I just went to bed in the middle of the night I wake up and I'm still
angry and um I meditated and I fell asleep and then
when I woke up I just started to feel the anger in my body and I felt oh is there a better
way to react to this and um to this
situation and it just open up you know a whole new uh thing
for me but I would have not described this experience as patients but it makes
a lot of sense the way you're bringing patience because I had to be patient
with my not being able to see my negative contribution to the
situation um and it's only
um giving me that that chance instead of staying in in in the reactivity in a way
I love hearing that very nice so the patients gave you the chance than to ask
the question is there a better way yes and I couldn't I couldn't have asked that question before because I was just
focused on I need to tell this person this is not a good way to behave
uh and yeah so I I really appreciated um this angle in finding
Beauty and patient instead of enduring something I didn't
like very nice thank you so maybe just
maybe there might be some little occasion over the next few days to have
some patience just maybe and so maybe you'll be better
prepared and um so thank you and if you want to say hello to someone who's next to you and wish them well and the
adventure their adventure with patience that that might be nice and then thank
you all