Welcome to our meditation
session and to begin with a ritual of
posture maybe with a homecoming of
posture maybe with the attention on posture being an expression of care care
for your body care for yourself and so assuming a supportive
posture for
meditation giving yourself a little bit of time to make the even subtle
adjustments in how your hands are your arms your legs your feet
subtle adjustments to the maybe even the back of the
neck there is a kind of up alertness or
a wakefulness that can happen in the back of the neck as the neck elongates a little bit
or comes back a teeny bit with a little bit more space created
between the last vertebrae and the
skull reorienting oneself from
[Music] concerns that have nothing to do with here and
now to a ritual of settling into here and
now gently closing the
eyes and gently pausing at the end of the
exhale just momentary to feel the body's
urge the physical urge maybe very Gent gental calm urge to
breathe in and give into
that and ride the inhale let the
inhale the movement and expansions of the chest the
belly let it touch you from the inside out
to the degree to which air fills your lungs as you breathe
in let that feeling of becoming gently full and
expansive appear for you fully as you breathe
in and as you exhale to relax your
body to soften
breathing in and becoming aware of the thinking
mind not what you're thinking about but the sensations and
feelings embedded in that thinking
mind as you exhale
soften Relax The Thinking
mind if thinking are like waves on the surface of
water let the winds die down in the mind
a quieting of your thoughts and the softening on the
exhale a stilling of the
Waves as the surface of the water spreads wide and
calm the Mind becomes expansive and calm
and then centering yourself on
breathing as as if perhaps breathing is a
refuge breathing is a a place
that protects
you from The Winds of the Mind the storms of the Mind
breathing maybe almost like the the calm in the middle of all
things
for for
and as you accompany your
breathing as you become one with with your
breathing is there any
wellbeing any pleasure
Delight any Joy or happiness
however modest it might be that Som so that somehow is
associated with this
meditation and let that become
The Gentle Wind or the
gentle absorption of
water like water is absorbed in a sponge let that
wellbeing slowly spread get absorbed throughout your body
not so much trying too
much just
gently breathing breathing with the well-being
where the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out connecting to breathing sustaining
attention is a
gentle massage wind
water that spreads
into your body
expanding field of
wellbeing to which gives you a kind of attitude of
yes yes yes to being present
here
for
e
for for
feeling whatever well-being is present for a few minutes put aside any
resistance to feeling well-being
take the risk to feel some degree of
well-being so well-being accompanies you your
practice and if there's some ways that you feel challenged emotionally or physically or
socially if that challenge seems to be standing in the way of well-being
let the them accompany each other like the two flat hands Palms come
together in angel in
bowing and if it supports your well-being and joy
have a little half smile on your lips your
mouth letting well-being
enjoy be massaged be worked into
everything your whole being gently
slowly
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting some care self-care goes
into the end of meditation just as there's care and going into
it might first begin by a gentle recognition
of what is going well for you through the
meditation and that could be a very modest criteria what's going
well maybe you're a little more
settled maybe there's more self-awareness
some understanding of yourself maybe there's more
calm maybe there is some form of meditative
well-being and whatever benefit that has come let it register in your body in
your heart in your mind take it
in some people use the metaphor drinking drink it in or taste it with
your whole
being when there's something good that's happened in the Dharma it's invaluable to appreciate
it without appropriating
it without holding on to it
or appropriating it to build up another form of self just
appreciate and that appreciation that benefit of the
well-being can expand and grow if we open ourselves
up to in a way to share it with all beings almost like we're going to give
it away let everyone else share or receive
my calm I'm not going to hold on to it I'm not going to cling to it
please let it spread for me out into the world as a gift
may this calm well-being Insight
understanding be shared for the welfare and happiness of
everyone may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you
for e
so good morning everyone and good day welcome and um
so welcome to this talk this is the fifth talk on the first
jna and um uh continuing talk on a wider series
on the samadi and um uh samadi as I've often said is a state
of being it's not a particular mental activity of being concentrated or
hyperfocused and um and so uh it's a state of being that we enter
into and um and as such it's a radically different way of experiencing ourselves
unusual we're always in some State and uh even the expression in English that
person's boy is that person in a state is usually meant that they're kind of something's really unusual about them or
odd about them and um but we're always in some kind of state and uh
unfortunately we take some of our states we're in as being normal and ordinary
that doesn't just how it is um but often there's we're fragmented
we're stressed we're de-stressed we're pre occupied we caught in things and
that feels normal and there's certain attitudes or even emotions which persist that can
feel like this is this is just life as it should be because that's what we're used
to but when we let go when we let things fall away all the extra all the
unnecessary activity of mind even the unnecessary activity of heart uh even unne activities of the
body and let all that Fall Away uh in a
at least metaphorically uh up upright uh uh position stance way of
being uh what we're left with can be a state of well-being state of confidence
a state of it's just it's it's enough just to be alive it can be there's no no
tendency to want to judge it or interpret it as being something is wrong or inadequate or it just uh things
things become better and better it just feels good to be alive good to be here and uh it's a state of
well-being so that's one of my definitions of samadi is a state profound state of well-being in which we
feel immersed and so uh the first jna is uh
represents a very particular kind of samade uh there's other many forms of
samade of immersions and but the particular one that is very very significant and
powerful and can be a game Cher for some people uh in the ancient Buddhist
tradition the Buddha said that uh once a person is in in the first
jna in that sense of well-being and peace and and letting go of so many
attachments that um it's kind of the first taste of what it's like to be
awakened to be free and some people might even uh confuse it with full
Liberation Buddhist Liberation because it's so so special and so nice but it
gives us a first taste it can be quite inspiring oh this is possible it's
possible to have this who would have known that such a thorough feeling of wellbe being of uh that feels like a
homecoming were possible there are plenty of people who will say have said that this is not
possible to uh to have this level of Som and well-being but there is it is
definitely possible so in this first jna uh the
state is one that's often characterized by the five genic factors that I talked about yesterday
and um so there are the initial application of mind the sustained application of Mind of attention there
is the uh Joy my translation of the word po
word pity P TI and there is happiness my translation
of the PO word Suka s u k ha a and um and then there is um said to be
some overall um State this that state of uh of absorption of immersion that's say
characterized as I'm I'm calling it becoming one sometimes called
one-pointedness sometimes called unification and
um and uh and so those all kind of come together and uh in the first J there's
the various uh strengths by which it can occur it can be very m mild and so mild
that the difference between the approach State and the Janna is not so clear uh
kind of uh we slide back and forth between them even but other times it's quite strong and it's very clear this is
you know now we're in a new territory and um and and the degree of
strength that it has has a lot to do with the degree of Joy the strength of
the pity and uh there can be a range of um strengths to it um there's uh in the
classic teachings there's five degrees or ways that that pity This Joy can be
experienced I find it kind of inspiring to hear this list of all the possible ways you don't have to have them all but
it's sometimes it's nice to know that these are in the range the stronger forms of it people can get sometimes
afraid of it or scared like wow this is intense so the first one is minor so
it's just a subtle maybe subtle or minor it's not like uh something that's so
dramatically different than what a joy or U that one has in daily
life another one is momentary that uh it's uh it just seems like it's Sparkles
it comes it comes and goes maybe with every uh breath that comes and
disappears appears comes and disappears um it uh it just there for a moment it
kind of sparkles or Sparks someplace uh then there is um uh
something called showering and uh and this is where there it feels like there's a shower of of um
water pouring through Us in some way a flow pouring through us moving through
us um it's stream that's moving through us uh maybe a um uh you know like sand
going through a um hourglass it just be where where at the thin Edge Of The Hourglass and just moves flows and flows
something as streams going and that stream can be quite intense sometimes and it might go in different directions
it might go um you know up the spine up the head it might go down into the feet
um the different things and sometimes when it gets too intense the sense of the Stream this um of it
um that uh sometimes people find it helpful to relax the body even more so
the stream becomes softer and wider and sometimes people even kind of uh
redirect it if so it's more grounding like down down the feet and um and then there is
um the um uh something called
um uplifting the joy and now this is quite
inspiring and this is kind of almost like people feel they get very light sometimes they feel they're like they're
being lifted up and sometimes actually the posture uh will change because the
this lifting up sometimes straightens out the spine and and it's like the re everything's alert and present but uh
you know it can feel like we're lifted off the cushion even because everything's so light and inspiring
and and uh it's kind of you know Wonderful to experience and then there's
pervading the um the showering sometimes can be quite intense uh I've had the
experience of it's feeling feeling like huge cascading uh waves so just kind of like
you could feel the wave coming and then crashing down and um and sometimes I've
had it after meditation and when it happens I have to stop what I'm doing uh just kind of just pause and wait for
this wave to Crest and break and pass um so there's all kinds of very
unusual things that can happen with the intensity of it mostly when people are in Retreat and um but the one that I uh
that uh I uh like is this last one called
pervading and this is the instruction the Buddha gives is to let this well-being This Joy spread and that's
the only instruction he gives as I said yesterday is to let it spread Let It Be
suffused almost like uh with every breath there's a massage that spreads it
for further and further every breath is like the wind the the air of a Bellows
letting it fire warmth to get warmer and warmer and let it spread so it's not
there's no bottlenecks for it there's no place that gets contracted there's no tension in the body in which the flow is
blocked uh which can cause little bit of challenges for people just relax and so
it's it's a continual relaxation continual opening opening to the
well-being feel it fully and that uh that's kind of
continued Letting Go continue falling away and that prepares a person for the
second J which which we'll talk about in the next when might pick up
again and um and
uh and so built into this so what tends to happen when that first jna gets
strong is that um the the joy Factor can predominate but the happiness
factor is still there as well and so these two together they're kind of like a combination of joy and happiness that
arise together but it is possible to also distinguish them and um and the
distinction is that the happiness is more um I like the word sublime it's
more calm it's more settled it's more content content uh whereas the the pity has kind
of the mind is a little bit brightened and excited by it um with the happiness
the Mind actually quiets that even more there's a pervasive feeling of
well-being more than a pervasive feeling of inspiration or little bit of excited
Joy so uh these are the five factors and uh they can be very minor and and you
don't but and you don't have to be in Janna to have these present and there's
an art to recognizing uh even if they're here very subtle in an ordinary mind
where you're maybe somewhat distracted preoccupied there's a way of discovering that these are already here in some way
and um and you're allowed to feel it to support you to to um to uh get absorbed
to get into the meditation to let for temporarily let your everyday concerns
preoccupations uh uh uh Fall Away and the it's that sometimes called the
happiness that leads to more happiness the joy that leads to more joy is to feel even the subtle feelings of calm or
well-being that begins to come as you meditate there's an art not to cling to
it not to try to make something happen but to register and let it kind of be
massaged or o open to it and supports you to let go of
your everyday orientations preoccupations just to be
here so um next week I'll be back at uh the retreat center and uh
IRC uh for some more private event we're doing down there and then uh I'll be
back in uh the following week and Matthew Bren silver will be coming next week and uh I think that'll be quite
refreshing to have him uh as an interlude and uh and then I'll be back
and then we'll following week we'll do the second J and the idea is to spend a
week on the next three so so that you can have some sense of what these are
about and I thank you for attending and listening and practicing together and I
very much look forward to being back in about 10 days 9 10
days so thank you and um