so for those who are just arriving my name is May It's so nice to be here with
you especially on this beautiful Sunday And I'd like to start with a poem
So this is called uh Lasu's peace prayer It goes like
this If there is to be peace in the world there must be peace in the nations
If there is to be peace in the nations there must be peace in the
cities If there is to be peace in the cities there must be peace between
neighbors If there is to be peace between neighbors there must be peace in the
home And if there is to be peace in the home there must be peace in the heart
So there's a lot of suffering in the world right now Uh and there's many things that can
be done when there's suffering in the world Many uh external actions um
volunteering donations having bridgebuilding conversations lots of uh
really important things that can be done uh and uh I don't think it should be
underestimated the importance of uh cultivating a heart of
peace If there's to be peace in the world there must be peace in the
heart Uh one way I like to think of it is that uh wars and famines they don't
typically happen because a of a shortage of land or resources Uh they happen
because of greed hatred and delusion in the human mind As uh Nizaradarta uh Nisaga Darta
Maharaj said uh if you want to save the world you must first save the world from
yourself So uh this morning we'll be talking about a very particular way of cultivating a heart of peace Uh we'll be
talking about kanti or patience So the Buddha described patience as uh
the highest virtue and yet what I found is that um not everyone knows exactly
what patience is uh or how to how to cultivate it So that's our focus for
today Um uh maybe about a month ago Gil spoke about patience here for the Sunday
talk Uh but it's such an important topic that I thought it might be useful to return to it and approach it from a
slightly different angle So that's what we we'll be doing today Uh and maybe to
begin uh let's start with the basics So uh by one definition patience is the capacity to
accept or tolerate delay trouble or suffering without getting angry or
upset So it's this ability to uh bear difficulty calmly uh to be steadfast
despite adversity Uh one of my Zen teachers used to say uh
the first element of patience is a willingness to
suffer And this actually makes a lot of sense because the uh the Latin root of
uh of patience is pi and pi literally means to suffer So embedded right in the
word we have this um uh this uh willingness to rest in
difficulty right at the heart of the word patience So I found that one common
misassociation with patience is that it it involves gritting our teeth and bearing it kind of bearing our
circumstances Um but true patience it's not uh it's
not a tightening against our circumstances Uh rather uh it's the
ability to be with difficulty uh while maintaining a wholesome attitude And
this was pretty novel for me to really understand that patience is the the ability to be with what's difficult
while maintaining a wholesome attitude Uh so how then do we cultivate
patience how do we actually of bring it forth in our life uh so it could be easy
to think that uh the way to patience is uh by getting rid of impatience Uh but
that that is not actually the case Um the way to patience is actually through
impatience It's by studying impatience uh that we grow the heart of patience
So um so let's zoom in on this a bit Uh let's take a look a closer look at
impatience and that'll be a lot of our study today is looking at how impatience functions because so much of cultivating
patience is looking at its opposite Uh so one thing I found through a closer
look at uh impatience is it's it's actually the coming together of a
variety of different factors of mind And what I found is that uh when impatience
arises it's always coming along with a companion And the companion is craving
or aversion wanting or not wanting So impatience is always arising in tandem
with wanting or not wanting They kind of uh we could say they walk hand in hand
So um maybe narrowing in on this a little further uh we can look at the way
impatience arises with wanting So uh let's say something obstructs us from
getting what we want Um let's say we want a cup of coffee or a bathroom break
or a better job you know whatever it is Um if anything gets in our way from
getting that thing impatience can quite easily take hold So typically we want uh
rapid and unhindered access to that which we we desire and if anything gets
in the way of that then impatience can re supreme Uh this is one of the ways it
functions Uh on the flip we can look at the same pattern with not wanting with
aversion So when we experience something unpleasant uh something we don't want uh maybe pain
in the body uh a dismal mood an illness um sadness
loss when that happens often impatience then urges us to rush through
it Uh so this is one factor of impatience wanting or not wanting but
there's one additional element um that really makes impatience what it is and
that's the perception of time this sense that um I can't bear
this another moment or I need what what I want needs to happen now
uh the thing that I don't want it needs to stop now And there's this sense of
urgency associated with this perception of time So with wanting maybe we could
say the the universal refrain of impatience are we there yet you know
it's just like sitting in the backseat of our life you know totally oblivious of the beautiful passing scenery and
just obsessed about getting to the hotel pool right this is like um that uh that
tendency towards impatience like are we there yet are we there yet or with not
wanting um impatience can have this timebased element of like you know when
will that annoying sound go away or I can't bear this headache another moment
or you know how much longer until this meeting ends I imagine all of you have have had the experience of looking at a
clock over and over until you know you get to the end of whatever that unpleasant event is So um so we have
this these this element of wanting or not wanting plus the perception of time and boom impatience arises
So um so what's kind of interesting about impatience and maybe we could say this
for um uh many challenging states of mind is um they tag along a little bit
like a shadow uh in the way that they they often go unnoticed So um when pat impatience is
present uh often we don't even realize it's there So our very first task for
practicing with impatience for getting to know impatience is recognition Just
simple recognition that it's there Um and as we start recognizing it
uh starting to see it when it's there uh it can be kind of kind of surprising to
see uh what a common visitor it can be like it it appears while driving in
traffic uh during conversations with others uh while stuck with a slow internet
connection while waiting in line at the grocery Uh the other morning I pulled my
breakfast out of the microwave and rather than waiting for it to cool down I chose to burn my tongue on molten
oatmeal you know so it's like um this sense of like urgency or you I want my
breakfast now Um so um so impatience can be really
pervasive Um so whe whether it's mild impatience or strong impatience our task
uh is just to recognize it just to see it Um and as as humbling uh as our
impatience is um these minor league occasions uh they
provide opportunities to grow uh grow the muscle of patience uh before it's
needed in more difficult circumstances So uh we can't really expect patience to
be present for us um in situations where we're we're enduring really difficult
hardship if we haven't already cultivated it with lesser challenges So um so in order to to be
able to say patiently endure something really difficult like the loss of a
loved one um we need to start small If we go to the gym uh it doesn't it
doesn't work so well to start with the 100 pound weights Works a lot better to start with the five pound weights So
same story with patience Uh we we start by working with small situations of
impatience and we grow that muscle gaining the capacity to be patient uh in
more challenging circumstances So when I was in my my early 20s
um I was presented with a 100 pound weight and I had to learn the hard way
So um uh I think I was I was 24 years old and I went to bed a perfectly
healthy young person and I woke up the next day not a healthy young person and
I was very sick Um it was kind of like my digestion had stopped functioning Uh
and uh I went and saw the doctor The doctor didn't know what was happening I saw another doctor that doctor didn't
know what was happening Saw a doctor after doctor You know days went by weeks went by months went by and I started to
get pretty impatient about getting better Really wanted to get better Did
not feel good So during this time uh I went to go see a teacher a dharma
teacher in the East Bay and I told this teacher about how unbearable this circumstance was how difficult it was Um
and he said something to me that I that that I found uh really
[Music] um that it changed me He said something
that changed me And he
said uh he said uh how would you be with this if it were
to be this way forever how would you be with this if it were to be this way forever
so of course this uh this prompt it wasn't to provoke future tripping or
fear or anything like that but the way that it functioned was that it undercut
my aversion I realized if I were to be with this forever I would have to accept
it now Otherwise I'm just going to burn in the um the fire of my own aversion
Uh so if I were to be with this forever I would have to accept it And as you
know uh impatience arises with aversion If aversion drops out impatience drops
out So uh so over time I found a way to be with this experience uh with greater
patience And of course there were times where I wasn't patient you know where impatience
was present and that's when I would do this practice That's when I would recognize impatience when it was there
Uh and then I do the next step And the next step once we recognize impatience
it's to feel it in the body What's it actually feel like uh to be impatient is
there a tightness in the chest maybe a clenching in the jaw heat in the face
like can you get to know it almost like an ecologist in a new ecosystem like
what is the human experience of impatience like so as we do this as we become
curious about what impatience feels like we can become so and this is this is
true for any uh difficult state uh if we become really attuned to what it feels
like in the body the next time it arises we know it right away So we're much less
likely to get hijacked by it And I've seen with some states that really used
to be difficult for me Sometimes the moment they arise because I've spent so
much time feeling them in the body I can just drop it It's like you know no need
to get hijacked by this because I see it I I've really gotten to know it So this
is one of the advantages to to really feeling these uh these challenging experiences in the
body So okay So once we've recognized our impatience we felt in the body uh
then we can call on wisdom or compassion So um we might bring in some wisdom by
reflecting on impermanence So remembering that whatever this is whatever is happening uh this too shall
pass And this too will pass in time now And and in the meantime even as
it seems to persist uh often what we experience as fixed kind of es and flows
like there's changes to it And really being able to sense those eb the es and
flows it can begin to um to loosen our
sense of of fixity that fixed perception that you know it's like this and it's going to stay like this for too long and
I don't want this Kind of get to see some um uh kind of cracks in our fixed
perception as we really observe change
So when we uh when we really begin to see how quickly things pass and that
often they pass on their own without our valition um wisdom begins to emerge and this can
soften patience or impatience excuse me This can um this clear seeing uh can
soften impatience So that's a wisdom view uh we
can also after recognizing and feeling impatience in the body uh we might bring
in some compassion So uh the way that compassion functions is that it it
softens impatience with its warmth It softens impatience with its warmth So in
the same way where if maybe there's a little kid that's having a tantrum a parent can approach that child and uh
speak to that child in a soothing way and really comfort it be kind and gentle with it Um we can do that to the um the
child within the impatient child within Uh often there's uh there's just
a vulnerable part of oursel uh that longs for things to be otherwise So can
we meet uh that part of our heart uh
with kindness with gentleness with compassion and uh sometimes uh sometimes
this softening uh the softening that compassion provides uh it reveals that
impatience is covering up deeper hurts So we might find that below our
impatience um emotions like sadness or loneliness
or grief may be underneath Uh just asking for our loving attention
So one time I was uh I was walking through the flower garden uh at Green
Gulch Farm and Zen Center up in Marin and I ran into an old friend
there This was a friend that I had uh I had trained with as a Zen monk at
Tasahara many years before And uh so it was really love to love it uh lovely to
see him and he was there with his daughter who was maybe I don't know four years old at the time So she's very cute
and small and brighteyed Uh and so my friend and I stopped started talking a little and we weren't talking long Um
but uh his daughter started to she she was fine at first maybe I don't know digging around in a flower bed or
something Uh but it wasn't long before uh she started feeling like this
conversation is done it's time to go Come on Dad Um and she
expressed this in the way that kids do Uh which is not by saying "Oh I'd like
to go now." Uh I think I think it began with you maybe pulling her dad's pant leg and then some you know whining and
maybe a little yelling and kicking and it was one of these moments where I just
felt uh awe at parenthood and this sort of like how is it that parents don't eat
their young like it's just extraordinary Um
uh and so I just am uh wondering how my friend's going to respond to this And uh
and I was just I was just amazed by how tender and patient and gentle he was
with her He knelt down on one knee just spoke to her really soothingly kindly just so so soft so
gentle Uh so we all have this capacity to meet the impatient child
within with that same kindness that same compassion that same gentleness
Now uh ironically um after watching my f
my friend respond in this way for a little while um I was so amazed by his
composure I I said something like like Kogan like how do you do it you are so
patient with her and he raised an eyebrow and with a ry smile he said "You don't know what it's
like in here." And that really stuck with me
because I think a lot of times um we don't feel patient we don't feel kind Um
uh but what's the next best thing uh and the the way that this friend uh
was with his daughter even though he didn't feel patient he enacted patience
Uh and so uh in a lot of ways um our practice is about uh not leaking our
defilements onto others to not leak our greed hatred and
delusion onto others Uh and I'm not saying that we should never share how
we're feeling right uh there's a time and a place where it's tremendously skillful to express our impatience or
our dissatisfaction or whatever the feeling is Um certainly so And I think
there are often a lot of times uh when we don't need to express those things
and when we don't need to leak them onto others in a way that's unskillful So I just I thought that this friend's
uh enactment of patience was such a a beautiful expression of um of being in
the world aligned with one's values even if the heart isn't quite there yet Even if the heart isn't uh
uh isn't going along with the intention
So there's um there's another point of discernment that I'd like to clarify
regarding uh patience and it's that uh patience
shouldn't be conflated with complacency or
non-action Uh some people think that when um it's like oh well if I'm if I'm patient if I accept things as they are
uh then there's no energy to act then we just don't do anything Um uh
so I don't know a few weeks ago uh I did a one-day sitting and it was uh one of
those days where the mind was just everywhere Uh uh there was tons of
thinking and so um it was just all it was a lot of bringing the mind back to
the breath letting go of thoughts coming back to the breath letting go of thoughts coming back to the breath over and over and over again I probably
brought the mind back a thousand times that day Would I have preferred a quiet
mind yes definitely Um but fortunately
um there was some level of patience present with the mind as it was Um I wasn't uh striving to get a different
mind Um I wasn't uh longing for it to be otherwise Um I was just with the mind uh
as it was and continuing to bring it back So So even though there was
patience present um it didn't mean that I was complacent with the thinking mind
It didn't mean I just went "Oh it doesn't matter if I'm thinking I'm just I'm gonna stop trying." No I kept
bringing the mind back But I did it with a heart of
patience So um so tremendous effort can still be made uh from the heart of
patience from the heart of acceptance um uh when I was really sick uh I was
able to accept what was happening to me but that didn't mean that I stopped seeking medical
help right there was still action uh that came from that place of of patience
from that place of acceptance um yeah so so I share this because uh a
lot of people wonder if fear or anger aren't motivating us uh how do we
respond to injustice this you know uh there's no fuel to act
Uh and sometimes fear and anger is all we've got Uh and we do our best with that with that Um but uh we don't
actually need fear uh or anger to drive our
activity There's actually a much more powerful force for wholesome activity in
the world and that's the power of love
Profoundly powerful action can come from a place of
love As the Buddha said "Hatred never ceases by hatred but by love alone is
healed." This is the ancient and eternal law
Yeah So you don't need to worry that impatience will uh render you uh
ineffective or complacent You maybe uh maybe it's exactly what you need uh to
have the stability and the resilience um to act
most powerfully So patience can really serve
us uh can serve us in some really significant ways
uh and amazing things can become possible uh when we have access to patience So I
sometimes uh I sometimes think about Nelson Mandela as this really just
incredible uh figure um that personified patients in such a a magnificent way So
as most of you know Nelson Mandela is the um anti-aparid activist who spent 27 years
imprisoned in Rob uh at Robin Island um in really harsh conditions uh tremendous
isolation and who you know eventually became the president of South Africa Uh and I was reading a while ago
about uh what the conditions were like there uh on Robin Island And just a few
a few things I learned I learned that he was allowed to have uh one visitor a
year for a 30 minute period He could exchange no more than
one letter every six months So of course this is just the tip
of the iceberg right uh the tip of the iceberg of what he experienced and what was so
um so beautiful for me uh was to read
that he related to his imprisonment as quote an education in patience and
perseverance An education in patience and perseverance
So whatever difficulty we might find ourselves in uh can we meet it as an
education in patience and we we all have this capacity for a heroic
patience amidst uh amidst even even life's um most significant hardships
And we all have this capacity to rise above our aversion uh our craving and really meet life as
it is And when we meet um when we meet our
difficult circumstances with this type of patient nobility uh we're not the
only ones who benefit right you know our our children our co-workers
uh everyone we encounter can benefit from our peace Uh and this peace um it it doesn't
require perfection Um uh you know when patience is present
great And when impatience is present we recognize it we feel it And when we do
that um it opens the door for wisdom and compassion to free the
heart And what's um what's amazing is that uh we can even
learn to be patient with impatience itself So we don't have to wait for
impatience to leave before patience can arise
So I'll um I'll close with a very short quote from the Daly
Lama and it's said that the Daly Lama was once asked uh what's the fastest way
to enlightenment he gave a one-word answer
So when we are faced with crossing the great flood of samsara
uh we could think that patience uh patience provides us with a raft and a
sail for crossing the flood Uh and when patience is
mature we might even enjoy the ride So let's sit together
[Music]
So thank you for your kind attention your patient attention Uh we'll now have a little
time for any questions or comments So anything that might have
come to mind for you you can share It doesn't have to be a
question Any reflections
i just have to say love is the answer Oh okay
It's worth saying twice Okay I just have to say love is the answer Thank you
Thanks
Scott I just wanted to express my appreciation
for the image of leaking defilements That's very powerful Yeah
Yeah there's something that feels different to you know to really recognize a defilement in oneself to
recognize our craving or aversion and then to consider you know is this useful to share um how might I share this in a
skillful way and to communicate that in an upright way um which might be very skillful versus leaking defilements uh
so um some people think oh well either you know you know I should never share
my defilements But there's a time and a place for it Um but what happens more often than not is
just that we're leaking them which um doesn't work so well Yeah Thank you
Scott Oh and please share your name if you're willing Yeah sure
Um my name is Craig and my question is in those moments where we notice that
there's anger and rage and and kind of pushing away what is that what are some
next steps you can take to kind of reorient towards love in those moments
yeah So um uh something that's kind of useful is the the um the practice that I
offered for working with impatience uh is also effective for any other difficult emotion So if anger or rage
are present recognizing that's what's happening because often I mean often we
don't even know we're angry when we're angry you know we're just hijacked by it Um so to recognize it to feel it in the
body Um and something that's really helpful as we do this is to meet it with acceptance We're not suppressing the
anger and we're not acting out on the anger We're just allowing it to move through and we're not feeding the story
line Often anger is um fueled by the narrative So by landing in the body
feeling the body that's um starting to like um kind of cut off the fuel to the
fire Um so we're letting go of the thoughts being in the body uh and grounding in the body In that way um as
it starts to diminish the fuel for the fire we can be able to become more grounded more stable more at ease moving
us more in the direction of love Um so um so yes sometimes people think that we
need to get rid of our anger or suppress our anger Um but it's really uh it's
going through anger you know we need to allow it to be felt I mean often anger is uh just trying to communicate
something like a boundary You know don't step on me
Thank you
My name is Jill Um my question is only recently I've
started thinking that patience and impatience are not
opposites It's way more complicated than that But I can't sort out what I mean So
do you have a thought on
that maybe could you say a little bit more about what you're sensing into there even if you can't quite fully
articulate it i I think I've spent a lot of time
thinking patience and impatience were two sides of the same coin but I
think that's been really misguided Um and
um so maybe it's just we need you I need to relabel impatience instead because I
in the in the labeling it sounds like they should be opposites but
um I'm I'm just not sure I'm trying to work it out And I thought it you replace
one with the other and it's not that simple right especially you know if we
can be patient with impatience if they can coexist Um so here's one way
that we can think of patience and impatience as uh not opposites one way
that we could think of them a little differently Um uh often forces of mind like um our
craving and aversion um uh it's not that they're evil forces
in us They're trying to do something good for us You they're trying to make us happy you know Um you know uh I might
feel like like gosh I really just have to have that piece of cake I have to have the chocolate cake Um so that's
your craving speaking Um so it's trying to make me happy It's just a little bit
misguided about how to do that So most of our desire and aversion it's really
trying to do its best for us You know it thinks that you know yelling at our spouse is what'll make us feel better
Um so it's just a little misguided And so our impatience you know that's fueled
by that wanting and not wanting um you know it's the mind and heart trying to do its best with a difficult
circumstance um and just being a little misguided Uh in the same way um patience is also
trying to help us be happy So we might think of them as both forces of mind
that are trying to make us happy Uh one is just uh a little off track So if we
think of it that way um we're not seeing them as polar opposites Um but um uh two
different uh attempted paths of happiness Um one just being misguided
Very helpful Thank you Yeah And maybe I think this is the last
one we'll have time for Hey I'm Colin Uh I have a similar
question Maybe you can help me uh form Um I guess I'm trying to figure out where preferences kind of fit in this
like like when you were sick you know you you said like maybe you maintain
that preference to not be sick but you still were able to be patient
Yeah There's a a famous Zen poem that starts with um the great way is not
difficult for those without
preference So that's the Shinshin Ming Uh so um what happens with our
preferences so maybe I should start by saying uh preferences are not the
problem Clinging to our preferences that's the problem So it's quite natural
as humans um that we experience certain things as pleasant and certain things as
unpleasant And so naturally we gravitate to the pleasant and um away from the
unpleasant Um and of course for each of us what's pleasant and unpleasant is different I might love strawberries you
might hate strawberries Um uh so that that natural gravitation um that kind of
magnetic pull in one way one direction or the other um shape like becomes
preferences right it it turns into what we like and dislike Um when we start to
cling really tightly to that that's when suffering occurs Um so we can hold our
preferences like this and that's going to feel a lot
different Like if I did this for another like 10 minutes my hand would really hurt Um or we can hold our preferences
like that So you know so we don't get what we want No big deal right so um so it's our
relationship to the preference Thank you Yeah Welcome Thank you all for
your attention So lovely to um uh uh
that you would all take your time maybe your day off today uh to come and
cultivate a beautiful heart This is such a valuable thing to do uh with your time
and your life uh to look within uh so you can help all of those around you So
may all beings feel the benefit of our practice today together so we can have a
world where beings are happy healthy safe and at ease May all beings know
happiness and the causes of happiness
[Music]
Thank you And feel free to stick around for tea time Take care everyone