welcome welcome good evening nice to see you
all so tonight I'd like to talk a little bit and in a way of just like throwing
some seeds out and in some way maybe the seeds will take root and germinate and Sprout into
something and maybe they won't or maybe maybe it'll take some
time maybe they have to sit in the darkness for some time or
maybe uh there has to be more rain or more sun or something like this until the seeds
sprout so just this idea of I'm doing this with my hand kind like just throwing out seeds and uh see if they
land and produce something partly I offer
this just as an encouragement to maybe uh to see what's being said here and
maybe just feel into it and if it feels like I don't know can you just hold that
I don't know can you just hold that and take what's helpful and just leave
behind what's not helpful and I want to start by talking
about thoughts like what are thoughts like what are they for me this
is like such a fascinating topic like what are they made out out of where do
they come from I think we all know there are like these mental events that kind of like
arise and pass away there there's temporary appearances that just show up on
occasion but it happens that they show up more often than just occasion I'm fascinated by this that U I saw that
there was a study that said that people have up to 60,000 thoughts a day I'm fascinated by
like is somebody going click click click one two three four five you know like how do they measure this I don't know
I'm kind of curious about this but I think actually just the act of being
curious and wanting to like count one's thoughts means that they're not lost in
them but instead they're observing them and that in itself could be really powerful
but so we have up to According to some scientists 60,000 thoughts a
day also to these same scientists between 90 and 95% of them
repetitive either because what they had earlier that day or maybe they're the same as what you had the previous
day that's a lot 90 to 95% and then 80%
of all of them are have this negative tone things should be different I should
be different why are they doing it that way it should be done this way who's responsible for this I have to go fix it
and tell them or you know all these different ways that these negative thoughts show up I'm not good enough
this isn't good enough there's cold air coming out of this vent I'm not sure
why in the winter but you know today the microphone had a little thing and HVAC
system's been a little weird it's just the way it
is so we have a lot of thoughts but there's something that
they're repetitive they're arising and passing away and like what so what are
some of the things that are these 60,000 thoughts sometimes we are worrying about
the future how am I going to handle this or maybe there's a little bit of
planning in there oh in order this thing's going to come up and so I better be prepared for it so okay I got to
remember to uh bring this to work today and tell this person that and you know
whatever it might be are these like the certain amount of planning or big uh
huge uh component of thoughts is a self judgment is this idea of like I should
be doing better or I should be better or I'm inadequate or at least I'm doing better
than that Bozo over there or maybe there's this sense of
like well why can't I be more like this person who has X Y and Z or seems to be
a b and c why can't I have a physique like this person why can't I be as smart as that
person why can't I be as um spiritually mature as such person or whatever it
might be it's amazing how much of this kind of
is part of our thoughts or also maybe part of in our fantasies sometimes I
find myself doing this a lot like H I wonder what would be like to live here you know as I'm kind of like driving
through some place or I wonder what it be like to have this job you know as I'm
interacting with different people in different uh professions like I wonder what it's like
to have that job to be a bar [Laughter]
so there's all kinds of things you know that we think about these 60,000 thoughts that we're having a day not
only are they temporary just arising and passing away but we don't control them they just
arise when they arise they leave when they leave right if we could control our
thoughts you would not need a meditation practice you would just only think about certain things and be done with it not
think about other things they're uncontrollable we're not
making them arise nobody knows why they arise nobody knows why they go away they
just do this is the nature of thoughts is that that we don't control them this
is part of the human experience it's just having thoughts arise thoughts that
we don't want thoughts that we're trying to not think
arises anyway I'm sure you've noticed
this there's also this thing about thoughts that they don't have a core
substance to them they are like insubstantial in some kind of way they
they are like clouds and rainbows you know they appear when
there's certain an example of cloud and rainbows right there certain atmospheric
conditions are there clouds arise but clouds don't have like a something in
the center that's like this core or Essence it's just a diffuse
Cloud Rainbows are the same way right they don't there isn't one thing that you could pull out and say oh okay
here's the rainbow instead it's just a an
experience a process that's arising when we could say when rain and sunlight
are there so there's this way that they have
this real insubstantiality we don't control them and they're coming and
going and it turns out that so much of the building blocks of our stories our
dramas our suffering our thoughts so these things that are ins
substantial and uncontrollable are so much are kind of creating the stories we
have about ourselves the stories we have about what is good what is bad what is
the meaning of life what I should do with my life what I shouldn't do with my
life and there's a way in which we could consider that we spend so much of our
time going from one little mini Daydream to another
is so much of what our inner life is about it's kind like being lost in these
insubstantial mental events that are coming and going
repeatedly but there's one particular way in which we sometimes these stories
or these dramas these um big uh
sufferings difficulties in our lives which all all of us
have are intimately tied up with our thoughts the thoughts we have about
what's happening the thoughts we have about what it means to me as an
individual makes me a good person makes me a bad person makes me look good makes
me look bad or maybe it's just doesn't match the
idea we have about ourselves I want to be people to think think that I'm kind and when somebody is complaining about
me it just doesn't feel good and I have to
defend myself or support myself in some kind of way with more
thoughts these insubstantial incontrollable
things there's so
much there's so much about our sense of self that is just really tied up with a
sense of our thoughts I want to talk a little bit more about this but first I want to
say a little bit about what do I mean when I talk about this sense of a
self I mean we have this Common Sense uh model this notion of what a self is we
have like there's this core there's this Essence at the center
to which you know other things happen I talk about this you know sometimes in Dhat talks I'm pointing to
this and certainly our society and the way that we're raised in um our culture
really promotes this you could even say like this whole idea of a horoscope because you're born at this
particular location this particular time you'll have these qualities and that's part of your essence or your core or you
might say well we have these personality tests Myers breaks or anog or I'm I'm
sure there's others say no no no this really is your core your
essence for me I have something uh I thought back when I was a research
scientist SP in my days in a laboratory I um was thinking like oh it doesn't feel quite right for me I don't know
what to do with myself this is a little aside I took Myers Briggs
and the it came back that oh you might want to be a spiritual teacher I thought that's so crazy I'm never going to do
say anything like that for me that's just a funny thing to think
about inconstant one worldview not knowing what our future holds
right or there's also ways in which I remember also when I was a teenager I used to love to do
this there'd be magazin and there would always be like a quiz what is your learning style and then you'd Circle
Like A or B or C then however many A's you got means your learning style is
this or what's you know whatever whatever I was measuring so we certainly have this idea
that supports this uh notion that there is this Core Essence that we are and it
can be described with a personality test or the results from some kind of a test
or something like this or our
horoscope so there's this idea that this core this Essence this um way in which
we think that there's maybe this um this quality this inherent
quality that uh we have and we say that it accumulates
these different experiences that is maybe it has these memories maybe it has
uh memories and these memories are kind of like what's part of this core but
memories are thoughts in a way there's mental events
and these are insubstantial coming and going
uncontrollable we have desires it's part of uh we might say is
the experience of having a self and for example more cookies more
well-being but those are also thoughts which are also insubstantial we have
beliefs about the meaning of life what happens after death what it means
to vote one way or
another these beliefs are also thoughts they often are a little bit quieter and
maybe perhaps hidden and not obvious but those are also just
thoughts we have knowledge maybe we're trained in a specific field but those
are often just thoughts too Concepts right the knowledge is
often Concepts things that we learn and
memorize and work with and these are just thoughts too
so there actually isn't this core or this
Essence the center doesn't exist it's a model it's a common sense
model we feel like there is but so what is there if there isn't
these uh this Essence here there's a way in which there's the
components we might say of our experience is
connected they belong to one body and brain so
they they're not happening to somebody
else but there's a way in which we might say that the sense of self is a
narrative it's a way in which there is this sewing
together of different events into a
story there's a way in which we're linking things together the
linking is happening with our thoughts the events are just happening
the memories are just happening the sensations are just happening they're
coming and going we can't control them and then we want things to make sense
and to be neat and tidy in some kind of way so a narrative gets created oh this
happened because of that but that's a
thought thoughts are insubstantial uncontrollable coming and
going and there's a way in which we say well things are connected also means that well we do
things because of other things maybe we could say that what we desire is related
to what we believe our beliefs our
thoughts maybe what we desire is a certain amount of
well-being happiness peace
freedom and then well we're doing something because we have that desire
but the way that we think that we're going to achieve this well-being or Peace and
Freedom our thoughts which are insubstantial coming
and going and we can't
control so there's all these things these beliefs
desires experiences and they're all related to each
other and there's just a way that this connected things
are you you might say or a self we might
say so that's different than having a core or an essence
it's more like well there's just maybe this Cloud
here that is a
self and then often when we hear things like this I know this certainly was the
case for me there's a certain like puzzlement like what H and there's often
some like disbelief because like I don't really just I mean of course there's a self I mean I'm here and I'm not there
and I'm this person I'm not that person what is she talking
about so when we hear these things often we have this experience of maybe um we
want to dismiss it because it runs counter to our experience it runs
counter to kind of like what Society is pointing to and promoting
and so I'm just planting seeds I'm just throwing seeds out there it's perfectly fine if they don't uh sink in and
germinate but I'll say and probably you know this too that so much about this
practice is about maybe having a sense of uh
inquiry or curiosity or investigation of
hm I don't know
maybe investigation is a factor of Awakening and this is part of what gets
investigated like what is this sense of self the sense of
identity that we have how does it feel what is it made
out of when is it really strong when does it seem like it's not so strong
when does it even feel like it's completely
absent this Spirit of inquiry this Spirit of H maybe willingness to not
completely dismiss it but just uh have some openness to the
notion that there isn't this core so this isn't so much a belief to
adopt this isn't a uh Doctrine to sign up for
instead it's a invitation to investigate be curious
about be open to and maybe you know poke around and uh
and see in feel I'm using this maybe like feel into are there times when there's a
really strong sense of self and often the way that we can tell this is when
it's countered with a other me versus you US versus them when there's a real
strong sense of oh my gosh they are a problem implicit is I am not the
problem and that's when there's a strong sense of self so just get curious how does that
feel when you have this sense of of uh righteous indignation or saying somebody else is
wrong this also means that this this me I'm right dang
it and just feel how and sometimes there's a sense of energy and maybe that
feels nice maybe to feel like I'm in the right and everybody else is wrong maybe
that feels nice in some kind of way but wowe is that
limiting it's really Li limiting cuz really what we are is so
big and expansive and this flowing and generosity and
freedom and peace and well-being as opposed to this I'm right
and now I have to make sure that everybody else knows that I'm right and now I have to make sure that people uh
treat me the right way and if they're or not then I have to push away all those thoughts that make it think that looks
might look like I'm not right or that I'm not here or
something to maybe illustrate this uh idea what is it mean to be a sense a
self like to borrow this idea that I this is terrible I didn't write it
down and his name is slipping my mind right now it's a an American philosopher I
think his name is Julian bini I want to say it'll come to me in a moment probably but I um and stealing this idea
from him he gave this in a TED Talk a number of years ago I think it's I just love
this he said let's take the idea of the notion of water H2O 2 H is one o H2O
protons two protons and a oxygen H2O we're all familiar with this
that water is this for water we don't take this word
water this concept this idea this thought of water make it be the essence
make it be the core and then we don't like stick a h here an H over here and
an oxygen an O over here and say oh okay water is H2O doesn't we don't have
like this thing water in the center that then has an h and an h and a o no of
course not it's a collection of two h's and an
O and then later we kind of like put a lay a label on top of it but it doesn't
need that label these two h's and an O H2O perfectly fine doing whatever it is
that they're doing without this label getting put on top of it it's just this
collection of atoms that are in a particular formation that we call
water or the same for way the
microphone microphones have a diaphragm in them that uh vibrate in some kind of
way and they have magnet and coils and wires and I don't know all the things
that are in mic mhone somebody does though and so a microphone is just a
collection of all these little bits of wires and coils and microphones and diaphragms and stuff like
this and when all these bits are collected in a particular way associated
in a particular way we call it a microphone but it doesn't need that name microphone it's just this collection of
things that happens to function in a particular way it it'd be perfectly fine without the
label so these are collections of
bits for a microphone that's a diaphragm and a magnet and
stuff for water it's protons and oxygen and then we later we put a label
on top of it but that label is extra sense of self is the same
thing it's a collection of we might say mental events
experiences that are just happily doing whatever they're doing and then we put a
label of self on top and we might say
well but it's is it real [Laughter]
is it not
real it's this microphone is real we're not saying it's not real
we're not saying that it's doesn't
exist and the self isn't different than anything else in the universe and I mean
like neuros science shows us that there isn't a portion of the brain like okay
there's the self right there and then psychology they often aren't talking about this I'm not a
neuroscientist nor a psychologist but so this is my understanding they're not pointing to
yeah there's all these psychological patterns or there all these uh neurochemical or reactions and then
here's the self that's you know right here and has these particular uni things they're not saying that at
all so this doesn't mean that we don't exist that would be
silly to say that that we don't exist instead we're just saying that
there isn't this nucleus this core at the center instead it's a collection
it's a process it's the cloud it's not clearly defined doesn't have
like clear edges in the way that we think it does and there's this way
that acknowledging this or being tuned into this allows for some growth and some
change allows for some sense of Freedom allows for some liquidity maybe
in the way that we think about ourselves or the way that we think about the
world that can really support
freedom and we could even say that this whole entire practice this mindfulness
practice the Insight practice concentration practice loving kindness
practice listening to Dharma talks reading Dharma books all of this we
could say all of it is point to this that our
identity is not necessarily what we think it
is and that greater Freedom goes with the um the more
uh um ease we have with this sense of
identity this sense of self that we have and we could say like Awakening
Liber a these types of things I'm move I'm doing this with my hands CU this like imagining that maybe like it's a
road that goes over here it's not quite like that but often how it gets
conveyed we could say it's just this shifting shifting of this
identity so it's not that we have to get rid of our s it's not that we have to
transmute our self into some beautiful thing it's not that we have to transcend
of self and there's spiritual teachings that point this way but this tradition
is just to notice yeah it's just not there the way that you thought it
was that's all that's all you have to do and there's this wave this
recognition often if it's been again and again and seen in a particular way this
is not something intellectual it's not something that you'll get having just hearing a dma talk
but it's a an experience then that's what brings
greater and greater Freedom this recognition like oh this
uh there's this letting go that can happen of this sense of I need to be
this way and the world needs to be that way
so one way that we can practice with this a I mean it's often on meditation
Retreats when the mind is a little bit more quiet that we start to notice all
the ways in which we're creating ourself in which we're some ways thinking
ourself into being I don't want to make this be wrong
I don't want to make this be a big gi problem this is what most humans are doing but here's just an opportunity to
think like H maybe there's another way these are things that we're just
assuming the thought or like the thoughts about the self we're just assuming there's a self there and
viewing the world viewing our experiences through that framework it turns out that that's extra
this framework is extra and one way we could work with this is just to
notice thoughts just notice your
thoughts often not so easy because we're lost in them but if you can even just
for like you know two minutes at a time and say okay I'm going to count
maybe one minute maybe 30 seconds just count like okay how many thoughts and
then you'll have like oh wait was that a thought oh that's a thought that that's thought okay then you know just but the
fact of just observing them and then it becomes easier and
easier to observe them and then we start to see their insubstantiality and uncontrollability
and then just seeing this again and again we start to see how oh they are
making this self they're creating this
self that's one way in which we might uh work with this work with this notion
that uh notion that we have that there's this
core this Essence when in fact it's just a collection of
experiences and often what's stitching them together are
thoughts which of course are insubstantial how many times have I said
that today this is my new favorite word so maybe I'll end there but maybe
before I end I'll say there's a lot that we could say about not self this is just
you know I just took one Road in there's so many different things we can say I am
not expecting that having heard this you'll be totally convinced
um and I know that the first first time I heard this teaching I kind of got
mad what are they talking about I I thought this Buddhism thing was going to be good but what is this I don't know I
just I found myself irritated and
and that's okay irritation is okay too
so I just want to offer that um take what's helpful and leave behind what's
not helpful and now maybe I'll open it up to see if
there's some questions or comments thank
you so there I mean like in to BM especially
there's a lot of talk about reincarnation so if there is no self what reincarnates I know right this
such a great question I have no idea
yeah because it almost seems to contradict yourself right you know like they talk about the five Aggregates and
then there's no self then okay it's very peaceful when you very still but then
what reincarnates I don't know if it's helpful I'll say in this tradition we
don't use this word reincarnation didn't we use rebirth with more the idea that uh what
gets reborn if such a thing exists it's impossible for me to know that uh it
would be like the momentum of some of the mental patterns that we've had or
habits or something like this the the momentum maybe but that that this is
what I can offer yeah
um had kind of a a comment but then also just to uh touch on um question you just
or or the comment you just brought up um because big part of why I started coming as well was trying to unpack this
concept of nonself and one thing I was able to gather from a talk and perhaps you know
feel free to correct me but there was a talk um uh on this about year ago Spirit
Rock and it was on the concept of no self and the thing that I gathered was that it turns out to just be a really
awkward translation um turns out in the Buddha
was saying was not that there is no self he wasn't metaphysically proving that oh
we don't exist and there is no actual self uh not that but the actual like suta and the teaching is that think look
at your thoughts observe your um your physical habits the Aggregates do you
control any of them and if you don't control them there is no self there so
the idea of self is tied up a lot with the control is what I had gathered and that's merely what the Buddha was saying
and so to meditate on non-self is to realize like we just have like a modum
of control versus a self that can control you know our thoughts and all these other things so that was actually very
helpful and it was like um but it also pays to like read more and go to these these talks that that
really clarified it for me though it was just tough translation great great thank you that's
right that at the time of the Buddha there was other spiritual teachers and they were saying oh no there's a self
and here are the characteristics of it and one of the characteristics was is that you could control it so thank you yeah and he say no no no
we don't control try it and it turns out you can't yeah uh and then just to
comment on I really appreciated the talk tonight and um one thing that I I think
is a barrier it's tough when we hear things like this is just linguistically you know we grow up and for me it's like
we there are nouns and there's verbs right to keep it very simple and nouns
are are everywhere in fact Concepts become nouns and we're like this is yeah is this and so one exercise I try to do
and it feels just impossible I occasionally try and do it is take something that comes to us as a noun but turn it
into verbs yeah like this is verbing or this chair it's actually a bunch of verbs it's chairing it's chairing yeah
what are the atoms inside or whatever we want to describe um or some you know ideological ISM that we we say is
happening like it's actually just this thing that's verbing U I found that to be helpful but it's really tough to
break I feel like every time I hear this concept that what's the essence it's uh
Linguistics is a huge barrier to it yeah very nice thank you I heard uh lee braon
want to say there are no nouns they're just slow
verbs it's kind of a playful way to think about this just slow
verbs so I was remembering about 30 years ago um the do Lama came to
Shoreline Amphitheater I don't know if anyone else was there but he gave a 4-day talk on and I wrote it down the
concept of self is empty of objective reality and I understood the first five
minutes of the four days um yeah I wasn't I wasn't ready for that but what
you were describing was something I kind of stumbled on to about 5 minutes into tonight's sit
which was that what I do about thoughts when I'm meditating is I energize them I
think it's when I do that that I turn them into
self and there's a sensation when I'm energizing them and if I'm paying
attention it's not pleasant so I have a motive for not doing that anymore and then sometimes I'm you know supposed to
be meditating so I shouldn't have thought so instead of pushing them I'm trying to stop them and that's
unpleasant in a different way uh and what I was trying tonight was just stuff would arise and it's not like
that's the intermission between the good meditating um that's doing it right and
I would just greet these thoughts with love and would be like sit next to them in the sun on a park bench and hear what
they have to say and then and then they go away and it was um it was quite
lovely thank you can you say a little bit what you mean when you say
energizing the thoughts yeah so the thought is telling me this and then this and then he said
that um and it's like there's this other part of me that's going for sure for sure and then actually this other thing
yeah and it's as if I I get involved with it yeah yeah getting involved I
kind of like the word get tangled up in them somehow yeah yeah great thank you
thank you Phil
anybody else have a comment or something they'd like to say I have I back
here I'm super new here so I don't know much about the Traditions um but I was wondering what
your thoughts are on prayers as
thoughts can you say a little bit more prayers is thoughts um because it's not
about yourself it's about um can you hold the microphone
just a little bit closer thank you yeah I mean it's not necessarily a replay of
what's happened to you um it's not commentary necessarily about you
but it is about what you would like or what your intention
is so I know very little about prayers but I This Is My
Idea um is that praying is
um there's still mental events and it's about
uh like a wish for something or an intention for something is that true
would you say yeah I mean I would have called it an intention yeah yeah so in some ways it is related to yourself in
that it's like an intention that I wish for world peace for example or I wish
you know for everybody to have enough food whatever it might be that uh it's um related um wait so your question is
about the relationship between prayers and thoughts or prayers and well when
you talked a a lot about um thoughts they seem to be very
inwardly directed or about your self or about how you relate to the
world but sometimes your thoughts are not about yourself yeah that's true the majority
of them are self-referential and I don't know what happens in people's prayers so maybe
they're not self-referential there I imagine many of them are though that you know I am
praying for something in particular and there's this fact that I want this so that X Y and Z and the so that part is
often uh related to somebody's wishes and desires
um so there are thoughts of like okay so um um the pasta is going to be done in
two minutes so maybe I should put the sauce in now so that it's done at the same time as the pasta right has nothing
to do with actually you know ourself and that's just um thoughts that are just
arising and passing away and solving the present moment what's arising or what's being
experienced at that moment so those aren't self-referential and
they're not a problem is this helpful at all what I'm saying here I'm I'm getting a
little lost
um it's just that you know when you talked about thoughts it was like these are not yourself right and I kept
thinking well of course those are not myself because that's not I wasn't thinking like myself had nothing to do
with those thoughts does that make sense like I have a friend with
cancer and I hope she heals and I hope her
treatments work yes and I pray for her health but that has nothing to do with
me or how I would relate it to me so this is what I mean
by thoughts that don't have to do with self at all
are you sure yeah I feel pretty confident about
that then [Music] um yeah so I'm trying to feel into the
best way um to talk about
this there's a way in which
maybe I'll just use this uh language in which we get uh Tangled Up no is that
that's not the right word
um who is it or what is it that's wishing for your friend to heal
what what what what is what is it who is it what is that experience of wishing
your friend to heal that's maybe the
question and this doesn't have a easy answer this is uh sometimes a question
that people work with for a long time because they come up with one thing and
they go oh wait no that's not quite it but it's it can be interesting to just explore well what is it
exactly and it's helpful to say this word what what is what is this what is this
wishing for my friend to heal beautiful wish
what what is a wish what is a prayer is that the question
or like what's what's where is it originating from where is it what what is it coming out
of and you would say not the self no this is something to
investigate what is is there uh what's inside here that FS that's fuel
that that's giving rise to this
wish it's not an easy answer it's not something that you're going to find this moment or if you do you might but then
you can just say am might continue to work with it or something like this Love
Like Love there you go love is nice
is love
self what is love combination of stuff it's a combin
yeah it's a little bits of stuff I guess yeah yeah that we call love
yeah love it's
nice so with that maybe we'll close here I'd love for you all to have a
lovely rest of the evening thank you all