good hello everyone welcome and welcome
to this the end of this week on the pleasure aspect of
samadi and one of the things to consider when you're interested in
somebody is that as you meditate uh
to there's some there's value in taking in
absorbing whatever healthy sense of pleasure is
present and to become wise over time what forms of pleasure support uh the settling the
calming support uh our mind and body feeling a sense of stability
we become in the we're in the present moment awareness is in the present
moment in a stable way often our attention
is agitated or flighty quick to disappear wander off
with our thoughts our preoccupations
sometimes even if we are in the present moment it's flighty or agitated because of
anxiety and we might be very much in the present moment hyped up in the present
moment where every sound is a of concern and and um and the stability of the mind
is lost in the constant searching out am I
okay or it might be that we're not so stable because we have expectations or Ambitions around
meditation and we're riding every moment kind of breathlessly to see you
know you know how to get further so to find the joys the
pleasures which support a calming a
stabilizing a quieting of the mind and
body and um so often in beginning of a meditation I
emphasize relaxing the Buddha's way of doing the
same maybe with somewhat the same effect is to emphasize a
calming a calming of the body calming of the mind and the calming the difference is
that calming maybe goes a little deeper than
relaxing it's also calming might be more more of a
pervasive of influence on our system than relaxing
which might be just relaxing the shoulders or the belly particular muscles but to calm the system to calm
the nervous system and then to see if there's any
pleasure in that calmness any pleasure in the
relaxing any pleasure in being here and now any pleasure in being connected to
the body any pleasure in how we're
aware in a sense the deepening Som
is a wonderful joining together of the body and
mind so the mind
is in Harmony and in connection and in cooperation with the body and vice
versa and so how we're aware is very important for
that sometimes I think of my body as being shy or
and it appreciates when the Mind approaches it with a relaxed gentle
awareness un forceful undemanding
unjudged and sometimes I think of my mind as um an
overactive engine that really appreciates when the
body receives it so the Mind attention can rest with the
body so in this way mind and body come into Harmony and that feels Pleasant
that feels good might even be a sense of Joy so
to gently close your eyes with the eyes closed
feel your posture from the inside out and feel it the way that you feel
it feeling is kind of the mind and the the feeling that the
sensations we have is kind of like the body so to feel the body with
a soft mind
gentle mind and to adjust the
body to be a body and posture conducive to
attention and
calm and in this coming into harmony of the Mind and
Body the Mind directs the body to take a few long slow deep
breaths the body provides great more Sensations more
connection for the mind to be aware
of and the place where Sensations [Music] occur is the same place as we're
sensing and that's the meeting place of the mind and
body and let that meeting be calm maybe
gentle light
and as you exhale to let there be a calming of the
body maybe a pervasive sense of like a
wave of calm traveling through the
body softening the muscles the tense the tensing the
bracing
letting the breathing return to
normal and taking some time to feel your body almost like you're checking in with
your body with a wide right angle
lens and just very relaxedly take in absorb
in the sensations of the body throughout the
body without searching or trying to do it
right whatever way the body reveals itself a wide angle lens for your body
for
as you exhale an ordinary
exhale let there be a calming wave being carried by the
exhale a calming wave through the mind
a settling of the
Mind perhaps are calming on the edges of the
body
softening maybe a calming on the edges of your heart the edges of the feelings
emotions you're feeling
a softening on the
edges and then feeling
sensing whatever is Pleasant that feels like it's part of this
meditation
practice The Simple Pleasures of settling sensing being
present the pleasure of being more embodied
maybe there's a very subtle hum or glow or vibrations through your
body somewhere in your body that
feels like a settling like a like a pleasant abiding Here and Now
and then within
that becoming aware of the breathing as if breathing is a gentle or
maybe not so gentle movement within a wider
field atmosphere of
calm pleasantness
and being aware of the body breathing in a light way gentle
way but also in a committed way devoted
way without any strain
the Mind meets breathing softly
gently and the body receives the mind so it can rest in the body be at
ease know it's okay to soften and relax
into the present moment
breathing and for whatever pleasure there is however
subtle maybe on the
inhale this inhal is like a drinking or breathing in throughout the body that
pleasure and the exhale is further spreading through the body
whatever pleasantness whatever feels good and
about being here
meditating
e
for for
feeling the pleasure taking in and registering in your
body whatever is Pleasant about breathing and attending to the breath
being in the body letting it absorbing it spreading
it as if there's a gentle
attitude of yes maybe even the subtle word
yes maybe even a small
smile supported by this yes to being with the breathing
for
e
for for
being aware of the diffuse
broad feeling of being here in your
body Maybe the way that Cal or
pleasure might not be localized to particular
place but more spread quietly throughout the
body easy to
overlook but which is support
for steadying the Mind Here and
Now with a breathing at the
middle
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to take a few moments to feel whatever way you
can a pervasive pervasive sense of the
body that the body has three dimensions
it's has width and
depth into which there can be a glowing feeling
of calm or subtleness
or quiet even in the middle of noise and at
your
ation to feel the body
widely almost as if there is
a a glow of attention that goes beyond the body
and may it be that your glow of care glow of Love or kindness
Goodwill travels like a
Radiance like a gentle light or a soft
warmth with no specific Focus but except to gently
touch all things as it glows and flows outward
into the world touching the
world with kindness with kind
attention the warmth of kindness and imagine that light of
kindness the glow the warmth spreads far and wide
carrying with it good will for all
beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may this these wishes spread outwards in all the ways
possible so that other people know they're not alone to know
that there are people who care and are kind
let us be forces of kindness in this
world may we be friends with everyone
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this
fifth Friday the Friday the fifth day of looking at the pleasure of
somebody that to enter into
somebody and really is deeply supported by being attuned to
pleasure the pleasure that comes with meditation not the pleasure that we can
get by having really wonderfully soft
clothes to meditate in or the most perfect sensuous cushion to sit
on but rather the kind of pleasure that begins to radiate or flow from the
inside out and as we start being sensitive and
attuned to the pleasure of the simple very simple pleasure of maybe being
calmer and it might be a relative or relative in that relative in that we're
little bit calmer than we relief pleasure and the hope that it
provides it might be that we feel a little bit more at ease in ourselves at
ease with what is difficult and that sense of little bit more ease or ease is
Pleasant it might be that um that uh there's a calm that begins spreading
through the body or a feeling of being stable uh after being agitated feeling
like we're not going anywhere we're settling down more and more into
ourselves there could be that um there begins to be some Joy or
Delight there could be some um feeling of ease in the breathing I
think one of the great experiences that really was uh very meaningful for me
when I was quite young and beginning to meditate was discovered um a breath that
breathing that was free that was had its own ease it breathing was breathing
itself and sitting quietly in meditation or having tea or something and just
feeling this complete freedom in the breath to breathe itself before that I would never have
imagined I thought my breathing was relatively free that I wasn't involved in it but there were so many ways in
which my mental and emotional life was somehow uh involved with the breathing
and have all that settled down enough so that the physical breathing was just breathing itself felt like such a great
pleasure so there's many kinds of Pleasures that can come with meditation
and uh and some of them really feel like they're healthy like they're beneficial that they're supportive because they
feel wholesome they feel like they're good for us to feel and so we
don't uh tighten up or we don't bore down on it we don't try to Pump It Up we
don't try to uh be selective about it to be like okay this is the one this is the pleasure to really focus on and build up
but rather we kind of trust it we absorb it we let it register in our system and
uh in particular I find very useful is the kind of very subtle pleasure or
maybe joy that can feel like it's pervasive through the body and um becoming more and more
embodied more and more present in our whole body is phenomenally useful for
subat uh when people try to get concentrated only as a mental exercise
they they often they can get certain kind of concentration and certain kind of satisfaction from
it but in the bigger picture it's not so useful because it's not part of a
movement towards becoming more peaceful more settled more free and there's
something about opening up and settling into the full body and feeling the
goodness of that and the pleasure of that there's pleasure in breathing so
there's all kinds of pleasures and so each person is going to find their own but there's something about the mind
that it's more mind is more interested in being present if it's enjoying it if
there's pleasure and uh and certainly we can
develop a lot of mindfulness strong mindfulness being in the present moment with things that are unpleasant and
that's valuable when we have to but um the um
and the um um but it just makes it easier for and
nicer for the mind to want to be there to become partners with the body partners with the meditation so that the
Mind begins to gather the Mind begins being really interested yes this is good
this is where I want to be some people might complain that this is hedonistic and um it's uh it can be if
that that's the purpose is to only really just um uh Savor or indulge in
the pleasures of meditation but it it's not meant to be that it's meant to be able to dip into
drop into uh a state of health state of well-being state of Harmony that uh the
kind of pleasure that comes when uh we're at ease in a deep peaceful way
when we're not in conflict and not agitated not chasing things are running away from things and not judging and and
uh making commentary about everything happening but the whole psychophysical system begins kind of come into kind of
very healthy place I think of somadi as
health and uh and it feels good it feels Pleasant to pleasure to it and uh and it
leading Us in the direction of becoming good people leading Us in the direction to become kind more compassionate more
caring more intelligent more attuned people attuned to the world attuned to ourselves attuned to others somat
provides a tremendous amount of benefit for how we're going to walk into the world if we um uh if we kind of shift
the whole way in our stance or attitude in Buddhism Samar is the means
for Liberation to become free and uh to become free of suffering
is one of the great purposes goals of a human life and
it's a great goal for supporting other people great goal of compassion and so
to know and discover for oneself how thoroughly and fully we can become free of suffering uh makes it possible for us
to be attuned or attentive to how that's a possibility for other people and so
we're not uh overly influenced by their behavior or their quirkiness of people
but we see them their different eye we see them with this deep love and care
knowing what's possible in them and knowing that there is goodness and beauty within them that can be grown and
and become full we feel kind of uh in kind of uh
kinship with people a deep kinship with Samar because the strong lines of Separation that we
have uh become softer so it's not hedonistic but it is
going along supporting and with with pleasure so this is a piece of the
puzzle that's needed to be understood to really begin finding a way to settle in
and getting concentrated in the samade type way and um so we'll keep building as we
go along here and hopefully this uh week on Pleasure will support us as we go
further at some point that pleasure becomes uh a pervasive feeling of joy
and pervasive feeling a very deep peaceful happiness so the pleasure
shifts and changes as we go along and for now the next step in this
which we'll talk about next week is uh is H kind of the prep Preparatory final
prepar preparation for dipping into uh uh what most clearly is called Samar in
in U in the teachings of the Buddha to really get absorbed into this and for
that there's something that's sometimes called access concentration and uh and so this
pleasure supports a kind of attention kind of awareness that uh now begins to
become uh in the groove of the present moment so that'll be the the topic for
next week so thank you very much and as uh week
comes to the end um one more time here for the our YouTube Community I want to
uh evoke or remind that we have this fundraising drive that uh I'm so
grateful for all of you who've made donations it's quite inspiring that so many people come together and uh we've
raised you know maybe close to I don't know 2third or something of uh
what we're hoping to raise we're trying to match what we raised three years ago when we did a fundraising drive for for
um save the children then and maybe even surpass it and um and so uh
um I think for given the challenges of our world uh these days it's uh particularly
significant to support these kinds of nonprofits that are trying to do good in the world and I think everyone benefits
that the benefit spreads widely through the world uh for this kind of uh
offering this support for to save the children so um thank you and you can
find information about it on the IMC website just go to go to imc's website
and there's a red banner on the top of the website and there's a a little discussion about it in the bottom right
where there's the what's new section so thank you and I look forward
to coming here on Monday to continue