hey maybe we'll get started
here wanted to say something in general about poems
and I said this a little bit before but there's this way in which poetry can be
a doorway can be a uh entry point to
shifting our relationship to experience for me I'm fascinated by this by how
poems and they're use the same old words we use all the time for the most part
but it's their Arrangement it's the way that you guys
can't see this but the way that there's line breaks you know in a poem that's different than often we would do with
Pros that encourages uh just a different way of um
maybe shakes up expectations or something that there isn't a period at the end of each line instead there's a a
way that the line goes to the ne the words go to the next line and then their Punctuation is there or way and we have
to kind of like lean in and pay a little bit more attention because things aren't exactly as we expect them to
be and it's this power of them of us having to pay just a little bit more
attention and them and the words not precisely meeting our
expectations that I think is part of the power of poetry of how it can not only point with
the content point to practice but it's a way of practicing to read poetry itself
independent of what the content is so in this that way I think poetry can be
quite powerful maybe it helps us to be more aware more
connected to what's actually on the page in my case now right what's
actually on the screen as I'm reading these on the
screen so maybe an invitation here to let the
words wash over you as a drop in a poem during our
guided meditation this morning please don't feel any sense that
you have to get it that you have to like it that it has to be some profound
experience just let it be what it is and it'll be what it is for
everybody so I don't want to like have this tyranny if poetry is supposed to elicit
some particular response or be a support for practice or anything like that can
it just be what it is including a yeah I don't get
it really poetry there could be such a wide range of
experiences and I know some of you are putting things in the chat that it's helpful I appreciate that I find it
helpful but I also want to acknowledge there's plenty of people who are kind of scratching their head going yeah
whatever and uh I used to be one of those people maybe some of you know I'm trained as a research scientist I used
to hate poetry I thought it was
silly okay [Music] so we will just
uh if you haven't already to take a meditation posture
and allowing the attention initially to kind of like
tune into the sounds around
you if you'd like you can even maybe even open Open the Eyes for a moment and
just to orient to the location where you are there's
sounds there's things in the visual
field you're here things are just as they
are and closing the eyes and again maybe can I
with any sounds not in so much a way that you have to label them identify them figure
them out but receive
them receive the
sounds we don't have to push them away
and then tuning into the experience of the body as it's in this location in this
ge I like to start with feeling the pressure against the
body the pressure where the body meets the sitting surface that cont
contact this is often an obvious sensation once
we turn attention to
it it helps support a sense of groundedness connectedness
the foundation upon which we're meditating
bit of a body skan starting with the sense of contact
with our sitting surface back of the
legs the feet the
bcks the back
the sensations don't have to be otherwise they just are what they are
staying in the Torso and there be some
ease in the belly
maybe some warmth and
tenderness the
chest holding shielding our Tender
Hearts and there'll be a little bit of a softening for some of you this might be
just this tiny movement of the shoulders going back behind you that brings just a
tiny bit more openness in the chest
and a lower back does so much work for
us some people it's uncomfortable painful some people they don't even
notice whatever your experience is can we tune in the lower back
want some
kindness the upper back
shoulders
the face
bringing a sense of aliveness to the
body sense of presence
and resting attention on the sensations of
breathing ordinary always
available
breathing maybe I should say always occurring not always available for lost and
thought e
inhabiting the breath the experience of the body moving
as it breathes
e
e e
now I'd like to drop in a
poem again you don't have to figure it
out don't have to do anything with
it and you just re receive and allow the words to wash over
you maybe you like it maybe you don't that's not the point
here a new experience hearing a poem
m is called No More same old Silly Love
Songs by Neil kathos no more same old Silly Love
Songs by Neil carpathio
when the radio in my car broke I started to notice the
trees I began to stop exaggerating the color of leaves other the Reds and
oranges needed no wordy
embellishment I started to open the window and smell the wet pavement
after Morning Rain grows on the phone
line their Blackness and stubborn
dignity I even noticed my hands gripping the wheel the small dark
hairs the skin the knuckles and the perfect blue
veins
repeat the poem no more same old Silly Love
Songs by Neil carpathio
when the radio on my car broke I started to notice the
trees I began to stop exaggerating the color of leaves other Reds and oranges
needed no wordy
embellishment I started to open the window and smell the wet
pavement after Morning Rain grows on the phone line their
Blackness and stubborn dignity I even noticed my
hands ripping the wheel the small dark
hairs the skin the knuckles and the perfect blue
veins e
and you be with whatever's arising In This
Moment
e
e e
thank you thank you for your
practice maybe I'll start by saying a number of years ago quite a few years
ago the radio in my car broke and it only play cassettes so this
gives you a sense of that era right this was the cassette era so you know I put a cassette in the
car in the car radio and I listened to that single cassette for at least a year
just every time I was in my car just the same I said over and over and over and
over it's quite something quite something when I think back on that and also when I reflect back on my
life I can see that there was a way in which I was kind of a dis connected from myself from my life I was
just trying to be so busy busy busy all the time and trying to do do do and
feeling like uh whatever I was doing just wasn't enough and I had to do more
and quite something when I think about this and to be honest I mean there was
this certain amount of comfort of listening to familiar music over and over again right I knew the words to
every single song you can imagine but there's a way in which just
listening to the same thing driving to work and the same way every day this
type of thing well there was a way in which encouraged a type of
autopilot you know just going through the motions and so I like to say that poems
are a way that they're encouraging us to connect
and I don't know maybe the word is connect with the words because it's not the usual way of
words the usual way that we communicate and so we kind of have to bring um all
of us or a bigger portion of ourselves in order [Music]
to let me feel into what the poems are pointing to because I would say that's
part of the power of poetry is that they are very uh clearly pointing so the
content is just used to um suggest a direction suggest an
orientation it's not so much that the words the literal words themselves are
where the what the poem is about so maybe there's this way that
um we can allow poems some poetry to really support support
us um Orient us to just be to feel into
to be connected be embodied so in the guided meditation I
offered this poem I'll say it again it's no more same old Silly Love Songs by
Neil carpathio and occurs to me there's so many different ways I could do this title No More same old Silly Love Songs
right that has this kind of a rhythm to it but I'll do it as no more same old
Silly Love Songs by Neil
kathio when the radio in my car broke I started to notice the
trees I began to stop exaggerating the color of leaves how the Reds and oranges
needed no wordy embellishment I started to open the
window and smell the wet pavement after Morning
Rain grows on the phone line their Blackness and stubborn
dignity I even noticed my hands gripping the wheel the small dark hairs the skin
the knuckles and the perfect blue
veins I don't know there's something that I want to smile every time I read this poem
and maybe I'll just start by saying generally there's just so much in our culture that is designed specifically to
distract us there's this way in which like there to pull our attention away from what's
actually happening and we might say well you know to uh live with some
mindfulness or to experience some mindfulness and awareness is a way in which we can feel more relaxed feel a
bit more restful but it's also enlivening and
energizing because instead of being pulled or thought or dragged into
thoughts and just entertainment infotainment dragged into tomorrow
dragged into the fear of uh of what the media often wants us to feel outrage or
fear or something they they know that these human conditions are what to get people to click more right so this is
their business model but we might have our own like concerns or distractions completely
independent of the media but there's this way it can be energizing or enlivening to actually be
connected with what's actually happening in that
moment because there's this way in which we might say that uh feeling
disconnected from our experience our life experience is a way of suffering
could say it's a type of Dua this feeling as if everything is behind some
glass or that we're only touching it with a 10- foot pull again using
metaphors and imagery perhaps to help us point to that uh we're not often really
with our experience instead there's this a way in which
we're disconnected in the same way that I would just be listening to the same song
driving the same route to the same job doing the same thing you know there's
this way in which this kind of autopilot can show up so we might say that one of
the functions of mindfulness is to connect us with
life have a be intimate with life have us be embodied have us
inhabit our lives and we grow actually to love this connection this intimacy
with our experience because there's this way we start to feel like oh this is my life we
start to feel like we belong we start to feel
less disconnected less Dua and that's a Priceless feeling there's a maybe a
preciousness to this connection and then we start to have a
feeling like oh this is what it means to live
life this is what instead of feeling like wow another year is passed us by or
another season has passed us by we start to feel like oh yeah I'm living life
doesn't mean that all of our preferences are being matched it doesn't mean it's easy it doesn't mean it's Pleasant it
just means that we're have a sense of aliveness can be a way in which there's
this deadening and maybe even a certain dullness that can arise because as we
start to practice mindfulness just being with what's being experienced there can
be this way in which we like wash the dullness from the
senses maybe some of you who have been on meditation Retreats whether they're
online or in person you might have had this experience I know I've had this
experience many times where the kind of the grass really does look Greener and
the sky really does look Bluer and the food is fantastic it's quite
something how with a meditation practice the sense of dullness that's been over
over our senses gets washed away I like maybe the the screen the windshield gets
cleaned like wow there's a things
they're ordinary but there's a beauty in the ordinariness and with that there's also
this sense of connection the sense of beauty there also the suppor of aliveness that
arises the sense of maybe we might say brightness
and then as we pay attention to walking the breath in the
body what's being heard what's being seen where the hands are on the steering
wheel so we might say that with mindfulness practice there's a we could
use this language maybe a sensitization that starts to occur there's this way in which we start
to feel connected and there a sense of aliveness and I don't want to say that
it's all joy and happiness because sometimes what we're connected to is painful it's really is I
don't want to pretend like it isn't there is really terrible stuff that happens in people's lives or even if
it's not an obvious event there's this low grade constant feeling of things not being
quite right so with practice though is a way
in which we can feel like we're alive we're
living we're connected we're embedded there's this way in which that
feels a certain amount of Freedom as I said I'm not saying
everything's good all the time there can be tremendous Joy with us no doubt but
sometimes there's a way in which we've disconnected because there's
uncomfortableness and the way forward often is just to be with this uncomfortableness but as we start to
connect as we start to be sensitive to what's actually happening as we start to
stop distracting ourselves then there's a feeling of
perfection oh yeah things are this way because
there's no other way they could be they're this way because causes and
conditions came together it couldn't be otherwise I don't like it
necessarily but I can appreciate the Beauty and the
lawfulness of what's being experienced
sense of perfection and there's a way that the heart sings When It aligns with the I'll
call it the Dharma the Dharma oh here we go here's this
poem no more same old Silly Love Songs by Neil
kathos when the radio and my car broke I started to notice the
trees I began to stop exaggerating the color of leaves their Reds and oranges
needed no wordy embellishment I started to open the
window and smell the wet pavement after Morning
Rain grows on the phone line their Blackness and stubborn dignity
I even noticed my hands gripping the wheel the small dark hairs the skin the
knuckles and the perfect blue
veins I love how this poem kind of like starts with external senses and then comes closer and closer more and more
intimate went from the external all the the way we might even say to the
internal perfect blue veins noticing the Perfection of what's being experienced
how could it be otherwise so thank you thank you for
another day of exploring the Poetry of practice wishing you all a wonderful
rest of your day and may you notice the perfection
that's arises in each moment without making that feel ooey
gooey making that feel the tyranny of trying to find the
Perfection the I don't know without it feeling
oppressive and you just notice yet of course things are the way they are how
could it be otherwise thank you