good morning everyone good day good evening um it's lovely to see all your
warm greetings and um uh little loving
emojis um so this morning um I'm going to talk
a little bit about um reflective thinking and um in our meditation we'll
do a contemplative reflection um contemplative reflection
is a complimentary practice to the mindfulness practice we do uh where we
you know pay attention to the present moment just as it is it uses the
thinking mind to consider something specific a dharma aspect or something in
our personal lives of course in in meditation you know we'll do something
um uh more related to uh to our spiritual
life um but um but to direct the
thinking um with a meditative mind it's different
than thinking about it it's allowing the responses to the uh contemplation to
arise from a deeper part of ourselves
um so um in this meditation um I'll
offer a contemplative reflection uh we'll begin with getting settled spend a
little time in silence and then I'll drop in a couple of questions you know more silence and then another
question and um we'll see how you respond to that what comes out of that
um uh I hope that it's fruitful for you
um so take a comfortable but alert [Music]
posture finding your seat gently closing the
eyes you might take a moment to consciously put aside any thoughts or
concerns set them aside for later put it Put them on a
shelf taking a few deep breaths and with each
exhale relaxing a little bit more deeply it's relaxing into your cushion
or [Music] chair into the earth that supports you
and now allowing the breath to return to
normal getting a sense of the whole body
and allowing the attention to travel freely throughout the body relaxing any obvious
tensions anything that can be
relaxed if anything doesn't relax easily just soften around it it's okay
and now finding the breath within your body allowing your attention to rest on
the breathing breathing in and breathing
out like waves in the ocean searching and
receding breathing in breathing
out resting in this body in this breath
now allow for a reflection as you consider it allow a
response to arise you might just feel or
sense or you might think a response allow it to
arise however it
is where does your spirituality live inside of
you where does your spirituality live inside of you
maybe an area that feels more connected more
intimate more enlivened
you might imagine that you're breathing through that area
whenever you're ready feel free to return to mindfulness of breathing okay
now I'll offer a contemplative
question here the question you don't have to think of an
answer it doesn't have to be a verbal answer but it might
be allowing something inside to respond or be
evoked eventually coming up with a
sentence the question is what is your deepest
intention what's the intention that you most want to base your life on
you may have various intentions that feel deeper important to you but which
are you gravitating to the most right now at this
moment what is your deepest intention the intention that you most
want to base your life on
if the attention has drifted just gently escorted back to the
breath to this body welcome home
we'll end with a quote allow it to resonate in you
just as the great ocean has one taste the taste of
salt so also this teaching as one taste the taste of
liberation
[Music]
so um I'll talk a little bit about some reflective thinking um uh in my own
practice mostly uh at different times in my practice
uh maybe once to twice a year I've taken a formal time to reflect on my deepest
intentions and inspirations and practice at different times um I'd ask
myself uh what was the edge of my practice what felt the most
challenging or what felt the most nourishing an area of growth it helped keep the practice at
the center of my life um the method I I was taught uh was
I'd go for a long walk or just sit somewhere peaceful and
reflect i'd take a little time for the mind to settle and then I'd ask the
question what is my deepest intention i'd allow my mind to answer
freely and then after a while after all the superficial answers that showed up
uh kind of died down a little bit I'd ask it again at first um you know by the third
or fourth time I asked it begin to be a little deeper and arise from deep
within um for myself I chose not to do it on my meditation cushion because I
wanted to keep it separate i was concerned that it might make me begin to think more in my
sittings um and then it just became the way that I did it um then after I did that I would keep
that intention close to me i would make it a point to connect with it daily and
often many many times a day my deepest intention was usually
some version of wanting to be free of suffering but at different times it would point to
different aspects of freeing the heart for instance
um um at one point I connected with the intention to develop unconditional
love at another time to prioritize equinimity in my
life so I'd come up with a one-s sentence way of phrasing it um then I'd reflect at some point
during my days what is it like to have my deepest intention at the forefront of
every communication I had every conversation every email every phone
call what's it like to wash dishes with equinimity without rushing forward
trying to finish them what's it like to sit in gridlock with the intention to incline towards
unconditional
love um when I worked with one edge of my practice that was particularly
impactful for me um was when I was struggling with
impatience um it seemed that I was impatient a lot
and uh the reflection inspired me to steep myself in Dharma teachings about
impatience and to just generally attune myself to the many ways that impatience
showed up in both my daily life and my meditation for instance um I you know
the impatience I felt listening to someone at a meeting I thought was long winded and boring
and how that impatience actually developed into strong aversion and dislike for the
person or the impatience I felt when a friend was late for a planned
lunch and of course the regular visitor I had in meditation how much
longer and as I kept attuning my attention to this I was just so
surprised how often during the day I felt it waiting for the shower water to
warm up waiting waiting and I slowly developed the habit
of mindfulness of waiting until waiting transformed for me into great more time
to practice
so a contemplative reflection is taking time to think on purpose about something
specific but to think about it from a deeper place than the discursive mind
from a place in us that feels connected one of the ways that um many um
teachings recommend is to do contemplative reflection to deepen our
understanding of the dharma of particular teachings for instance one might ask
"How do I understand karma at this time how does this understanding affect
my life personally?" Or at other times it's been appropriate to reflect on impermanence
or dooka or not self but we can also reflect about
something mundane something in our lives we want to clarify or decision we need to
make um with decisions I've spent lots of time going over pros and cons pros
and cons many many lists multiple times and still getting
stuck the rational mind could not come up with a decision so I would go meditate for a
while get settled and then I'd bring up the decision to be made and I'd allow
whatever came up to arise it was open-ended though i purposely
didn't insist on deciding that day but just opening to making a decision from
something deeper and something would usually shift in me and and when I finally made the
decision the decision seemed to flow there's a sense of harmony to it
sometimes a simpler form of reflective thinking can be helpful during
meditation for instance I was in a retreat once and even though my mind
seemed relatively calm I found myself bored and I kept wondering how much
longer i kept trying different methods i distract myself with them uh some body
scan which worked for a little while some meta worked for a little while but still bored
and then finally a teaching by Tnatan came to my mind if we're suffering something is being
left out of our attention and it finally dawned on me
that boredom was unpleasant that I did not want to be bored and that aversion
had shown up and I had not noticed because it looks so much different than all my other juicier
aversions like anger and fear and um sleepiness i just didn't recognize
it so I finally turned to the boredom itself what is it I don't want to feel
and so I explored the felt sense of the boredom the flavor in the mind the
feelings in the body the strong desire for my mind to be
stimulated i became interested in boredom for the first time
um my first introduction to the power of reflective practice before I even have
had heard of insight meditation um you know somewhere where in yoga
class somebody told me about this 3-day retreat that they took that was fantastic so I went and sat at 3-day
retreat and the instructions were to live with the question who am I every
waking moment including when eating you know and you know when we're
walking we're eating when we're sitting um and at first the mind would come up
with all sorts of verbal responses but the idea was to keep going
keeping the questions open-ended challenging the conceptual
answers that the conceptual mind gave
the mind would get quieter new things would arise and then at one point I saw myself
I'm the observer but then the I had the observer ask who am I and it was a little bit
like nesting dogs oh the observer is observing the observer and on and on and
on until logic gave up the conceptual mind stopped for a while
and a deeper wordless insight
arose and um lastly I want to tell you about someone who was an inspiration for
me um her name was Peace Pilgrim
some of you probably have heard of her but she um she was a woman who in the
early 50s became a renunciate when she was 45 she gave up
her name and possessions to do a walking pilgrimage a walking pilgrimage for
peace and for 28 years she walked across the US and Canada living on handouts
from strangers and spread her message for peace her only possessions were a
toothbrush a comb a pen and small leaflets with her message of
peace if someone offered her a place to stay for food she accepted if not she'd sleep on the
ground somewhere though she wasn't a Buddhist her message that people could find peace
within themselves by cultivating love and compassion
that message was universal when she first became a
renunciate she spent 50 days fasting on water and her goal during the fast was
to see if she could keep her prayer to God
constant and her prayer was a prayer of gratitude it wasn't asking for anything
it was a prayer of
gratitude so maybe that's um that's what I had this morning may May your
reflections deepen your connection with your own hearts thank you