so good morning everyone and welcome to IMC and um I do have an
announcement and I think of this announcement as part of the talk as May
me a prel pre Prelude to it um for quite a while I've been
wanting our community both in person and online out in the wider world to to be
involved in a second large fundraising drive that follows the one we did right
after the invasion of the Ukraine three three years ago where we raised money
for save the children and um and uh in order to
support the children affected by the war there and a lot of them were ref became
refugees going going out of the country and and the save the children did wonderful work supporting children and
families and they've been an organization that's been around for decades maybe 100 years or something
doing wonderful work one of the more greater reputable nonprofits
around and um been wanting to do it for a long time for the last year or so and
um it took a while for our community to kind of get organized or properly around
this and so we finally could do it now and uh it's for the save the children
emergency fund uh that goes for children and families and really emergency places
around the world and uh and things are pretty dire and risk of starvation all
kinds of things and um and uh the primary places now are places like um um
Gaza and Sudan and Syria and different
places Ukraine still may be and um so we started that fundraising
Drive uh maybe officially today and um and and officially it kind
of was posted available on I think Friday and um and so last time we did it
we raised $70,000 which I thought was pretty fantastic and so we're now
launching it again and this this time and it's a CH opportunity for our community to come together and feel like
we're coordinating and sometimes working together we get a kind of bigger impact
in the world than if we just do it individually and uh it just seems very timely that we're doing but it wasn't
wasn't the plan that um that the the federal government should
have kind of in a certain kind of negative way cooperated with their efforts that by shutting down the US Aid
the agency for instance International Development there's a huge huge a bigger crisis now with international support
and so now in our small way we're stepping into that vacuum with our ability to donate to the save the
children and so I think in some ways will'll make more of a difference than we would have been if we done this some
months ago so um so this is uh you know an attempt in our community to meet the
need and one of the key people organizing it is ram ram Jo I saw here
somewhere he's standing all the way in the back he has a wonderful little kind of red sweater and a
hat cat so if you look for some more a cat you'll um he um if because he's also
involved with a lot of wonderful humanitarian efforts kind of connected to the Outreach from the IMC orbit and
um and our orbit is to me it's I'm quite inspired by it I just went down to um
IRC this last two days one of the things we were our orbit
is involved in is chaplaincy training and we uh so we're training people to be
um spiritual caregivers in the kind of chaplaincy mode and um and so once a
year that the the yearlong training we do it at IRC for two days the retreat center and there was something very
significant for me of being at the retreat center with the current climate of things the chaos of this world that
sitting in the meditation Hall there it felt like it was one of these places of Refuge of that's protecting the good
heart protecting spiritual practice as a as a through line that will stay
constant through the ups and downs of civil ups and downs of civilizations that the like I have this
idea of my image of monasteries being places deep in the woods or mountains where no matter what goes on society
there actually preserving uh spiritual practice spiritual ideals ethical life
um in a in a very important way that to make it continue through time and so I felt like we were down
there in this place that has that kind of role in our society and uh training people to offer
spiritual care out into the wider world and uh I loved it and then I realized
that coincidentally that um that last two days the next two days
Monday and Tuesday uh I I'm training one of the other chapy programs coming out
of our orbit of IMC which is the EAP Buddhist Eco chapy training people
wanting to offer spiritual care in the context of the environment environmental crisis and um so that's pretty wonderful
wonderful group of 36 people and they all have to do a project for the year and a half program and so last night I
read all their project proposals and I was so inspired wow we put we we created
this program out of thin air and now these people have out of thin air doing these wonderful projects in the world
having to do with Eco Chaplan I like wow that's pretty cool that we have this and
then coincidentally Friday and Saturday uh we have the kind of a third kind of
spiritual care chapy informed program called anukampa which is bringing some
of those ways for uh that we do in chaplaincy some of the orientations
there for personal growth for people who are not necessarily going to offer spiritual care but want to touch into
that world and grow from it and so it just kind of represents how much that
this orbit of IMC is doing is doing a lot of things that here and there that are usually not
publicized and uh Rah who just announced uh he's connected to a lot of it and so
some of you are interested in learning more of what we do you can talk to him at the tea
time so in this world of chaos that we have seemingly and and uh it's quite amazing
uh we were planning yesterday met to planning meeting with the faculty of this Eco chapy program which starts
which will continuing through a two-day session Monday and Tuesday as I said and
we had planned some weeks ago what we were going to do and we real realize wait a minute the world has changed so
much in the last two weeks we have to kind of rethink the whole thing we can't just kind of we didn't know two weeks
ago three weeks ago that the world would look like it is now so we've now kind of
re reorganized it to try to better meet the circumstance we're in for PE for PE
especially for people offering one spiritual care to the world when the world has changed we should and probably
a lot of them are dismayed by what's happened and so how do we support them and care for them um sometimes you have
to care for the caregivers before you they can go out into the world and
um and um I was very moved to know after
the fact I wish I'd known while it happened that this week this last week
twice um students from the high school which is one m one block away uh March
through the streets March down to the the the C the city Courtyard uh and in order to protest the
the way in which the ice the immigration police is uh coming and taking students
out of high school coming taking them or maybe here undocumented and uh I don't know if
they've done that in local high schools right here but it's happened in U San Jose and where they've gone into the
high school and it's a to me from what I understand of it it's kind of a horrendous thing to do because to take a
student out of high school because they're undocumented as bait to get
their parents to come and retrieve you know come and get them means now the parents are also in that mix and to have
that kind of dynamic between that kind of tension and that kind of challenge for a family it must be absolutely
awful there was a movie many years ago called Sophie's choice and I wondered you know wow what what kind of what kind
of thing are we doing to families and um and so um and so they
had they had a walk out in that High School in East East San Jose for the students protesting
that so we have uh high school students and other students perhaps in this in
this country now who are afraid and Afraid for themselves afraid for their fellow students and so we live
with a lot of people now afraid maybe some of you are afraid some of you are quite con con ER maybe some of you are
in danger because of this some of you are know people who are and
um and uh and some of you might know people in the The Wider World whose
communities there are now their aid Their Food Supplies have been cut off because Aid has been cut off and and
people are and Med medicine supplies have been cut off and Medical Care has been stopped and people are starting to
die because of what this the very quick way in which this Administration has decided to make this change without a
care planning and consideration for the impact so um so these actions that are
happening that are dismaying and frightening alarming for many people certainly we should name it the name
that recognized how difficult it is for some people and some people are finding it as
that it's the med medicine they've been waiting for for a long time the change they've been hoping for and and you know
uh that's also happening and so how do we find our way with all these what's happening in our
society so that was a long Prelude to my talk it turn so I want to tell you a
Buddhist myth and it might be in the context of all that telling you this
amazing you know strange myth uh is um
is it would seem like maybe diminishing or underplaying what's going on in the
response to it but it's uh how the Buddha responded to similar things
happen in his time uh you know we have some of us have this image of the Buddha
sitting quietly in the forest peacefully and he probably was just all Serene and
wonderful but uh periodically through his lifetime societies fell apart around
him there was war that he was not in the middle of necessarily but the places
where he lived and traveled for 40 years 80 years between um there was Warfare
and War and famine and all kinds of things Society falling apart the
representative of that is that he died peacefully and we tell this wonderful story of him laying down on the ground
between two flowering trees and to and to die very peacefully
and serenely in a deep meditation practice and it was nice for
him um and uh around him his societies
were were were falling apart and around him Ward drums were being were being uh
beat beaten and uh kings were being Thrones were being
usurped and taken over and there was a lot and his uh his some of his followers
is one of his prime his kind of kind of one of his prime disciples had been murdered just a few months before he
died and so he was even though he died peacefully the context was one of great
upheaval and there was no courts to go to to say you know please stop there was
no check and balances for these monarchs who were King who were basically dictators who could just help people to
you know offer their head at a moment's notice and there was no check and balance except unless unless the
neighboring country attacked you that was a check and balance and um so it was a you know in
some ways it was an awful time and the Buddha responded with myth maybe because
that was the safest way it was kind of and there was not a it was oral culture back then so there was you couldn't
write a Manifesto and post it on doors or get it you know put it down on the
news or something um the way that things traveled was uh Through People speaking
and so a good myth a good story uh probably traveled a lot more by some
someone standing a soapbox and say you know it's not not not a good idea to have war and um and so the Buddha supposedly
composed these these myths and and this particular myth uh is designed in a in a
classic literary form if if you know about literature call it kismos and
that's a ritual way that that that's done in the Bible and Homer and many places where the the the literature the
the writing is done as a journey into a a a a pivotal point and
then the journey is going out kind of in in the uh mirror image of going in and
so this myth is kind of you know so people in the ancient world they they knew knew this kind of form of
ritual myth telling or mitual ritual storytelling so they kind of knew to
kind of be carried Along by it and and dip down into it and then come out of it
maybe in an inspired way and I don't think I can tell it that way but um but you know maybe you'll
follow along you'll understand how it is and
um so um it it's a you know it's I think it's a myth because it starts off at a
time long long ago when people's uh lived for 880,000
years that was a lifetime that's a long time and uh it describes how society
devolves and as Society devolves it affects how long people live almost
biologically people get bored and their lives get shorter and shorter and shorter and uh and so goes through you
know from 80 to 40 I think to 20 to 10, years and eventually you get to um 7
days and uh that's pretty bad and me think then it's real that's the worst that it evolves to society and the world
and people just become uh uh just horrible to each other absolutely
terrible and uh and that's when things change and um and then then it come
comes out and then life as over the over the centuries I guess or Millennia the
lifetimes increase back until the Glorious time when we can live for 80 80,000
years and um and the pivot point of the story has
to do with people going into the forest leaving the ordinary constructed world
of human beings where we have institutions and government and all these things that we create and to make
sense of our social life they actually leave they go to the forest and there
there's a the the turn what has to happen to turn society around happens
there in the forest and there's other places that Buddha tells kind of a story this is not
a myth it's just kind of a metaphor he uses the same thing that when he
discovered the path to Awakening he likened it to a person
who goes into the woods um someone who works in the woods a woodworker or something goes into the
woods and finds an overgrown path but he sees the traces of the path and then he
comes back to the monarchs of the of the realm and tells them I found the traces
of an ancient path and they say oh okay and they go into the forest and they
clear the path and they found the path takes them to some glorious
overgrown Aztec city that's been covered over
for you know for a long time and um and so here again the idea is something in
the forest so the forest here represents some other dimension of life that is
outside of the ordinary constructed imagined synthetic world that we live in
of um you know building up our ego building up our concept of self building
up our concept of the world that we have the cathedrals and the edifices we have
of of abstract constructed engineered society
which is both good and challenging to live in and uh you know we have to deal with
Twitter now and I was just thinking about how uh it's this imagin constru Ed
unnatural world doesn't exist in the natural world whatsoever uh is now the source of the
wealthiest people in the world that is not because they're really good farmers and they produce things
people need and that makes them wealthy it's they're making these things that just a few decades didn't exist and it's
you know it's a part of a build comes out of this constructed imagined world of uh the human mind and that's kind of
the world that's taking over in some ways and D dominating and has the power and so here the Buddha is offering
another way going back into the natural world it's represented by going into the
forest so in this myth the um I'm going to tell you it's the myth of the wheel
turning monarchs and the wheel turning monarchs are kind of like this Universal monarchs
who own in the Mythic times a huge uh area of the
world so they're very powerful and um and for many
generations of uh the monarchs uh know how to live and be how
to rule ethically and um and this is a description of how they
rule rulers honor respect and venerate the truth
have truth as their banner and guide they provide
just protection protection in a Justice way they provide just protection and
security for their Court troops Aristocrats assistants brahin and
householders towns people and country people religious practitioners animals
and birds they do not let let Injustice Prevail in the country they provide
support to the poor this was written 2500 years ago in
the Bronze Age I love saying that and um you know this was relevant
that long ago for human societies for someone to say that to describe monarchs the ideal Monarch the Mythic
Monarch however that went on for about six Generations and Seventh Generation is
somehow seven is a good number so that in the Seventh
Generation uh uh one of the monarchs stopped doing some of this um and um and it says he uh he
governed the country according to his own ideas so governed the country people did
not Prosper like before as they had when former Kings proceeded in the noble duty
of a monarch so the noble duty of the what the first one I read and uh but then the ministers came
to the person and said wait you know you're not doing it right and the people are suffering now and
um and um um and so they said to him they said
people are suffering you should ask us they didn't they weren't going to tell them something maybe you don't tell them
on what to do he said you should ask us about the noble duty of a monarch we
will answer you and so he asked and uh they explained it to them
and after listening to them he provided uh justice and security and for his
people but he did but he did not supply uh uh he did not provide support for the
penniless in the realm and so poverty grew
widespread when poverty was widespread a certain person stole from
others makes sense Roger starving with the intention of to commit
uh theft so intentionally stole he was
arrested and they presented him to the king saying your majesty this person
stole from others with intention to commit theft and the King said to him is it
really true you stole and the man said yes it's
true remember this is back in the ideal time when everyone was living ethically and honestly yes I still
um what was the reason said the king sire I couldn't survive
otherwise in um I was born in burgund Norway and they have their still on the
wall of the old castle that was living back there supposedly one of the first
rules of the of the land that it says explicitly if someone's starving it's
not a crime to steal
um so the so uh so he said I can't survive and so the king um provided him
with some uh support material support saying with this
support keep yourself alive and provide for your mother and father partners and
children work for a living and provide an inspiring donation for religious
practitioners that's conducive to happiness so maybe it's a littleit self-
serving for the Buddha too just to say
that and um but still this idea here's support to get started with a career and
support your people and Thrive with it so it's kind of nice and so the guy said
yes but then another person stole some something from other people and was
arrested present to the king and same thing happened is it true yes why to
survive and so the king provided that person with material support and to in
order to to build a career and and support the
people and um but then people heard about this and they thought it's seems
the king is providing support to anyone who steals from others it occurred to them why don't we
steal from others so then another man stole something from
others and that person was arrested presented to the king did you steal
yes why because I couldn't survive then the king thought if I
provide support to anyone who steals from others it will only increase the
stealing I'd better make an end to this person finish him off and chop off his
head he's a decisive person strong and decisive and he's going to you
know so he ordered his men to do so um but people heard about
this it seems the king is chopping the heads off anyone who steals from others
so it occurred to them we better have sharp swords made then when we steal
from others we'll make an end of them finish them off and chop off their
heads and so they did that and um and
so the Buddha uh points out and so from not
providing material support to the penniless poverty became widespread when
poverty was widespread theft became widespread when theft was widespread
swords became widespread when swords were widespread killing living beings became
widespread and for the sentient beings among whom killing was widespread their
lifesty lifespan and Beauty declined these people um lived for 880,000 years
but their children lived for only 40,000 years so now we're beginning to see the
devolving not just of society but there's a in Buddhism there's kind of a direct kind of correlation between our
lived life because of the karma that we live and so the karma affects us in a
dramatic way and here it's got being passed on to the next generation and what are we passing on to
our next Generation Um among the people who lived
for 40,000 years a certain purple person stole something from
others the person was arrested and presented to the king your majesty this person stole from
others the king said is this true no sir he deliberately
lied and so from providing from not providing support to the penniless poverty theft
swords and killing became widespread when killing was widespread lying became
widespread and for the sentient beings among uh whom lying was widespread their
lifetime and Beauty declined these people who lived for 40,000 years there had children who lived for 20,000
years and then the people who lived 20,000 years they did it got even worse
because not only do they lie but then behind the king's back they disparaged
him so kind of back backbiting started to happen and so that reduced lifespan
to 10,000 years among the people who lived 10,000 years uh some were beautiful and some
were ugly the ugly beings coveting the beautiful ones committed adultery with
the partners of others and so from not providing support to the penniless poverty theft swords
killing lying and backbiting became widespread when backbiting is widespread
uh sexual misconduct conduct became widespread and so then the LIF span
reduced to 5,000 years and this process continued the
next thing that happened was harsh speech came into play divisive and hard
spe the how people spoke and uh then the lifespan reduced to 20 2,000
years oh actually says 2500 years and then those people
uh had ill will ill will became widespread and then the lifespan reduced
to a thousand and then a wrong view uh the wrong view is the view that
you can do whatever you want it has no impact uh and but the right view is that
if you do things which are UNH wholesome unethical it'll have a ne ne negative impact on the world on yourself there's
consequences to it and having right the wrong View not believing in that um and more likely people are going
to do unethical things because there's no no repercussions anywhere so people had wrong view um
they um lifetime declined to 500 years then greed and a harmful culture
kind spread into the a culture of just harm and hate and things like that and
then it reduced to 2 the years and from that um respect for mother and father
religious practitioners um decreased and also for
elders and so with lack of respect uh lifespan went down
to I think a 50 years and
then uh just all this mean all this stuff all the killing and everything's going on at the same time right like
it's getting more and more terrible and the next thing is um
um the people who lived I guess anyway 50 I don't know what's going on here but
[Music] um they lived for 10 years and among the
people who lived for 10 years um I don't know if this you know maybe I should not read this but it says uh girls became
marriageable at 5 years maybe that was very significant back then
and and the following uh um and then the
following flavors disappeared uh butter oil honey molasses
and salt things are getting worse and um and then people started
doing more and more UNH wholesome unethical things and and the lifespan went down
to um oh and there was no recognition of the status of mother aunts or wives
Partners uh Partners tutors students and other respected people the world became
dissolute like goats and sheep chickens and pigs dogs and
jackles everyone was full of hostility towards each other with acute ill will Mal avence and thoughts of murder even a
mother will feel like this for her child and a child for its mother father for child child for father brother for
Sister Sister for brothers they'll be just like a deare hunter when a de
Hunter sees a deer full of hostility ill will malevolence and thoughts of killing among the people who lived for
10 years there was a a a middle period this limbo period this is the turning
point of a turning point of so it's called the inter period
of Swords the lasted for seven days so imagine lifetimes are seven days and
also that period of seven days sharp swords will appear in their hands it's
kind of like like a science fiction thing like just born with swords or something
um which will take each other's lives crying and call calling everybody else
it's a beast a beast everyone's called beasts so this is the worst if we come
to the end of the worst but then some of those beings
thought let us neither kill nor be killed why don't we hide in thick grass
thick jungles thick trees inaccessible riverlands or rugged mountains
and survive on Forest Roots Forest roots and fruits so they
did what so that's what they did so the idea of surviving on roots and fruits is so they don't have to kill any animal
for food so really they were going to live non-violently get away from it all when those seven days were passed
having emerged from their hiding places they embraced each other maybe because they're the only ones who
survived um uh and they and they come together and
cry in one voice fantastic dear enemy you live fantastic dear enemy you live
remember in the 7-Day period everyone's enemies they all went away maybe individually when they came out they
didn't see them as enemies anymore um they called they were the dear
enemy uh then they thought it's because we undertook undertook UNH wholesome
things that we suffered such an extensive loss of our relatives we better do what's
wholesome what wholesome thing to do why don't we refrain from killing living
beings and so then they slowly started to lifespan started to increase in
reverse order as they each went systematically well let's not kill people let's not steal from them let's
not lie let's not involve in sexual misconduct let's have let's have divisive speech and harsh speech Let's
respect people and slowly slowly and they came back eventually to live
happily happily for quite a while because they lived for 880,000
years and um and then it all started over again with the monarchs of the Realms knowing how what to do knowing
that they had to uh rule with Justice protect the Justice protect everyone
that they should uh support people provide them with the means for livelihood and let no one be poor and
this idea but you know kind of the central focus on poverty and that poverty was really where the the the
source was Society devolving and um and it looks like we're
moving in a direction in our society probably for a while of increased poverty don't know what to predict into
the future but it looks like there's going to be some people maybe the poorest in our society who are going to
suffer the most and um and and what is our
role you know in this kind of if if this is how Direction it all goes um I don't know what to say it's
kind of a for some of us it's kind of a difficult time to be in a situation like this and not know how to respond in a
sense it's a waiting game to see where it's going and where the response can be
but this kind of myth I think is actually extremely important because it says there is
something very deeply natural that's not part of that unnatural world that we
construct of governance and things that resides in ourselves in the natural
world within to go into the forests the natural world we can do that in our own
hearts and that's why we practice that's why we have meditation practice and these kind of spiritual
teachings and ethical guidelines so that we can live in an ethical way so that
our standard of Ethics is really high for ourselves and others we don't kill
we don't steal we don't involve in sexual misconduct we don't um involve in
lying we don't involve in greed and hatred we don't involve in involve in
disrespect backbiting we don't involve seeing anyone as beasts anyone as less
than human and um and so we really want to care for ourselves and to do all those
things is a way of harming ourselves I think that's one of the message of this myth that we harm ourselves and our our
descendants our society uh by how we do
things and we also harm in immediate now others who are impacted by those
behaviors of ours and so Buddhism the Buddha put tremendous emphasis on
Behavior like that and calling out the necessity of not behaving the those kind
of actions that cause harm and so for me to say at the beginning of this that
there were there are children being harmed right down you know potentially right down the street of bla away uh
unnecessarily uh is to critique Behavior action activity effect
without saying anything about any individual or any groups of people but look that kind of behavior has to
stop and uh I wish that I had known that the students were out on the streets but
it wasn't announced anywhere maybe it was spontaneous it was so one block away I would have joined them and uh because
I wanted to protest that kind of activity that kind of action and that might be all of us maybe
might feel called to say no to killing say no to stealing say no to sexual
misconduct say no to lying say Lo say no to specific ways in
which people are being harmed and I hope that we don't we're not silent in speaking up and maybe through
for a while until our LIF spans can grow up a little bit
longer rather than decrease because people will hate
us that um maybe we'll do it sometimes by telling
myths at least on this Sunday morning we use a myth to say that like the Buddha
did long long ago so that's my um my talk trying to be relevant for the
current times and hopefully it is enough and so we're it's all a work in
progress this practice of ours this life of ours so uh we have this tea today and
that's going to start in a few minutes but I think that um it's possible this
topic because it touches current events is a little bit tender for some of you
and uh and it might be nice and I I evoked in the beginning that I'm doing this kind of spiritual caregiving
trainings three of them in a sense that happens I'm involved in this week and maybe it's maybe we can care
for each other just very briefly by turning to a couple of people next to you make sure no one's left alone look
around could be four if necessary two or three and um and say hello and just uh
offer some care some respect some appreciation some welcome just just and
maybe maybe tell each other a little bit uh what it was like to hear this talk and what I evoked and what came out for
you and and listen to the other person with uh you know care and respect don't
give them advice and and don't offer your opinion
your opinion about what's supposed to happen out there just just be human together in a very simple way and don't
tell long stories about you you know what this talk was like just a few comments just to share who you are and
say hello and and break the ice of saying hello especially people here here the first time and then uh in a few
minutes there will be that the tea I'll ring a bell so that you know it's really clear time to stop and then if you can
continue talking afterwards the Bell but then the tea will be available and you're all welcome to stay so thank you