so hello and welcome to this 30 minute
meditation and uh as we begin and and also continue the
series on samadei a word that I haven't uh
evoked uh that's closely connected to samadei is the word
samata and samata has a sounds like samadei but it has a very different
ethmology and it means to calm and
to and the whole world of samadei has a lot to do with
calming calming the body calming the heart calming the
mind and uh and so one of the ways maybe of
practicing today that maybe builds on how we've
been practicing samadei for the last now over three
months is um to have a gentle emphasis
on calming the mind and what I mean by gentle is that um almost as if you're
not doing anything uh except maybe uh at at a choice points
saying the word calm or calming in a very unforceful
un expecting kind of way and allowing something in the mind to come the
primary kind of the real important area of us that's for samadei to calm is a
calming of the mind calming of mental activity a quieting of mental activity
even certain mental activity uh uh ceases during deep
samadei for example there's the end of discursive thinking commentary
conversations in the mind images and of great stories and the the
image-making mind quiets down dramatically and the mind gets quieter
and quieter and one wonderful metaphor for this is um the waves on a on a lake
or lay waves on the ocean when the wind is there big big waves can be born can
arise when the wind quiets down so do the waves till finally when there's no
wind there are no waves when there are no discursive thoughts no active
thinking reacting to what's happening in the mind uh that uh now the waves of the mind
become very quiet and as the waves on the lake become still then the uh the
lake becomes clear we can see right down to the bottom so as we do this practice today
um for the uh inhale just let the inhale fill your
with the with the air filling your lungs uh with the movements of the body as you
breathe in have a feeling of that attention spreads through your body so
you feel and sense uh widening circles of your body just a kind of a feeling a
sensing sometimes different parts of the body sometimes more like a starting from
some the resting point the centering grounding point of breathing that it
spreads outwards into your body like a broadening wave and then on the exhale begin the
beginning of this sitting have the exhale be a place that relaxes
relaxes the body just allow something to relax and then let there be a brief
pause at the end of the exhale just long enough to say the word
calm or calming which functions as a
reminder for the waves of the mind to become calm
no matter what is happening to you nothing to solve nothing to fix and
nothing to figure out it's just a time to let the mind
calm calm calming of the mind and uh trust just the increasing
just letting the mind become quiet and still the waves of the mind settle out
so breathing in to feel what's here breathing out to kind of in the
beginning of the sitting to relax the body and then it's and then a brief
pause then long enough before you breathe in saying
calm reminding the mind it can become calm after a while you want to stop
doing the relaxing on the exhale it's no longer needed and at some point maybe
you don't even want to do the active kind of expanding of awareness into the whole body it's enough just to be in the
whole body um breathing in and breathing
out but maybe again at the end of the exhale calm and if you get particularly calm uh
you don't have to say the word calm anymore you can just say just a nonverbal recognition ah this is a time
to calm or maybe just say in your mind
ah so assuming a meditation uh
posture a posture that in some ways makes you
bigger whether you're lying down or sitting or standing
for meditation kind of be be somehow
stretched opened a feeling of being expansive in
your posture not crunched not crunching any part of your
body as if you can become large
big expansive posture and gently close your
eyes and take three or four deeper breaths to begin this process of feeling
the body on the inhale relaxing on the
exhale and saying the word calm to yourself at the end of the exhale
and then to let your breathing return to normal and
gently let your awareness spread through your body as you
inhale relaxing ing the body on the
exhale pausing with the word
calm calm mind no matter what you're concerned
with no issue nothing to do or fix or solve
except trust the value of calming the
mind stilling the mind
if any part of this
exercise seems stressful
are too much work lighten up do it
simpler and simpler
rather than waiting for a pause in the
exhale to say calm you might begin or gently ly say
it during the exhale in a way that
slides into the stillness at the end of the exhale
so you feel the silence of the mind at the end of the
exhale
as you meditate trust the calming distilling of the mind
and it might be that all you
do is very
quietly whisper the word
calm as you breathe in and as you breathe
out making less and less effort
at meditating in [Music]
favor of a stilling
quieting of all distractions all
thoughts being here in this
body with an expanding sense of
calm pervading all things
any agitation you have any active thinking you
have focus on calming underneath it
let there be a deep calming in the mind that's
below the thinking
mind that is the source of the thinking
mind trust this deep stilling of the waves
by trusting the peace and the
quiet that's in the lake below the waves
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to feel or sense whatever degree of calm is here
for you even if it's quite
small feel the calm of the
body feel the calmness in your
heart feel the calmness of your mind
and as if your
calmness are you are your eyes it's through your calmness that you
can see everything else with calm eyes
see whatever agitation whatever activation however
small is here for you calmly knowing what is not
calm in whatever spaciousness it's here spaciously
know what is not
calm quietly know what is not
calm may be a silent knowing
allowing whatever is here for you to be known within a field of
calmness spaciousness
openness in the same way that you can hold your own agitation activation calmly
now through the calm eyes of practice calmly gaze upon this
world spaciously openly as if your calm
awareness is medicine is a gift for this world
the more the world is agitated the more a calm
person is reassuring is a reminder to
others is medicine for an agitated
world may it be
that you do not contribute to an even more agitated
world may it be that you contribute a gift of calmness reassurance
may all beings be calm and
peaceful may all beings experience
happiness and an inner
contentment may all beings feel peace
and non strife
may all beings be
free free of tension emotional pain
suffering and may how we walk in the world calmly contribute to the welfare and
happiness of all [Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to the next talk in this samadei series
and today's talk is um kind of one of the themes of it is
calm because the general topic this week is the fourth Janna and the fourth Janna
represents a very profound calming of the mind calming of mental
activities and if you understand that a lot of the agitation that we have comes
from thinking as the thinking quiets down that doesn't trigger
agitation and we appreciate how um the mind that is for and against
things or reacts to pleasure and pain u quiets down and calms down the
relationship to pleasure and pain recedes and quiets and surprisingly
enough uh we might not feel much pre pleasure and pain certainly there are times when uh
pain gets uh actu
accentuated by our preoccupation with it by our vigilance against it by
our meaning making and fear and predictions around the pain we feel the
micro muscles around the pain tighten up the pain just seems larger in the mind it's like a magnifying glass on it but
when we no longer are caught in the preoccupation with pain something of
sometimes even the pain recedes into the background and in this quieting calming
of mental activities in the fourth genre um that uh pain and pleasure of all
kinds just recedes and becomes irrelevant disappears from the
mind and it represents a a kind of a uh
a uh a certain kind of coming into fullness or
completion certain kind of the gradual calming uh of the mind that goes on throughout
samadei practice and the somati practice has a general uh name of being called
samata and samat s a m- a t h a uh
sounds like samadei but it's a different word and samata means to calm
tranquility and uh it's a calming tranquilizing of the mind making
tranquil peaceful tranquil like a deep clear
tranquil lake and um and so we're we're calming mental
activities and the mind gets calmer and calmer and it's not turning the mind off
it's just quieting certain activities of the mind that are extra that they're not
needed and uh and in and what comes in return is um a a tremendous sense of
clarity and uh the tradition calls it a pure clear
mind and um and uh it feels like this is like the
way the mind is the healthiest most present most fully alive uh in this uh
vast pure clarity of the mind that can be there clarity of clarity of
awareness and um and so it's not going into a trance it's not kind of checking
out it's not becoming unaware but uh there's no thinking
uh no um acts of you know
um recognition of what's there but there might be a deep nonverbal knowing that
is part and parcel of the clear pure mind but there's no
thoughts and uh but there's a kind of clear knowing that there's no thoughts
but we're not telling oursel there's no thoughts it's just kind of it just it's just known without any effort without
any agitation or any waves and um and because this calming of
the mental activity has gone more and more the way that we take in sense data
from our body from the world around us begins to quiet as well we're not
actively taking in sense data the places that we register sense data on the body
don't operate in a conceptual way anymore it's not taking in the data and putting it into the usual concepts we
have of body hand room sound distance here there there's
all these subtle ways which we take for granted which is kind of kind of
recognizing the truth of reality that it is a kind of
conceptualization of the sense data that comes in in a particular
way and um and so even something as innocent as me you know recognizing this
here as a bell it is a bell but there there's
a a subtle mental activity that recognizes as a bell and um and it feels
effortless it feels you know nonverbal but uh it is um uh it's
contextual it's uh learned it's um
um a concept an idea that in another time in another situation this same
object might be used as a holder holder of paper clips a pen holder it might be
a spatoon it's so solid it could even be someone's pot that they put on top of a
fire to cook their soup and someone called call this a pot so the context
changes what this is and so so that there so there's a very subtle
conceptual activity of the mind that makes that choice what they able to call it and then deep in the fourth genre
this kind of conceptualization is quieted down and so there might still be
a recognition that there's something here but it doesn't have a name it doesn't con it's not
conceptualized so in the same way with our body we're We're not conceptualizing
our body in the usual way and the body begins to become diffuse no clear
boundaries no clear details it's just kind of a generalized peaceful
clear kind of vibration or flow and this explains a little bit the metaphor
that's used for the fourth Janna sitting in the fourth Janna is just as
though a person were sitting covered from head down down with a white cloth
so that no part of this of one's whole body so no part of one's whole body is
not covered by the white cloth so a white cloth represents a cloth that's
very clean and and um in which um
the light that comes through a white cloth sometimes feels very diffuse and
clear and wonderful and um and so the idea of sitting with a white cloth covering
ourselves our whole body is um wouldn't it's not strange for the ancient Indian
world because that there was no de there was no mosquito nettings and so the way
to be kind of untroubled by insects was to cover yourself with a blanket with a
shawl with a cloth and um so the people meditate monks would
sit meditating that way and and from the outside you know there's a human body
underneath the cloth but there are no details there's no clarity of exactly the shape the sit the shape the
characteristics of that body it's diffused and kind of uncar characterized
except for a general sense of the outline that's in the cloth and um at
the same time the person inside it feels very cozy and very safe and very
comfortable um where where there's no real sharp kind of boundary in a sense to the outer
world in the felt sense there's a soft kind of clear light feeling light with
weight and light that's as luminous and um and uh some people uh uh
in order to harmonize this metaphor with the idea of the lake in the second and
third um uh Janna the metaphors for the third
second and third Janna uh the lotuses that are floating in the lake the person
just floating in water and they get very clean then they come out of the water
and sit under the tree to meditate and they wrap themselves in a clean towel
completely wrapped and covered feeling a pure clean
uh fresh quiet content in this way the feeling of being
in the third Janna feels very clean
pure content peaceful kind of indistinct nothing's
needed everything is cozy so um and there's no pleasure and pain
because the quieting quieting of that part of the mind that registers and conceptualize and engages in the
construction of pleasure and pain has gotten very very quiet that's both physical pleasure and
pain and also a mental pleasure and pain that might be emotional
so this is the description abandoning pleasure and
pain with a previous disappearance of mental happiness and mental
suffering one enters and abides with neither pain nor
pleasure in the purity of a quantamus awareness of the
fourth Janna when sits pervading this body with a pure clear mind when sits pervading
this body with a clean clear mind so that no part of the entire body is
untouched by the pure clear mind it is just as a just as though a person were
sitting covered from the head down with a white cloth so there is no part of
one's whole body that is not covered by that white
cloth so
um may you find calm may you find the calm that
comes from not overthinking
overreacting over involved being over involved with our present
moment let calm be your companion through the
day and in whatever way you can and maybe the calm is the calm of not adding
more agitation to the circumstant you're in may it be a calm day thank you