so welcome to our meditation weekday
meditations offered here from Insight Meditation Center
and today's meditation is part of an ongoing series on
samade and we come to a kind of a turning point now in this
series where we're now going to uh
consider um the role
of um pleasure in different forms as part of
samade so pleasure can take the forms of straight kind of physical pleasure it
can take the form of joy and happiness gladness and um and other
qualities of uh that come with pleasure and so
um so to begin very simply and and maybe if you can suspend
disbelief at Your Capacity to feel pleasure and
meditation and um and to be open to
recognize ways maybe subtle ways that um
there can be pleasure and there can be pleasure at the same time as
pain and uh and has a little bit to do with how much or how little
we prioritize certain Sensations over others and certainly pain can be very
difficult and it can be very feel like almost a survival Instinct to focus on on it and try to
manage it and so and of course you should try to manage it the best you can and certainly never use meditation is a
way of injuring yourself with pain through pain but uh there's also an art
to not being reactive to the pain not being in the mind fixated on it in some
kind of way but to be open to the pleasure
that's also present and so the pleasure can accompany the discomfort the pain
emotional pain physical pain there might be and it creates a different context
maybe a different opening an openness maybe a a calmer or kind of a Freer
relationship to it all so to assume a meditation posture
and [Music] to spend a little bit of
time seeing if you can find a posture that ex that somehow manifests
both some degree of calm and alertness that at the same time you
enjoy you appreciate maybe because it's familiar your meditation posture
and to feel the gladness feel the relief for
appreciation of beginning meditation in this
posture and as a way of
waking up and relaxing at the same time waking up the
body see if you can breathe somewhat Fuller or deeper than you usually do but
to do it in a way that's Pleasant for you you enjoy
it so to let the breathe Fuller so
that rib cage expands
deeper so the belly expands just enough not more than enough
just enough so that's a very simple ordinary
enjoyment pleasure and
breathing and to Exhale longer than usual maybe mostly by relaxing at the
end of the exhale so it
continues and maybe they're letting go the
release of exhaling is there any pleasure meure in that any
pleasantness anything Pleasant about the Rhythm breathing in and breathing
out sometimes the pleasure relief can
be that we're not so no longer caught up and involved in our everyday
concerns they might still be there but it's nice to be now in a posture and a
practice that where we can begin taking taking a step away from
it a step not away from ourselves but into ourselves
and letting the breathing return to
normal and I often teach spending time relaxing the body at the beginning of
meditation and as we do this see if you can feel any sense of pleasure
pleasantness enjoyment relief
in the relaxation so that as you
exhale to relax the face the eyes the
cheeks the
Jaws as you exhale to soften in the
shoulders sometimes it's difficult to relax the shoulders but to soften
around any holding in the shoulders
on the exhale softening the
belly sometimes that's little bit uncomfortable but there can also be
something pleasant in it side by side from the
discomfort for this meditation feel the pleasure
and if it's easy enough on the
exhale relax soften open the thinking
mind the thinking muscle
and to feel whatever pleasantness pleasure relief there is in that
softening of the Mind
and centering yourself on your breathing and whatever way is easy for
you feel your body kind of in a wide
Broadway the global body
to feel where in your body there is some modum of pleasure
pleasantness comfort and feel that Comfort feel that
pleasant as you
breathe it might be just a little spot
someplace in the hands somewhere in the
legs the lips touching or it might be
broad it might be in this inct more like a
Radiance in the vibration hum of the body
and then to feel your breathing within
that maybe feel within that context of pleasure
and the idea is to breathe in an ordinary normal way no special effort to breathe in any special breathing
technique but within the normal range of
breathing there is room for slight adjustments in your
breathing to breathe more from the belly more from the chest more from
with nostrils and maybe the whole all of the
above at once see if you can find where in the
cycle of breathing where in the body there is some degree of
pleasure comfort with
breathing no matter how small or
brief and ever so slightly just enough can you adjust your
breathing so that there is more pleasure more comfort in
breathing maybe a slight breathing deeper
Fuller maybe not by doing it but having there be a letting go near the top of
the inhale so the inhale continues
letting go at the end of the exhale so the exhale continues in a nice
way
and as part of breathing the Cycles are breathing in and
out let yourself be touched by whatever
pleasure there is in breathing whatever Comfort
pleasantness maybe
Joy whatever sense of well-being is found
with breathing in the sensations of breathing
or radiating from them around them
and no matter how small the pleasure is maybe your mind stays more
interested in being absorbed in breathing absorbed in attention to
breathing if you keep touching into what's
Pleasant what's comforting in breathing
for
for for
if there is any Pleasant in
breathing as you breathe Relax The Thinking mind into
that pleasure so the thinking mind becomes
quieter and more
content just to be quiet attentive
for
for for
and if you do feel any pleasure or have a soft mind that can feel the
pleasure of the
breathing in a way that is maybe similarly Pleasant
gently count the exhales so that the
quiet maybe Whispering ex
count quiets the thinking
mind so you can better feel the pleasantness of
breathing
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to feel
notice is there any way that you are calmer than you were before more
settled less preoccupied
maybe a greater sense of being in touch with
yourself is there something you appreciate about how the meditation has
changed or shifted something for
you and is there something pleasant about the appreciation or what you're
appreciating is there some gladness that you feel glad and
content to be meditating is there any pleasure
pleasantness that's grown in the course
of grown in the course of the
meditation and as you exhale to imagine yourself settling back into a soft
chair easy chair recliner settling back down into that
pleasure pleasantness and from
there gazing out upon the
world gazing upon maybe the people you will in your
life people in your communities out across the land and across the globe
with all its suffering
enjoys and perhaps your ability to rest in Pleasant
state is better for the world than for you to rest in an agitated state or a
troubled state or an unpleasant
State at least for these next next minute minute or
two whatever degree you can rest in
pleasure in comfort in
goodness as you gaze with your mind's eye out across the world it's medicine for the
world for
and as you go forth into the
day May there arise from your
actions from your speech and even from your mind and how
it thinks May there
arise when ways of relating to people that can be manifest these kinds
of words these wishes may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we contribute to contribute to that
possibility at least locally and in small ways
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this 21st talk on samadi
the the the phenomenally useful um ability to
be happily absorbed in an
activity absorbed as in a state of being absorbed
connected and uh and this is one of the gifts that can happen in meditation and
it's a state that as somebody develops that involves a lot of
pleasure some of that pleasure can be experienced as gladness comfort some of it as Joy
sometimes as happiness some people will describe it as um uh some of it in when it gets
intense as a Rapture and Bliss and um when the Buddha was
searching for a path to Awakening uh he there is a story that's
told that um he remembered being a child and uh being left in a safe place
while the adults were working on or doing the the spring plowing Festival in
the field and he was in the edge of the field under a tree it's kind of lovely that they
record of what tree it was it was a rose apple tree and somehow watching the events
around him he got very calm and settled and peaceful and and um and in a way
that was noticeable and felt a lot of joy and
happiness and um and then um and he
entered into a state of some that was very enjoyable and he remembered having that
as a child as an adult and he said wait a minute maybe this is the way forward maybe this
is the way to Freedom he had been doing aestheticism where he was denying
himself and experiencing tremendous amount of pain intentionally and he had realized that
that that wasn't going to lead to his Awakening and in Ancient India to feel
pleasure was considered a little bit taboo among religious people some at least some of them
that uh somehow that was indulgent somehow that was self preoccupation of some sort but he
felt the quality of this pleasure of absorption was actually quite
healthy and useful and that it was onward leading it led to kind of a
deeper unification deeper arriving here connection here and a deeper Clarity
that was going to allow him to do the work of coming to the end of suffer offering so we have here in Buddhism two
kind of things that might seem contradictory but are important to understand they go hand in hand one is
it's a very uh direct acknowledgment of suffering suffering in
the world and our own suffering there's not a turning away from it or denying it
or pretending it's not there or overriding it with some kind of even
meditation there is a kind of mature serious like yes there is
suffering and at the same time in appreciation that there is a healthy
pleasure healthy sense of well-being that we can cultivate and develop as a
way of meeting that suffering holding that suffering finding a way through that suffering and so how we can hold
both at the same time is part of the art and one way to do that is to not be
fixated on the suffering not be overly afraid or concerned or trying to fix it
or solve it uh maybe to understand that the at least in in in the context of
meditation not in a restor our life but in meditation at least there's something
about our challenges our problems even some deep psychological
suffering that we carry that um it won't be solved but it
will be dissolved and uh there's something uh so
that it's almost like better not to fix it on it but let the discomforts and stuff be on the edges or and in the
middle of it um without denying it start
uh as we develop and get settle in meditation more and more to feel the
pleasure of meditating of course this is not something someone can do when suffering
is new and fresh or big or someone's new to meditation but as meditation deepens
and we have a sense of it then we start opening up to this the the pleasure of
meditation and um and you know this is the 21st talk on somebody so there's been a lot of foundation hopefully to
lead up to this that um if some of you are new to this that maybe by now uh
maybe you can start seeing a little hint a glimmer of the pleasure that might be
there the pleasantness the sense of well-being and um and when the Buddha
recognized it from his um uh uh uh you know that he had it as a
child and then now this is the way forward um he said I don't have to be
afraid of this kind of pleasure and again because of and his
time people were afraid of of pleasure and and uh sensual pleasure and all
kinds of things because it kept them trapped in the world and created more Bad Karma or some idea like that they
had and for him it was revolutionary to discover that there is a kind of
pleasure kind of well-being that is not a trap is not a problem but actually you don't have to
be afraid of it you can embrace it you can use that as an entry
and so the mind it's easier for the mind to want to be present if what's we're
being present for is enjoyable listening to really Pleasant
things like music listening to doing an activity that we enjoy a lot uh it's
easier to stay present and show up meditation is can be a little bit like that too eventually as we begin
understanding ourselves learning the art of being present um it isn't a direct kind of
sensual pleasure because we're getting a massage or something there starts to well up from some deep inner Source a
sense of uh rightness a sense of relief a sense of delight a sense of
pleasure that is not because of something good in the world that our
senses are being stimulated in a good way but is more related to something
begin to working in harmony the harmony of breath and mind
the har the the breathing is relaxed enough that it feels harmonious and easeful within us an easeful breath a
relaxed breath and um and an an awareness that enjoys being there and so
start be start becoming more and more sensitive to the maybe at first very
subtle sense of enjoyments or pleasure that seems to be part and parcel of the
meditation itself it might be a growing Global feeling of a hum a pleasant hum
throughout the body it might be particular part of almost like a little
you know square inch inside of a square centimeter that just has a as we breathe
when we touch that centimeter of the breath or that little brief point it just feels so poignantly
delightful uh to feel that or it might be the whole exhale just feel feel so
pleasant to Exhale but maybe not in a in a in a square centimeter kind of point
but maybe more uh like a almost like you can't fixate the attention on that
pleasure it's more there in the periphery on the edges of the breath and Edge of the sensations of breathing and
so you you you better not fixate on it look for it but you kind of just allow it to be there as a nice supporting
pleasure that provides a kind of biof feedback mechanism where when that
pleasure is there connected to breathing that um then we're on track and that
kind of encourages the mind yes stay there keep doing what you're doing stay with the breathing ride the breath stay
absorbed in the breath and allow that pleasure to be there and even allow it to grow as you're
there so sometimes that pleasure is is a growing pleasure is the tingling of the
air going in and out of the nostrils that can get more and more intense it could be the the um the soft Rhythm and
the smoothness of an exhale in the chest or the belly it could be the the
sensation of breathing in that um maybe the the speed of it and the smoothness
of it if if it is that way um it could be that uh it's not connected to
breathing itself as I said but maybe it's more there kind of on the edges of
it just beyond the edges of breathing there's something that just feels comforting and nice and like a Radiance
perhaps so I don't know how it'll be for any of you there's in many many many ways maybe infin number of ways in which
we can feel the pleasure that's related to meditation um it's not because it's
Pleasant in the room for just the right temperature but it's really there because the way in which we're getting
connected and present for uh the focus of meditation the centering place the
settling place we're really in the in involved in that process that it feels
good like reading a good book or involved in a wonderful activity that we enjoy doing so that kind of Joy begins
welding up so I'll talk more about this this week this is the those week will'll
focus on this aspect of pleasure and um and hopefully you can
find something and so you might through the day today until we meet again 24
hours um spend more time noticing the
pleasures you feel in the activities you do and um maybe there's ways you can
drive in a pleasant way you have to adjust something so driving is Pleasant maybe how fast you drive and all kinds
of things how you sit um maybe there's ways you can bring in more pleasure in
how you cook or clean or whatever you're doing see if you can find and appreciate
how you can feel pleasure in activities you do and it might be better than the alternative if you don't do
that so thank you and I have an announcement so uh partly inspired by
what happened three years ago with this YouTube Community um we're imc's uh
having a fundraising drive this this week three years ago we did a fundraising drive for save the children
for the children and mothers and families that were suffering from the Russian in invasion of the Ukraine and
we raised $70,000 which was fantastic made AIT and we're trying to do that
again this time for the save the children's emergency fund which is going
to the places in the world where children are most uh in danger of starvation starving to
death most uh hunger homelessness all kinds of great
challenges so there'll be as money will go to Gaza to sedan I think to
Syria variety of places in the world and um and it I'm hoping that what the you
this community that we're here inspired last time will continue to inspire The
Wider IMC Community to participate in this fundraising drive and so you can read a little bit more about it and by
going to the IMC website and um and I had asked someone to post it on
the chat here today I don't know if it's appeared there but um um but if you go
on the homepage of imc's website uh there's a banner at the top that takes
you to the the donation page for the drive and also in what's new there's a
page which describes it so um so um this is one way that from out of
our meditation Community we can benefit the world and to feel like we're doing it together as a community and to the
collective power is a wonderful thing and it just a a uh I think a very
significant uh I don't know I don't know coincidence is the right word but that we plan to do this uh before the us uh
closed down the agency for International Development uh where there's now even
more challenges in this the world to get food and supplies and medicine to people in distressed situations so to uh be an
alternative to this uh has even more meaning now um and
um so thank you very much