all right let's get started then uh hello my name is May
Elliot and this week we're focusing on the theme of insight one of the conditions for
insight is samadi it's the Pali uh also known as concentration so today during the
meditation we'll do a somata practice uh a practice that helps calm and steady
the mind uh and uh the intention of doing it is that it supports the cultivation of
somebody it supports the mind to collect and gather uh so this will be a practice that's probably familiar to a lot of you
um because we'll just pay attention to the breath just a really simple breath meditation um uh and today we'll do this
by employing two of the jic factors vaka and varara sometimes these are
translated as aim and sustain or place and rub
so vaka is referring to um to placing the attention connecting the attention
with the object so it's kind of that moment of making contact with the breath becoming mindful of the felt sense of
breathing so that's vaka and then vichara is sustaining that contact you
know maintaining the contact almost like rubbing the breath with our
attention um so um so when we do this with a breath it's like we're attending
to the moment of breath starts and then really being with it for the full inhale and full
exhale I remember one uh one Retreat where I was really struggling to stay with the breath it was like I would like
touch the attention on the breath and then just like immediately slide off into thought um and uh during that
Retreat I heard this teaching on vaka and vichara and what it illuminated for me was that um I was just making contact
with the breath I was just practicing vaka um but I wasn't making any effort to sustain that contact to maintain the
contact with the breath so it was almost like um almost like stepping on a banana peel you know just like sliding right
off the breath as soon as I touched it so um hopefully as we do this practice this morning it will invite the mind
just to to um bring some continuity to your experience of breathing to help you uh help you stay
in contact uh one of the commentarial teachings talks about taka and vichara
as being a little bit like a bird in Flight you know a bird needs to exert a bit of effort to flap its wings before
it coasts in the air um so that flap uh is like making contact that's like the
vchart we make a little effort to be here to make contact with the breath um
and then we Coast right and then the the birds coasting in the air that's the vichara we Coast on the breath uh so
today we'll do some uh some flapping and coasting as we stay with the breath
making that initial effort uh and then gliding for the length of the inhale and
exhale um so that'll be our primary practice for the meditation um but
before we go there uh we'll start by cultivating a little contentment and
this is because contentment is a condition for sombody contentment can help the Mind naturally
settle so uh go ahead and find your meditation posture
a posture that helps you um feel both um upright um there's some energy in the
body also allows you to be relaxed without falling
asleep softening the
body relaxing the face and the
shoulders releasing the
belly and begin by connecting with the uh the attitude now can can you touch in to
even a slight bit of contentment as we get started
maybe connecting with a sense of this moment is enough as it
is no matter how pleasant or unpleasant this moment is can it be enough can it
be okay
even if there's a challenging mood present or emotion any discomfort in the mind or
body and there be an okayness with
it and even if there's a sense of discontent can you be
content with discontentment
so this contentment can be uh so subtle just a little okayness with
things as they are
when the mind is content uh it's less likely to chase the future uh it's less likely to try to
change the past so when the mind's content it can naturally
settle so touching into any sense that life is
okay and allowing whatever you can touch into here allowing it to settle and
soothe the system to soothe the mind and body
and from this place of contentment no matter how slight we'll connect with our anchor
with our home base whether that's the breath or the
body whatever works for you today I'll be offering instruction on the breath um
but if you use a different anchor a different home base you can translate the instruction for
yourself so Landing now sensing the breath sensing your home
base
and you might Begin by noticing the moment each breath
starts almost like catching the moment the Sun Co comes over the horizon at
dawn seeing if you can notice that moment that first moment the breath
begins
when you notice this moment this moment the breath begins you're making contact
with the breath this is
vaka aiming connecting the
attention and at any point if you lose track if you become lost in thought this
is fine just Begin Again connecting with that moment of
breath arising a beginning of the inhale
now we'll add the step of each Chara of sustaining
contact so connecting with that first arising of the inhale and then coasting
for the length of the
breath sensing feeling the sensations of breathing with that full inhale and
exhale
like a bird flapping its wings and
coasting making that little bit of effort to connect at the beginning of
each inhale and then Co
in flap and
Coast
e
e e
connecting with the breath and sustaining
contact clap and glide
very little effort to sustain contact just receiving
Sensations for a bird to Glide they just need to
allow the air to keep them Aloft just keeping their WIS their wings
out just keep your wings out keep your lungs receiving air
receiving [Music] sensation and connecting again at the
beginning of the inhale
if you find that you're frequently getting lost during the breath
cycle you might try adding another moment of
contact another moment of the taka in addition to noticing the moment
an inhale begins you might see if you can notice the moment the exhale
begins so connecting at the beginning of the breath coasting for the
inhale and connecting at the beginning of the exhale and coasting for the
exhale
adding this extra contact Point uh increases the
engagement sometimes just enough to be here just enough to support greater
continuity
e
e e
sing and feeling the
breath knowing you're breathing as you
breathe left and Coast gliding on the
breath e
for
welcome back everyone for those just arriving my name is May
Elliot and today we will be talking about samadi or
concentration as a condition for sight uh and I'd like to start by
acknowledging that there are many misconceptions about Sam when I first started meditating I
thought that the way to get concentrated was to turn the Mind into a narrow laser
beam kind of straining and focusing and bearing down to try to bring the Mind
into a unified Point um and many people have these sorts of
associations um uh even if it's on a much more subtle level concentration uh doesn't usually elicit
a sense of uh easy relaxed colle collecting um uh but turning the Mind
into a laser beam this is not exactly what the Buddha had in mind when he talked about samadi so even though
concentration uh is the most common translation uh for the word samati it really doesn't do justice to the full
meaning and Nuance of the word uh fortunately for us the Buddha offered
a variety of descriptors for somebody um that can help us kind of have like a
more robust picture of what he was uh he was speaking about so here's a quote
from the Maj manikay he said my concentrated mind was thus
purified bright unblemished rid of
imperfection Mal able wieldy and
steady so the Buddha is giving us a description of a concentrated mind um so
this is a mind that's steady that's stable uh we could say it's obedient uh
you know it's responsive if it you know if we tell it to sit it sits if we tell it to stay it
stays uh so this is a mind that's um very responsive and it's stable so today I'll be
focusing specifically on the steadiness that somebody provides this stability
that it provides and um the relevance of talking
about samadi today um is that this is what a lot of you are cultivating in your meditation practice already right
you may not feel like you're getting concentrated but the practice you're doing is training the mind to stabilize
so today uh one of my intentions is to show you the link between what you're
already doing and how this unfolds into Insight how what you're already doing um
can uh bear the fruit of insight in your practice and what I imagine is that most
of you or many of you are already doing a breath-based practice a breath-based
meditation uh where your breath is your anchor your home basee um so during the
meditation maybe you um you would direct attention to the breath and when the
mind gets lost you just reconnect with the breath this is you know really standard instruction it's a common and
skillful practice um and it's also it's a su practice a practice that cultivates
samadi and I should mention here um that there are other ways to cultivate
somebody too besides focusing on the breath you know some use the body as a whole or is the soundscape um metaphases
can be used to cultivate Som so these are there's many ways I'm just focusing on the breath because this is one very
common way um so I wanted to talk about samade um
because this is something uh you're already cultivating um and also to
clarify some of these misconceptions that ALS that that frequently go along with concentration practice um and one
of those misconceptions is that many people think that samade is the goal of practice that
you know kind of like I'm sitting meditation and I will have had a successful meditation if I get
concentrated if I don't get concentrated it's not successful and that's the goal
um so and a lot of people associate that with the thinking mind you know if I can get rid of thoughts uh then you know I
have achieved the goal of meditation um but that's actually not how it goes thinking is actually an important fun F
of the mind I couldn't be offering you these teachings without thinking we wouldn't have the for truths if we
couldn't articulate them so um the purpose is not to get rid of thoughts um
but to have a wise relationship with them and sometimes that means being able to put them down for a little
while so uh so yeah what I want to clarify here is that uh concentration is
not an end in and of itself we're not cultivating uh concentration just to get
concentrated but rather we're developing concentration so that we can see clearly
so that we can see the three characteristics uh and when we see the three
characteristics um uh impermanence unsatisfactoriness and not self when we
see these Insight is born and insight is how wisdom develops in other way words
um uh wisdom it's wisdom that liberates us it's wisdom that frees us from suff
suffering and it's wisdom that does the waking up uh so we're not just getting
concentrated to have a pleasant meditation State though that's very nice and nourishing um we're not getting
concentrated to get rid of thinking um but rather the far-reaching potential of the practice is that we can become
completely free of suffering from uh we can become free of discontent
um so um so this uprooting of greed hatred and delution is really powerful
like think of what a different world this would be um if everyone purified their heart and mind in this way that
would be a really beautiful thing um if everyone took the time to free themselves of greed and hatred this is a
powerful practice to transform our own heart and mind and a practice that benefits those around us so this this is
where our journey is taking us uh so knowing that samadi is supportive to our development on the
path um how does that work you know how does somebody function to support
Insight why is it a supportive condition for insight um so I'll use the analogy
of a snow globe to explain how this works so let's say we have a snow globe
um if we shake it uh there's going to be a little blizzard in there and you can't see anything but falling
snow but if you if you let that snow globe stabilize
uh the snow begins to settle and over time uh the liquid in the snow globe it
becomes uh crystal clear so when we're lost in our mental
movies um it's a little bit like we're always shaking the snow globe and I'm
sure you know what I mean when I mention mental movies right um you know this is when we're lost in our inner dramas you
maybe we're playing an Adventure film or a romance or a suspense thriller you know the the inner um
uh the inner movies that we play these inner dramas that are so compelling for us that we get so lost in uh so when
we're lost in these narratives in these stories of the thinking mind it's a little bit like we're always lost in a
blizzard um and what's pretty pretty amazing is that the vast majority of
humans spend an entire lifetime never allowing the blizzard to
settle you know they've never stopped shaking the snow
globe and when that blizzard is flurrying we can't see clearly um so
when we do this practice of settling the mind of being with the breath um it's
like we put our little snow globe on a cushion or a chair and we let it stabilize it actually it has the
opportunity to settle and every time we come back to the present in our meditation it's a little bit like one
snowflake uh one snow snowflake settles in the snow globe and eventually after
we return to the present enough times one by one all of the snowflakes land
the Mind settles um and it's it's a little bit like all of those snowflakes in the snow
globe finally rest on the bottom the blizzard has settled and we can see
clearly I learned a term recently for um for that particular type of silence in a
landscape ese after a snowstorm the term is it's snow
quiet and you might sense that feeling um of what it's like to step outside
after a snowstorm you know stepping out into a maybe a freshly fallen field of
snow there's a certain magnitude of Silence kind of like the whole world is
hushed I like to think it is a a soft PA
of snow so this this Stillness this quiet
settled quality of um this sort of snow
blanketed landscape Um this can be a flavor of
somat so by practicing mindfulness of breathing mindfulness of body letting go
of your mental movies you cultivate enough stability for the blizzard to settle you cultivate enough Sade for the
blizzard uh to rest and when all the snowflakes settle
uh what's hiding within the snow globe is revealed uh so some snow globes they
might have uh a quaint Village on the inside or maybe there's like a che a
Cheesy Christmas tree or something um but your snow globe is AAC ulous snow
globe because as your blizzard settles three wise sages are
revealed one is the sage of impermanence one is the sage of
unsatisfactoriness or suffering and one is not
self if the blizzard continued you would never see them but because of your
stability because of your s you could see them clearly enough you know you could see clearly enough that the three
characteristics could come into
view the Buddha said when my concentration is limited then my vision
is limited in other words when I'm caught in a blizzard when I shake the snow snow
globe I can't see clearly when I'm lost in thought all the time I can't see clearly my vision is limited
and then the Buddha went on to say the purpose and benefit of concentration is
to see things as they really are he's saying this is he's saying this is what
concentration is all about it's to see things the way they really are and what's the way things really are things
are impermanent unable to provide lasting satisfaction and without a fixed
abiding self or as one teacher phrased the three marks the three characteristics nothing is permanent
nothing is perfect and nothing is personal so this is what we're seeing
clearly and um so now that you know the purpose and benefit of concentration um
it could be really tempting to strain and strive to make it happen but as you already know that doesn't work wholesome
somebody does not come about through straining and striving um so rather than thinking of Sade as something that you
huff and puff to get um or make happen um instead you might think of it as a
visitor that arrives on its own time uh when we've put the appropriate conditions in
place um and there are many conditions for concentration as I already mentioned
um but one of these one condition for concentration is contentment uh so this is why we started
our meditation practice let's see if we could connect with with a little contentment
um and as as I share about this remember um that we're cultivating the Dharma to
grow in our heart and when we do that we can't we can't demand that it grows faster right we can't force we can't
force growth um and so in the same way that we can't force Insight we can't
force somebody either but we can provide these supportive conditions so so
contentment um it's how translating the word Suka Suka is often translated as
happiness um um and I I mention contentment as a
condition for somebody because so often um we sit down to meditate and we think
we need to get concentrated in order to be happy in order to be content but
here's what's radical it's also the other way around it's contentment that
conditions concentration so contentment is a condition for concentration and this makes so much
sense because the mind that's Happy the mind that's content it's not worried
about the future it's not spiraling and planning mind because it's so anxious uh
it's not ruminating about the past and regretting and uh filled with shame and
guilt you know it's not seeking sense Pleasures a mind that's content it can
naturally collect it can naturally settle you know it doesn't it doesn't have any reason to be flying around like
a a pinball it's content so uh what's the relevance for
you um what's the relevance of um knowing that contentment is a condition
for concentration so let's say um you're interested in cultivating
somebody what would it be like to sit down to meditate and instead of trying
to get concentrated to start by cultivating contentment to see if you can connect
with a sense of contentment with whatever is happening for you even if there's a difficult mood or
emotion or a painful sensation in the body um can there be just like a thread
of contentment there a simple okayness with things as they are and like I said
in the meditation even if there's discontent can you be content with
discontentment so um so this is one condition for
samade um contentment and then our samade becomes a condition for
insight so tomorrow uh we'll begin our three-day exploration of the Three core
insights of the Buddha starting with anicha or impermanence so I will see you
tomorrow for an exploration of the changing nature of
phenomena very glad to have you here take care