hello on this Thursday in Redwood
City at the Insight Meditation Center
welcome and um one of the amazing capacities we have
as human beings is attention and using the word attention to
highlight this is to point out that attention is a very uh broad term that
encompasses uh all the different attentional faculties that we have so to
to pay attention to offer attention to be attentive um is uh different ways that
we attend to something attending with
attention and sometimes we attend sometimes we we are aware sometime
through our eyes sometimes uh we might be aware
mostly through our ears some people who can see will close their eyes in order to hear
better we might uh attend through our
nostrils or through a taste when we're eating food or and
um remember when I was a kid haven't done this for a long time and we wanted
to know whether a a small battery was uh especially was uh still had a charge in
it and we would put our use our tongue to taste to feel to feel the the little
charge that was left um and um there was uh we attend
through uh something something that uh is not exactly connected to any of the
sense stors we might attend or by knowing something carefully it's
cognitive if we see an oak tree uh we might know it as being in
California a Valley Oak or a coastal oak or a Black Oak and
um and that's how we attend to it to recognize it and we might have a kind of there's
something called the inner eye nothing mystical about it but the way of being
aware that um it's kind of like uh seeing with the regular eye but kind of
just kind of uh being aware without any of the sense doors at the center of it
and uh just somehow some deeper place in the mind that knows that watches that
senses that feels what's happening so all these ways in which attention comes
into play and um and when people meditate
they'll use sometimes one or two of these uh with uh some
tension with some prioritization with some sense that uh that we're the doer
of it that we we are it in some ways we are defined by by by being aware or we
have to engage awareness in some way that we get contracted or tight or put
pressure on something and um the art of
Somali is to more awake to awareness
more allow awareness more trust the capacity for
attention rather than active applying it in a way that is tense or
straining so there's a softness or an openness or broadness or a lightness to
the how we attend how attention operates when we're entering into the in the
practice of samadi and um and at the same time there
is a kind of a there is a persistence there is a gentle stress
free um um kind of I don't know if commitment is
too biger word uh devotion dedication there's a a uh hanging
hanging in there a a
engagement that has no stress in it but it kind of like Keeps Us close to it like this is important this is
valuable this is interesting fascinating important this is precious a treasure
stay close to it be it so that it we stay in that world
continuously we stay attending continuously with a attention
and I'd like to offer another aspect of how to do this uh and this theme today
of being inclusive that Sadi is including everything rather than excluding and um at least
initially and that is to associate Sade with
composure to be composed in the middle of things to be at the middle of your
experience to have some choose a place that's a centering spot the settling spot the
place around which everything will be composed and then we're composing
ourselves um kind of when I when I was young the older generation used the
language of compose yourself and um it was an important concept for certain people in the
english- speaking world word world and when I was growing up I think we kind of pulled away from it as being maybe a
little bit too formal or a little bit too contrived but there's something quite
lovely about being settled being whole being
all of us there in a aligned balanced kind of composed way
whether we're standing or whether we're sitting or lying down or the idea that we're there to compose
ourselves bring all of who we are together and um and be centered
in um and then with that composure to stay
there stay composed stay centered stay
grounded stay
present so a light soft attending awareness
that supports our whole being becoming
composed holistically without being caught up in the concepts
so much just enough Concepts to support composure and presence in the midst of
it all so to assume a meditation posture
a posture in which it might be easier to compose
physically compos settle be
balanced and softly closing the eyes
and as you breathe in see become
aware let your attention almost expand
outwards to become aware of your body
globally almost as with the inhale the attending the attention the
sensations rise from deep inside and spread out
through the whole body as much of the whole body that's
easy and maybe even delightful to
experience and as you exhale not just settle or relax the body
but do so in a way that feels like you're composing yourself
that you're Gathering and settling
yourself around a central settling Place Gathering
Place grounding place
and as you breathe in feeling the global
body imagine that your
body is like a There's No Boundaries there's no
edges especially with your eyes closed it might be easier
that there's no edges to
awareness imagine that your body from the inside and
outside is like vast open
space and the awareness of that space
spaciousness is inseparable from the space
itself to be aware of any kind of
spaciousness awareness of some kind is
present breathing in and letting there be a spreading outwards into that
space space beyond your body and as you
exhale settling in here
and see if you can recognize the
lightest easiest softest way in which you could
know be aware as attend to the global
body the spacious body as you breathe
in in a soft relaxed way relaxing
way that you compose and relax and settle your whole being on the
exhale and while you're attending to the body breathing in and breathing out
there's a very light soft connection
intimacy between the experience of breathing and the awareness of
it almost as if it's space spaciousness
that attends to
breathing e
and maybe like you would be sitting firmly relaxedly on a
bench where there's a vast view of mountains and
space great distance and both are there you are
centered on the bench content
happy while there is this wide
attention so allow yourself to the allow attention
allow yourself to sit on the bench of your settling
Point centering place place
where from where your inhale
begins where the exhale ends
stay close to that feeling the
changes the oscillations the Rhythm rest
there softly with a peripheral
attention the wide soft
attention lightly aware of the whole
body the spacious
body all of which
is oriented all of which is
settling all of which
surrounds the settling place with
breathing e
relaxing the thinking mind so that the
spacious body can
feel the vacuum that's left when there's very little
thinking
e
for
for e
and as we come to the end of the
sitting with the exhale maybe even with the inhale
feel a gentle weight in your body or a gentle pull
or to be settled in the
body as if the gentle pull from gravity is welcoming awareness
attention to settle with the settling
body into a settling
place a grounding place within
and that radiating from that grounding Place spreading from
it is an open
awareness simple relaxed form of
attention that's available for the world
that's open receptive
available while settled in the grounding
place and from there to have the Gaz spread out into the
world or from there have all the
world come to you come to your
awareness and to meet that with
friendliness to meet that with compassion and
love to meet that with a dedication to honesty and
Truth to an ethical goodness that arises from the Simplicity
of this subtle Place deep
within trusting being
settled and being available in a kind way to whatever
comes available with kindness and
care may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we realize that we don't have to react or go out or be
actively responsive we can be available
and peacefully
responsive to offer Good Will to our entire world may all beings be happy
[Music]
[Music] thank
you e
so welcome to this um now the 19th talk
on on samadi as we go very slowly into this
topic and um avoiding a headlong dive into
Samad an assertive kind of approach to really getting it and being deeply
concentrated but almost allowing it to grow in its own partly out of becoming more and more
familiar with your inner life your inner life of attention the different ways of
being attentive the different ways of being being aware the different ways of
that we can begin Gathering ourselves together becoming
composed being settled being gathered here all of us who we who we
are and for each of you this is going to be a different process and my words my instructions my
suggestions uh are just suggestions or pointers for you to begin to discover
what works for you what how are you what's going on what's your inner landscape like and how could your inner
landscape become whole not divided not
fragmented and um and somadi has a lot to do with becoming whole and uh the classic language for
that is unification and um and uh
and I like to think of it as a you know Gathering everything together to be so everything's
included and everything is a lot of stuff you don't have to make an inventory of everything that you could
possibly do to kind of bring it in it's more a sense of um of uh a kind of
availability and expansiveness a presence that we have attention we have
which is not divided which doesn't actively limit and block things
and it's so easy to be preoccupied and the world that we're available to is
just very narrow and small uh it's very easy to have a particular idea belief
orientation about things and then we just zero in on that that becomes
important and uh and we don't notice anything else and the idea that samade is a
one-pointedness can lend itself to the idea of it's attention with blinders on
and uh and we're just really going to really bore into some some objects of
attention but rather than that to open awareness up to take take off the
blinders and um and be available in a very relaxed open way to the whole world
to everything and in the process of that to um become composed settled gathered
um in a in a way that we're sitting at the center of all things we're sitting at
the center of vast space or a center of all things
included um and um and uh and you know I've said this
many times but um I I to me it's very meaningful to use the analogy of uh
central vision and peripheral vision and so there's kind of a
central way in which we can become be aware attentive to what's happening we can have a center but then also there's
this peripheral awareness that this place where there's no edges where we're not staring at it you can't stare at
what's at the periphery of attention you have to kind of be have a soft and relaxed and kind of kind of a wide
angle kind of seeing to see peripheral awar uh uh attention
eyesight and um so the same thing with awareness and so to to be aware of
ourselves and be aware to find a place that's the the I call it the S settling
place the centering place the Gathering Place the the
um the um I have other words but uh uh that
that's that's a center of it all that it can be the place where we uh stand take
a stand take to compose ourselves on and uh it's almost like being there maybe
taking a stand but then opening our metaphorical arms really wide to be be
available to what's what's there to all around but we feel grounded settled on
this place and uh and then the other analogy is out of a bowl and the bowl
has a center at the bottom and and so everything can begin kind of angling
towards that Center and be included in the bow but everything kind of points to
the center everything um rolls towards a center that's going to roll it's all included in this wide bowl of
spaciousness um and um the um so the
um so the language of today the the the
the idea today is that of comp being composed in ourselves so uh take a deep
breath relax be composed osed and maybe be oriented the whole
attention now is oriented towards that place at the center where the centering
place is we compose ourselves We Gather everything else around it and so that
there's a wide open sense of light awareness that supports the primary
attentiveness to that Center Point and if that is connected to breathing that
it's the place where where the inhale Begins the exhale ends at the same place
uh and maybe the whole time we're at that place that point where it begins we
don't actually leave it there's a way in which that's the bench we sit on that's
the ground we stand on as we open up and become aware of what's wider not with
this active intentional attention exactly but rather this peripheral awareness that um that opens up and
allows everything then to get become composed around that
Center and what happens over time is that uh this uh if there then can be
this not a straining attention a narrow attention a laser focus attention there
can be a um a a a centered attention there that
over time um that becomes uh more and more
the kind of Fuller and richer and fills awareness more and more and and in some
ways the objects around us the objects in our body elsewhere begin to recede
into the spaciousness kind of become less and less attentive and aware and uh
and uh at some point you people even feel that there's no body anymore around
it it's all just kind of space and particular sensation ations maybe that are floating in space uh because the
minds latching on the mind holding on looking and wanting and not wanting um
labeling uh being concerned with judging as quieted down and its very mind
becomes more and more content to rest at this centering place at the spot where
we're getting oriented we're getting composed we're getting
settled and um and uh how big that place is and spot is varies from person to
person some it can be very small some people it can be a broader place but it
is a place where we're kind of this is where we're there's a continuity of attention and we're kind of not leaving
it we're not losing touch with it we're not uh uh getting lost in thoughts and
preoccupation ation and so one of the supports for this uh is this
gentle but but ongoing uh counting uh and some people can just
count up to one and start over again and that keeps the mind really simple but there's something gives us a little bit
like a little bit that gives us the emphasis stay there rest there stay open
there sometimes it's useful to count to 10 because that requires a higher order
um tracking of it in the mind and so the mind is a little bit more engaged uh
instead of its tendency to wonderand off in thought some people don't like the counting but it might actually be better
than the alternative the alternative to have the mind wander off that CH that um
Groove to WAND off is so well oiled and Slick that it just feels smooth and nice
and easy to wander off in thought and be lost and it's not really helpful for who
who allowing somat to arise and so even though it feels less
satisfying to count then to let the mind wander off uh it still might be the better alternative to keep you there to
keep you there and um and what happens with something like the counting is
after a while the counting becomes softer lighter easier more natural and
it supports the Gathering it's like the Mind begins to um
uh accept that this is what we're doing being here on the Simplicity of the
moment moment after moment and when that happens when the Mind finally relaxes
and settles and you know is no longer afraid or Desiring or wanting or um and
you really settle in to being right here it can be such a
relief it allows so much sense of uh goodness and health and satisfaction and
contentment to beginner Rising um but there is a transition and uh sometimes the counting
can help us overcome that hurt that bump to really be able to settle in so
counting 1 to 10 and at this point I recommend uh you count the exhale so the
inhale can really be living there in the wake of the each count on the exhale to
really allow uh this quiet awareness to fill us
being and being centered there so
um so to sit
quietly and and begin learning the wonderful
art of using this wonderful multifaced capacity that we have for
attention that can be a vehicle for love so much so that at some point attention
and love might seem the same thing and Somali can seem not as a engineering
feat but can seem as a flowering of a kind of love that we're very happy to be
completely in as uh and let everything else kind of dissolve into the
spaciousness of awareness as as we stay uh in the settling spot the grounding
spot and maybe that description I just gave is what's coming and uh maybe it
gives you a little preview but we'll continue step by step and uh and uh thank you very much