hello everyone greetings greetings wherever you are in the world
um good morning good afternoon good evening and uh I'm joining you from uh
Tuscanany still this is the last uh day the fifth day of our there perfectly
timed ears oh okay we get lots of bells at the beginning the um the 400
p.m so lovely to be with you and share um
these teachings about SA about community this
week excuse me sharing uh the uh teachings and feeling into the
importance of community of spiritual friends and not just our receiving of
community which is where our mind goes usually but but um how can we be a a
caring kind beneficial member of the community
so we've been covering different themes different aspects uh this week and
um and today I wanted to uh speak about
the um the six principles of
cordiality and um the Buddha talks about these six principles and and yes the
um Buddhism has a lot of lists the Buddha loved a lot of uh lists i love
lists i hope you love them too and um this particular list of six principles
of cordiality are from Angutan Nikica 612
the the S ra the
Siauta and a difference between the the teaching today that
these are the the six principles and I'll mention them very briefly and then
I'll guide a meditation uh aligned with them is the way we think the way we hold
others in our hearts and minds minds so the three of the six aspects have to do
with loving kindness actions of the body actions of speech actions of thought how
do we think about others do we think of them with kindness and
um and the uh the other ones also have to
do with sharing virtue sharing views uh li uh this this living ethically whereas
what we covered yesterday just to bring a distinction was the four principles of
embracing the four grounds of embracing others so there were more um
actionoriented yesterday we talked about generosity Donna we talked about kind
speech and uh uh service acts of service
as well as uh embracing others with equality with openness of heart with
with um seeing them on the same level as as I so so nuances in the teachings and
maybe I'll expand it further so so without further ado the guided
meditation today as we settle um after we settle in the body of course
mindfulness of the body mindfulness of the breath first and then inviting some
of these principles of how do we hold in our hearts ourselves others these uh
these principles ways of being in community ways of being in
community practicing ways of being in community so so with
that let's um let's sit
together so landing
arriving arriving in our
bodies arriving in this moment in time
this moment has it has never been and will never be exactly like this
and can we arrive in the body relaxing
softening the shoulders the neck opening the chest a little bit as if we're
greeting the world greeting ourselves and this human life settling
into our sitbones taking our seat on this earth
does it really feel like to take your seat in this moment in time really take
your seat in the midst of this being human
just as you are embracing embracing all of you all your beingness taking your
seat with confidence and humility both confidence and
humility feeling the connection of your feet your legs with the earth
earth on
earth connection of your sitbones let your sitbones soften offer their weight to
the earth relax release
allowing the breath to be received relaxing and receiving the
breath calming soothing settling each inb breath and
out breath
any clear thoughts arising taking us into the past
future can we see them can we see them with kindness not with
aversion perhaps smilingly and say thank you not now i'll come back to you later
please come after I'm done practicing smilingly knowing what the
thought was about and releasing
releasing feeling the goodness the peace of
release and settling with kindness
right here right
now where the heart and mind can be nourished
and now I would like to invite you if you
would bringing to heart maybe
one or multiple if that feels more appropriate for you
friends good friends benefactors maybe spiritual friends maybe members of
your community SA whether it's this community
here online or a dear good friend you
have who's kind and wise
allow your heart to be free to invite anyone that feels right feels
appropriate one multiple people one person multiple people
let your heart be relaxed as if you're sitting
in the comfortable space opening the door of your heart
inviting inviting who feels appropriate to come and sit with you maybe one person enters into this chamber of your
heart in this moment in time whatever feels appropriate see if
you can sit with this
friend these friends part of your community with
kindness with
friendliness in the space of goodwill very simple space of goodwill thoughts
of goodwill permeate the space of the heart feelings of
goodwill well-wishing
friendliness if there are phrases that want to come in naturally from your history of doing meta practice it's okay
you can bring in phrases or just let it be
wordless receiving and sharing goodwill friendliness
holding space holding space of kindness goodwill in your heart
friends benefactors spiritual friends community
members SA members make your make sure you are included
too in this holding with goodwill and
friendliness don't leave yourself out
it feels okay expanding the heart to also invite folks
who are practicing with you through this sa through this
community on YouTube you might have never met them but maybe
their names have become familiar as they say good morning good
afternoon inviting them to this heart space to
this sitting space this hall of your heart that you've opened this open house
open house of your heart letting them come and take a seat
all of us together all of us a space of goodwill
kindness fostering goodwill for one another for ourselves
this is the [Music] glue in sana goodwill
meta and thoughts words and
actions stay with thoughts thoughts of meta goodwill
imagine all these beings from various places around the
globe this invisible network that connects us all sharing
goodwill like Indra's net this invisible net invisible
net where we give and receive this golden light of
friendliness goodwill friendliness the benefit of the doubt training ourselves
In seeing
goodness seeing friendliness acting speaking
thinking with friendliness
and as we keep stretching my last
invitation if there are people in your community in your circle and you're
having a little bit of a challenge with you feel stretched by and they feel
stretched by you can you invite them to let them come and be in this space of
goodwill not condoning the harm but seeing allowing their
humanity
including them in the goodwill
perhaps with some relationships where there's been strain for a long time
unresolved it's time to move on and share goodwill
move on from holding on grasping to the
hurt not being so loyal to our
suffering moving on to possibility
and we allow and invite our heart to grow to
grow
expand
possible and our sense of this being who is me sense of ourselves growing with it
expanding with it
in a human earthy
humble kind way
as we turn to bring this sit to a close
together inviting ourselves to be held in the
community with kindness with goodwill with appreciation or having showed
up or practicing kindness goodwill aligning our
actions with our intentions may all beings
everywhere know their own goodness may all beings everywhere be
kind to one another may all beings everywhere be happy may all beings everywhere be
free including
ourselves thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so nourishing and beautiful to to sit with different aspects of of
friendship community and and especially for me as I was practicing with you who is really beautiful and heart expanding
to to um imagine all of us sitting together all of you all of us different
places in the world just really uplifts my heart and um yeah so much goodness so
much goodness to uplift the heart so much goodness in this community if if
you've been coming for a long time or if you're new the first time you're part of this community because you're showing up
you've showed up So taking a pause before I transition to
the teaching Hey
So hello again and welcome everyone
so today is the fifth and last day of sharing teachings
um exploring teachings together on sana on community on friendship
um how to show up how to embrace others
um how to be with others uh spiritual friendship and spiritual friendship how
uh to be with others and and Anga etc so so today I want to um share uh
teachings from Angutara Nikica 612 and um this is
um the English translation is the six principles of cordiality six principles
of cordiality and um the name of the uh the in Pali
they're known as the sa rania dhhamas sana dhammas which literally means the
qualities that are worth remembering or the virtues that create harmony and
endearment so in other
ways the the theme really is the how can we live together in with kindness with
cordiality in these six principles um are ways that the Buddha instructs us
invites us to be in our hearts and minds the way we share of ourselves and our
mind space and heart space and again it's a little bit different from the
teachings that I shared yesterday and uh the teachings yesterday as I mentioned
earlier um where uh basically what they
the um they are referred to as the sana vatuni the four saha vatuni
And those four principles those are known as the four means of embracing
others the four ways and they're more actionoriented if you remember the list
yesterday again Buddha loves lists um the on the list yesterday was um donna
generosity acts of giving sharing of resources and goodwill there was kind and affectionate
speech uh pavaja uh there was beneficial action or service for the sake of others
atacharia this um beautiful term atachara beneficial action and sama
sama I'll say it again sama sama tata
sama how many t's wait hold on I lost track of my t's sama
[Music] samaata samaata there we go samaata
which means impartiality equality which basically is this beautiful idea of of
embracing others as equals not with pride not looking down on others that's
the way to embrace others so these ways of embracing others again with generosity with with kind speech with
service and with equality this open heart um being equitable humble fair
open so those four principles of of embracing others beautiful teaching now
today these another way of seeing this and the Buddha's teaching the the six um ways of
the six uh qualities the six principles of cordiality and as we I talk about
them and and the six are maybe I'll just mention what the six are first so the
six the first three of the six are loving kindness in bodily action meta
kayakama so meta in bodily action pra uh practicing acts of kindness towards
others helping protecting nonharming service the second is kindness in a
verbal action loving kindness and verbal action in poly meta
viama meta I'll say that
again meta so kindness in words uh speaking
kindly encouragingly honestly gently avoid avoiding harsh and divisive
speech and the third principle of the six is loving kindness in mental action
i love this one in particular the teaching on this one in particular
this is about uh thinking of others with kindness so
meta kama so silently thinking thoughts of
goodwill about others wishing them well in your heart even if there is no
outward expression of words or actions but but thinking about them in in kind
ways giving them the benefit of the doubt i especially love this one is really the way we silently in in our
thinking even when we don't see them how we regard them what we think of them do we regard others with
kindness so the first three of the six principles again have to do with loving kindness in action in speech and in uh
thoughts and so you see that loving kindness really meta goodwill has is is
six is 50% of these six principles right one two three have to do with different
aspects of meta and I love that the Buddha has unpacked it it's not just oh
go do meta now just go do it in your in your thoughts it's it's there is this nuance of oh do it in in your actions do
it in your speech do it in your thoughts silently
Um again putting so much emphasis on goodwill and then the fourth here the
fourth principle here is um is sharing of material possessions sharing material
gains uh sa da ran boi
s I'll do it again maybe I'll put also these polies in the chat afterwards sa
sabogi sa this one is a tough one for me uh sa
dan boi which means sharing of uh sharing
with our reservations but it always good to have a sense of humor of course about uh about oneself and and the the the
beautiful poly language with all the dietitics so um so the sharing this
sharing of of uh one's resources um it
it brings it creates a culture of a
generosity trust non-possessiveness and non- jealousy so
so especially in uh in the Buddhist communities when uh monastics for
example uh monastics live together the invitation or the teaching here is for
them to be sharing of all sharing alms foods with one another so often only one
one monk goes to the village and gets alms food and brings it back and shares it with everybody else to share medicine
to share ropes to share all the resources that they have which is very
little the fifth one of the principles is sharing ethical conduct
sila sa mana this one is easier to say sila the word for ethical conduct sila
sa sila sila sa which is sharing our ethics sharing
our ethics with one another living ethically with one another the five
precepts the five ethical trainings to live according to to them with one
another which again ensures a mutual trust and stable foundation for deeper
practice because when we trust that this other person is not going to lie to us
or or steal or take or harm us this just automatically creates a sense of trust
in the community so sila sa mana sila sa
[Music] mana and the sixth and the last one in the series is um is sharing of right
view which is di sa di sa di is wise
view right view sana is to share it with others
so here is about um sharing this view be
in this community having speaking from living from sharing the the perspective
uh that is uh that that one that upholds wisdom and wisdom and compassion and the
various principles wise view the four noble truths the eight-fold path it's basically this view of uh of as if we
had um we had the wi uh awakened perspective as if we had the awakened
perspective in the way of you know fake it till you become it so so living from that place treating ourselves living um
and exuding this this sense of um this vision of a bigger a bigger sense of of
possibility um of ourselves and each other and community so living sharing that view
with one another not living from this smallminded place but but sharing
um living from this this higher this this more expansive place of our hearts
uh with with one another and again when I say community there's so many different shapes uh and forms to a
community there could be community of two your spiritual friendships could be the community of hundreds here on online
etc so many different ways to really consider the teachings on community
so so um and and these teachings really allow for a nonvisible
uh field of safety and trust in in the way that we interact with each other and
with ourselves and we hold ourselves and there's so much more dignity also the sense of dignity that arises for us as
we um live in this way so so I want to leave you with some reflections as um I
have every day of this week so um here are the reflections for today uh which
of these six principles are most alive for me today um in this moment that I
want to really take on and and feel into today um and how can I more fully
support the harmony of my SA through conscious daily practice of of these
principles of these six principles and I and here's a third I I'm particularly
fond of this reflection I'm about to give you um what might change if I
silently if I silently held others with goodwill throughout the day what might
change if I silently held others in goodwill throughout the
day and maybe I'll leave it at that i think that's enough those three
reflections and I want to thank you all actually um and I want to thank IMC for
and also Gail for inviting me to share these teachings with you this week and IMC for offering all this support to us
in the background and also a host of awesome tech support volunteers online
who have my back and your back and and really are supporting these teachings
and here come the bells maybe I can Let's see um
so let's see there we go so you can hear the
bells and I also wanted to say that um this teaching this week has been
inspired by uh a book by Bikubodi um which is called the Buddha's
teachings on social and communal harmony i'll put it in chat and also I'll put my
website in chat which is where you can find me so and I want to thank you at
the end thank you so much to all of you for for your practice for your sharing
for for uh being here being online practicing with with one another and
being part of this community and I just put both
um both links in chat maybe I'll do it again here we go so here are the
teachings here is the reference to Picobody's book there we go
and here is my website also there you go great so thank you all thank you so much
for your practice this whole week it's been a delight to be with you from here
in Tuscanyany especially with the bells okay take good care thanks
everyone be well