and hello again greeting you from Redwood City
California on this guided meditation as part of the samade
series and one of the at some point as the mindfulness
gets stronger the sensitivity gets stronger the momentum of the practice
gets stronger that's what we feel is the momentum or we feel the movement of the
practice or we feel the way or the place in which the practice is
growing or the place with that that feels onward
leading that there's a place there's a there's a feeling that
yes uh something is happening here and it's good and it's good to stay
with it and go along with it and um to be kind of very simplistic
about it it could be as simple as feeling the muscle tense in some way and
feeling that if you really sense the muscles that are tense tight you can almost feel the
desire a momentum movement that wants to happen
which is the muscles to relax and so it is that there's a kind
of easing kind of relaxing a kind of onward moving a gathering together a
unification a feeling oh yes yes this is good this is going someplace or there's
this is the place to be or this is where things are
releasing this is the place where things are becoming concentrated gathering
together this is the place that feels like we're growing or something is developing or something really good is
about is happening and that feeling of onward leading is really when it when it
happens it doesn't always happen there has to be some deepening of the
practice then we're starting to approach What's called the approach stage of
somebody where we feel that we're coming into a territory or getting close to
something so there's many ways of describing this feeling of onward
movement of the meditation practice and to feel it and sense it and
then to go along with it or that supports the Gathering it usually comes
with a sense of rightness yeah yes a sense of this is where I want to be not
anywhere else and so it supports the Gathering Together the unification of
who we are it's not necessarily going to feel it from day to day it can vary quite a
bit but when to know about it means that um when you recognize it that supports
its growth that can that can then it can help there be there to support you
can also so it could also be there to trip you up if you get too involved with
it part of the beauty of this onward leading feeling is that it's not part of our
Desire System it's not part of our willful system or system of self me and
my and I it's almost as if it's something profound within us that is not
us or not part of our willfulness or our
desires or our Cravings that is operating it's something to let go
into so to assume a meditation
posture and part of the role of an intentional aligned
posture is to begin that heightened sensitivity in the
body that can sense the subtle movements the subtle
unfolding that might appear and softly closing your eyes and
letting your eyes rest in their eye sockets
sitting quietly in your
[Music] posture sitting quietly Here and Now
and feeling your body whatever is happening in your
body and sense if there's any place in your body that would like your
attention not that it's screaming for it necessarily but any place in your body
that says please my friend come come here bring attention here to this
part and to take a few long slow deep breaths breathing
through or with this place that wants attention that calls on you
and as you exhale relax and soften all around
it as you have a longer exhale than usual is there a place in the exhale the
end of the exhale that would like your
attention welcomes
it some place in the body where the final feelings of exhale
appear and and letting your breathing return to normal and spending some time relaxing
in your body on the inhale feeling the muscles of your
face Maybe feeling if they would like to relax or
soften on the exhale to soften in the face
on the inhale to feel the shoulders and feel if there's any desire
or momentum in the shoulders to
relax on the exhale
to soften the
shoulders and inhale feeling the
belly on the exhale softening in the
belly on the inhale feeling the thinking mind feeling and if anything wants to
relax or soften or quiet in the thinking mind
on the exhale let there be a softening a
quieting in the thinking mind
on the inhale feeling any way in which your whole body
is bracing itself or
collapsing on the exhale to to relax the
bracing or release the collapse so your body
straightens
aligns for
relaxing into the body
breathing as if there's a wide circle of sensations of the
body that around breathing and as as you breathe as you
exhale all those
Sensations incline towards the
breathing the sensations of breathing
and in the softest way
gently count your breaths up to three and then do it
again a counting that is loving that is caring
gentle as if it's gently brushing
stroking each
breath
for
e
for for
with a heightened sensitivity
allow your body to feel the
entirety of breathing in the entirety of breathing
out perhaps mostly in some place where the
breathing is Pleasant
quiet where the experience of breathing
welcomes you to stay with
it for
and as you give yourself [Music] over to your
breathing is there any feeling in the breathing any place in the
body it feels like the right place for your awareness to be
where there's a subtle feeling of yes
here perhaps where there's some semblance of an onward leading
feeling this is the way forward staying close to
this and if so re
give yourself over to
it allow yourself to
feel the very subtle momentum
of here this is onward
leading
e
for
e for
one aspect of the onward leading nature of the
practice is related to Faith or
confidence that has within it a
desire to be more present to be awake and present for our
experience because knowing how good this is having faith in
mindfulness attention brings an onward leading
desire to being more fully here for our experience
and as we come to the end of this sitting to appreciate that Faith
confidence in being present for our life being present for the experience
translates as a kind of a love care respect for those we
encounter there is a very subtle maybe sometimes not so
subtle faith and confidence it's good to be
present each person in their own way
but to be present and attentive aware of those were
with and this is onward leading onward
leading to a peaceful and harmonious Society
may this practice of mindfulness the practice of
samadi support us in being Mindful and
present for that onward leading nature of building a harmonious Society
may all beings be happy may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
safe and may all beings
everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you [Music]
hello and welcome to the 35th talk of this Samar series
and um and as the Mind
relaxes as our ability to be centered and be more fully present
here there is this amazing feeling that to be here fully and completely is not a
static thing but there's an onward leading nature to it there's something
that wants to move through us something that wants to express itself something wants to be for us and that can be many
things but in terms of somi when we're giving ourselves over to this giving you
know one primary activity of just being present here for example for the
breathing that starts to kind of become the place that the whole Mind Body
Gathers enters into and the goodness of it the rightness of it yes the feeling of yes
this is where I want to be this is healthy this is appropriate um it begins to stand out
and highlight when we start realizing that
to be cut up in our thoughts cut up in our plans our worries our memories our
regrets our know our irritations or
complaints that is not not as healthy as being really here
fully being here in the deep samadi is almost like having entering into a deep
vacation a deep rest a deep healthy alternative to the usual way in which
the mind is stressful what what it does and it feels good to be there it feels
like this is a healthy mind this is a healthy heart and body and there's a kind of feeling of yes to
this and that feeling of yes uh has a kind of feeling of there's an onward
leading nature there's a it's um it's similar to being on the top of a slide
and you're you you maybe slid a little bit down the slide and then hold on to
the side so you don't go any further but you can feel the tug the pull of gravity
that wants to kind of pull pull you down if you just let
go and uh and so the same thing there's a kind of a slide or a kind of a of a of
a movement that we can feel that is not um that it's kind of like the pull of
the the heart's gravity or the gravity of the inner life that um is not willful
it's not a desire from the usual uh self that wants and expects and demands and
is disappointed it's almost as B it's a kind of a biological feeling that is
deeper than any mental movement of the
mind and um and to appreciate that uh to be fully present
is not static but is being part is to join to join a kind of momentum to join
the living uh stream of life that now is
kind of going along into more and more presence more and more just here just
with this experience and certainly there are times in ordinary life where we get absorbed
in a particular activity it just feels so good to some people say they feel
lost in the activity and they just can't wait to get go back into it they might
get pulled out and sometimes it's interesting to see how being pulled out of activity we're absorbed in their part
of the mind just wants to come back it's like the momentum is there and and
um and then as soon as we let go of the other thing that has to be taken care of
it feels so good to be back in the groove and this is the way to go this is the way to move
forward and um so uh it's actually very
useful for the purpose of somebody to not just be willfully trying not not at
all to be kind of willfully kind of pushing and straining to concentrated
but a lot of it is letting go but not but it's letting go at some point
into uh the onward leading nature into this way in which our
system wants to move forward by stepping into to more
into the experience more deeply give ourselves over to the experience more deeply and sometimes this onward leader
nature can can uh take the form that we Fe just a subtle feeling that says oh
this is where the attention should be uh it might be if it's connected to
the breathing it might be this part of the body should where attention should
be and like rest having attention rest there like a hand hand resting on a
maybe on your thigh uh just now it's the the the hand of awareness is resting on
some place in the body where breathing is felt and sometimes that shifts and
changes as we develop the practice um I've often had the experience of uh I
stay I'm often centered on my belly as I breathe feeling the movements of my belly as I breathe but then sometimes as
the mind as the breathing gets quieter and quiet sometimes the the the place that feels
like the this is where the attention should be moves up to the middle of the chest and I feel this little movements
in the chest there and then sometimes it moves again sometimes it moves back to
just a little Point uh of pressure a little point of of sensation uh deep
somehow deep in the belly below the belly button somehow and it's just like that this is where the attention should
be and there might be almost no movement if I'm really still and quiet but
there's a feeling oh this is where the attention wants to be this is onward leading or this is where the request is
this is where the where it feels the yes is there and this yes this onward leading
nature can also be related to a number of other things one of them is it can be
related to um faith and Faith s in P is
um is um is a kind of a desire a healthy
desire that says yes this is where it's right to be this is what wants to happen
this is what I have faith in this is what I have confidence in and again it's not I even though I say I it's something
deeper inside that not really the control tower the control self this is
the place where there's a natural system operating the natural system has this
faith has this confidence has his yes has this desire yes stay here be with
this and um but don't push it don't if
you feel the onward leading nature let go into it participate in it but don't
bring the the control self the control desires um to bear like okay now I'm
going to do it really well I can feel it and now I'm going to really push against it or or you know but it's it's more
like be soft ease into it trust it the faith is
the TR is it can also can be a trust trust this experience and Trust to go
along with it and this is particularly important for samadi because any degree
of concentration that we have always has a lifetime concentration you can't just
get into a state of Som and stay there for forever it always has a lifetime where it Peaks and then it's going to
fade away and so if you're uh coming with your kind of control desires to want to
get concentrated um then you might be overriding uh the the wave of somadi
that's going through and part of the art of somadi is also to appreciate when the
the peak of whatever degree of subtleness you have and
past and uh and partly you know that because a thinking mind begins to start up again and it's not wrong that the
concentration waines it's just a natural part and what part of a healthy kind of
relationship to some and concentration is to learn to recognize when the
concentration fade starting to fade and then be gracious about that uh just
continue the practice for a while but not with any idea that it should be any different that it's not supposed to fade
um maybe switched to mindfulness more than concentration and um and uh don't fight
it don't try to override it that fading away when that time comes and if it if that fading way
happens before the end of your normal meditation then just continue with the practice the best you can but don't have
a high standard it's not going to look that great as your concentration wanes
but the effort to continue with the practice um is building the muscle of
practice the strength of practice that then will support you at other
times so um the onward leading nature and this uh
becomes important for what we'll do next week which is uh uh go go into a little
bit more detail or in different way the approach stage of going into deep samade
deep absorption and uh and becoming skilled a little bit in the approach stage is
helpful which is where we really kind of start uh feeling the we're in the
approach where where the momentum is starting to kick in and to learning how
to ride that is important so uh the other thing um next
Friday um after this 7:00 a.m. at I think it starts at 9: or 9:30 uh I'm teaching an online dayong
for the inside Retreat Center that um will be on
zoom and um it's on mindfulness of emotions so it's a different topic than
Sade but um uh it's certainly the more we're mindful of emotions and are wise
about it the more that actually supports somebody because in a certain kind of way um samadi is emotional belongs to
the deep Deep Emotions profound emotions of uh well-being of Peace of confidence of joy
of of um equinity so learning how to be with emotions can be
supportive and if you're interested in doing that you need to register and um
it's uh in the Insight Retreat Center website so thank you all very much and I
look forward to our approach next week