so good morning and welcome good day and
welcome and one of the
invaluable characteristics of deepening meditation so good morning welcome
good well so one of the characteristics of deepening meditation is
um no longer clinging to anything no longer being preoccupied by
some anything in particular including at uh experiences
we can have in meditation itself and for example some people are
preoccupied by getting concentrated and so that's the focus and that's what the mind is concerned
with but as the meditation goes deeper there's less and less uh clinging
preoccupation about anything and
uh and it's a little bit of a paradox or something
that the thing that deepening meditation you can't try too hard to have it happen
because then you're focusing on something so when we get to the second Janna
uh one of the characteristics is inner
clarity and in my understanding clarity like when
the the fog has cleared and then you can't put your finger on where the
clarity is or you can't take out your hand and grab it clarity is not
something that can be grasped clarity is something that you
allow and appreciate and enjoy but we don't appropriate it and it's not
something that you can easily push away you can close your eyes
if the sky is clear and close your eyes and not see it but the the clear
skies is um is um not something you can push away
or hold on to or it it doesn't lend itself to
clinging we might cling to the idea of a clear sky but the experience of clarity that
the clear sky uh provides is not not something you can hold on to
so in the second Janna an inner clarity arises and this sense that we're
settled in the moment here and now kind of resting or being with this
inner clarity some people might feel it more as their body starts feeling very
spacious the body seems like there's a lot of space in the body and so there's
kind of a kind of like the fog has lifted and the much of the body from the inside
out starts feeling like empty space you don't want to get too logical
about that but it's the way that it's experienced and then uh the mind starts
getting very clear awareness is clear and for the mind that it's a
clarity that comes when thinking has reduced to a bare
minimum it's like a vast open sky where
maybe occasionally there's a small cloud that drifts
by i was in the high Sierra some years ago in the mountains resting
after having lunch and the sky was completely blue but it was a particular
spot in the where the the updrafts were happening in the
mountains where we could see these little clouds form and dissolve and it
was such a pleasure to sit there watch them in a sense in a sense from my point
of view the clouds arose out of
nothing they just manifested and then they disappeared into nothing
and it was it was a real pleasure in the clarity of the great blue sky so in the
same way that that there's thoughts they seem to kind of just float in the vast
clarity of the mind vast clarity of the
body and so the alternative to thinking a lot is this wonderful feeling of
spaciousness or clarity the mind becomes more and more
clear a mind that's claustrophob not claustrophobic but crowded the mind
that's crowded with thoughts and the cascade of thought one
thought after the other so that there's no there's thoughts lined up crowding in
ready to fill the space there is no feeling of
space but in the second Janna there's lots of space in a very satisfying tranquil calm
way and it's a spaciousness a clarity that can't be clung to we can maybe cling to
calm but not with clarity so assuming a meditation
posture and Gently closing the eyes
and taking some slow slower and deeper breaths and on the exhale relaxing your
body
as you as you exhale relax and let the edges of your
body dissolve
soften into the surrounding air
and letting your breathing return to
normal and as you exhale as you
inhale feel the sensations of your thinking
mind maybe there's pressure or agitation a lot of energy feeling of
activation maybe there's tightness constriction
whatever might be in your thinking mind as you
exhale soften without ambition
like the thinking mind is a thinking muscle that relaxes as you exhale
the energy the pressure to
think dissolves into the edges beyond the edges of
thought as if the edges of thinking the cloud of
thinking vanishes in the clear sky around it
and then to center
yourself on the grounding spot with breathing
the settling spot at the end of the exhale where the inhale begins
where the sensations that are born as you inhale and spread through your
body are moving through a vast space all around you
there's a spaciousness space that is the container
for all your inner experiences
and if you're pre preoccupied by anything or have some certain emotions
that are strong it's all okay
with a rhythm of breathing breathe
with the sense of preoccupation the
emotions as if everything is dissolving into the space around it
itself that everything is
received by the
clarity beyond the edges of your thoughts
if you feel the pressure to think the activation for thinking if you
feel it carefully you might feel that
that within it there's a desire to relax to
release as you exhale release your thinking release the
pressure allow for this desire to be fulfilled the
desire to not hold on to anything
allow there to be a settling
spot deep in your body where breathing begins and ends
where that settling spot is at rest is soft
relaxed [Music]
calm and at the same time a kind of peripheral awareness
of clarity of space all around everything
a clarity a
space that is more
evident when there is no thinking
even if it's just for a few moments stop
thinking so you can feel
clarity spaciousness
as you breathe in the middle of it all
Feeling whatever degree of calm however small there might be within
you breathe with the calm gently
softly let it radiate outward through your
body as if whatever calm is
within is received in in the space of
clarity nothing to hold on to nothing to be preoccupied with
[Music] allowing
come to merge into the space of clarity the clear sky of the mind
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to allow your calm to spread out into the
room to let whatever peace inner peace you might feel however small it
is whatever peace you can
imagine to allow it to spread into the world as you
exhale Perhaps one of the gifts you can give the world is your calm is your
peace in a world that's
agitated calm can be
reassuring in a world at war
peace can be
settling in a world where there is hate
love can be healing
may we be medicine for this
world by our calm our peace our
love may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to the second talk on the second Janna the
second absorption the second state of deep samadei immersive samadei
and uh it's a state where the word immersion uh is particularly apt that we're feel
like we're immersed in a state of maybe of the calm
clarity and unity so I'm going to read to you the the standard description of
this state from the ancient texts that I read
yesterday with a stilling of a applied and sustained
attention a practitioner enters and abides in the second Janna consisting of
joy and happiness born of
samadei inner with inner inner clarity and unity of mind
free of initial and applied attention the practitioner fills
pervades saturates and permeates this body with the joy and happiness born of
samadei so no part of the body is not touched
so um uh one of the great delights of this
kind of deep uh concentration is it's kind of like we
have joy and happiness for no reason uh or to say it more accurately that um
it's a joy and happiness that's born from the samadei not from external
conditions not because wonderful things happen to us in the world we get what we want we get pleasant experiences in the
world uh but rather it's not something that's not dependent on the world uh being any
particular way but it is dependent on being deeply ly
settled and deeply settled here means among other things that there's a lot of
calm uh that there's a lot of unity a lot of settleness coming together just here
we're not fragmented we're not divided among ourselves the feeling of being
whole and there's almost no thinking and for many people this would
seem impossible because of how incessant thinking can
be but uh thinking is an activated state
that is you can it's your friend it's have a very friendly relationship and
certainly don't want to banish your thinking or it's very unfortunate to have a negative relationship your
thinking um it's with time through this practice you become friends with your thoughts and your thoughts can be your
friend but is also a time where it becomes you can relax
deeply um for people who um like to listen to music it can be
quite lovely to listen to music wonderful and they can be even more
special sometimes when the music stops and there can be a deep sense of
stillness of calm of peace uh with the absence of the input and so much so that
they have the music start again even though it's wonderful music just seems like there's too much input now there's
too much activity going on and it was just better to be in this very simple
quiet peaceful silence so maybe you have better metaphors for this than than music um uh
walking some people I like to walk a lot and um but also it's nice to stop
walking and just sit and uh and uh and then not get up to walk again it can be
so content and happy just sitting and and being and so the same way with thinking
is that at some point thinking is can get so quiet that it almost seems to
disappear or it does disappear uh discursive thinking certainly stops and it's rep in a sense
it's replaced by clarity that the awareness is still present when there's
no thinking the awareness is not dependent on thinking and um and so the ability to
sense to feel to be conscious to be aware is still there but now it's it's
not filled with thoughts and um and uh and because
thoughts are kind of like the smogs thoughts are kind of like the the waves on the ocean on the sea on the lake and
so when the waves stop then the lake is clear you can see to the bottom of the
lake perhaps and it's so amazingly enjoyable sometimes to look into the
water of a very still lake where the water's completely clear right down to the rocks
below and um uh the um
um so this beginning to appreciate uh the quieting of the mind the stilling
of the mind and that can't do it easily and quickly if you're just coming off the busy busy life to meditate but as
things get quieter more settled in meditation there comes a time where you kind of see you have a choice where you
see that oh I can leave the thoughts alone i don't have to be involved in them they can I can just let them fade
away i can trust the clarity trust the calm trust the place where there is no
thoughts and um and this allows the calm to grow and if you're still staying with
something like the breathing uh then there's this wonderful delight this joy
this happiness from being really settled calm unified the idea of beingcoming
unified is in my mind is kind of like all the different psychophysical systems
inside of us are now working in harmony flowing together
and that harmonious flow of our inner energy inner sense of
being can come with it a tremendous sense of joy and happiness and um but one that has has a
peacefulness and calm associated with it and um so uh I want to read the metaphor
or the simile that Buddha gives for the second Janna
it is like a lake that has water welling up from the
depths like an underground spring underwater
spring which has an a lake which has no water flowing
in over the ground from the mountain side from the east south west or north
and where the rain god does not occasionally supply it with
water so this is a mountain lake beautiful
basin and the um uh there's nothing uh coming in from
the outside so meaning that um um
uh there's uh no stimulus coming so in the second genre we don't not really
involved with hearing sounds um you kind of that's you you could in a sense but
it's a loud sound maybe but you kind of that's not the orientation and you're not oriented
towards seeing you're not oriented towards smelling or tasting so there's not any input coming from the
outside and uh the rain god doesn't uh rain into the lake and I understand that
to mean that um the rain god perhaps if the if our thoughts are the rain
uh that if the rain god floods us with thoughts
uh then it we we can drown in these thoughts that we have but even the the
the thought maker uh the rain maker is no longer creating thoughts to stimulate
us and to agitate us or to uh kind of those are also kind of coming
from outside certain way thoughts are kind of an external input on this deep sense of being in a lake immersed in a
lake so um uh then the
cool upwelling water so cool in India being a hot very
hot climate is refreshing and wonderful and and uh delightful uh maybe a cool uh
lake in northern England where on a damp
foggy day uh doesn't feel very inviting for people kind of steeped in the
English language in India where they're steeped with um you know Indic languages
and the word cool is very welcome word very inspiring word
even so the cool upwelling Water from this underground well spring underwater
spring would fill pervade saturate and permeate the lake with cool water so no
part of the entire lake would not be touched with the
water so also a practitioner fills pervades saturates and permeates this
body with a joy and happiness born of concentration born of samadei so that no
part of the body is not touched so here there's a feeling of this vast kind of
clarity of of being in a lake kind of wonderful kind of pool of samadei pool
of goodness pool of calm pool of clarity pool of unity that is completely kind of
feels like it has no boundaries but also feels completely kind of contained in
itself without any input come from the outside and there's an good energy
coming there's a sense of joy or delight or happiness well-being that is flowing
or or um tingling or radiating through
the body and and that is what the clarity
the calm is making room for almost like allow the room for it and allow that
calm that joy and that happiness um sometimes it's feel stronger can feel
like rapture and ecstasy uh allow it to kind of fill the whole body fill
everything so no part of your body is not touched by those good feelings by
that pleasure so the main point I'm trying to make today is that um when the time is right
to let the thinking mind become quiet let it become so quiet and
still that um you feel the the remaining clarity the remaining spaciousness and
calm that uh uh the reduction of
thinking provides and then that clarity and that calm then creates more space for
uh for um the joy and happiness the sense of
goodness the sense of well-being the sense of contentment the sense of uh
coziness the sense of sweetness the sense of beauty that can kind of well up
from deep inner are well so the welling up of joy and happiness letting it
spread through the body so this is hopefully gives you a feeling a sense for the second Janna and um and
uh and even if you don't experience this in meditation
maybe this kind of talk is maybe a little bit evocative like poetry might
be that maybe touches something uh inspiring for
you so thank you and um we'll continue tomorrow