so good good morning everyone is this uh loud enough for everyone well
hello so I have one announcement same I did last week last week we launched this
fundraising drive for save the children and um and so it's partly a
followup and announcing it again we're for this week for like this eight days
or so we were focused as a community on supporting save the children
and uh this is a longterm longtime one of the Premier best rated Charities or
humanitarian organizations in the world focused on caring for children uh in uh
especially in areas of great distress and they have an emergency fund for those who are in overd distress and
great emergency places like Gaza and Sudan and and
um and uh uh we raised uh money for them three years ago
and then we I was surprised I didn't know what to expect but there were $70,000 thought that was pretty cool
coming out our community so we're doing it again now and uh and we're close to
that goal uh on the on the if you if you donate you you'll end up on a page and
if you follow follow the links on imc's website you'll get to a page on Save the
Children which is for IMC so they're tracking how much is coming in from us and uh and uh and right now there's
about $53,000 and then another $10,000 or so have come has come in in other ways that
uh that is not not listed there so that's like $63,000 and that's pretty
close and that's kind of inspiring and the $70,000 is
arbitrary and um so you know it's not like it's all fantastic that we're what
we're doing as a community and it seems very um invalu more invaluable to do this for
the children who are going to be supported but also because um so many nonprofits like this who are doing
really important work in the world and now have now been defunded by the current Administration and including
save the children so that uh the now I I imagine
the donations now are worth much more than what comes in because they'll probably put it to really high use and
and um so it seems like particularly important time to support these things so if you're all interested that'll it's
on you know imc's homepage there's a two different places to connect to
it so so the last uh two days espe
yesterday uh I've been teaching dayong Retreats on the topic of
identity and uh so it's still fresh in my mind and it's such a phenomenally
important topic to address to become wise about um because it follows us
everywhere we go in all situations down through times people have struggled and
and uh cause a lot of pain through the topic of their identity and their
identity in relationship to other people and uh so to have some sense of
some focus on it I think uh is the focus in one of the core
human dimensions of being a human being and um and so yesterday my co-
teer for Vanessa Abel read this poem by David White and so I'd like to start
with reading it the sound of a
bell still reverberating or a blackbird calling
from a corner of the field asking you to wake into this life
or inviting you deeper into the one that
Waits either way takes courage either way wants you to to be
nothing but that self that is no self at
all want you to walk to the place where you find you already know how to give
every last thing away the approach that is also the
meeting itself without any meeting at all that Radiance you've always carried
with you as you walk both alone and completely accompanied in Friendship by
every corner of the world crying
Allelujah one of the reasons I like this poem for for now is David
White uh is going back and forth with different ways of understanding the self different kinds of identity at times
identifying with everything at times being being nothing there's nothing here to
identify um and uh and we find that the whole topic of identity is really a
fluid phenomena that comes and goes and disappears and arises and exists in so
many different ways as we go through our day and any attempt to solidify it and
make it into this is how it is is bound to dissolve at some point or crack and
break and um so um uh the other thing about this topic
of identity is what we'll do today is talk a little bit about how the Buddha addressed this issue because the topic
of identity was uh very big in his time as well and there was a lot of suffering
around it that he wanted to address and uh and the way he addressed
many things including this topic could be understood to be both
spiritual and from the Buddhist point of view which is pointing towards the possibility of some kind of profound
deep Liberation but also he addressed it ethically and over and over again he you
see him pointing to living an ethical life as being at the heart of it all and
it comes together with Liberation Liberation itself is a source for an ethical life for
people and so in these last uh while now uh uh with what's happening in our world
uh uh I've kind of feel like I've been I've been wanting inspired to replicate
what the Buddha did and really to emphasize ethics the Buddhist approach to ethics over and over again it seems
like this is really a key time to emphasize it uh as a response as a way
of responding to what's happening in the world where there's so much of it which is unethical where there's so much
cruelty and hostility and so much creation of US versus them uh which has
to do with identity in a way that is creating more suffering than it's
alleviating and uh and so this topic of Ethics is addressing the issue of how we
cause harm or how we stop causing harm and that's the kind of simplest
definition of ethics from a Buddhist point of view ethics is the study of how
not to cause harm in any kind of way so in the time of the Buddha there
was a class of people who called themselves brahans and brahans considered
themselves to be the superior class and it wasn't just that they were
off by themselves happily thinking about themselves as being Superior they also
uh had all kinds of ideas how everyone else was a lower class than them and
they had various classes that they was distinguished in their time and they had
a hierarchy of it and in at least from the Buddhist uh texts where the how the Buddhist
describe it um uh sometimes uh when they when the brahmans wanted to be critical
of the Buddhists Buddhist monastics um they put them at the very bottom of that
hierarchy and um and had various not so kind things to say about them
and um so um um and so but this was a a
topic of the uh issue in the Buddhist time and it was an issue among the brahmans
themselves and there was a debate between two friends who were brahmans
and one of them made the claim that one becomes a Brahman by by birth that it's
a hereditary phenomena it's a biological thing you are a Brahman and then you somehow pass on that Brahman Hood to
your children to your children in other words uh superiority in society is a
genetic thing is a is a biological thing that gets transmitted through birth only
meaning anybody who's not born as a Brahman does not deserve to be in that Superior
class so that was the one of the friends was claiming that and the other one was
claiming no one is a Brahman by action by how one lives one's life what one
does and so if it's by action then anyone can be a Brahman even the people
who would may be considered to be the lowest C class sometimes the Buddhists
maybe even they could be uh brahmans um by what they did how they acted so they
were having this debate and they couldn't uh come to an agreement so uh they went to the the
Buddha to ask him and what is interesting to me one of the interesting things about that is uh
the Buddha um took
sides he was very clear and
quite strong in taking the sand that one is a Brahman by action he did not stay
above the fry he did not stay somehow Det ped from it all without taking sides and somehow taking some kind of other
third position in this kind of situation he took a clear stand and given uh how the Buddha often
teaches I suspected it was very much because uh the the approach that you're
Brahman by birth was causing a lot of harm and he saw that harm that was being
created in his society and then he went on to say
that a Brahman the word Brahman is simply a verbal
designation it's just a word it's a word that's applied or defined in a certain
way there's nothing inherent and absolute about the word and um and it's
just you know it's a convention and and the Buddha felt quite
free with these conventions so he simply redefined it
and um and so uh and he defined so he used the title
Brahman but he said uh let me tell you who's really a Brahman since he's going to talk about it from the point of view
of action before he does that he did he did go through in responding to these two
brahmans with their debate saying in human life among humans there is no kind of biolog
logical visible way to really distinguish people from each other human
beings we're all human beings together in common kinship and uh and so uh that you know
so he first made clear in his view that's what he believed and then he went on to say well now I'll tell you who a
Brahman is so um so I'll
um so and this is he does this in a series of I don't know how many 27
verses and uh these verses are then kind of canonized or held up in higher
respect than Buddhism they they appear at different places because they're so important maybe and um and one of the
places in the dapada it's in the end of the dapada it's kind of but here's here
it is in this this other text having given up
violence towards living beings both timid and strong whoever kills nor
causes others to kill I call a Brahman whoever speaks what is true
informative and not harsh who harms no one I call a Brahman
whoever endures abuse assault and imprisonment without
animosity and and who has forbearance as one strength as one Mighty Army I call a
Brahman whoever is wise of profound wisdom understanding what is and is not
the path and who has attained the highest goal I call a
Brahman so he goes on there's a lot of verses like this he's ending I call the Brahman so he's not shying away from
using a term that implies an identity a Brahman he's defining it in a way that
fits life of not causing any harm some of you might not agree with
that strategy that to use an identity to apply that to people the way he chose to do but that's what he did but it's a
definition of identity based on action what people
do and um and then he goes on to say or in the same context he says that um just
like Brahman is a verbal designation based on what a person does uh we call someone who Farms a
farmer we call someone who is involved in Commerce a merchant someone who is a
crafts person does craft a craft person so people get identity based on the
activity that they do which has functional value if
um uh if your neighbor ordinarily works as fixing cars and is known as a car
mechanic and your car doesn't start one morning and you need to get someplace important you know it might be useful to
remember oh there's this car mechanic next door and uh that's a useful identity at that time um you could not
have that word car mechanic because you think it's kind of oppresses people that
be narrowed down to such a thing you could just kind of do say it more complicated to yourself there's a person
next door who's able to fix cars but in shorthand you do everyone a
favor sometimes to have you know a single word for what's going on but it's
also understood to be contextual it's a verbal designation that has a functional
role that is not necessarily who the person is so that was the Buddha's
preferred way of seeing identity if you behave a certain way
live a certain way then that's who you're called and if you change you
change you become something else so each of us probably has many identities in
the course of a day some of them are applied to you by others and some of them is ones that you
happy to have for yourself um if uh you know if you're
driving on the freeway and uh and maybe you drive a little
funny on the freeway then someone comes home and says to their friends there was
this driver on the freeway he drove funny so you you were a driver for that
purpose that was your identity that you applied to you at that time uh if you
uh were buying food in the supermarket with eth very ethically very careful
choosing exactly what to do for the best possible thing someone else might be watching you being so careful and slow
choosing what you're going to buy they go home and say there was a shopper at the store you become a shopper
and um if you're at home cooking you're a cook if you're um and you know you
might not be thinking your yourself that way but functionally you're maybe behaving that way it becomes more
relevant uh if you're if you're with your children you're a
parent if you're uh with your parents you're kind of a child or a son or a
daughter or something sibling and uh and so
uh identity how we're seen how we're related to changes many times through the day and
uh sometime they have to do with roles we play where we earn our living we have
one role and one identity and then you might leave there and um be a coach for
the high school volleyball team and now you're all the kids in high school think of you as a coach and that's that's your
identity there which is useful in that context uh when I'm here with you
all trying my best to give a talk um I'm a teacher Dharma
teacher um if now if I care keep that identity with me like this is really who
I am boy is this this and people need to know that and I go home
this is this is not good when I first started to teach a lot
you know many many years ago a couple of times my wife would look at me and said to me
gil you're using that voice
again so you know I I couldn't be a teacher at home so um and so we pick up and we put
down and it's fluid how it goes or we don't
and some of the identities we have we need to have somehow or stay close to
them because of how Society identifies us it sees us a
certain way and treats us through the lens of that identity and sometimes they
Society causes a lot of harm to people there are people right now who uh for
how they live their lives and conduct themselves and um uh the current
Administration is is uh has extreme hostility uh towards certain category of
people and so those people who are living their lives um now are afraid
because they're being identified and searched out by by people who don't like
them and so those people now have to kind of live uh in the wake of that live
under that so it's kind of they might have an identity of their own but now
they're forced to kind of relate to it in a much more solid way and carry it with them just to be safe to think who
they are so harm is being caused when we have identity and create US versus
them and um so action
so um
so the
um so that's kind of nice that our actions define us or identify us but it
feels inadequate because it can feel like who we are as a person is much more than a
role much more than an activity and it feels almost like we're
reduced to much and certainly we're something else we're something more something greater something more
intimate and deeper and um and there is a word that I
believe the Buddha used for this kind of sense of self sense of
identity and um and uh I translated it as
personhood he called it ATA Baba and personhood and personhood is
made up of the sum total of all the things things that come together to give
us a sense of he for who we are and in some ways it's a some total of all the
actions not just what we do with our bodies you know the work we do or the activities we engaged in but also the
feelings we have the emotions we have the attitudes we have um the mental
activities the mental actions that we do and there was an idea in the time of
the Buddha Buddhist teachings that uh that people could also be
recognized by what they were attached to in their mind and that uh something about uh
being attached clinging to something and some activity of the mind some belief some attitude clinging to some identity
the clinging created something that had a certain which is in action created
something that you could say that person is clinging it's a Clinger and not everyone could see that but in
the mythology of Buddhism there was a um a mythological figure called Mara and
Mara is kind of like a demi demigod or Demi Satan or some hybrid of those two
we don't quite know what what this person is but the primary activity that
Mara wants to do stop in the world is to stop people from getting
enlightened because because Mara really likes it when people cling and see so the last thing Mara
wants is anyone to stop clinging in this mythology Mara
identifies people by the clinging in their minds and Mara gets confused when the
mara sees a a liberated person because there's no
clinging and you can't see the person in a sense so this point to another important
topic around identity it's one thing to have an
identity it's another thing to identify with the identity there's one thing to
have an identity it's another thing is how we relate to that identity how we hold it how we are with
it and um and so if we have some sense of personhood it's one thing to have it
it's another thing how we relate to it how we hold it how we participate in it
and for the Buddha personhood is something we contribute to and we help
cocreate it's not something that we're passive recipients of just because we were born some way
or and um and uh and the way and what
the Buddha wanted us not to not have any identity some Buddhists thinks that some
Buddhists think that if you're a Buddhist you're not supposed to to have an identity and uh harm has been caused in
Buddhist communities when people have said oh you know there's no self and therefore you're at
you're living in your world from the perspective of your identity should be overcome should be let go of and that's
you have a problem here and I think this is uh unfortunate that this is this this not self- teing has been interpreted
that way the way the Buddha talked about identity and talked about especially
personhood he said there's a a healthy way of doing this and unhealthy way of
doing it that's my language um his language was more there's a wholesome way of doing it than
an UNH Wholesome Way in other words there's not a categorical rejection of
identity there's not a categoric categorical rejection of some inner sense of a person there my
personhood but rather are we in the activity of personing the activity of
selfing the activity of identifying is it done in a way that
creates health for us that creates uh wholesomeness in US creates goodness in
it is being do do uh being done in a way that is
ethical and the word there's one word that covers all these things I've been saying Health
wholesomeness uh ethics uh and that's the word um cusa some of
you might know it that is is probably the closest Buddhist word to our English
word ethics but it also means wholesome which kind of means healthy
but I love it that it means uh belonging to the whole the issue around identity
sometimes is the way in which we select out of the whole a piece of who we are
that we hang on to or limit the perspective on and uh and what Buddhist Liberation
is talking about is dropping the limit limiting ideas of identity in certain
situations so that we can have experience of the whole so that that sense of the whole and that freedom of
non- clinging then becomes a reference point for understanding how we
participate in identities and personhood where we hold it as functional useful
designations that have a role but we hold them lightly we don't get attached
to them we don't cling to them and so this idea of uh of relating
to our personhood relating to the even the activities of our mind and a
assessing evaluating them is what I'm doing healthy for me is it wholesome and
is a contribute to Wholesome cultivation growth in the wholesomeness do I grow to
become a better person do I grow with my mind my heart is
Kinder more generous more loving more caring for others is it Freer is it more
peaceful is it more at ease or not which direction are we going
and sometimes when people attach to Identity to their own or sometimes in their their uh projection of that onto
others it's clearly causing harm to the person who does it some people hold on
to Identity for dear life in a way that actually harms them some people acquire
or take on identities that uh are identities of hostility and hate
identities of US versus them and that creates alienation that is bad for the
person who has it and um and so uh so the question is how
do we hold identities was what the Buddha was most interested in and is it unethical or
unethical is it wholesome or un wholesome is it healthy or unhealthy where all three of those categories are
talking about the same thing and um and so this is where
Buddhist practice comes into play Because as especially a meditation ation
practice because as we sit and meditate we become more and more sensitive
to what is healthy and what is unhealthy what is wholesome what is UNH
wholesome what what is uh in a sense ethical and not ethical what is harmful
what is not harmful what brings stress and what doesn't bring
stress and uh and the the the clear the mindfulness becomes the more stable and
subtle we are in the moment the more we see this movement sometimes very subtle
sometimes not so subtle of the impact the effect the influence the mind has on
itself or the mind has on the heart and in some ways we're shaping our
personhood by the very nature of what we're choosing to be involved in and in
ordinary life we don't track ourselves so much we don't even track ourselves not only what the mind is doing to make
a choice but we all not tracking the influence it has on us but not a few
people are ruminating and thinking over and over again bad thoughts about themselves critical thoughts about
themselves seeing it as being this is what's you know the nature of the true nature of the universe that I'm a bad
person that very is making them sick making them depressed that has a a tremendously negative influence on them
but when we sit in meditation and get quiet enough we can start seeing these
thoughts operating and if we're lucky enough we come to a place where we see
we have a choice to either continue with those thoughts or put them
down and we can even feel some points that having no thoughts as as harmful as
they might be self-critical thoughts um just having them is
tiring and it's just nice to take a rest and that
applies to positive identities as well you might have done a lot of kind
things in your life and it might be reasonable for you to think of yourself as a kind person you're sitting
peacefully in meditation and you start remembering yeah I'm a really kind person yeah I'm a
kind person yeah I'm pretty good kind person I've been kind person a long time yeah I'm a kind person isn't it great
that I'm a kind person and after a while it's going to occur to you
hopefully sooner rather than later but unfortunately it's many time it's later because these kinds of things are almost
subconscious this is tiring you know I I got the message the
first time I have better things to do than repeating this kind of thought
uh and so even good identities at some point it's just good
to put them down you know it's
nice and then there's also deeper senses of personhood deeper senses of identity we have you know not involved individual
thoughts but kind of a gal of it all the whole and it's fascinating to watch as
that shifts and changes too and one of the places I think some of you maybe have had this experience of it
changing is on meditation Retreats those of you who've been on them and maybe
those of you haven't maybe there's situations where you've um you've experience yourself in a totally new way
that you've never had before so in meditation Retreats people in the course
of their longer retreat will get softer Kinder uh less ATT atted less
preoccupied with thoughts less rumination and caught up in the usual things and there's a softening of the
personality there's a uh there's a feeling of Greater kindness and care and preciousness and intimacy with life that
happens that people feel they have a whole different Persona whole different personality whole different sense of
self that feels so much healthier than how they live their life usually where there's a lot of
stress and some people will say say this is it I'm home this is what home is in
myself this is what I want to how I want to live my life and then they leave the retreat and
their personality returns before they leave the driveway of the ret Retreat
Center you know the personality starts coming back and and after a while we know it's back but we know we've seen it
coming back but um after a while we just forget that we could be different
because we're so lost in that world world of this new P the old persona come back it's just how things
are uh sometimes people have that shift uh when um of something when their
ordinary life stops in some way I've known people for whom had serious illness or injuries and there was
something about how much their life changed that they came to terms terms with that they the whole sense of how to
be a person shifted sometimes in a better way wow I'm a different person
than I was before uh I was so caught up in my previous identity I was so um Angry all
the time I was so ambitious all the time and I'm a whole different person now this is
phenomenal some people when they become parents their experience of who they are
becomes radically different and um there's a powerful book I for
parenting called um far from the tree and it's children who are born who
are very different than their parents and um and what's interesting
about this book The the author studies different kinds of different people
different who were born differently like people are blind or deaf or different condition all kinds of different
conditions prodigies and and then studies their the parents
and he his observation is that um parents of certain kinds of
children tend to become better people especially if the kids have great
disabilities parents of other kinds of uh children tend to become not so good
folks more selfish or preoccupied and that's apparently especially true when
when parents have prodigies that that somehow does something to the
conceit that is not so good so um so we we we shape this all
the time it's shaped and changed and we're actually more changeable than we
realize in all kinds of different ways and you could wake up tomorrow and find
yourself radically changed in unbelievable ways in terms of what you consider your identity
or it might be slow over a long time and
um I had a new identity recently that I said out
loud I uh I was teaching a retreat at our retreat center for people is in the
20s and 30s you might ask what business I have doing that but I was I was
invited to teach it so I had a role and you know I look around the room and I
was clearly the oldest person there when I started in Buddhism I was like the
some of the youngest ones there and so at some point during the retreat I described myself as a as a
designated old person I had a new identity for that
Retreat and I thought it was kind of humorous so the sense of
self and then when mind gets really quiet there's a very interesting thing that
happens there's something that gets simpler and simpler and simpler about
Identity or about this notion of self and if you turn your attention to
sense and feel where that sense of self is in us when things are quiet enough
and still enough it might feel like it has a location there might be a a a feeling of
enness that's all it what is amness just that I M it might be a very subtle
feeling of um of of a Locus a center
someplace it might be a Locus or Center has a little bit of pressure or little nice feeling of
tension or nice feeling of vibration or aliveness or something like
that and it can feel oh that's who I am the core the center of it all you know
free of all these identities free of everything left alone that's who I
am now you can sit there and spend time hanging out with it looking at it
recognizing it and at some point what'll happen you'll
feel that it's a little bit tiring to do this focus on this place it's a little
tiring to keep looking at it and thinking about it just like it's tiring to keep having thinking the same identity
and so in meditation some point because it's tiring to have that Focus there's a quieting relaxing letting go that
activity and lo and behold that sense of amness that may be
a sense of locus the the center Falls
away it seems that it's the looking at the self is the
AC it that creates that little sense of activity and energy and vibration or
pressure it's the seeking and searching for the self in the end that creates
just a thing that's feels like this is who I am but if there's no looking for it no
searching for it where does it
go it becomes an irrelevant question because what's left is very peaceful
very spacious very free it's possible to have a tremendous
feeling of ease and peace without any reference to any kind of self self any
kind of creation of self identification of self a sense of personhood not to negate any of
that but it's just like in context from time to time it's really
good to take a vacation from it all it's really good to take a break
from all this selfing that we live in in our society where selfing goes on all the
time it's really healthy to do take that break because then we can see much more
clearly how selfing is constructed how selfing is something we participate in
and how it comes together and come comes and goes and morphs and
changes and um and we can hold it lightly why for what
purpose so we can live with it in an ethical way so we can live with it in a
with causing less harm in the world but actually doing the opposite live with
identity live with the personhood live with how we see other people in ways that support them
that is beneficial that sees them kindly that sees them generously that sees sees them with care
sees ourselves with care and maybe one of the identities
will will develop over time is we're a person who cares we're a carer for this
world and that can't be too bad so I'll read this um David uh White
poem again and then we'll stop so maybe you'll um this poem will have a little bit more
meaning now the sound of a bell still
reverberating or a blackbird calling from a corner of the
field asking you to wake into this life
or inviting you deeper into the one that Waits
either way takes courage either way wants you to be
nothing but that self that is no self at all wants you to
walk to the place where you find you already know how to give every last thing
away the approach that is also the meeting itself without any meeting and
at all that Radiance you have always carried with you as you walk both
alone and completely accompanied in Friendship by every corner of the
world Allelujah so I don't know if we want to say Allelujah that often these
days but let's let's at least be friends let's go into the world ready to
be friends with everyone and may that change the world if we want to change the world
Let's Be the Change by being ethical ourselves and if we and and then as we go about trying to make the world a
better place let's find a way to do it that stays ethical stays
wholesome and that way we become better people in the process may all beings be happy
thank you