So hello and welcome to this morning meditation
and for
we're in the middle of this series on insight and coming to the part of insight meditation
insight practice where we're looking at um the amazing poly word
pronounced duka And uh as I'll talk more about it, it's an adjective.
And um and in English uh sometimes
there's um the preposition before one translation of duka is suffering and
the word that sometimes precedes it is suffering with or follows it. someone
suffers with something and um and what I'm trying to say here
is that um and in poly it's an adjective.
It's always something that is painful.
And when there's something pain something that's painful there's also something which is not painful.
When there's suffering, there's also that which is not suffering.
When there is affliction, there's also that which is not afflicted.
When there is something with suffering, suffering with something
that uh it is um there's that which is not suffering, not with suffering. And
so this in this meeting of what is suffering, what is not suffering is a
fascinating place. And um and sometimes we emphasize things
are either one way or another. But in the dharma, it's helpful to think of them as uh as not either or, but there's
an and. And the dharma happens in the and the
and in between. It's it's not just suffering and it's not just happiness. There's an and
suffering and that which is not suffering. Happiness and that which is not happy.
Exactly. But it's not yet suffering either. It's that that's even happier than
happiness. That and that is freer of sufferer of
suffering. So to have a meeting
to feel where things are stressful, tense, uncomfortable
and know it with a knowing that is free of
suffering, knowing that's free of stress, knowing that is free of of um
contraction, tension in relationship to it. that meeting place of what is
suffering, what is not suffering. Look for that in this meditation.
And uh don't try to have it one way or the other. Don't try to have it only no
suffering. Don't try to only focus on suffering. But try to find the place
where then that which doesn't suffer can meet what is suffering. So that the in
the end you can find stability in the end you can find a steadiness
in the end you can find freedom even
so to assume a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes and take a few moments to feel your
posture. ure and maybe swaying back and forth.
Kind of adjusting the positioning of your weight in your
body to find a feeling of balance
with your posture.
loosening up places of holding. I was long ago was taught when I did Zen
to um flap my elbows a little bit when I'm sitting cross-legged or sitting in
the chair to loosen up any subtle ways the arms
are being held.
I've also been taught to gently kind of
uh shake or move the fingers so they can loosen up. The hands can loosen up.
Sometimes it's nice to
rotate the head a little bit. Sometimes just like almost like you're saying no,
but not to say no to anything, but rather to loosen up
in the neck, maybe in the shoulders.
And then gently taking some deeper breaths.
And on the exhale softening the whole body
on the exhale like the whole weight of the body can settle
into the pull of gravity.
And then to let your breathing return to normal.
And with a normal exhale, relax different parts of your body.
Soften in the body.
With the exhale, softening
some of your tension or holding in your
thinking mind.
And then to settle into your breathing
or to settle into the present moment here
in the body this time and place
in whatever way allows you to feel a settling, stabilizing
and entering into a fullness of this moment.
A fullness with the body breathing
And to
soften, relax.
how you're aware, how you're mindful,
but clear, being aware clearly,
knowing clearly
the present moment experience.
So the sense of present mo present moment knowing
present moment awareness is valued is appreciated
is its own thing that's being established
separate from being entangled with thoughts emotions s
attitudes. Entering into
knowing awareness mindfulness
of the present moment with every breath.
And if there's any strain, tension in how you're aware, how you're
mindful, see if you can
soften, relax,
open up. How you're aware There.
There is breathing and there's how you're aware of
breathing.
And then noticing
that in the meeting of breathing breathing
and awareness. Notice if there's any part of that
experience where there's an absence
of suffering, tension, stress.
Notice that absence.
Breathe with that absence.
Open to that absence.
And then as we continue, if there's any if you're feeling any
suffering, any stress,
tension, emotional pain.
Allow it to be there, but let it be there in the meeting place
with what is not stressful, what is not suffering.
Don't lean into suffering or hold on to it or react to
it. Let it coexist
with awareness which is not suffering.
Let it coexist with something here that has no strain in it. No tension.
Rather than feeling or believing that
suffering, uneasiness
is global global experience.
It's always a partial experience
where a global experience includes that which is not suffering.
And with this practice of mindfulness,
hold them both together.
The meeting place of suffering and non-suffering.
and then leaving suffering alone.
Any uneasiness you might feel, however subtle, leave it alone.
And settle into some of the feelings, characteristics
of that which doesn't suffer. Maybe there's a feeling of spaciousness.
Stability,
stillness,
openness,
aliveness.
Enter into
that which doesn't suffer and breathe with it. Feel it. Sense it.
Let it grow and spread.
And as we come to the end of this sitting, may it be that the practice of
mindfulness shows us
how not to be afraid of suffering.
May it show us how to be how to show up for s the suffering we have the
sufferings other ha other people have to meet it to know it
without suffering.
to meet suffering in a mature, honest way. With that part of us that has stability
and openness, receptivity, that doesn't suffer.
And may this ability to meet suffering
our own and the suffering of the world, may it allow
for for us to meet the suffering of the world, to meet our own suffering. ing
with love, with wisdom,
with compassion and care.
May we find a new way to be with suffering
that can transform the world,
transform ourselves
to make this a peaceful world, a safe world.
A world where happiness and care and love can flow.
A world where we feel free. We can breathe freely and easily
and be at ease with each other.
May all beings be happy. May all beings
be safe. May all beings be peaceful.
May all beings be free.
[Music]
Thank you.
So, hello everyone and welcome to this series on insight. And
it's um we're now into the second half of the year. And
what we're in what I'm introducing this week is um built on all that we've done
the first half of the year. So this is not out of the blue. It's not meant to be
self-standing. It's meant to have a phenomenal support that we're ready to
bring mindfulness to uh to excuse me
we're ready to bring mindfulness to that part of our life that's quite difficult
uh to the world that the Buddhist English Buddhists call suffering
and uh an essential Part of Buddhist practice is a mature, clear, honest
encounter with suffering, with stress, with tension, with um the emotional
difficulties of our life, the ways that life can be so uh challenging for for
all of us and how to be able to meet that in an effective and useful way. to be able to
be present and not uh collapse in the face of challenges. To meet it and stay
in some way strong and open. to meet it and not be defined by the suffering, not
be overwhelmed by it, not be um
uh confused by it, but to be able to really be present for it um in a clear,
effective, and honest way so that we find our way to freedom. So we find a a
radically different way to be with suffering than how ordinarily we might
be. And um and so
uh to hear this emphasis and come ready hopefully many of you who've been doing this now for six months this feel like
you have this is in the background to be able to uh meet this in a new way. So
the the word for s uh that we translate by suffering is duka in in the ancient
language of the Buddha poly we call it the way it comes to us and uh duka d u k
k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k k h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h h j is in the ancient language is actually an adjective
whereas the English word suffering uh is usually considered a noun.
kind of maybe a verbal noun but a noun. And um but in in poly it's an adjective.
So that very different. It's um it uh means that it's always referring to
something. It's a characteristic of something. It's not its own thing. It's not its own
event that's there. And um so a little bit uh uh maybe uh demotes
the word suffering from how it can be seen as being this grand uh catastrophic
kind of catastro catastrophic kind of thing that is so big.
Um uh so the literal polyme of the word
suffering is painful. uh uh and it doesn't uh distinguish
between emotional pain and uh physical pain. Uh it's whatever is painful and
human life has pain in it. But the Buddhist orientation is to uh give uh
extra attention to the emotional pain that that we might experience because
the emotional pain is uh uh or the psychological pain that
part of the pain that we feel that um in one way or the other we are contributing
to. We're not necessarily responsible for our suffering, but there is a way in
which we contribute to it and that adds to it that makes it much
more difficult. There are certain forms of emotional pain which um comes with
being a human being. Uh to grieve is painful. But it's not ne it's not wrong
to feel that pain. There's something sacred about grief and about that pain
of grief uh that's very tender and very human to experience and make room for and allow for.
And it's not it's fairly easy to be able to add uh a degree of stress tension that's not
necessary to it. And we can suffer more by how what we contribute to it. the
fear, the resistance, the the u collapsing into it, the excessive
reactivity to it, the the heavy beliefs that we live under around what we're
experiencing. So, we have a contribution that we we we make.
And so the duka as an adjective is the uh the stressfulness, the painfulness,
the uh tenseness that uh we contribute
to whatever the experience it might be. And it's um
it's uh maybe um challenging to to talk about our
contribution because then we feel like maybe that we're wrong or that we did something a
mistake or that somehow now I'm being blamed for the suffering that I have.
And that is not what we're trying to do here uh at all. We're actually trying to
free us from this complic comp more complicated way of interpreting and
concluding what who we are, what we are, what's going on here and learn how to be
very simple, very quiet and simple so that we can
feel the the the ways in which we add
stress, the way where there's tension, the way in which there's um um
suffering. uffering uh that can be met with with that which
doesn't suffer that can be met with something that uh holds it caringly,
compassionately, openly, some way of holding it. So there's a peacefulness.
We don't add second arrows. We don't add ways that we make it worse.
uh if anything we're what we're adding is how to be how to make it better for
ourselves in relationship to suffering. So some people uh translate the word
duka as stress and the advantage of that is that it doesn't that's that's not
such a big word and it's not necessarily so automatically tied to our psychology
to our identity uh that it sometimes does if it's the word suffering and stress is kind of an
inherent part of human life as well and it maybe it's easier to appreciate
that stress is extra and that uh we can kind of work with our
stress in a in a responsible way to
de-stress. And the advantage of stress as a translation of dooka is that as the
samadei gets really strong as the meditation goes really deep and full uh
we wouldn't call it suffering anymore what's there but we can feel very subtle
tension very subtle stress uh that's maybe even right in the midst of feeling
a lot of joy right in the midst of feeling a lot of happiness right in the
midst of in a very subtle way in the midst of feeling a lot of peace.
And um and so to feel that stress, to feel the subtlest little pieces of
tension uh is part of the onward leading nature of freedom. And even there to
find tension and stress in the subtlest in the deepest kind of peaceful states
of meditation uh expands the fullness of that which
doesn't suffer. the experience of freedom of openness, the absence of
suffering into which we can um fall into
which we can open.
So um so the idea that uh duka
is not its own thing. It's an adjective
that means that it's part of something which means that suffering is never the
whole thing. That it's always a piece of our
humanity. It's a section. It's a it's an aspect of it. And and I know that
sometimes the whole atmosphere, the whole world can just feel distressing and fearful and and u dis you know
dismaying and difficult and the weight of the world can be on our shoulders.
The idea in a mindfulness practice is to practice with the world that we have,
the experience we have. Not to make it worse, not to suffer more because of it,
but to be able to find some degree of stability, steadiness,
stillness, some ability of clarity, clear
awareness. So, we begin to recognize there's always
more going on here than whatever it is we're calling suffering, whatever it is
that's painful for us, emotionally painful, physically painful,
and to um and to begin to feel that which is more, feel that which is not
suffering. So that so we can be with suffering in a mature, responsible,
caring way and a wise way. And what uh
uh when there's enough stability, enough ability to meet suffering without adding
second arrows, without making it worse, then the hope is that uh we have we can
think more wisely, more clearly about it and know how to address it
appropriately. And sometimes uh something needs to be
fixed, something needs to be addressed. Sometimes we need to speak to someone or
take care of something or do something. Sometimes we need to take a break or we need to kind of find relief. We need to
find a vacation. We need to find some way to um even occasionally to distract
ourselves so that something can relax and e be easeful. But it's never meant
to be an escape. Buddhism is not Buddhist practice is not an escape from suffering. It's to learn how to work
with suffering in a wise way. And there comes a time when the
meditation, when the mindfulness, the practice is strong when the
best strategy is to learn to suffer better.
And that's a a provocative statement to suffer better. What I mean by that is
not to just suffer for the sake of suffering. Suffering better is to suffer
in a way that's wise. Suffer so there's less suffering. Suffering so that
suffering is met with that which doesn't suffer. Suffering is felt is only part
of the picture. something we can breathe with, something we can find our ease with, something we can practice with.
Where the idea of practice, we identify more with us as a practitioner of peace,
of mindfulness, of clarity, of stability, of calm, then we than we
identify with whatever suffering we have. We can meet our suffering
with that with that which doesn't suffer. And if we can't
to be mindful and clear about that, it's okay.
If we can't be together with our suffering in a clear and useful way because we're
spiraling out, then the appropriate thing to do is to find another way. Then
mindfulness is not the way at that moment. Then it's to do something, shift something. Uh go for a walk, talk to our
friend. um um you know maybe do some
exercise or occasionally as I said we distract ourselves so that we retreat
only so we can come back later and begin addressing the edges of what is
difficult and not to address it to try to fix it
but rather to um to uh and this is the amazing thing about this practice is uh
we're not trying to fix something but we're trying to find our freedom with it.
Find our freedom with suffering not be and so that suffering and that
which doesn't suffer can meet each other and there and that and between them
that's where we find our freedom. So thank you very much and um we'll
continue this topic of insight into uh suffering.
Thank you.