good evening welcome
welcome lovely to see you all here thank you for ringing the bell Jim
it was a little bit loud and I thought I don't know it just made me happy like it's Memorial Day
boom it was really nice
so I wanted to start with a little bit of a poem today that in some maybe not
completely directly way that kind of like honors this idea of people dying in
wars and the wish for wars to end those of you who have been listening
to me for a while will not be surprised by the poet it's uh Rosemary
Tramer and this poem is called because it's because by Rosemary Tramer
and it goes like this so I can't save the
world can't even save myself can't wrap my arms around every frightened child
can't foster peace among nations can't bring love to all who feel
unlovable so I practice opening my heart
right here in this room and being gentle with
my insufficiency i practice walking down the street heart
first and if it is insufficient to share love I will practice loving
anyway i want to converse about truth about trust i want to invite compassion
into every interaction one willing heart can't stop
a war one willing heart can't feed all the
hungry and sometimes daunted by a task too big I tell myself what's the use of
trying but today the invitation is
clear to be ridiculously courageous in love
to open the heart like a lilac in May knowing freeze is possible and opening
anyway to take love seriously to give love wildly to race up to the world as
if I were a puppy adoring and unjaded stumbling upon my own exuberance
to feel the shock of indifference of anger of cruelty of fear and stay
open to love as if it matters as if the world depends on
it this is because by Rosemary
Tra this is a a beautiful poem and there's lots of things I could say about it
a few things I want to pull out uh this evening is we could say that part of
meditation practice is like in the gross generalization but in a way that can be
really helpful to think about too is this movement from just concepts and
ideas and living in our minds to actually being present for our
experience like what's actually happening this moment and instead of all
the thinking that's going on in the ways that we think it should be and disappointed how it's not and that kind
of thing and she has this poem so I can't
save the world and then she continues so I practice opening my heart right here in
this room this idea of I can't save the world in some ways you know the world is just
an idea in our head in some ways right we don't experience erience the world we experience whatever's being experienced
in this moment and so she's practicing to be
meet her bring her heart uh bring her love to just what's actually being known
in this moment and we could say all of this meditation of practice is about this is about noticing all the ideas we
have about what should be and what shouldn't be who we are who we aren't those people over there how they should
be different or how I should be different you know all these thoughts that we
have just noticing that they're just thoughts it turns
out and what are thoughts they're they're just right they're insubstantial
ephemeral how many quadrillion bazillion thoughts have you already had in contrast to hearing the voice
feeling the pressure against the chair the cushion maybe there's an emotion that's being pre being experienced at
this moment so we could say that this is one uh arc
of this poem one kind of uh element that's been being expressed in this poem
but I appreciate that she also talks about this feeling of insufficiency this feeling like yeah
whatever I'm going to do it's not going to be enough this sense of like being inadequate not quite enough maybe not
good enough or inadequate in some kind of way and of course those are also
thoughts but uh there's a way in which we can really I don't know grab on to
those ones those particular thoughts and make them feel like well these ones are true those thoughts about the snowman I
had earlier today that that was just a thought but uh this this feeling of
inadequacy that that must be true and she
says "I practice opening my heart right here in this room." And then the line
continues and being gentle with my insufficiency so there's this way of
like being gentle with one's feeling of inadequacy or
insufficiency she's not talking about being feel filled with shame she's not
talking about pretending like it's not there just acknowledging yep there's a feeling
of insufficiency like I can't do enough or I'm not enough in some kind of way
there's some power in just saying it yeah this feeling is
here and we might say that it's you know this turns out to be
so common not everybody has this but it was a big wakeup call for me when in
part of my training to be a Dharma teacher to initially to be sitting in on
practice discussions that another teacher was doing and just to see how person after person after person on
retreats would come in all the details different but all of the sharing this
flavor of I'm not good enough it was really heartbreaking to realize
wow so many people are having this feeling and we could say well maybe it's
not surprising there's so many messages we get from our culture from our family
from our upbringing education there's all kinds of reasons
and there's also maybe even this way in which the we see these messages that
uh it's a individuality like okay you know I have to do it all by myself I got
to make it happen and I want this and I don't care what you want you know I'm exaggerating a little bit but there's
this way in which this message is there in order for you to succeed you got to go out and do all kinds of
stuff or or if you aren't like that or if you do say you know I need to uh like
honor and respect my actual experience right now there's a way and sometimes it can seem like selfish if you're not out
there trying to save the world or doing I don't know trying
to end the hunger that she talks about in this poem so there's been a way in which we've
kind of uh often been dismissive of our what's happening to us our inner life
our specifics in this way that kind of like undermines
our sense of worth maybe our sense of being okay sense of being adequate or
sufficient so there's this way in which with
Buddhist practice some of you may be familiar with this is
that we don't have to wait for chance or
we don't have to assume that we have to have have had
a different childhood or something in order to feel okay inside
instead this is something that can be cultivated and in fact we would say
needs to be cultivated and it's a tremendous benefit for one's life to cultivate this feeling
of warm-heartedness this feeling of goodwill not only to
ourselves but to others and to all
beings this like expanding out this feeling of care and warmth and goodwill
respect and in Buddhist practice this gets uh developed we would say to these
universal uh dimensions having this without limits without
exceptions without distinctions just having this orientation of
goodwill and for some of us we might hear something like that like Oh isn't that cute and might feel like maybe this is
saccharine or artificial or feels uh
ooey gooey in some kind of way but there is this way in which we
can train the heart and the mind and that it does have this natural
orientation towards goodwill or warmth or care or love and
kindness or respect different words to uh you can choose which word
you like the best often this is called meta meta often gets translated as
loving kindness but it's not a like a single thing it's not like a single
feeling and we're like do I have it do I not have it like it's this binary switch or something like this more it's like a
maybe sometimes it feel like it has some warmth or and
gentleness or maybe sometimes it feels bright and energetic or maybe sometimes
it has this quality of healing and caring for ourselves or for others but
maybe it has a soothing quality to it just this
warmheartedness or maybe even that's going too far maybe it's just this softness and
openness because when I first started practicing with meta with loving kindness I started to notice like how
all the ways in which I wasn't feeling loving kindness all the times and places
I got irritated or annoyed with myself with other people
was kind of really highlighted that and it was uncomfortable it was hard to see that i thought I was a nice person but
then I started to notice everything that wasn't meta started showing up and this turns out I didn't know it
at the time but this is a standard part of the practice it's not a mistake it can feel
like oh I must be doing this wrong but it's part of this we could say the
purification the cleansing the opening of the heart and
mind so some of you will be familiar with this idea of loving kindness
practice this uh just briefly I'll say that it's
a practice um it's a all it's a like a different meditation
practice and maybe as a brief aside I will say Monday through Friday 6:00 p.m
to 7:00 p.m is uh what we call happy hour that's happening on Zoom so 5 days
a week this is uh being taught that type of meditation practice on the IMC website you can find a link
there and I taught that for a number of years it was beautiful beautiful all these people that uh coming to I don't
know open the heart so briefly I'll describe what is that
practice start where it's easy absolute easiest like the easiest to feel
warm-heartedness for many people this kittens or puppies or babies maybe like
generic kittens puppies babies whatever it feels like oh whatever whatever kind of has that feeling for
you and then you maybe like connect with this what we can call a lovable being
this could be an actual kitten puppy baby that you know maybe grandchild or
maybe there's somebody in your life that's really helped you often it's like maybe coaches or mentors or teachers or
somebody that has really uh touched you in some kind of way that you easily have a sense of uh
appreciation bring them to mind and then to help the mind and the heart kind of
like soften and stay connected we repeat phrases may you be safe may you be happy
may you be healthy may you live with ease these aren't prayers as much as
it's just this intention this wish for goodwill for this person and that could be it it could be
that simple just stay in words absolute easy and sending goodwill to this
lovable being many of you will be familiar with but there's to go on to all these
different categories but uh what I've discovered from teaching this and with my own practice if you just stay where
it's easy it just naturally overflows into the other categories we don't have to force
ourselves because sometimes then it feels too contrived and uh constrained
instead it can be really helpful to just connect with a lovable being
i could give talks and talks about this and I have but uh and just connect with
this sense of goodwill or warm-heartedness and there's Rob Burbaya
who was a dharma teacher he's uh did a number of uh dharma talks and did a
number of retreats on meta and he had this uh expression that I really
appreciated about it he said "We don't have to be a squeaky clean meta
machine." Like this idea like when we hear these ideas of loving kindness we might have this idea that well it feels
like maybe it's robotic we repeat phrases and we wishing goodwill maybe it
seems a little unreal or unrealistic in some kind of way
but there's a way in which we all of us it it uh allows our personality our
uniqueness to be a part of it it's not like we're just uh marching along to a
particular drummer and exact in step it allows us it honors our own humanness
our own potential for having big beautiful
hearts and importantly this meta practice we start
with where it's the easiest and sometimes then intentionally
often not always turning towards ourselves
may I be safe may I be happy may I be healthy may I live with
ease it turns out this is really difficult for a lot of people this whole
notion of uh just caring for oneself or sending love for oneself is
uncomfortable but there's this [Music] way that it can make such a giant
difference as I said before some people feel like "Oh that's selfish i should only be doing it for others."
But we could say that having a relationship with ourselves of care and
warmth then we stop demanding it from everybody else we stop demanding it from
everyone else and then just think how your life is different if you don't feel
like every you have to just always be uh met with care and warmth and uh some
love just think how your life would be different if you had this healthy
positive regard for yourself you'd be willing to take risks learn new things
you'd be creative like you because you're not so much afraid of fear you don't have fear of failing like oh okay
that creative thing didn't work that's okay i'm still okay even though I did
this or what would it be like to just love others
freely and maybe they exchange or maybe they uh reciprocate love and maybe they
don't but just love what's lovable about people and then you'll find that people
start to show you their lovable the most lovable aspects it's quite something if
we kind of there's a way in which what we expect from people they often are showing us not in the obvious ways that we we'd
think but it's quite remarkable don't underestimate how
powerful this can be to have this positive regard for ourselves
so not only does it help our love our life unfold in a different way but it
becomes a foundation from which we can give to others it becomes a foundation
from which we can grow from or build from
so rather than it being about what we think we deserve or what what we think
that we've done or not done it's this this recognition
that we exist we're here and that's good
enough it turns out that's good enough it's not like we have to achieve
and attain something and this such a way in which it definitely is a gift to
others not kind of like demanding this love from
others and then maybe I would say importantly
there's this warmheartedness towards ourselves helps us
meet our resistance to so much of what's happening in our life it's not uncommon
for us to meet our experiences with this subtle or obvious no i don't want
that i don't want to feel that pain in my knee i don't want to feel hungry i
don't want to be too hot i don't want to have a boss that's like this i don't want this i don't want that i don't want
this i don't want that and so much of our life is saying like "No no no no."
And often this no is thoughts because we've thought up in our
mind completely 100% made up in our minds how things should
be and then we lay that on top of what's actually happening and they never match
it's I don't I'm saying the word never rarely let's say rarely what's made up
in the mind isn't precisely matching what's actually happening and then with
this what's made up in the mind somehow seems to be the what's the authoritative and there's this way we're saying no no
because it doesn't match this and this practice is about saying yes to what's
actually happening what's actually happening sometimes is uncomfortable what's
actually happening is frightening what's actually happening is
sad what's actually happening is beautiful or joyful and lovely as
well but there's something when we stop fighting with things and being
disappointed in them and saying no to them and just meeting them like we saw
in this poem there's this way in which there's this
relief of just putting down the burden of always trying to make things be
different i am not saying to be passive i am not saying don't have goals and
work towards them i'm just saying notice how often you're saying no and subtle
and obvious ways and doing this loving kindness for ourselves helps us say yes
to what's happening the uncomfortable experiences because let's be frank a lot
a large part of life is uncomfortable it's doesn't go exactly
the way we thought sometimes it goes better and sometimes it's just different it's just
different it's not better or worse so how can we or maybe I should say I
want to say a little bit more about resistance there's this way about like acknowledging the resistance
and like maybe even just be becoming familiar with the experience of resistance this way in which we're
saying no I want it to be different if we can say yes to the
resistance like the resistance doesn't have to go away just say yes to the resistance because that's what's
happening in the present moment it turns out this can be a
gateway to more and more freedom this is a definitely a gateway to a way in which
your life can have much more peace and ease
this way of which going into the resistance can be a
portal into as I said so many of the ways in which we're saying no and they begin to
soften they begin to maybe we're choosing what we've been
rejecting in some kind of way sometimes the way the reason why we're saying no
is because maybe there's an aspect of ourselves or um something we're really
trying to avoid because it's uncomfortable but saying yes is a way in which things can kind of be more
collected we don't have to try to excise those uncomfortable parts and they start
becoming together and there's a sense of wholeness that starts to become gets
created and experienced so loving kindness for oneself really
can make this giant difference in our lives it might seem sappy and I like
this word saccharine but it turns out to be really
powerful really powerful to help us meet what's
arising you might say okay well that sounds nice but uh is there a way that we can do this cuz really I you know
it's not so easy necessarily i know for me the first
time that I did ment I thought like yeah yeah yeah give me the real stuff i I
wanted to uh you know do some insight practice and insight practice is absolutely important and uh is a
integral part of this path toward freedom but I would say you there will be a limit to how far you can go with
insight practice if it's not also a certain amount of willingness to open
and soften the heart so how can we do
this there's this way can we just have a little this a little confidence in the
notion of practicing with loving kindness is very much like planting
seeds planting seeds in the soil so we often don't see when seeds in
the soil are starting to germinate and they do their first part of growth right there in the soil we don't see
them in the same way love and kindness practice wishing goodwill for the
lovable being may you be safe may you be happy may you be healthy may you live
with ease you can feel like really is this all I'm going to do but there's a
way in which it kind of like conditions we could use the expression
neuroplasticity is this continue reorientation this
reorientation and it gives the mind something to do other than ruminating about terrible unhelpful
things not even terrible but so many of our thoughts turn out to not be so as
helpful as helpful as we wish they would be or could be so what helps this meta
to expand and to have a big impact in our life it's a little bit of confidence or
trust and this idea that even though we can't see that the seeds that were planted are immediately sprouting
doesn't mean that they're not having an impact doesn't mean that they're not
having an impact and if it feels like well this is kind of dry and mechanical
i'm not so sure about this or even if we feel as I said
earlier I started to everything that wasn't loving kindness started to come up all this anger I couldn't believe it and this hatred like wow we're like I
was so surprised so surprised by it it just started to come up so I was on a
retreat and I had been practicing for some time with loving kindness and I was
very sheepishly telling the meditation teacher and she's like "It's okay it's okay Diana just keep going just keep
going." And I trusted her and I did and it made a a big difference
so even if what's coming up is the opposite of uh love and kindness can you
hang in there with it and not jump too much into judging how things are like ah
this doesn't work or I don't like it or something like that because maybe there's this sense in
which what's going on under the radar isn't uh maybe isn't seen isn't and
felt so you might say well what's the relationship between loving kindness practice and insight practice and I'll
just say briefly different people practice it different ways some people will and there's been
seasons of my practice that I've done it differently but you some people will start the first part of their they'll do
5 10 15 minutes of loving kindness practice and then do 15 30 minutes of uh
insight practice or there'll be some people who will just start without insight practice
or I'll say mindfulness of breathing and then realize is "Oh my
gosh the mind is crazy all over the place and I'm really agitated and restless." And so then they'll just
switch to loving kindness practice which has a calming and a soothing way to do
it and some people will just say "Okay I don't know Monday Wednesday Friday I'll
do loving kindness tuesday Thursday Saturday Sunday I'll do uh mindfulness and breathing." Or Mondays I don't know
you just like do a whole sit one or the other so you can play around with it
explore with it and you'll start to see that if we have this loving kindness
practice it really starts to impact the like mindfulness of breathing the insight practice there's this
warm-heartedness that starts to show up with whatever is being known whatever is
being seen with our meditation practice it just starts to unfold in a
much more smooth way helpful way
so I'm going to read this poem again maybe in this uh context after her
hearing this this poem is called because by
Rosemary Tramer so I can't save the world can't
save even myself can't wrap my arms around every frightened child can't
foster peace among nations can't bring love to all who feel
unlovable so I practice opening my heart right here in this room and being gentle
with my insufficiency i practice walking down the street heart first
and if it is insufficient to share love I will practice loving
anyway i want to converse about truth about trust i want to invite compassion
into every interaction one willing heart can't stop
a war one willing heart can't feed all the hungry and sometimes daunted by a
task too big I tell myself what's the use of trying
but today the invitation is clear to be
ridiculously courageous in love to open the heart like a lilac and
may knowing freeze is possible and opening anyway to take love seriously to give
love wildly to race up to the world as if I were a puppy adoring and unjaded
stumbling on my own exuberance to feel the shock of indifference of
anger of cruelty of fear and stay open to love as if it
matters as if the world depends on
it to love as if it matters as if the world depends on it
so I think I'll close there and open it up to see if there's some questions or comments so thank
you so when I was 21 um like my uncle was in the Navy he was
a pilot and I was a really good athlete i was working out all the time i I was thinking about trying to become a Navy
Seal the good trying to apply and see what would happen well ultimately stopped me was I thought you know what i
don't think I could shoot anyone i couldn't kill anyone so I didn't even I just said "Forget it." My question is
hypothetical question is for someone who is a Navy Seal and the president has
ordered them to assassinate uh some terrorist leader can they have loving
kindness for who they're about to kill do you think or would they have to kind of like suspend that within themselves
so they could so they could do the mission i don't
know i'm not a Navy Seal and I haven't been in that position so I I don't I
don't spec I don't need to speculate i can't speculate exactly but yeah no I
love your talk cuz your talk was why I chose not to do it i can't do that i
just couldn't do that you know my my uncle wanted me to and he was pushing me to but I said you know I can't I I
couldn't I couldn't shoot someone so that's why I just gave up on that so and
there's lots of avenues of things to do with one's life other than that yeah great thank you thank you
thank you for the speech um in the middle of the speech that you mentioned uh meta the loving love kindness uh
practice would help with the aversion and that will help us to say
yes to the reality um yeah I heard about that too
could you I mean I was on a retreat and my teacher taught about talk mentioned that too but that was inside tree so
they didn't talk further so I could you like elaborate more how the like what
part of the practice will help us say yes to the reality yeah yeah so let's
I'm just going to make this up let's say that you're at a dharma talk on a Monday night in a meditation center and let's
say that you feel like oh why is this person talking so long i want to go home so there's a certain amount of aversion
can you just recognize the experience of the aversion not what's you don't have
to uh change what's happening an aversion and how does that get experienced it's often like maybe
tightening of the jaw there maybe the shoulders go up and maybe there's this like sense of restlessness like wanting
to leave so to be willing to even turn towards the aversion is not so easy
because so often we have aversion to aversion so this like the loving
kindness practice to help us soften up like okay I'll I'll she's saying in this
I forgot what the exact line is but to have love the world okay can you just bring have this yes love the experience
and so what often happens is you have aversion to the aversion to the aversion and then you have aversion to the
aversion to the aversion and it just goes on and then at some point you're feeling like oh wait I think I can meet
this this experience and it doesn't matter whether it's the third iteration
of a version or the first or the 300th but there's this way with softening the
heart somehow just makes it easier to turn towards
it thank you
anybody else have a comment or a question yeah right behind you can
Thank you for this reminder can you Can you use it put the microphone like this like this yeah there we go yeah thank
you for this reminder that this practice can help us open to what's happening and
not turn away from it one way I heard this phrase is to make fear feel safe
which I didn't always understand what that meant but I think I do now thank you yes yes make fear feel safe this is
exactly that is to have some warm-heartedness towards towards the uh
what's being experienced thank you thank you for the beautiful words uh and
the poem my question is regarding um just if you could comment a bit on
when this feeling of um you know wanting to care for oneself
uh arises but then there's this other other uh uh force that is like um maybe
inertia or just as you said like just the forces of the world and so on uh
what type of things uh can we do to to promote this sort of um just
caring for oneself mhm mhm can you care for that feeling of not
wanting to care for yourself whether it's the inertia or you know often there's this sense like no you have to
work harder you have to achieve more attain more right there's so much of that message can you care for that feeling
like oh yeah okay oh here's that feeling i have to achieve more i have to attain more hello that feeling I kind of wish
you weren't here but here you are so there's this way we don't just to
acknowledge it and it doesn't mean that we're not going to stop wanting to achieve and attain immediately but to
not make that be a problem what happens is things start to just come together and it's like oh yeah okay this feeling
of drive achieve attain and even sometimes to not take care of myself
okay that can be part of the mix too and I also have this feeling of wanting to take care of myself and can I honor and
respect that there's these two different things that are going on and can that be okay and so without
insisting that one's wrong and one's right And that's the beginning like it was like okay yeah it's a mixture it's
not neat and tidy it's not so obvious sometimes how to go forward or with
wanting to take care of oneself but for that to be okay
thank you
anybody else have something they'd like to say sure
i forget how to do this like so okay thank you well I always feel like I have
to fix the world i have to fix all the things I don't like that I see in the world and other people too of course of
course that's how it works and I can't seem to get away from that i don't It's just this obsession I have like if I see
a woman walking down the street and she's just she could so looks so much light nicer than she looks but she's
dress dressing like a slob and all she has to do is just you know what not much
but you know it sounds like maybe you know what I'm talking about maybe I don't know
yeah this is quite something so I have a few things to say about this okay um
often when we're about the way that we have about what we're seeing external it's not so different than what's
happening internally that same kind of voice is often where think like oh I
really should be doing this or that and that person over there really should be doing this and that the same type of
thing if you look closely we'll see these same type of uh energies so that's actually me then and
not the other person right we're just one person right and
we're not like we have a completely different inner life that's uh completely separated from our outer life
but often our inner life is really uncomfortable for whatever reasons so
we're really focused out there like I want to fix things and this idea of
wanting to fix things is related to wanting to control things of course we
want to control the world and so there's because then everything would be fine right
but turns out right we don't control other people and we don't control the world but we keep trying but there's
this way if we can just realize yeah actually I don't
control this or that or this person or that or that turns out we control so
much less than we think we do and just even noticing that makes your life just
go so much easier just to recognize oh yeah I don't have to control what's happening over there and to kind of step
back and be with our own experience because it's frustrating because we
don't control things and yet we keep on trying so these are two big giant things
the idea of trying to control and the way that often we're busy with things out there I'm using this word busy just
to this we're oriented towards things out there when what's in here is really
uncomfortable or Maybe not always uncomfortable it's just not a habit to
be familiar with our what's happening with ourselves sometimes we've been
socialized or something to just really be focused outwards so I shouldn't say it's only just to be
uncomfortable how does this sound that sounds pretty good well a girlfriend of mine is just always trying to fix me
always so so my situ result what I should do is just change the subject
right cuz she asked me how I am i tell him I tell her I how I am and then well
you did this you did that and have you thought about doing this and that i'm becoming like her in a way and I hate
that because I don't like when she tries to fix me well yeah and so what I'll tell you
sometimes what I say if this happens to me oh Diana you really should and I say I know wouldn't it be great if you could
control everything and then I kind of laugh and I recognize oh yeah okay I'm just trying
to control you Diana that's a pretty big responsibility yeah right right
so I I think we'll end there it's uh 8:30 here but thank you all for your
attention and your practice and I'm wishing you a lovely rest of the evening and safe travels home thank you
and if you'd like you're welcome to come up here and uh talk to me if you'd like