good morning everyone good morning good day warm
greetings this is a sound check and while I'm waiting to hear from
you for the sound check because there's a minute or two delay
um just want to express my delight at being with this worldwide SA and also um
to check in and see those of you who um tried out the homework if you
reflected on one action of body speech or mind yesterday what did you notice
i would love for you to take a moment in silent reflection or perhaps to share
that reflection either now aloud or with others later or by writing it down later
so with
that just name that reflecting on actions body speech and
mind can be a lifelong practice
and in the talk today I'll be talking a little bit more
about bringing a perspective of lifelong
practice into how we practice how we live
so some people are saying loving and kindness with a conversation with your
son wonderful some things lots of things can
remain unsaid yes that can be
wisdom
so I promise to look at the rest later and
[Music] um I want to invite you now to settle
in to meditation take a posture that allows
for receptivity
groundedness [Music] calm
[Music]
kindness allowing the eyes to close
the eyes to soften and the tongue to
soften turning the gaze inward and softening inner
speech or perhaps even allowing it to slow down or stop
starting with a few deeper slower
breaths and inviting a wave of
relaxation down your body
tuning into the context the surroundings of the room
being receptive to sound
[Music] sensation warmth or
cool the weight of your body taking your place your seat on this
earth
and allowing the breathing to be
natural and inviting the attention to rest on each breath
inviting the attention the awareness to [Music] brighten on the inb
breath and to let go relax surrender to the
outreath allowing the attention to be
invited encouraged to be here
immersing in the breath
noticing and appreciating any moments of
ease comfort
any soothing qualities of the
breath of being present
allowing the attention to steady to
unify with the ease simplicity of breathing
if the mind is pulled away it's
natural to be kind and
gracious with what minds do
and to appreciate
welcome the return of awareness of this
moment this breath
noticing appreciating any
softening
relaxation any sense of Being soothed or pleasant
sensations no matter how small in the
breath in your heart
letting go with kindness with
compassion on the
outreath inviting present awareness on the inb breath
if the mind is pulled away [Music]
allowing the sensations of
aliveness of the inb breath and outreath to call the mind
back here now
staying in contact with all the sensations of the
inb
breath to the very top fullness of the inb
breath and all of the sensations of the release of the
outreath like stroking A beloved animal
perhaps noticing the still points the
pause at the end of the
outreath and letting go into
that
releasing before the natural arising with the inb breath
as the mind begins to steady if it
does inviting a letting go into the
moment a loving letting
go on each exhale let go let go let go
[Music] immersing
softening into the moment
in the last remaining moments of our meditation
together noticing taking in
appreciating Any [Music]
softening any peace any
steadiness [Music]
savoring any little glimpse or corner of goodness
is reflecting back on these moments of
meditation and gathering them up in your
heart in your body
and from that
place offering perhaps with an internal gesture
the sense of generosity of letting [Music] go offering that goodness those benefits
out into the world the others your life touches or
has touched
may they be safe
happy as healthy as possible no matter what their
condition may they heal into
peace may they know ease
and may they be
free may our practice here together be a cause and
[Music] condition for greater peace and letting
go in our own lives
and in all of the lives we touch and all of the lives they touch
outwards and outwards rippling may all beings be
safe peaceful and free of suffering
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
i feel almost too calm to think or speak but um I guess it's my place in
our time together to speak so here I go
first just to um to say that if you would like to practice together more online I'll be
offering a half day through the Sati Center for Buddhist
Studies and um that is August 16th I
believe can go to their website for more information
and we have now reached the fifth talk in our series here this week
on inspirations for insight stories and myths from the Buddha's life
and how they relate to insight freedom practice
is and this is indeed the last story of the Buddha's life it's the story of his
last teachings his final words and his last
meditation so as some of you may be
aware the Buddha lived to quite a good old age for ancient India and according
to his own words in the ancient discourses he was around 80 years old
and he had been traveling teaching on foot for 40 years founding an
order and in the months before his death he knew he didn't have very much time
left and he was very clear about his priorities so he traveled around
emphasizing a certain teaching that I'll get into a bit more later
and then in his last hours he arrived at a little town and sort of was a bit
cloistered he saw one or two visitors and then when it was approaching the
time for him to go he settled between two Saul trees and the members of his order
gathered around and I think other kind of disciples lay disciples gathered
around and he lay down and he took the time to ask if they
had any last questions anything he needed to clear
up and no one
did so his last words and I'm paraphrasing of course here is make of
yourself a light a lamp an island look for no other
refuge and then right after that he said "Make the dharma your light your lamp
an island no other refuge take refuge in the practice in other words take refuge
in the teachings and he did this without appointing a successor very pointedly
did not name a successor the teachings the practices the ethical framework that
had developed within his time with this sa those were his
successors then his final meditation he entered into
samadei systematically going up and down through all of the janna and the
immaterial jas or immaterial bases which Gil covered in the last weeks and then
he went back down back up and entered the fourth
Janna which is deeply peaceful and equinimous and it was from there it said
that he released he let go into the final nibana pari nibbana unbinding and
death and in this story the trees beside him and all of the trees in the area
went into bloom out of season and scattered their petals down like I think
about knee deep by rubbish pile deep and it's quite something you know this
beautiful scent and if we take this as a mythic element just like in the story of his
awakening flowers here are linked to inner beauty ethical
virtue so that's a very brief version of this story
what might contemplating it offer in terms of supporting inspiring
insight well first the Buddha
repeatedly presumably intentionally gave a specific teaching
in the weeks before he died when he'd already realized it was time to let go of his life energy
and I'm summarizing here um this is from dean Aaya long discourses
16 concentrated concentration that is samadei fortified with virtue brings
great benefits understanding fortified with
samadei brings great benefits and great fruits that is
insight and a heart fortified with understanding A heart fortified with understanding
becomes completely
liberated so that's a summary it's based on Nyanamole's translation i think it's
significant that this is the theme that he expounded in his final
days to summarize the summary virtue is a basis for concentration beneficial
samadei which supports understanding but yields insight which in turn supports
complete freedom liberation and his meditative process
then demonstrated and refined that teaching
it's an understatement perhaps to say that the Buddha lived a life of great
virtue and this supported his capacity to easily access Janna near
death at death in particular the Buddha chose the fourth Janna as his final
release and the tradition teachers to this day teach that the fourth Janna
that place even less than um full Janna is the best departure point for
insight that kind of peace that kind of equinimity it may be for a split second
in the middle of a storm or it may be a long period of calm relaxed equinimity
the process of letting go dissolution is important for insight and
for liberation and the Buddha demonstrates for his total unbinding at
the moment of death so to just bring this into our
contemporary world as a hospital chaplain I had the profound privilege of
being in the presence of a number of people dying it changed me it changed me
those who can enter samati states at will at death are rare
but less rare and just as beautiful are those who have done their inner work who
have served the dharma selflessly or served others who have lived true to
themselves ethically who have cleaned up any messes in their
lives at least in their hearts and let go at peace it's
palpable when you're in a room with someone in that kind of peace
perhaps one way to summarize this from a Buddha Buddhist
perspective is to again paraphrase the Buddha's last
words make of yourself a place of safety refuge for yourself and
others allow yourself to be a light a lamp an
island let the dharma let the practice and the teachings be your lamp island
refuge refuge in the practices of ethical and
meditative cultivation and of a generous
heart keeping death in mind in life can
serve as a reminder of what's most important what do I want to look back on
eventually oh becomes very easy to make certain
decisions in other words to be peaceful in the dying
process it's helpful to live in such a way that one can reflect back and feel
at ease with
so this supports insight it supports wise relationship supports a vibrant
loving peaceful contented life so in summary for this week the Buddha's
example can inspire each of us to insight and living well by
cultivating simplicity and contentment by
cultivating wise nourishment and a learning mindset with whatever arises in our
lives hearts and minds and by cultivating
mindfulness non-contention kindness and honest
self-reflection may this path support you in a life of peace love and
ease thank you for your kind attention