okay uh welcome uh welcome
all um yeah nice to see your
names so
uh see if I have any inspiring words to say before
sitting I do not but I'm happy to uh to practice with
you so uh yeah find uh find your posture
just over time the months and years maybe decades
just coming into Stillness has so many connotations kind of muscle
memory the muscle memory of uh Dharma practice
maybe we touch into some of the
tranquility open-heartedness
the ways in which um our practice is a kind of
recollection of uh that which we've always
loved e
we relax whatever can be
relaxed and whatever tension remains we allow to
remain e
the sense of self is the kind of locust uh
headquarters uh for controlling samsara controlling this
realm and
surrender there's this gesture of uh um the self laying
down always trying to uh grip experience and then
we
release
e
e e
the Machinery of thinking and feeling it's kind of the the uh
tools we use to orchestrate are
clinging our feeling system sounding the alarms
and our uh words mental
images visual thinking and auditory thinking
orchestrate the control
and so in practice we become
aware these Dynamics
emotion in our body mental images words
we feel our feelings we see our visual thoughts image of your
body or scenes or memory image of
me and we hear our auditory thoughts e
rather than using or thinking to control some
Sor we become awake to
it and practice laying down
surrender
e
e e
we're moving from a life of acquisition and
control to the intention simply to be
awake ordinarily Moment by moment we're forming
the kind of ground for Action
formulating strategy even if it's very
subtle drawing up our war plans for samsara
practice
surrendering wa don't
uh need any plans the ground the
headquarters headquarters of uh strategy
and our knowing doesn't have to know much at
all doesn't have to be quietly nursing some secret agenda of
control acquisition we lay
down
e
e e
in a sense we're just noticing the
contraction of
self the ways in which um sense of uh
control is experience as a um as
tension as a
weight we keep relaxing renouncing
equinom ising the sense
of
uncertainty that sponsors the attempt to
control we habituate to
anicha
e
e e
[Music]
[Music] e
okay good to uh practice with you um
let us continue my fake list
um Leonard uh Leonard Cohen towards the end of his life kind of
uh reflecting on his uh suffering well-being was asked if he you know um
if he still uh still suffered the way he used to and he said uh no
and uh then added you know it's not so much I got what I was looking for but
the search itself dissolved so yesterday was uh
awe and today uh surrender and that's a word that's not
not used so much in in our um
tradition uh Associated more with the monotheistic
tradition um love this from from uh St Augustine um we are but a particle of
thy creation thou a wakest us to Delight in thee praise for Thou made us for
thyself and our heart is restless until I Repose
until it Repose in thee hide not the face from me let me die lest I die only
let me see thy face my soul is like a house small for
you to enter but I pray you to enlarge it it is in
Ruins but I ask you to remake it it contains so much that you will not be
pleased to see this I know and do not
hide but who is to rid it of these
things there is no one but
you I I've always found that uh moving since I
read read that uh in college many years
ago and I was probably averse to it uh then
in some ways and now kind of recognize something about
it and we in Dharma we don't exactly
surrender we're not surrendering to God exactly but um you you might say
we're surrendering to the moment surrendering to love surrendering to not
self surrendering to uh to the
path so on the one hand in practice we're encouraged to be independent to
verify aaso see you know ex explore for oneself
to verify the teachings directly right the you know
popularize kalas you know of um when you
know for yourselves these this is skillful then you should enter and
remain in that right
um so there's a measure of Independence in that and of course surrender is um
can be dangerous many of us in one way or another at some point have
surrendered to bad ideas or bad people or bad
habits but the surrender of which um I'm speaking
um ah so much of the goodness of the path requires a measure of
surrender and maybe we can say in the Dharma our our
power comes from a kind of surrender we're
not surrendering to someone not exactly surrendering to the Buddha or something
like this but we are surrendering to the moment and trusting
that it will shape our heart well you know
that that's not um that doesn't come naturally to us the Dharma practice about trusting
that all phenomena can nurture Freedom no no
phenomena discriminate against
freedom and when the the kind of confinement of this self melts
and the all the agendas of control uh all facts are friendly to again quote
Carl Rogers the will to um Power the urge to
possess to dominate to control that cannot take us deep into the Dharma
practice can stay kind of like uh um kind
of autant of the ego or sort of like a
you know a tool of our control but something there's a kind of phase shift
in practice whereby we um start letting
go we offer ourselves up meditation is no longer a kind of instrument of our
controlling tendencies that sense of self is just like is the Locust of
control and for me you know willfulness seems to to
draw its energy from something very young feels like very deep in my biology
feels like a kind of white hot core of very
Primal anger maybe anger is too much but it to say
it's like doing this will not be
stopped will hold control the sense of self almost
constellates as the Locust of control that's what I was pointing to in the sit
the way in which we're always like cobbling together the ground of our
headquarters and a lot of the ground that we make that sense of peering out
on experience from headquarters is is about controlling
experience and the doing this of the self begins to surrender amidst you know
begins to to rest amid
surrender and so we we don't like this process but we want
to look to examine you know like what does our practice look like on the other
side of our willfulness and we don't like
it but uh the most transformative practice often
unfolds when the ego is all out of mood
that's um when we really discover the necessity of
love we surrender in some ways at the beginning of our path to
acknowledge I don't really know how to live you know which we're too ashamed to
say explicitly maybe even to ourselves but love look if
you're sitting you know if you're if you're on
this PA this path is not plan a sitting with Matthew Bren silver 7
a.m. Pacific Time listening to him ramble about suffering that's not plan a
none of you dreamed of that as a
child I didn't either
but here we are don't quite know how to
live that's the intensity of this
realm and uh to be present is to
surrender to stop trying to predict and govern the future that's
surrender mindfulness is a kind of surrender we don't emphasize it so much
we emphasize generally the active attentional marshalling of the spotlight
and that's that's that's one dimension of it but then the receptivity and the
openness is the self laying down and we
often want to do something to the moment
right rather than be changed by
experience and a lot of this path is about just like the trust I want to be
changed by This Moment by this
breath until to um to stop fidgeting with Sam Sara to
let go of ownership and acquisition and control this entails a measure of
some of of surrender to uh you know to forgive the
imperfection of this realm we have to surrender at least in
some moments in order to relinquish the kind
of um stories that no longer serve us the Frameworks that have animated our
life we have to surrender to not
knowing the need to to know to always be
oriented to always keep tabs
on self and other like and dislike past and
future the the need to know is suffused with volitional Energies
urgencies and motives intentions
control and everything looks different when the volitional energies dissolve
and surrender is the dissolution of volitional
energy surrenders the dissolution of of volitional energy
and that's not resignation there's a lot of dignity in
that many people on this path describe the sense of self Getting
Thinner and they're as they're thinning out um
getting deeper quieter they're sort of jerked back into the
self by their kind of oldest habit you
know maybe fear and we're practicing surrendering
to groundlessness and trusting that uh the Stillness is Refuge
that's protection enough the heart is maybe we say protected by
Dharma even when we're disoriented or lack the ordinary reference points of I
Me Mine ownership and
acquisition when the cultivation of somat that Gil's been speaking to
there's effort involved but often less than we imagine and at some point the
effort is just more agitation we actually have to surrender the you know
the disolution of volitional energies of control at the kind of gate way of of um
you know of uh Sade of johana meditative
absorption that that uh that gate is patrolled by willfulness you
know and we actually have to let down trust that the
silence will not harm you trust that it's safe to fall into the present
and insight this is Insight Meditation which is discovering a radically new way
of perceiving the world that requires surrendering the known surrendering the
known relinquishing the control
and yet this path is about cultivating our power
it's about cultivating our power a lot of what we do on this path is cultivate something like
power but it's uh in surrender that we find our true
power so offer this for your uh consideration and um yeah I wish you all
a good day and uh we'll be back uh tomorrow
okay you uh you take a care