so hello and welcome to this uh meditation
session and as I as we begin a few words of introduction that
uh there are various perspectives that come into play
in samadei the deepening of practice and different states of mind bring to bring
to mind different images different
sensibilities and different images can evoke or give us a feeling
for what uh different states of samadei meditation are like and today uh to introduce this
week's uh topic which is the fourth jam the image I'd like to offer
you is uh being in some place in nature maybe on a
mountaintop maybe on a vast expanse of plains maybe on a hilltop or something
where maybe the vast plateau um seems to go almost to the
horizon and um and uh it just feels like
there's tremendous space tremendous openness tremendous uh
clarity and uh and some there does something to many
people's sensibility that it's captivating it's interesting it's uh something very
special happens when we get a sense of the grander or the majesty the
expansiveness of some part of this earth that we live in um maybe it's somewhat akin maybe but
different I believe to looking deep into the night sky and imagining the vastness
of the stars and the universe the difference is that uh from a
mountain type kind of over overlooking a vast expanse of the earth with the space
above there's a maybe a feeling of um of being part of this earth maybe a feeling
of kind of a lucid awareness uh that almost doesn't call attention to
itself because the vastness the majesty of the of the vista
is what frees the mind frees the the eyes
from staring at any one thing the mind doesn't get preoccupied
by anything but rather the eyes float gently in their sockets and just
roam taking in the vastness certainly seeing the distant
mountains the distant plains the clouds
the birds but there's a way in which the eyes get very
soft easeful relaxed with nothing being fixated
on a kind of lucid awareness so with that as an
image to sit in a meditation posture and feel
yourself imagine yourself sitting like a
mountain or if you're lying down
imagine that you are on a laying on the on a high
mountain ridge you are the
mountain mountain ridge solid and
stable feel the stability of your body against whatever surface is
holding it up and to gently close your
eyes and then in harmony with some inner
stability weight the substantiality of this
body in a speed and a fullness that's in harmony with it all gently take a few
fuller breaths and as you exhale relax and
settle into this mountain settle into the stability of here
and letting your breathing return to
normal and on the exhale continue a process of
relaxing softening in the body
to be on top of a mountain in a strong wind is not so
pleasant but the winds can quiet and even stop
and to let the winds of the mind become quiet and slow
down the energy and activation of thinking the tension associated with
thinking the movements in the mind that is thinking
As you exhale softening relaxing the thinking mind
as you sit quietly soften your
eyes as if the eyes could rest in their
sockets freeing the eyes in whatever way that they want to float
and in their eye sockets
and settling the awareness into the body
breathing the movements of the body as you breathe the sensations that appear and
disappear as you breathe
and let your awareness of the shifting changing sensations of
breath be relaxed soft as if you're on a great
mountain watching but not fixating on anything
floating or you're looking at a flowing river and the eyes again are soft
relaxed not focusing on anything awareness floats and dances on
top of the river of breathing
and breathing [Music]
occurs surrounded by a space spaciousness openness
surrounded by kind of a lucid awareness
even if there are thinking going on there's something else that's more
important than whatever you're thinking
about this the broad
view lucid a awareness of the body
breathing of the relaxed
awareness that is not defined by anything it's aware
of but roams and
floats gently touches is whatever comes into
awareness and that floating can be on the river of sensations associated with
breathing or it could be broader
wider where the whole
body becomes the field
of awareness
one breath at a time
in gazing across a vast vista from a mountaintop or the edge of
the shore of the ocean the eyes roam
and open to take the vastness
in without being for or against anything that's there in the
eyesight in the majesty of
this overview of vast space of the
earth the details of what's happening recede from the judging mind
preoccupied mind
vast space vast
view taken in an elucid
awareness where it's all part of nature it's
all seen without for against without wanting and not wanting
all things are allowed to be
appreciating relaxed open
awareness in which all things come and go
if you are thinking feel your way beyond the edges
of your thoughts
just feel your way to the spaciousness the
openness that's beyond the narrowness
tightness of
preoccupation
feeling the spaciousness or openness on the edges of your
body a spaciousness openness which contains no thinking
even if there's thinking in the
background and feeling in your
body the silence in which the body
operates even if your mind is thinking thoughts let them be in the background
fading away each thought allowed to
fade as it appears but centered on the silence of
the body the awareness which is silent
nonverbal a silence that saturates permeates the
body a spaciousness that saturates permeates the body
allowing your awareness to gently float or
roam in the spaciousness in the silence not picking up anything or
fixating on anything
and even if your mind or mindfulness is not so
clear is there a way in which there's clarity ity in spaciousness in the
silence the stillness that's here in which awareness
floats perhaps a field of lucid
awareness an awareness that in and of
itself is not reactive not for or against
allows all things to be
themselves as the sky allows a cloud to be itself
and then coming to the end of the sitting maybe
imagining awareness is a wide field that extends way beyond the body
so that with awareness with your
imagination you consider how to be with
others that radically fully allows them to be as they
are in the way a sky allows a cloud to just be
itself not wanting anything from it
not reacting to it and an awareness with which you're
independent free of others vast awareness that holds all
people in the space in the
stillness that can be the medium for your care your kindness your
love that's unruffled unafraid
unresisting wishing with a magnanimous mind and heart may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and as a minimum may I provide these things for
others in how I hold them in my
awareness how I hold them in my heart may all
beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this
Monday beginning of the week continu continuity continuation
of samadei the theme of samadei and today this week we begin the fourth
Janna which is in some some ways of understanding the the deepest of the the
Janna sometimes there's a list of eight Janna but in the teachings of the Buddha
uh the final four he calls uh the four
bases the four kind of uh fields maybe and um and
the what's called Janna is reserved for just these first four and but then
colloally people have because there's even these are the next four are even deeper states um that they call them all
all four Janna all all eight of them are called Janna but uh we come to a very
significant step in the Buddha's teachings around the fourth Janna because it's a a time when the mind is
most malleable most ready most um at ease
so that it's not there's no lingering clinging anymore there's no lingering
uh resistance or pushing or um
preoccupation and so the mind has gotten very aquamous very peaceful and it sets the stage for being
able to have deep insight and for that insight to be
liberating now there's very little filters of concepts ideas that uh stories that with
which we experience ourselves there's a lot of equinimity a lot of ease with what we how we are and
that combination allows for insights to happen uh and the mind is just ready to
uh just kind of um receive that in a dissolving opening way to to so that all
clinging and it's some radical deep way can let go and that deep letting go uh is the
ultimate purpose of going through these Janna it's not the purpose is not the
Janna themselves so I want to be a little bit careful not to overvalue the importance of these they serve they
serve a a purpose and the purpose is freedom and that freedom can be attained
other ways besides the Jonas so it's a little bit important not to over
prioritize or feel like we have to experience these but at the same time it's remarkable that these are h part of
our human potential and uh and they create a tremendous feeling of beauty the fourth
gen is considered to be the most beautiful of it all so the experience of the most probably one of the most
beautiful things we can experience in life and um it provides phenomenal peace
and a reorientation a healing uh quite quite a wonderful uh experience to be
had so on one hand we don't want to strive for it we don't want to measure ourselves by it that spiritual success
is only had by attaining these things that then we're somehow you know the best meditator on our block and we can
get lots of status for it so we don't that's that's all extra at the same time
we don't want to uh dismiss them as unimportant or that they don't exist i
remember when I was many years ago when I was a a graduate student in Buddhist
studies there were professors who um didn't believe in Janna they thought they literally the language coming from
a borrowing from a Buddhist scholar from the 1930s that Janna were um the overactive
fantasies imagination of starving aesthetics and um and uh so it just
seems so far-fetched from what uh they could imagine was humanly possible
but it is possible to dip into these Janna they is possible to experience them and and they are far from
imagination in fact these are uh uh uh almost the opposite of imagination it's
when imagination drops away sometimes they're called it in the in the old
school of translators uh they're called transances and these are not transances
these are the almost like the opposite of trance this is uh when the mind wakes up in a lucid and clear way and uh
there's very little that the mind is aware of in these states so that can give impression maybe it's a kind of a
trance a disconnection but uh it's not actually it's a more of a we're more
deeply connected to life to the experience of being alive than we are
when we have a lot of thoughts and ideas in which we're navigating the ideas the
thoughts um and some people who are living a very active life in the world
are mostly living in their imagination and Um and that's where
imagination can can interfere with our experience of of freedom of deep
spirituality and so these uh these Janna where the imagination quiets down and
stills and there's very little thinking uh the mind becomes elucid kind of a
lucid awareness and uh where very little else is going on uh partly because we're
not focusing on our sense we're not focusing on hearing and listening and
hearing and smelling and tasting and all this and even to some degree we're not focusing on sensing the body uh uh when
there's no focus there's no tightening of the mind narrowing the mind to to
focus on anything in particular it's more like we're floating in this vast sea in the of lake of the third Janna
but where now the even the water disappears and the we'll see tomorrow
the metaphor of the of the fourth Janna is someone um uh sitting uh meditating
in the open air um in a particular way so the softness
and the refreshment of water is even fallen away and in some ways you just feel so free and light to u be in the
open air now in this deep meditative way uh and even that so even the sense of
the body in this is not there in the usual way so it's a kind of a lucid awareness
that's very aquamous very peaceful and uh in both the third and
the fourth Janna there is um
um equinimity but it seems that in the third Janna the equinimity has a little
bit more substance its own thing in the fourth Janna uh uh awareness and
equinimity uh are almost are the same thing just about the same thing it's like a compound word um
uh quantumous awareness aware equinimity it's just this uh uh it there's
no texture there's no flavor there's no substance to either
the awareness or the equinimity it's and you can almost not say it's a thing it's
almost like what's left in the absence of in great space can you say that um as the sky is
a quantumous as a bird flies through it i mean we don't attribute
consciousness to the sky but um the mind doesn't react to it but the mind holds
it it's like you don't equinimity is not a thing that is done it's just that
there's no movement of reactivity whatsoever so it's called aquatamus
awareness aware aware equinimity so I'll read to you the the description and um
the description of the of the fourth Janna and the metaphor are shorter than
the earlier three Jas and that's maybe appropriate given that
um uh there's so so little happening now it's so little to
describe so letting go of pleasure and pain how do you let go of pleasure and
pain that's a that's like a what that doesn't make any sense you either you have pleasure and pain but if you
have pleasure and pain can you let go of it well certainly the mind can let go of its orientation preoccupation
um with it letting go of pleasure and pre pain with a
disappearance of mental happiness and mental
suffering so this is a kind something very different is going on here there's no pleasure and pain no mental happiness
and suffering at all in this state one enters and
abides in the purity of a quantimous awareness of the fourth
Janna and so the only description of the fourth Janna is the absence of happiness
mental happiness and mental um suffering a phenomenal state to be in there's no
suffering whatsoever and there's no pain and no pleasure now is this is can be
seem like very dull you know there's nothing but um this is one of the most sublime
peaceful feelings of well-being that is possible for human being and so the
description maybe it doesn't you have to almost experience to see oh this is good
um one abides in the in the purity of a quantumous awareness of the fourth Janna
one sits pervading this body with a pure clear mind so that no part of the entire
body is untouched by the pure clear mind so the word uh pure here some people
don't like to use it in their in this you know in their spiritual life um it
can also mean clean so um one sits pervading this body with a
pure with a clean clear mind and here mind means more like awareness um and uh
so the whole body is becomes almost like a field of awareness it's what it is and
it a feeling of being very clean very pure
um and clear this clear awareness so I like to call the awareness here lucid
awareness a field a state of vast clear awareness and what's the characteristic
of this field of clear awareness that spreads through the body um it's aquamus
and um it's clearly aware and
um and uh so that's the kind of classic description uh
and um the um so we'll go spend this this
week kind of going into it with a little bit more detail and look at the metaphor
and so forth and um and my hope is that
having done these now over 50 day sessions on samadei that as we go
into the fourth cha not expected to go into it but uh maybe there's some way
that uh uh you can you can kind of feel the edges of it or kind of feel some
qualities of it that um uh give you a sense of what this might be when it's
complete and and um and if not that I hope it's at
least inspiring that this is a potential for each person's heart and
mind so thank you very much and uh look forward to
um continuing