Okay, welcome uh welcome folks. Welcome friends. Um happy to uh to be here. have been uh
away for a little bit but the practice continues for all of us and um
uh yeah happy to uh to practice together offer some reflections.
So, let's um let's uh let's yeah get stone together.
Maybe you give yourself some space and time to
take your dharma heart posture
kind of gentle way that maybe yoga teacher might counsel us to
get into a particular posture asa.
Maybe you take your time.
Maybe you start on a dime
and just drop everything.
Even though putting down what's uh sticky leaves a kind of residue of some
pain, some sense of neglecting something. Maybe it's okay. You start on a dime.
At points in practice, we uh become uh bored with
Samsara
bored by
the promises of praise and gain.
You just become uh fatigued by the compulsive effort to
keep everything together all the time.
And craving is always about one word,
next.
We dignify our next by talking about spiritual growth, samadei,
progress. But next is next.
Just this breath.
We're too busy knowing to congeal
the notion of my life, my practice, my sit.
Sometimes it it feels almost impossible to take just
one mindful breath.
It's like we'll never make it through the meditation period.
But um actually often only takes
just a few conscious breaths
in order to land in a slightly
or significantly different place.
The burden of agitation
and avoidance
melts. Even a little, it's worth a lot.
Just forgive all phenomena.
Whatever you call your mind, your worry, hope and fear.
the sounds and the sensations,
the pleasantness and the pain.
Forgive it all deeply.
Trust that in the wake of that forgiveness, you don't
have to do much at all.
[Music]
Okay, it's good to uh good to practice with you.
So one of the the characteristics of the
self that it feels feels accessible. It's me
sort of right here closer than close.
And the self feels uh unitary. We we have access to it. We literally
hear the self. We can visualize the headquarters of self.
Uh Dan Danet, as I've often shared, described the this the sense of self as
the center of narrative gravity.
We sense it, hear it.
And whatever I am, it's amenable to conscious inspection.
And we might say there are different different facets of the self, but
they're available to us. And
to put it uh differently, um self view
doesn't really have room for the unconscious.
And Freud um famously said that our species has suffered
uh three humbling discoveries that have
eroded our uh quote naive self-love.
And the first was was capernicus, you know, and heliocentric that we we circle
the sun. It's very funny to me that we we thought I mean, you know, hindsight
is 2020, but it's funny to me that we thought we were literally the center of
the universe rather than like
one planet in one kind of incidental
galaxy, whatever. Uh, okay. That was the first
humiliation. And then uh Darwin, you know, that we
evolved from earlier creatures, monkeys, primates,
you know, and uh and now we're like I I do my best to differentiate myself from
monkeys by getting haircuts. And you know, we're very conscious about,
you know, we're not that, you know, we're humans.
And then Freud, maybe grandiosely, maybe not, said the the third kind of
discovery was his own that we do not govern our own mind.
And uh in Mahayana Buddhism, the the yoga
tradition um the uh Elia Elia vijana
um is is I my understanding I'm not a scholar somewhat akin to the unconscious
and uh the phrase that I've always heard um the rendering of it was storehouse
consciousness. iousness, storehouse consciousness. And it's described metaphorically
as a kind of um receptacle for karma.
You know, where the kind of potential energy of our
habits, our karmic seeds lie in weight.
And um and so I I begin with this um cuz a
couple weeks ago I did something that I could not explain.
On the one hand it wasn't a big deal. It didn't cause serious problems
but um it was unskillful. you know, involved a a yeah, close friend and
colleague and required an apology and uh
uh and the details not not uh the point. What's important is I did something that
couldn't be explained by my conscious mind.
you know, I couldn't I couldn't point to it was like something else was acting on
me. And I remember dimly this kind of
conscious moment of deliberating, should I do A or B? And I did A. And it was the
wrong thing to do. And in retrospect, it wasn't clear how I
thought it would possibly work out in a skillful way.
It was like so obvious this was like a bad plan, you know,
and it was a kind of example. I'm talking
about it um because it was an example of the kind of disruptiveness
of the unconscious. The unconscious, you know, unconsciousness forces
uh it they highlight the the limits of willful self-control.
And we have these these patterns that just sometimes they just don't add up.
And they only make sense when you add a variable to the equation.
And the variable is I'm a little crazy.
That's the variable. You know,
I'm a little unknown to myself.
And when we're um propelled by
unconscious forces like our behavior is is it's less
adaptive. It's distorted. It's mismatched to the context
and we leave a little wake of debris, you know,
and the the kind of unconscious process is a is a form of overdisclosure.
What we said means too much. What we did did too much. We're exposed in some way.
And the the self-curation project is
shattered by unconscious motives, the leakiness of it all.
And the kind of fantasy of pulling off the performance
of self is challenged by the disruptiveness of the unconscious. It's
like we break roles, you know, like uh the breaking down the fourth wall,
right? Um yeah of per actors or whatever you know it's like okay the role
the role cracks somehow the performance of self is as a leak
and we're seen for precisely what we do not want to be seen as the klesas the
defilements ments have leaked out. And that often comes with um
some shame, you know, and the the the gap between our
preferred self story and the experience that
others have of us. It's often filled with shame.
And in these zones, we get so moralistic about our inner life. Very young, very I
don't use the word poratively, but very kind of primitive moralistic mind
states. And then maybe we want to hide or deny
or no, no, no, you don't understand. No, no, no. Okay, breathe.
The defilements are not self. Shame always requires a self, requires a
measure of identification
and we come to appreciate our mind is not in our possession. We do not belong
to ourselves but we can do the work of integration.
And to uh wake up is to wake up to more.
All all self-nowledge is good news, you know, in this sense. Even when it's bad
news, it's good news. And um
often we need another person to wake up to the kind of unconscious forces
that um the tectonic plates of our mind.
We we often need another person. But sometimes our behavior lights the
way. Sometimes we do something that we don't understand. We don't know where it came
from. Okay. Yes. Let me investigate.
Uh wir solich war den right. It's famous um
from Freud sometimes rendered as where it was
there shall I become. Where there was unconsciousness
there shall be understanding.
Okay. Nonshame. Nonshame. We find ways to
uh soothe ourselves. To soo ourselves to make room for the pain
by connecting with some goodness. And how do you take refuge in something
other than selftory?
And so we have to feel our way through the exposure, maybe the shame
until what's left is actually just some very clean kind of remorse about any
difficulties that were caused. And maybe there's some rupture,
a repair to be made. Maybe not. But either way, we're enriched by the
experience, enriched, changed by it, and we've
uh learned something about oursel. These kind of like dimly sensed
disruptive forces of our mind, the storehouse can be appreciated.
And the more we develop a kind of awake relationship with those forces,
the less we are, you know, are they kind of move in this subterranean way to
sponsor distorted behavior.
And uh it's possible that um
you know meditation without ever making the you know without always
making the unconscious turning it into propositional
self-nowledge things we could say I'm like this I have this.
Even without those words, it's possible it dissolves some of the forces that the
pressure on those tectonic plates eases
without even knowing what we've let go of.
We don't need to know what we're quantumizing in order for some of the disruptiveness
of this storehouse consciousness to be discharged.
But uh we'll never be able to do it all
alone. We need each other. And uh in other words, we might say that
um that wisdom is a is a property of diads
rather than individuals.
So, I offer this for your consideration and um
I didn't do anything really bad. It's not going to be in like the newspapers tomorrow.
Matthew Brent Silver Buddhist minister da da da. It was but it was just like
okay this is um this just requires some
investigation. So um yeah may we all uh know ourselves
well. I uh wish you wish you well. Lovely to be with you. Happy to be back.
I'll see you uh see you next week.