so um so good evening uh
welcome welcome folks
um okay you know what we're going to
do so uh find your uh find your
posture find your your heart
just take your cues from the silence
sense of actually attuning to silence even if there's
noise elsewhere
yeah we don't just infer the silence by the absence of sound and
we listen to the silence
and for a little
pleasantness and unpleasantness our preferences become
incidental for a little
while the the blizzard of details that constitutes your
autobiography becomes incidental
for a little while what you thought you
knew also becomes incidental
just to receive the
moment is enough
no projects no
building you're neither the project
manager nor the project
In meditation practice we stop messing with ourselves
surrender is the
dissolution of uh valitional energies
to the extent you build anything uh let it be
love otherwise just
receive space receiving face
each moment a kind of new opportunity to let down
our uh lives so-called lives are
um worries and hopes
and it's kind of going take care of
itself we'll win some and lose some
but for now for these
minutes we're practicing surrendering
control of not medicating this thought and that feeling
and when we emerge our life will be waiting for us
the same just a tiny bit different
[Music]
okay it's good to uh good to practice with you such a wild path
it's It's sort of like uh you know it looks like a
Labradoodle from the Flyers but um it's a
tiger and um I love labradoodles
so Dharma um is in in conversation with um with
science uh I think in a uh increasingly respectful
uh way meaning that both sides are listening both sides are learning from
each other and there are a lot of um dharma dharma kind of um scientific
research people who are have a genuine affection for the path and understand it
and um that's having its effects i remember uh I think it was
2006 you know I was a summer research fellow for the uh mind and
life you know conference and uh sort of scientific conference but then also par
retreat sitting on a Zafu and next to me is kind of like the eminent uh
researcher Richard Davidson he's like there sitting on a Zafu next to me he
didn't send one of his 500 research assistants or something to do his
sitting he's there you know and um the
science folks are kind of like taking dharma concepts exploring them bringing
in new new language and concepts and um and
then sort of like importing it back to dharma you know and and um you why it's
been meaningful for me to to consume some of that uh work
so this is uh kind of edited from a couple social psychologists uh uh
Richard Ryan and uh Kirk Warren Brown and um shared this over the weekend but
wanted to unpack it so uh the authors write um some people are preoccupied with
questions of worth and esteem see their worth as dependent upon reaching certain
standards appearing certain ways or accomplishing certain goals the very
process of placing oneself in the role of object and then evaluating its worth
is a motivated act whether such individuals come away with positive or
negative conclusions the very fact that one's esteem is in question suggests a
psychological vulnerability although self-evaluation is a natural human tendency with both
evolutionary and developmental foundations ongoing concern with the
worth of the self is a byproduct of need
deprivation or conflict the salience of self-esteem to
a person is a sign of need deficiencies rather than need
fulfillment they go on to say regulation based on mindfulness rather than contingent
self-regard associated with healthier and more vital living and provides a
basis for acting more authentically
so they say um self-evaluation
uh is a natural you know human tendency and it makes sense that in our pursuit
of goals we assess we sometimes measure we're not
um you know the teachings on not self they're it's not getting moralistic or
idealistic Remember Ajin Sado saying like this is not an idealistic path the
Buddha just spoke about the way things
are and the delusion in the the kind of
quest for self-esteem the compulsive measurement
and comparison the delusion is to think that we're going to drive the same self to
the goal and arrive and find
rest the very process of placing oneself
in the role of object you know then evaluating its worth is problematic they
say making oneself a kind of object Matthew then turning into kind of
spectator it's a little what I was alluding to in the sit spectator and
evaluating my worth what's my what's Matthew's worth it's painful
and to even have that question you know they suggest is
um a function of psychological vulnerability and health by this view is
finding a way to step out of the debate of worthiness and
unworthiness entirely to step out you enter you lose you've already
lost i remember Jack Kornfield saying in a in
a retreat talk um to the SA something like uh you were a child of the
Buddha and was sort of like never thought of myself that way but was
touched by that and um it was not not your special it was
not not like Matthew you you're the Buddha's favorite
child so ordinary you know so ordinary and of
course worthy i really we normally link worthy
with extraordinary but I link worthiness with with like utter
ordinariness the path moves us towards
ordinariness and uh that's strange you know that the the practice makes us feel
so ordinary but that feeling is a blessing that's a way that we begin to
step out of the kind of morass of self-
view the pros and cons what I find uh intriguing here is
that the selfing is understood to be a symptom of need
deprivation the selfing is a symptom the selfing arises out of pain
normally we um we talk about self as a cause you
know here it's an effect we normally say the self-causes da da da da da here it's an effect and
it's the effect of pain of need
deprivation and uh in the past I've I've suggested that um the self is an effect
of fear that fundamental force kind
of tied to survival and just intuitively seems like you know
we really would not need a self were it not for the brutality of
samsara this uh realm of gain and loss birth and death
if there were no pressure to track and integrate threat and
opportunity we wouldn't have to stay so glued together there's a sense of like oh yeah
the self is the kind of like intersection of the pressure to
act and control
and so we can begin to um understand why
uh you know teachers say the the self is done by
grasping not exactly the self that grasps the self is done by
grasping and then the question from Brown and Ryan is like okay how do we
resolve the need deprivation that made self-worth a
preoccupation and there's a kind of like intermediate steps in between
um self harshness and forgetting the self there's a kind of thawing process
uh so that our in a sense our needs somehow we find them
met and the question of our worth recedes becomes more and more incidental
um a yoga teacher i remember um in LA
and uh when I was when I was living there and she would say maybe quoting
Ayenar something like um whatever we'd be in a pose it would
be I don't know how much yoga is supposed to hurt but it hurt from the
beginning to the end hurt good but it kind of didn't stop
hurting anyway she would say whatever Whatever is heavy make light whatever is
light make heavy and I was just trying to like
survive but I love that line you know and I could get it i could sense like
all the places I was heavy i needed to make light places
light make heavy whatever is
heavy with self we make
light and the dharma normalizes our pain at a very deep
level and the shame you know begins to for the the
wounds for the needs met and unmet shame begins to melt and dissolve thaw
out we're instructed to um to align our conduct right to live in
accordance with our own deepest values and cila sila the
um ethical conduct is associated with a certain kind of self-respect
non-regret certain kind of dignity okay I'm living I'm not perfectly but I'm I'm living in accord
with my what I care about what I think is worthy of my
love some dignity in Yes and we take refuge we take refuge
buddha take refuge and the details of our life they
still matter but more and more they become that word
I came back to a few times in the sit incidental
that's not uncaring but
incidental in the sense of of um life always happening to me to me experience
happening to me life is just
happening and we look how much self is needed to
function you know how much self is needed to
function and when is self just kind of expression of
some pain and one just you know tends to uh tends to that pain like
a wound when is it enough just to
um just to be a person
um Garfield from the book uh losing ourselves the self is taken to be
pre-existent primordial unitary and transcendent of the world of
objects transcendent of the world of objects independent of body mind social context the person is
constructed the person is dependent on the psychopysiological
and the social network in which it's realized the person is complex embodied and embedded that's the difference
between the actor and the role we are roles not
actors it's enough just to be a person
i can play my part play my roles without ever having the sense that uh
need to prove who I am questions of worth and
unworthiness doesn't occur
anymore so offer this um for your consideration appreciate the chance to
uh speak with you about this and uh yeah I wish you wish you all well and maybe
see you um see you next week okay