so uh so welcome folks
um yeah good to um good to be with you um yeah thinking of the La Sa and uh
others um have very uh visceral impact on me been not that it did anybody any
good but uh been up since 2 am just couldn't go back to bed there something
about the the images that stayed with me and
um and um and we practice we do other things but we
practice and practice um
the the invitation practices this very deep surrender
to in a sense to put down the world and that feels like some kind of
Abandonment and maybe it is maybe it is a certain way of like really radically
putting down the world but we come back to it we come
back to it with a fuller heart and um more effective action more
clarity but it's almost like we have to abandon the world to regain
it and and so
um yeah we'll practice just um just resting in this radical way of not
transacting anything not uh
trading this moment for anything you know there are outcomes there
are there is progress there is development cultivation goodness fruit fruit of
practice but um we arrive at the fruit of practice
by not Trading you know not trying to trade this moment
for anything so
um yeah I invite you to uh find your your
posture uh settle in just some sense of um
alertness kind of
brightness a
non-tension e
the invitation is to put down greed and distress with
respect to the
world and it feels like no no no
no I can't put the world down
can't abandon
it but to some extent it's uh a
delusion that we're propping up the world with our care and worry
and it's delusion to think
that if we put down our care for a
moment it won't be
stronger in the next
moment e
oh the these ideas Notions
of my
life the density of our
autobiography the density of time
compulsivity of our
care we actually put all this down in order
to discover a deeper
love but don't don't fixate on
love just enter the
territory of your mind
mind Simplicity of how experience constellates right
now the sound sensation this breath
let the breath breathe
itself
e
e e
all thoughts of getting somewhere making something of
yourself or kind of buffer
disrupting the uh intimacy the experience of being alive
breathing
e
for e
you're not bartering with time
trading in this moment of mindfulness for something else in the
future practice um falling into the
present
e
e e
the more completely we lay down the world lay
down greed and distress with respect to the
world the more full our love becomes
the less tenable hate
becomes e
the experience of no world
deepens the poignancy of the world
we just uh perhaps find our [Music]
own simple little ways of helping out here or
there
e
e e
[Music]
e
okay as a child
um uh I would I would get so um enraged by
hypocrisy not not um not annoyed but really deeply
affected and uh usually mobilized a lot of a lot of anger in
me and it wasn't that
I thought I knew the ultimate truth but it wasn't hard to spot
lies and when I would see a society say one
thing and do another or I would sense someone living deceptively using
words to hide the truth or when I would see something but
nobody would acknowledge it or talk about it uh pretended it wasn't even
there um it's hard and that that was sort of how I
felt about dukka you know suffering like nobody's talking about this all
pervasive force that keep bumping into and as children we
um we learn and understand by interactions with others often not
always apparent uh we sort of arrive at a sense
of consensual reality through
interaction and so okay what you're experiencing is is coldness here's some
warm clothes you don't feel good because you're hungry here's some
food you're worthy of Love here is my
love and this is really the basis for empathic connection for ma making sense
of the world together and in
um in grad school School my uh the the research I was I was working on focused
on risk and resilience in um maltreated kids abuse
neglect and um and when many of those kids faced um
trauma part of what was so destructive and
disoriented or disorienting was um they they didn't even really know what was
real you know often they didn't have anyone to help them realize like
yes this is true this is real I'm
sorry and in this way honesty feels like a kind of moral
debt and it's owed to others so that they can
make sense of their lives there's a um
tadan uh commentary um said something like all
all evil States converge upon the transgression of
Truth and to deceive another is to um
you know is to induce uh induce a measure of delusion in them what we
are attempting to uproot we induce that in them and
deceiving and the Buddha said one who feels no shame in telling a deliberate LIE there's there's no harm they won't
perpetrate and then there's a related issue not quite a lie but um but
and uh almost 40 years ago philosopher Harry Frankfurt wrote this
this essay a philosophical Journal like Co titled on you know defining it
distinguishing it from lying and uh he wrote um one of the most
Salient features of our culture is that there's so much  everyone knows this each of us
contributes our sh but we tend to take this situation for granted most people are rather confident
of their ability to recognize and to avoid being taken in by it so the phenomena has not
aroused much deliberate concern or attracted much sustained inquiry in consequence we have no clear
understanding of what is why there is so much of it or what function it serves in other words we have no
Theory I propose to begin the development of a theoretical understanding of
the bullshitter cannot be regarded as lying for they do not presume that they know the truth their statement is
grounded neither in a belief that it is true nor as a lie must be in a belief
that is not true it's just this lack of connection to a concern with
truth this indifference to how things really are that I regard as the essence
of
as Dharma practitioners if we take a stand against anything it's
against that in our own lives with our
people this is um Thomas metzinger this scientific very so sober
rigorous approach to reality and life and the spiritual approach to reality and life stem from the same values the
same normative core has something to do with truthfulness I guess the English word is
veracity the will the pure will to Absolute veracity and to accept the
obligation of veracity toward oneself
at various times in um in my practice I felt such
a such a deep longing just like let me
understand I don't care at all if the truth makes me happier just let me
understand and so in this um political moment in the United
States when there's H so much deception and such pervasive
BS such a fundamental indifference to how things really
are I I find myself returned to my adolescent
rage and this anger motivates a kind of deep wish to
show no you're wrong there's this kind of hunger to
prove for the final piece of evidence to be revealed to finally agree on the
epistemological terms you know uh of of the moment to to show no
this was always a con and it feels like okay I'm trying to
maintain my sanity as a citizen I'm trying to maintain some you know sense
of consensual reality but marshalling evidence doesn't
matter at all in the face of indifference to
truth and so this sends me into a kind of
self-righteous spiral where I need to find others who agree with me
totally and there's a kind of bond in the outrage finding consensual reality
together and I get why I have these feelings
but it's not a healthy
cycle and there I there's there's I feel like there's got to be a better
way now you say yes Matthew there's a better way let me tell
you there is a better way
probably many things to do but um a few came to
mind in the first being just simply may may I treasure may I treasure the
truth speak the truth as best I can discern it it's the part of me
Saka truthfulness and I try to do that in my own way you know
here certain Wednesdays the rest of my
life may I um May I give up on some
sorrow this realm give up yeah meaning I
cannot make my sanity dependent on the world honoring the parmy of truthfulness
and in a way to enter the debate is to lose to enter it
is to lose now I understand the incentives to
deceive the incentives of BS I'm even sympathetic actually to some of the
incentives may I be relentless relent ESS in perceiving
self-deception it's sort of like at the heart of this path you know when we dimly sense that
we're pulling a kind of fast one on
ourselves we we need others we NE can never have 360 degree
Vision but we can make a kind of commitment to veracity may I not live
cocooned in the Mythic story that is
ego may I be willing to see that
burn Tanya broso um I think social psychologist she
said that people tend to think of themselves as scientists seeking evidence to arrive at the truth or
something but we actually think more like Tri lawyers where we've predetermined what our case is what's
true and then we make the case for that more like trial attorneys rather than
openly Gathering evidence to determine what
so n said um
uh truth is apportioned according to one's strength
okay may I become strong enough to tolerate more
truth and then there is SAA not that we
believe all the same things or have the exact same political
ideology or anything like that but it is a place where we don't have to pretend
what's in front of our eyes is not
there and there's healing just in
that nature bats last anyway which is to say anicha bats
last so let us know how to let go
before the illusion of holding on is
shattered okay offer this for your
consideration and uh I appreciate being uh with you uh
this evening May uh may you all be well