at least the birds so let me pause for a minute
yes you can hear me very nice so thank
you and uh so welcome to our
meditation done here at Spirit Rock Meditation Center in Marin County just
north of just north of San Francisco and um beautiful uh rolling
hill kind of rolling hillsides with lots of oaks and some redwood trees
and uh with some wonderful wildlife wandering around and
um maybe we'll see some walking behind me in the hills
so we continue in our samadei
practice and I would like to read to you as we start uh the briefest description
of the third janna the texts say that the ancient
practitioners the noble ones described the third janna this
way um equimus and
aware one abides in
happiness equomous and aware one abides in
happiness the word for aware is sati more commonly translated as mindfulness
so it would be aquamus and
mindful one abides in happiness this idea of abiding in happiness
so to assume a meditation posture
and if you've been sitting regularly in meditation posture maybe the familiarity maybe
there's something about assuming the posture that's a happy thing a comforting
thing yes to the to entering into This quiet time for the
body to be still yes
to putting aside the responsibilities of the
day and to abide in the present moment the simplicity of here and
now with nothing else to do with nothing else to do but
to sit
quietly and to gently close your
eyes feeling again anything that feels nice for you with the eyes closed the body
still and into that niceness take a few long slow deep
breaths breathing in deeply and
exhaling a long exhale
letting go as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to
normal and one of the first words associated with Janna is is
to enter not to hold yourself apart from your body your
heart not to be in the control tower watching from up there or thinking up
there but to enter into like entering into a refle
refreshing ing bath or pool of
water or refreshing grove of
trees so to enter into your
body as you exhale lower yourself into your
body into the torso all the way down to where your
weight is received by whatever is holding you up
from gravity
breathing normally but pausing at the end of the
exhale not to hold your breath so much but to pause so you can dip deeper in to
the body to feel the source that
urge to breathe in and to
receptively receive the inhale
dipping into the
body relaxing on the exhale
softening into whatever feels good in the
body softening into the stillness softness
that you find in the body
and as you exhale to relax the thinking
mind a softening quieting of thinking
and every time you relax your thinking mind letting go of your
thoughts let go into your body into your body breathing
and then as you exhale see if there can be a
resting with the exhale
resting in the sensations of breathing
out resting as a diaphragm
relaxes the rib cage pulls in
exhale is partly a release of tension or pressure in the diaphragm and the chest
in the
belly abiding in the rest
abiding in their rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
with each exhale
resting resting the thinking mind resting
into the end of the
exhale abiding in the body here and now
and then looking around especially in your body for any feelings of
contentment happiness
well-being even if it's in the corners of your body wherever there might be some
feelings associated with breathing the torso the
body and as you
breathe rest in that well-being rest in the body's
contentment
happiness abiding in happiness
one breath at a time
as you breathe see if you can find in your
body a peaceful happiness
and even if it's just a hints of
it a happy peace and as you
breathe enter and
abide with that happiness in such a way that your
thinking mind becomes quiet
empty open to better receive
believe
feel embodied well-being
wow wow
resting here resting in whatever contentment
well-being is in your body
and imagine or have that well-being feel it spread through your
body spreading out beyond the edges the
soft edges of your
body as if well-being radiates from you happiness radiates
flows spills out into the
world sharing your well-being your happiness
with everything your awareness thinks of everything you see and
feel everyone you know
everything that comes into
awareness received in
happiness may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may be may
happiness be a stepping stone to everyone's
freedom may all beings be happily free
thank you very much and uh with this bow I end the
sitting not having a bell here
so welcome everyone
to the next week of our series on
samadei and um if you hear in the background all the
many birds um I'm sitting meditating outdoors at the
lands of spirit rock and um accompanied
by the birds and occasionally by the animals that are here and
Um it's nice to be meditating outdoors so this week the topic is the
third Janna the third of the three absorptions that the Buddha
emphasized and with this happiness comes to the
foreground and the word is suka s u k h a and
um and perhaps it's uh in when we get into this third genre things get very
simple very ordin not ordinary exactly but very simple
nothing nothing really special exactly except that it feels so
good feels so nice and so still and so quiet there's virtually no thoughts at
all certainly no discursive thinking no conversational
thinking and um and
uh there's one uh wonderful descriptions of all the Janna that uh maybe is a nice entryway
into the third Janna um abiding in the Janna in any of the
Janna is called the happiness of
renunciation the happiness of seclusion the happiness of peace the
happiness of awakening i say of this kind of happiness that it
should be practiced cultivated that it should be frequently
done that it should not be
feared it should not be feared so I don't know how many of you fear
happiness and joy but certainly some people fear going
into this very deep stillness where for temporarily we're putting aside all the
reference points we have for how we live our life uh including any reference point of me
myself and mine uh conceit and self- concerns kind of
fall away which for some people is quite frightening
um in a certain kind of way um our connection to other people is no longer
salient no longer operating in the moments of being deeply in meditation
and for some people that feels like a betrayal or feels not possible in the time of the Buddha I
think the reason why he said this should not be feared is that the renuncient
aesthetic traditions of his time uh didn't feared any kind of uh happiness
because they thought there was a form of attachment it was a form of keeping you trapped caught in in attachments
and the Buddha is saying no there is a happiness which is not a trap that does
involve attachment doesn't involve doesn't keep you in the world of clinging and uh this is the happiness
that comes from the renunciation from a certain kind of seclusion from peace and
certain kind of awakening awakening from clinging with a clear awareness so happiness is the primary
characteristic of the third Janna and um in the second Janna there's
uh uh joy and happiness and joy as I said last week is
a little bit the genesis the source of it is a little bit more uh kind of a
mental excitation there's a little bit more thrill or or
big the mind kind of say yes or something and uh it manifests often with
the strong sensations in the body energies in the body but uh it's uh it
has something to do with the excitement or the activation of the mind in a joyful
way and at the same time uh in the second Janna there also is the sweetness
of this happiness contentment of this happiness that is deeper more settled
more restful more contented and so the the shift from the
second Janna to the third is a quieting of the joy the joy fades away is the
classic language it um and um and so sometimes
for many people just the natural unfolding because as we get more and more settled more present um we're more
we feel safer more content not to be thinking a lot not to be trying a lot
not to be trying to make something happen it's enough just to be present
just to be here and there's a movement towards calming that happens it's just a
natural movement and at some point there's a calming of this joy and what's left is the happiness
this sweet happiness this deep sense of well-being that feels very embodied
and um some people uh their their the way to shift from the second Janna to
the third is to feel the joy certainly but at some point see if you can
distinguish the happiness that's there from the joy that's there find the more
sweeter the more contented the more softer happiness from the more excited
kind of joy find it in your body and then put your attention there rest your
attention in that sweeter kind of happiness and maybe even the exhale kind
of settle into it rest into it more letting the joy kind of fade away fall
away um and uh so some people can kind of kind of it's a way of entering into the
third Janna and um and
uh and with uh the mind getting very quiet so there's no discursive thoughts
there might be knowing there is knowing it might be a nonverbal knowing and um
the Buddha describes that in this third Janna there is still
sadana which is a poly word that means clear recognition
so there is a very simple knowing that simply recognizes what's going on and
that it's good and that doesn't have to involve you know conscious thoughts
nonverbal thoughts perhaps but there you know it's really a registered you we know that oh this is this is good this
is happy and uh and because the thinking
mind the the reactive mind the mind has gotten so quiet there's almost no
tendency to be reactive to be for and against any experience uh different
things happen if they do and it doesn't rattle the mind doesn't stir up the
mind so there's a lot of equinimity in this state and uh and there's a lot of
awareness and it's not the mindfulness that is a doing mindfulness it's not a
mindfulness that uh involves mental noting or or um uh it is no longer any
need to be focusing on uh something um the mind is just very
present and in the midst of it there might be breathing very and the breathing has gotten very maybe very
subtle now very quiet um and uh and that breathing might be
almost continuous with the happiness and um with that well-being
and and it all happens in a real sense of awareness a field of awareness field
of openness uh clarity and uh so the classic
description is with the fading of joy
A practitioner abides at quantamus
aware with clear recognition and experiencing
happiness with the body so here now there's four primary factors
uh of the third Janna that are here that they're kind of the
primary characteristic and whether these are really distinct
states or whether they're somehow all part of the same that can be kind of you
know like different sides of a diamond i don't know
so these four are being a quantumous aware clear
recognition and experiencing happiness with the body so here the emphasis so
much with the body we're at rest we're at peace with the body um and uh it
really feels that for the time we're in the third Janna that we're not anymore
in our normal body we're not experiencing the karmic body we're not experiencing the physical
body so much that with the aches and pains and all that and um uh these all
kind of re that that that body it's almost like we have different bodies to abide in and the state of the mind has a
tremendous amount to say about how we experience the body not that the state of mind is
responsible for the experiences of the body but the state of mind has a lot to
do with how we experience the body and when thinking becomes very very very
quiet and still when the mind is very focused very still and
centered when um there's very little effort needing to be done to just abide
dwell float in the present moment um when uh uh kind of active active
energetic joy and energies in the body get really quiet and still at that
point the body is experienced very different the body feels very very light
almost like it has no weight the body feels very open or transparent as if
almost as if there sometimes it's beginning to feel like almost like it's completely translucent or something
there's no it's like very clear the body can feel just very cozy and sweet it can
feel like it has no boundaries um not so much because there's no boundaries because the mind
is not oriented or constructing or tuning into that sense of boundaries to
the body and um very very sweet
uh deep very quiet
so key factors of the third Janna is the fading of
joy equinimity awareness clear
recognition and happiness of the body
all of which one abides in one abides in these
experiences one rests in them it's almost as if we become them
we're one with them we're unified with them so um that's my introduction that's
the introduction to the third genre and um we'll go spend
the week with this and um maybe there won't be too much to say but to practice
with it and we'll see how this goes so thank you and I'll be here at
Spirit Rock for two more days and um back at IMC on
Thursday thank you very much