good evening Welcome Welcome Nice to see you all practice together
So tonight I would like to talk a little bit about a simile that gets used a lot
in Buddhist teachings But I'd like to look at a different aspect of it a
little bit different uh emphasis and a little bit different perspective than on
what we normally hear or and you know what Jim can we have the volume go up just a little bit i'm sorry I didn't ask
you to do this earlier Let's see how that is
I guess I have to talk to see how the volume is I think that'll be all right Thank you
So the simile is the simile of the raft
And this is a a loose translation He goes "Imagine
a person in the course of a journey arrives at a great expanse of water
and the nearshore is dubious and perilous and the far shore is a sanctuary free of
peril But there's no ferry boat or bridge to take them across the water." So the
person thinks what if I collected grass twigs branches and leaves and bound them
together as a raft and then supported by the raft and paddling with my hands and feet I should
then be able to reach the far shore There's more to this simile but I'm
going to just stay with that This idea that we are here and we can see oh
there's some water That's going to be a trouble And over there not here over there is uh where it feels like it would
be safe and comfortable And part of the reason why I wanted to
uh talk about this is I saw a translation recently that used this word dubious I just love this word dubious
This idea that well where we are on this shore seems a little bit dubious and perilous And I want to talk about that
But before um I do that I'll unpack a little bit just at a very high level I'm
thinking in the next talk I'll do I'll continue u on the simile of the raft and unpack unpack some other elements but
just to give you guys a high level this idea the person on a journey
encounters a great expanse of water So we could consider like journey is life
just in the course of life and this great expanse of water is sometimes
understood as like a flood is you know something that's uh
has a lot of power behind it a lot of force going a certain uh direction We
can think of it as kind of like this overwhelmed feeling or just being like swept away feeling sometimes that we get
when we just feel like oh this is too much and just getting carried away And maybe this happens when we have some
particular stress or difficulties Or maybe it's when we have some
existential enst when we realize oh yeah death's going to happen to us too Or we
have a loved one that has a terrible diagnosis or perhaps some terrible loss
a grief with some maybe somebody has died and just this sense of okay this
movement is happening and there's we can't stop it There's nothing to do to stop it It's just the way things are
We could also say that this great expanse of water is uh in the Buddhist
teachings we might say it's this uh notion of ignorance this thinking that we can
control everything that we can avoid everything that's uncomfortable and then
we realize wow I can't even though you feel like you're doing everything right
there's difficulties are arising And I'll talk more about that
So being on a journey and coming across this flood this big expanse of water And
then the nearshore is uncomfortable too The translator here is using the word
dubious and perilous I'll unpack that in a little in a moment But then there's
this notion or maybe it's intuition or maybe you've some glimpses or maybe
you've uh heard some teachings that touched something deeply inside of you There's this recognition
oh there's freedom is possible There's something different than the
uncomfortableness that's being experienced on this shore There's something else is possible
is available Some freedom some peace some ease
This translator is using this uh word sanctuary a place where there isn't the
same suffering that we're experiencing And then this whole notion of the raft
of what's going to take us from where their difficulties is to the peace
freedom and ease number of ways we could translate that Excuse me And in this
context um I'll say the path of practice or we could say the dharma the teachings
the way things are or maybe specifically some people would even say like maybe the eight-fold path or something like
this is a way to get to the other side
So what I want to talk about is this nearshore where we are
The far shore is freedom and peace and ease And we have a maybe a sense that
it's possible Chances are you wouldn't have started a meditation practice or come to a meditation center unless
there's something in you that has this uh idea this belief that oh yeah it's
something different is available Maybe it's not clear what it is Maybe it's
very clear what it is But whether that's clear or unclear what
often is clear is like "Oh I'm here." Not in the midst of that peace and
freedom and ease And on a basic level we could say that
all beings think they should be happy want to be happy but most often find
that they're not not as happy as they would like to be or think they should be or as happy as they think they could be
We could say even that's one way of thinking about this nearshore and far shore I'm not as happy as I want and I
believe that happiness could be over there and there's just something in between where I want to be
So one thing about this nearshore is that it's uncomfortable
because right if it weren't uncomfortable if we were on a journey and we encountered a big expanse of
water we would just turn around or just hang out there and enjoy the view or the
sound of the water going by we would just enjoy it But we have this feeling like no we want to be somewhere else
that's part of itself is uh part of the suffering
So there's something um I think that's
really noteworthy or for me that touches me and that is that the Buddha he talked
a lot about this near shore like where we actually are including there's
nowhere there's expectation that we have to be anywhere else We don't have to be
somebody else We don't have to be having different experiences or create a
completely new uh life or something like this
In fact the first noble truth many of you are familiar with this There's four noble truths And the first one is there
is duka Duca is this word that has this wide wide range of meanings just mild
irritation to absolute tear dread the most awful experience So
uncomfortableness and in the whole uh range sometimes gets translated as
suffering as stress dissatisfaction
Sometimes it's just that feeling like it's not quite right
even if we can't even say what is not quite right And sometimes it's just flatout awfulness So this one word
covers this big range And there's obvious dooka We all know
this about just pain You know the our bodies are vulnerable They
have uh they get injured Last week I took a little tumble when I
out for a hiking and I thought "Oh okay you know it's going to be fine Wow
Yeah The bruising and the I don't know It just turned out to be Oh okay Yeah This is Dooka This is what it means to
be have a human body is uh to have some pain after uh taking a tumble for a hike
Like nobody's immune from this Of course this is what happens
Illness loss right these are like the obvious things of Duka Then there's also at the subtle ones just the way that
things change We think "Okay we finally got all our ducks in a row and then something else happens."
It's like these ducks never quite stay in a row They're always swimming and doing something or paddling or maybe
this subtle duke of always having to prop up this sense of self making sure that we look good that people don't
really know uh how unsure we are about some things or making sure that uh
people understand how capable we are or whatever it is whatever ideas we have
about ourselves trying to defend an obvious and not so obvious ious ways
And I would say a subtle dooka that turns out to be so prevalent that
supports the real real set of dooka is this way that we're always trying to get
away from the obvious dooka How we're always have this resistance this sense of well
things should be different things should be otherwise I've spoken about this in a number of
different ways including this way and sometimes we're often saying no no to our experience whatever it is there's
this subtle like no it should be tweaked a little bit or no it has to be
different in obvious ways and this uh I appreciate this is the
first noble truth there is duka and it's not to discourage us it's not to say uh
like oh everything is suffering you better just get used to it You know it's
not that kind of a feeling Instead it's just so that we can stop like blaming
ourselves So we can stop thinking like "Oh I must be doing something wrong
because I'm having some uncomfortableness in my life It's not that you're doing your life wrong It's
just that life includes dooka That's just the way it is
And part of our suffering duka is not really believing that And this is a
little bit what I want to talk about today We tend to personalize it and feel like it's a personal failing when
there's difficulties I'm not saying that you know we can't do anything about it and everything we do
is perfect and any discomfort we have is uh somebody else's fault That's not what
I'm saying at all But there is this way in which we often have this subtle sense
of what am I missing if I'm having uncomfortableness We have this subtle
way in which we just think we're failing or doing it wrong and we're just blaming
ourselves So maybe
what we could say one of the main points of Buddhism or this practice is to dissolve our habitual tendency of trying
to make everything be better which is perfectly natural Of course we
want to feel comfortable It's just not always possible It's that simple It's
just not always possible I have this terrible knot and bruise on
my leg It's just not possible that that's going to go away and that I'm going to be able to sit and walk comfortably It's just not going to
happen right now So this idea of the near shore where we
are is dubious I want to unpack that a little bit Dubious maybe we could define it as
filled with false promises And this an unreliable foundation for
happiness and well-being If anybody's interested the poly word is
asanka This is not a common word It's we could uh translate the poly as like
suspect or unreliable or deceptive And so what does that mean what does
that mean for us as uh practitioners sometimes we have this idea that okay
well if I just I'm using this expression get our ducks in a row but I could use this other word like if I could just get
things perfect or this perfectionism shows up in our life okay if I just
meditate perfectly whatever perfect is right that that's a moving target of course also but just these subtle ways
we think like well clearly I haven't I'm not doing something Right I I just need
to do it more perfectly Be the perfect Our life would go better
if we were the perfect meditator or the knew the sutas perfectly or uh some went
to per had perfect retreats uh or something like this This is dubious
because of course perfection isn't attainable It's just this mere concept that uh we
make up to say well whatever perfection is is uh something over there
clearly not what we're having because it's uncomfortable and then if we were to come over here then perfection would
be just a little bit more something else right it's something that we're seems to be chasing after
just look at people who you know have a perfect amount of money they have a lot
of money and then they're Oh no no no they need more Or I have a certain amount of fitness Oh nope They need more
This like just this inherent like just not being satisfied with what they have
So this perfection is unattainable or just getting everything exactly all
lined up That's actually doesn't exist
It's a little bit dubious because we often are chasing some external
experiences to help us feel better Some validation from others or some
attainments like I achieved this I have that whether I mean we can attain
anything We could um put the the grasping for
attainments onto any project meditation to be able to count the
breaths up to 10 and then once you do 10 oh okay now I need to do that again or need to sit so many retreats or have so
many meditative experiences or something like this or meditate daily for so many
days or read so many meditation books whatever it might be but I'm sorry I'm
this uh validation we kind of feel like these attainments
and We let people know oh I I did this I sat a threemonth long retreat Look at
me And we feel like oh was okay that didn't
quite work You know maybe it works for one second And then like oh I'm still the same person And you know there's
this way in which we often are looking for things outside of us to make us feel okay
praise or love attention from other people to make us feel like we're okay
And this is dubious because any sense of okayess that is built on
things external to us right it's not reliable Of course it isn't
because turns out we don't get to control the whole world so that they we only get the praise and achieve the
things that we want to achieve in the way that we feel like we want in order
to feel good But there's a way in which we want this We to feel like okay I'll
be happier if I have some more external validation
And this also ties into this idea of control Like we do not control nearly
what we think we do And sometimes we have this feeling like okay well things
would be okay if I could just control myself control my thoughts or control my
emotions or control those people over there you know if they would just stop
doing whatever it is they're doing that uh doesn't seem quite right for to us
But there's this way that um even though we realize that we can't control we we
just keep trying Controlling other people turns out not to work It's a
little bit annoying for the other people and it's annoying for us too because it doesn't work And it kind of like uh has
this uh way it impacts our relationships So it's this dubious
trying to control things We just keep on discovering that we don't actually control what we wish we could or what we
do So that's the dubious side of the nearshore of kind of like the the Buddha
talking about the first noble truth There is dooka
I also want to talk a little bit about perilousness
because there's been ways in which we've been trying to deal with these difficulties that just lead to more
difficulties We thought that it would be helpful and maybe some of these patterns or behaviors were helpful at one time in
one setting but we find ourselves repeating them in a way that isn't so helpful anymore
We might have some um addictive or compulsive or some we just feel
compelled to do some behavior that just isn't helpful
Maybe it offers some short-term relief but it just ends up deepening suffering
Whether we're turning to just uh entertaining ourselves on these little rectangular devices we carry in our
pockets or whether we are distracting ourselves or zoning out with Netflix or
something like this or doom scrolling or writing mean comments on on uh social
media or something like this or whether we find ourselves overeing or drinking
things in alcohol in a way that's not helpful or so many ways in which we kind
of find ourselves compelled with uh behavior that turns out to just lead to
more suffering So this is a perilous way just turns out to lead to greater and
greater suffering Or maybe there's this way that's also perilous that we have this habit of uh
blaming others like just oh it's if this
I wish I could come up with an example right now Let's see I'm thinking of I know somebody who does this an awful lot
So somebody who has a tremendous practice but can't see the way in which
they are always like blaming others They have a certain amount of uh freedom and
inner knowledge but when something goes wrong they're always like "Oh that person
should have done this or this company should stop doing that or you know something like this." Instead of kind of
like turning around and seeing like "Oh well you know you have a role in things." And blaming is not a way
forward Maybe in the moment it feels good because we get to be self-righteous you
know I'm the right I'm doing everything right and those people over there or that person did something wrong But it
perpetuates perpetuates resentment or the sense of separation and doesn't
allow us to actually be with the discomfort It's a way in which we distract ourselves so often is to start
blaming But then we yeah the resentment gets uh
really really eats on us really eats one's
insides or maybe that uh there's this par
something that's perilous is that we really believe something is fundamentally wrong with us and we have
this deep shame or this inner critic is really loud and we believe it and we
have this voice that's telling us that uh we're inadequate in some kind of way
And this of course is perilous because it kind of like closes the heart and closes the mind and causes us to kind of
shrink We don't have the confidence to maybe take risks and learn new things or
to see a bigger picture or something like this So I could go on with more ways in which
things are dubious and perilous but I don't want this to just be a long list
of all the terrible things But for me there's a way in which it
feels also a little bit freeing just to read like oh this is a human condition
This is what humans do It's not like a personal failing
So often like in this era of uh social media where we get a curated view of
people's lives we don't you know what they want us to see but the truth is
here so many people so many people I wanted to say everybody
I don't want to say I don't know everybody so I can't say that but I don't know of people who don't have
this So what do we do what do we do with this
so this path of practice is to acknowledge the first noble truth is there is duka and rather than turning
away from them can we acknowledge them
as best we can as best we can This is uncomfortable Just to say to notice like
to be with uncomfortableness and not distract ourselves not blame others not
blame ourselves not collapse into it but just to be able to say "Yeah this is
Stuka." And there's this way that when we give up beliefs that life will just be smooth
and comfortable when we give up that idea that it should be smooth and comfortable and that it's
smooth and comfortable for everybody else there's a way that there can be a certain amount of relaxation like right
okay it's just human This is what it means to be human is to have some of
these difficulties So what are some of the things that we can do when we do kind of a acknowledge
that there is dooka i'll I'll mention a few This this is a
really could be a really long list I'll just say a few things
Can we recognize expectations i talked about we're here on the
nearshore There's this expanse of water and then there's a far shore
So that we have this idea like oh I should be over there on the far shore and I'm not I'm over here
There's this way in which we could say this is type of expectations
So in this simile somebody is literally looking across water to the far shore But often what's happening is we have an
idea in our head It's just imagination It's just
something in our head about how things should be and then we have a
relationship with this imaginary thing and then we have what's actually
happening and then the expectations get laid on top and they don't match They never do
So just to notice oh yeah I'm making up this idea of how it is and I'm feeling
that discomfort from how it's not matching what's actually happening
as best you can notice your expectations and just say "Oh yep Those are thoughts
and what's actually happening is that I'm hungry." Or I I thought that uh I'd
be able to sit down for dinner but now I realize that the neighbor needs my help
right now and I'm going to go help And maybe there's a little bit of grumpiness there or crankiness or something because
you're hungry Instead of feeling like I really wanted to have dinner just realize oh yeah I'm
just hungry and this is what I'm doing now
And then this way in which we can meet this uh what's happening here on the
nearshore what's dubious and perilous is can we meet it as best we can with
care with warmth Can we welcome it as
best we can this is a tall order This is so much what practice is about is how
can we actually be with what's happening Meditation practice we would say is big
part of it is to just build the courage and the capacity to be present
in a warm-hearted way instead of saying dang it dang it dang it dang it just uh
being like "Oh wow Yeah this is hard." And just to acknowledge this is hard and
can we be okay with that i keep on saying as best we can because
what I'm pointing to is not something that's we're just going to start doing immediately or you know we'll change
everything tomorrow But there's this way that meditation practice really trains us this
non-resistance and presence and that turns out to be actually the
way to the far shore The way to let's say that we're at the
near shore might say is uh point A Some of you have heard me say this before And
the far shore is point B where the peace and freedom is over there and the dooka is over here
How we get over there we could say the raft is to be completely at point A
is how we get to point B And how do we be completely what does that me even mean to be completely at
point A that means to let go of resistance of how things are let go of
this secret idea like yeah okay I'm gonna tolerate this but I hope it's going to be better in the next minute
Just saying yep this is how it is
And to help with that here's a poem I'd like to share
And this poem is by Rosemary Tramer a poet I'm often quoting
And um she's using the word love in this poem We could say just meeting without
any resistance as love It's complete uh
welcoming and allowing This poem has a little bit of chemistry
in it So for me it's like the dharma and poetry and chemistry It doesn't get better So for me this is a I don't know
may maybe my fellow a fellow chemist here will like it appreciate it as well
Okay here we go It's called love like water by Rosemary
Tramer Love like water
We could say the pain was a block so great it could not be moved
We could say love did not try to move it
Love simply dissolved the mass and surrounded it The way water meets a
block of salt breaking apart each ionic bond until every atom of sodium and
chloride is surrounded by molecules of water And in this way and sooner than you'd
think the pain was rearranged into minuscule bits And there was no part of
the pain that was not touched by love The pain was no less It's true But mixed
with love dispersed the pain became something new
something vital that encouraged a different kind of life a substance that
supported buoyancy a medium to carry me
Rosemary Trauma is pointing to we don't need to change the pain but can we meet
it directly and the pain and us both get transformed
when we do that and this path of practice is all about
can we do this and meditation in the same way sometimes we're having bodily
discomfort or mental discomfort and as best we can we let go of the tanglements
we have with it or the stories we have and just come back to the object often
that object is the breath or come back to the anchor just come back as best we
can this is what's being asked of us in this
practice it turns out not to be really complicated
just not so I'll read this poem again
Love like water by Rosemary Tummer
We could say the pain was a block so great it could not be moved
We could say love did not try to move it Love simply dissolved the mass and
surrounded it the way water meets a block of salt breaking apart each ionic
bond until every atom of sodium and chloride is surrounded by molecules of
water And in this way and sooner than you'd think the pain was rearranged into
minuscule bits And there was no part of the pain that was not touched by love
The pain was no less It's true But mixed with love dispersed the pain became
something new something vital that encouraged a
different kind of life a substance that supported buoyancy
a medium to carry me
I think I'll end there and open it up to see if there's some questions or comments Thank you
If we're in a relationship or even a job or career and we find that it's causing
aggravation in some way or suffering in some way how do we know whether that we
need to find a new relationship or a new job or whether the issue is actually that we're just not being mindful and
present for what we're going through now do you have a sense what what would you
say it's tough because you know if you're suffering I'm I'm not always sure
whether it's something I I need to make a life change or if it's just me not
deal not with not with the right perspective in the current situation It's very challenging I find it to be
very challenging Yeah So there's a way in which uh we can have this idea about
what something a new relationship a new job or whatever it might be and there's
a way in which we're only uh focused on that in order to get away from this That
might be a clue that um cuz chances are
if we're not cuz let me say this while we're on the
nearshore the dubious and perilous and all this kind of stuff there's something that we often can learn we can learn
about ourselves I absolutely am not saying that we should stick in stay in
suffering or stick with the suffering but there can be a way in which we can learn and grow from suffering So this is
the question is to ask yourself is um is it just to get away from something
that's one question And the second and do I feel like there's something I can learn about myself here and if you feel
like nope I'm just uh I'm meeting this with a lot of freedom and I'm meeting
this with I have some clarity here and I'm seeking help from other people if necessary But this is just a really bad
situation my boundaries are getting crossed I'm being disrespected or you know something like this then it's time
to move on Is is that helpful
you're you're talking about this practitioner that tended to place blame
on other people And I guess my question is uh at certain points I found myself
the target of blame despite whatever efforts I make
the blame remains there Uh so I guess I'm just wondering any
guidance on how to be in a in in relationship with somebody
who who receives their view is blame Oh yeah Who blames you who blames you
well this person I'm thinking about sometimes blames me for things I try to think well what do I do uh
yeah It's funny I just think like oh isn't this interesting this person's blaming but I don't I don't know I don't
take it personally I just feel like oh this is the way that they're trying to deal with this discomfort And I don't
defend myself I just uh and I don't try to make it better or do something
different Uh I don't know if that's helpful at all but I just say like "Wow
okay So they must be uncomfortable because there's blaming going on here." And I don't defend myself because I just
feels like that just kind of like um it validates the blame in some way to even
start that conversation about don't blame me or something like that
Yeah Thank you
I think I'd be home Yeah
Um my question was with regards to navigating giving um advice to somebody
in a crisis situation So I tend to just tell them that um I think the best thing
to say to somebody would be that um there's a lot of hope for them I'm sorry
I didn't hear the last part that there's that there's hope in the future Oh that there's hope in the future Yeah So but
what you're saying is that you know not necessarily like you have to try to be um present in the moment Um but
sometimes that moment is so like such a crisis for them Yeah That I often
don't know how to navigate that Yeah Yeah Of course Right This is really difficult And what's being pointed to
here is to not pretend like it's a not a crisis Is to if it's a crisis to kind of
like acknowledge the crisis quality even though people often want to oh it's going to be fine Don't worry about it
It's going to be later So I'm not saying that we need to uh uh wallow around in
the difficulty but there's uh I know this like when uh my father died it was
it was kind of a relief when people actually said you know I'm sorry your
father died it was just instead of you know trying to tiptoe around and not knowing what to say it just felt like oh
okay yeah now now we're speaking authentically and instead Um yeah So
I'll say that this idea about hope for the future Um
I guess the language that I often use is we don't know exactly what the future
holds but we do know that things change And sometimes that feels like tangible
That feels like oh yeah we we all have this experience that things change We don't know exactly We don't know if it's
going to be better We don't actually know if it's going to be better but it will be different than how it is now
So you don't look convinced No I do That's
just my face Thank you You're welcome
Does anybody else have a comment or question
okay Okay So thank you for your attention and I'm wishing you a
wonderful rest of the evening and safe drive home Thank you
Good