hello everyone welcome to this meditation and
um to begin straight off to assume a meditation posture
here and to gently close the
eyes and to become aware of what's happening with you Just
right off like this Now
recognize how it is in your body
Recognize how it is in your mind
and and in a very general way to recognize how it is in your
heart Take a few moments also to recognize how is your breathing at this
time
And all these acts of recognition are activities of the
mind that are recognizing things that maybe you would not have noticed unless
you were directed to do
so Sometimes the way the tensions in our body how our body
is is not noticed because we're not paying attention
We can feel what's happening happening in our body and we can also do
recognition of it We can be so busy thinking we don't
recognize how we are in our mind
Recognition is an activity of the
mind in and of itself It's distinct from what it
recognizes What it recognizes can be there whether it's recognized or not
And this distinction between recognition and what's
recognized is a distinction where peace calm equinimity can be established
Sometimes the act of recognition comes along with a lot of
associated activities judgments preferences
opinions
attitudes And sometimes the act of recognition is very
simple ordinary and carries no
extra complicating factors Just simply recognizing calmly
peacefully And it's the calm recognition that begins to come into play as we
meditate So now
calmly take some fuller breaths and relax on the exhale
relaxing your
body If you're open to relaxing whatever your
body
relaxes can you recognize calmly what relaxes
letting your breathing return to normal And take a few moments to calmly
know the experience of breathing an ordinary breath
Calmly know the quality of your mind your thinking
mind how is it right
now And as you
exhale to soften that thinking
mind
recognizing what it feels like to Relax
And then returning to the breathing and calmly
recognizing breathing in and breathing out in any way in which the breathing
the muscles around the bright breathing can relax and soften Mhm
Breathing in Breathing out
And then settling
in [Music] to focus on breathing in and breathing
out And with the lightest touch very
softly let the mind's ability to recognize Breathing in breathing
out the sensations of breathing Let that support and entry
into the world of breathing
There are simple acts of recognition that the mind is doing all
the time
Let them be simple
calm Sometimes they come with thoughts
words Sometimes they feel more
worthless And it with a light touch without trying too
hard appreciate the almost spontaneous acts
of recognition calm peaceful
knowing that occurs with present moment experience
with the sensations that come into play
And as we come to the end of this
sitting to imagine what it might be like to see
someone maybe in a
distance and to recognize
them in a clean simple
way without agenda without fear or
desires without judgments
allowing yourself to have a very calm clear simple
recognition that creates space [Music]
room for a wellspring of goodwill to arise
Clear simple calm
recognition that can function as a gateway for good will
And may it be that we
trust a calm mind a clear
mind that sees the
world without our judgments biases
agendas but sees it simply ly so we can wish the world
well May all beings be
safe May all beings be
peaceful May all beings be free
May all beings be
happy And may all beings see each
other through a simple clear recognition That is the gateway for
mutual respect and care May all beings be
[Music]
happy Thank you
So hello welcome to this series on insight the meaning of insight and how
it's practiced in the insight meditation uh
practice And uh in some ways insight is less interesting than samadei It doesn't
have the excitement the thrill the great promise of wonderful feelings of joy
happiness and peace And um and it is there is a way in
which it it has a more of a cognitive role that has to do with a clear
recognition of something And for some people that's kind of boring or why would that be
interesting but uh in this uh insight meditation uh
understanding is that um uh clear seeing a clear insight
uh allows something very deep inside to release It can allow a lot of letting go
and along that way Uh but the deepest forms of release
the deepest forms of freedom um uh are touched with with very profound insight
which we'll get to as as we move along here But that process the path of
insight is a process It's a path It's a journey in a sense And uh the different
kinds of insight that a person can have can be um kind of put together as a
journey as a progression and sometimes people follow that progression but sometimes it's in a different
order So yesterday I mentioned that the one the important of the five forms of
insight is personal insight and to understand something unique about
yourself that helps free something helps you be wiser helps you to be resol
resolve certain kinds of issues and not be in conflict with yourself or the world or settle something in a deep way
And these personal insights are phenomenally helpful and some people have a profound need to settle aspects
of their personal life so that they can come to meditation to settle further So
in a sense this journey begins by enough self-standing to be able to engage in a
process of meditation that's not involved with the stories of our life
The the uh not involved with you know our history and biography and
who did what to who and things like that Those are important but at some point you want to settle them enough so you
can really start being in the present moment And what we're beginning to move into in inside meditation is to see
something which is uh universally true for everyone And uh and that doesn't
mean that it's unimportant It means that actually we're getting into the underlying foundation of what builds our
personal world and uh and rectifying it cleaning it up finding how to find
finding freedom in it So in the the first the next insight the
first of these universal insights is um uh has to do about seeing
the difference between uh the role of the mind uh and the role
of sensations to see that there's sensations that we have and then there's the mind's recognition of it and those
are two different things The tradition calls this appearances and name Name and
appearances Nama rupa And so the appearances here
primarily you can understand it as being the direct experience we're having in the present moment uh which comes
through the sense doors And so the sense experience is happening and then there's
the recognition of what that is And those are two distinct uh activities
So I'm very fond of how uh the intimacy between uh sensations and sensing If I
put my hands together like this I feel the warmth the pressure the smoothness
the texture of the palms of my hands touching And uh and I also feel uh the
play of sensations is kind of somehow some random way uh attention moves
around the different parts of the palm to feel different things at different times And um and I feel a teeny bit of
moisture ever so slight and teeny bit of stickiness as I move my hands a little
bit And um so the sens all those
sensations occur in the very location of sensing Sensing and sensations arise
together They're almost can't be separated So they're really in a sense part of the physical bodily
experience The recognition of what's happening there the knowing of what it is is um is uh an aspect of the mind
uh to know that my hand is touching my other hand that's an act of recognition
Uh I you know I've done like this uh with someone else's hand and I've known
that it's their hand It's such an innocent ordinary non you know non-event
almost to rec do that kind of recognition but that level of recognition is going on all the time
Uh now I feel a slight tiredness tension a little ache ever so slightly uh in my
muscles my arm for holding my hand up like this and um and knowing I can know
that ache and know enough enough of it to wonder now should I rest my hand have
I had enough holding my hand up and so the recognition then allows for
consideration allows for wisdom to operate Um but it's two different things It's
possible to have sense contact without the recognition
Sometimes that's confusing or sometimes the recognition is inaccurate We see
something and the mind projects something onto it and we think we're seeing what we're seeing something but
it's not I've seen people from the back who have the same hairstyle the
same height the same maybe kind of clothes and assumed I was seeing my
friend and uh and um and so I wasn't
seeing accurately The recognition factor was kind of jumping ahead before I had all the information I've seen as I've
often said um a stick on the ground in the hikes I do in the hills here and for
a moment will think it's a snake and um and so this kind of sometimes the
recognition is not accurate Uh and um and so but it's a
distinct mental activity their recognition So as we mind gets calmer and quieter
in meditation at some point the insight is to see the insight into a these are two
different events Uh there's the sensation and there's a knowing of what
it is And uh sometimes with sounds I don't know what that is there's a recognition
not knowing and then at some point uh I I know and there's recognition oh that's
what it is and um and so uh maybe recognizing a bird and I don't know it
at first and then some I recognize oh that's a woodpecker or that's a a
dove and u so this act of recognition is going on all the time and to see it as
two different events Hence uh is called uh in a kind of to paraphrase or to
adapt a traditional language is to have uh clear seeing Um it's a um
clarification of our view clarification of how we see that these are two different things Why is this important
because it sets the foundation for the deeper insights If our
recognition and the sensation are entangled or caught up with each other
uh then uh the uh they things get confused The act of recognition is a
kind of a concept and concepts have a kind of enduring value I mean they're
kind of enduring life I mean a concept can be unchanging and uh and so we have concept
of a circle and uh and kind of that never changes A circle is a circle We
you know never the circle never becomes a square and um and uh so if I see the stick on the
ground as a snake the concept of snake kind of is more or less a concept that
doesn't go away And unless I take a second look at the stick I could uh run
off uh down the trail and never change my view of what I saw I was you know
think it's a snake But if I see that the the seeing and this and the recognition
are two different things then I'm more likely to uh see more clearly that uh
these are two different events and in fact it's a stick If I'm walking down the street and
I see someone um who looks like maybe my friend but I don't really see
the person And I see that uh I I recognize the seeing and I recognize the
thought friend and I see there's two different events then I can question is it really
my friend but if I see them as the same as if
inseparable this the seeing and the recognition then I might not question whether I'm seeing accurately I might
run up to my person and give them a hug and the person is not my friend and I'm they're totally surprised There's
something about the entanglement of the way that we recognize something with the
ex the sensory experience we have that gets us in trouble Uh we uh we sometimes
live with the recognition the activity the judgments all the desires the fears
all the things that come along with recognition pile on right away as if it's that's the way it
is We have judgments about people So if we see someone and uh and uh the seeing
of them the recognizing of them uh as someone who is you know an angry person
you know not a nice person for example uh it's almost as if seeing and not a
nice person are one of the same thing As we begin seeing as two
different things then we can see more clearly and we see each event as its own
thing and now we can begin to have wisdom Wisdom can operate much better in
seeing that distinction So in the course of insight practice this this difference is
invaluable And it isn't that we have to work hard to make ourselves see this way As
the mind gets quieter as the mindfulness gets clearer then at some point this
becomes easy to see At some point we see oh there was a um uh a sound and
recognition of the sound of hearing recognition car and those are two
different events Sometimes uh it's quite lovely to not have the recognition really operating
and we don't and it's kind of the mind is just kind of very relaxed um and sometimes it's invaluable to have
their recognition Inside practice works uh partly by the support of recognizing the
present moment Uh the recognition keeps us here Stay here Don't go on don't
wander off recognize what's happening As we do this
uh we start recognizing better and we wander off and then we have maybe more
personal insight of what's driving that Don't get lost in the personal
insight They're useful but for the purpose of meditation they're useful for the way of helping us um not get caught
in that world Stay present Stay here Stay let the recognition keep you in the
present And over time as you calm and relax and
soften you'll start seeing the difference between um recognition and appearances
appearances and recognitions sense experience of all kinds and then knowing
the recognition of what that is and being able to see that uh difference is
invaluable and we'll continue with this tomorrow uh because this sets the stage page for the further kinds of insight
that are going to go that are important for insight meditation So thank you