okay so uh so welcome folks nice to uh see uh see your
names and um yeah let's uh let's practice together
so finding your
posture whatever posture it is a sense of um
Your uh heart being open to the
world sense of uh sanctity and uh relaxation
we know we're doing something maybe we say
sacred and ordinary and we can relax amidst it
just breathing into your
belly maybe a slightly fuller
Slower breath than you've taken today
meditation can feel old hat or familiar especially if you've practiced for years
or decades but we ought not forget that we're
uh stepping into something
sacred that we're connected by our breath and our
sincerity to a 2600 year [Music]
lineage wisdom
compassion and so the thought uh just little old me meditating in my
home
online now that's not the end of the
story we uh take our seat and remember
the lineage all the shoulders we stand
upon all that we owe to those who will come after
us and we breathe with that
it's a practice of uh reverence also
renunciation in other words what is u skillful to put
down renunciation is not animated sponsored by
uh a version
moralism not sponsored by the egoic processes but uh a simple
recognition this can be put down
perhaps we renounce
the multitasking of our mind
or we renounce uh some measure of worry
other grasping
we renounce
the false promises that clinging
makes we renounce the urge to make story
out of this moment
we have sense contact and the
proliferation largely a function of the lack of
equinimity feels like I must tell some story maybe just a sentence about
this sense
contact in amidst the sanctity of our practice we renounce not forever but for right
now
we renounce knowing that uh may
rearise just moments
later we renounce uh not uh like
holding 50 pingpong balls underwater at the same time
but opening the fist and putting something down on the
ground in this way we become more intimate with uh our breathing
it always feels like we're preparing for the rest of our
life but our life never arrives
yes and so
we practice um putting all of our hope into this
moment
clinging uh complicates
everything turns me into a spy and a crook conniving
scheming letting go
simplifies and samadei is the momentary
Resolution of all ambivalence
[Music]
okay good to uh sit with
you so every
um excuse me every uh every dharma
teaching is a kind of footnote on some other dharma
teaching uh in other words no no teaching is the last word
one teaching is never enough and the more I practice the more I find
that the path is found in kind of dynamic tension between two
teachings and uh so yesterday humor
playfulness just indispensable
actually uh and today
grief also
indispensable and so the the gap between
uh the freedom we know is possible and the the
unimaginable vastness of suffering that gap is filled
with uh with grief and for all the ways in which
um [Music] no consolation exists for the agony of
this realm grief
exists the dharma is said to meet the second arrow but what meets the
first i would say there's some measure of grief in the first
arrow that's not exactly a consolation for
it but it means there's something left over
even when the dharma is practiced exquisitly
and so I I feel like grief is a kind of irreducible element of dharma
life uh in other words there there is no cure for
love lar Cohen uh said uh I don't consider myself a
pessimist i think of a pessimist as someone who's waiting for it to rain and I feel soaked to the skin
if you're awake you're soaked to the
skin the the Buddha witnessed aging sickness death
and this anticipatory grief launched his spiritual
quest and the inevitability of loss for many many of us is um a profound engine
for dharma motivation it's said to be one of the thoughts that turns the mind
to the dumb dharma and the story of the the the Buddha as I
understand it is that his mother died around the time of his birth you know
the most primal primal form of longing and
grief and generally the the the Buddha wanted to be free from grief beyond
grief sorrow and lamentation it's the the refrain um but then again when Sar put uh and uh
Mgalana died the Buddha's in this hall with 500 monastics and said uh you know
without them here feels this hall feels
empty and then to my mind kind of
unfortunately the suta goes on to say but the Buddha did not un did not
suffer you know and it's
not maybe controversial and don't know about you but um
uh yeah I want I want my Buddha to uh to
grieve And the notion like if we only
understood impermanence anicha more completely we wouldn't
suffer i don't know you know understanding a niche does
not even understanding it very deeply I do not feel like implies the absence of
grief and this kind of explaining away of
grief may be um a a a kind of example of uh what um
the primatologist France the wall called um anthropod denial the implicit denial that we
humans are animals false and so I I don't um place grief in
the cluster of afflictive emotions there are many painful emotions I could
imagine being free
from one of them and yeah we can get stuck in it
grief can become a kind of placeholder for more
amorphous pain you know it's like grief becomes the explanatory mechanism for
everything wrong in our mind in our heart in our life that's not the species of grief I'm
talking about sometimes it's true where we must act in disobedience to the
grief but um generally speaking I I feel like it's it's onward leaving leading uh
in the sense of grieving consciously
sensitively receptively
listening it's hard to look at the world even for
all the progress our species has made over
centuries it's hard to look at the world and see the carnival of greed and
delusion and not feel some measure of grief
sense of powerlessness in the kind of face of the
the you know and so I I associate grief with
some of our our best qualities of sensitivity and love and
morality and I I don't I it's hard to imagine what our sila ethical conduct
what our sila would look like without grief without being informed by grief
loss is part of what makes the sanctity of life
intelligible and grief is a trope in our practice even when we haven't lost
something for many not for all but for many you know just as children have
growing pains or something maybe say like "Oh my you know an 8-year-old says
their leg hurts at night or something like that." Growing pains dharma
practice it's growing pains too and the growing pains of dharma
often taste like grief how does it actually feel to change in
the trenches of change how does it feel to grow to deepen our compassion to to
release to let go right release feels great right once we've put
something down but the process of opening the clenched
fist of grasping that process of letting go
often is inflected with a sense of
grieving how does it feel to mature ethically to have our heart expand to
include more beings to expand over space and over
time to beings not yet born how does this feel often it entails
a measure of grief the Buddha said
"Comprehend duka comprehend suffering." Sometimes that will hurt that process of
comprehending of really really opening one's heart to the first noble
truth but that truth uh enobles us even as we grieve
it and that enobling quality of grieving the first noble truth that goes on for a
long time i don't even know if I understand duka
some research on um uh from Shelley Taylor and some of her
her colleagues and on positive illusions you know and she she writes like self a
grandizing self-perceptions an illusion of control
and unrealistic optimism are widespread in normal human thought these ill quote
illusions foster the criteria normally associated with mental health called it
positive illusions right it said that these illusions bolster and
stabilize our sense of self and um I do get the comfort of those kind of
illusions um and certainly I'm not commending that we live every moment in
death contemplation but there's a subtle agitation in that
selfdeception in the grandiosity in the fantasies of control the sense that
everything goes on and when some part of us knows we're
fooling ourselves we can't settle and so the dharma is longing
for truth the chickens come home to roost and if we've not grieved the
homelessness of ego the ungovernability of existence the
end of all things we've not grieved that we will be shattered when we
discover that Buddha was not
joking and the expansion of our heart is the circle of empathy grows and we
evolve as moral creatures our sila evolves that that growth you know the
growth of waking up to more to wake up is to wake up to more to moralize more
in the sense of more and more things matter morally that did not
matter that entails a measure of
grieving and um this is not the grief of stagnation
james Ball once said um people can cry much easier than they can
change not wallowing in stagnant tears
this is a process by which uh something else becomes
love grief is completely pregnant with
bodhicitta pemma children said awakened
heart completely pregnant this is the path of purification where
we're transmuting that which is not wisdom and not love into wisdom and
love and um grief might hurt but uh the
love never feels far offer this for your consideration and
um yeah tender to uh speak about these things
together okay see you um see you tomorrow morning