hello my friends and I very much appreciate the gathering
of this meditation community that's represented by all of you who are chatting and greetings in the chat and u
for those of you who are not it's wonderful that you're here and I hope that you also appreciate that uh the
goodwill that's being expressed rest in the chat that may that represent all of
us um and how we hold each other
So mentioned something yesterday that I'd like to mention again today that the nature
of attention the nature of awareness is a little bit uh magical or
special because the way that we know many things is reconstructed in the
brain Uh the present moment experience comes in like when it comes in through the eyes Um it's a uh it comes in in
little packages of sense data pixels in a sense and then it gets recreated in
the mind and sometimes it gets recreated uh in a faulty way and for example when
still happens at least once a year or twice a year that I'm walking in the hills here hiking in the hills here and
I'm convinced that I see a snake and it's just a twisted root that's exposed exposed above the ground on the
trail And um and so the nature of awareness is that uh
whatever we are aware of in the present moment um is kind of in some ways reconstructed
So if you're sitting in a room it's accurate enough to say you look around and see the room But the seeing of it
and the room are as you see it is the same thing Seeing and the room are seen
with the seeing of the wall Um the the wall appears in the seeing The capacity
to see and the wall don't really occur separately in the direct experience
And um and because it's all reconstructed inside the the skull in a
certain kind of way there's a way in which uh the whole experience is of
whatever we know in the present moment is in a certain way permeated by awareness by attention by sense ex sense
experience And I don't want to say that consciousness extends out into the physical world
But it's as if the experience everything we experience happens uh together
intimately inseparably from our capacity to be aware which involves many different
faculties of attention seeing hearing knowing sensing smelling all all coming
together And many of us are living in a world where it's very much centered on
how we construct things So just a memory is an example of that
So for this meditation I want to first emphasize that um that sometimes it's interesting
to consider that the weight of awareness the weight of that attention that is
coterminus with everything that is suffusing and
penetrating everything as we experience it in the mind as we reconstruct it in the
minds that that has no weight It's very light It's
open in and of itself There's a way in which awareness has no pressure and no
strain even though we might add it to that as extra
baggage And in the same way what I'd like to suggest for today and there's another quality that's
coterminus that's also can be susive in our experience that
also has no weight and that is
love That is kindness That is a not not even an
attitude but maybe an attitude or a feeling that everything that we touch
know feel experience is
known with love weightless love a a warmth a tenderness a
kindness a care an
appreciation maybe a kind of respect which is also sused with
love And I use the word love here to be a broad term that each of you maybe can
find your own way to do this but to practice
samadei with love So
that starting to immerse yourself into this world of of meditation the world of
samadei is more attractive more engaging more like yes this is good this is
nice Of course the mind wants to be centered here Of course the mind doesn't want to wander off when you're in this
wonderful pool of awareness that is suffused with love
Love that is sused with present moment awareness Not love that requires a lot
of thinking Maybe no thinking almost but just the nature of awareness
almost is with a care a tenderness a
gentleness love So to assume a meditation
posture and [Music]
to as you assume a posture if possible assume care
kindness for this body for this posture
A kind of gratitude and appreciation for this body sitting
here and to feel more deeply into this
caring body caring for this time and place yourself here
Gently close your
eyes and without doing anything
else feel the places in your body that are tense muscles are being held where
there's tightness And don't relax them Don't let
go and soften yet Instead meet those places the aches and
pains and tensions with love and care
compassion caring for them caring for their well-being That that's the
orientation And then as you
exhale to allow for
release in your
body Allow for a softening around the holding the aches the
tensions
Allow for release without needing release to
happen because the love the goodwill the kindness is
there regardless
Simple weightless care kindness
love feeling the tensions the holding in the mind the thinking
mind At first do nothing more than feel it with compassion with
care almost as if it's good for the mind the thinking
mind to be acknowledged and recognized how it is to be
seen with respect and care
And then allow the thinking mind to release to
relax allowing thoughts to float away like thought
bubbles that evaporate
And then finding in your body is there a location your in your
body that you most associate with
love with kindness or care
compassion And if there is take a little bit of time to feel
that part of your
body Breathe with it
And if there is any bit of kindness or love here now in
you gently feel the weightlessness of it the
lightness of it that way in which it has no demands
No fear Just a very simple simplest forms
of love
care Breathing with it Breathing through
it And maybe just maybe
You can find love care
kindness susing your capacity for to be
aware Attention awareness the way you know anything in the present
moment is known with a even
modest undemanding attitude of care kindness
And to let that awareness kind
awareness loving awareness Now begin to
accompany breathing
As if breathing is
surrounded by loving awareness
Where that loving awareness lightly tenderly
rests on breathing in and breathing
out That love has something precious to attend to
that love has an
object an experience of breathing that arises together with
there being love Not that you have to bring love to
it but the very experience itself of
breathing is inseparable from an awareness of that
has care love kindness
and staying close to this caring attention loving attention
Staying close to where it meets and mingles
with breathing
And you can lower yourself into that pool of
loving awareness Lower yourself into the resting place
the grounding place of breathing
floating lightly openly
continuously in the pool of breathing in and out
Awareness breathing
With the expanding and contracting sensations of breathing let there be the
expanding extending opening movement of Love care
letting go of thoughts in such a way that there's
more space in the mind vast open
space quietness that can be
filled with awareness Love with a
love of
awareness So that somehow the experience of breathing in and breathing out
And you are immersed in the wider and bigger
field of openness an open field of
love with breathing at the center Breathing
as the nest to be cozy with
When we're immersed in the field of awareness Awareness immersed in
samade immersed in
breathing Sometimes it can feel that's not
us that is doing it but we are on the receiving end We're
being done too It's not that we
love but we are being loved by this
[Music] profound immersion
Deeply
centered in a pool of samadei
And if you find yourself thinking in these last minute or so
don't don't let go of your thoughts
We say the mind wanders away wondering off in
thoughts Don't bring them back Don't bring the mind back
Instead extend your love out to
where your mind goes Extend your love
beyond the edges of whatever you're thinking So thinking is held within
awareness Love awareness Awareness Love
And then bring to mind think
about what you'll be doing in the next hour or so after this
meditation And let your awareness love become bigger and bigger to hold
that those thoughts those ideas those places those
people all held within this field of
care And imagine that [Music] your awareness
love expands outwards into the wide
world where nothing is outside of
it A vast field like
the atmosphere of the earth the atmosphere of the mind
that holds everything in a field of kindness care love
Maybe arising with the inhale expanding with the
inhale lovingly returning on the inhale on the exhale
In this wide world that we share with other living beings may our care our love our
kindness extend out to include all living
beings all people May all beings be happy
May all beings be safe May all
beings be peaceful May all beings be
free And may may we as we go through the day
Stay close to our practice of
awareness as if whatever we're aware
of we touch it with kindness touch it with
love And maybe no one else needs to know
Maybe it doesn't have to be more complicated or elaborate than
that And see how your day is If everything that you're aware
of is a touching with awareness is touching with love
[Music]
Thank you
So hello and welcome to this continuing series on
samadei and now that we're been doing it for good number of
weeks I'm now bringing it to uh introducing We're more than
introducing now bringing you into the approach stage of samadei and it's approaching a deep
immersion a deep kind of clicking in a deep kind of settling into just here
It's almost like a physiological shift and change like where we become
so fully here that the mind you know is is is clearly at home
clearly settled clearly has no inclination to wander off and um and it's a deeply satisfying
immersion into something wonderful And so the approach stage is is
beginning to appreciate this movement movement to immersion movement onward to
really being here And part of that is to begin
recognizing the symptoms of sami the feelings that feel good about somebody
that um that are the encouragement are the kind of the symptoms are the very
things that the awareness wants to stay connected to awareness wants mindfulness
wants to stay here wants to know this Um it's like standing in the sun on a cold
day and the system the body kind of almost like it wants to stay
there you know with it fully facing the sun so we get the maximum amount of heat
on the body And um so there's something in our whole system that wants to be here because it's so good It's so
nourishing So good And classically
uh more often there's a lot of attention given to the
joy pleasure that can come as we get into this approach stage And it's the
it's being kind of absorbed into the pleasure the joy that is kind of the
avenue to this deep deep immersion of samadei But sometimes that emphasis on pleasure
and joy is a little bit too technique focused a little bit too maybe much
desire involved It little bit too narrow scope of what the full immersion can be
And so in this last meditation I introduced the topic of love
The Buddha did describe beautifully uh states of samadei deep absorption in the
Brahma viharas in these divine forms of sublime love which are we capable of The
first one being um kindness or goodwill or loving kindness and then compassion
and sympathetic joy and the particular kind of equinimity called uh love
particular kind of love called equinimity But there this kind of sense
of tenderness or rightness or goodness or a kind of a love that's there This is
good This is uh and so uh to begin
feeling that uh there's care there's love there's uh gentleness there's a
friendliness there's a a feeling of goodwill to what's happening It's not
greedy to be enter into somebody It's not you know narrowing down to just feel
pleasure for pleasure's sake It's um or joy for joy joy sake It's just a little
bit too narrow Um it's the uh uh the the love the goodwill is a support to keep
it all very light and to keep it from being selfish to keep it from being
um about me myself and mine It it gives kind of a wider space a wider goodwill a
wider sense of of um of not
contracting in for the Buddha when he talked about you know just a penult
penultimate kind of obstacle to really deep going deep into the well-being of
samadei um are the five hindrances one of them which is ill will And so this idea of
ill will getting in the way even the subtlest little not liking subtlest little not for this not this Um there's
plenty of experiences we can be having in meditation that are unpleasant The body can ache the mind can be
challenging and the heart can have its difficult emotions and we don't want to
push them away or think they don't belong there But uh there's a way of including them so that we're not
preoccupied by them by and this is where love can hold it
all that the and this idea that awareness itself is love Mindfulness
itself is a kind of love And uh one of my favorite reference points for this uh
well so it's favorite and also maybe sad reference points uh but is that um I've
learned as a teacher and talking with a lot of people about their lives that
when they were children if they were not really seen if the parents kind of
ignored them or never really stopped to get to know them or saw their difficulties saw their challenges saw
their joys that uh they were kind of overlooked by the busyiness of or the preoccupations or the alcoholism of
their parents That not being seen as children is equivalent to
not being loved not feeling that they're loved And uh there's something about the
act of seeing as adults There's something about the act of people stopping to to listen to really listen
out and hear that is so nourishing so good that uh uh when people listen well
it's because there's a kind of a deep care a love here So this love of samadei this love
that can be part of awareness doesn't have to be a dramatic thing It doesn't
have to be something that um people write songs about but rather it's
something very soft something very gentle something very modest something that is very kind of pervasive and fluid
but it helps with this Yes this is good This is really
nice to be here Of course I want to be here Of course I want to enter into this
world of of experience If the experience itself has this wonderful light
uh inviting awareness if experience itself comes along with this inviting
sense of love or care that is not added
to being aware but is part of being aware Um you know it's possible to be
aware unself-consciously It's possible to be aware of things that we're not really focusing on Uh we go through the
day talking with a friend walking walking through a park and we might step over a branch or a lizard in the path or
something We might kind of avoid a rock or something We're aware
of the rock We're aware of all these things simple things in the park but we're not focusing on them It's uh it
the the degree to which we know it is almost effortless because we're involved in you know conversation and looking
around and so we have this capacity for very very simple
unobtrusive or undemanding kind of awareness that uh in the same way we can
do that for care and kindness Um the uh you know maybe there's a a
earthworm on the trail as you're walking and you would step on it if you just
continued the way you are but it's the most natural thing in the world to step aside to put the foot down a little bit
different place so you don't hurt the the worm It's a kind of care It's a kind of love but it's not self-conscious It's
not just a big thing It's you don't even realize in two seconds later you probably don't even remember you did it
Uh it's not in your mind So to immerse ourselves in the simplicity of awareness simplicity of
care don't make somebody a difficult big complicated thing It's a dipping into
the pool into this immersion into this state It's so we're looking for the
symptoms of somebody and one of the symptoms is that um the mind wants to be
present wants to be there And when that awareness kind of wants to be there look
for the love look for the care And that then is part of the funnel that keeps us
kind of there and wanting to be there Look for the joy Look for the pleasure
Look for how the satisfac the satisfactory feelings Maybe there's kind
of a the body feels much more light than it has no weight Maybe the
body feels very spacious and open and kind of be in that space Feel it Be it
Maybe there's a delightful tingling or a vibration or a sense of vitality aliveness that comes Be in that Feel
that These are all symptoms Sometimes people have experiences of of
uh light the eyesight filled with luminous with maybe a white field of
light or clear clear field of kind of light Maybe it's colored light Don't
focus on them Uh don't get messmerized by them But that's part of the kind of
delightful things the symptom of samadei where you can kind of accept it and and
and appreciate how yes I'm on track This is where I want to be Let the color the
colors the lights let them be there on the periphery Uh let them be a part of
the goodness of it that wants to keep you right there with the breathing staying there staying connected
So with approach at the approach stage of samadei
um it's helpful to start appreciating the symptoms of samadei how what's
shifted and changed the calm that's arisen Sometimes the the mind can feel
very incisively that's the right word precisely or
penetratingly sharp in its attention awareness right there And um and it
doesn't have to be with any kind of strain but there oh this is good to be there sharply precisely right there on
the breath or it can feel like awareness is like a petting a cat and the breath
is the the petting almost and or the awareness that's resting on it and
something begins to purr inside And so the symptoms of sami and
one of those being love care and that um that's one of the great
gifts of Buddhism of samadei of practice is to
feel the the almost almost the oneness of
awareness and love that you can carry with you into
the world So that whatever awareness touches is
also touched by love with care with kindness And you'll lose touch with that
You'll get caught up in your thoughts and preoccupations But know that you've lost
it Know that you're no longer doing it Maybe just recognizing it that
difference can bring you back into this relaxed way in
which awareness love awareness that is
love can can then return to becoming part of how you walk through the
world May you love may you walk through the world with awareness Love
Thank you