my name is Maria Stratman i am here for Diana tonight and it's really a joy to
see you all here this is really delightful um I am recently returned
from Bhutan i've been back about a week from a trip that was uh amazing and
that's what I'd like to talk to you about tonight
my impressions of this place which it's a it's a small
country it's sort of sandwiched between India and China and it is a Buddhist
country through and through a Buddhist
country its laws are Buddhist its its attitude is Buddhist its culture is
Buddhist its way of life is Buddhist and it it is a culture with
which I am totally unfamiliar it was it was quite astounding to visit these people and the
one thing that I found most remarkable about these
people was their attitude of kindness kindness
kindness as a value as a way of being in the way that we think of
individualism you know here it's not that we're opposed to kindness we value kindness but for us you know the rugged
individual is pretty important for them kindness is really
important and it comes out almost immediately just immediately
people are kind i was so struck by
that it was an incredible experience just an incredible experience for me so
um there are about 780,000 people in the whole country which is you know about
the size of San Francisco the country itself is the highest country in the
world uh pretty much we actually stayed for a
couple of days at about 4,000 ft that's about as low as we got but most of the time it was you know 7 8 9 10,000 ft
that we were operating so while I'd wanted to go to Bhutan for I don't know
25 years or so I'd sort of written it off as I'm never going to be able to go there because you know I'm too old i
have trouble with altit altitude i'm in pretty bad physical shape it's not something I'm going to be able to
do and I
went and I was scared what am I doing and rightfully
so it was tough it was tough i have I have a need that's due to
be replaced and pretty much everything is you you hike up we visited
monasteries and nunneries all over the country and everything is up they they
live at a high level and then you climb up to the monasteries i'm not quite sure what the reasoning is but everything is
up up to the monasteries well you know they have to go up there and isolate themselves and
the monks are that's what they do the monks and the nuns
we actually visited two nunneries which is unusual for tour groups they usually are limited to the monasteries
um these buildings are uh hundreds hundreds of years old and
the iconography inside of the walls are all covered with depictions of various
Buddhas and Buddhist lives all painted in mural like on the on mud walls and
they're periodically refurbished and re redone and they have schools where they
train people to do
this and they have to they have to be of certain skill before they're allowed to
perform these these refurbishments and so everything was also being
rebuilt so the the second day we were there we climbed from 8,000 ft to 9,500
ft just about killed me just about killed me and that's when I first became
aware of kindness the number of people who helped me get up that
mountain who urged me on took my backpack from
me insisted and told me I didn't need to carry that backpack that I could just
get myself up the hill and that would be fine
and I learned another part of kindness not only the attitude of caring about
somebody else but the willingness to accept kindness is also a part of
kindness a really important part of kindness if you can't accept kindness
you can also not be kind
and so I had to learn how to accept kindness you know I am kind of
a I don't need help sort of person but I needed help i needed quite
a bit of help
so that involved a certain amount of
humility and the interesting thing was you know I made it i made it to the top
and I was there it was great the monastery was astounding
we sat in this ancient monastery and the monks served us tea and we heard the stories about what
occurred at that particular monastery and we watched the troop of
monkeys and we looked at the the rebuilding of part of the
monastery and I didn't feel a sense of accomplishment i felt an amazing sense
of joy just overwhelming
joy just wow
being around people who are kind being able to accept
kindness elicits a feeling in the heart of such
freedom such ease that we are simply not used to
we're not familiar with at least I haven't
been it was lovely just lovely
quite remarkable it's part of their national
identity now I've kind of lost track of all the days we went to many monasteries but one night we had a speaker who was
in the education department so they they provide education for everybody as long
as they want to go to school it's free uh as long as they're studying if they're not studying then they can't go
to school anymore but this guy was um studying how to teach kindness to
grade school kids because they teach kindness to elementary school kids
that's how important it is to them and he found the most important thing was to model
it that that seemed to be the best way to teach it was to model kindness
okay that sounds good to me works that that's the way you spread
kindness so on that walk that I told you about that went up to the the Tego monastery
which means something like horse head there was u there they had signs to
encourage you partway up and one of the signs said if you want to know who you
were in the past look at who you are today if you want to know who you're
going to be tomorrow look at your mind today
that inculcating kindness as an attitude of mind determines who you're going to
be determines how you're going to be in the world whether you want to be a
person who is a caring person or
not it's a habit of mind this caring this being kind
people actually would stop and listen to you can I help
you what do you need did you get what you wanted and they they didn't ask casually they
really wanted to know did you get what you needed did you get what you wanted is
there anything else you need here it was quite phenomenal
quite phenomenal the being present just being present stopping
stopping you know when somebody would give you your hotel room key they would look at you and they'd hand your key
over like this and you'd have to look them in the eye to take the key you know it's not
"Oh here's your key." And go on to something else it was "Here's your key
with you know a certain amount of expectation behind it yeah your key
right let us know if you need anything do we need any more water and
in the in the rooms instead of a Bible it said "What makes you think you're not Buddhist?" There was a book said "What
makes you think you're not Buddhist?" which you know I I didn't actually read because I didn't have time
but I thought that was
interesting and if you said that you weren't happy with something the face would just
fall it was just catastrophic oh
i had a room a roommate that I didn't know very well and and uh you know when
you're tired it's easier to be irritated about things and we got very tired after
some of our tracks and one night nothing in our room seemed to be right and when
she couldn't turn on the light and couldn't get her adapter to plug in she just went ah
And so somebody made the mistake of asking how we liked our room and she said "Well," and so they decided to move
us because they couldn't stand the fact that we didn't like the room you know it was sort of
"Oh it wasn't that bad they were uh they were so
accommodating they were just uh it wasn't individuals it was
everybody that did that so um the last day that we were there
uh five of us from our tour group went up to the last nunnery and it if they'd told me what we
were going to do I probably would have said no but since I didn't know what we were going to do we ended up doing this
walk up a very narrow steep trail to 11,825 ft elevation
and uh it was about a 20 minute high cup so it wasn't very long but it was
high and there were 21 nuns at this nunnery
maintaining this 8th century monastery they didn't have a teacher
anymore because there wasn't one that would come there and this nun had been there for seven
years and because she'd fulfilled her seven-year obligation she could now go
and do what she wanted to do as a nun which was enter into a three-year silent
meditation period and her only requirement was that she could go somewhere
warm it was pretty cold up there and this is you know spring pretty warm for
Bhutan and she was just tired of being cold and so she was asked "Why why after
seven years in the nunnery do you now want to go do 3 years silent meditation
somewhere?" And she said "Oh I'm so worried about the world i'm so worried
about the world and so I need to go settle my mind because I have to settle my mind
first what a way to think what a way to
be in order to create peace in the world I first have to create peace in my own
mind
it was quite inspirational quite
inspirational and she was so taken that we had come up there they they can't grow their food up there everything is
brought up to them you know at at that altitude they can't really grow anything
so all their food is brought up on somebody's back up this narrow trail so
they mostly eat rice and uh the government supports them
so each nun gets $20 a month the equivalent of $20 a
month and that buys their food and their fuel
you know they burn they burn wood in a a wood fireplace and they light butter
lamps to remember people so I got to light a butter lamp for my brother and
they promised to pay for pray for him
was a really moving experience to be among these people who were so
profound for for whom for whom their religion was their life it wasn't
something added on it was the way they
lived it was the way they lived and people would there are uh prayer wheels
everywhere and you're probably all familiar with prayer wheels so the form of Buddhism they practice is a a
vajarana Buddhism which is like Tibetan if you think in terms of Tibetan Buddhism it's similar to that there it's
a a sect uh of vajana Buddhism that they practice and so there are these giant prayer
wheels everywhere and stupas and people are walking around them all the time and in their
daily practice everyone does
is that's just what they
do that's just what they
do they don't know any other way of
being they stop they listen
they pay attention they
care and it's an attitude that they carry around with
them now the country has problems we heard a lot about their economic
problems and bringing the world them into the 21st century is not a
trivial activity for them their number one source of income is is hydroelectric
plants and they sell their their electricity to India and they don't actually see any money from that because
it goes to paying off their debt to India for building the hydroelectric plants so their second source of income
is tourism
and they tried to limit that and they have a policy that 60% of their country has to remain in
its native state they're the only country in the world that is actually
not carbon neutral but carbon negative they they plant more trees than they cut
down and
uh you may have heard they're the country that has that instead of talking about gross national product they talk
about gross national happiness so they're going to build a new city which is called a mindful city
in southern Bhutan that they think is going to bring them into the 21st century
and uh it's not at all clear to me how that's going to work but that's not the topic for this
conversation so I I don't want to create the idea that it's uh a utopian place
but I found the the character of the people quite
remarkable and the ease with which they go through their day quite remarkable
it was just stunning and to be in the presence of
kindness as an attitude was truly delightful
so I am here to procilitize in favor of kindness and to encourage you to think
about how you too can engage in kindness and make it part of your
life and finally there is gratitude so I have this little book
called the power of kindness and it's written by Pierro Ferruchi i don't know
if it's still in print i've had it for I don't know 15 years or so and since I came back I've I've been rereading it so
it's on the subject of kindness but he has a little thing here I want to read
you to be kind without being grateful is
dangerous perhaps impossible people who do do not know how to receive and do not feel thankful for
what they've been given are in trouble when they try to be kind they think they're being great benefactors and
everyone should be indebted to them maybe they even remind others of their own good deeds expecting gratitude they
become condescending also it's harder for them to appreciate subtle seemingly m
insignificant aspects for example a smile half an hour in someone's company
a witty remark they value only concrete and measurable gifts such as a watch or a
fountain pen but kindness not does not fit onto a balance sheet
so one of the feelings that I had when I was experiencing all this kindness was
the feeling of gratitude i think it's impossible to be in the
presence of kindness and not experience
gratitude and practicing gratitude is part of practicing
kindness and I don't mean you have to go around thinking thinking up things to be thankful for but rather notice things
like when I came in I noticed the dog woods are in bloom i love dog woods so I
stopped and was just silently grateful for Dogwoods it's the stopping and just
paying attention to a moment of isn't that great i'm glad I saw that i'm glad
I experienced that i'm glad I got to hear that i'm glad I got to see you i'm
glad just that amount of grat gratitude that's the other half of
kindness it's a very important part of
kindness so through my whole trip in Bhutan mostly what I felt I've told the
story about how I'd wanted to go to Bhutan for 25 years and I'd written it
off i'm not going to go i'm too old it's not going to happen and then I went not once did I have a feeling of
accomplishment i'd call my husband i'd say "Here's what I did today." And "Wow Maria you did
that." Not once did I have a feeling of accomplishment but always I felt like
every step was a blessing a blessing a
blessing don't fail to notice all the blessings in your life just a
blessing because you never know you never know how great a blessing will
just drop on you out of nowhere so be in the habit of noticing it so that you
don't miss it so one of the one of the greatest
experiences of Bhutan was in fact the
occasional feeling of being overwhelmed by a sense of
joy i listened to the to one of Gil's talks on the third Janna which he's been
going through the samadei and he he talked about
happiness and the feeling of happiness and I thought "Yep that's just
what it was just just happiness for no reason." Not
that you can point at and say "This caused happiness," but just
wow notice when it arises in your life it's there don't let it pass you by
one of the people who talked to us was uh Kenpo who was a teacher at the
Buddhist University in Tempu which is the largest city in Bhutan and I went up
and talked to him after he gave us this talk and he said and I did a
little you know may you know peace and happiness for him and he
said you must smile like this every day and I didn't know whether it was a
blessing or an instruction and I've decided it was
both so smile every day let it be both a blessing and an
instruction thank
you so those are my thoughts any questions
comments yes
do I press something uh this is very new to me kind
of almost kind of confusing i grew up in the 50s and my parents never said never
talked about kindness and mindfulness and everything that I hear constantly on television i'm a TV watcher my age oh so
it's just a Well I don't know what to make of it
i've just never thought that way
yeah yeah i just never think that way but it's
possible you know could just wonder what's going on with the
other person this what's going on with you
how does it feel to
not just How does it feel to be you well I This seems to be a buzz word
kindfulness no me what did I write there me uh
meta what do you What's the buzz word mindfulness mindfulness i don't remember
my parents never talked about anything like that they were ra I was raised episcipellian
and I did some TM and nami huro i've done a
different forms of religion and this is nice because I just like sitting here and it's quiet and there's nothing
there's no cat jumping on my lap and you know it's just very peaceful so I really love it but it's just I don't know
mindfulness when did that come to is this a thing five years ago 10
years ago all of a sudden where Well I I think mindfulness is has
entered into the the everyday lexicon and it means a lot of things to different people but so so let me just
talk a minute about what it means to me so so mindfulness means that you're aware of some object there's an object
and there's knowing the object but mindfulness is knowing you know the object so what I mean by that is you
know I know I'm sitting here but until I say I'm sitting here and I'm aware of my
bum on this cushion I don't really know I'm sitting here you know it's all in my
head but I'm mindful of sitting when I notice I'm sitting so there's an awareness component to
mindfulness okay so when I was going down those hills I was extremely mindful
because my knee is so bad right so part of the time it was slick downhill and
part of the time it was stairs well neither is good when you've got a bad knee and you're going downhill so what I
would have to do is decide I have a partially torn ACL so that means that
twisting the knee is bad but because I have no cartilage and a torn you know
shredded meniscus in my knee I have bone on bone so when I step down off a step
that hurts so with every step I had to decide am I just going to take it straight on and take the pain that way
or am I going to go sideways and twist it and take the pain that way and every
step I paid attention to how I was putting my foot down that's mindfulness
okay that's mindfulness when you're paying attention with every step all right now when I'm walking down
the street I don't pay attention to every step i'm paying attention to something else but walking down that
hill I was extremely mindful with every step i was also the last person off the
hill all the time well no there was one guy who's three years older than me that was sometimes
later than
me so mindfulness is what are you aware of what do you what do you what do you
know when you're aware of something i think I'm too aware of everything all
the time well maybe maybe you know if if your mind is off wandering around and
you're lost in a fantasy you're not aware but if you are aware you're thinking of something you're aware i'm
thinking I'm thinking thinking planning planning i know that's what's happening that's
mindfulness okay so the point of mindfulness is to be in the present and
not lost it's to be to actually be living your life to be totally present
for your life that's the point of mindfulness
well maybe I am mindful just didn't realize I was well there you go i guess
I mean I'm I'm becoming more aware that I need to be nicer to people polite when
I'm driving you know every Well I usually am but just just say nice things
to people because I'm very critical of people and myself that's where
the Yeah so uh it might be useful to make a distinction between being nice
and being kind so we can be nice we're polite we uh you know we're socially
adept and we um we put out the tea but but you know
it's just automatic but being kind is being present for someone and doing
something that they want and not something just because we think it'll make them happy when when what I noticed
in the hotels in particular of people is that I never had the impression that somebody was doing something so I'd give
them a tip and you can tell you know when [Laughter]
somebody's or when they're really trying to help you the difference between being
nice and being kind and that's worth sort of thinking through for yourself
you know am I being kind to someone and and that can be
uh am I using someone's time appropriately
now am I am I being considerate of this person
yes thank you very much it was nice to hear about your experience
um I'm curious about a couple of things one is um your thoughts about kindness
and gratitude in relation to emotions like anger and uh self-p protection
um and what your observations in Bhutan were of how people um are able are able
to set boundaries for themselves okay that's that's very appropriate so
um so I can't speak on behalf of people in Bhutan so let me speak on my own
behalf so uh I often in discussions with my husband you know we've been together
for 40 years we have things that each of us does that irritates the other and you
know it comes up right and so you can be in the middle of a
conversation you can feel it heating up and I can I I notice it's heating up
here and I can pause and say it's my intention to be kind to my
husband yeah but I'm right yeah but it's my intention to be kind
so is it important is is this conversation important because I need to
be right or is it because the consequences of my being
right are important for somebody's health or it you know if it's just that
I want to be right that's not important compared to wanting to be kind and I can
tamp it down but I have to be able to pause to do that so I have to be mindful of
what's going on in order to do that now if if it's a case where
uh in a previous marriage I won every battle and lost the
war because I didn't I'd always give in in the end this was not healthy and the
marriage ended so you have to know you have to also be
able to discern when to say "Okay I can't have
this conversation when I'm heated because we're going to say things that are unhealthy to one another but we have
to come back to this when I'm not emotionally overrought and can't say
things from a reasonable place." So you manage it based
on being mindful of whether you're emotionally stable or not so you
don't have to walk away from what you believe or what is important to you or or
um uh advocating for what's
right but acting out of anger is almost always negative
does that answer your question yeah yeah i will also say that in on the
final morning that I was in Bhutan I had a very long conversation with the hotel owner who was bemoning the fact that it
was very difficult to find trained personnel to work in his hotel they have a school where they train people and
people get trained and then they go off to Australia or Canada where they can
make more money and live a different life so they have a very hard time
retaining their young people so we were talking about that circumstance and he said some of the people
here believe so much in work life balance that they only want to work four-hour shifts and he says,"I need
people that are going to work eight hour shifts." And he'll say to them "I need
you to work an eight hour shift." And they'll say "Well I'll I'll just go live at my uncle's place for a while he'll
take care of me because he
will." So wise effort is also
required so the gross national happiness has
its overextension problem in Bhutan
yes behind you
um thank you for sharing your story i loved it like I'm I've done a lot of solo traveling
myself um and experienced the anticip anticipatory like fear and everything
that sounds like you had also i'm sorry am I having a little trouble hearing you oh oh sorry um I'm a fellow traveler
myself a solo traveler yeah uh-huh so I I relate to a lot of the things that you
said and I also have had five surgeries on my knee so okay i understand um
needing to ask for help to get up difficult hills and have people carry bags for me so yeah i wanted to ask um
two questions one um the woman that needed
to quiet her mind for 3 years mhm how does she know that the world is not
well if she's just up on a mountain meditating for seven years i don't Are
they reading the news there are they watching social media like
uh she's not unaware of the world she's not in silent meditation now she's at
she's at a nunnery so people are visiting her all the time the people who bring food they talk about the condition
of the world oh they they're they're not in silence
in these monasteries they they have to go to separate places where they they do
silent meditation i see so she's a she's aware that the
there are troubles in the world
um my other question is I wonder if the joy that you
experience is actually bigger than the joy that they
experience because yours is comparing to life in America
well you know my life my life in America is not terrible
um I think of kindness joy um
uh my my times of joy were not directly related to this person is
kind to me and now I'm feeling joy i just was experiencing
joy you know at at unrelated times I just noticed oh my goodness there's
this ecstatic joy that I'm experiencing at this moment and at one point one time
it was at a breakfast table one time it was coming out of a monastery you know just it was at various times
i I think that because I was traveling and out of my normal
circumstances and vulnerable that it was that it was more
accessible to me so in that sense traveling certainly impacted that freedom that I
was experiencing i think that's certainly true that makes sense i think that's one of
the joys of traveling if you allow yourself to
experience the raw experience without coloring it with the rest of your life
that's that's one of the great joys of life so I'm really really grateful that
I was able to take that trip yes
um you mentioned they want to come into the quote 21st century and that that was
a concern and an issue and building the city i'm wondering if anyone's thinking
about how much of this emphasis on kindness might be different if like what
coming into the 21st century means exactly and that I I see the possibility
that that kindness might um be shifted by that in ways so I just wonder if
anyone's thinking about that or Oh believe me they're thinking about that the because the the goal uh the
first afternoon we were there we met the CEO of uh
DHI which is Droldolding Industries which is the investment arm
of the Royal Family and they own the airline and they
they own the big companies of of Bhutan and they
outlined the strategy of of building this city in southern Bhutan which is uh G is uh the place
name of the city uh mindfulness city GMC and uh the idea is that it should be
something like uh Hong Kong or Singapore after 20 or 30 years and that it will be
independent of the rest of the country and then eventually they will merge the two i I see big problems with that but
what they want to do is protect their culture they really want to protect
their culture and they know that if they don't do anything they will be absorbed by
either India or China and they want to protect themselves from that as well so
they're doing what they can the the king was educated at Harvard and he is
um he's trying to mastermind this
by absorbed you mean they might take over the like take over yeah yeah like
just Yeah right now they per perform a diplomatic barrier
and do diplomatic work bhutan forms a diplomatic buffer between the two very
often although there was a report in the economist last week that Bhutan had
a disagreement with China over some portion of land and India stepped in and
Bhutan was really pissed that India stepped in because they don't want to be seen as a vassel of India blah blah blah
blah so yeah they have real concerns okay thank
you all of this is not Buddhist in nature but it's related to how do you
make how do you maintain a way of life and an attitude
of life in a world that is very
different uh and it's a very real concern thank you
so thank you for your attention may you know smiles may you
know kindness may you know joy may you be happy