hello everyone and Welcome to our meditation and um I want to
begin by the usual way of that I teach and because it's so usual that way
I it can be seen as um you know rudimentary or so basic or
beginners or simplistic but it's actually quite important and has very
profound possibility and that is to
relax and to be able to recognize the difference between when we
are tense and when we are relaxed is invaluable for finding our own way with
Dharma practice in a way all the way to Liberation because what it keeps us from
being liberated will in one way or the other
in one way or other we can understand is involving tension clinging grasping
Contracting and so to begin recognizing diff difference between uh tension and release of
tension and um penetrates deeply deeply into our hearts our minds our
body and um and so uh
so starting off with relaxing is uh very
significant now one of the reasons why relaxing is so important is that
tension um um pulls it's like it's almost like it
pulls something out of the hole it's like if there's a lake and it's all one
big nice Lake but then a piece of it begins to freeze up and now it's frozen
rigid and um and it's kind of pulled itself out of
the liquid state and might not even recognize or be so attuned to being uh
with its partners with the water so as we kind of get tense something about us
our attention or Focus or preoccupation something tends to become small or
narrower and we're coming away from the fluid state of being that we can be when
there's no tension no rigidity no tightness and
contraction and um so um
um so as we get ready to go deeper into samade over these next time period of
time this is very important because the zadi is a is a unification of all of who
we are bring all of us together to become like flu a fluid Clear Lake of
water that's the metaphor that Buddha gives and
um and uh so to relax and return and
feel how relaxing kind of begins to return us to something that's more whole
it kind of opens us and fills us to more of what's actually
happening so to assume a meditation
posture and maybe thinking of your
posture as the wide soft Basin of a lake
in which which holds all
the changing fluid flowing water of our
life and to establish and ground oneself in that
Basin so of feeling your posture
gently closing the
eyes and taking a few long slow deep
breaths gentle breaths not too big a breath that is tiring or
challenging just enough to be comforting and
pleasant a reminder of the wholeness the fullness
of who you are in your
body and as you exhale long longer than
usual let go relax soften the body
and letting your breathing return to normal and breathing in a normal way
scan through your body to see where there is tension
contraction tightness and see if you can be
untroubled by that it's okay and as you breathe in
feel the tension and as you exhale
invite the attention to relax welcome it to soften back into to
be part of the whole of the
body no longer
Frozen welcome back into the into the Lake of the body
and as you relax whenever you have the opportunity to
relax don't let relaxing be the a simple task to
do relax soften release take your time to feel
the goodness of relaxing What flows the pleasure of
it feel how it might be how it feels better to relax the
muscles than it is to keep them tense
where the gentle rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out is a gentle massage
for the Holdings in the body it can be quite subtle maybe in the
fingers the
wrist the elbows can be a little bit tight held
the
shoulders the
belly the area around your diaphragm
center of the chest
and then up into the face sometimes the tension associated
with thinking manifests in the area around the eyes the
forehead sometimes the
jaw sometimes in the throat or the back of the neck
sometimes thinking is a sense of pressure
contraction deep in the
head be untroubled by this
and also as you
exhale
relax maybe letting there be a calming in the
Body Sensations connected to
thinking
for for
and then centering yourself on the on
breathing and even in the middle of breathing in the
body is there little [Music] room to relax and soften
maybe at the end of the exhale so the exhale extends a little
bit baby near the top of the
inhale relaxing that allows the body to
receive the
inhale
e
for
for e
from time to time in a relaxed
way notice if there's any tension in your body mind
heart and if it's easy enough relax the
tension don't make it a big
project and if it's difficult to relax the tension
then relax your attitude around it
soften around
it and notice the what is Pleasant or good
or wholesome in the relaxing the
softening
for
e
e e
as you're sitting here meditating where in the field of your
attention do you feel an absence of
tension an absence of contraction tightness
maybe an absence of
clinging breathe into that breathe with
it relax
into where there is no clinging there is no tension
right
for
for e
and as we come to the end of this sitting take a few moments to feel or
sense in whatever way and wherever you might be
calmer less tense more
relaxed from having done this
meditation and sometimes the more calm or relaxed we become
the more it highlights where we are still tense and if that's the
case don't be troubled by that
appreciate how valuable it is to hold our
life in the in our attention in awareness
maybe a calm awareness relaxed
awareness sometimes when there's both tension and relaxation at the same time in our
body it can be an inspiring contrast
Inspire what's possible and Inspire what practice needs
to still be
done and may it be that our ability to stay relaxed
with our tensions decreased that it allows us to be more
present for others in our
life people we know people we don't know gives us a chance to take our
time to see more deeply listen more carefully
and may it be that this practice that we do increases our
capacity to be present for others with kindness and Care Good
Will may it be that even in a silent way
way that we're with others wishing them well a well wishing
presence may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you
e e
so hello and welcome to this uh Wednesday morning talk third Talk of the
week and the eighth Talk of the series on samade which will go on for some some
time and in laying down the foundations for somebody and effective
samadi um what needs to be in place first um I'm emphasizing how
we um divide ourselves limit ourselves lose
the sense of our wholeness the fullness of all of our capacities
sometimes if we really want something um that uh our eyes something we want we
might be focusing only on what we can see if uh if we want some particular
object we don't see anything else we just kind of focusing on what is that thing that we want and so the full
capacity of hearing and smelling and sensing and taking in the wider world is
limited by the strength of Desire now of course there's nothing inherently wrong
with that from time to time it's helpful and important to do that to have be kind of focused
and but we get stuck that way and people get stuck for a
lifetime sometimes uh uh strong desires strong aversion strong
fears strong pulling that way closing up closing our hearts um leaving uh
avoiding what's really difficult in US difficult unresolved emotions staying in our head
and our thoughts staying focused on others rather than ourselves or staying
so focused on ourselves that we're not aware for others and this kind of partial attention being selecting a
piece of the whole to be caught in or to separate
from is uh is what gets in the way of a healthy
samade and healthy samadi is to is a state of being that's going to open up
to all of we who we are in a sense samadi is what knits together heals it
all so it could all be together in some kind of wider wider um whole of
attention and um the Buddha uses a lot for uh Sade metaphors symbol having to
do with water and sometimes flowing water sometimes very Still Water
sometimes um uh a um a very clear pool of water
especially Lakes pools of water and uh something about being in somat uh can
feel like different different forms of lakes lakes with a nice current in it
lakes that are very still lakes that are very clear and
um and uh and what all these legs have in common it there there's no mud
there's no um you know uh algae that covers it there is no um It's not
nothing is frozen there's no dams that are blocking anything it's just a natur
a water a natural Basin just being there and um and so it's possible to go
to down to the lake and pull out a bucket of water and walk around and tell people this is the lake this is my Lake
I'm having the lake but the bucket of water is just a bucket of water and now we've left the lake behind taking a
piece of the hole and so this this movement
towards uh dividing ourselves up being separated from the hole often comes
along with tension uh some kind of clinging some kind kind of tightening in our muscles
in our hearts in our minds some kind of closing down some kind of contraction
constriction uh sometime of craving and uh and this movement uh of
tightening that goes on one way or the other uh is something that we want to
become aware of and aware of the unnecessary cost that that comes with it
now temporary tightening doing something that needs to be done um that has to be
taken care of of course is fine it's when we get stuck in it that is the
problem and uh and so when we sit down to meditate that's the time where we try to
set up situations where it's safe enough simple enough and nothing needs to
happen much that it's okay for the tensions and the tightening that have built to relax and to
soften and to and and to learn from that it's profound to become aware of um of
tensions because uh one way or the other the um all that keeps us from being
fully liberated fully awakened is something which is being held tight
something which is contracted something which is tense and something which is closed or blocked off again in the body
in the heart in the mind and the progressive softening of of that relaxing of it sometimes they use the
word Letting Go releasing Liberation Liberation is very glorified and
powerful and impactful form of relaxing and um so to begin becoming
wise about the distinction between relaxing on one hand and tightening on
the other that teaches us so much and we can question is it necessary to stay
tight is this situation necessary is there another way of being so I've a little bit going through
the five hindrances these first few days and the the fifth hindrance is doubt or
uncertainty and we can have doubt about many different things and uh to think
that the word this word for doubt here in the hindrance is for any kind of doubt we might have um actually can
limit us from the full potential of becoming free so for example if I need gasoline
for my car and I see that up ahead and opposite side of the streets are two gas
stations that I've been to both of them before and but I'm uncertain which one do I go to wow look they have both the
same gas price today but one of them has clean bathrooms but the other one has
good coffee one of them but one of them has uh very clean keep their machine and
their nozzles really clean so I feel comfortable grabbing it with my hand but
the other one has it kind of dirty but the dirty one uh the clean one I have to
make it a little bit dangerous U-turn to go to and the other one I can just pull into quite easily but there's a lot of
people and a little line of cars in the one where that's easy to get to but the
other one after all this a little bit dangerous to go to so what do I do and so I'm kind of stuck and so I just stand
in the intersection light turns green it turns red green again I'm just sitting there my car kind of what do I do I'm
uncertain I'm I have doubts I'm filled with doubts that's not that kind of doubt
we're talking about in the Dharma in the same situation there's no doubt about where
to bring my attention the attention should go in how I've now gotten tense how I've gotten
contracted and uh and Frozen in some kind of way and to that is where things
are UNH wholesome that's where things life is becoming deadening and to soften that
relax maybe it doesn't maybe it's not so important maybe the decision of where to
go to gas gasoline maybe what I should do if I'm relaxed and open and and don't
allow myself to tense up around this maybe I see when the light turns green
that I go and I if I need to kind of wonder what to do let me just pull over
uh in a parking spot and uh I have better things to do after all I had a nice meditation this
morning and still I'm feeling the the the the the Resonance of that still in
my body and now I'm getting tense around this gas station question um I'm better
off coming back into the calm of my meditation let me go to the park over there I have a lot of time today let me
just sit there for a five 5 minutes let me sit and just forget about the whole dilemma of G gas stations and let me
kind of I'm better off staying close to my relaxed State I have no doubt I have no
uncertainty that this more relaxed open available state is a healthier place to
be I still don't know which gas station to go to but now at least it doesn't
matter that much anymore because what matters is that I've returned to some kind of healthy way of being
and um so when we're talking about the hindrances of Doubt uh it's not
necessarily we can have thoughts about a lot of lot of different things but we have no doubt that it's
useful to stay relaxed not get Frozen and caught and what we want to do as we
prepare to go into samade we want to prepare we want to get ready by becoming
conosur experts on recognizing all the ways in which we
unnecessarily get tense unnecessarily tighten and how we can do one of two
things either relax the tension in the body heart and mind or if we can't
easily relax it open up around it soften around it recognize it's happening where
the recognition is very different than being swept into the tension and the
concerns and the preoccupation and this beginning to kind of uh open up and relax and soften
around tension and learning to see that distinction between all the variety of
tension which is every part of the kind of the suffering we're trying to overcome in Buddhism is always suffer
suffering that has some kind of tension in it some kind of stress in
it and uh we want to really be able to see that and do that and as we begin
seeing it we'll slowly begin to learn how to open up more widely and maybe not so wide before we
start doing some the SM part of this course but then we're prepared to
receive the opening to allow the opening into the whole lake of our being that
somebody is we're not blocking it we understand the Dynamics we understand where how we're holding ourselves back
and we can maybe then allow it to soften and open up so so for the
next 24 hours the next week the next month the next
lifetime um uh make it the best study you can of
your your own experience of tension and relaxation and make it a real study you
can Journal about it you can talk go for a walks with friends and talk about the experience and what you're learning uh
really kind of try to sensitize yourself by so that this is something you're really focusing on and as I said
yesterday you might want to put a timer um on um on uh some kind of you know
clock and maybe in some kind of reasonable interval every 30 minutes
maybe or something it could be sooner it could be longer uh where you're the an
alarm goes off to remind you to check in where are my tents have I what's what
tension am I holding here so that really keep it on the Forefront as exercise for
the next while uh it'll be invaluable when we eventually get to
somebody so thank you very very much and um and as usual I'm very much looking
forward to continue in the morning tomorrow morning