good evening good evening welcome Happy President's
Day I admit I kind of forgot it was President's
Day until just uh as I was uh driving here there was a sign like oh right I
don't have a regular 9-to-5 job so uh sometimes forget that some of these Mondays are holidays so whatever you did
today I hope it was delightful and nice I know when I was a kid um this
was ski week right with the president's holiday we would uh go skiing or something like that go enjoy the
winter so we'll see if there's something that uh arises in my mind to tie what in
President's Day what I'm going to talk about there might be nothing but there might be something we'll
see but I want want to talk a little bit uh starting with this story that's in
the suit does and the story is of this woman her name is danan
johnni and she stumbles and she like trips and then as she recovers her
balance uh she says like the homage to the
Buddha so in my mind she see she some like oh my God or Jesus you know it's
something like this right except that she says NASA
a some of you will recognize that that's a part of a chant that we do even now
today but here's something that was uh you know thousands of years ago kind of gets recorded as the way that she like
this thing that she says when she uh trips so the veracity of that story is a
little bit questionable because I don't think somebody would say something quite that long nevertheless the story is she
says this and then somebody nearby a man named sarva who was a
priest of the dominant religious tradition of that time brahmanism says like is quite offended
that she would say something like that and he says to
her um I can't believe you know that you just paid homage to that bald pained
recluse so he's uh insulting the Buddha but even though right the Buddha has
hair but that I guess in the in this story he's bald and that that this is a
common insult that other people talk about the Buddha they say he's a he's a
shaving you know because he shaves his head or something like like this and then she says well you don't
know the wisdom of the Buddha and if you did you would not be insulting
him and I I give him credit he says okay well the next time he's in town let me
know and I'm going to go hear about this Buddha person and see what he has to say
because this is how it was right back then right you had to hear the teachings there weren't books or or you know there
wasn't certainly a meditation centers or Retreat centers or anything like that right so you had to hear from the
teacher themselves or one of their students so as The Story Goes and the
Buddha eventually Finds Its way to that part of uh where they were living and he
goes to talk to him SAR this guy goes to talk to the
Buddha and he says
asks about him that says there are spiritual teachers this is paraphrase
There Are Spiritual teachers who teach others after finding a final and
ultimate insight and where is Master Goa so he's
not even calling him venerable sir or uh the blessed one or anything like this
he's using his given name Master Goa where does Master Goa stand among them
so Sara is asking okay there's all kinds of spiritual teachers like where who are you amongst
all these do you are you a follower of this person do you do something else like who are you what's your
story and uh the Buddha replies well actually there's a difference among spiritual
teachers based on how they uh what wisdom they teach about
there's three different like bases or foundations that uh PE teachers can use
for Authority for their teachings and he says one is what he's calls like the
traditionalist and these are teachers that are relying on uh like the tradition what other
people behind them have discovered or taught and this was the truth for
brahmanism at this time so sarva he's a PRI and he follows this tradition that
is that they had this uh that tradition I just use this word
believed that everything that needed to be known to live a good life to have a
good life and a good whatever happens after death is already
known and it was revealed to other people a long time ago and it's been
preserved in the tradition so you just have to know the tradition you just have
to study what other people have know you have to memorize it and really know that
a lot a lot of memorization so that's one way that
spiritual teachers come to be is because um they are just memorizing what people before them have uh been how what's been
passed down through the tradition excuse
me and then um they believe that just you know the sacred text were the most
authoritative or whatever it says in the text that's all you need and then
there's a second group the Buddha is describing that uh actually they think
that the spiritual texts have some value but needs some logic and some reasoning
and some philosophy to be added on to them maybe some way to um work with them
uh like well okay if it says this in the sacred text then it must also so mean that so there's a little maybe some more
interpretation that they add on to the sacred text and he called these the
reasoners or the philosophers or the logicians people that are you know
taking it one step further and then the Buddha says there's a third type of teacher who teaches based on their
direct experience from what they've actually known for themselves
this um this idea that you need to have this like a personal and
direct uh experience of reality or acquaintance of reality of the way
things are by things that they really are and this is often the contemplatives
or those who have meditative practices are the ones that can touch into seeing
things more clearly was this idea then the Buddha says I'm one of these one of
these third ones these experientialist these ones who have come
to know things through my own experience through discovering them through and
then he goes on to give sarava this uh his biography where he talks about where
the Buddha is talking about where he did all these uh meditative practices he did all of these aesthetic practices and
realized that neither of those were the way to complete Awakening but instead it
was um some meditative state of calm and ease and
stability and Stillness that allowed the Buddha to see things clearly and that
allowed for his Awakening so there's this way in which
the Buddha he's telling sarava that uh well he's teacher that he's based on his
direct experience and in fact we can see in the very first teaching that the Buddha gives this is the one that's a
the tradition holds is the very first teaching in it he says in regard to
things unheard before so saying like you know I didn't hear this from anybody else this isn't something that I just
learned there arose in me Vision knowledge wisdom higher knowledge and
illumination so he's talking about like this wisdom arises and this knowledge
and higher knowledge we could debate what does higher knowledge mean exactly but what I
want to point to here is this idea of direct experience there's a way in which
we know things differently when we've actually experienced
them we know what it's like through our experiences is so different than if we
just hear about it or read about it or may maybe hear somebody else talk
about it or listen to a podcast people talking about
it this is a silly example but uh not too long ago um I was going outside in a
place in the temperature was cold and I looked at the you know thermometer or
look to see okay what is the temperature like oh okay that's not so bad I'll be fine with what I'm
wearing and then I go outside and I'm like okay it's fine it's fine no it's
not fine it's really cold so then there's this like oh yeah
there's something when 38 Dees like I read that like okay that's kind of colder than what we normally think but
it's not until you actually experience 38° for some people who might be
listening to this who think 38 de is nothing I'll just say you know we're here in the Bay Area where 38 degrees is
a cooler temperature that uh it wasn't until you experienced it like oh this is very
different than just reading about a number and imagining it and thinking it's cooler and just to have this
experience I don't know if that's a good example I mean the typical example that I'm often giving is something about
maybe you have this experience too is we all understand that people are
going to die pets are going to die we all know this intellectually we know
this but I'll say for myself it wasn't until my father died that I realized oh
yeah this thing about death is different when it touches you personally it's
different than just an understanding and so the Buddha he he's
pointing to this this different way of knowing things just through experience
or maybe we might even say some insights this um Vision knowledge wisdom higher
knowledge and illumination and I appreciate in this list is both we have this vision and
illumination and even in um contemporary times we might say things like oh I see
like there's something about like seeing and then there's something about
knowing and like these are related but maybe they aren't exactly the same and
we see this uh in the Buddha's teaching sprinkled throughout about all kinds of things is this expression
y that means like knowledge and vision of things as they are so knowledge and vision like putting
together knowledge and vision like to see things
and to know things and these things are as how they
really are and I'll talk about this in a moment I'll unpack that a little
bit but I also wanted to say that um the Buddha he also when he was um describing
to sarava as part of his biography about like how did he come to have these
experiences that uh supported him and having becoming an awakened becoming
liberated and then in part of this biography that gets repeated in a few places and the suit does he says this
Dharma that I have attained so Dharma we could say is teaching or the way things
are are different ways that we can translate that Doctrine
but it's not Doctrine here because it's something that he has attained it's not something that he's heard
this Dharma that I have attained is profound hard to see and hard to
understand it's peaceful and Sublime but unattainable by mere
reasoning it's subtle and to be experienced by the
wise so he's pointing to also like it's not just reasoning it's not just
thinking about things but is experien Ed by the wise so the wise are being those
who maybe are following his teachings or
who yeah how do we Define the wise it's we kind of get into this uh loop here
um the word is pandita for wise here
um one who has wisdom is experiences this Dharma so maybe we
could say it's the wisdom that has put aside what is extra what is not needed
that enables them to see this deeply so the Buddha when he's talking
to sarava he says well there's these three types of teachers who come to
teaching through three different routes and I'd like to offer that we
actually need all three of these types of teachings or these three ways of
coming to understand things both um teachings from others who
have gone before us some reasoning some logic maybe some philosophy if you have
an inclination that way as well as some direct experience this is a way in which we can
make the teachings our own and in which we can find The Liberation experience
the freedom and the peace that's uh being pointed
to because maybe when we first start this practice certainly this was the case for me I heard a
talk by accident I was at a in a yoga class and
uh somebody came in and started to uh talk about the Dharma which was
completely unexpected for me and I certainly would not have gone to that yoga class if I had known that was what
was going to happen but uh this person started speaking and uh something in my
heart I don't know I don't know what it was it uh I found myself kind of like
with tears in my eyes kind like oh my goodness this it just resonated with me so
deeply and here I am all these years later having dedicated my life to this
now but there's a way in which we might read a book hear a talk these days
listen to an app Listen to a podcast and then we might say oh okay
yeah this makes sense I can see this maybe there's something that
resonates for us and maybe there's something that um feels like okay yeah I
can um I can feel that there's some truth truth here and it's not asking me
to get rid of all of my uh logic or uh independent
thinking maybe maybe for example we hear this teaching that uh clinging or um
grasping leads to suffering and then the teaching says well if you want less suffering do
less clinging we could just see oh there's some clear logic here it's not asking us
to just believe something so we could say I heard this expression number of years ago and I
really liked it that just like hearing these teachings in the beginning before we perhaps we have a meditation practice
or perhaps before we've like really tried to bring them into our lives we could call them as like borrowed wisdom
like you know we've heard from others they seem to make sense but then for us to find this own
wisdom this uh own knowledge and true knowledge or direct knowledge for
ourselves we bring them into practice we um engage with them maybe
like roll up our sleeves in a particular way and so maybe there's a aan Amaro who
is a uh he's a well-respected monastic uh in this
tradition he used to be here in Northern California and uh he now is in England
he's uh heads up a monastery and he said that the teachings
need to be fully internalized fully actualized made real brought to life
through our practice during the course of the day
here in this moment and I appreciate this this way of internalized actualized and made real
by experiencing them discovering them for
ourselves and so we might say well how do we do this wh what is
this I'm going to have a drink of water here
there's a way in which we can maybe use some of this borrowed wisdom wisdom some
of the teachings as a way to help support this exploration this exploration in our
lives exploration in our practice and there's there's a number of
ways in which we can do this and I'm just offering one can be really powerful
and transformative well ideally I I could
say all of them can be powerful and transformative but I'll offer these and
these are some of the this teaching of anicha Dua and
anata some of you will recognize these as the three characteristics that is
that uh there's change and uncertainty in
eacha that things are like unsatisfactory that there's this little
sense of like things aren't quite right they could be a little bit better
daa and then this sense that there isn't a constant stable
controllable self that's inside here
somehow and that's a anata an Dua
an I'm using a lot of poly words uh today for some reason I apologize if
that's no need to remember any of these uh some people like it some people
really dislike it that's perfectly fine I think I started teaching poly recently again so that's maybe why it's uh more
in my head so these are ways in which we can use to
explore our experience so just exploring this idea of inconstancy and
impermanence is what we're exper experiencing whatever it
is is it completely static never
changing or are there some fluctuations are there sometimes it's
there sometimes it's not there or is there some
gradations or flickering or same intensity maybe a
different intensity just whatever experience you're having completely mundane washing
the dishes is it the same time exactly the same as the last time you wash
dishes is the experience itself just one thing that's exactly the same getting
repeated and this seems so obvious like no the things are changing so the
intellectual mind understands that but there's a way in which if we really like bring this question and
explore driving to work is it exactly the same we might be going the same
route leaving at the same time but it's not exactly the same is
it so using this exploration of what a inconstancy the changing
nature and then the second is to this idea of well is this completely satis
saory is this a lasting source of happiness because if this is
satisfactory will it always bring me happiness will I always be happy now
that I have found this this whatever it might be and when we initially we'll say but I
have lots of beautiful wonderful experiences in my life hopefully you do hopefully
everybody's life has these uh experiences but then if we start to look at them
there's often just this really quiet oh I hope this
last oh what did I do so that I can get here again so I can have this other
experience so I can have it again or there's this little thing like oh I
don't want this to end okay how can I prolong this there's this quiet little
niggling that's happening during even the most fantastic experience es that
we're having and so it's pointing to even the things that are wonderful there's this
tiny sense of this afraid of loss or wanting a little bit
more I'm not saying that's the dominant experience I'm saying that we don't
discover things that are completely 100% uh stressfree
forever if you found it you would not be here on a Monday night
right so they might be sources of happiness and pleasure and all that kind of stuff but they're not like lasting
sources of happiness and so this is another way that we can explore not not uh to make
it be a downer because actually what I have found is that um if I'm having a
tremendous experience something that's just fantastic hiking and seeing like these
views that are just so uplifting and it was hiking not too long ago and
went to a place I hadn't been before and there's these views I just thought wow it was just amazing it was just I don't
know a little bit breathtaking and then I and then I start
to notice like why didn't I come here before how come of all these years I've never been here before and I'm going to
have to come back here later and I need to show somebody else this and like there's all this kind of stuff that uh
shows up but what I noticed is that when I recognized oh yeah there's that little
bit of I'm going to call it Dua Dua is this really can it's this one word that
has this huge range of ex uh meaning and one can just be that tiny niggling
little yeah something not quite right but when I acknowledged oh yeah there's
that little uh tiny voice that sometimes shows up that says oh why didn't I or it
should be something like this then I could let go of this why didn't I know
this earlier I better show somebody else and letting go of that just made it more
beautiful like oh yeah there's this experience here won't always be here at this
particular I mean that the view will be there but this experience will be
changing I will be different the weather will be different the light will be different some of those trees will grow
and you know whatever it might be so acknowledging that little bit of
Dua allowed a certain of Letting Go which made even the beauty be a little bit more poignant and maybe even a
little bit more beautiful appreciation gratitude
arising so that's a second way in which we can explore our experience have some of these direct experiences of this
unsatisfactory not the source lasting sources of happiness and then the third way in
which we can explore our experience is this idea
of just exploring what is it that feels like there's a
me that's having these experiences maybe out there in some kind of way or maybe
there isn't a location maybe there's just a sense of a just all these experiences that are happening to this
core here this Essence here what what gives me that idea what
what makes me feel like that we all do it's a natural thing to have that
experience or to have that belief or to have that uh
interpretation but what is it that makes it feel like there's this constant or
there's a me somehow this humulus maybe that's a inside to bring some curiosity
to this because if there's a me then there's often there's this sense of mine
and not mine what belongs to this me and what
doesn't certainly there are plenty of
um things that we don't think are
ours or we don't think that we think they're ours if you were right now wherever
you're sitting if somebody were to come in late and to say can you move that's
actually my chair I'm sitting there that's mine I I sat in it uh two
weeks ago I was in that location and uh and I'm pretty sure that's the exact same chair
or that seems silly right but there's a way in which we often like okay while
you're sitting there you feel like okay this is my chair but then you know as soon as you go away it's uh not it's
just a chair again there's a way in which we have these subtle ways of thinking this is mine if I asked you
guys to stand up and stretch or something and then to sit back down chances are you would sit back down in
the same chair because you have a feeling like oh this is mine or not not
mind in terms of you own it but somehow it has a relationship with you at this
time maybe that's not a very good uh example but there's this way in
which the sense of ey or the sense of me is getting created by these thoughts
that we have these just mental events that they themselves don't have any
substance but is this way that we feel like
um I'm this way well I'm a person who is likes to do things in a
XYZ I like to uh think about things
analytically I like to or I just like to think about I like to figure things out
so they have this way in which um they've identified that they're an
analytical person but are you an analytical person
when you're dreaming when you're asleep and dreaming are you an analytical person when you um knock on wood after
you say something that uh you don't little superstitious thing and you feel like you have to knock on wood or uh
whatever it might be right there's we have times when we're not that way even
though we might think that we are all the time so we might have the sense oh
I'm the one that's like this but actually it's just that that's
a pattern that arises and that's a pattern of thought a pattern of uh um
behaviors but it's not inherently who you are it's something that happens
frequently and that you're identified with there's nothing wrong with having those identific ations but it turns
out that we need thoughts to support these
identifications we need plans we need programs we need um to do lists and uh
ways that we spend our time to support
this so there's this way that as the mind starts to quiet down with
the meditation practice as well as when we're just in daily life outside of
meditation we can just have this exploration like what what's what is
this sense of me what is it and there's this way there can be
kind of like a like what what what's spe there or kind of this like turning around and looking at what's
looking what's doing the thinking what is feeling these feelings what is
thinking these thoughts so this idea of having our own
direct experience and then we can borrow some of the wisdom that the Buddha has
offered to help us like explore our experience so that we can have our own
insights our own understandings and then we don't
have to rely on what the Buddha is saying we don't have to have this borrowed wisdom instead we can have our
own so these teachings uh anich Dua anata these teachings of uh inconstancy
changing impermanence of unsatisfactoriness and not a stable
inherent core to the self or to anything it turns out that just
doesn't exist we can use these teachings as ways
to investigate our experience and you might even say that's
what Insight is is when we start to have our own
understanding of them where the Insight Meditation Center we might say Insight is to have your own direct experience of
of these in a way that leads to less suffering in a way that leads to more
peace and ease and freedom there a way that we can Define
insight and and become our own teacher or maybe even become a Dharma teacher or
become a just have a our own
understanding maybe one last thing that I'll say here one of the the Beauties I
think of like exploring our experience through these lenses through these Frameworks through this borrowed wisdom
of impermanence not satisfactory no inherent substantial
core is that it doesn't require that we have any particular experience it's not
like meditation has to be always Pleasant in order for it to be impactful
it's not like that we have to have things going our way or the way that we prefer things like being our life or
meditation practice or anything we can bring these queries to
whatever is happening whatever is happening and then we kind of like fall
the tyranny of wanting to have a good meditation session kind of starts to fall away and you realize whatever is
happening in your meditation practice if the mind is all over the place or if there's a lot of calm and
Stillness whatever is happening we can just bring this this uh exploration to
all of our experiences so then to close out the
story Sara having heard this from the Buddha feels quite touched by this and
decides to become a follower of the Buddha so maybe there was something in that the Buddha said uh because he was a
priest in this uh in the dominant religion of the time and he became a follower of the Buddha so maybe there
was something that recognized some of these teachings and sadly this little vignette
with danan johnni this is all we know about her is that she just trips and falls and says namot
tasa so thank you for your attention and uh if you like I will have some
questions and
answers this idea of direct experience for me I'll say this is really meaningful
that we don't just have to adopt
beliefs but you know just like to investigate and explore for
ourselves can anybody tie this in with President stay
yeah I think uh that's one of the things I like best
about the practice is that it's not dogmatic I'm very rebellious in many
ways if somebody tells me to do something not alwayss but um so yeah I
love uh so far I've loved exploring what how these things come up
in my daily life and what it means and one the impermanence one I really like
lately uh early in the morning I sit with my coffee stare out the window and
watch the light change so I can see impermanence in the world and I also see
okay this is how I am when I wake up what's my state of whatever being and
then I see how it can shift and change in that time while I'm staring out the
window nice nice thank you
Elena okay okay thank you thank you all
and if you like you're welcome to come up and talk to me in person but otherwise I wish you a happy rest of the
President's Day today thank you