hello on this Monday beginning of our week together
and welcome all of you and for me it's very nice to be back after having been
at um our Retreat Retreat Center in Santa Cruz teaching a week-long
retreat so
um the last week I was teaching on this samadi
series The I talked about samadi is involves
Simplicity and a subtleness a
steadiness a spaciousness and a
sweetness and these this is definitely true but all those qualities can lend
itself to an a suggestion idea that somebody should be like kind of
making oneself really cozy like reading a really nice book or
something and well there's something something true about that uh the rolling kind of curling up
to read a good book on the couch uh it becomes mostly kind of a
mental effort the body has gotten cozy but the body is not engaged
included in the effort so with
samadi the body is definitely included as part of the picture samadi is
inclusion samadi is um unification somebody is uh integration somebody is
gathering together all of who we are including all of us and part of it is
our body our posture and um we can see in sports and crafts and
different situations in life where we really kind of get into a
posture that we're ready we're prepared we're ready for what comes next
we're um engaged with the whole body attentive with the whole body so I can
imagine for some of you if you had the occasion uh to drive
um the Dal lamba around a very busy City on the freeway and
we're a lot of traffic that uh if you knew that was going to be the case when you sat down
at the steering wheel you might sit up straight you might have
both hands on the wheel you might really be fully there for this important
activity you wouldn't be casual and just kind of have one arm you know draping
out on the window and one hand kind of casually maybe with two fingers holding the steering wheel and kind of kind of
slumping back and low writing kind of you would bring all of yourself to be
there for that event out of respect and care for this wonderful guest that you're caring for
so the balance here is to how to be settled and simple
and and but also come along with your body be inclusive of your
body and for some people that's uh sitting in a
posture that manifests or expresses
attentiveness a Readiness
availability I remember when I was uh parent of young
children the children might stand on the edge of something like the trampoline which is you know I don't know it's
maybe four feet high and there was pretty small and they wanted to jump into my arms and I'd say wait a minute
and I would get my whole self ready this was important I didn't want to not catch them drop them on the
ground so I would take a stance I wasn't they weren't heavy it wasn't going to be a
big thing to catch them but I wanted to get ready and be available really be
there relaxed but fully there with my whole body ready to catch
them so to assume now a meditation posture a posture that maybe for you ex
Expresses in whatever way your body allows you to do this
expresses um
attentiveness expresses a Readiness an
openness to be here to catch to be available with all of who you are to
this moment for some people that's adjusting
this spine a little bit even if you're laying down you can
maybe sometimes wiggle or move a little bit
so maybe so the middle of the spine by the between the shoulder blades can be
little bit more flattened or shoulder blades come
down chest little bit more open
that the hands are in a position that is not too casual it's
intentional hands that show that you're here and ready and
available the hands are not forgotten
incidental and with the whole body being the arena for
samadi to gently close your eyes so you can better feel your
body and to take some time intentionally letting your attention roam around your
body almost like awareness is like a soft kind hand that
gently touches the different spots of the body
and and conveys the message yes you too are included
here you too were going to knit together into a
[Music] whole body participating in meditation
and then within this body just as you are not changing
anything be aware of the body breathing but continue roaming the
attention round to different places in the body
where the movements and activity of breathing can be
experienced maybe the movements of the
belly and gently softening the belly
if that allows the movements to be Freer more
open the movements and sensations of the chest and diaphragm
perhaps there's if it's not too subtle you can feel the
movement of the back rib cage or the sides of the rib cage
and maybe you can feel the movements of your collar bones and shoulders as you
breathe and if you can't very gently just enough breathe more
deeply until you feel maybe the collone and shoulders moving
and maybe you can be aware of the sensations of breathing in and out through the
nose maybe a slight tingling changing temperature
and as you breathe in and out
almost as if writing the wave of breathing in and breathing
out become aware of the thinking mind
the activity agitation any tension or
pressure even it could be as simple as a location we're thinking or
visualizing occurs and with breathing being like a
massage for the Mind soften the thinking mind
mind and then on the next two or three
exhales relaxing and softening the whole
body especially any way in which you're bracing yourself against life in your
whole body
and then wherever you feel your breathing
begin feeling the place maybe deep inside first sensations of
breathing in maybe deep in the belly
area or the diaphragm maybe someplace in the
chest and as the inhale
grows let the whole body receive the
inhale Let the Body receive the
movements of the
inhale so that with the inhale
the whole body much of the body where it's
easy is filled or alive
or with Sensations the sense of
receiving into the body the movements of breathing of in
inhale
and then on the exhale a sense of the other direction
that the whole body settles relaxes
towards the settling point the end of the exale
a gentle expansion outwards through the
body and a gentle whole body body settling back
towards the settling point at the end of the exhale
maybe deep in the b in the belly
with the inhale receiving awareness
throughout the body with a
wave the movements of breathing in letting awareness
spread and be received through the
body and on the exhale allowing a settling
relaxing where the whole body somehow relaxes towards the
settling point
and then very gently with a voice that is a whisper
quieting the mind count the
exhales one to
10 so the count participates with a settling towards the
settling point and don't count the
inhales let the silence be spaced for the Body
Sensations to be received in space in the
body
for
for for
e
for
for for
gently give yourself over to counting 10 breaths 10 exhales
maybe each account being said in the mind is spreads over the
exhale
one
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting do again or continue to feel the
rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and maybe with breathing
in to
receive whatever sense you can feel the outer
World appearing Here and Now
sounds spatial awareness
your imagination of where you sit neighborhood
community the whole world arise as you breathe
in and as you exhale you let it all spread wide
outwards on the tip of your care and
love to receive on the inhale and spread Good Will kindness
meta out into this
world breathing in breathing out kindness
breathing in the world breathing
out
love breathing in and having space for all things in a relaxed
awareness breathing out compassion
and may whatever ability we learn to be
present steady concentrated in
meditation may it support the way that we can do so
for the people in our lives for this world that we
share May our meditation support the growing sense of kinship with all
beings in which we're
receptive to the whole world so that
we can transmit basic kindness to
everyone may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may we live to contribute to those four
[Music]
things for [Music]
hello and welcome to this ongoing series on samade and uh this week since this is
Monday this week I'll say that the theme will be um related to
the literal meaning of some body which is a gathering
together and sometimes some is called a process of unification unifying the
mind but not just the mind because anything the Mind knows and feels and
experiences is part of the mind um every you know our nervous
system neurons uh go throughout the body
and um and wherever the nerves are activated by whatever stimulates them is
part of the mind when we die we don't feel anything
any sensation we feel in the body is part of the overall mind that we live
within we live part of and the unification then one of the
key things about the unification of the mind that Sade is that's really helpful
is to be grounded in the body to include the
body so this unification means inclusion and inclusion of as much as we
can and the people who develop concentrations without including the
body some people live from the neck up and it's possible to get a kind of a
laser Focus really focused with the mind some people who spend the day doing uh
intense maybe concentrated work on the computer on the
screen can be very focused and uh people can say wow that person's concentrated
and so much so that maybe they don't hear other people in the room or someone coming in you're so involved but it's
all from the neck up it's all a mental um mind kind of brain activity that's
being and if we use that for developing the Sade of
meditation uh meditation tends to become kind of lopsided and occasionally it
actually develops a u uh kind of uh
unhealthy States uh within sometimes tension builds up in the rest of the
body that's not useful for somebody um and U but when the whole
body is included then there can be a more relaxation it's easier for the mind to
then to be balanced be settled to not be contracted or
narrow and so to include the body as part of um uh the practice of
samadi is invaluable and one of the reasons for this is that as we continue practicing
samadi and some point um different I just for the time being I'll call them
energies different uh uh Expressions
energies emotions feelings um uh that arise with somadi uh are much more
supportive and much more uh supportive of further samat supportive of us uh if
they're if the whole body is included in feeling them it's almost like some of the emot states that come with Z are
felt so much better and Fuller if the body is available to receive them or
transmit them or to include them so the body is a tremendous support
for the unification process if it's if somebody is unifying the mind then um
and the mind is the you know wherever the nerves are in the body we want to include the body the body that we can
feel feel and sense every sensation we feel
is uh an extension of the Mind the nervous system that we
have neurons and uh and to be willing to relax and open and
feel allows this growing movement towards inclusion this too everything's included
no there's no outside and um
and as the settling of somebody we might not be so hearing the external world we
might not be thinking about the external world but there's a growing feeling that
that the awareness is now inclusive it just Broad and everything's included
within it and um and the Paradox is seemingly that uh the more we settle on
some settling spot or gather some Gathering Spot that we have it could be
um the movements of the belly some as deep settling in the belly a spot where
the breath begins and ends it could be the movements of the chest could be Sensations in the nostril there's
different places that can be the Gathering Place where everything's
included and as the the the the Paradox is that as we get more settled in that
Gathering Place uh steady settled present at at the same time there's a
the Mind becomes wider bigger more expansive if the mind gets narrower and
tight and contracted um then um probably somebody will be a little bit
lopsided so for today what what I want what I want to emphasize is the inclusion of the body in a process of um
of that helps both settling and allows the unification it's almost like the more we're in the body more we have a
receptacle to receive whatever is happening in the world uh we we increase
our capacity to include all that's happening in our mind our hearts our
bodies here now and U not a few people will feel
that as their Sade develops there's a lot of calm that allows them to go into their
life and have kind of a calm spaciousness that allows there's a room for what happens in the world and what
people say to just come and be held and be there without
reactivity BEC partly because of this sense of expansiveness through the body
and beyond that can happen so again the Paradox is that there's a way of
relaxing into this settling spot the Gathering Spot and um and let that be
kind of like the the um Center the centering spot that allow that then begins to open
up and include and allows things to gather everything is included everything is here so one way to do this in
meditation with the breathing is um is to uh uh allow the
inhale be to be a time to feel the body more fully more
expensively and uh it's almost like the breath is a massage and and you have to
release your hands to uh to feel and make room for what's there so when the
massage your hands come down to neede to to uh to relax to uh as you you know
then the kneading happens there has to be this rhythm of releasing and and you
know kneading so the same way kind of the the breathing in this this uh making
space relaxing opening allowing things to open and feel the hole receive it
kind of a receiving of everything in the body as we breathe in and so that inhale
out receiving the inhale and then the coming together the
Gathering the settling the Contracting of the body as we exhale and to ride
that massage ride that wave of expansion and contraction some people have used
the image of a jellyfish for breathing you if jellyfish moves itself through the Water by opening and closing
expanding and Contracting this opening to everything and then Contracting coming
back and um and then to count and uh for the for
um to be sometimes the counting uh is such an invaluable thing to do so the
thinking mind has something to do rather than the thinking mind taking us away
from this inclusive kind of awareness it's the counting is using a thinking mind to stay present it could be
something different than counting it could be a label or word it could be the
word he that uh just maybe every exhale saying here is a reminder to really be
here and so rather than again the thinking mind just thinking about something unrelated and off you go but
the counting also there's a little extra oomph that has to be there to remember the count and um and kind of really Hold
Steady with the count and that engages the mind so more of the mind is involved
the part of the mind that has to remember uh to be present and remember that
remember the count also the same kind of mind that has to be remembered to stay present so we're kind of gently just
enough to remember the count so one on the exhale
two on the next exhale three and um and so it might seem like
I'm suggesting a lot of things to do but it's a unified ho of receiving the
inhale settling on the exhale as we settle the count
one and uh all for the purpose of Simplicity subtleness
steadiness spaciousness and sweetness
so don't be hooked into don't be tricked by all
these words and instructions that I'm giving that you make it complicated
keep it simple and uh and we'll continue so the
theme today this week will be inclusion that how we gather together unify as
part of samadi and the body is invaluable part of that and so for today
going through the day you might see if how you can be more inclusive in your
body how you can have a posture that supports readiness
engagement presence steadiness stability be careful kind of study your
posture see what you can do uprightness and uh and see what you can
do for um uh staying in this body feeling it as
you go through the world as you like the inhale receive it almost as if through the receiving the inhale you're more
there to receive the people you're talking to you're with so your body is
with you here and may be keeping you steady and calm in the middle of difficult
situations so thank you very much and uh I look forward to continuing tomorrow