so good morning everyone can you hear me all right loud enough speak up if it gets to soft my
voice or wave your
hands so
um there was a time when I was in conversations where the question was is
Buddhism religion or not and it made some sense to have those questions
because uh oddly enough for me who my background is um I have a PhD in
religion so and that that's the area where you know that question comes up
you know and I was there studying Buddhist study so was I in the right
place and um oddly for me because I did not grow up religious and uh and oddly
enough being you know maybe now you're all abandoned IMC but um I in some ways
I don't not so interested in religion in some ways maybe maybe it doesn't look like
that and um but uh uh so is Buddhism a religion
or not so there's all kinds of question debates about that and the the the
funnest way of referring to that kind of humorous way I think it may be is that
um uh definitely is United States because uh then you get all kinds of tax
benefits whereas I was told in the Soviet Union it was definitely not a religion because there were benefits
because they were back then kind of anti-religion so B Buddhism is quite flexible that
way and um but I think uh another what's
more interesting for me uh as I've navigated my own practice in Buddhism
and practiced in different schools of Buddhism and had different kind of
philosophies in a sense of what Buddhist practice is what the bud Buddhism
is is um is um Buddhism more an art form of
art or is is it more a form of medical
research is it more Medical Science and um and the reason for that
distinction is that there are forms of Buddhism where the emphasis
predominantly the rhetoric predominantly is about just being in the present
moment and allowing some deep expression to come out of us and some people when
people have this will often refer to some something like the Buddha nature something profound within us that gets
freed and can move through us and respond to the world and uh and it's
more like the response more like the expression of an artist like someone who's a
dancer who who dances just to dance to express something in the dancing and
they're allowing something from inside to come forth or a singer maybe just singing for the singing um not singing
in order to do something else um maybe some painters are that way
maybe some painters are not some painters are painting to have a perfect picture you know for the con for the
results but some people are painting just for the expression that's there and in uh in uh uh in kind of
close to Buddhism in Japan the representation of this sometimes is in Te
ceremony uh and and Associated Arts where it's really the the the the Beauty
and the art or the the what what gets born what arises in the care the love
the attention to detail the quieting of the mind and the heart to be really there for the activity itself that is
the purpose of it and it's more of more of an art than it is in order
to uh medical research or medical science um has a bias or maybe we call
it a preference um it's doing it for a purpose to have a
result when people are unhealthy the purpose is to find a way to help people become
healthy and um and uh there might be some deep upwelling of compassion that
Wells up from the Buddha nature of the researcher that inspires it but still uh
the research is all about looking for understanding something in order to
um bring Health to someone so is Buddhism more an art or is it more a
kind of uh personal Research into yourself to understand how you live
unhealthily may maybe if you prefer a spiritual way but uh you know uh I once
got criticized when I was a Zen priest for never using the word spiritual now I do it use it more often
and I don't know if that's better or worse but um but it it kind of touches something I think in the hearts to use
that word uh and so uh is it um you know
is it some kind of some spiritual Heth uh some people have uh become have an un
unhealthy relationship to spirituality because they've been betray maybe been betrayed by their
religion there are uh spiritual or ethical wounds that people carry because
of you know how they Liv their life or how people associated with them have live lived their life that they carry
for a long time so you know sometimes there's deep psychological healing
repair Corrections free uh that people are involved in and to Simply say just
kind of express your Buddha nature just sit here and just be um sometimes with
the School of Art uh often has the the the wonderful and challenging
instruction just be and that's a wonderful antidote to people who are
overd doers who are always straining and working and doing but um but you don't
tell a medical researcher just be it's okay just sit there and you're
you know in your office and just just just be and everything will
work out fine the researcher needs to be in the lab needs to engage there's something they have to
do and uh and sometimes the the just being school is a wonderful correction
for some people they finally relax and settle and then at some point when they really settle into the being then
they're ready to do in a beneficial way to to be you know to find the right
doing that moves along but sometimes the over emphasising of being I've seen the
emphasis then becomes um well it's completely okay just to be neurotic I just I'm so glad I found Buddhism
because now I can just go along and just keep thinking and fantasy think a lot oh just be okay that
for me that means just you know Daydream and think and plan and worry and that's
what I'm supposed to do because that's what being is for me and that's a little bit unfortunate it's kind of like saying
um you know that um if you have a scab just be with picking the
scab you know and just and then uh and you know everything will be great but
this scab just gets the wound just gets bigger and bigger the more you pick it so so there's something about um but
then the people who are the medical research side of Buddhism some of them just research all the time and some
people they never get around taking the medicine or they are just you know
there's never any real healing from Being Human you know it just comes with its
challenges it comes with its tensions it comes with difficulties and um you know
I mean the classic difficulties of Buddhism highlights is that a few people
will eventually experience sickness old age and
death and um and so uh that's a challenge and so how do we live with
that and find our way with it and so if we're constantly looking for the cure for those things uh then you never
really get to the heart of the matter which maybe has more to do with the metaphorical
heart and so both both directions can be problematic but also in both approaches
I've seen in Buddhism can be at odds with each other we're the better way you're the lousy way you know but I
think maybe they need each other other maybe they they really should go together and uh and that's really the
best of all possible World worlds I love that I didn't think about it before when I did it but the fact that I put my
hands together when I said that in this uh Angel you know that's kind of
symbolic of how I see these two coming together and uh maybe in a reverent way
or respectful way they both need each other in some way the school of terad and Buddhism
that we teach here at IMC is more on the medical
research uh Direction and The Core teaching of the TR of this tradition goes way back to
the Buddha is very simple so simple that this is where someone people would look
and say is this really religion really this can't be enough this can't be the
core and that is um to not cause harm a
radical life of non-harming and uh and the Buddha
defined a um a wise person is someone who doesn't harm themselves doesn't harm
others doesn't harm self or others doesn't harm the whole
world uh that's an unwise person a wise person is someone who does the opposite
a wise person is someone who benefits themselves brings about the welfare of
oneself is involved with the welfare of others involved in the welfare both self
and others and Welfare of the whole world is that
religious that's that's what is that um maybe it's maybe Buddhism is
form of therapy medical therapy psychological therapy maybe that's what it is it shouldn't be a religion because
that if that's the heart of it everything follows from that the core principle ethical principle in Buddhism
is don't cause harm and uh this is a beautiful way that this is expressed I believe for
me abandoning The Taking of life one abstains from taking
life this gives freedom from danger hostility and oppression to Limitless
numbers of living beings in giving others freedom from
danger hostility and oppression one gains a share of unlimited freedom from
danger hostility and oppression this is a great
gift so number of things that this is the first ethical principle all the
Buddhism in a sense follows from this one principle one ethical principle and um and uh uh don't cause
harm and we learn in meditation how not to cause harm to
ourselves and in some ways the four noble truths are often held up as the Buddhist primary
teaching and uh usually they have this very big complicated confusing word suffering
that it's worded but maybe if it's word the the first Noble Truth is a truth of
harm the second Noble truth is the truth of how harm harm appears how it
arises the second is that it's possible to stop harming and the third is this is the way
to to not harm faithful path and so we learn not to
harm uh we learn and meditation is a a phenomenal place to learn how not to
harm ourselves one of the things that I learned uh uh primarily I think through
vasna practice when I was first started doing it in Thailand was that
um if I wanted to harm others I was harming
myself and became so glaringly obvious as the mind got quieter and Stiller
as I started sensing and more feeling of being more embodied in my body sensing
what was going on in deeper quieter or more peaceful ways that uh if there was a thought of
causing you know being angry with someone or being lustful for someone or
being you know resentful to someone or all kinds of things that I could feel
that I was harming myself directly I hadn't been able to to feel that earlier in my life because my whole
sense of I was so activated with all my preoccupations concerns desires feelings
busy busy mind that I didn't I wasn't that sensitive but meditation taught this
deep sensitivity that sometimes I like to call ethical
sensitivity because you feel so deeply the impact of certain kind of ways of
being that if there's greed or hatred delusion it limits us it harms ourselves
to do that uh not to speak of if we do act it out and harm
others and also with this deep ethical sensitivity deep sensitivity we're much more attuned to
others we much more closely feel uh their
pain you know how they are it kind of harms ourselves kind of feel the pain in a certain kind of way when we harm other
people or we around people who have been harmed who suffer and to care for
that and um and so one of the things I discovered through this kind of deep
subtleness and meditation was that uh in a sense this place of just being that
from that was this deep sensitivity and from this deep sensitivity there came compassion
and uh and to my surprise that um that started to
become who I am more than any other way I ever had
thought of who I was as a human being before that that if someone had asked me
no I think nobody's ever really asked me this maybe but if if one of you asked me gil who are you I could sincerely say
maybe I don't want to say it because it sounds a little bit conceited or too much so so I'll kind of whisper
[Laughter] it I'm
compassion the compassionate response or if I want to kind of make it a little bit more simple I would say I'm the
appropriate response I'm the beneficial response and uh when I was at the Zen
Monastery I found myself spontan iously saying to my zen teacher when we passed
each other on the trail one day on the path one day and I said I'm becoming a
response machine and so you have to forgive the word machine because that doesn't sound
so human or something but it was just what came out that was just expressing how I be you know this change that had
come over me so that was just the language I used but I was becoming just a a response and that response is very
much sent thir in compassion but that response of
compassion uh care is
both something that just is it's a beingness it's the art it's the dance
it's the song that we sing of course but built into
it is is the medical researcher the medical
scientist built into it is well if there is harm here if there is hurt here if
there is suffering here let's understand it let's see how it can come to an end we don't just say
oh you're suffering just be
suffering just suffer better something you know that's kind of
what we don't say even though I do tell people that sometimes I'll explain why in a minute but um but
you know the idea is not just to continue perpetuating the suffering the idea is what what does it take to end it
what's the medicine what's the cure and there are things that Buddhism
teaches there are things that therapists can do there are things lots of people can help with and um and the Buddhism is
to really and the reason I chose Buddhism is in my youth
uh I knew nothing that went as deep into the human heart as Buddhism I knew
nothing that addressed the issues of being attached to self as Buddhism addresses that self attachment and I saw
that when I was young it kind of the deepest attachment we have so I wanted to be able to kind of come with that
medicine to the world or have that medicine for myself and um so we want to bring
suffering to the end so it do it's not just you know just be as you are be as
you are but there is a way that that being as we are has within it the
movement the desire to the end of suffering the end of harm causing it and experiencing it
and living with it and that's phenomenal is that
religion if it is that's my religion Dal Lama said my religion is
kindness so if he could say that I can say that my religion is the end of
harm the U and the reason sometimes I say you know to tell people you know you
you need to just suffer better it's kind of outrageous right but the reason is
sometimes we actually need to understand and feel and experience our suffering to really understand it to really be
motivated to bring it to an end and they usually I say this to people if they're struggling with something and they know
that it's not healthy for them and they're trying to find a way um when I get a sense that they're actually have
never stopped to look at it they're always kind of recoiling from it or trying to find a solution from it but
the solution is by going through it rather than avoiding it or finding a
cure and so if the idea is to go through it I say you need to suffer better you
have to really experience it fully then I usually explain what I mean I don't just it's it's kind of cruel just say
suffer better but uh Buddhist teachers have certain permission to say certain things one of
the thing one of the things I feel like I permission to say this is also done very with in context you know and
usually people are willing to go along with it when I say this sometimes it's kind of a wonderful job because some of
the things you can say in order to help people you know
that's that's that's the that's the that's the whole purpose right so it makes me glad that I can help people but
occasionally I told people you know you're conceited where do you get away with
that you know that's kind of insulting to some people but usually it's in
context I prepare people for it and and usually they appreciate it
because it's [Laughter] true and um so is Buddhism a religion or
not is it a art or is it a form of medical research
is it more like that and I kind of like to think of it as both an art and medical research and
the way I said that if we understand it as art if
you really do it well if you really become a dancer or singer well I think
it requires a deep deep sensitivity to oneself to one's emotionality to
one's expressivity a deep ability to let go of the inhibitions and the preoccupations
and the hindrances that get in the way of really being the art which hopefully
provides this deep sensitivity that what lives in US is compassion is care is the
desire for health is a desire for wholesomeness is a desire ire for our
goodness it's a desire for freedom and then it
becomes more the little bit more the medical research side of Buddhism okay
now let's let's work for that conversely or you know if you you
start with it being medical research and you do that really well then you start
finding the cure for your hindrances the five hindrances you start finding the cure for preoccupied mind and start
finding a cure from all kinds of things and you settle and relax and get
distressed and that reveals this place of deep inner
sensitivity that's the birthplace of you know this deep uh you know deep healthy wholesome
Source within us that we in our school we don't call Buddha nature um but
sometimes we can call it the literal word for it sometimes in our school which uh is is the
womb so that's kind of nice maybe uh that this that there's this profound place within us that's something
beautiful and wonderful can be born that can be expressed so we have these two areas two
two approaches and um and it's interesting I've been involved with different Buddhist
traditions and um and it seems like the rhetoric can be one or the other
but in practice they both kind of come together they both contain both within them these are not in practice are not
so separate from each other but it's kind of nice to know both and to and to
appreciate both so that um uh you don't become overly
complacent and you don't become overly striving and you find the middle way
between complacency and striving and so the over striving is the
medical approach the complacency can be the art approach but so they you have
either one they come together so that's my hope for how we
practice so um so it might be interesting
now for either the art approach or the medical research approach for you to
have a chance to say a few words words about where you fit in this
spectrum where do you fit how do you understand yourself if there if there is a spectrum between art and research
medical research where are you in this spectrum in your practice or your life
and your engagement or what struck you about this talk and um so you're welcome to sit
quietly and not participate in a conversation with someone you're welcome to leave if you're more comfortable with
that but the idea is to take about 10 minutes minutes for a conversation with um maybe a couple of people next to you
groups of three perhaps and um and uh and have a little conversation the idea is not for any one person to tell a long
story you know a 10-minute story to make your point no one has any chance but
actually the the art of this kind of conversing is to say just one and don't say all that you could say just make one
point make it well but somewhat succinct because the fascinating things about these conversations is not what you say
but what you hear so you have to give a chance for them others to hear
something but uh but you you want to you don't to speak too long because you want to be impacted by what you hear from
others and then you might learn more about yourself and you might find yourself when it's your turn again to uh
to say things you've never would have dreamt you would say new something new arises so um
so that's uh you know and then we'll come back to the whole group for a few minutes and maybe have a little more
discussion as a to group and then at at um 10:45 we'll um we'll um stop for the
potluck or the formal ending so if you don't mind if you're up
up for it to turn to someone near you and look around make sure no one some sometimes people one person's in the
middle and people turn away just because coincidentally just look around make sure everyone's
included well that felt like a lot of energy in here it felt like happy energy for the
most part I hope that was nice for you maybe given all the energy maybe we take 30 seconds to sit
quietly for
so in the silence I'll read two quotes from the
Buddha if Desiring
happiness you use violence on others Desiring
happiness then you won't find
happiness one who neither kills or makes others
kill who neither steals nor makes others steal is one who has love for all beings
so it's a religion of love a religion
of nonharming of
happiness or it's not a
religion it's about love and happiness and non-harming whatever that is it's good
so we have a couple of minutes before we we any last words any questions or
comments that you anyone wants to briefly make before we break for the
potluck
yes what's the poly word for womb oh it's uh
Yoni thank you and yeah Yi and it it doesn't literally mean
womb it just means Womb for humans it's uh it's the source for where
life comes from so like the egg is the Yoni for a chicken so there's you know
so so um so there are different different living beings come out of some
other various various things but uh for humans it's Yoni happens to be the womb
there's a wonderful story of but I've told this maybe too many times but the Buddha said something like if a
chicken sits on its eggs and properly and incubates them just like they're supposed to even if
the chicken does not want the eggs to hatch the eggs will
hatch and the same way if you live properly with the eighth fold path
even if you don't want to be enlightened you will become
enlightened so maybe like so so in that metaphor it's not a womb it's your eggs
sit on your eggs incubate you incubate let something gestate let something kind of be
nourished and
supported um uh thank you Gil um could you say a little bit about how you think
about or how you would recommend we think about so often times we're trying to not do harm but we feels that we're
embedded in a system that is either intent or designed to do harm so how do
you think about not doing harm when embedded in a system that feels like it wants to push us towards doing harm or
is built to do harm many years ago I was at a
uh kind of a panelist on a on a in a conference about uh Buddhism and ethics
and uh the panelists were all asked a question about um what's your biggest
ethical challenge as a Buddhist teacher and there was a Burmese monk who lived
in Bay area for a long time named Yanda until he died lovely
man and uh he was there and he said yes that my biggest ethical challenge is
that um um when the Burmese immigrants come to United States it's hard for them to
find work to take care of their family and some of them only can find work in the military
industrial uh industry and they come to me and ask me is this ethical or not
that I do this and I know it's unethical but I can't I don't I I can't I don't want to
I know how hard it is find work and take care of their family so I don't know what to say to them so I mean this is a
challenge many people have and so I just want to appreciate the challenge I don't know if I have a good
answer um and um but that's a kind of question that's really important to keep
and reflect and analyze and think about and certainly a small solution would be
can I make a difference can I make a difference within it many years ago there was a
I was teaching a class on Buddhism I think it was an academic class and uh
one of the students was a police officer and he said my department is kind of
corrupt and uh and I said well why don't you leave and he said uh no I feel like
I have to be there in order to try to make a difference make it better so that's one one answer and the other
answer that's one end of the extreme I guess the other end is to leave it
find another way to to have a life and then everything in
between I want to thank you for that question I appreciate very much that s
sensitivity you
have okay well thank you all very much so we have aplu which means means that
everyone's welcome to stay it uh really doesn't matter how much food there is or isn't um it just matters that we're here
together in a friendly way and uh have a chance to hang out and um so um we'll
serve the monk who's here aadama thank you for being here first as as the
custom and then um and then uh I hope you enjoy your company thank you