so hello and welcome to this meditation session that is part of the series on
samadei and the last two days I've emphasized that or taught how samadei
can be understood as a progressive process of calming the mind stilling the
mind in a way that leaves the mind not frozen or offline but leaves it kind of
luminously awake and clear and and uh kind of a kind of a very peaceful lucid
awareness that and then yesterday I talked about the the process of
um uh stilling the mind stilling the mind
not just calming it but um letting go of clinging a progressive process of
clinging less and less and less less contraction less tightness less holding
on until there's a feeling of of a kind of a phenomenal degree of freedom in the
mind because it's not disturbed by anything and it's not clenched or held
or resisting feels it it doesn't feel safe but it has
a because that's too active to have that feeling and idea but it's a situation of
predominant pre pervasive a kind of safety that is so safe the idea of
safety and danger disappears and then today I want to emphasize that uh
samadei going through the jas is a progressive Um stilling
quieting or releasing or
dropping the activities of the mind that involve
selfing that involves taking something using it to define who I am commentary
about oneself having concepts and ideas of uh who I am in some way that we're
living in those concepts and ideas even if they are subconscious and they're not
really even part of the conscious thinking mind uh we are stilling and quieting
even the the very subtle activity that of amness I am it's just a feeling I am
not I am anything in particular but we'll see as we go into this
that that uh the feeling of I amness that there's a locust there's a kind of
a place or something kind of a concentrated area of a a concentration
or a coagulation a contraction or a pressure point
inside that identified emnness that seems to be here no matter what
unconditioned by the by events of the world there's still the one who knows
the one who thinks the one who is and oddly enough because it's so
strange from how we normally live our lives uh this is an activity of the mind
that constructs that that makes that and that quiets down so all the
constructions all the thinking all the the mental formations that have to do
around me myself and mine that has to do around
I not none of that is rejected none of that is no philosophy that says that
that shouldn't be there somat samadei has nothing to do with philosophy nothing to do with
beliefs but rather samati is a deep
appreciation that we don't need to
do we can let go of what is stressful in the mind we can let go of what is uh
hinders a kind of natural radiance of mind the luminosity of mind perhaps
a clarity of mind a peace of mind these are all metaphors rather than looking
for exactly these things themselves maybe metaphors for something
that cannot be discussed so much um the Buddha you know in the description
called it a pure clear mind or a clean and clear mind
and some of that is uh the softening that relaxing of what is often quite active
for many people in daily life is selfing referring things to myself and how it
affects me and and what the self wants so it's a
it's a uh again it's not something we have to do it's not a rejection of self it's not a letting you know in a sense
not quite a letting go of self it's just feeling sensing through the calming through
understanding clinging the disturbances of the mind that they're not those the
activities of selfing are not needed and we can just be we can just be in such a deep way
that even the the practice of being a practice of being is too much falls away
so to assume a meditation posture and
to one of the associations I have with meditation posture is to assume a dignified
somewhat dignified upright posture that
somehow allows the the body to be expansive
if maybe simply that the chest is a little more open than usual one way or
the other for people on laying down there's a way of kind of adjusting the back so
that um if you're on your on your back to uh get the shoulder blades in the
back kind of go down the back a little bit the shoulders a little bit turned and the chest a little bit open
maybe rather than having the hands on the body or just to the side to have the hands if you're laying down kind of open
expansive sitting in meditation i like these days to have my
hands on my thighs the feeling of more openness a little bit
bigger and this idea of a bigger in the posture is the idea is
to grow bigger than the skin of snake a
skin of the skin like a the snake snake skin that falls
off as the snake grows as we take our bigness
the skin of self can begin to crack and fall
off we don't have to be here with a lot of selfing and self ideas and
comparisons and right and wrong and worthy and not
worthy even thoughts I can and can't do this just become bigger than all of
that gently close your eyes
and with a way that maybe you can enjoy slowly take some deeper breaths
just deep enough so it stays enjoyable but these deeper breaths again
make your inb breaths make you bigger
big enough to shed thoughts
ideas memories feelings that make you
smaller that keep you
small and as you exhale long exhale imagine all that keeps you small
falls away relaxing the
body and then letting the breathing return to normal
and continue feeling the body and on the exhale relaxing the
body sometimes when we relax the muscles they might
settle but they might also expand a bit
because they're not held in clenched and there's a way of becoming
larger
generally relaxing the body will relax the mental constructs
that we live by relaxing the mental constructs
relaxes the body
and then sitting quietly centering yourself on the breath
maybe resting in the resting place at the end of the
exhale the grounding place and from there feeling the expansive of the
inhale the return of the exhale feeling that
rhythm as a way of helping the mind settle also and relax
as you breathe to see if you can
[Music] feel the tension or
pressure maybe even clenching that might be
associated with the activity of selfing often manifested in the thoughts
that are centered on
self the pressure to think the tightness to think that about things related to me
myself and mine or
perhaps the emotional center of some
emotions that
arise from stories and ideas and experiences that we
carry as a concern of me myself and mine
so the center of self in emotions in thoughts in the
body feel that as you inhale and on the
exhale let it fall
away let it float away relax
that for these few minutes the tension the
pressure is so associated with that has any association to me myself and
mine is not needed and you can stay
large and have the snake of snake skin of self fall
away so that a natural way of being that's free of self
ideas contractions feelings
judgments as a chance to open up
every exhale letting
go not of self but any pressure tension
activity activation in the body and
mind connected to selfing self-
concern self assertion self
imagination letting go of it all
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to feel and sense any way that you feel calmer or
more settled than the
beginning or any way that you are
not in either way
and you for the last few moments
here let go of anything that is not
calm anything that is not peaceful
even if it's just letting it recede a bit to the
periphery let go of
holding let go of
resistance let go of pressure
let go of wanting and not
wanting and as you do
so does that soften any self-
concern self-p preoccupation
and in the middle of it all maybe there's some feeling
sense of a clear clean
awareness that takes a form of a radical
simplicity just to be alive is enough for these few moments nothing
more is needed and to sit here quietly
peacefully allowing the body the mind to breathe to
exist with as with nothing extra at the center of awareness
like an open window that allows sights and
sounds to come and go freely
so open
awareness clear clean
awareness with which you allow yourself to feel
see the people of this
world where that clear seeing is a
gift a gift that you don't impose yourself your self- ideas self
assertions needs and desires onto others
you don't require them to activate their self their ideas
of self in your open
awareness all things are allowed to be themselves for a few
moments just this
and then connecting it all a simple goodwill and
care that wishes for the well-being of all
beings may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this and be the last talk on the samadei
series and um and the idea is that uh
uh when when I'll be away for three weeks we have guests coming to replace
me and then when I come back in a sense I'll do the second part
of this series which will switch to vipasana to the clear seeing to
insight and the reason for that or how this works is that uh there's a
traditional Buddhist idea that Um the purpose of samadei to to go into the
jannaas or deep concentrated states is for the purpose of then at some point uh
coming into a capacity for deep insight deep seeing
there's something about the clarity of mind and the softness of the mind the
the readiness malleability of the mind in deep states of meditation that uh
predisposes it to both see clearly but more importantly to have the mind let go
of any clinging which is not needed and I say it that way that's not
needed so that's a little bit more welcoming this idea of letting go and uh
and it's a little bit of a I don't know a trick in that there is no
clinging that's needed but until you know that don't worry about it if it's not needed if you
see that let it go let it go let it go but the ability to let go the ability to
relax the ability ability to calm the overactivated mind is part of what
samadei helps us to do and so samadei in Buddhism is not an end to itself but is
a means to discovering the end of suffering a means to let go of what
often is impossible to understand how to let go of there's uh feelings of distress dismay depression sadness uh
all kinds of deep emotional pain that people carry that it's inconceivable how
can this be let go this is who I am this is the nature of the world this is the
consequence of my how I live my life and this is how I'm stuck
with and uh and it certainly can feel like that in ordinary states of mind and
there might not be an avenue in to let go of it in a conscious way but uh in
this very deep quiet and and peace and well-being of samadei uh unusual things
begin to happen in terms of the ability to let go the ability to see clearly the
ability to heal uh samadei is also a healing phenomena and uh we can't I
shouldn't underestimate how significant it is to allow the well-being the goodness of samadei to recondition us
from the uh difficult conditioning we've had growing up or through our lives which is uh can be so deep um that
um I was really surprised when I sat my long retreats to get the mind so still
and quiet kind of going into kind of the deepest places of my mind and find that there was things I was attached to that
I had no idea I was attached to um and um and one of my thoughts was kind of in
kind of in surprise about it all was how did I let those people into my mind that deeply and uh
that doesn't make any sense them to be have occupied taken up space in that
depth of my mind that is so personal that's a place of that doesn't you know
you know that uh where I should be free I shouldn't be caught I shouldn't be preoccupied
with these people these kinds of activities um that's not that's kind of
like being possessed in some way so um so samadei really helps
so we go through this process of samadei of the deepening the the stability of mind
deepening the settleness of mind deepening the unification of mind
deepening the calming of the mind uh filling out into the vast
uh centerness simplicity and that simplicity matures in the fourth Janna
where it's radically simple and one of the things that um uh you becomes comes
into highlight better more and more as we go deeper into samadei is when
selfing when attachment to self in any kind of way attachment to self-image
attachment to uh ideas of self ide attachment to what the self needs what
what's right what's wrong with self any kind of attachment to emotions connected to self thoughts judgment connect to of
we start seeing them in more highlight and we see that they're not needed so we
see how they diminish us how they um uh
disturb us how they um uh in a certain kind of way take us
away from deep in a deep intimacy with ourselves if we use that word self all
the time so it's it's almost like preoccupation with self takes us away from the self pre preoccupation of self
takes us away from a deeper intimacy with uh with who we are that's it's a
little bit oddly enough too much preoccupation in self caught up in self for example in extreme diversion
narcissism or heavy duty conceit delusions of grander is in fact an
alienation from self and then losing touch with ourselves in that
process so deep samadei we start seeing how this works and we see we're better
off to let go let go and not to have any preoccupation with self and the metaphor
in the fourth Janna I kind of see as being expressing this in this to me in a nice
way as a person uh sits covered from head down with a white cloth
um so there's no part of its whole body there's not covered by that white cloth
no part of the whole body is not covered or sat filled with a clean clear
mind and um what I like about this idea of being covered with a cloth is that
the details of a person are not seen someone walking by they don't see
something they don't see their physical characteristics very well a lot of the details of who they are what their
gender is what all kinds of things about the person are not seen uh but you see
the general outline just this is a human being there and um and it's not just
others but also ourselves uh we're not caught up anymore with our particular
physical characteristics or our particular emotional capacities or
particular mental activities or what our thoughts do these recede and settle away
and so there's this beautiful feeling of uh m maybe some a piece of cloth that's
very very clean un unt unarnished uh uh beautiful letting a beautiful sunlight
come through that's very peaceful and clear that uh we that without even
ourselves seeing all the details that we've been so caught up in maybe for a
lifetime and so there's much less self in these deep Janna and uh and then
there's because of that there's insight to seeing when self arises to
see the idea of self and and you see very clearly that's just an idea that's
just a thought um the thought doesn't really represent what's really most more
intimate deeper more fuller more true about what's here in this lived life
and then there might be a letting go so with the fourth Janna in
particular we are um uh the fourth J in particular we're
ready for this insight part of the practice so when I return in three weeks
uh we'll start uh with that journey together and just as uh we've done this journey
with the samadei and um and you don't have to have experienced the fourth genre for
this that is not what I've been expecting through this series but I wanted to give you a feel for it a sense
for it for those of you and some of you it might be relevant someday or it is already uh some of you it might just
kind of help you trust this process and and understand the process and the principles of letting go of being
settled and studied and unified that uh you don't have to go into Janna but it
it will help you be be prepared to go through something similar
through the pasta insight practice there is a correlary to uh samadei janna in
doing deep insight work and that's called insight janna vipasa janna and um
so um we'll have the chance to talk about that a little bit when when I return so I want to thank you all very
very much for coming along for these 60 talks on samadei and I hope that uh this
has uh been supportive for you and made it interesting for you this world of
samadei some of you maybe are noviceses to it and um and that uh rather than making you
experts as samadei my wish is that this uh this series has helped you have a
deeper appreciation for this body mind heart deeper appreciation of the natural
processes that are at play here that processes that uh samadei helps us to
trust more deeply and uh so um I hope that that helps you
settle be more settled on yourself more appreciative of yourself more um uh have
greater faith in the process of uh mindfulness samadei meditation and
being present for this life that we live may this serve for the benefit of all
beings so thank you and um I do look forward to
beginning the next series