so uh I'm really happy to be with you all this week
um I'm down in Santa Barbara about 300 miles south of of Redwood City and
uh uh it's uh it doesn't really make any
difference where I am because uh this SA this worldwide SA is uh is always
present here and now so Gil is teaching a retreat this week
and I'm really happy to be able to offer something in his absence and I I hope it will complement um this introduction
he's doing to how insight arises you know our practice prepares
the mind um through a deepening sensitivity to our lived experience our
lived experience moment to moment to allow these deep insights to arise
and on Friday last Friday Gil spoke about how the arising of insight is a
it's a natural process it's a a deep seeing and it happens when the obstacles
to that uh deep clear seeing have been left behind have been cleared away so I
thought for this week I would focus on uh some of the obstacles to clear seeing
uh where they arise and how they how they get in our way
so long before the time of the Buddha there was a special kind of
uh super walking human and an individual named Rohitasa was one of these and then
later hundreds or maybe thousands of years later this same rohitasa after
many um intervening lifetimes in different forms had been uh reborn as a
dva you know a kind of god or angel or some kind of mythological being that
exists in the in the text and he came to the Buddha and he asked him if it was
possible to reach the end of the world by walking by
traveling and the Buddha told him that it wasn't possible rohit Tasa was uh he
was really pleased to hear this because during that earlier super walking life
he had walked taking strides that apparently were a couple of thousand
miles in length each stride for the entire time that he was alive which was
about a hundred years only taking time out for his obvious physical needs and
he had never reached the end of the world so he was glad it wasn't
possible and then so the Buddha then replied to Rohitasa saying that though
it is not possible to reach the end of the world by walking in order to reach
the end of suffering it is necessary to reach the end of the world and then he
went on to say for it is in this fathoml long body with its perceptions and mind
that I describe the world its origin its sessation and the practice that leads to
its sessation and uh Bikubodi has has called this you
know Bikubodi the American monk who's such a um prolific translator of a
translator of many of the um of the early teachings of the Buddha wonderful
teacher he called this um maybe the most profound proposition in the history of
human thought that's pretty high praise
so in this story of Rohitasa of course Rohitasa was asking about how to reach
the end of the the outer world you know the physical earth but the Buddha's answer was about the world we
experience and some of us might not measure a full fathom i'm pretty a lot shorter than that it's about six feet
but no matter what size we are our entire experience of the world lies
within this body this is where we practice this is what we practice with
this is where our practice is realized where insight
arises so this week I'm going to offer some words about what the Buddha said uh
makes up our world are loca loca in the poly sometimes the word is translated as
cosmos but I I really prefer the word world because um it's simpler you know
it's our world how the world comes to us how we
know and experience it so here within these bodies is where we develop insight
and also the obstacles to the deep seeing of insight arise here as
well so to begin let's uh let's meditate
and I'll invite a little bit of exploration excuse me during the
meditation into what makes up our world
so if you'd like to take your comfortable meditation
posture posture that expresses both alertness and ease
yeah we want to be awake to our experience but in a relaxed peaceful
way so inviting ease into any areas where there's
tension
maybe doing a brief body scan
just beginning with the top of the head forehead and the brow
area just noticing any kind of tightness straining
and letting it ease as much as possible the cheeks and
jaw the throat and the tops of the shoulders
trapezius muscles just see if you can let those ease
up letting the breath be full
the chest can be open not held
tightly the belly can be
soft the thighs and calves just
relaxed feel yourself sitting or lying whatever posture you're in and feel the
weight of the body being supported by whatever is under
you the earth foundationally fundamentally
Like maybe taking a little time
to connect with your breathing taking a few deep breaths
just to help connect to the what's happening in this present
moment and to settle a little
bit closing your eyes just sensing into what can be
sensed with your eyes
closed it's actually happening
breath in the body whatever is happening in the
mind other sensations hearing
If there are sounds where you
are noticing what is heard and the knowing of what is heard
knowing is a a mental function and sensing happens at the
place where something is
sensed when we hear a sound you know where is it heard sounds are sensed at the ear
door but it's the mind that knows that something has been
heard that hearing has occurred when the mind recognizes it
identifies it usually maybe reacts to it
the sensations in the body the sensations of breathing all the sensations from the tip of the nose all
the way down into the the lungs the depth of the lungs the movements of the
belly all those sensations they're sensed where they
occur the sensing takes place there but the
knowing of the sensation is in the
mind the mind can simply know and it can also complicate that
simple sense contact but it's all kinds of activity and
reactivity
i I want to invite you to to stay with what is sensed just as much as as
possible letting mental activity settle maybe ignoring it if it arises
turning attention back to the simple sensations of breathing or hearing or
other sensations in the
body doing that staying with what's simple it can be easeful it can be
peaceful just sitting back and and watching the
flow of experience knowing it sensing it
whatever is happening in the body sensations of
breathing other
sensations even mental activity can it be known
simply just sensed into without
complicating let go of the
complication just sense and know
this uh just simplicity in the the way we
relate to our experience that I'm
inviting it can um it can be a way of warming our hearts
i think when there is simplicity in our experience there is
more access to uh to what is
uh friendly and welcoming within us towards our own
experience and towards others and maybe we can turn that outward uh now with a
wish uh that uh all beings
um enjoy a simple relationship to their
lives that they can have ease that they might uh have peace in their
hearts might feel safe and protected
might be healthy and one day might
uh have the deep insight that leads to freedom of heart may it be so
[Music]
so welcome again um if those some people weren't
uh weren't here at the beginning um just to let you know this week I'm going to
be talking about uh some of the things that get in the way of uh of the clear
seeing that leads to insight in our practice in our in our dharma
path and uh here's that that line from the Buddha that
Bubodyi was at such high praise for for it is in this fathoml long body with its
perceptions and mind that I describe the world its origin its sessation and the
practice that leads to its sessation
and after the Buddha had given this pathy teaching on what constitutes the
world um some other monks who had heard it asked Ananda you know the Buddha's
dear cousin and attendant to try to to explicate what the Buddha meant because
it's a little bit a little bit enigmatic and Ananda
explained the world is that in the world by which one is a perceiver and
conceiver of the world it's kind of a convoluted sentence the world is that in
the world by which one is a perceiver and conceiver of the world so what is
that by which we perceive and conceive the world
and what what the teachings tell us is that
what it is is the six sense basis the six sense spheres hearing seeing seeing first
usually seeing hearing tasting smelling touching this tactile sense and mental
activity and so the path to the end of suffering is found in exploring getting
to know working with seeing the true operation of these six areas of
experience and gradually letting go of any clinging and craving that's
associated with them so often over the years I've heard
Gil say that in any one moment there are only two things happening there is what
is happening and there is how we relate to what is
happening and what is happening is always happening at in one of these six
sense spheres that's all there is and how we relate to what is happening through the
mind is how we get caught how we get obstructed how we create dooka and it's
also how we get free so Gills begun this series on insight on
the insights that lead to the end of the world and uh last last week he spoke
about different categories of insight that we develop as we practice and first uh first there are
what he called personal insights you know seeing into our habits our habit
patterns noticing the way we do things how we've come to be conditioned by our
personal history i think of those as psychological insights and often I think
uh uh we spend uh our first years of practice maybe many years of practice
with these being the primary kind of insights that that we have we develop
more wisdom about our conditioning we start loosening the attachments to our
our stories our stories of blame and regret and self- judgment we start to
not take things quite so personally and then we become ready as
we have opened in that way to our conditioning we become more ready for
the deeper insights the ones that apply to all of us to all human beings
and Gil introduced uh the insight we can have into what is sensed and what we
make of it namar Rupa appearances and recognition as as he translates
that name and form is the the of literal
translation and this is the beginning of wisdom developing in us seeing the
difference between what we experience through our senses and the mental
activity that accompanies it and what I was kind of trying to uh invite during
the the meditation and then uh the next day he
introduced conditionality um beginning to see how we experience uh what we experience
through the physical senses is conditioned by what's present in the mind and vice versa you know how what
comes to us through the senses gives rise to mental activity everything is conditioned in
our lives and we begin to see this river of conditions flowing that that make up
our entire life all the way from birth to death and when we begin to see that
you know we begin to see that impermanence you know inconstancy ana that it's continual it's it's constant
inconstancy is constant and then because we see this flow as
constant we come to realize that nothing in our experience is stable nothing is
concrete nothing is to be relied upon including a sense of
self and gradually as a result of this we lose interest in clinging to what is
continually slipping away slipping away and then we become ripe for the the
deepest insights to arise the insights into the the three perceptions that Gil
introduced on Friday
so to use Anandas language all the practices that lead to insight
illuminate the way we perceive through our physical senses and conceive through
our minds the world our perceptions condition the
mental conceptions and our conceptions mental conceptions conceive how we
perceive there is this uh kind of feedback loop between between those and
gradually our practice illuminates what obstructs freedom and ease in that
relationship and leads us in the direction of the end of suffering gradually the way we relate to
experience the way we conceive our experience it becomes it's reconditioned
by our practice
so the the first uh sense sphere that's spoken of in the texts is seeing sight
the eye as the instrument of sight and the objects that are seen so seeing is a process that happens
between the eye and its object and of course um the mind
interprets what is seen what is being seen it recognizes the object if it's
has seen it before it makes assumptions often about its use or intention might
begin to tell some stories about the object the mind has the the power and
seems like it has the inclination quite often to complicate the simple act of
seeing and it does that complication conditioned by all its past experience
um with that kind of object and what that kind of object has come to mean in
our life we know what a door is because we've been opening and closing doors
since we were little kids you know but the way the mind interprets what is seen
the mental activity that is triggered that's where we get caught and that's
also where we where we can get free so a door you know a door is
a a pretty neutral object for most of us I imagine but what about the idea of a a
tropical beach and warm blue water palm trees with breezes wafting
through are you getting a kind of a visual of that for many you know such a
site maybe in a travel brochure will trigger some kind of desire some strong
desire maybe and for others that might just look like torture you know hot sun
sand in your shorts noisy people on the beach how we relate to the sights that
we see depends on what's in the mind old stories memories attitudes current
conditions all those things condition how we see what we see it's not clear
all the time and I think it's it's helpful to uh
to make a distinction between um seeing and
looking um this is something we talk about often it's a it's really useful as
long as our eyes function we're going to see what is before us but looking is a
more intentional activity there's a focus on one thing usually usually
accompanied by some kind of curiosity or interest in the mind maybe there's
desire maybe there's aversion or fear there's cognitive complication involved
in looking whereas seeing on the other hand it can be a simple receptive
process you might experiment right now just looking intentionally at something
maybe the screen maybe something else in the room
look at it as if you want to know you know what is this exactly really a
curiosity and notice what's what's the mind like you know what are the muscles in the face like especially around the
eyes i could feel my own eyes kind of squinting a little bit with that uh even
though I'm I knew I was going to say that and now just let go of let go of
that let go of the effort maybe close your eyes for a couple
seconds and uh just kind of reset and now opening your eyes
again just let your eyes receive what's in front of them maybe the screen again maybe the
room you're in notice what it feels like you know in
the eyes in the muscles of the face in the mind to just receive the images rather than
reaching out for them is there more calm in the seeing is
there more
ease moving from looking to seeing is a way of relaxing of calming the mental
interaction with uh with what we see
so we want to notice what it is that creates attachment between the act of
seeing and what is seen because that is where our clear
vision gets clouded distorted the things that arise when we're looking instead of
seeing sometimes there's some form of aversion maybe some form of desire and I
think doing this simple practice of switching between receptive seeing and
actively looking it can kind of help us see it can point to whether there's something tying our seeing to what is
seen that's maybe uh something we want to look at some way of relating to
what's happening that's taking us in the direction of more stress of less ease
and of course in our in our daily lives we we need to be looking actively quite often in order to na navigate the world
in order to avoid bumping into things using uh what we see to help us act
skillfully but noticing this difference um I think it can it can help us to
become more sensitive to what is it you know that's driving the
looking i know a teacher um who long ago uh gave a
talk a talk on sense restraint and something that he said uh then has stuck
with me ever since um he spoke about doing walking meditation on retreat and
how his habit in his life at that time he was a young man at that time had been
to be on the lookout for attractive people for the possibility of starting a
romantic relationship and so he knew he was often driven by sense sense desire
sensual desire and he described you know being determined to simply practice his
walking meditation and he he felt this urge to look at the other people walking
in the same area when he was doing the meditation and he said to
himself "If I look I will see if I look I will see." Not meaning that he would
see in that receptive way we just experimented with but that he would see
something he liked and be pulled into desire
and he recognized that if he used his eyesight to look at the other people walking that attachment that hook would
arise he would begin wanting something as a result of looking and so he kept
his vision lowered he didn't look at anyone in particular just seeing his
walking path and as a result his mind was able to stay
calm in daily life you know we aren't likely to be so careful to avoid looking
at what we know is going to give rise to unskillful reactions in the mind but uh
it's something to think about you know looking at the newspaper or the news online more likely
for most of us i think if we choose to open an article that we already have a
sense is going to lead to becoming angry upset filled with hostility no do we
really want to do that we can't always avoid seeing what might give rise to unh
wholesome reactions but we can look at what the pull is the hook that arises
between seeing and what is seen in those moments
so seeing is a really uh a powerful way that we perceive and conceive of our of
our world and becoming aware of what arises in our minds and hearts when we
see certain things certain people certain landscapes aware of whether what
arises serves us you know leads us toward more peace toward a a more open
heart to a sense of beauty and connection or in the opposite direction toward
unhealthy desire toward ill will toward rage noticing that seeing the difference
we can't always control what we can hear or see or smell or
feel and we don't want to ignore important things that are difficult to see but we have agency in how we relate
to the world um that arises in our experience and
learning to be wise in the ways we relate to all our senses is a really big
part of how we come to the end of uh of the world of suffering becoming wise about this is a
is a really gradual process of course so tomorrow I'll talk about
hearing which is another way that we perceive and conceive of our world and
in the meantime you know I invite you to spend some time really attending to what it is that you see and noticing when you
get hooked in some way in the looking you know maybe there's just simple
interest curiosity navigating the world but notice the hooks that might be there
desires or aversions judgments or comparisons that diminish your inner
well-being your clarity that get your thinking going in a direction that
doesn't seem so healthy it's only through noticing the
conditions that uh that give rise to stress that we will eventually let go of
what gives rise to stress so with that a little over I see
um thank you for your attention and uh I look forward to see you tomorrow