hello friends hello and good morning good afternoon good
evening wonderful to be with you um from wherever we're showing up in the
world um I'm in Tuscanyany in Italy it's 400 p.m here and
um and uh yeah good afternoon good morning good evening where whatever time
zone you're in and wherever on this earth you're in um again a bit of technical issues
but I hope you can see and hear me okay I trust that that is the case i see the
hellos and bonjour that's very sweet hi everyone
um so so today we'll continue with our
um with our exploration with our meditation and exploring the theme of SA
sa one of the important just as important as the other two jewels the
triple jewel being the Buddha the possibility of us waking up the internal
Buddha the external Buddha the dharma the these beautiful teachings that we
practice um capital D the teachings of the Buddha
Dharma with capital D the teachings of the Buddha uh dharma with small D the
lawful way that nature unfolds
and sana community concord spiritual friendship just as important this
relationality of practice which is just as important as the the Buddha the
external Buddha the internal Buddha the possibility of waking up as as important
as the teachings and it is said that the next Buddha is going to be the Sana so
the next Buddha the next entity the next being that wakes up is the SA is the
community that wakes up together so this week we're exploring as as me as
I mentioned yesterday um as Gil has been very skillfully
guiding uh the community through samadei 12 weeks of settling collecting
gathering the mind and later when he comes back vapasa these these beautiful
meditative meditative practices I figure that this week I'll bring in this
relational element of our practice which is just as important part of the triple
jew so sana community spiritual friendship kalana concord etc etc so
that is the theme for this week and I'll um
um say a little bit about the meditation uh for for
today and the meditation for today uh the theme for today so yesterday's theme
was the power the importance of spiritual friendship but I'll say a little more during the dharmat uh as a
review of yesterday and today the theme today is the qualities of a true friend
the qualities of a true supportive relationship so it could be friend
relative but this this the qualities the important qualities for us to um foster both in in
the relationships that we um we look for
we we receive and also in ourselves as we give as we intend to be a good friend
a good friend to others may I be a good friend to myself may I be a good
friend to others so today the theme of the
meditation well I'll introduce the theme of the meditation as we meditate how is that so we'll just start as usual
settling arriving in the body and uh I'll introduce the theme
so so with that let's settle as as it's comfortable for you to
settle arriving settling in this moment in time in this
body feeling feeling your connection to the earth
you ever on this planet you are in this moment I am in this moment I belong i am
part of this human family both the wider human
family as well as this community i belong in this
community just for showing up i'm a member of this
community you don't have to pay dues there's no cards to issue i
belong i'm a member i belong here i'm practicing i belong i'm an important
part of this community i'm part of this web
interconnected web and allow your heart to feel the way you belong you are
interconnected inextricably from this community and landing in your body
taking your place taking your place in this vast
space this vastly interconnected space taking your
seat if you're sitting really
feeling feeling into your sitbones feeling into your sitbones into
your bottom landing into the cushioned the
chair feeling your feet on the earth if you're sitting on a
chair or if you're sitting on a cushion the underside of your
legs connected to the
earth sense of stability connected
wellrooted sitting dignified upright taking my place taking my place
for this limited time with this flash of lightning that I'm alive for this limited time taking
my place feeling my
presence sometimes it feels supportive for me to feel as if there is this
uprightness this this centrality to my whole spine
eye as if there was a pole in the middle of my body a bright pole
ah where my heart my heart is
centered around this upright [Music] pole my heart is centered my belly is
centered my sitbones are centered around this upright vertical pull
and I can relax around it i can feel upright and I can be relaxed and soft
and allow the breath allow the breath to move
through emptying emptying emptying my
heart from what's not needed nourishing it with brightness and kindness emptying
my mind from what's not needed in this moment
allowing the breath to move
through emptying
calming stabilizing more as we take our seat
even in the midst of difficulty it is so sweet it is so sweet to be
alive to have this opportunity to be for this limited
time can I appreciate my beingness
the miracle of my being in this moment and settle just
settle let go settle the body settle the mind and heart just relax let go settle
into my heart
i allow the sweetness of sitting with Sana to uplift my heart in this
moment the inspiration aspiration can I sit just a little more
upright a little more with
heart spaciousness for the sake of my fellow
practitioners trusting that they too are rooting for me are cheering me
on we're all cheering each other with heart with kindness
i allow my heart to be brightened just a little bit even if
things are hard to know that I'm not alone in this moment
supported in ways I cannot imagine or see and supporting others in ways I
can't imagine just through this being sitting breathing very simple not
complicated not heady
Now if you like you can stay with the breath with the body the feeling of
interconnection or you're welcome to drop in the invitations
[Music] ions that I will
share and these invitations reflections again like yesterday let's drop them
into the body into our hearts as if we're dropping pebbles into a body of
water and let them resonate reverberate we're not dropping them into
our heads thinking about them no we drop in the reflection and just sit with
it breathe with it and here is the
reflection considering considering qualities of a good friend
can we bring to our hearts perhaps a
friend or a benefactor or a relative or parent
or anyone any being any being who has
been a wise counsel for
us or has been compassionate
kind or has been loyal maybe there is a friend [Music]
who's continues to send emails and calls us checks in on us this good
friend any of these qualities in this meditation is enough not to make it
challenging but any of these qualities in a being in the recent or distant
past that comes to your mind comes to your heart space
welcome yourself to sit with this quality
maybe it's been a wise friend who's given us wise
counsel perhaps gently [Music] kindly sharing with
us something that we didn't want to hear but they had our benefit in
mind or a friend who was compassionate
kind when we were having a difficult
time
inviting this friend to your heart space just spending time with them breathing in breathing
out allowing your heart to be lit up
by this quality by this particular quality of
goodness bringing some nuance to the recognition of the quality of
goodness whether it's compassion love Loyalty wisdom ethical
conduct how are you fulfilled how is your heart
enriched inspired uplifted with gratitude
and now I would like to invite you if you would invite yourself to your
heart space as a good friend as a good friend
both to yourself a good friend to others
allowing yourself to feel into this heart quality again dropping this reflection into your heart not your head
quality of kindness compassion generosity of heart
generosity of spirit wise [Music]
counsel ethical
conduct that you have you've been there for somebody
else feeling into the goodness of this being who is you stepping outside of yourself and
recognizing your own goodness let yourself be
uplifted by your own goodness the nuance of it
and if your mind is one that doesn't see your own
goodness please know that you simply showing up you are being a good friend
to yourself and you're being a good friend to others others in this sa
others in your life simply by showing up and practicing please reflect on this
goodness if nothing else is coming up showing up in your heart
space breathing in this goodness breathing out with this goodness letting it uplift your
heart most of life is just showing up
the more we recognize the more we turn towards the goodness of ourselves and
others the more we water the seed of
goodness the more we see it the more we water it the more we seek it the more
we become it the more we turn towards it and as we turn to bring this guided
meditation this to the close together turning towards goodness of
ourselves of our fellow practitioners if any judgments are coming up that
you're you were distracted you were sleepy you were XYZ let the judgment come and go hear it
thank you for your opinion dear judging voice thank you thank you very much for
your opinion you don't have to believe it just one of many voices many opinions on the
council and trust that you've planted wholesome seeds of goodness by your
practice by your showing up even if there was one moment of
mindfulness of gratitude of turning towards goodness your heart
uplifted bright that's infinitely better than
none so together may all beings everywhere be well may all beings
everywhere know their own goodness may they be a good friend to
themselves a good friend to others may we all be a good friend to
ourselves and one another thank
you ding
ding ding
thanks everyone pause for a moment and shift
the recordings
hello everyone hello and welcome back well you haven't left
but two different recordings anyway good to be with you good to to practice with
you
so oh yeah and I appreciate you so much especially given that the the series of
talks are about SA my heart particularly especially lights up seeing all the
messages and all the the names uh in chat the SA really
um yeah it's this SA is its own this this alive
um the sense of aliveness in this entity that is
is made up of all of us um so beautiful it uplifts my
heart so um yes so dharmat yes dharmat
so um yeah continuing on this theme of of
saga of this interactive aspect of our practice just as important as the other
two jewels as I mentioned earlier Buddha Dharma Sana the Buddha the possibility of
awakening awakening intern uh the uh the Buddha inside the Buddha outside
uh the historical Buddha the uh teachings of the Buddha Dharma
with capital D small D with the lawful way that things unfold and SA the
community noble friends supporting one another towards awakening towards
becoming the best versions of ourselves for the sake of all beings for the sake
of ourselves and others so so the theme yesterday was about the
power the power of spiritual friendship kalana mita beautiful friendship
kalana meaning beautiful wholes wholesome and u mita friendship and the
few things that I mentioned yesterday is that spiritual friendship is not just a luxury uh it's the entirety of holy life
um and also we talked about how uh spiritual friendships these these wise
friendships maybe spiritual sounds like a heavy word but wise friendship let's say wise friendship otherwise it sounds
perhaps a little hoyy doy and it doesn't need to be that uh wise friendship good
heart friendship beautiful friendships yeah let's just use the poly word the Buddha has given us already the poly
word so so beautiful virtuous beautiful friendships there's also deep emotional
attunement uh that we talked about there's contagion that we talked about both emotional contagion and also
ethical contagion uh people whom we spend time with they inspire us uh we
become like them so there's a there's there's it's really the soil there's the
soil principle that the um the the soil of friendships the soil of the community
that we plant ourselves in can nourish us
and today I wanted to talk a little bit about the qualities of a true friend as
the Buddha has talked about it in the different sutas and um so in uh for example the
Buddha talks about a true true friend um is one who safeguards counselss and
stands firm through seasons of change so uh in digaya 31
uh the Buddha is teaching a lay person sigala about the duties of right conduct
including and how to honor and recogni recognize and honor true
friends and this is what the Buddha says the helper the enduring companion in
happiness and sorrow and good counselor and compassionate these are the friends
to be cherished it's just uplifts my heart when I hear these qualities it
also I feel inspired aspiring to to um to embody these as the Buddha says so
here we go the helper the enduring companion in happiness and sorrow the
good counselor and the compassionate these are the friends to be
cherished and in traditional commentaries these four types of true friends are known as the suha
suha sua the friends of the heart and these
kinds of friendships don't arise just through accident but
through purposeful cultivation of goodwill and shared virtue and trust so
they just don't happen to us these friendships right they take cultivation nourishment and again the four types of
true friends as the Buddha talks about are these four qualities one is the helper enduring
companion so this loyalty aspect good counselor wise counsel and the
compassionate these are the four qualities that he's mentioning in this there are other qualities in other
places and I'll bring them in the future days but
um um so so um yes so the Buddha also is
emphasizing here the rep reper the reciprocity of friendship just as a
friend protects you you should offer protection loyalty and your presence in
return and friendship ship isn't just about receiving care of course it's
about becoming a person who embodies it who becomes a refuge becomes a good friend for others so as I'm talking
about these good friendships today and yesterday as well if your mind goes oh I
want good friends oh I don't have good friends oh it's so hard to find good friends pause my dear pause what if you
shift it how can I be a good friend how can I be a good friend to others how can
I be a kalyanita to others woo wow that uplifts my heart there is no scarcity or
lack well it's it's my heart can I be uh a noble
friend so
um okay I'm going to move on uh more points I want to make and the Buddha
also talks about the counterfeit friend versus the true friend also in digaya 31
uh he talks about beware of the taker the sweet talker the flatterer and the
reckless companion for they abandon you when hardship comes
and these descriptions especially when framed for householders illuminate the
psychological characteristics of ego-based relationships where they're friendships that are based on gain uh
deceiving for approval and vanishing when hardship comes um and and the false
friendship is often propped up by mutual craving right uh rather than mutual care
mutual craving rather than mutual care and the
Buddhist teachings call us to notice the subtle difference between
attachmentbased connection and liberation supporting friendship i'll
say this again attachment you know this this clinginess this cling or craving
based connection versus liberation supporting
friendship and in living a wise life or
intending to live a wise life a friend who flatters but does not
challenge you is considered dangerous in in this context
but a friend who lovingly corrects corrects you lovingly corrects
you when they see that perhaps something unethical or challenging or difficult you're doing or or perhaps you have a
blind spot spot in your mind and they lovingly correct and support you that
friend that kind of a friend is considered invaluable in these teachings
and uh friendship is sustained by virtue and mutual connection mutual support
mutual protection in this old language so true friendship rests not
only on emotional closeness but also on shared ethical
foundation and it's so interesting because in psychological research in the west uh it is said that the foundation
of a relationship is trust trust and trust is the most basic level really is
the the ethical foundation right when you trust someone's word their their uh
their actions they that that level of trust is based on this ethical
foundation so so again there's so much I mean this is uh not so much you know
Buddhism doesn't have hegemony over wisdom over world wisdom many times uh
various traditions of course and and psychology that does research on these
various very very human truths discover that oh yes they're they're the same of
course our friendships are based on shared ethical foundation ation of of of
trust and ethical behavior so in uh Angutra and Nikaya 735
the Buddha says the good person is one who uh faithful virtuous learned
generous and wise becomes a reliable companion and guide and again I'd like
to invite you to turn everything that I say instead of looking outside look
inside can I be this good person that the Buddha describes the good person is
one who uh faithful actually may faithful better
translation in this case is having trust having confidence in the dharma in these teachings virtuous ethical having
ethical integrity learned generous having dana and chaga wise
uh becomes a reliable companion and guide how beautiful is that how beautiful is that for us to in as aspire
to be this for for ourselves and others so a friend who keeps the the
precepts of non-harming the five precepts of nonharming practices generosity and reflects on impermanence
is the one who uplifts not just your comfort but your liberation not just
your comfort but your liberation and in traditional terraada
commentaries such friends are said to be a I'll say it
again sorry I I put the ax in the wrong place
assistant companions those who point out your faults with kindness celebrate your
progress and remind you of the dharma in the times of despair isn't that
beautiful i love that description
a those who point out your faults with kindness celebrate your progress and
remind you of the dharma in the times of despair in difficult times and last thing I want to say is
how noble friendship transcends personality again um it's it's a
friendship that uh is supporting you is not just uh uh supporting you know the
ego and making you feel comfortable but is is actually offering you um pointing
out your faults really this this out of compassion out of love out of
care so a true friends that sees beyond your moods and self-image but speaks
from the perspective of your highest potential not your passing preferences
but really seeing your highest potential your your true goodness and
beauty and [Music] um and maybe yeah given that we're out
of time I'll transition to sharing the reflection questions so here here are
the reflection questions for today in my life who offers
counsel that pri prioritizes my true welfare even over my comfort are there
friends who uh offer counsel that prioritizes my true welfare over even
over my comfort and how do I receive that how can I be with
that here's a second reflection how might I strengthen my own practice of
being a reliable wise and compassionate friend how can I strengthen my own
practice of being a reliable wise and compassionate friend and the third and last reflection
for today where do I need to become more discerning between superficial and noble
companions is there a place that I need to become more discerning between superficial and
noble companions and friends so with that my dear friends
this is uh this is our dharmat and invitations for reflections on on the
qualities of good friendship how can we embody them and
also see them in others so thank you so much for joining today
no bells today thus far i think yesterday was beautiful and special so
may there be bells in your heart may there be bells in all of our hearts
thank you so much for joining may you have a beautiful day of friendship yourself and others be well and looking
forward to seeing you tomorrow take care