when the Dal Lama said uh that kindness and
compassion are Necessities not luxuries
what uh did he
mean discover the the necessity of
love in the baren desolate Landscapes
of hate misattunement
when the heart's been drying out in the sun or
uh becoming more brittle the
intensity life
the heart's been living in a kind of state of
forgetfulness around the necessity of kindness compassion
love it uh can be very powerful just have a
moment of reunification with love
our whole body
can and quiver with it
the Mind goes to work figuring out how to trace out the implications of our
love what to do in the face of the the
enormity
hate just put down those details for now those
details of the effect of dampening the brightness of the
love don't worry in other words about anything except caring for your
heart in this
moment the only nourishment for your
heart it's wisdom and love
for
e e
without uh flirting with any tribalism sense of homogeneity of this
group we can say can take
some Refuge the fact that
um sa is uh gathered
around uh commitment to goodness
to
nonharming to restraint and care
part of why s feels good is
uh this um mutuality and the sense of uh oh this is
a an ethical
culture a little community within
society that uh is trying not
to trespass on the hearts of others
whatever goodness means to you
abide in
it an image or word or
phrase uh kind of vibrational frequency in your own body heart
just abide one form of or another abide
in
love
e
e e
there's a recognition that um every movement of
uh our mind and
body uh expresses this longing to be
happy and yes some of those movements are unwise May maybe they don't work out
but this uh thread of longing to be
well runs through the entirety of our life
and the recognition of that engender a tremendous amount
of compassion for ourselves
one who loves thems that budha says uh will not harm
another CU it does not take much work to trace out the
implications of our own
experience to recognize
how urgently all beings long to be
well safe protected
so we kind of melt into
uh web of uh billions of beings
abiding in a sense of goodness ringing the bell of Love
reminding our self Moment by moment of its
necessity
e
e e
sometimes touching into
goodness is uh like
grief and sometimes like ecstasy
just stay uh close in
strong back soft front Joan alifa says
the fleshy underside of our bodies that we
call our face and chest and
belly
soft but the trust courage confidence that love Eng
genders the strong
back
e
e e
sometimes love feels like love and sometimes love just lets you feel whatever it is that
needs to be
felt e
either way we come
to something like a very deep Faith In
Love
e
e e
[Music]
e
so I got a uh an you know uh anonymous questions I quite
quite moving uh to read your your questions and um just answering one but
uh maybe we'll get to others certainly they they inform how I'm thinking about
the the group so this person um said um said
sometimes your talks uh resonate so strongly it's as though I already knew
and understand all along and you just brought it to the light but then there
are talks that feel out of my reach teasingly standing just outside the
realm of my understanding making me feel like I'd missed an important class and I wish
there were a Makeup Session I could have attended which brings me to my question
of whether there are there are makeup classes in the forms of readings or books transcripts
of previous talks in some accessible order you could suggest to bring some of
um more complex teachings Within
Reach so first off I don't know if I'm
teaching the right way you know who who even knows how to do
this you you can kind of follow uh the the Buddha's model and
pedagogical advice but in the end you have to make a million in any Dharma talk a million
editorial decisions and uh teachers can can merely
Express their particular loves as best they
can and so I don't know if I'm teaching the right way and just because certain ways
of teaching get reinforced by the SAA you know doesn't mean they're
optimal like sometimes I wonder maybe I should be tougher much
tougher and then I think but I don't want to and then I'm
not but maybe I should
be so you know that's kind of like the footnote on all of
this there's a kind of uh sincerity in the the question that I found U sort of
charming and uh everything beautiful that happens on
this path depends on sincerity and by
sincerity I I mean a kind of true willingness to be surprised by one's
Mind by the path and the person says yeah I
understood that all along that is that's right that's how Dharma recognition
feels something kind of Clicks in and
the knowledge feels like remembering knowledge feels like
remembering and it's a very very intimate experience to have
one's mind spoken plainly by by a stranger and that's an
experience I've had many uh many times as a practitioner you know sitting with
a teacher teacher says something and it feels like they're
almost like they're in my mind and that can
feel um that kind of like
intermingling of beings can feel very
intimate and because that can feel so
boundaryless all the other boundaries are so
important and it's um it's easy to confuse the the the messenger for the
message Dharma teachers kind of all kinds of credit that uh belongs to the
Dum so yes there's knowing recognition knowledge as a kind
of remembering and there's not
knowing there are parts that um that won't be understood and what I
say or what other teachers say but the recognition of non- understanding is
itself an expression of wisdom to
know and respect what one doesn't understand that that
is kind of Hallmark of
sincerity this um Agnes kard book I mentioned to the um the the dayong on uh
Sunday um on uh Socratic dialogue and um
investigation and uh she writes um it's not hard to admit that you were wrong
wrong but very hard to admit that you are wrong it is not clear how someone is
supposed to ask a question to which she thinks she has an
answer when she is currently using that answer to guide her
life she's not going to solve the branch she's standing on
Dharma practice um involves sawing branches
sincerity sawing branches yeah how is one one supposed to ask a
question to which she thinks she has an answer that answer is currently required
for her living but Dharma practitioners and we
we see the kind of epidemic of uh
overconfidence uh the crisis that actually creates but Dharma practitioners live
with an abiding sense of suspect I'm
wrong I suspect there are real limits to my wisdom I suspect
that my pain in one way way or another distorts my
view and accordingly we have to hedge
sometimes knowing the kesas that our own pain
Infuse infuses our
view when I um when I first got into practice I was too too knowing kind of
uh arrogance and
um it took me I was sort of like unprepared to be surprised in a way it
took me a little bit of time to get my Dharma sea legs and then survey the
terrain and the conclusion was like oh my God I don't know
anything you know just gazing at the kind of ocean of
Dharma so humbled by my ignorance and energized by the
possibility of learning and there was a lot of aliveness and so many kind of dramatic
discoveries as early years of practice and it felt like my life kind of hinged
on understanding more I was living a ordinary life was
not a monastic or something but it felt like I know this is the
priority and it was really a kind of um a process of falling in love with the
Dharma and uh delighting in the revelation of
my own ignorance
callard highlights like that one of the um characteristics of Socratic
dialogue you know that that Socrates apparently like would be as delighted to
be proven wrong as to prove the other wrong the point is the learning not the
being right and so
now 24 years after beginning practice
um I've been practicing exactly half my
life kind of wild
uh things have evened out and some of the dramatic discoveries
of the first decade have yielded to more sense of cruising
altitude but um sometimes I get too comfortable in my
knowing and then my own practice or especially spiritual
friendship or students saying things or the world shakes something
up and the rugs pulled out and practice is
a kind of dialectic between making a comfortable Dharma home [Music]
we can't live without a nest you know some of the
time and then the rug being pulled
out so part of what I'm saying here to you to you to whoever asked the
question is um is to enjoy the not
knowing and your hunger to stand is a very wholesome
engine for practice for growth goodness will surely come of
it a way it's kind of like the most important ingredient in
that and no there are no makeup
classes and uh be
patient be patient you kind of can't swallow the Dharma in one Gulp and
there's no cramming for wisdom you know it it
kind of just ripens and the circadian rhythms of
wisdom are not observable to oneself
so patience and when
um I give a a
talk I don't need you to understand me I just want you to believe
me and understanding that can come whenever you
have time I do want you to believe me and believing someone before you
understand them a kind of cognitive dissonance opens
up and the Dharma flows into that
Gap so offer this for your uh consideration
um okay folks good to uh good to be with you and
um I'll be uh away next week so no class on the
26th but um be back the next week certain
Wednesdays okay I wish you uh wish you all well