so hello everyone and Welcome to our 30 minute
meditation and I feel happy sitting down here thinking
about sharing with you this theme this of samadi something that I hold very
dear um and partly because samadi is is
um something quite special um uh you know nowadays we talk
about uh secular mindfulness I don't think it makes sense
to talk about secular somadi at least in my
mind because samadi has a I have a profound sense of reverence for
samadi and uh to give you a little sense of this
maybe is that um there are two general movements that uh of Buddhist Meditation
terad Buddhism and the way I'm going to say it now is uh little bit um for the
purposes of distinctions and they in practice they
they don't actually play out so dramatically different but there's still a significant
distinction and so there's two general movements of Buddhist tabot and Buddhist
Meditation one is uh to focus on the objects of
attention and to do that thoroughly is to make everything into an
object and um without and the subject disappears the other way to
practice is to
focus on being subjective everything becomes a
subject uh all objects fall away and everything becomes part of the subject
the subjective experience and somadi belongs to the latter and mindfulness a little B more
belongs to the former and to make there's more to be said about this of course but just for
the purposes of today um and so when we sit for
somebody there is a shift into the subjective world of
experience not the world that we interpret not the world of being
self-consciously subjective it's not subjective and that it we tie it to me
myself and mine but rather there's something kind of like we're living inside of
it as opposed to looking at it or considering it as
something that uh we look on it's more something we experience we enter into
and the Buddha used the language of entering when he talked about
samadi and uh finally uh as an introductory words of samadi
today um it I think it can be useful for those
of you who are so inclined to consider
samadi entering into samadi is like entering into
a uh sacred Temple sacred
spot entering into a sacred uh
location and not a location you just stumble into or um casually go into
but something that you would as soon as you come into the edges of it you would become quiet you would change your
demeanor you would enter with attention present moment attention you'd enter
with reverence and care with u a sense of now the
place is has a significance a atmosphere
a value that um it's important to be
attuned to be respectful for maybe even
with a sense of reverence so so for me these qualities of respect
and reverence and Care Attunement belong to this subjective
world of how we bring all of ourselves into the situation not just treating somadi as an
object like there an object of of concentration that we're going to zero in on and stick with but we're entering
into a new mode of being a mode of being where
subjectively we are offering ourselves or allowing ourselves to be
changed by something that is not our doing
exactly just like you if you walk into a sacred Grove of trees or power spot in some
place of nature just being there something shifts but if you stay on your phone
looking at a YouTube channel walking in you probably nothing would happen probably for
you so here we are so assuming a meditation
posture which is beginning to build
evoke the temple of
somebody and perhaps entering into the
posture not treating it as an object where the Mind focuses and
arranges things but within the body
itself as if the body from the inside out is aligning itself ATT tuning itself
adjusting itself to be
alert to be
awake to have a
balance and part of this turning inward to the subjective experience
is to lower your gaze and perhaps closing your
eyes and as a preparation for entering the
meditation to adjust yourself prepare yourself by taking a few long slow
gentle breaths just long enough to not become winded or strained
by it but long enough to
feel a fuller embodied connection to your
body and as you exhale to relax soften the the
body and as you relax to take all the rest of you and
let it relax into your
body for
and then to let your breathing return to
normal and with if it works for you with a feeling of
reverence or tenderness or gentleness
feeling different parts of your body as you breathe in and as you exhale soften relax those
parts of your body a kind of
relaxation where that part of the body can feel like it join joining the
rest of the body tension in the body is kind of a pulling
away relaxing is a
joining on the inhale feeling the muscles of your
face on the exhale softening the face
on the inhale feeling the shoulders on the exhale relaxing
softening the shoulders
on the inhale feeling the middle of the chest on the exhale
a gentling tendering of the chest
on the inhale feeling the belly on the exhale exh ale softening
the belly and as it
softens settling relaxing the body into the pull of
gravity
on the inhale feeling the thinking brain thinking
mind and on the exhale quieting the thinking mind
and then finally when you go into a sacred Temple
sometimes there's little rituals of
purification and it's not so far-fetched to see breathing as a process of
purification the byproduct of carbon dioxide is
exhaled to bring in oxygen that's so necessary for life
centering yourself on the rhythm of breathing to the subjective experience
of the body breathing the
lifegiving purifying process
of breathing as a sacred
process into which to enter and
settle to be intimate with
exploring the Deep subjective
experience that flows from the experience of
breathing
for
e
for e
as you exhale let go into your
body and as you inhale fill your body with
awareness release your torso and chest
as if you're entering deeply into your subjective
experience free of self reference free
of being self-conscious about it like you would perhaps if you went
into a sacred
location
for
e
for e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting ever so gently follow the full cycle of
breathing in and breathing out in a tender way a gentle
way as if you're caring for something invaluable
as if you're touching something with care and
gentleness and then breathe a teeny bit deeper
Fuller as if your edges of your body your
chest is beginning to open up out into the wider
world as if you're breathing your
being is available to be attentive to
care gently for the environment in which you're meditating
for the people and living beings that might be close
by out Beyond into your neighborhoods towns
districts across the lands across the seas
a feeling of sacredness feeling of
tenderness a feeling of kindness that spreads out from you
across the
lands we're we're all together as subjects it's all a
subject no objects out there in this field of
care and then wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may it be that each of our care each of our kindness
friendliness touches everything we see and know today
may we leave in this world traces of kindness wherever we
go thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this third talk on series on Long series now it's going
to be on samade and this first uh five days of it
is really setting the stage it's introduction to the topic and entering into it and and today in particular uh I
want to emphasize that uh uh Som is something
that I believe uh is appropriate to enter with
humility with care with um reverence
with respect that um uh too many times I have
and people I know have uh attempted to get concentrated without humility or
reverence or care with a kind of uh forcefulness the
kind of expectation I'm going to do this and I can do it I'm going to really kind of Bear Down and laser focus and just
stay focused and and um and um and it is
possible to get somewhat concentrated that way maybe sometimes very concentrated in certain kind of way with
that kind of attitude but I don't think that that's the useful attitude to have
and useful for what purpose in the Dharma in the Buddhism
samadi is the the precondition it's often considered a precondition for the
rising of liberating insight and that uh if uh and liberating
Insight is not just an understanding that we appropriate for the purposes of the self and but it's
liberating Insight from the appropriation of self from the
attachments to self and doing things for the self it's allowing ourselves to Step
Beyond the limitations uh that we create for ourselves when we Orient ourselves
Around Me Myself and mine and uh
and that is pretty special it can feel like Grace it can feel like something
transpersonal sometimes people even use the word Transcendent a word that I don't care too much for but uh uh it's
for some people it's the only thing that can represent something that seems to take them out of their usual
understanding of self and um so samadi and uh in my studies of
Indian religions it seems that there are some of the religions in India or yoga
Traditions India that uh use the word samadi the way Buddhists would use the
word nibana that samadi is sometimes a word for the ultimate uh experience that
these yogic Traditions will emphasize and uh in Buddhism that's usually not the case but uh it does
point to this kind of very special feeling of what samade is it's and so I
like to think of it as um uh samade sometimes and uh as uh a temple a sacred
Temple that I enter into and um maybe some of you don't care
for that kind of metaphor um sometimes I've thought about it a sacred grove of trees I've been in
places in nature where uh it just felt like everything got quiet and peaceful
and clear and and um and this is something inside shifts and
changes in my whole demeanor um because of the place that and it calls a certain kind of clarity
of attention like now I'm really here and I'm here with a kind of reverence
and sometimes there's a a wonderful feeling of being quite small because of
the great Majesty of uh of the
Natural Things natural world world that's in that place but uh but it's entering a sacred
Temple and the reason why I think this is useful when we talk think about um uh
samadi is that um uh when we sit down
specifically to practice samadi uh it's helpful to reorient yourself to spend a
little bit of time preparing yourself similar to how you prepare yourself if
you were going into some some kind of sacred location and if a temple is a
think that works for you sometimes you go to these places you might put on clean clothes you might uh clean
yourself with take a shower and be show up clean you might
um uh you know some places you go in and you uh bow as you enter the temple or
you touch a sacred object or you um you
know do something that kind of marks the transition going in sometimes you would um uh you know
you really feel like you're outside in the busy hustle and bustle of the world but inside every you get quiet now
you're ready to for something that's not exactly you something Beyond you or
bigger than you that is found in the quiet and the care and the
and um and rather than objectifying that like you know this is some sacred place
where a sacred being or something lives um I kind of prefer to see it that it's
the very shift in the subjective nature of our experience that then allows us to
feel or sense uh something that's uh doesn't feel like it's part and parcel
of the usual ual way we think of ourselves usual attitudes
orientations judgments feelings we have so it might not be so easy to make
this kind of shift in or in orientation but I think it's helpful to realize when
we practice somadi that uh we are involved in a process of Shifting and
changing our subjective experience and so to the degree to which
that can be a choice degree to which we could prepare ourselves for that or or
care for that and support that so we have have kind of like a uh we we start
we start the process um to you know live A busy life
run around and do a lot of things and check a lot of websites and check all
your text for all your texts and emails and social media just just you know
because you know you're not going to be on it for 30 minutes 45 minutes of meditation um you sit down and the
momentum of all that greedy attention doing things
wanting things with attention uh follows you and uh or any attitude you have and
so to have a transition to practice samadi where
we're leaving all that behind long enough that we allow for a settling allow the whole system to become calmer
more settled more ready to feel uh the Deep maybe sacred dimensions of
subjective experience um so this is very different
than just sitting down and being determined I'm going to get concentrated there is a kind of
humbleness or humility uh where we're preparing
ourselves almost like to receive a gift we're preparing ourself you know it's
almost like uh samadi willing Samar will come we're kind of um uh shifting
something about how we are to become a vehicle become a vessel I guess is the
word a vessel in which to receive something that bubbles up from deep
inside something that spreads or something that appears maybe there's no
clear sense of whether it's inside or outside but now we're really here to be
open to be available to be receptive to be a vessel for
something and um and uh so to give you some sense of
this that how the Buddha presents it um for him uh just as samade is a condition
for liberating Insight uh uh well-being happiness is a
condition for samadi so he's already focusing on a
shift in the subjective experience that's needed in order to open up to
this world of samadi and um so when you sit down to
meditate what can you do that supports that
transition can you give yourself more time in preparation to sit not just Rush
from what you did to just sit down but maybe always come to meditation 5 minutes early whenever you meditate
maybe go into it slowly maybe do some stretching some settling maybe do a little bit of walking meditation maybe
quietly have a cup of tea and let things settle and then maybe uh sit down and
and uh just kind of be uh before you start even close your eyes maybe look around and and uh look
at the walls look at the floor look at the objects where you are look out the window to kind of begin really feeling
connected to here and now this place so that the momentum of the mind being
concerned about other places and other times begins to fade away and so we're
beginning to gather ourselves to Here and Now be here to prepare ourselves for
a new subjective way of being so uh in these introd these still doing
these introductory introductory remarks about samadi um the uh I want to review that
the first day I talked about discovery that we really want to see and understand how we
are uh and the more we can discover about how the mind body heart
is um it's the more material we have for the unification the Gathering Together
process we have and then um uh Discovery
involves attention an important part of samade is to find a form of
attention uh that um has a lightness to it that's not forceful it's not uh
contracted or straining very light uh transparent translucent just
open and um and it's easy then for the every the mind to wander off into
thoughts um and get distracted but uh then if we start now
today to uh appreciate that we're entering into we're shifting ourselves we're
enter into a new mode here then that preparation that new mode now can maybe
be a vessel to hold that light attention that is going to be the Gathering point
or the support for a deeper a deepening into a dimension of our life which uh we
often don't experience in everyday life a dimension of our life that um uh is
healing somebody can be quite healing a dimension of our life which can feel
sacred and dimension of our life that can give us a tremendous amount of wisdom and
understanding and um so
um with that um one more thing I'd like to S Suggest as we go through these
weeks around samade is uh as we settle into it I would encourage you to uh
consider a time a time where you're going to start meditating a little bit more uh each day than you do uh maybe
add a second meditation and to sit uh twice a day at least uh maybe 15 to 45
minutes and uh because Som Builds on a familiarity a
connectivity uh Builds on the residue that's left behind each time
we're practicing meditation that helps it to build over time so if that works for
you uh so thank you for today and look forward to being here with you again
tomorrow