so hello and welcome to our meditation and we're
during a period of time now for the last couple of months where we're focusing on
samadei and samadei has this uh dual characteristic
that's can seem a little bit like a paradox and
um and that is that um there's a both simultaneously a
feeling of wholeness that arises where everything's included or a feeling of um the mind
being quite expansive or the mental state the awareness
being expansive open wide inclusive of
everything on one hand And the other hand there's a centering on
something and that centering uh can become
so central that that's in terms of what we're aware of that's all there's left
that we're the world gets so relatively small uh in terms of what we're consciously
focusing on or centered on and those two things go
together so the expansive mind the whole mind that includes everything
um uh is not actually aware of
everything and the sense of being centered on
something it it does not exclude anything
so it's a little bit like this that as we get absorbed
in some wonderful activity we're doing we're not thinking anymore about the
past and the future we're not thinking anymore about uh right and wrong or it should be
different or should be better or we're not thinking anymore about other places
that at the same happening now we're no
longer the mind is no longer interested or involved in or
concerned with things so as we get more and more absorbed the world of where the
mind rests becomes smaller and uh while at the same time
this expansive mind that we have this holistic quality is there definitely
there but it's almost like it doesn't nothing is in
it everything could be in it but because we're so centered so focused focused on
this central thing a lot of things begin receding so in samadei at some point uh
people will say that they no longer hear sounds around them they're quite capable
of hearing but uh somehow the the absorption in breathing the mind is not
interested or not oriented towards sounds anymore at some point it's so absorbed
in just the simplicity of breathing that uh parts of the body seem to disappear
some people describe in samadei that they they don't feel their body anymore
and of course the body's there i've sometimes thought the body disappeared so I wanted to make sure I was still
there and opened my eyes of course it was there it's just
that somehow the the what the mind is taking in what the mind is interested in
what the mind every rather than the the field of awareness is so involved in
something very small though it's still very expansive so it's just kind of
like so a whole a whole wholeness of practice that becomes simpler and
simpler and simpler and one of the things that remains in this wholeness of
experience is um this first Janna is the there's still
a lot that remains there but it's getting simpler and what we're starting to feel now is this kind of we're now
we're really getting centered really there's a and so there a center that has
this wide hole and so one one way I think of it is that of a standing in the middle of a
trampoline where the weight of the body has the whole trampoline sagging and everything all the balls that the kids
have left on the trampoline will roll down on the center of the trampoline and so the center of the
trampoline is where the mind gets centered and everything gathers and then
after a while we're no longer aware of the what's outside of the trampoline and then not aware of the edges of the
trampoline just here where we're standing so to take assume a meditation
posture and taking the place where you're
sitting is so important because it is in a sense the going to be the middle of your
trampoline the middle of the circle of awareness in which we you sit
and so to really assume the place where you're sitting the place where you're lying the place
where you're standing
as a place to connect to feel the weight of the body against
the surface that the surface
that supports you from falling and falling by the pole of
gravity and maybe the surface your body's resting on feels
firm solid and gently closing your
eyes in some ways with the eyes closed the center of the trampoline the center
of your circle is the sensations of the body the
weight of the body the substantiality of the
body the solidity of the body
the simplicity of sensations of the body
and then within the body is there a center of your
body do you have something intuitively or place that you feel maybe deep in the
torso center of gravity
some place where the torso the weight of the
torso or
the central
location maybe deep in the belly below the navl
that somehow the center of the trampoline of your
body and maybe from
there receiving the inhale as it
begins not so much you receiving the inhale but the body receiving it
and allowing the exhale allowing the release
And also on the inhale have your awareness your
mind open as you breathe in like it's opening a window for the
breeze to come in open the mind wide to
receive the awareness of breathing breathing
in and as you exhale allowing the mind be to become
wide
the mind wide like the surface of a lake where the waves and ripples calm
down and the surface becomes calm and
still breathing in opening the
mind breathing out stilling the mind
and with the mind open
wide centering yourself centering the awareness your
attention on the breathing
seeing if you can be relaxed and easeful with whatever way your body is
breathing it's all okay
and then beyond the edges of the body's experience of
breathing are there any feelings of pleasure
appreciation
gladness as you breathe in let the pleasure calm of your body
whatever is there let it receive the
inhale allowing the exhale
to ride through the pleasure the joy
as you breathe in
connecting to the sensations of breathing in as they are received in joy or
pleasure
as you exhale connecting to the
exhale and riding the
exhale bringing the joy or that pleasure with you to the very end of the exhale
so there's a very gentle engagement
involvement centered on
breathing without the mind becoming tense or tight
giving yourself over to the simplicity of
breathing or anything more complicated anything not involved with
here and now that the
mind takes a
vacation the mind takes a break from concerns with
anything but a devotion to breathing in and breathing out
not trying too hard with anything
but giving yourself over to receiving
breathing receiving the inhale as if that's all there is to
do we're breathing in is received in the wide open field of
awareness and the exhale is [Music]
allowed in a wide field of settling calm
appreciating the rhythm of receiving and
allowing supported by whatever well-being
That's being massaged as you breathe
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to feel into your body your heart your
mind for whatever ever feels good about coming to the end
of the meditation how you're more settled or calm
maybe there's something you enjoy about all this something that can be called
pleasant or pleasurable maybe even some joy
or well-being that as you think
about might bring you a little smile or maybe you would turn up your
corners of your mouth just a little bit to bring a
spark of something that feels like
joy and with whatever joy or pleasure or calm that you
feel imagine that that it's through the lens of
that that you gaze upon the
world that how you see the world is a gift you give the
world if you gaze upon others with appreciation joy delight
pleasure it does them a world of good to be seen that
way even if they don't know that you look upon them that way it
spreads the conditions for friendship for kindness for
care gazing upon the world through the eyes of well-being of joy
delight calm may all beings
experience happiness may all
beings experience
safety may all beings experience
peace may all beings experience freedom
may all beings experience
joy well-being so we can
meet through our joy through our mutual appreciation our mutual
care the mutual way that we give each other space and
freedom may our practice of samadei
serve to bring benefit into this world
thank you
so welcome to this next talk the 43rd
talk in the series on samadei and these talks are certainly
building on the 42 earlier talks so they make more sense in the context of that
so the samadei is experience of immersion
absorption that involves a number of characteristics and one of the forms of
samadei that they're emphasized in Buddhism is called Janna and there are
four Janna four of these kind of almost
quantumly different uh states of absorption or
concentration and these are states uh of mind or states of being so that we want
to be careful we don't use the word concentration too much and the idea is that it's a laser focus of the mind
where the mind gets tight and narrow and focused and penetrating that's all too
easily narrows the field too much it's a wide open field that uh
settles into samadei and the first genre is generally
in uh it's taught they're characterized by five primary
um kind of activities mental states that are going on and those five are called the
five Johnic factors and um and so those are the um
initial or um the um connecting
uh attention the sustaining of
attention joy happiness and then the fourth the fifth
one is uh the poly is eagata e k a g- a
ta and uh sometimes it's translated as onepointedness and sometimes it's
translated as unification or I like to call it wholeness a gathering
together and um so uh one way to kind of
uh bring those two different ideas together well I say
before I do that the idea of onepointedness uh lends itself to uh narrowing
attention to a single point and getting tense in the process it doesn't have to be that but a lot of people who practice
onepointedness on something will try to penetrate or have this laser focus it's
very tight and and um and uh it lead can lead to headaches even it can lead to
some kind of tension building up and some of the and negative consequences of samadei
are are born from any kind of tension involved as we practice samadei and
sometimes people are not aware that they're tense uh there's a can be a lot of pleasure a lot of goodness it can
even get concentrated with that tension But sooner or later that tension will
create some kind of unfortunate byproducts that can interfere with healthy
samadei so the word onepointedness is a little bit risky um unification or wholeness or
gathering together maybe is a little bit abstract for people to understand
so the the word that maybe kind of combines these two in a nice way might
be uh becoming one ekka means one gata can mean like going to becoming
something uh the state a state of one maybe a kind of oneness but becoming one
so every all of what we are becomes one becomes absorbed with the breathing and
there's no sense that anything is being left out but uh there's no awareness of
what's outside so it's you know if you close your eyes maybe laying on the couch and
listening to some really nice music and pretty soon uh the couch disappears the
room disappears uh the time disappears the future disappears the activities of the day
disappear in a way maybe even you disappear because you have become one
with the the music you've you've kind of centered now in the music you the
wholeness of experience now is defined by music so but there's you're not narrowly
focused on the music zeroing in on it uh there's a feeling that the mind is quite
you know expansive it's like the the mind has become the music become one
with the music but the music is you know broad and wide and everywhere in a certain way
so with samadei there is becoming one but you can't do that with tension it
has to be very soft so it's almost like um uh so soft it's almost like a feather
that slowly lands on the ground and then is centered on the ground there becomes
one with the ground maybe i don't know what feathers are thinking about but becoming just there so
that uh it's that that love that kind of more like gently settling in and very
light feeling and so to find a way to be with um with breathing uh to be with the
sensations um and um and uh and and coming become
becoming one with it becoming simple with it becoming whole just with this
experience of breathing and so these five mental factors all work together
they're all there and they're kind of part of the whole so at this point in the first Janna there is a kind of
activity going on we are still engaged in doing some kind of practice that
gives but the way we engage it almost feels like we're we can enjoy it more so
this an uh applied attention we connecting attention yes we're here ah
connect and then and then um sustaining i sometimes uh liken it to getting a
massage where the masseuse went puts their hand and it feels so good to have
the hand touch us because we know what's going to come is the needing and so the
needing the and then or maybe the it's more like um the rhythm of needing and letting go
squeezing and letting go of a massage so there's this kind of rhythm of of a of a
making a connection fully with the breathing and then sustaining it writing
it feeling it and so the mind is gently involved with this so there's a little
bit of intentionality a little bit of participation but the sense of participation is just a delight just ah
it's so good to do this maybe it's like uh being really uh thirsty on a hot day
and then drinking um uh cool refreshing water and just feels so good to take
those sips and the gulps and have it you feel ah this is good this is good each
sip feels good in new ways like the rhythm ah and so that speaks to um this applied
and sustained attention uh is related to some of the sense of well-being that can
arise and I'll talk more about that tomorrow but um uh uh there's a sense of the pleasure
the joy the delight that comes uh uh almost as if it's like a thei that
rhythm of massaging applied s attention and sustained attention is almost like
um blowing on a gentle flame keeping it going keeping it going and
um and so it's it's not work it's not like we have an agenda it's not like we're trying to make something happen
ideally it's just really good for its own sake and so as we go deeper into
this these deep absorptions very important the more we go into it to not have trying to make
anything happen and do something um and try to do better but it's more like just
really enjoying what what's here now and just to be content with that and and that
allows for a deeper settling that we'll see so there's five factors then the first
four is um connecting attention and then sustaining then two forms of well-being
a joy and a happiness and I'll talk more about these tomorrow and then today the
emphasis is on this ekagata this onepointedness of becoming one this
unification and um which is a simplification where we allow allow the
mind to become simpler and simpler unconcerned about anything but just this
process of the samadei itself and we might be very aware that
there's a field of openness field of goodness field of joy and um and we're
just allowing that everything to be there everything there mutually supportive of this process of being
content just to be with the breathing uh just the simplicity of just breathing in
and breathing out nothing else needs to happen and in some ways the world
disappears like on the couch listening to music um the the your your cushion
disappears your the room
disappears yesterday disappears tomorrow disappears maybe even you disappear in
just simply staying there with the breathing so
um so you might see as you go through the day today if there are certain activities
you do that uh lend itself to this kind of becoming one with the activity
so it could be something like washing dishes or or putting the dishes away in
a way that or cleaning the kitchen floor or folding the laundry
or chopping vegetables or making your bed or um you know uh putting your
clothes very nicely away in a drawer where you just give yourself over to that activity not to get it done quickly
to move on to more important things but to that this is the place to do become
one with this activity and often that means that somehow we do it with care we
do it so it feels really nice it looks like like like you know that folding it
in a neat kind of nice way the t-shirt before you put it in the drawer is not
because we're fidious but because that's what samadei does to be fully involved
with what we do is to do things in a way that are harmonious beautiful pleasant
enjoyable and see in the course of the day whether you can begin experiencing
some of the benefits of samadei in being absorbed in what you
do and uh you probably your heart will love it if you give yourself more
chances through the day to become one whole
unified one pointedly absorbed in what you're actually doing in the
moment so thank you very much and we'll continue thank you