so good morning everyone and before I start I some of you have contacted us about a
hum in the in the recordings and so I'm
using a different mic the issue might have been related to the mic that you had and so I know if those of you who
noticed this uh want to say something at some point in the end of the the session that would be nice to
So welcome everyone to our morning's
meditation and one of the
invaluable areas to care for be careful with and
caring is um uh has to do with our thinking thinking during meditation
some people are at war with their thoughts some people are enamored with
their thoughts some people are 100% committed to their thoughts some people
are uh are subservient to the authority of
their thoughts every thought is true or something and but in meditation
uh you what the idea is to start learning how to think and what to think about that
supports somebody and at this uh approach stage
of samadei there can still be thoughts but the difference is that
now the thinking comes from a deeper layer level deeper source within us than
anxious thoughts uh desirous thoughts thoughts that have a lot of clinging
involved or force behind them or a lot of ego or self around
them and um and the thoughts that the that come into play are quieter softer
lighter more like more like they float float through rather than they don't
have any force they don't have any force behind them or there's no tension connected to them and they are thoughts
that have to do with the meditation itself very simple thoughts about yes
this is good yes here is where the attention should be what happens if I
come a little closer in to the sensations of breathing what happens if
I open up more widely to the sensations of breathing can I just stay
longer with the sensations of breathing these very simple sometimes they're a
little bit like giving ourselves instructions sometimes a little bit like exploring the
situation just trying very subtly different um ways of being with the
experience it's very small adjustments very small things it would be almost as
the thoughts would be almost as light almost as almost not there as it would be
driving down the freeway and the subtle ways in which you're constantly
adjusting the steering wheel to stay going straight and it's done almost probably without any conscious thinking
but there is a conscious engagement that's there that
so that that light almost so there's a way of thinking and that way of thinking ah is
also uh can be akin to love can be akin to uh being uh gentle
non assertive a kind of thinking that is not
going to be judging not going to be reactive or alarmed but just just
like oh here here my friend let's try this let's be here um like you're with a friend who's
maybe trouble with something and here let me let
me you know let me let me put my hand on your shoulder or here would you like to
link arms as we're walking through the park um here
um I'm here with you and so there's no kind of thoughts
that are making opinions up or stories up or reacting or projecting ideas it's
very simple instructional about the experience and sometimes they're very subtle thoughts that just to yourself
kind of very simple are doing field notes describing the situation no and
you know you're doing this thinking appropriately if it doesn't distract you
it keeps you on track keeps you right here in a nice way you feel the support
of it it's like a friend who you know puts their hand gently on your back shoulder saying "It's okay it's okay um
uh you can do this something." And
um and then uh and part of that is to begin to recognize oh here this is the
onward leading nature this pleasure this well-being this is
good yes this can help me stay stay with this stay with it what's happening and
this is the onward leading this is where I adhere and the onward leading nature
of samadei at some point can feel like a
gentle thread a gentle cord which is pulling you along
um and um maybe like you have a
um uh you know maybe you have a you're on a
a sled and you can feel that your friend in front of you or maybe it's a a horse
or something is is pulling you along and you can feel the pull you can feel the
direction or you can feel the the slide yes here
here and maybe that's the thoughts the very subtle here yes
now so feel the pull the pull of
samadei so assuming a meditation
posture and as you're sitting here without anything else just recognize in the broadest
possible way how you are how are you now how would you answer
that question even in very simple ways
feeling how that is for you to be this
way and then taking a gentle but full breath and on
the exhale settle into the very middle of how you
are where the edges can relax
closing your eyes and feeling how you are in your
body what's the global general feeling sense of being in your body
and then in the middle of that taking a few long full
breaths and as you exhale to settle into the middle of all
that allowing the edges to relax
and a more general way what's the global experience of
breathing and then breathing a little deeper than usual on the
exhale settling into the middle of your
breathing with the edges
relaxing taking two or three more deeper breaths
and the exhale letting your thinking mind settle
relax letting your breathing return to normal
and feeling the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
At the end of the exhale Having a pause that's just long
enough that the urge to breathe in can be accompanied by a little
thought subtle quiet loving thought yes yes to breathing
in as you allow the inhale
at the beginning of the exhale maybe experiment with a very
subtle quiet thought that simply says
instructs "Let go with no demand no expectation
just a reminder to be with a letting
go of exhale
and very calmly
gently recognize maybe with little thoughts
recognize any signs you have of becoming
settled becoming calm becoming
intimate with a cycle of breathing in and breathing out
the quiet thinking sometimes a nonverbal
thinking the nonverbal knowing thing that keeps you connected to the
process of settling
concentrating entering into an
immersive experience of samadei with your breathing
and might there be a some place deep
inside deep inside the
center of your settleness or calm where there's There's a gentle
pull that says here come along
here settle here focus here
or perhaps more profoundly you can feel the
gravitational
pull that has the message let go
here let go into here
this place this spot
and if it feels right let there be a subtle quiet
thinking about your meditation experience
that helps quiet the thinking
mind that reassures the thinking mind it's
okay to be quiet to be
here to simply
engage in dipping in to the samadei
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to see if from the quietest place where you can
think or maybe the deepest place
The place that is most settled and
calm
content have thoughts of
goodwill thoughts of generosity
of respectful care for the people you might encounter
today
strangers people in stores places of
work neighbors people on the road
friends and from the deepest place available for you the deepest place of
well-being or memory of deep sense of peace
well-being wish this for
others almost as if you can offer what you have to
others wish it offer it may all of
you be happy calm
content may all of you be
safe breathing breaths that are
reassuring may all of you be
peaceful free of agitation
may all of you be free of
suffering clinging and may we share
together may we mirror for each other
our deep human capacity for feeling
happy safe peaceful and
free may this be something we see in each
other and support in each other
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this next part of the series on
samadei and we're in this approach stage of samadei sometimes called access
concentration and um and as we get more and more
settled into meditation more settled more
absorbed more intimate more immersed in our
experience this is what samadei is is and sometimes samadei is
felt to be uh any situation not just meditation
where you're we are absorbed in what we are doing immersed in what we're doing
some people will describe this as becoming one with what we're doing some
people describe it as being deeply intimate some people describe it as being um kind
of onepointed gathered together just at just here just with
this and um some people describe samadei more as a state a broad wide expansive
state that is centered fully here with one thing right now at this moment at this
moment sometimes it's called there's a momentary samadei where we're
very established in the present moment but the awareness is fully there for one
moment of experience then something very different another moment and it's freely takes in the range of things that come
in through the different sense doors and um so it doesn't necessarily have a single object um which uh going into
deeper samati really usually uses simplifying into a primary kind of
object and a lot of this different sense doors start kind of uh receding from
awareness and so in deeper samati uh person might not be hearing sound so
much not conscious they're they're still capable of it but that's the the attention is so absorbed in like the
breathing that uh we don't necessarily hear very much
or smell or so so the the whole world of samadei things begin to shift and change
and it is a state shift there's a radical sha changing from business as
usual with how we go through our lives and one of the ways that this takes uh shape is that our thinking begins to
change as we start getting into this approach stage thinking more and more
tends to be wholesome there's less and less unh wholesome thinking there might
be still some desires aversions doubt that come up the hindrances might still
be there but they're fairly weak now and
so if you you should people who come into sumati should really understand the
hindrances well have studied them a lot and familiar with them so that the
subtle pull of them no longer grabs us we're able to say no not now stay
here and there's kind of an overriding movement towards kind of a healthy way of thinking a meditative way something a
supportive way of thinking thinking about just here just now being here stay here continue here
relax here don't cling don't push don't pull back stay
persist and But that thinking feels healthy it feels wholesome
and uh to some degree we can come to this juncture with approach the approach
stage where we begin to either it happens naturally this kind of more healthy way of thinking about the
meditation itself about the present moment experience or it's easy to make the
shift and it is a shift where we're no longer involved in the usual way of
thinking which maybe for many people is not so healthy that uh is not so
productive of calm stability peace even
well-being and so uh to begin to uh appreciate we're actually shifting out
of business as usual it's not a rejection of it is not from a by a version of it but it's important to
really appreciate that uh um uh you know if you want to go for a nice swim in a
pool generally you go and change into a bathing suit so that you're shifting
into a state into way of being that makes more sense that's more appropriate for a nice swim and
um there is a kind of recognition oh we're going into a different mode here
so that we're not because otherwise many of us are so committed to the usual mode of thinking the usual mode of being the
usual preoccupations but at least in principle to understand this is a shift we're
taking and we're going into we're going into the pond we're going into the lake
for a swim in a sense and yes it's appropriate uh to take on my take off my regular
street clothes to have my bathing suit um that um and so yes it's appropriate
to put down our preoccupations about work and family and thoughts and desires
and all kinds of things that um resentments that we have it's appropriate for this time because we're
now entering into this kind of a new world a new way of
being and um and this is where this this transition really begins to take hold in
this approach stage and there it's a little bit wobbly still the mind wanders off and we we come back be here and this
is where it's really helpful to have this quiet peaceful way of thinking it says yes here stay here it's okay you
don't have to go off not now not now stay here
and as we're staying here with present and the approach begins to happen some
of that approach feels like a onward leading like there's momentum like we're on a slide and we just kind of need to
let go to let the slide carry us uh it might be the onward leading
nature might have different ways it's experienced by people um sometimes it can be feeling like um
you know I very much follow my breathing in my in my belly the movements in my belly and sometimes it's almost like
there's a little thread in there that's pulling pulling me along come here
follow that thread stay right here where there's there's a little bit of pressure
a little pulling it's almost like almost like it's not exactly that but it feels like Oh yes here is
where I'm being absorbed in here's where I'm really
connected i don't know if this metaphor works for for you but I I've found it um
helpful for me um uh sometimes that I'm a that uh I'm kind of like a kite that's
in the sky floating nicely but there's a nice little thread uh cord that goes
down to ground and and that thread uh that rope holding to the kite in the air
it needs to be constantly taut uh you don't want it to be slack and you don't
want to be too tight if it's too tight the string might break if it's too loose
the kite will fall and um and so the job of the person who's with the kite is to
keep the just the right tautness there uh so that it flies
well and so just the right tautness there just you here stay there feel that
pull don't pull too hard don't lean into it relax it's always a relaxing always a
letting go a releasing into releasing into the onward leading nature releasing
into the immersion releasing into the lake into the
pond releasing it down the slide and um and
uh and the uh when my kids were growing up we went to a lake nearby that had a
water slide and it was fun you could go fast and splash in the slide of samadei
there there's not really a splash it's like it's very peaceful but sometimes it
could be sudden a sudden shift like oh I'm here i'm in the lake or sometimes it
can be a slide that has no bottom and it just but you find yourself in this
peaceful space so subtle
quiet soft thinking not too much not too
little a different kind of thinking than ordinary but a thinking that's about the
meditation itself thinking that's without greed without trying too hard
without criticizing anything just simple just the facts just the field notes just
a little exploratory aware so that that subtle thinking is part of this
gathering together unification that all of us is participating cooperating in
just gathering together into this immersive experience of samadei and then feeling the pull
feeling the the little bit of onward leading nature and not to get excited not to
push it more but to always remember to feel and relax let
go almost like letting go into the experience is the way to be with it more
fully so I hope that uh
uh this makes sense and um just as I was saying this in my mind
back of my mind I I wanted to say um refer to it as the poetry of samadei and
I don't think I've been anyway speaking poetically but uh maybe there's
something about the aesthetics the sensibility of poetry when it's really
moves us in a deep way that uh comes into play that supports this
onwardleading nature this subtle thinking where the poetry of samadei the
poetry of beauty here poetry of sweetness here yes this
is good so thank you very much and
um if some of you would like to meditate more a dayong it's not quite on this
topic of samadei but certainly hopefully supportive that tomorrow I have a dayong
retreat on Friday on uh mindfulness of emotions and
um and that will be uh through the insight retreat center on their menu you
see um uh uh online retreats it's also there's a note about it uh in the what's
new section of IMC's website and I think it's from 9 to 4 at California
time it's uh online so thank you very
much and uh we'll do another day tomorrow on approach