good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all it's funny how sometimes I find like little pieces of dharma just in little
snippets in the daily life and recently I I came across this uh
quote from Rilka letters to a young poet and just these few
lines let everything happened to you beauty and
terror just keep going no feeling is final
let everything happen to you beauty and terror just keep
going no feeling is final it's so like compact and there's I
feel like there's a lot there a lot there so I want to talk a little bit about
feelings about emotions kind of how to be with them and
the what our meditation or mindfulness practice can do as a support for
them i'll start with a little bit of a definition we can consider that emotions
are a form of communication from ourself to
ourself in some kind of way there's this opportunity maybe to learn something about
ourselves when we are in tune with our emotions like "Oh wow i'm really angry i I guess this is more important to me
than I realized or I feel sad." And this recognition like "Oh yeah
maybe I was more uh harmed or hurt or feeling grief or
loss more than I realized or something like this." or maybe some anger like wow
okay so maybe some borders or some boundaries were crossed and felt like I was disrespected and what is important
to me so it's a way in which emotions can be an important part of you know
having a rich and healthy life and it's a way that emotions can really be a
support for our lives but we can only learn from our
emotions if we can allow them to be there if we can allow the emotion to
exist and in some way be able to have some contact with it and to recognize as
best we can what it is and maybe the message it's telling us is obvious maybe
it's not obvious but there's something about not
pushing away your emotions or trying to run away from them which you know I I
spent a lot of time doing certainly many of you know I'm trained as a scientist and when I reflect back I think maybe
part of the reason why I went into science because I thought like oh they don't have those messy emotions there
little did I realize until I was a scientist right of course that uh
scientists turn out to be humans too plenty of
emotions so there's a way in which uh we can also consider that emotions are a composite so part of it are these
physical sensations the way in which we feel like fear or dread or something
like a lump in the throat or maybe there's heat in the face with anger or
maybe there's a knot in the gut with uh anxiety or something like this so all of
these emotions they have sematic signatures not the same for everybody
but uh it turns out if like if you have a like an outline of a human body and you ask people to color in the areas
where is sadness where is anger where is loneliness where is outrage whatever it
might be turns out that most people generally are coloring this in the same areas of the body tends to be the face
and the front of the torso for the most part for the most part it's not exactly
the same for everybody so there's these physical sensations there's also physical
expressions our faces are expressing emotions and there's some people who even get trained
in this and noticing the smile small flickers of the corners of the mouth or
the eyebrows or the eyes or something and can determine emotions so our
emotions are getting expressed maybe to others even if we're not so much aware of them and I'm sure we've all had this
experience where somebody is saying one thing but their uh ex emo their
expressions are saying something different it feels you like it feels a little confusing do I believe the words
or the what your eyebrows are saying to me and then of course there is the
thoughts the stories the whole narrative that we have that are going along with
the emotion i can't believe they said that and the next time I see them I'm going to do this and this is the third
time they've done it or you know whatever it might be or oh my gosh I can't believe I'm feeling sad again i'm
always sad i've been depressed for a decade and I'm never going to feel any better and I always feel terribly sad
you know there's this way in which the stories can like be perpetuating and fueling the emotions as well so these
different aspects and different might be considered a composite and so in this way we can work
with different aspects of uh emotions and from one perspective we can
say or consider that emotions of course are very personal there's something that
we experience and maybe are related to our life story and our history of our
life what we've experienced and how we've interpreted it
but for me I found this helpful to also put in perspective that yes all of our
emotions are our own but they are also you know part of the human experience
and this common humanity that we all have
emotions and it's also culturally and temporally specific
for example there's so many like books and movies and TV shows that about 19th century uh
United Kingdom I don't know exactly where we could say England at least very unflapable and very proper you know this
way right you know not a lot of emotion and you know kind of like uh upright right so there's a certain area era and
location and they have this certain type of emotional I don't know
expression and Jack Kornfield tells this story jack Kornfield is a an elder in
this uh lineage he tells this story of this was probably decades ago teaching a
retreat in Switzerland this was at a time when there weren't so many meditation retreats people from all
around Europe came to Switzerland to attend this retreat and at the end of the retreat he was reflecting maybe I
should say that during retreats there's uh individual practice discussions where each uh retreatant has a private
conversation with the teacher and at the end of the retreat uh Jack reflected wow it's quite something
everybody from this one country was had some anger and self- judgment was what
was coming up for them so members from another country were wildly just justiciculated talking
how painful and beautiful and wonderful everything was and then like from a
third country they had all these existential questions of doubt and the meaning of life so just this recognition
right that there's cultural um influences on our emotions
too and for me that was very helpful to just realize oh yeah it's like of course
I have these emotions I'm part of a cultural meu in addition to having
a a particular story particular
experiences and there are some that would say that the cultural male you
that is uh influencing our emotions today is this culture of
outrage everybody this is seems to be like the one thing that everybody agrees
on is to be outraged and this is pretty unique that like all the social classes
all the professions everybody's outraged and this is a way in which kind
of this in some ways that we could even say the western economy is built on this
there's so much of the media outlets and political discourse and advertising
these types of things are really promoting this sense of
outrage and part of this is um that we assume that outrage is a
reliable source for social change we can feel like oh yeah I need to be outraged
this is the only reason or only way things are going to be different than they are and dang it they need to be
different so I'm not going to comment on that except maybe I'll just share this story for me that uh has had a big
impact on me there was a time when I worked for a company that uh publicly
traded and we had missed a major milestone that was going to affect the stock price so right we have to uh send
out a press release so we sent out a press release saying that we had missed this milestone just the nature of my job
i knew all the details and it was fascinating to see like all what was
happening i can't believe this company is doing it they all are only doing this because of X Y and Z and I'm like wow it
has absolutely not one thing to do with what the truth was but then there's this all this media
kurfluffle that was 100% fabricated had nothing not one it was just fascinating
it was actually that we had made a stumble and we had made took a chance on some manufacturing process that turned
out not to work very well and they were made up all these stories about something quite something for me to just
see the media the all the I don't know social I don't know all all the um
comments on things was just not even close and not only was it not even close
it was filled with outrage like we were all of a sudden bad terrible company but just turned out
that we took a chance and it turned out not to work well on something completely
unrelated so now I have this story in my mind so now when I'm seeing the media and saying things about I'm think well I
wonder if that's the full story it might be the full story but it might not and
chances are it isn't chances are it isn't
so this idea of you know emotions whether it's outrage or sadness or
loneliness or grief or joy or happiness but in particular the difficult
emotions and difficult might be different you know what's difficult for one person might not be difficult for
another but I like this story this is also from Jack Kornfield now that I
think about it um I just love this story that kind of talks about this
idea of one way to work with difficulties
so this is uh about the poison tree and there's this tree that uh has this fruit
that turns out to be poisonous and there's this uh some people when they discover or see that
there's this tree that has this poisonous fruit they their immediate reaction of okay we got to cut this down
got to get rid of this tree before somebody's harmed before I'm harmed and
let's make sure that you know get this out of here that it's uh doesn't harm
anybody and often this is our initial response to difficulties that arise like
oh get this out of here this I don't want to feel this i don't want to even acknowledge that I have this type of
emotion in me this rage or this despair whatever it might be
and sometimes there's this way in which we have this idea we just want to distract ourselves and we have these
little rectangular things that we put in our pockets that are computers that we tap that can help us distract ourselves
and entertain ourselves all day long right and we do this very often so that's one way to respond to a
poison tree is to cut it down and get rid of it so that the or try to cut it down try to get rid of it
but there's other people and we might say they've journeyied a little bit uh further on the spiritual path and they
recognize you know the power of the heart and they want to bring some
compassion and care to this tree so they have this idea that no no let's not cut
it down let's just put a fence around it we'll let the tree live and of this
fruit but we'll just put a fence around it to protect people so that they don't get harmed out of this so they have this
kindness they put a fence around it and so this is a really different
relationship to the emotions from get rid of it to like oh no it can be there we're just going to be with it in a way
that is not going to cause harm and then there's a third group of
individuals who meet this poison tree we could say they've have uh gone even
further down the spiritual practice that might be one way to consider it and they come across a poison tree a
tree that has poison fruit and their response is to say "Oh poison tree
perfect just what I was looking for." And they pick the fruit very carefully
and extract some of the elements of it mix it with some other things and make
medicine make medicine out of it for themselves and for
others i love this story this sense of so often what we think are our wounds or
our difficulties and I certainly have found this in my life turn out to be
source of strength and source of connection to other people a source of
some vulnerability which allows some intimacy with others some some
closeness so this way that how can we be with what we might consider to be the
fruit from the poison tree in Buddhist practice how we how
might it be a support for us to meet what we find difficult in life and be
able to transform it into medicine for us and for others
and so some of us might have even come to Buddhist practice to a meditation practice because of emotions maybe we
felt like terrible grief have had some tragedy in our lives or maybe we just have some
depression some sadness and maybe it's not entirely clear but we thought we
would give meditation a chance or something like this
there's a lot of people come to the dharma with suffering maybe you just
have this general sense I don't know what to do with my life it's not quite
going the way I thought it was going to go this job that I had was a great job
it was a great job it felt I felt like you know I wouldn't be able to get a better job
probably but somehow even though I had reached a
enviable position I felt like yeah something's not quite right something's
not quite right with my life is not going the way I thought it would even though I had I don't know did what I
thought I was supposed to do right so Many of us are bringing this um
some emotional discomfort or some uncomfortable emotions with us and part
of the reason why we find our ways to practice and we might have this belief that okay if I just practice hard enough
or um then all emotions will just go away i know I secretly had that idea that they
would uh somehow I would be alleviated from these pesky emotions yeah turns out it doesn't work
that way just like the scientists turn out to be humans that meditation and Buddhist practice turns out to be filled
with humans notably ourselves and others but we could say that with
Buddhist practice like this idea of freedom peace well-being awakening
liberation whichever words relate to you which are meaningful for you we could
say that awakening to emotions is to actually feel
them and not have them be a problem to feel them to nothing less and
nothing more just to feel them and have the problems of them drained
out and maybe we might even have like our range of emotions
um can increase my years of practice I've experienced happiness and joy that I
didn't know was possible i've also experienced just terrible like despair
and darkness too but there's a way in which our practice
is designed to hold it to help us be with it to increase our capacity to be
with it so that we don't have to organize our life our social situations
in order to just avoid any uncomfortable emotions it's amazing how much energy we
put into okay well I feel a little bit uncomfortable in that situation so I'm not going to go to that gathering or I'm
not going to stretch myself into this new thing that I might learn or because
uh I might get embarrassed or so many ways in which we limit ourselves just so
that we can avoid some emotions what would it be like what
would your life be like if you weren't afraid of emotions like yeah okay i might be disappointed i might feel
frustrated but I'm going to do it anyway i might feel sad if this doesn't
turn out the way I want i'm going to meet it anyway my partner my co-worker the
person that I see at the coffee shop all of them might be having uh strong
emotions and sometimes we feel like we want to avoid people like that after you know there's been a death in the family
or something and we want to like I don't know what to say and so we avoid them
what would it be like to be fearless and be able to comfort others if comforting
was what was appropriate and needed that would be freedom that would
be freedom in our lives
so one way that we might think about this is that mindfulness being
um feeling the feelings is being present for our
emotions is a way that we can for ourselves allow maybe an evolving or
resolution or a movement or I like this word metabolism of our emotions allows
them to move because that's their nature often emotions can feel
stuck but there's a way in which they're stuck because the thoughts are like
ruminating around and around and around and around and around and around and around and around often is what's
happening but if we can just meet our emotions and I'll talk a little bit in a
moment about how to do that there's a way in which they can evolve and
transform and shift and change that is their nature it's not their nature to always
be the same and often if we are can meet it we
might see that it's maybe it's not just one big terrible emotion maybe it's a
collection of emotions sometimes this grief may have some sorrow a little bit
of fear in there maybe some disorientation or sense of
powerlessness and there's a way of which when we make the room for them these different ones like we can meet them and
care for them these individual ones and allow it to kind of be seen and
known and pass away arise be known and pass away
often with anger there's sadness underneath or fear underneath for
example or maybe we're not even sure what emotions are maybe we're like okay
there's some fluttering going on deep inside and it feels uncomfortable and I don't want to look at it and we just try
to ignore it or maybe we're not uh feel like we have a wide emotional
vocabulary that's okay Do can we just meet whatever it
is so maybe this way of meeting emotions is a way in which we can make friends
with them some of us are some people are
comfortable with emotions and have a rich emotional life that uh supports them and help
connects them with others some people are not so aware of their
emotional life and prefer it that way but they find that their life is kind of
flat and maybe feels uh stale and dry in
some kind of way maybe some people just have a lot of
resistance and fear about their emotional life don't really want to experience
them and I feel like in my life there's been different uh uh
seasons where I felt like you know I've had a lot of emotions i felt very emotional and times when not so much but
I felt I could feel them and and I would say certainly now I
like it's really been transformed i certainly there had this like well okay certain emotions are okay
to feel happiness well-being joy the sad ones the confusion ones the anger ones
not okay but I don't feel have that feeling anymore and this absolutely is
due to practice meditation practice so is there this way that we
can make friends with our emotional life however it is right
now this practice is not asking us to be somebody we're not it's not asking us to
completely be different than who we are so we start with whatever might be
arising for us now maybe we have this idea that
um we want to be friends with our emotional life which means can we offer
emotions we might consider them as energies maybe can we meet them with
acceptance and compassion and if it's difficult to do
that can we meet the resistance to meet the
emotion and then if it's difficult to do that instead we find ourselves doing this intellectualization and
rationalization and just thinking about things and not really feeling the I'm
going like this in the body because often emot I feel emotions in the body it used to be all exclusively in my head
but now it's in the body but we can just start with oh yeah okay
there's more just intellectualization and rationalization and uh a certain way
in which we actually aren't feeling emotions but maybe they're just some mental activity around with them
we can start with that and maybe just hang out there for a little bit
with the intellectualization and just allow that
to maybe it's some breadcrumbs to something else that's richer that's
deeper but there's a way that being in particular with difficult
emotions can be like getting into a pool of cool
water okay we'll put our toes in and maybe that's enough to begin with
there is no timetable we don't have to push ourselves force ourselves to do things in a
particular schedule and we put our toes in we put our feet
in our lower legs and when we feel comfortable we can
go deeper in on another time maybe there is a time when we feel like we can go all the way in and then
maybe sometime in which we go into this cool water and with under putting our
head under the water and there's this way in
which we recognize that like with this idea of like being underwater we just
recognize oh this emotion is just part of the energy of life it's not a problem
it's just what's being experienced right now so how do we do this this whole idea
of putting toes in the water like how do we do that so I'll talk about some practical
things here so some of this is like can be on the cushion or off the cushion in
your daily life or during meditation i'll start with some easy
things some obvious things posture of course the mind and body and
emotional life and everything is are connected and it's striking how you
notice how when I was talking about depression I was kind of like doing this with my posture because this is how it feels we often are kind of like slumpy
and collapsed into ourselves don't underestimate the impact
it can have to have an upright posture it's some it kind of it uh
communicates a certain amount of respect for ourselves for whatever emotion is
having and there's something about being upright that uh brings a little bit more
spaciousness and openness like literally like in the chest and the torso but just having a more upright
posture can be a tremendous support so just notice if you're feeling like whoa these emotions and sometimes we want to
like get into a fetal position or something like this when it feels terrible if possible can you be in an
upright posture if possible if your body allows you to not use a back rest but to
sit up with your own own you know your own under your
being supported by yourself sometimes on retreat i know
I've done this sitting upright posture with tears coming down but sitting here and there's something like okay sadness
is happening but it's not like the end of the world just it's just tears and
it's just sadness this is what it means to be a human all of us have loss all of us have
sadness so one posture maybe I'll sprinkle something in
here too maybe even If posture doesn't work feel your feet on the ground get like grounded feel like connected to the
earth in some kind of way this can be a tremendous support feel maybe what your hands are touching just you know
something tangible because the mind is wanting to spin out in
stories and we're trying to just like disrupt the momentum and just be here
now because the stories are elsewhere and that's not what's actually happening
what's in the mind so the hand
placement also can be something I said about what the hand is touching but sometimes it can be like you to put your
hand on your chest like oh my gosh this is hard but there's a way you know to
sit upright and have your hand on your chest is a way to acknowledge the
difficulty but it's also like a gesture of care and respect for yourself instead
of this I know trying to hide or something or maybe there's in the belly
you just like wow you know maybe some
breathing so that's the next thing the breath it can be that uh you know with
mindfulness we're just noticing what the breath is doing but if we feel like there's a lot of emotions whether we're
meditating or just out in daily life the breath can be a tremendous support and
one way is just to in a subtle way not a big giant exaggerated way but just to
extend the exhale a little head just be a normal inhale but extend
the exhale a little bit this works with the parasympathetic nervous system just helps our physiology our nervous system
just to calm down so that we feel a little bit
more less frantic maybe or less uh fearful maybe or this way of just like
okay I can be here i can be here with this
so is there this way that then we can maybe explore the physical
sensations this way that as I said emotions can be
experienced in the physical body and letting the the mind is going
to protest it won't it will not want to do this but can you just be with the
physical experience sad sadness for example pressure around
the eyes this heaviness in the shoulders maybe there's this feeling of wanting uh
to collapse and just to be with the physical
sensations as best you can and most likely what will happen is you'll be with a physical sensation and then the
mind is going to want to tell you why you really shouldn't be doing that you got to think more about this terrible awful thing and then you just come back
to the physical sensation and then the mind is going to pull you away just come back to the body the mind's going to
pull you away come back to the body exactly like we do with meditation of coming back to the breath again it
doesn't matter how many times we do the same thing in a kind gentle way just coming back to the bodily
sensations and then there's a way in which this bodily sensations if we can
be with them as best we can if you feel like whoa I can't do
that it's just too much then be with your posture as best you can if this
just feels like whoa I can't do that do something else go outside be with
nature talk to a friend call somebody do something like this we we don't want to
get into overwhelm but is there a way that we can just start to put our toes in the water
or our foot in the water or our lower body in the
water there's this way that to be with the physical sensations
a way there's a way to that we can trust the like the contact with the
emotion and kind of maybe trust that it knows the emotion knows how long to be
there or maybe there's this way to recognize
that emotions are a natural process we might say that they have
their own I don't know if it's makes sense to say they have their own intelligence but
can there be a way in which we can trust that we don't have to fix it that moment
we so often want to just fix it we turn it into a big giant problem and we turn
it into a nail then we come along with our hammer and trying to hammer it but can we allow it to be there and
to be felt as best we can and allow it
to transform itself we are not doing the transforming we are not the one that are
making it change we're just making the space we're creating the conditions in which it will naturally do what it does
what emotions do i am not promising any particular timeline i am not promising
any miraculous cure i am promising this is a way
forward if we work with this as best we can without any particular demand that
emotions be done at a particular time or only certain emotions be
expressed there's something that happens when we meet them in this way our confidence grows and our capacity to be
with them grows and it gets easier and easier and easier and
easier the more we do this as best we can it will be
uncomfortable can that be okay can that be okay to be have some
discomfort to feel uncomfortable this is a way to have greater freedom in
life not only for ourselves but so that we can support and care for others not
to be afraid of their emotions this is a way in which our practice can be a benefit to the world
maybe in some tiny way maybe in a giant way
so emotions no one can tell you how to feel them or what to do with
them but is there a way that we
can practice to find the freedom with them and learn to make the
medicine out of our emotional life for ourselves and for others
maybe I'll end just by with a simple simple thing here a lot of words I said
but really the physical body is really a
support for emotions we so much want to think our way through them
if you could think your way through them you would have done it already because how much rumination
thinking do we do about our emotions it doesn't work we have to actually experience them
in the body it turns out so with that I think I'll end and
I'll open it up to see if there are some questions or comments thank you
does anybody have some questions or
comments nobody is emotional about emotions this is good
maybe this felt like oh his old hat I knew all this
well Diane I'll say something thank you for your talk yes and I was thinking about outrage back in the 1980s I had
sat a retreat with um James Hillman and he talked about how people
were this this was a retreat for men how many men were um instead of having
outrage were having enrage oh so they had they saw things that they didn't
like in the world but it was all being going inside and it wasn't being
expressed as as action in the world
so that was I mean so sometimes when I hear the word outrage I always think well am I more of an outrage or an
inra or is there some skillful way to work with both of those thank you thank
you i never heard this expression enrage and I never thought about this outrage enrage has the word rage in
there thank you Jim it's fantastic in the 80s in outrage or they weren't
expressing their outrage it's always causing the inra yeah well James Hman was talking about how people would have
this energy about wanting to respond to the world but they would bring it with
them into the therapist's office and it would all get processed in the therapist's office and nothing would
happen out in the world so he was he was actually
um advocating for people to do something constructive with that energy
yeah yeah and emotions can really be a fuel for uh energy it's we might even say it's a type of energy that uh can be
a fuel for action in the world great thank you Jim thank
you anybody else have a comment or question
just a couple days ago I was talking to someone about this idea of outrage
and he said "My thought is we need a new bumper
sticker." And it says "Um if you weren't outraged you might
actually be able to do something about it." Very nice
so I don't know it was food for thought yeah yeah yeah thank
you yeah people are busy being outraged and they're outraged if you're not
outraged and you're Yeah yeah yeah that would be
great okay so thank you all thank you for your attention and I'm wishing you a
wonderful rest of the evening and safe travels home thank
you and if you like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me otherwise I'll see you next week