so hello and welcome and as we now
approach entering into samadei to appreciate that there starts
to be a turning to be really here present as if
here is a home here is our nest in which to settle
into that here is a really good place to be and so to begin
today with assuming a meditation posture
And in this posture of meditation to
appreciate doing nothing for a few
moments in the doing nothing of being able to put
aside the agendas the things we feel we have to do even putting
aside doing meditation just doing nothing
doing nothing in the posture of meditation as if it's a homecoming here
now where meditation the posture is a nest that holds everything about
you what's wonderful and what's difficult it all has space just to
be in a situation where it doesn't have to do anything about it at
first so beginning a meditation is turning away from the
usual activity of doing of accomplishing getting away
And then gently taking a few deeper inhales and let the
exhale take care of itself let the exhale just release the body the tensions
where a deeper inhale is a kind of a
clear intention to be here
now and the exhale allows there to be a softening
relaxing here and
now and then to let your breathing return to normal
and the inhale can be
a opening awakening into the
body the breathing body and the exhale a softening a settling
the inhale can be a time to clear the
mind and the exhale a time to soften the tensions of the mind
breathing in breathing out
and to come into the approach stage of meditation of
samadei is to feel the call feel the
welcome into something that feels pleasant a sense of well-being
even if there's things about your experience now which is uncomfortable pain emotional pain
anything it's okay but to feel more
deeply in this meditation posture in the
settling is there a way to give yourself over
to the pleasant sensations of breathing wherever they might
occur however brief the pleasantness is the goodness of breathing the
relaxing of
breathing or a sense of well-being that's broad through the body maybe very
faint within which the experience of
breathing occurs
putting aside the usual way of thinking
about having sensual pleasures sensual desires
even in meditation for something that is
deeper a deeper sense of at homeness a deeper sense of
well-being maybe at the core of where you are
maybe it's associated with a certain
relief for these minutes to not be involved in the usual preoccupations
with any kind of sensual pleasure that the mind is able to put
those aside is
good in favor of turning towards a
depth of contentment a depth of wholeness a depth
of being nested here maybe at the grounding place the
settling place of
breathing staying close to the entire inhale the entire exhale
as if that is the thread that's keeping
you gently connecting to a deeper place that feels
wholesome good just being
here just being present
a wholesome sense of well-being that maybe spreads a sense of
health goodness throughout your body
as if the rhythm of breathing is the massage is the
kneading of the dough of meditation
there comes a time in meditation when rather than focusing on
thoughts instead Focusing on the thoughts that are about our
experience about things the focus
switches to the direct experience here in this
body as if awareness arises out of the
body arising with The inhale with the
exhale with a delight of having the mind no longer
centered on thoughts that are about
things that objectify
I delight in being centered in the body with the subjective
experience
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a few moments to feel in your body and
mind any shift that's happened for you through the
meditation are you a little calmer more settled
are there any feelings of
well-being however subtle that are in your body now that
were not there
before do you feel if there's been a
reorientation from
preoccupation to being centered in your body
whatever beneficial change has happened over the
course of the sitting that shift is important and
valuable to recognize so that we can feel the
shifts that support entering samadei
and so we can appreciate how we are and how it might support us in going
into the world how would you stay close to the
sense of well-being with the ringing of the bell
to end the sitting listening to the little talk that I'll
give and getting up to begin your day or continue your
day with some reference point some reference to this shift that's happened
in meditation a shift in understanding or
orientation and may it be a shift
that heightens our care our
awareness of the well-being of
others may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may we have confidence that the people we encounter
today can in fact be happy safe
peaceful free at least in our presence with how we are
with them
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this series on samadei and Today
uh also marks the maybe the 5year anniversary of beginning these uh YouTube mornings
together some of you have been along for the whole ride for five years and I'm
very grateful for all of you who come and and uh I have some confidence that
uh that the goodness of our time together
spreads from you into the world so this kind of network of of radi radiating
network of bringing good to the world is uh is a great thing to be part of and um
thank you for these five years so uh samadei this week we're going
to kind of cover the territory more of the approach called access concentration
usually in English but um uh the the stage of approach approaching somebody
and this is when uh it's relatively easy to stay in the present moment if we lose
the present moment it's almost like it's obvious it's easy to come back or there's a almost a
a call inside to come back be here and um and uh there starts to be a
shift of orientation where uh the orientation is
towards the goodness of meditation the joy the happiness the well-being of
meditation or of concentration of really staying present over the mind not
wandering not being scattered not being caught by other things
really be here and it's a kind of almost a little bit of a quantum shift like okay now we're here
um and uh and uh it is a a reorientation
of some kind and with that reorientation it becomes a a form of joy a form of
delight or this is good and um and uh so uh in the in the classic
teachings about going into samadei going into Janna's um there's the the penultimate activity
that is done is to learn to uh let go of the
hindrances and uh and these are the we've talked about this before but here
the five hindrances are very subtle they can be very big forces in the mind huge
and and that can be very destructive for people but in deeper meditation it's
that we're getting into the kind of the subtle subtlety of it how easy it is to
kind of be drift off into thoughts concerns of sensual pleasure easy is to
get involved with movements of um of aversion how easy it is to move into uh
getting kind of uh sloth and torper rigid and resistant the subtlest
versions of um restlessness and regrets
the subtlest versions of uh uncertainty like what am I doing here
and so uh and it's somehow settling those and appreciating the goodness the
rightness the pleasure the the well-being of not having the mind caught
in those kinds of concerns and I think of this as a switch a shift from
objectifying thoughts to a subjective feeling and what I mean by objectifying
thoughts is that to when we're caught in s desires for sensual desires sensual
pleasures they usually go with thoughts about the the experience of sensual
pleasure about the object of sensual pleasure same thing with aversion there's no aversion without something
we're averting pushing against wanting to go away and that involves engaging
the thinking mind where that whatever we have aversion for or desire for is now
an object of the thinking mind and to the we're not strong it
keeps us disconnected from ourselves there's an we're no longer present for the deeper subjective experience of
what's actually the feeling of being alive the vitality of being here
and so the shift and now it's really begin happening deeper and deeper in as
we approach is that we're no longer satisfied content to be objectifying to
be caught in thoughts that are about the world about desires about
diversions and so there's a shift to trusting or resting in the subjective
experience uh so and with the breathing for example
it's the deep subjective experience of the breathing that we linger with we stay with and uh to give a little sense
of what the subject experience is like how directly almost sematic it is it's
kind of like if you take two fing two fingers your thumb and your pointing finger and press them together
um you'll feel some some sensations maybe of pressure maybe heat maybe
firmness something there some s sensations are there those sensations you feel as you
press your fingers together uh occur together with sensing them if
we didn't have the capacity to sense to feel we wouldn't know that there was
pressure and and the sensing of the pressure or and
the uh the sensation of pressure are one and the same you can't really separate
them linguistically we can say there's a sensation is a thing out there that
we're aware of something that the sensation but uh but uh in order to
sense the sensations that's not out there that's in the fingers and and
so and so the sensing and the sensation together make up the subjective
experience now I can be objectifying it by saying I'm not having the right kind
of feeling of pressure there's a particular right way of doing this and I'm not quite getting what the sensation
is supposed to be it's supposed to be maybe harder or softer or more pointed or more spread out and um and and this
makes me think about you know I wonder why why is Gil doing this as an exercise it could be doing it with some really
pleasant delightful sensations of the body that would be the way to get my attention those thoughts are in the
objectifying world the subjective world here is the
place where sensing and sensations occur together and so with the breathing it's
those sensations of breathing that are known where this they are being
sensed where the awareness is the attention is and so to stay right there
in that subjective world of sensing and sensations and as we stay there the
subjective experience can grow because there's a goodness there's a sweetness
there's a well-being that can arise that is not the
well-being that comes from physical pleasure that we know if we you know sensual pleasure and so
there's a shift of orient orientation in the approach stage from being concerned
interested enamored with the objectifying thinking mind and and
instead feeling like we're at home in this is where it's good it feels delightful to be here in the subjective
experience where sensing and sensation occur together and uh and that subjective
experience can be quite broad through the body there could be a tingling a warmth a vibration a flow a opening a
lightness that happens even as we stay very close to the inhale and exhale
maybe counting them so really stay right there with them and um but the idea is
not to be in the control tower tightly focused but rather to
be relaxing into the subjective experience letting go into it trusting
it uh thinking of that subjective experience of breathing is kind of like
the nest the resting place the grounding place for our sense of being in our life
and so the Buddha talks about how as we make this shift from the hindrance of
sensual desire uh to this deeper subjective experience
just that feels good it can feel like a relief it can feel like um kind of a
happiness or contentment that now we know something that's more satisfying this is good and uh it's less exhausting
it's less tiring thought thinking about sensual desire is exhausting there's the
mind is kind of restless kind of forceful kind of agitated and um and uh
you sometimes with a contraction and tightness in the mind the resting in the
subjective experience allows the mind to soften to open the the the control tower
no longer has to work so much it can just settle back and allow for the
subjective experience to inform it to arrive to be there and um and it there
can be a great sense of well-being in the approach
stage of practice uh this is where you're allowed or encouraged to start
feeling the well-being that's there in meditation uh however subtle it is
to recognize it and and trust it allow it to be there there's something about
giving our attention giving awareness making room for what is wholesome that lets the
wholesome grow and the wholesome gives us a different subjective way of being
with everything in our life i know that our lives are difficult
i know that there's all kinds of difficult emotions sensations in the body that can that can happen but as we
get into this approach stage um we've learned how to be mindful of
them how to relate to these difficulties in a good way through mindfulness practice and it's okay to recognize them
allow them to be there on the edges it's it feels now it feels in this approach
stage it feels just right to open to the deeper feelings of well-being however
subtle they are and so the breathing into the sweetness breathing with the
beauty with the subtleness with the contentment this is the work of the
approach stage but maybe I shouldn't use the word work some people think of it as
play some People think of it as an act of love love making some people think of
it as uh nurturing and caring and um
um uh nourishing ourselves the the deeper experience of
this kind of joy sometimes is because of a word play in Pali um where pity in
Pali also means to drink we're we're in in invite we're drinking the goodness
we're drinking the wholesome so for today uh as part of this ability
to make a shift orientation I'd encourage you to um um
spend a day kind of look feeling the difference between the
objectifying world of thoughts especially thoughts of sensual desire whether it's food or sex or some other
pleasant wonderful experience that uh the objectifying that living the
thoughts of that versus deeply the subjective experience
the metaphor that I have for this is that uh a person can be on a hot day or
cold day sitting at the edge of a beautiful lake and um and thinking about you know
all kinds of sensual pleasures that would be wonderful to have daydreaming and wishing being angry for not having
them and and preoccupied by difficult it is to have this sensual desires and
right there in front of the person is this delightful lake pond on a hot day
it feels so refreshing to go into it on a cold day it's maybe hot hot pools it's
so good to go into it and as soon as we go into it what brings a tremendous
sense of ah relief joy happiness is the subjective experience and it's not just
simply the subjective experience of being on the wonderful water it's also
the subjective experience of putting to rest putting aside all those
objectifying thoughts on the control tower ah this is good so study
that and uh during the day the objectifying mind versus object
subjective mind and maybe you're can step into the lake uh more often through
the day than you realize thank you