welcome everyone is I'm taking a lot of uh joy out of reading your chat messages
from all over thank you so much and Welcome to our week of practicing
supports for samadi as well as samadi uh and doing a little bit more
independent practice um working with the instructions that we've received from
Gil so yesterday I shared the wisdom from the suta whatever one keeps
pursuing with one's thinking and pondering that becomes the inclination
of one's awareness and the invitation was to see
how you use your attention throughout the day and to understand what supports
Sama and perhaps some of the things that lead to a distracted mind or a a mind
that has more difficulty settling and all of this was also part
of an invitation to strengthen both samadi and Sati Sati mindfulness
strengthening that during the day by coming back and to it as often as you
remember noticing any hindrances that are happening in sitting practice and in
daily life and meeting them with compassion
the more we see them the more we disentangle from them because just by seeing them we're already taking one
step towards Freedom away from dissatisfaction stress and
suffering so there was also the experiment yesterday to
visit for just a few minutes at a time perhaps throughout the day that place of
deep Stillness and to join a second sitting or to practice in a second sitting on your
own so we're dedicating the week or I'm dedicating the week to helping support
what helps us with somadi discovering what supports us with Sade and what stands in the
way so today again we'll continue to cultivate it in the way that Gil's been
teaching it extending the time that we spend uh in
this morning sitting by just a few minutes and we'll do the same technique
if it works for you well to count the breath very softly in the background the
primary focus is on the sensations of breathing and staying with being present
with the entire breath from the very beginning through the entire inhalation
maybe a little pause if it's there between the inhalation and the
exhalation and following the entire exhalation beginning and returning
perhaps in a place deep within of Stillness and then very softly in the
background see how softly it can work for you using counting so Gil introduced
several different types of counting and he encouraged this week that we try
counting the breath from 1 to 10 the breaths from 1 to 10 and that could be
each whole breath as one two Etc or it
could be if you need more uh stimulation to maintain mindfulness one with the in
breath two with the out breath three with the INB breath four with the out breath so with that Brief Review there
are lots of different ways to count and whichever one you find that works for you settle in with it commit to it and
work with it throughout the practice could just be one and with the next breath one so
using the method that you find most helpful so we'll settle into meditation
here
and allowing yourself to settle in
gradually perhaps taking several long
slow deep breaths
letting the breathing return to normal
naturally and taking in In This Moment how you are in the mind the heart the
body what here right
now noticing if there's any mentally or physically that could be
relaxed In This Moment consciously relaxing
it and if there are areas of preoccupation or tightness that cannot be
relaxed it can be help helpful to soften around
that and to appreciate it's here just as it is with some kindness
for what's
here if there's some tightness perhaps deliberately releasing it with
the out breath
however you are in this moment is simply showing you things as
they have come to be there's no right or wrong way to be in meditation
we can greet all experience in this
meditation as we would greet a very dear friend
recognizing our friend with kindness relaxing and listening to them
with kind attention experience is a friend in
meditation simply showing you things as they have come to be
perhaps beginning with a few minutes of meta this practice of sending wishes of
Good Will of kindness or friendliness and doing this in a way
that is supportive for you I'll offer some
phrases and you can silently repeat those in your mind or if it's more conducive for you
to Simply radiate the feeling of Goodwill from your heart and
mind letting the phrases Fade Into the background whatever
way of coming to this that feels right to
you perhaps [Music] Beginning by allowing yourself to
acknowledge the goodness the whole wholesomeness of your
intention for meditating the goodness of your
intention for developing
samadi and Ne recognizing those good
intentions sending wishes of support for yourself and for those here
in this meditation may we be
well and
healthy really allowing that to fill your heart fill your mind
may we be free from inner and outer harm safe
may we be happy contented in the
practice contented with what we're discovering about
ourselves but mostly about things as they have come to
be may we practice with ease
as you take these in and radiate them
outwards allowing yourself to come into more silence more Stillness
rely centering on that very still Place
deep within perhaps
and turning attention towards the experience of
breathing as the inhalation arises from
Stillness following it as it comes into the body
present for any tiny pause and then the
exhalation following it as it leaves the body
as we're feeling the expansion and
contraction the rise and fall perhaps beginning in the
background very quietly counting the
breath leaving the counting in the background and the experience of breathing the
sensations of breathing in the foreground of
awareness
e
e e
what
if the Mind drifts away sending some some
kindness some understanding for the Natural Way human
Minds drift and gently with good
will bringing awareness to where the mind has drifted for just a few
moments and then gradually turning awareness to this sensations of
breathing with a light touch and resuming counting in the
background in whatever way supports maintaining
wearen sticking with it as soft noting in the
background while keeping the sensations of breathing in the
foreground
as we come to the end of the meditation extending some
appreciation allowing yourself to feel a little appreciation for any
amount of time time that awareness was settled
stable appreciation for how awareness was able to return
to attention to the breathing again and
again and radiating the benefit of this
practice to everyone around you everyone your life
touches those you know and those you don't
know may all beings be healthy and well
may all beings be free of harm be
safe the all beings be peaceful
May everyone without exception be free of suffering
e
so as we've been practicing an integral part of this
practice of samade are these Wellings up of Good Will
compassion appreciation and equinity Tanis biku wrote this
translation a part that I'll read to you of one of
the numerical discourses of the Buddha called the samadi sutta subtitled
immeasurable concentration wise and mindful you
should develop immeasurable concentration that is concentration
based on immeasurable Goodwill compassion appreciation or equinity
so these four qualities of heart good will compassion appreciative
joy and equinity are often called the immeasurables they are also called the
Brahma viharas which or Brahma vihara which translates
as Divine abodes in other words really beautiful Elevated Places to hang out
ment and you know with the heart and body and mind um and we could consider them
beautiful qualities of mind um this reference to
immeasurables means that as we practice them regularly they grow and grow to the
point where they're capable of encompassing all beings they're boundless
so maybe many of you have already had experience of the way that good willll
compassion appreciation and equinity tend to grow the more you practice and
maybe you've even noticed them welling up spontaneously at times this is one of the beautiful things that happens with
continuity of mindfulness it's often one of the gifts of being on Retreat is just
out of nowhere feeling the heart fill with kindness or with
compassion so these Brahma vihara support the calm and peace the St
stability the settledness that help Som to become
stronger so we can apply the brah vihara during the cultiv a of
samade in both in formal sitting and also we can apply it in daily life
certainly so one invitation today would be to see what it might be
like to greet everything that arrives with one of these prah
vihara perhaps uh treating everything as though it were a gift from the Buddha a
teaching from the Buddha so you could ask yourself in any particular moment that stands out or
that when uh mindfulness comes back to mind what might it be like in this
moment to greet this experience as if it were a dear friend sometimes our friends call for
just a general they bring forth a general feeling of Goodwill so what might be like to agree this as with
Goodwill sometimes friends are in trouble and we greet them with compassion so there may be moments that
arise that could be greeted with compassion of course we take joy in the
things that our friends uh have in their lives that bring them happiness or a good fortune
so you might greet some experiences with that appreciative joy and then there are
times when what a friend is going through pulls us so hard that we need to
find our own balance or keep our own balance some imity is called
for so we can ask ourselves um what might good will or kindness or
friendliness teach us today about
ourselves about practicing in daily life and what might
compassion help us understand that might be perplexing at this moment
what might it be like to greet certain things with appreciation so for example
something unpleasant arises or something you don't like what might it like what
might it be like to have some appreciation for it as a teaching as something we need to
learn or as one of these moments that has arrived just things as they are in this
moment or as they have come to be and what might we learn
about equinity or balance being an ally at times that feel
tumultuous what can we learn today about freedom from
dissatisfaction freedom from stress freedom from
suffering so practicing in this way throughout the day with whatever arises
with hindrances as they arise may bring further stability to
samade and again uh an invitation today is to find your way through both the
difficult places that arise not to pave over them with this practice because if
you do that if you just try to substitute paying attention to breathing
for some difficulty that you know is going on uh there's a way in which that
actually stands in the way of somat so if something tough is
happening noticing it so taking a pause meeting it as a friend understanding it listening to it
and if something beautiful arises greeting it as a
friend so the invitation today is is again to come back to mindfulness as
often as you can during the day in addition to greeting things with the as if they were dear friends with Brahma
vihara and then uh as I did each as I will do each day this week I'll offer a
silent sitting this afternoon for 20 minutes on zoom and you can find the
zoom link and the uh password that you'll need on the IMC calendar so you're
welcome to join that or if that's not a good time for you or you just prefer to practice on
your own maybe consider finding another piece of time during the day when you
can practice and also coming back to this practice noticing a still place or
the calm noticing the breath here and there throughout the day for even just a
few minutes it all counts so may this practice bring all of us
greater and greater stability subtleness
presence and may that radiate out from us and support everyone else in our
lives so that everyone feels that calm that peace that collectiveness of mind
the mind that can be with everything and anything name that's happening right
now may we help those around us in this way may all beings be
free thank you