good morning everyone welcome here this
morning um my wife read me um headlines from a news site that
she was reading and the headline said something
like uh to have a happy life don't be
frightened stop being frightened that sounds nice
and but I also thought that's great that that's maybe what my topic is
today because that topic is uh a very buddhistic topic and it's the topic of
refuge and um so those of you who don't know much about Buddhism it'll become clear why you know how Central it is and
refuge is and the idea is to um often we talk about going to Refuge or going in
Refuge going to some place that's safe or some place that's protected and
um and uh and that can be both inspiring to some people to know there can be
safety to be had in this dangerous world world we live in and for some people it
could seem kind of offputting because it seems like we're it's withdrawing it's pulling back into some place that we're
going to be all safe and comfortable and not really in the world how it
is so I'll tell you um a story from some years
ago um that just delighted me when I understood what was going on kind
of got all turned on a moment so I uh I was in a
training and um we invited a trainer to come and uh as a way of beginning our
time together the trainer said take out a piece of paper and pen and write down uh
what do you need to feel safe here and um and I thought this is okay
this is good to cre safety and if we have safety then we could all share and be together nicely and and I kind of
imagined we would share what we had written and that would create community and safety in itself or something like
that so everyone was very Earnest and was writing away what they needed for
safety and then uh she said okay and so then everyone came back and was sitting
there and ready for the next thing and she says she said okay now you bring
that with you if you need safety you bring that
with you that very thing so she kind of turned it around in the way that no one expected it and as you turned it around
kind of to make each person responsible for themselves to create the safety that they would have
there now this also could be inspiring and it could also be off-putting because there are real
dangers in the world and what now now I'm responsible I've been people have been dumping on me forever and now I'm
supposed to be the one and um
so but there is a refuge there 's a place to find protection and safety that
is not withdrawing from the world but actually allows us to be in the world more fully and it's a little bit like
and maybe it's a little bit too pedestrian of a metaphor but um most of us most of you
are here I think great majority of you in order to come here today you probably
put on shoes and putting on your shoes you're
protecting your feet so it's a little bit easier to walk around and get here by having protected feet safe feet it's
actually easier to go where you want to go in this world and we don't say we're you you
we're take we're giving Refuge protection to our feet and it's worried like well now you're you're disappearing
you're not available to us you you're you're disconnecting from the world you know this is really a problem these
Buddhists who wear shoes
uh no it's uh it actually allows us to step into the world more freely and more
available for World more connected rather than going on so gingerly and and
so it's the same way with this Refuge this Refuge that Buddhists
discover that to have that Refuge actually allows us to go into the world better and Fuller it's not a
withdrawal and um so uh the the usually there's
considered to be three refuges and these are called the Buddha
the Dharma and the S so the Buddha is the Exemplar and the founder of Buddhism
Exemplar of what's possible he's more important that he's the Exemplar than it is he is the
founder of Buddhism he's the example of how thoroughly a person can become happy
and free there's Dharma which are his
teachings for sure that point to that possibility but also the underlying kind
of patterns of life that we tap into in order to find our inspiration in order
to find our safety and then there's a sa which is the community of
practitioners especially the community of practitioners who have really tasted the freedom that Buddhism is about but
it's so it could be any of our fellow practitioners and um and then the um the
way that it's usually chanted it's actually one of the core rituals of Buddhism where people will chant
[Music]
um and it goes on and uh the gami the end is a literal meaning means to
walk and um buddham is Buddha and saranam sarana is
refuge and with the way the grammar is it's actually you have fair amount of
choice about how you put it together grammatically the most common perhaps in
English is I go for Refuge to the Buddha
but uh what I'd like to offer today is something different I walk in Refuge together with
the Buddha I walk in Refuge with the Dharma
I walk in Refuge with the S and the word walk is kind of a
metaphor for moving through life um when just saying it in my mind I
come come um reminded of a Native American religious idea that is to walk
in Beauty it's inspiring and for Buddhists we say walk in
refuge and we have company for that process we have companionship we're not
doing it alone their support and so we walk in Refuge with
the example of the Buddha with the guidance of the Buddha with the the way
uh the way leading the Buddha provided we go for Refuge with the
Dharma we go we go we walk in this world with a support with a companionship of
these teachings and then with the community and this idea of walking is
something that each person needs to do themselves so bring your own safety
bring your own Refuge you have to do something you it's not like just this going for Refuge just not sitting you
know on your couch it's looking at wait waiting for something to protect you and like I'll be fine if I just hold on
tight to these things it does require stepping into the world it does require
living a life A Life That's dangerous to some degree a life that has its
challenges a life where maybe the biggest challenge is you yourself to yourself and so to step into that and
see it to hold it to be with it to walk in this
world and so that comes to something that seldom talk about in Buddhism and
there is a fourth Refuge that the Buddha taught the Buddha never actually told
anyone that they were supposed to engage the Buddha Dharma as The
Refuge the one thing he did say in terms of Refuge he said make yourself a refuge
and so the fourth Refuge is yourself and so that goes back again you
know to be safe bring it with you or to save maybe nicer uh we have to find
something it's up to us to find a way of being in the world that we create we
make a refuge and eventually as we make ourselves a refuge we make ourselves a
refuge for others we we become someone who's safe for others we makes ourselves
someone that we then accompanying and supporting others in their deep process
of becoming free becoming themselves and um so there are three
different kind of main meanings that this walking in
Refuge uh implies it implies an
understanding something that provides meaning gives meaning to our life and
understanding to our life it implies um something that is
motivating something that we can commit ourselves to or be devoted
to and it implies some form of inspiration something that's heartfelt
some kind of uh the classic language in the tradition is some kind of some kind of
gladness or joy that uh bubbles up from the
inside so those are the three kind of elements of what means to walk in
refuge and so it there there's an understanding we come to so it's not magical thinking oh if I just trust just
trust the Buddha without knowing what you're doing the idea is you have to understand something and that
understanding doesn't come from reading books it doesn't come from listening to
my talk the real it might it might be somehow a byproduct of it these things but the
real understanding comes from yourself you begin seeing and experiencing for
yourself uh uh you know something profound something very
meaningful and for different people this can be different things I don't want to be very careful I don't uh only give one
example or just give it leave you an impression there's only one thing I can mean for some people it's seeing
dramatically clearly how they are contributing to their own
suffering by what they're clinging to attached to what they're resisting what they're fighting what they're rebelling
against what they are running away from uh and um it's a whole slew of
things and to see that so clearly wow I thought it was the world that was doing
it but I'm contributing to this in the way and lo and behold I see that it's
possible it's difficult I might be I'm inspired I'm
motivated I know it's possible to chip away at this way in which I'm
contributing to my suffering even if it takes me a
lifetime that's how I want to walk I want to move through this life engage in
this life so I stay close enough attentative
enough to my inner life so I begin chipping away at how I keep adding
to my suffering adding to my challenges how I keep making it worse for
myself and so the inspiration there might be the understanding there is
maybe the motivation is encapsulated by the expression I won't make it
worse no matter what's going on I'm not going to make it worse and for some
people that's maybe a really great and great Poss
seems like that's at least that's possible I can't make it better that's too high a bar that's that
just seems too much to make it better but at least I'll stop making it worse that's how I'll walk through this
world and we'll chip away at it for other people it is something
better that they discover through this practice and um and I was trying and
thinking about this talk I was trying to remember for me what words would I use to describe what I discovered because
there was something positive that I found that really changed my direction of my life through this
practice and um and I I couldn't quite settle on one word when I was younger I
used the word integrity for it but not an ethical Integrity it was more of a sense of feeling whole like all of
myself was there I felt complete and I had never felt that way in my really in
my life in this regular way I started to be awakened through my
meditation and it wasn't that I was n less neurotic or less troubled or my Minds
got quieter because I used to think a lot but there was something about the
the being present for it that something felt complete something felt like I'm I'm including it all here and this
inclusion of all of who I am wors and all that just created a sense of Health
a sense of well-being a sense of healing or something it might have been a feeling
of peace I felt more peaceful at ease I might have been more um feeling at home
here in this being and this world there were variety things I was starting to feel through my meditation
practice and that became important enough for me that it kind of turned my
whole life in a New Direction and at first it was uh just a small turn of the
ocean liner but then slowly it got bigger and bigger turn and that was I
want to now have this whatever I was discovering in meditation this is so important this has so much value so it
feels like nothing else is richer or or true this way of being at least for me
as I walk through the world I want to walk through the world with this way of being because this seems
right and um now I want to find out how to do that in the world I want to find
out how to be working outside of meditation how can I have what I have in meditation how can I have this in my
daily life and that became a multi-year process and I made step by step I went
deeper into Buddhism not to get more out of Buddhism or be more buddhistic but I
wanted to answer this Quest I had which is how do I live from this place of at
homeness or completeness or peace or Integrity that I was feeling can may
live this way in my whole life because that seemed valuable and
important and so I had an understanding which is part of Refuge
that it was possible to live a different way it was a possible to live a way that
was settled at ease at peace I was motivated to do so Not only
was I motivated I was committed but the commitment was not
like hard and fast I didn't even know I was committed it was like this you know this
is what I'm doing I mean I it wasn't even deci I I I didn't even have those words in my mind I'm saying this in
retrospect looking back at my life when I was my early 20s that yes that's what
I was dedicated to this is what I was going to do and um and it it was
heartfelt there was an inspiration to do it it just felt so good and in in fact the truth was that
both of these two things positive and negative motivated me I could see the
more I felt better how I was making it worse for myself and so I was inspired not to make
it worse and and I could see what this
better way of being was and I wanted to stay close to it and um and this and and it wasn't
just hedonistic it wasn't just selfish to feel you know just better and not
feel worse it had a much deeper kind of feeling of rightness because because it
was almost like this is what allowed me to be stop being selfish this allowed me
to stop being self preoccupied and caught my my neurosis and it was clear
that what was being born in this process was uh a greater sense of community a
greater sense of compassion a greater sense of care for the world around me
that I didn't have before I started this process so for me the process these
three different aspects of Refuge you know very alive it involved an
understanding and for some people you know it's related to the topic I talked about last week the four noble truths
for some people that's make encapsulates it beautifully for them that this new
understanding and it encompassed the motivation and it encompassed something
that was felt heartfelt or in or an inspiration that
oh this this is like makes me happy this seems right this feels good that doesn't mean that there was
clear sailing for me and I just kind of like just you
know um I had a lot of ups and downs a lot of challenges as I went through this
practice but I never doubted it and so that's was The Refuge I walked
in Refuge ref I walked in refuge in the practice in refuge in myself that I was
going to do it because I kind of could see that what this is about I can't
contract it out for someone else to do it for me I had to do it I had to show up I had
to show up every day in some ways you know every minute to show up for this
life and then and then I had to um
um you know keep walking the walk keep walking the walk keep doing it
keep finding it keep discovering it here and now and so this idea of so then
going in Refuge walking in Refuge means that we're accompanied we're surrounded
we're we're filled by um something that's profoundly important something
that's invaluable and there stay close to that to be reminded of that so when I was in
my 20s for a while actually I was living in a place where they had mananita
berries and I picked all these dry berries and and then I very went to the
shop and clearly and and kind of flattened out little sides of
them so I could drill a hole through them and then I made um Mala beads from
them so made my own kind of you know you know little thing I carried on my arm
for a while and um and it wasn't because I was showing off that I was a
Buddhist it there was they were kind of they were kind of big and long you know like many beads uh it was kind of
awkward and so when I I I was going to do anything I had to I was always being reminded I was this awkward thing it's
you know bracelet kind of thing was there and so so it was reminding me of Refuge reminding me of the practice
because I needed help sometimes to remind oh okay remember remember and sometimes I would go through and you
this thing where you you're like prayer beads I you just count them through you know and I wasn't doing anything else
but doing that just just you know running through them with my thumbs um
but that too reminded me kept me connected and remember stay here stay
here I know people who really can't concentrate in meditation and so they
find that having these you know Mala beads is like prayer beads and every
time they breathe they do one and then they stay
connected so what does it take to walk in
refuge and so it's important in Buddhism this topic of Refuge because it's a
turning point for someone it's some it's a point where the that the Dharma
becomes the practice becomes maybe the centrally important thing in their
life uh where they have a lot of faith a lot of inspiration a lot of love for
this and some people say that it's nothing more important than
this and then other people say what the spouse says what
[Laughter]
your kids say what um nothing is more
important because we're so much
better and more present and maybe even more have more love for all those people
in our life so they get you can tell them you know it's a
trade-off okay if you don't want if you want you to be the most you're gonna if
you want you to be my most important thing let me tell you the trade-off if
you're the most important thing I will not be so happy and then I'll not be able to offer
you as much love but if you allow me to have this practice be the most important
thing then I'll have so much more for you that's the
trade-off and if you need to bargain negotiate
you know that's one one approach but so um so Refuge refuge in
the Buddha Refuge with the Buddha Refuge with the Dharma Refuge with the S and I
like this wording I go I walk and refuge with the
Buddha I'm the one who's walking I'm the one who's engaging I have to do
it and um so like it's the kind of like these shoes
if you don't wear them they can't protect you you have to
walk if you want the shoes to protect you you have to walk if you want the
Dharma to protect you you have to go and enter into this
world and um with all of who you are so this quote that I started by
there was something like to live a happy life stop being
frightened I'd like to offer something different to live a happy
life bring all of yourself
along bring all of you to the table bring all of you in as you walk
including your fear hold it all together let it all be here and that's the
possibility and why I think this Dharma this practice is so powerful so wonderful it's not to reject any part of
ourselves but finding a way to walk in the world to be in the world to be ourselves where we bring all of it along
and doing so live a wise life doing so live a
life that doesn't harm ourselves or others that's at the heart of the
Dharma so those are my thoughts today about this topic of Refuge so we have
about 15 minutes before the scheduled end if any of you would like to ask any
questions or have comments about this or you're welcome to ask or so
speak um I'm wondering if you have any suggestions on Refuge hug with the S
when you're by
yourself are you ever by yourself that ever
happen um physically yes oh physically oh
physically that happens occasionally I think that the the the
classic practice of doing that is to bring the s to mind think about them remember them
consider them you know some people have um pictures on they have little altar at
home and some people have pictures of the Buddha well pictures uh they have maybe of their
teachers teachers that Inspire them um so so find some way to remember
recall maybe going for a walk and thinking about it so being intentional and this is an example uh uh where they
answer these kinds of anwers always um what how are you going to walk now what
are you going to do how are you going to be active in the process of looking for what you're asking for and so these are
some of the ways to bring them to mind maybe write a letter to the
S you ever written a letter to your s write say write a letter you don't
have to mail it but that might bring it all to mind and the connection you have and make it
come kind of come alive in your heart in a ni way nice way thank
you hello everyone thank you um my question is
about finding Refuge during conflict during a moment
that your body is triggered
and how to work through that rather than walking away from it
yes well I mean there's so much to be said about that you know very important
topic um depends a lot about who it who you're with who who the conflict is with
and you know and what what's possible um there are times where
because of who I was with I I asked can we take a
pause and uh I think a few times I've actually asked you know can I can I step
away for a while I need to kind of be be with myself and process this so we I can
come back and process this with you because you know I'm a little bit I don't know my wife says I'm equally
introverted and extroverted but so there are times where I need to really go off
by myself and really process it ints often need to be time alone it's hard with introverts and extroverts because
extroverts want to do it right now in person and that's what works best for them and so you have to explain you know
I have a need I I want to take care of this I want to be honest and and really come to the bottom of this but in order
for me to do this effectively I need to pause and uh sometimes I've done it for three you know can I take two or three
minutes just to breathe here and just check in so I can come back in a way that's more effective so so this so
sometimes that's was necessary so but knowing you have that option then you don't have to run
away um the other is to assess what the other people are capable of you have to
be you have to be kind of have certain Street smarts to see are they capable here and and maybe the maybe the only
thing they're capable of is let's lower the temperature a little bit we can't really resolve this but let's lower the
temperature and and um and one way to do that is just to name little bit what's
happening in a safe way like oh I see this is difficult for you and you know I
see it's difficult for you it's difficult for me and I'm not sure what to do but I just want to acknowledge
that yes this is this is not an easy thing just that I learned um many years
ago that uh one way to deescalate the conflict really strong if it's if it's
the true the a statement is to let people know you're frightened like you know wow you know
this is really difficult for me I'm I'm scared right now especially if someone's angry with you because they're kind of
hostile in the in the conflict um some people when they hear that they're shocked like wow I had no idea and
they're not put on notice like is this really what you want to do maybe unconsciously it is they want
you to get but when they when it was made conscious it's hard for them to kind of want to keep doing that so but
just saying you know and you're not saying anything about them you're saying wow I'm really afraid and I need a minute to catch my breath
here and then sometimes it helpful if you have um established ahead of time so if you
if it's with some a friend or a partner or someone who you're going to be seeing for a long time uh when things are good
you might say you know you might say you know I kind of suspect sooner or later we're probably going to have some kind
of conflict maybe it might be accidental but um could we have a
plan you know how we talk to each other what we do what can we have a plan of
what we can ask of each other so that we don't just go into it with the all the
plates flying through the kitchen but so that we can say if I lift
my hand say hey let's at least sit down together or let's both of us go outside
and get some fresh air before we continue or let's both of us now talk about uh this only from the only using
eye statements and uh and and then so anyway so make it if you can plan
ahead and then but then in relationship to this talk I gave today uh which is really where you have
the most possibility of success people are hard are difficult so
so getting everyone to kind of you know Harmon harmonize is not always so easy
but at least harmonize within yourself and so one of so that's where the how do
you walk walk in Refuge walk connected so if a person really has a
strong sense of what refuge is for them or what's really strong sense of a good inner way of being even if it's not
available right away we have a practice to reconnect to it we have a practice to try to come back to it and if we can't
really get back to it then we have a practice of mindfulness and mindfulness is uh what
part of what mindfulness can do is uh especially if it partners with the practice of getting
grounded so just sit up straight or stand straight and and uh breathe and
just feel what's going on and hold it all in some kind of way and uh really
become very clear what your experience is right now and that Clarity of what's happening is a
refuge so those are some things to do but I I don't want to imply that it's
easy thank you so yes Cheryl number of years ago in
fact probably more than once he told a story which was very interesting a personal story about um being on the
street at night in San Francisco is that a story I don't know if youve told it lately or
not would you be willing to tell it it's not that long a story and I doubt whether you've forgotten it I I have all
kinds of sanan San Francisco San Francisco street stories but maybe it's the it's the one woman in the the woman
in the car no you were walking with a friend you were walking with a friend and these guys came up to you with a gun
I think a what gun with a gun oh it wasn't no that's not me no there was
a there was a there was a a friend of mine who uh someone came up with aun
okay and and um I had a few friends who were held up at gunpoint in San
Francisco but maybe the one that I'm you thinking of one of them was useful seemed like a very useful thing to do I
remember one of them was um the person uh just looked at the this young man
with a gun and said something like you know
um you're not a good Christian your mother would be ashamed of you
you and that was enough to kind of just break the whole thing and the person
left a number I wonderful stories of people but you know getting out of trouble in San Francisco streets like
that but but the um and there're wonderful stories but you C you can't use it as a
technique it's it's all has to do within the moment something feels like the right thing to do and
um and the one person who didn't do something like that and kind of was
reactive back in my friends back uh to someone who came and held them up um he
reacted and I think the person who held him up somehow was never apprehended but he
ended up in jail so because of his reactivity to it
all so it's good to stay calm and know how to be
non-reactive yes um I like the story about the um the
prir beads the pr beads yeah I like your sorry okay I like the the um part about
the prir beads but I would lose them I guarantee so but you know I find that um
staying mindful especially at work um is really hard um and I did set an alarm to
go off at noon every day to kind of try to remind me um and a lot of the times I
just turn it off CU I'm in the middle of something so do you have any other tips or maybe somebody else has other tips on
how you remind yourself to be mindful during the day at a when you're busy so
two things I could say one is to make it a habit to uh you you much of your work
sitting standing both both is to uh focus on your posture
and so sit in a in a good aligned upright posture and also stand that way
in since in a good way and let that uh the posture somehow uh call forth bring
forth as a form of mindfulness because if we if our posture collapses so does
our mindfulness and that and but if the posture is kind of aligned and good
sometimes we can see when we're starting to lose the mindfulness because the posture begins to collapse or give up so
posture is invaluable the other is to have reminders around and um I used to use uh
every time I went through a door frame that was my reminder and it was kind of nice because
when you go through a door frame you're going into a new space so it's good to kind of notice what you're doing and not just be kind of lost in thought and so I
used to go through a lot of door frames so I used to that was a great thing to do um some people put stickers on things
that they'll see regularly I've known people who put a sticker like says remember or something on top of their
computer screen so that it's always there so they see it regularly and and
um so you know you know something you do regularly and it can be a series of things so if if if it's you know if your
thing was to only at noon once a day I bet you go to uh the bathroom more
often than once a day so make that your
thing you you know say
Yes um as far as staying mindful at work I have a mug on my desk a what a mug a
mug that says take a breath and remember who the heck you
are so as far as taking refuge in yourself you know I've got the Dharma
I've got a long life of experience I'm looking at turning 70 so come on you
know I I'm not helpless so um uh I just
find that really you useful great I love it yeah if I didn't have the mug I'd put
a little sign there you cuz you've got this cuz I've got some worries and I
realize that worries are related to fear yeah and I know how to deal with fear
nice so yeah yeah so there are people you so at work at home and the in the
bathroom mirror on the steering wheel of the car people put you all these little
reminders okay maybe that's enough so um I'll end this way
[Music]
s
[Music] me and may all the ways that you might
walk in Refuge support you to be a refuge for
Others May this practice we do be for the welfare and happiness of the whole
world thank you