hello and welcome to this Friday meditation at
IMC And as we come to the
final talk on uh the third Janna the third absorption
third immersion the third way of getting settled
peacefully into a
wholeness And I like using the word wholeness because
um the idea in these deep immersive
states is to um have
the the goodness of these states often described as joy and
happiness to be pervasive throughout the body The whole body is
included And the body that we talk about in Buddhism is not exactly the same as
our physical body Uh it's the body that we
experience It's the body we experience through the medium of all kinds of aspects of the mind the
state of the mind the orientations of the mind the preferences of the mind the
beliefs and thoughts stories of the mind We are not innocent
uh experiencer of this body We only experience a small subset
of all the things happening in our body It's a subset that has
uh you know where our the mind travels through the nerve the nerves that
stretch out from or are part of the mind It's almost as if wherever there's a
nerve ending the mind is right there as well And the whole functioning of the
mind then shifts and changes how we experience the body
And as we go into these deeper states of meditation
uh it is um we
[Music] are shifting the orientation to the body
what we pick up in the body what we amplify what we add to the experience of
the body And one of those things is that we start living more in a whole way We don't we
stop selecting out a piece of it or we stop having blinders on because we're
thinking so much and preoccupied by things
And one of the characteristics of deepening and deepening in meditation in
samadei meditation is an increase increasing feeling of
peace And in the third genre this is characterized with the word
equinimity Equinimity There's the peace of nonreactivity The peace of not making
something about making up something about what's happening Not making up stories or
living in the stories of what's happening Judging it commentary not tensing or reaching for
experience There's a deep settleness And the peace of the third
Janna is um is different than what's going to come in the fourth Janna The peace is
um kind of like the peace you might find if you kind of dive under the water
and rest there for a few moments It can be very peaceful and
still and but still there's a the texture the viscosity of the water
that's there There's something there that is buoyant maybe something there
that um presses gently against us if unless
we go too deep and uh it doesn't offer much
resistance We can swim through it but it's still there It's not as thin as the
air And so this piece of the third Janna has a little bit of density a
little bit of viscosity little bit of sub substantuality perhaps
something that um spreads through the body
It feels very whole and complete Everything that we touch in the
body everything the nerve ends touch and that we can be directly aware of is
felt in this lake of peace
So assuming a meditation posture
and over time the posture itself becomes the beginning of
appreciating peace with the body becoming still The
body not being so active anymore For a beginner in meditation the
posture is a challenge and maybe takes work and patience
and but as over the months and years of regular
meditation the body and the posture become a refuge a refuge in
stillness a wonderful form of
nonactivity that is satisfying just in
itself So feeling the peace maybe the stillness of the posture
the body and breathing deeply and relaxing
relaxing
peacefully If you feel your muscles relax the moments in which it's
releasing and softening are moments moving towards
peace
relaxing softening and letting the breathing return to
normal And the absence of the activity of breathing deeply and
relaxing means that now there's a different kind of peace here The peace of not doing those things
And as you inhale for a few breaths feel the thinking
mind Feel the tensions or pressure or agitation there might be
there And as you relax as you exhale relax the thinking mind
As a thinking mind relaxes it relaxes toward
into peace in the mind
And then to in a way that feels
peaceful gentle lower your
awareness into the body breathing
Maybe landing on the settling spot the grounding spot of
breathing And while you're aware of breathing also open your
attention peripheral awareness out beyond the
edges of breathing beyond the edges of the sensations you have of breathing
And maybe beyond the edges of
breathing there is some kind of
peace stillness spaciousness
In which the sensations of breathing
float
move or nested
did gently
softly feel the spread head of peace as you
breathe As if the movements of breathing are a gentle wind a gentle
warmth expanding the peace through your body
Reassuring the mind that it's
okay to quiet your thinking
Taking a moment to
quiet your inner life
So you can feel allow yourself to
feel the influence of any degree of
peace that's
present in the
body in the experience of
breathing in the mind and heart
And perhaps the peace found in any degree of
spaciousness here around you within
You allow yourself to feel silently
feel the influence of peace
And as we come to the end of the meditation I'd like to evoke an ancient
Buddhist idea around samadei
that there is something about the well-being of somebody the peace of
somebody that we can drink we can it's like medicine or
nourishment And so to drink the nourishment of
peace take it in the nourishment of peace and let it spread through your
body through your
arms your legs
legs the back rib cage the
spine the belly and the front rib
cage into the head
and to feel peace as a nourishment
Whatever degree however little there is maybe it's a homeopathic dosage of
peace feel it sense
it and then wish it for
others May others have a chance to experience peace
Those who are experiencing violence may they be
peaceful May they know peace Those who experience
hate may they feel
peace an experience of peaceful
time Those who are ignored and
marginalized may they feel peace
peace that allows them to be whole dignified in their own
right And those who grieve may they feel
peace to hold the grief to allow it to be
there And may it be that what we learn about peace
through meditation May it be that it spreads from
us as medicine as nourishment for our
world May all beings be happy May all
beings be safe May all beings be
peaceful May all beings be
[Music]
free Thank you
Hello and welcome to this fifth talk on the third Janna as part of this samadei
series And um sometimes I've thought that the third
Janna is my favorite of the Janna Maybe because it certainly has a degree of
wonderful degree of peace but it also has kind of a very satisfying comforting or deep feeling of well-being that's
part of it that seems to fill the whole body
And so but one of the so I want to read again the gen the ancient description of
the third Janna as part of completing this
week with a fading of joy a practitioner abides at quantamus
aware and with clear recognition and experience experiences
the happiness of the body The practitioner enters and abides
in the third Janna of which the noble ones declare a quantamus and aware abides in
happiness The practitioner
pervades pervades saturates permeates this body with
happiness that is freed of joy So that no part of the body is not
touched by the happiness So one of the characteristics of this
third genre is equinimity and uh and that's a form of
peace There's something peaceful about not reacting about not being caught and
being for and against or preferences Um partly because there's no
reason for it Um but partly because even in this third Janna where uh the
experience is just predominantly or only pleasant that um uh we don't lean into
it We're not grabbing it We're not uh involved in any kind of reactivity
positive reactivity towards it We're aquatamus We're peaceful about
it because it's allowing something deep in our mind deep in our psyche to relax
to let go to not have to be constantly chronically
active doing making wanting protecting figuring
out responding to every little thing that happens The mind can have this
tremendous clarity It's a quantmous It's aware There's a clear knowing of what's
happening But at the same time uh everything is allowed to happen
freely Uh and the classic metaphor as I've said is um beautiful flowers lotus
flowers that are open and just exquisitely pristine Perhaps
uh lotuses are uh considered somehow pure and uh uh floating in water
underwater peacefully very peacefully and everything that we
experience is held in the in the water of the mind the water of of uh happiness
the water of peace equinimity And as we come to the end of
this week on the third Janna uh the word the word peace itself is not in the
description of the Janna But equinimity is a form of peace It's not uh there's
many flavors of peace This is one of the great delights of meditation of dharma practice Maybe one of the delights of
human life is uh to be able to appreciate the flavors of peace the many
flavors that that we can experience And um and if you never heard
of this idea that peace can have many flavors many be experienced many different ways that different
characteristics Uh you might want to make a study of that maybe over this
weekend before we start again You might uh give yourself an opportunity to
experience peace Maybe there's places you can go that you can experience it Maybe
there's some kind of um cathedral church in your neighborhood
that has very peaceful inside Maybe a park with the grove of trees
Maybe there's um a peaceful bank of a river that you can go sit by Maybe it's
a corner of your home that maybe looking out the window or maybe with uh maybe
with you know setting up a certain kind of context Maybe when you're alone at home or you just allow yourself the
chance to not do anything except begin to sense and feel
uh peace and the different ways peace can be experienced Maybe you find yourself in situations
that are quite agitating and difficult but with a assignment to feel the
different flavors of peace maybe ask yourself in a way maybe you've never done before in this in a trying
situation Um where's the peace here where's the peace while people are
arguing where's the peace when there's a difficult tension in the room is there
any and there always will be somewhere uh provide and at minimum it can be
found in the calm mindfulness the calm awareness that searches for
it and um so in this third genre there's a degree of peace and that peace feels
uh not personal exactly it can feel almost like it expands beyond the edges
of the body or beyond the edges certainly of any ways that we we usually
define ourselves or want to be and uh there's all kinds of lessons around this
uh in the third gen and one of them is that um any appropriation any kind of
movement towards making it mine or this is me having this experience can be seen
as um creating agitation on the surface of the lake It can feel like it's
unnecessary it actually detracts from the richness of the experience
And so to begin kind of appreciating the peace feeling what peace is here and
um and uh and becoming a connoisseur of of peace and the reason
for this is that in the fourth Janna uh the it's the equinimity becomes
stronger and more peaceful and so uh being able to kind of sense and have a
kind of um registering of the qualities characteristic of
peace characteristics of this happiness that's there Uh that's the the means by
which or the condition by which our psychophysical system can move into the
fourth Janna So it's one of the charact one of the characteristics of this instructions
in the four janna is to pervade saturate and pervade the body with the joy and
happiness with the happiness with the peace Um partly so we can know it well
We can feel it well Um we can feel it in a deep way that it's almost like we are
not feeling it because we're not appropriating it or measuring it against me myself and mine or or or uh defining
ourselves by it or wanting more or wanting less Just really getting to know
it on its own terms how that is and this deeper
familiarity So sometimes I've known people who go into the Janna and are
kind of in a hurry to go through it They want to be masters of it They want to be
somehow this idea of being a good meditator or a successful practitioner There might be a little bit conceit
around going into these deep states And this is rather unfortunate
because the conceit gets in the way of the deeper lessons of these states And
one of the deeper lessons is to take in the kind of the selfless
experience of something profound going on a profound movement a profound opening a profound quality of well-being
and peace that um we want to really
register and uh and get to know well without any interference any kind of
agitation or or that comes with um trying to do something with or get more
from it or speed along and just just being very subtle led very
peaceful and uh discovering the almost selfless quality of these deep deep
states because we're not selfing around it There's a deeper
peace So um so if you're at all inclined I encourage you to spend this weekend
um um getting to know the flavors of peace for you Search for it Look for it
Uh search it out where places you can go what people you can be with uh what ways
of doing housework what ways of being at home Um that uh you can actually take
time to begin exploring the different qualities characteristics of what how
you experience peace And then you'll be a little better prepared for next week
when we do the fourth Janna So thank you very much for being part of
this and I look forward to our continuation