so good morning everyone it's a delight to see all the
uh comments um I read them all and I really appreciate them
um and it's great seeing some very old friends there too
so good day good good uh morning afternoon evening for some
[Music] um and uh we'll go ahead and start with um you know uh a little bit on feeling
tones or vana of thinking and um beta is a poly word
that's translated as feeling tone it's a very fundamental way that we
experience the world through our senses and through our mind uh when a sensation
arrives it's either pleasant unpleasant or neither pleasant or pleasant some
people call it neutral um it's immediate it happens
right away and it's much simpler than an emotion
it's important because this is how clinging arises we experience something pleasant
and if we don't pay attention we often just want more of it and we start grasping and trying to get more um
um but staying mindful of the level of the feeling tone and keep us from
grasping at what's pleasant at what we enjoy um and conversely the same is true
something's unpleasant it's very easy to fall into want into pushing it away
getting rid of it um for the first 10 minutes of this
meditation we'll emphasize noticing the feeling tone of our experience just as
simple as what we feel pleasant unpleasant or neither and don't worry about being
correct sometimes it's like well it's it's almost pleasant or uh you know
that's fine you know sometimes it's subtle it's really what you notice now
whether you label it correctly and sometimes it changes the same um uh
warmth that felt really good a moment ago can feel uncomfortable um so however it is just
notice this moment pleasant unpleasant or neither and just try to do this in a
relaxed way um without adding too much to the meditation so we'll do just the
first 10 minutes we'll focus on this um so let's take a comfortable but
alert posture settling settling into our
seat gently closing the
eyes and begin by taking a few deep
breaths and with each ex each each exhale relaxing a little bit more
relaxing into your cushion or chair to the earth that supports us all
now allowing the breath to return to normal you might get a sense of the whole
body and allow the attention to meander freely throughout the
body relaxing any obvious
tensions you might check the head the face the
shoulders the belly the
hands whatever can be relaxed
now finding the breath within your body allowing your
attention to rest on the breath just settling into the rhythm of
the breath
now shift the attention to notice the mood of the mind the mind
state just a larger environment of the mind in which all the sensations of the
breathing of the body are occurring how does the mind
feel is it tense or relaxed spacious or
contracted tired or
alert calm or agitated however it
is just noticing it
i said resistance or
accepting don't need to pick any words just notice how it feels
now shift the attention back to the sensations of
breathing allowing the sensations to come and go
but briefly notice the feeling tone of the breath it can change with every inhale
and exhale is this inhale pleasant right now is it unpleasant or neither
if any other compelling physical sensations arise also briefly notice their feeling
tone pleasant
unpleasant neither
and just for the next couple of minutes if any thinking becomes
obvious notice if it's pleasant or unpleasant
are you enjoying the thinking is it pleasant is there some stress there is
it unpleasant and you can easily change
from one to the other see if you can observe these
feeling tones without getting carried away by the content of the
thoughts or by any reaction to the thoughts
if no significant thinking arises just rest on the breath
now we can just return to keeping it very simple returning to the rhythm of the
breath but maybe your mind will notice a little
bit more easily the pleasant and unpleasant
qualities that arise with all our sensations all of our
thoughts just resting in our breath
if your tension has drifted or gotten
lost just gently welcome it back home
[Music]
so Um this morning I'm going to talk about a little bit about internal white speech
and um but also uh how vdana the the
feeling tone um of our inner voice affects
us um so
um vet and I it is that our experience is either pleasant unpleasant or neither
and we tend to cling to the pleasant and push away the unpleasant and usually not
even notice the neither pleasant or unpleasant but as the mind slows down uh
it's much easier to see that feeling tone of our sensations and we can relax into them
however they are and not get pulled into them uh life is filled with unpleasant
sensations they're not going to go away it's not like we can manipulate our life
for things to always be pleasant uh so the idea is not to have one over
the other but to be at peace with however those sensations
are um but one of the uh reasons we get caught in our thinking is that we're
unaware of the thinking the feeling tone of our thinking um worrying and negative judgment
thoughts regrets they tend to be unpleasant thoughts like anticipation
maybe thinking about loved ones gratitude they're they tend to be
pleasant and uh when we get into um our thinking often um can come in patterns
of thinking for many of us and um the patterns we get caught by and for
instance uh in particular during meditation uh so some of us really uh
fall into planning we might f plan and replan the same thing many many times uh now
planning in itself can be pleasant or unpleasant and it's helpful to know
what's feeding the pattern um I like to plan often planning
is fun planning a project planning a vacation maybe planning what we'll do
later that day um you know and sometimes we may do this during meditation because
we're bored we're bored which is unpleasant it's slightly unpleasant we
tend to think there's nothing happening but something isn't quite quite pleasant
and we become aversive to the boredom we push it away by entertaining ourselves
with planning um or maybe we're feeling really good which is pleasant and when
we feel good in in our daily lives we're used to doing something with that energy and and so we want to plan what we're
going to do next so we're excited and so um we get caught by the feeling
good um but planning can also be fueled by anxiety by trying to control things
it's usually unpleasant and usually not useful you know maybe we're having
friends over for lunch and uh we need to plan the menu and we've already sort of planned the menu but then we find
ourselves doing it over and over and over again all the details uh there can
be attention a compulsiveness to this kind of planning um in working with repetitive
planning it can be very helpful to notice if it's pleasant or unpleasant am
I enjoying it or is it stressful
so um in this path most of us um have
put some effort in practicing wise speech in our in our daily lives and
maybe have even refined our speech making our speech kinder more honest
um maybe we've noticed the separation we create between people when we're
gossiping or how our heart feels more closed or maybe how frequent complaining
is stressful and fatigues the other person and actually decreases
empathy decreases the connection between people
you know how unskillful speech can strain relationships it can isolate
us it can erode our sense of
selfworth one way of thinking about wise thinking in meditation is as internal
wise speech and the effects of internal speech are even more extensive than our
verbal ones so the guidelines um that the Buddha
offered for why speech can apply just as well to our internal speech to our
thinking um though it's not so easy to refrain from from those things but it uh
one of the ways that can be helpful though is when the guidelines are expressed as four simple
questions is it true is it helpful is it
kind is it the right time let's take a little time to look at
those um um you know I've known practitioners who
think to themselves I can't concentrate and they'll do that over and over in
their minds you know and they believe it you know and um had a student I worked
with and um and he told me you know I just can't concentrate you know I just
get lost constantly uh so I asked them to close their eyes and pay attention to
three breaths and then open their eyes and uh lo and behold they were able
to do that but the story that I'm someone who can't concentrate just
discouraged him stopped him from applying himself and even if you didn't get past three breaths that's
concentrating and we still settle three breaths distracted three breaths distracted we can still settle the
mind um so is it true whatever we're saying
to ourselves is it helpful and so if we're planning
something for the 10th time you know um we might be telling ourselves a story we
got to get it just right but is it helpful it's usually not it's usually
not especially during meditation um and is it
kind the quality of the voice putting down on ourselves is not
kind repetitive thoughts of not being good enough are not kind would I speak
to my child that way um in the 70s um 70s there was a
period of time when in some circles it became very popular for people to
practice brutal honesty a particularly direct and unfiltered form of truthtelling without
consideration for the recipient's feelings the idea was they're responsible for their own feelings i'm
just going to tell the truth and it often caused harm it often uh broke
relationships sometimes the truth might hurt and sometimes we do have to tell
painful truths but it can still be communicated with kind
intentions um is it the right time and uh sometimes something might be
true it might be kind it might be helpful and really deserve
attention but we're meditating uh it's not why we meditate to to figure these
things out it's not the right time and in meditation we can just very
easily say "Oh not now." It can come out of respect
uh for the thoughts for the idea you know I'll think about that later that's worthy of reflection and we put it aside
for later not a rejection of it but just a putting it
aside um you know it's just like in a relationship
uh you might have something you really want to say and you know it's true it's kind it's helpful but it may not be um
uh something that your partner wants to hear when they first wake up in the morning it's not the right time in your
mind it's like oh it's really it's really alive but they're still groggy
give them some time um so these are the the aspects of um of wise speech that
really can be internalized um to help develop more helpful
thought thinking processes
um so um you know some of the patterns repetitive patterns we can fall into you
know when a particular theme keeps reappearing in our thinking you know such as I mentioned planning we can use
those four questions whenever we're caught in one of those patterns one of those eddies just by adding the question
it adds a little bit of space it adds a wholesome element to the
moment another common pattern might be worry you know what if thoughts
imagining excuse me
um imagining um unwanted future events it can be really helpful to
notice the emotion underneath some form of fear or anxiety to attend to it is it
true often not i like to remember what Mark Twain said um some of the worst
things in my life never happened um and it might be true but
it's a kind when we bring kindness to worry it begins to change
it is it helpful are we going to make things better with worry with rehashing
rethinking um and if it's something worthwhile
considering meditation is not the right time
um so another pattern that's really common is um impatient thoughts which
are not pleasant usually and they're not helpful and in fact they can cause
harm this seemingly harmless kind of repetitive thought pattern can have a
great impact on us it tells us the present moment is not worth
experiencing that the present moment is not okay it's not enough and it creates a sense of
contention with our experience which adds tension and stress
so when we see this repetitive thoughts you know you know how much longer before the bell you know or um or however uh we
might be impatient um there's always like an underlying
aversion or pushing away the present moment experience and can we turn to
it um you know we might ask ourselves what is it we don't want to
feel in daily life how often are you waiting for something to be over waiting
in line waiting on hold on the on the phone waiting until the person you're
talking to gets to the point all that waiting is supported by
thoughts thoughts that ignore the value of the present moment
so can we get interested in that
moment and um you know one other
um pattern that many of us um have repetitive is judgment just a recurring
kind of um uh judging ourselves other situations we even judge or
judging you know and what's really important is that
um how to tell the difference between judgment and
discernment for instance the judging mind sees what's wrong with anything right uh what's wrong with ourselves
what's wrong with someone else and the discerning mind might notice what's
wrong uh but it's nonreactive it's with an easy heart um
it's reactive judgment has a meanness to it it's not
kind for instance um you know as a boss if you have to evaluate an employee you
have to know their strengths and weaknesses but there doesn't have to be any unkindness in seeing their
weaknesses and so when we view ourselves and um we do have weaknesses you know
that's we practice that's what we practice because we're we still have greed hatred and delusion that's why we
practice so it's there so do we need to um can we be discerning about it oh yeah
that that that jud that quality of mind that um that way that I didn't do things
the way I wanted to do them um you know that's what happened and if it hurts I
can bring compassion um but there's no need for that meanness
of judgment that harshness of judgment and not to push away when it
happens you know we can be uh kind about our judging
mind you know and and lastly of the of the patterns I want to mention regrets
Because sometimes we dwell on painful things from the past and they come up over and over can be a very very deep
habit that darkens our minds and when they're painful memories
can we bring kindness and compassion to the pain of the regret this is dooka you know even
though it happened 20 years ago it's still it's dooka right now when we remember it it's pain it's painful and
when we're hurting we deserve compassion and
kindness so lastly I want to say um you know most thoughts come and go uh and
they're just ephemeral we just they just go away very very quickly we can't hold
on to it it's gone before we know it incredibly brief but repetitive thinking patterns
are sticky they don't flow easily if we continue with it it gets stronger the
more we do it the more it's easy to do it but we can attend to those when they
show up with care and with kindness and maybe we can ask if it's true if it's helpful if it's kind if
it's timely so I'll just end with
um my wishes for all of us may this SA be filled with loving
kindness may we be happy may we be
peaceful may we be free may our good will spread to
all beings everywhere thank you