hello and welcome to the meditation session
and as an introduction to this meditation uh I think many of you know
that when we practice mindfulness meditation uh there's a big emphasis on
being with things as they are and cultivating the ability to be present
for whatever arises in experience and um and whatever sense
door whatever location mind body heart
and to cultivate a way of being with what
is but there is something subtle or maybe not so subtle that very important to take into
account is that um the mind has a tendency to prioritize
certain things to be oriented in certain directions as being the important thing
to notice and um so if
um we're you know looking for I remember
many years ago when I was looking for a futon couch I was surprised suddenly how
many futon couch doors there were uh I had no idea but now that I was looking for it or concerned with it I my
attention prioritized it and I noticed and saw and so some of us
prioritize certain uh way of thinking certain attitudes we
prioritize what's wrong we prioritize finding evidence that we are
somehow um uh wrong or a bad person or some something like
that and some people prioritize um um you know everything is wonderful
and and had live in kind of a rose-colored glasses of things and and
so they don't see things as they really are and so this idea of prioritizing some people prioritize around things
that are directly connected to themselves Me Myself and mine and there can be a tremendous over orientation on
myself and how it affects me and what I want some people prioritize other people
and it's concerned with caring for them and what they think so same thing when we sit down to
meditate there can be a bias towards certain experiences there times in my life I
bias towards of pain ready to notice and pounce on any slightest indication of
pain and discomfort sometimes with a magnifying glass glass and and making it
be much bigger than it actually was sometimes we uh sit down and meditate and the orientation we have is
uh maybe automatically around how we feel the emotional state we're in and some of it might be natural
because we have certain conditions that allow certain things to predominate and be very important for our well-being to
care for well but there might also because of that a kind of Habitual
reaction to keep looking in certain directions keep becoming aware of certain
things so when we get down to practice samadi um we're shifting that and being
intentional in the direction in which we prioritize not to push something away
not to be aversive to something or or to condemn anything at all but uh it's for
example if you're washing your dishes and pots and um um sometimes you know what I wanted
to wash it well um uh I'm paying careful attention to where their dirt is and if
I can't see the food that's stuck to the plate I might pass my hand over it to really feel and I might be a lot many
many other things might be going on in my life but um I'm really engaged
washing dishes require a certain direction of attention I'm not pushing things away or denying other things it's
just this is the task at hand so with samadi the task at hand is to is to
engage and notice what supports you to become gathered to become unified to be
really here with all of yourself in a nice unstressful
way and um and part of that that allows the subma to grow is to slightly
prioritize the good feelings that come along not to manufacture them not to
think they're always going to be there uh sometimes big part of practice is to
uh learn to be a quanus and peaceful non-reactive with what is and sometimes
the feelings of well-being that arise are subtle and it might be a feeling of
rightness of being with what's difficult difficult emotions difficult moods
difficult situations and pain there can be as we practice mindfulness and we develop some
non-reactivity there's a feeling of rightness oh this is good that I'm present and so it's a kind of subtle
kind of well-being that uh but it is a kind of well-being that something feels
right given what's happening it's right that I'm here and um so the um so with Sade
though as we settle in we want to gently prioritize ways in which we feel good
ways in which through the meditation with the meditation there's
feelings of well-being that begin arising and they might be very subtle at
first and um and uh but over time the guideline or the orientation might to
notice the pleasure that's there what's Pleasant and the growing pleasantness and
pleasure of prioritize that not to push anything else away but to just gently
kind of keep that as a reference point uh to really help you stay there in the
Rhythm like I put my gently feel the top of the plate to see if there's any food
still stuck that I can't see so the so the um so we gently kind of
prioritize the Fe feel this goodness here feel the well-being that's
arising and in due time the uh this sense of well-being and
pleasure um morphs into a sense of joy and um and so I'll lead you
now so to assume your meditation
posture and gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths and settle in to your posture your
body the Deep inhale is a getting the support of a deeper
breath to be present here in our body
as you exhale allowing the longer exhale than
usual help you settle in further become grounded in the body
deeper inhales and exhales is a little bit of a ritual
transition to help the mind the heart be ready to be here and now in this
body and then letting your breathing return to normal and for
maybe another four or five
breaths feeling different parts of the body that you want to relax on the
inhale and then relax those parts of the body on the
exhale for
and then to feel in your body any sense
of anything that you appreciate right now about Sensations
feelings maybe there's a subtle shift to being a little calmer more
settled more connected
maybe there's some certain pleasure that comes or a pleasantness inspiration that
comes with beginning the meditation and settling into
it it might be a mental appreciation pleasure
but it might be something in the
body maybe a diffuse feeling
of pleasantness that might be there in
addition to any places in your body that are
unpleasant gently lean into the Pleasant
let your
awareness become a little bit more clear or present with the help of what's Pleasant
in your
body it might be some soft diffus
generalized hum or glow in your
body or it might be some very specific spot that as you meditate Comes Alive a
bit with pleasure tingling
the
glow if there's a generalized sense of well-being or
pleasure allow that to be surrounded the experience of
breathing almost like a gent soft blanket
or that nurtures or nourishes the body's experience of
breathing
and then to feel in this cycle of breathing in and breathing out is there any point in that
cycle the where the sensations of breathing feel
Pleasant where the body can take in the pleasure of it
and if there is some pleasure in breathing something
pleasant let that be a slight
priority to feel it each cycle of
breathing as if it's a door to enter into to be more
in the breathing more centered in the breathing
and if there's any pleasure at all associated with the
meditation gently
lightly let that support the awareness
that begins in the settling spot the grounding
spot and remains throughout the
inhale throughout the exhale
feeling the full length of in and out breath as if there's a gentle way from
the inside breathing is stroking your
body and if that any of it is
Pleasant allow yourself to
feel the pleasure as an
encouragement to stay with a breath continuously
and when you let go of your thoughts see if in the
quieting and letting them go float
away there's some sense of pleasure well-being in the mind to not be caught
in
thoughts and allow that well-being or pleasure than to join the pleasure of
breathing
e
e e
sometimes the pleasure that can support
meditation is evoked by ever so
slightly with the corners of your lips your mouth making a little
smile just enough for there to evoke some pleasure
or Joy Delight
and if there is such
pleasure let it support an orientation
to being centered on breathing
as if the rhythm of breathing the
body is what keeps us connected to pleasure Joy
well-being however subtle it might be
e
for
for e
and as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps to allow yourself to
smile perhaps allow yourself to feel whatever well-being or goodness
that's here through this
meditation maybe is a subtle pervasion of the body with
being calmer more
settled maybe it's a
specific feeling of physical
pleasure somewhere in your
body or something that's between being invasive and
specific and for a few moments maybe there's a way of allowing yourself to
drink in whatever sense of well-being or
pleasure that's
here maybe turning up your lips to smile in such a
way that a sparkle might be there in your eyes for how you're going to open
your eyes and see the
world and with your mind's eye with a sparkle
of appreciation Delight that maybe can
see other people with respect and delight and
appreciation that softens them that disarms them
that brings forth their own relaxation and ease and
well-being so that the difficult people in the world become less
difficult so that the friendly people in the
world feel seen and share joined in their
friendliness May may it be that this practice that we do allows us to see the
world with fresh eyes without
bias but with a Sparkle with a
joy and with that to live for the welfare and happiness of all beings
including our own and in knowing well-being for
ourselves we can wish it for others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
free and may all beings be peaceful
and may this wonderful community of ours with so many people meditating
now feel like we're doing this together as we go out the
world that we're spreading human goodness out into the
world
[Music]
thank
you e
so welcome to the next talk on
samadi and um but before I do I I would like to make the repeat the announcement
I made on Monday that IMC partly inspired from what this YouTube
community did three years ago uh raising money for the refugees
from the Ukraine uh where IMC is inspired to do this
again for children in in areas of great crisis who are facing famine and illness
and injuries of all kinds and the way we want to do this is
with the making donations to save the children organiz wonderful
organization that um does wonderful work in the world for
children for many decades now and uh so we started this week the fundraising drive and we're about a
third the way to what I'm hoping is the inspiring goal for us and uh and if
you're interested in joining together and participating in the kind of the the
the the collective effectiveness of a community doing something uh with each
other uh you can go on the IMC website the homepage has a couple of places
where you can get to the uh save the children donation page that we're
using that um is specific to IMC and um and there's a red banner on
top of the website and there's a in the what's new section of the
homepage there's a notice as well so thank
you and uh in talking about that um the
the Gathering together of a community and the power that that can bring so in
meditation the Gathering Together of ourselves into a unified whole um
into to enter into a state being that's called
samadi uh gives the individual a certain power and uh that can then can be used
for good in the world and um and brings the the power of
of love the power of Peace the power of being
settled um and um the power of being present in a very full and embodied
complete way and um and so the um so this Gathering
ourselves together of samadi is supported by Pleasure supported by the
pleasantness or the happiness that can come from meditation and there are times when
meditation teachers have deemphasized the joy and the happiness and come with
meditation one form of that the emphasizing is by saying uh telling the
practitioner when they feel some Joy or happiness or pleasure in the meditation
to um to um um now now there's one more
thing for you to let go of and and but I think I would say it
differently uh it's one more thing not to be attached to but don't exactly let
go of it stay with it maintain it it's one more thing to open your hands to
hold kindly and supportingly uh so that something there
can grow and develop uh it's almost like um not
clinging not being attached not being resistance not not being afraid of the pleasure and joy that comes in
meditation is almost like we're opening up uh or there's an opening up like a
flower that opens when it's going well we don't say the flower is letting go of
itself when it opens but it is no longer bunched up and
tight and uh the reference to flower uh works well for some people who
uh talk about the the beauty that can arise in samadi and that's
sometimes a more useful reference point than pleasure or Joy where it's some of
us can have a complicated relationship to that and maybe we have a certain standard what Joy means or what pleasure
means that gets in the way of us appreciating what's here but uh or we
want to we appropriate it the joy we hold on to the Joy or the pleasure like we want more
Beauty uh of meditation uh it's difficult to appropriate that it's
difficult to grab onto Beauty because it's kind of a morphous it's kind of like it's not something that something
that can be destroyed the more we cling it's um it's almost like the an
open hand uh disappears if we grab onto the hand to hold on to we like that open
hand so much we don't want to share it with anyone and we make a fist well the open hand is lost and in that process so
Beauty can be that way so some people can feel the beauty of uh maybe of
breathing that some there's something very sweet that can start happening and may the word sweetness is another way of
talking about this positive positive feelings that can start coming from
meditation and um and uh it's okay to evoke it slightly not to make it a big
project but to um classic instruction is to uh
have a little half smile on your lips and sometimes that brings kind of pleasure Sensations around the lips
around the cheeks or the face sometimes it begins to shift some whole inner feeling that we have um kind of
reconditions Rec kind of shapes something uh that uh maybe creates an
alternative to how we might be shaped and affecting our body or hearts or Minds by doing with our mind something
that's the opposite of a smile uh sometimes we can be an automatic pilot with with resentments or
anger or aversions or finding what's wrong or or being critical
self-critical and it can be so much so so so common and so frequent we do this
that it just seems like the natural state of way of being and we don't even know that we're doing it but it has a
very strong condition effect influence on our whole being and sometimes uh it's
nice to do within reason a slight kind of re uh orientation towards what is
good right now what is Pleasant right now what is nice right
now some people find it useful when they sit down and and make sure that they're
sitting in a place where they're not no one's going to disturb them where they feel safe and then and and maybe even
look around in their room that the door is closed and no one's there and there's no monsters under the
bed and uh and uh and actually feel the safety of it some people feel very
little safety in their life and to um and so that the fear doesn't get the
upper hand it might be good to actually take time to feel the sense of safety
that might be there uh some people take time to feel gratitude at the beginning
of a sitting and being reminded of things that we're grateful for um is an
antidote to some of the other non-gr grateful ways in which we're operating some people like to evoke
sense of contentment contentment is in the family of well-being
happiness and um and so to find feel the ways in which you feel content in your
life as opposed to discontented and so to kind of bring into the meditation some kind of uh
appropriate way not forcing it not not paning it but some appropriate Way start
kind of uh evoking and bringing forth and being connected to uh a well-being a
pleasure in the pleas present moment for some people that pleasure
that can come from meditation comes from uh uh uh starting to be absorbed in the
focus of meditation such as the breathing to uh because just staying
continuously with the breathing means that we're no longer um concentrating
absorbed in thoughts and feelings which are create the opposite for us opposite
of Joy opposite of well-being and um and when those begin
quieting down and settling and the and and they're not fragmenting us or or or
um uh irritating the heart or the mind there's a natural sense of uh being
more peaceful more subtle more calm and as we kind of stay continuous with the
breath um there's something that gets uh evoked um that is clearly a feeling of
pleasure or joy that is not in the breath itself but
is in the way the mind mind is getting organized and absorbed with the focus of attention it
turns out that there's something about the brain that when it gets really peacefully absorbed or attentive
gathered around a thing that it seems to release uh maybe it's releasing hormones
or something it tends to re release something something begins to be evoked and pleasure and joy that comes maybe
partly because with that kind of absorption um there's no longer a feeling of
unsafety there's no longer a feeling of discontent there's no longer a feeling
of of uh being oppressed or being being put upon or no longer being reminded of
all the responsibilities we have to accomplished all the things all the plans we have to do the to-do list all
these things that make us fragmented and cut up in tense begin kind of falling away and just that feels good
there's the pleasure of relief ah just here in a simple
way and um and of course it's not like this
direct kind of highway to pleasure but it's helpful to realize
that pleasure well-being contentment gratitude can coexist with the
opposite and um and uh and it starts kind of creating a different atmosphere
a different uh influence on ourselves when we kind of begin centering
ourselves on the more subtle sense of wellbe again not to push everything else
away but to appreciate that uh we will take care of the world ourselves better
when we're really centered and calm and peaceful in a way that samade creates
samade creates a kind of a capacity and power and ability to meet the world in a
full and open way and direct way so that we can care for the
world out of from the place that's the best in us we don't want to care from the world
from how we um um we don't want to care for the world from how we
um you know are aversive or angry or greedy or
afraid there's a there is possible to care for the world care for ourselves
from Beauty from peacefulness from Love and that's that's the kind of
wonderfulness of samade that it um as we grows we have the ability to respond to
the world in that way so thank you very much and um I hope
that on this day that that you'll smile more uh I'd like to offer
a you know a little bit tongue and cheek but little bit
serious that if you find a nice way to smile twice as much today as you
normally would um uh probably you'll have half as
much feeling that you have problems in your life may you smile and may you share
your smile and your Sparkle with those around you thank you