welcome everyone I'm definitely getting my tech lessons this
week um and I'm delighted to have your input that you can see and hear me so welcome back to our practice this
week of supporting the growth of samade for ourselves we're taking a little extra
time to practice the steps that Gil has already taught us and we're giving uh
ourselves a little longer sitting in the these mornings to allow more time in
silence for independent Discovery one of the ways Gil offered to
settle the mind was by attending to inhalation and exhalation with that
process of being with the sensations of breathing uh following them very
thoroughly in the foreground and then counting with each breath or each half
breath in the periphery in the background just as a way to keep the Mind present and free of
distraction a simple settled mind a still mind inclines towards
somebody so the settled quality is encouraged by a couple of
wholesome qualities of mind that are considered virtues uh in the poly language they're
called parami some of you have worked on these so one is
patience which I've come to think of as infinite patience because that was
something that uh really stuck with me that the teacher Annie nent said on a
long retreat that I took at IMs years ago infinite patience and I still feel
that phrase echoing inside me uh because the way I am living I'm happy to
continue to cultiv at some for as long as I have it's a beautiful practice it's an
interesting practice watching it unfold and it really does help to be
patient um I once inherited a healthy Ficus benjamina plant from a colleague
and it continued to thrive so well in my waiting room that it was growing along the ceiling so I read about taking a
cutting from a plant and starting a new plant and I took a/4 inch little Branch
about 4 in long and planted it in soil and then I watered it as
directed so week by week I watered and watered and by about the sixth week I
suddenly stopped and thought wait is this crazy I'm watering this stick and
nothing is happening should I keep watering so I didn't really know
but I for whatever reason I continued to water the stick and within a week a tiny
beautiful little green leaf appeared and then another and another and it grew
into a very healthy plant what was really interesting about that process
was I didn't have to know why it was that I continued to water see seemingly
nonsensically or I didn't need to solve it as a problem I just kept
watering so the kind of patience we sometimes need to bring well I certainly
need to bring to cultivating samade is a frame of of mind that is not only
patient but it's also willing to not know it's okay not to know what will
happen with somebody or when it will happen in fact it's better not to know
because if you know you're being driven by Concepts and ideas and that will not
result in somebody it's also a state of mind that
cultivates another of the virtues called parami and that is resolve or
persistence but this is a very gentle quiet kind of resolve it's not a
demand it's not a should it's not striving and
pushing it's just a willingness to keep coming back again and again without a
lot of flap so I'll share something that might sound a little
strange but the way that these virtues have worked for me is not by doing a
lot actually all I've done is whispered those phrases or a phrase when I've
needed it so when I've needed it infinite
patience or not knowing just at a challenging moment or
a moment I'm perplexed or gentle resolve and just by saying those things
just by Whispering that phrase in the mind the mind seems to settle
itself I find it's more settled in general at the start and then continues
to settle by returning to that Stillness and allowing whatever wants to unfold to
unfold so being okay with unpleasant things coming up or other things than
what we're practicing coming up patience infinite patience not knowing and just
continuing to be with the practice so with that we'll turn to the lightly guided
meditation
giving yourself time maybe for those settling
breaths and certainly for noticing how you are as you begin this meditation
are there any qualities of Mind any little phrases that are allies that you
think would be helpful to your practice feeling free in this practice
to very quietly coach yourself with a tiny whisper in the mind of any of these
things or things that are useful to you infinite patience
quiet
persistence and if words are too much at any time simply
radiating the intention feeling it almost physically
in the heart in the mind in the
body and also offering yourself encouragement with some good will to
begin the practice either with silent words in the
mind or again just radiating some of these
intentions may I be well
may I be free of all
harm may I receive experience with
patience may I allow myself not to have to know what is going to happen or when
it's going to happen
may I practice with gentle resolve
settled resting in Stillness may I be free of
dissatisfaction of stress of suffering
taking whatever time you need to relax the body and mind settle
it or bring ease to any area that cannot be relaxed reled or is
preoccupying
you coming gradually into
awareness of that quiet quiet deeper place
within and Gra gradually allowing yourself to turn
to following present with all of the
movements of breathing as the inhalation
arises travels through the
body as breathing pauses whenever it does that
and with the exhalation following the sensations of
breathing out the rise and
fall the expansion and
contraction returning again and again to Stillness
quietness resting in the Stillness in the quiet of following the
breathing in breath
out
breath using counting of the breath as a support your ability to keep the
breathing the sensations of breathing in the foreground fully aware
of the
movement
e e
if other experience arises in the mind meeting it as you would kindly meet
a friend coming alongside of it with awareness for a few moments and then
gradually turning the attention turning awareness back to
being with the breathing and perhaps bringing in
counting the half
breath whatever keeps you present in the foreground with breathing the sensations
of breathing it doesn't matter how many times you have to come
back just keep bringing awareness very gently back
as we come towards the end of the sitting radiating out any
benefit any moments of quiet
any virtues that you're developing allowing those to be
embodied so that you bring a level of peace and calm
to others around you who so need this right
now may all beings be well and
healthy may all beings be free from internal and external home
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free of
suffering allowing time to call different beings to
mind different people sincerely wishing
them health
safety peace
freedom
e for
as we continue with learning what supports the cultivation of
somadi we have this continued opportunity as well today to practice
mindfulness during daily life every time we
remember we can notice what kinds of mental activity we're engaged in at any
moment we come back to awareness and see whether it increases
impatience or encourages patience see what disturbs the mind and
what settles it what agitates it what gets it preoccupied or
ruminating ah thank you I will try to speak up oh I know what I've done I made the same mistake the other
day I forgot to turn original sound off so thanks for the reminder about
volume so as to go through the day practicing mindfulness sometimes aided
by others helping us remember um noticing during the day what is bringing
about uh the qualities that are not helpful or the
um Tendencies of mind that are less helpful and what things are supporting
the Tendencies of mind that are wholesome and helpful to you
one form of uh cultivating somat and settling is what I mentioned in these
first comments this morning naming what's happening making a mental note if it's
un wholesome no problem just make a mental note and sometimes that is part
of or sometimes it's enough of a reminder to help the Mind turn back and
align with what more helpful so if we can say to ourselves ah wanting is
arising I so want I so want to strive for
somebody okay that sort of helps the mind go does striving
help maybe not so naming what's happening mentally is very
helpful impatience or patience and then maybe using phrases like patience that
are helpful to you you'll find the ones that are helpful to you not knowing when
or how this is going to evolve come to fruition we don't need
to know that actually it won't help to know it because we'll try to shape it and that won't
work so this practice of naming things has worked amazingly well for me in
daily life and in meditation so sometimes when I've been sitting I've noticed when a particular
trend of Mind comes up and I can name doubt or comparing
mind or trying to push something away just by saying that to myself I can
feel oh I need to turn back or I don't even have to try it just sometimes
starts the Mind back towards what's more helpful of course not every state of mind
not every hindrance is going to respond to that sometimes we're so entangled we're so deeply into it already that
it's going to take some strength of mindfulness to come back to the
recognition of what we're thinking and uh questioning the thinking is this really helping me and often to make the
shift from the thinking from the tangle down into the body feeling the impact of that and
maybe breathing in and out of the impact noticing what isn't
working being patient with that even taking the time if you catch yourself
after a period of being caught no problem you've caught it you've noticed it and over time this will start to
unwind and relax these conditioned Tendencies of
Mind a clean conscience a mind that doesn't have the burden of
knowing that it's done anything harmful to oneself or to others really is
another support for settling in
Soma the eight-fold path practices that the Buddha offered are really wonderful
ways to come to wholesomeness in your life to resolve conflict and to become
more peaceful if you haven't learned those eight-fold path practices IMC
offers a program every year that's available on zoom and in person for
those who are living closer to Redwood City um that supports it usually you can
sign up for it in July or August and it starts in September and runs through May
so you can support yourself with these practices and learn more wholesome more
ethical Ways to Live
as the Mind becomes more settled it's easier than to detect a
ripple of what isn't helpful earlier on to catch it and we are already
cultivating many of the qualities I mentioned today simply by what we're doing turning the attention to the
breathing to the inhalation and the exhalation again and again quietly
counting in the background those are actually cultivating patience the more
we see oh it worked a little bit I am feeling a little more collected than I
did at the beginning of the sitting or day by day there's just a tiny bit of
shift noticing that is building resolve quiet persistence it's working I want to
continue with this and another thing that helps which we'll
get into more tomorrow is noticing is noticing this benefit is noticing
anything wholesome that's coming from this so again today the
invitation is to practice stronger mindfulness every time you remember
throughout the day notice what's happening with the mind and also to
maybe take a few minutes at a time out of the day when you remember to check in
with the breath check in with any internal quiet that is also there and as
I've been doing all week at 4 o'clock today I'll offer a silent 20 minute
sitting that will be on zoom and you can click on the IMC calendar to uh find the
zoom link and also the password for that so wishing you the benefit of this
practice today today and may our practice support everyone around us in
coming to Greater peace may all beings be free of
suffering thank you very much for your practice today