and welcome welcome everyone to
the series on the five elements and insight
very happy to be sharing these teachings with you this week and um I'd love to
have you either share with a friend now or later or in your heart what you've
noticed about practicing with fluidity water water element motion
in the last 24 hours
And as we're getting started
the invitation is to tune in again to your body
Perhaps taking a couple of longer slower breaths
Noticing the weight of your body on the cushion or chair
Feeling a sense of being grounded
Then allowing the breathing to be natural
and feeling into moisture on the skin
perhaps in your mouth in your breath moisture or dryness
And inviting the mind the heart to bring awareness of this
moment to the forefront
Feeling
into a sense of warmth or cool
Heat in the body Maybe coolness of the air on your skin
Maybe warmth of the sun or coolness of a cloudy day
Just checking in and in general
feeling into the change the shift
the flowing nature of all of these sensations
attuning more closely perhaps to the motion movement
of the breath If that's your anchor
or the overall flow of sensation
coming and going throughout the whole body
inviting the heart to rest the mind to settle
in this embodied moment
tuning in also to any resonance of warmth
or coolness in the mind and heart
Noticing without judgment any agitation
Meeting that with the warmth of kindness and compassion
Allowing mental activity to cool to calm
As you allow awareness to move inward and downward
settling into the body
feeling into the warmth vitality
of this body
One breath at a time
Almost practice in silence for a while
From time to time reconnecting
with the felt sensations of aliveness
The warmness or the cool
the weight or lightness
fluidity or stillness
In the last remaining moments of this formal meditation together
Imitation is to open up the aperture of awareness
Allowing all of present moment experience
to be included within it
Just moving through
And as we bring this meditation to a close
considering for yourself any
moments of goodness connection
presence or peace in In this meditation
letting them nourish your heart and practice
And then turning your attention and intentions
outwards towards all the others your life touches directly and indirectly
Cultivating the wish that they may benefit
That the benefits of our practice here together ripple out
to all of the lives we touch and all of the lives they touch outwards
and outwards
May all beings be safe happy
peaceful and free And may our practice here together be a
cause and condition for greater love liberation and peace in
the world
[Music]
Thank you for your practice
So today we are picking up on the third in a five-part series on
practicing with the elements in support of insight The five elements
those are earth water fire air and space And today we are on fire
So um and continue this exploration both in
terms of contemplation that's intentional consideration of these um
qualities of experience and how um the Buddha framed them talked
about them in the ancient teachings and direct experience of the quality of fire
element which I'll talk about in a moment in our own practice And then I'll drop in a little bit about um some of
the inspirations that he offered um both for fire and for fire going out
So that's where we're going And first to say the direct experience
of fire element it's very simple Sensations of warmth or cool or even hot
or cold And the function whether it's in our
core of our bodies or the earth's molten core or in a campfire is to heat
Simple right So noticing shifting and changing
sensations like we went over in the meditation of hot or cold warmth or cool
can be one more set of embodied experiences
that can highlight the sense of nature and constancy change
And it can be interesting to notice other conditions including external humidity or dryness or our
internal emotional and mental perceptions and filters impact even
something as basic as how we perceive heat or cool
I was just camping on a retreat and um it was really interesting to notice that
over the course of the week my tolerance for cool because there were some quite cold nights We were at altitude went up
and um that would have felt what would have felt uncomfortably cool here in Santa Cruz felt just fine there And the
perception of heat also shifted over the course of the retreat
And in part that's true because not just of acclimatization in our bodies but how
our minds relate So if one is agitated for example
much more likely to feel warmer perhaps even more bothered There's that term of course hot
and bothered right this is duka
However if one is very calm can be likely to feel cooler even in the
exact same external temperature Equinimity
not agitated either way There's a kind of an internal coolness that's more of a a mental quality that allows for shifts
and changes without getting caught up bothered or overly attached
In terms of contemplation the ancient teachings have a number of
simileies and idioms about fire both in terms of helpful qualities and unhelpful
qualities There are far too many to unpack in a
short little talk like this but I'll just touch on a few of the more important ones in sense of the tradition
So many many of the Buddha's simileies and metaphors associate fire with unhelpful qualities
The Buddha likened holding resentment towards others like picking up a hot
coal and holding it on holding on to it hoping that they will get burned
Doesn't work does it Also in his famous fire sermon
the Buddha said "All is burning." All is burning And in that he was referring to
all of our senses burning with greed or lust hatred and delusion
As I mentioned Monday this picks up on the Buddha was a
brilliant reframer and um repurposer of the cultural soup within which he lived
in ancient India and the um upanishads which emerged before the Buddhist time
and continued to be spoken recorded perhaps during his time We're not sure
because all of this was ancient and quite oral oral history But in the upanishads natural elements
like fire were considered qualities or potentialities imbued with life
So especially for example when fire was provoked
agitated it ignited And these same exact words for anger
that were used in the upupanachads were used in the Buddha's teachings And
they didn't just talk about the physical igniting
They spoke to the emotional resonances emotional processes
Today we use similar expressions burning with rage right
A mature practitioner an awakened person
they are released from this kind of burning by a cooling an inner cooling of
disenchantment Disenchantment with being drawn into the stories the myasma of reactivity
based on greed hatred and delusion based on
senses and ideas The ideas that come from what comes
through our senses The Buddha taught that letting go of
clinging also releases the fires of greed or hatred or delusion
And I personally think it's fascinating that the word for clinging and the word
for fuel for a fire are the same ancient word Upana
So what that means letting go and check it out for yourself Letting go of some obsessive want or grudge
releases dissolves reactivity And when someone completely frees their
mind the fires of greed hatred and delusion are released
blown out nibban or nirvana
There was an illusion to this in the poem that I read at the end of the first talk in this series and I'll just read
the very end of it This is from Patachara and it's based on
the terriata the awakening songs of the first women who practiced with the
Buddha I let my mind go and it flowed downhill
with the water toward my little hut I went inside sat on the bed and lowered
the wick of the lamp all by itself The flame went out
So fire released or as Tanisro calls it fire unbound
is one of the most important simileies for fully waking up for not burning with
reactivity And at times the Buddha's teachings he
used simileies to help communicate helpful qualities too simileies about fire that communicated helpful qualities
In fact the ancient tradition likens the eye remember we're back in the Bronze Age here the eye to a fire stick And
there's actually kind of a detailed anatomy that isn't that far off if you think of what they had available to them
about how fire and the eye are linked to sight to vision to light to clarity
And this gets picked up on in the later traditions because fires after all they don't just
emit heat they also radiate light
So this is my fanciful riff on fire element combined with water element
that heat plus water brings steam capacity and power
Light plus water can bring the beauty of shimmering waves or the breathtaking
moment of a rainbow on a metaphorical emotional level
We can connect with the warmth of care the heat of determination
And the Buddha advised his son Rahula to make his meditation like fire Anything
bad or disgusting thrown into fire is simply used as fuel burned up
You said if you make your meditation like fire agreeable and disagreeable things will
not invade the mind and remain
For me this teaching demonstrates that even the most unwanted experiences
can be fuel for awakening and that one kind of fire meditative fire can contain
the damage of the other of reactivity Kind of like a controlled burn
So to recap practicing with meditating on the sensations of hot and cold heat and
warmth and our relationship to those sensations
can help open us up to the perception of an constancy
and how our minds and hearts can shift
our relationship to experience including our relationship
to reactivity and to inconstancy itself
Noticing any clinging for or against coming through our senses is a first
step towards shifting from burning reactivity to coolness
and eventually to freedom So thank you for your kind attention And
your assignment should you choose to accept it over the next 24 hours is to
notice heat and coolness in your own direct experience and how you're
relating to it based on your own state in that moment
And for extra credit notice moments of clinging and reactivity
and moments where the clarity of light awareness emerges
Thank you so much for your attention Look forward to being back with you tomorrow