okay so let's go ahead and get started with our
theme and meditation for today
and I think we'll just jump right in so let's go ahead and start meditating together
finding a posture that has some ease in it
allowing the body to settle in to sitting or perhaps you're lying down
gently closing the eyes if that's comfortable for you
it's encouraged and bringing the attention inward
sensing the contact points
the chair or the cushion that you're sitting on or the bed
your legs or feet against the floor
just allowing yourself to be supported by what you're sitting on
and bringing gentle attention
to softening the body into meditation
softening the eyes in the eye sockets
softening the jaw
allowing the shoulders to relax
maybe drop a bit
softening down through the chest and the belly area
releasing tension in the arms and legs
and sensing if the body feels aligned
balanced
i have found this sense of alignment or balance to be dynamic
so it's not that I can set it at the beginning and then it's there
more that I attune to it and find it to be helpful to keep adjusting toward
balance
and then bringing in the quality of mindfulness
consciously attuning to clearly knowing what's happening in
experience in a simple gentle way
and as we've been doing throughout the week
I encourage choosing some kind of an anchor for
awareness for mindfulness a common one is the breath the
sensations of breathing in and out
or more general sensations in the body
or sometimes what feels most natural is to just connect to the sounds in the
environment people can find a lot of ease in the way
the sounds just come and go
we're not controlling them
and the idea of the anchor is simply to have a home base for the mind
it doesn't exclude other experiences i sometimes see it as foreground and
background so maybe putting the breath in the
foreground and then other things come and go
thoughts or sounds
more peripherally or background
and inevitably the mind will
sometimes catch on to one of these other experiences and then we find ourselves
thinking or distracted did oring out in some way
and the invitation for today
is to see the return to mindfulness as an opening of freedom in a certain
way once we know
that the mind is being say tempted by
something that it wants or something it would like to push away
if we see that just stepping back enough to see it is a
little bit of freedom
and there's a wonderful phrase that people use sometimes
noticing forces that would take the mind out of
balance you can say I see you Mara
mara representing the forces of destruction
and then simply returning
to the anchor in the foreground and resting with experience
seeing Seeing the flow of the mind
and seeing the forces that distract
as somehow not really us
like winds that blow through
or Eddie is in a stream
and when we don't believe them or buy into them then the mind remains free
simple
and as we practice with
seeing the flow of the mind and its distractions
We begin to gain a sense of confidence
ah it is possible
it is possible to see just before the mind slips away
maybe there's a little wavering or a little flutter of energy
and there can be a moment where we see that and the mind doesn't go off
maybe it goes off again the next time but having seen that
there's increasing confidence
in the mindfulness in strengthening awareness
just seeing in this gentle clear way
and as we come toward the end of this sitting
sensing that just as in sitting We started to realize
ah many things can be seen
carrying this out into the world we can also bring a sense of confidence
that it's possible to notice the state of our mind
to be able to see things reactions perhaps
before we say something
and understanding that this way of seeing clearly and with a caring
attitude will protect others as well as ourselves
and sometimes it helps to have a deliberate sense of yes
I know this can work not every time
mindfulness goes up and down but yes this is a way that continues to
support me and others and as I practice it it becomes stronger
potentially it's always possible to see the mind
and to realize how wonderful how wonderful that possibility
of bringing our care to the world in whatever it is that we're doing
in support of ourselves and others may our mindfulness
and our practice be of support to those around us
may all beings partake of the goodness of this path
[Music]
okay so our our dharma path of insight continues today
uh through practice the mind is learning to see rather than
fall into things like greed hatred and delusion that come up in the mind
and we start to understand through the journey of insight that these issues are
not really us you know we're not a greedy person inherently
it's just that wanting and grasping can arise in the mind due to certain conditions
and as our view becomes clearer and more accurate we can gain some confidence in this
skill of seeing clearly so we're using the animal similes this
week as a way to understand the path and today we turn to the deer
in sutas deer generally have a positive connotation
so we talked about the cow yesterday and notice that deer and cows are
similar in the sense that both of them are herd animals
but cows are domesticated and handled by humans whereas deer are wild so they're
inherently freer more independent-minded maybe they have to be somewhat smarter
and tougher than cows by virtue of living in the wild
and so in the Buddhist texts the deer is a symbol of not being tied down they
have some measure of strength and independence and yet at the same time deer can still
be led astray or trapped or hunted so they're still in some ways vulnerable
and need some protection but overall these qualities add up to deer tending
to represent a person who is on the path so someone who is making their way to
freedom so there's a text called the napa suta
which means the bait that contrasts different herds of deer in how they
relate to a trapper's traps and starts out by noting that the deer
trapper has bad intentions for the deer right deer trappers laying down traps
and this is likened to the way Mara goes to distract or take over a meditator's
mind or person's mind and
deer trappers uh lay down this bait with the hope that the deer will unwittingly
eat the bait and become intoxicated and then be at the trapper's mercy and then
in the same way Mara in the form of our own habits can trick us into becoming
unmindful and then we become vulnerable remember at the beginning of the week we
talked about how the quail and the monkey stray out of their ancestral domain of mindfulness and that's when
they can be harmed or trapped or attacked so when we believe the stories that our
mind tells us or when we identify strongly with things that come up like
anger or envy then we could say that we are intoxicated like the deer we've
taken the bait and then we're likely to do things that bring harm and in
Buddhist understanding we would say then Mara can do with us as he will
so that's kind of the framework for understanding these uh herds of deer
that are described in this suta so it's said that the first deer uh goes
right in among the bait and gets trapped so they don't pay any attention and this
is like somebody who lives without is always falling into great hatred and
delusion always suffering the consequences of those kinds of mind states in their life
and then the second herd of deer sees what happened with the first herd so
they're they're learning by watching the others and this second herd decides to
ignore the bait uh shun the bait they just try to avoid it but then it happens
that uh near the it says near the end of the hot season so dear this is a time
when there isn't much water available they lose their resolve and they eat the
paint anyway so they also get trapped and so this is a little bit like trying
to avoid hindrances or difficulties by bypassing or ignoring them you know
we close our eyes or we plug our ears and say la we don't associate with any irritating
people we just try to restrict our life so that we don't have things that bring
up the challenge you know or hindrances in some way that kind of works but it's
artificial we're trying to control the outside to prevent uh in order not to
have those things come up in us and eventually that will break down so
that's not actually the path to freedom is just avoiding things that um we find
difficult in some way so then the third bird of deer is trying
to learn both of the other ones so they don't want to do those things and they decide to be clever and they do live
within the range of the trapper but they're very cautious about what they eat and they hide at night so um they
but the trapper is able to add extra surveillance and see where they are
hiding the trapper notices that they're being very careful about what they eat and don't eat even though they're right
there among the bait so the trapper adjusts and adds in extra
surveillance this is a way in which Mara is actually adaptable you know when we
try to avoid Mara in some way Mara might change his tactics too the mind is
subtle and clever he finds ways to be distracted even when we think we've
solved one issue way and so the trapper is still able to
this third herd of deer into eating the bait anyway
so the Buddha likens people like this to like this to want to adopt certain views
so they live their life seemingly peacefully because they're adhering to
some kind of a fixed view but they're not really responding authentically they're living more in an idealized
world in some way so this is a little bit more subtle kind of way of being caught to avoid seeing comments about
the um sound issues i'll check into that
hang in there please and then the um the fourth bird also
and so they make their home outside the range of
in this case the described as Jas or samadei practice in
the person so when the mind is deeply in the present moment and practicing
meditation like concentration hindrances cannot take hold in the mind and it's
said that mara is temporarily blindfolded when the mind is practicing
especially so
at the beginning of this Here
we become free of free of creatorally
we can use that samade insight and suta then goes on to say that if somebody is
used for insight completely can become free
so here are smart first of all they can learn by watching others and smart
meditators can outsmart mara in certain ways and the you know translating to a
dharma lesson it's through the training of our mind and especially by practicing
samati and even janna that uh this is all part of the path of the
forces of harm in our mind and hence in the world isn't really a way that we can
just fiddle with things externally and become completely free doesn't work that
way we have to train through the inside particularly through these um deep
mental trainings of orienting the mind around a concentration object in some
way so this is a an extended analogy let's say
for the path where we do what we can externally to try to avoid the bait of mara but all of that is for the purpose
of getting the mind into a concentrated state from which we can do insight
practice and really see down to the roots of suffering now the deer analogy goes on into many
other sutas they talk about how deer live confidently because of this
adaptability and intelligence so for example in the one of the sutas where
the Buddha talks about his own awakening he gives an analogy to a deer and he
says suppose a forest deer is wandering in the forest wilds he walks confidently
stands confidently sits confidently and lies down confidently why is that
because he is out of the hunter's range so there's something about the deer you
know when practice becomes clear in us and we're understanding what we're doing
we're not free yet completely but we kind of know how to walk the path there's a confidence that comes with
confidence that comes from our own stability inside
and this is where the gentle you know ongoing practice of the cow that we
talked about yesterday trusting in the instructions just continuing to follow
them it bears fruit into the deer of the confidence of yeah this really does work
i'm not free yet but I I can see the path and there's a lovely story of a monk
named who was a former king so he used to live a royal life with a lot of guards
protecting him but he became much happier when he gave all that up and
became a monk lived openly in the forest and it says uh he has a quote that he
says formerly was a lay person in the land my guard was well organized within
and without the royal compound within and without the city and within and without the country although I was
guarded and defended in this way I remained fearful scared suspicious and
nervous these days even when alone in the wilderness at the foot of a tree or in
an empty dwelling I am not fearful scared suspicious or nervous i live
relaxed unwled surviving on alms my heart free as a wild deer
so in this you know we have this you can do what you can externally to protect yourself
of meditative development of developing the mind in some way is what really
frees the heart wild deer we start to see the deer in us maybe the
the essence of the deer in us as we practice longer as we have more insights
we start to see clearly and start to understand something about how
suffering comes about how the mind gets drawn into it and how it gets free of it
and it all starts to feel like a process we don't yet but we see the path so is
about healthy humility in a certain way tear is about healthy dignity and
confidence going as far as overconfidence or conceit dear can still
be trapped they can still take the pain they can still be hunted but starting to
trust in our heart of sense of confidence and dignity
by vitality and confidence in a certain way
may we discover the dear within us as we continue to walk the path of its states
tomorrow thank you so much for hanging in there