well good evening everyone welcome my name is Jim Podolski i'm
filling in for Diana tonight as she's u off on
retreat over the last couple weeks she's been giving a number of talks that have included talking about the um five
hindrances and so I wanted to give a talk tonight that included
that um if you've been around this
dharma scene a while you've probably heard about the the eight-fold
path it's a foundational paradigm for our the
Buddhist tradition that we practice in the Tarvadan tradition um it's kind of a way of
organizing the most important practices that the Buddha
taught so that one if one is interested in
um experiencing uh liberation freedom from greed delusion and hatred greed uh
freedom from um duca which is sometimes translated as
suffering or dissatisfaction or in maybe common terms just the
bummerness of life um then these practices that the Buddha
um described that are in the eight-fold path um are really the way to get
there uh the first uh these all these eight path elements
are all interrelated and so it's not like you cultivate one and then
cultivate the next and cultivate the next
um but for purposes of talking about them it's easiest to to kind of make them into a a linear pattern so the
first two are um right view or the wisdom factors right view which is
uh really starting to look at your experience through the
um frame of the forable truths which is
seeing that there is suffering in your life seeing that there is dooka that there is um either just mild discontent
all the way to just out and out
um you know uh sort of almost unbearable
uh conditions and that it's important to
see what what's that coming from you know that it's coming from our clinging
to something and that there's a possibility
for the ending of that and then the fourth noble truth is the eight-fold
path this is the way to achieve
freedom so that's the first of the path factors the second one is right intention having intentions of being um
uh letting go of greed letting go of ill will letting go of harming of others um
that those those intentions really kind of set us
um uh on a path to be able to be free you know if we're trying to be free but
also um harming ourselves or harming others uh that's not going to
work uh the next set of the next part of the eight-fold path
are what they call the the ethical part developing right right speech right
action and right livelihood and those mostly have to do with how we
interact with others how we interact with uh other people one-on-one or in
communities or um you know in
groups so those all involve cultivation of uh
appropriate action towards others and then finally the the the
third set is the samadei set which involves wise effort wise mindfulness
and wise concentration
um and in this
um um center often people start with
right mindfulness and right concentration you know kind of wanting to develop
um a mind that is aware of what's happening as it's
happening and a mind that can be steady and focused so that it's not jumping all
over the place
um so tonight I'm going to talk about wise effort
um because the eight-fold path is so uh foundational to this practice uh IMC
offers a course every year a nine-month course going through each of these eight
um path factors and it just so happens this month they're doing wise effort so
that's why that's on my mind
um I was inspired by something that Gil said yesterday morning
um when you start the practice with something like developing mindfulness and
concentration there is a cultivation going on and often and most of it is
around observing most of it is about no you know developing a sense of awareness
of what's going on as it's going on um and being able to stay with it in
a very steadied steady and settled way or at the very least noticing that
you're not in a stable and uh steady way that the the mind is
jumping around and at least noticing that so those two really involve
primarily observing wise effort really involves
cultivating so it's not just noticing what's going on but it's
also making some effort you know uh actually using
whatever um
uh agency we have whatever choice we have to make to choose what we pay
attention to what kind of mind states
you know or states of the heart and the mind that we're um cultivating and which ones were um
uh eliminating so right effort really
um is much more of the kind of the active cultivating part of this practice
although it also includes the observing part you know you have to observe what's
going on so that you know how how to do the cultivation uh one of the descriptions
for wise effort is it's kind of like gardening right you know
you things start to grow up out of the ground and you have to decide which one
which of these things are what you want to develop what
you want to cultivate and and which are the weeds which are the things that um
really um are going to sap the the nutrients and the strength and the light from
those things that you want so so there are weeds that need to be pulled up and
in the same way we can think of our heart and mind as being like a garden
um so the first thing we need to be able to recognize is what are the
plant what are the things that are weeds and what are the things that are the plants that you want to
grow the the weeds are often referred to as unh wholesome mind states you might
also call that um unbeneficial or
afflictive you know what are you know the mind states that are like an affliction to
us and which are the which are the ones that that we want to uh encourage
so in some ways we have to we have to figure that out for ourselves you know
you you have to figure out which which you know which which which states of mind really
um aren't helpful to my development and which ones are
some of the guidance on that comes from this book by uh Bonte
Gunaratna see this one is called Eight Mindful Steps to Happiness
um and one of the one of the um
characteristics of the unh wholesome states um are that they
include the five hindrances and you may have heard Diana
talk about the five hindrances over the last couple weeks the first one is greed you know
that sense of um not just wanting but sort of in a
wanting in a
um afflictive way in in sort of a
uh you say sort of addictive way so uh greed sensual desire
um lust are some of the stronger forms of
that um when those are
operating it's hard to see what's going on right you know
they they become so enticing that all we see is what we
want and we don't necessarily see the harm that's coming to us or
others as we try to grasp for um more and more
the the second let's see
yeah the second hindrance or family family of hindrances it's it's really a
spectrum is um aversion or ill will or hatred
and whereas with greed we're trying to hold on to something usually something that can't
be held on to i mean pleasant only can be pleasant for so
long um with with aversion it's really trying
to push away those things that oftentimes can't be pushed away
and so there there can be a lot of
um a lot of suffering that that's generated from trying from being in that
state of um
aversion so those are the two biggest hindrances
the other three um the next two come in pairs the the
next one is sloth and torper that's where
there's little or no energy either one of them is little or no energy in the
mind you know sort of a dullness or little or no energy in the body you know
sort of drowsiness and when we're in if one or
both of those is operating then it's it's hard to see what's going on
um because we just we we don't have a a bright enough awareness a strong enough
awareness of what's going on the fourth hindrance is again is a
pair for body and mind which is uh restlessness and worry
so restlessness uh unlike sloth and torper restlessness
and worry is an overabundance of energy you know so the body just you know can't
sit still and worry is often the mind can't
sit still right it's just it's going all over the place and so when that's
operating again it it's it's hard to imagine that you can really
um settle down and and find
peace and then the fifth hindrance is doubt
and or skeptical doubt and and doubt keeps us going around in circles
you know it's kind of like a dog chasing its tail it's just you know should I be doing this or should I be doing
something else and it never resolves uh what it reminds me of is
when I learned computer programming in the early 1970s the program of choice was
Forran and it was possible to write a program that would have a loop in it
that would never reach a termination criterion it would just go
and go and go until the operator showed that your job
had run out of resources it had run out of time and then it would just get terminated so doubt can be kind of like
an infinite loop it just never
um on its own it can just keep
going there are some other more subtle forms of uh these unh
wholesome mind states that are called the 10 fedters and that's too long of a
list for me to go through tonight but if you look up the ten feathers it's it's on the internet they they tend to be
more subtle um experiences that keep us from being
totally free but some of them only
um are totally resolved when you become an arot so I I wouldn't start there i'd start
with the
hindrances yeah so So the first thing is to to learn for
yourself what are the unh wholesome mind states and what are the wholesome mind states
and it occurred to me as I was uh thinking about this
that in my mind one of the things that distinguishes wholesome mind states from
unh wholesome mind states is that wholesome mind states tend to be
associated with uh letting go and opening
up and unh wholesome mind states tend to be around closing down contracting and
grasping so that's a kind of a general criterion but you know when when you
find yourself you know kind of getting more and more contracted either physically or
mentally or holding more tightly grasping things more tightly that may be a sign that that
that the mind state that you're in um isn't going to lead to a life of peace
and freedom right so and likewise when you're in a state where
um you know there's a an openness a letting go some sense of generosity and
kindness um that you're on the right track so
that's that's kind of a general way to describe those two categories
right effort then consists of four activities the
first one is um preventing the arising of unarisen
unh wholesome mind states so how do you do
that well I think for me it starts
by falling into a lot of unh wholesome mind states and then over time you start to
recognize what caused that unh wholesome state to arise what are what are the
causitive factors what
um what triggered
it and then as you start to see what the causitive factors are that
bring forth that kind of a state you have a better chance of catching it before either before it
starts at all or before it gains much
momentum so I I probably have told this story before when I was
about 3 years old my father was doing a home
improvement job on our house
and when he would get frustrated when something would go wrong he would start to
swear and I was in the bedroom watching him work and all of this stuff and then at
some point I walked out of the bedroom into the living room and I started repeating some of these words I heard my
father use i had no idea what they meant i was telling my mother all of these words all these swear words and she was
a ghast um but I realized that
nowadays or for most of my life when I would do something where frustration would start
to arise where something would start going wrong almost immediately one or
more of those words would come out of my mouth and when I wasn't aware of that if
if I just let that go it would go from just being a mental
activity to my whole body would start to get agitated you know I I you know that
frustration could really could really build you know I'd just be ready
to I don't know you know throw a tool or something
nowadays i mean recently I was doing a plumbing project at home
and if you've ever worked underneath a sink and it's not much room and sure
enough one thing went wrong and I found myself you know swear word coming out of my
mouth but nowadays when I hear that I could go "Oh yeah that's a sign i must be
frustrated there must be frustration here." And so I stopped what I was doing
i thought about it i reread the instructions and I was able to proceed
without having to go through this really contracted agitated state of
frustration
so for the first one for the preventing really requires us to get to know what
are the warning signs what you know what you know it might be that you have to go
and talk with some particular coworker that just seems to trigger you
um you know or or anger or
um or what what triggers desire you know I mean I can sit on
on the website of Apple and look at this one particular laptop and it's like oh
god if I had that laptop you know I mean it's got 64 gigs of memory and it's you
know it's got 24 cores and all this other stuff um it's useful to look at it
and if it makes sense to buy it but to just sit there and look at it over and
over again and and you know kind of obsess about it uh you know
that's after a while it's actually kind of tiring and um doesn't feel very good
so for preventing that that one really requires
getting to know getting to know how your mind works
so that you can get those warning signs but you can't prevent all of them
you know things get through you know some some unh wholesome minds they just
they come so fast that before you know it you're you're in it they've arisen
and so the second one is abandoning un arisen unh wholesened mind
states and that there the Buddha gave some well number one was mindfulness is
always helpful being mindful really can help but for arisen on on wholesome mind
states he had a five element strategy the the first one
was if possible see if you can just ignore it like okay yeah yeah that's
right yeah that's anger or that's greed and then just drop it now you
might be able to do that if it isn't so strong the second one is to divert your
attention from that thought to some better thought you know so just
um you know yeah anger is here but I can also here's some other things I can
think about and so just divert your attention from what's unh wholesome to
something that's more wholesome
the third one is replacing the unh wholesome
thought with its opposite
so for example if greed is is arisen in your uh
mind you might think about generosity
you know you might try to replace those thoughts of greed with thoughts of
generosity uh the fourth one
involves the two parts one is it it can involve deciding well let's just
investigate what this unh wholesome um mind state is like how does how does
it feel in the body um and is this something that I want is
this where I want to hang out
and you can also look at what are the what are the causes that came together
for this to arise and notice that all of those causes are impermanent that they'll
arise and pass and so this whole unh wholesome mind state is also impermanent
so it's not like when anger arises it isn't that that's going to be there for
the rest of your life it's just it's arisen it's temporary and it and it'll
pass and then the final one which I thought I' always was kind of surprised it
sounds kind of harsh is there's sometimes when there's an unh wholesome mind state where you just have to use
force of will to kind of like wrestle it to the ground and
um I thought well that doesn't really is that what the Buddha said um you know but I started to think
you know there are times when people are just overcome with some really harmful
destructive impulse you know think of you know
well somebody harming another person you know injuring them or even killing them
and often it's just a spontaneous thing where the you know the state of mind is
is is strong and so it's in those cases it's really important to be able to have
a strong enough practice and strong enough effort to to be able to tell yourself no no I'm not going to do
this no I'm not going to tell a boss you know what a you know blankety blankie is
you know I'm just you know that may seem like you know it would be
so satisfying but it would only be satisfying for you know a few seconds and then you'd realize that
um it it harmed a relationship it harmed who knows what it harmed but um so being
a you know as a as a last gasp there there may be times when an
unh wholesome mind state really has to be dealt with with as much force and energy as as as possible
so then um so for unh wholesome mind states
there's the preventing and the abandoning and then for wholesome mind states there's the cultivating the
unarisen wholesome state
and one of the ways the the first thing that comes to my mind when I think about
cultivating a wholesome mind state is practicing some of the uh loving
kindness the Brahma Biharas um cultivating uh well-wishing for
others uh sympathetic joy uh compassion equinimity
um again those those qualities of mind that um are expansive you know that are
open-handed um there's also the uh the paramese some
of the foundational practices for for this for this um school of
Buddhism things like uh generosity you know being generous both
to yourself and to others um
uh offering safety to people through living an ethical
life
um being patient truthful
all of those all of those are some of the wholesome states of
mind uh and there's there's more it's it's really up to you to to discover
them for yourself which which ones really seem to support you give you a
sense of uh well-being a sense of uh
living in harmony and happiness
and then the final one is um maintaining so maintaining a risen
wholesome mind states so once you've
cultivated you know something like loving
kindness how do you maintain it you know that it that
it there may be a some momentum to it and that's great and it may also require
you know some continual effort to keep it going
one of the practices that I was taught many years ago and I've I've used
um when I travel is when when I go to an an airport you know you're often sitting in the waiting area you know for your
flight to be called and your group and so forth
um and for me it can
be a little stressful even though I've got my ticket everything's lined up I've got my
baggage still there's um you know strange people I don't know and uh who
knows what's going to happen and so one of the practices since I have nothing
else to do is I sit there and as people walk by on the
concourse I um I wish them well you know somebody
I've never met just walking by you know may you be safe may you be
happy may you be healthy may you be peaceful i don't say
it out loud but you know it's just it's just
um why not you know it's um it may or may not affect them but it
definitely affects me you know I go from feeling like I'm sitting in a group
of strangers who may or may not be hostile
I don't know to feeling like I'm I'm sitting with other I'm surrounded by other human
beings that I can wish well for and
that's it's easy to maintain that um you know
for 20 minutes or however long it you know it takes from when I get to the gate to when I get on the plane and of
course even once you're on the plane it doesn't have to stop
um I think as you start to feel how good it feels to
be in one of those mind states then there's more of a natural tendency to just want to stay there to just um keep
it going
i remember years ago Gil have saying this thing and I'm I can't remember it exactly the way he said it but it was
like when you have a sense of peace and ease what is important enough for you to
give that up like why would you what would you give that up for what would be so
important that you'd say "Okay well I'm okay i'm going to get rid of my peace of
mind." So I think the maintaining part you know also
takes effort um I suspect that there are
people who have practiced long enough that it's just kind of second nature it just keeps going but for those of us
that are still
um still affected by unh wholesome mind states
it's something we need to do
um over the last year or so I've I've been finding that um I don't sleep so
well at night and when I wake up in the morning the first thing when I wake up
is I feel kind of groggy and kind of averse to getting out
of bed and I could just lay there and go
"Oh poor me." You know why isn't life better and
uh you know why you know why didn't I get a better night's
sleep but instead what I do nowadays when I wake up the first thing I do is
that I notice that's the kind of mind state that's operating that's that's
what's going on and so rather than trying to do anything at all
complicated I just start by paying attention to my breath i just lay in bed
and I just I just do breath meditation
and one of the things that that does is I notice
um my breathing slows down and also my heartbeat slows down
i've had some stances put in a few years ago and so I notice sometimes when I
first wake up my heart beats seems a little fast and a little erratic and by
just doing breath meditation my breath and my heartbeat just really
um even out so there's a physiological component of doing breath
meditation in the morning um also some of that drowsiness goes away i I start
feeling more energy so doing so starting the day with
breath meditation really seems to make a difference to the mind
states and to the body and then then I may also then go
into loving kindness practice just um you know kind of see whoever whoever
comes to mind first just okay it doesn't really matter just who who comes to mind this morning I start doing loving
kindness for them and
then I don't set a particular amount of time I just decide to do it
until it's clear to me I'm ready to face the day i'm ready to get out of bed and I'm ready to
um you know face whatever uh the day
holds and it sets a tone you know it kind of sets a tone that
okay you can start your day by doing by applying right effort it isn't something
that you can wait till the end of the day till 9 at night after your last television
program is over and it's like okay well now now I'll do right effort or wise
effort you can start your day with it you can
um find creative ways throughout the day to to tune into what's going on in
my mind right now and is is this what I want or is there some way that I could
um change it i mean a lot of what happens in our lives is just habit it's just you know
it's it's it's not it's not necessarily something that
we can change instantaneously but we do have some agency we do have some choice
and by using the choice that we have we can cultivate
uh a more wholesome uh state of mind
and then the final thing that I'll say
is the practice only is effective if you do
it so you can hear as many talks as you want about right effort or any kind of
practice you can listen you can read books you can hear podcasts everything else all of that's very useful all of I
know all of that cognitive learning is useful but it's not enough you if you
want the practice to make a difference you got to do it
so I think that's the the the key take-home about um right effort is is
um you have to start paying attention well if you want the benefits you need
to uh make the effort so thank you
all we've got a few minutes if anyone has any
questions yeah Manny could you maybe Yeah either one of those
microphones should work
and then push push the button until the green light comes on
so I'm just going to add on uh what you said about just doing the practice um
I've found out that through through my personal journey that um when I'm
practicing in person so like with multiple people but doing it with consistency um maybe getting a little
bit obsessive with it uh that's when I found it to be most beneficial so just
adding on what you you said okay thank you find it useful thanks okay anyone
else also thank you for doing that oh you're
welcome all right well um thank you all for coming and Diana will be back next week
and I'll stay around afterwards if anyone wants to come up and ask me any question further questions so thank you
all