Welcome to our morning meditation and
I in coming down here this morning I Good
morning. I felt uh kind of happy uh with the idea of what I'm going to
talk about today. Then today I'm going to introduce the second insight which is
the conventionally in English we say uh the insight into suffering
and uh and why someone like me would be happy to come down talking about it um
when it could be a seemingly very depressing thing to talk about maybe as part of the the message.
So for today's meditation uh I'd like to suggest um four words
that can guide you through the meditation. And uh the four words are don't make it
worse. Whatever you do when you meditate don't make the situation worse for yourself.
And um and to um go further with it,
I'll do a little bit of guided meditation and set the stage for why this is so useful.
But um uh track yourself, monitor yourself. A
very important part of mindfulness is this selfmonitoring.
And so you know what you're doing. You know, if you
start thinking about things and uh having that train of thought is not good
for you, it's making the situation worse. If you're tracking about how you're
relating to the meditation practice, uh maybe you're straining or judging it,
your experience, and you can feel how it makes things worse. It makes you feel worse. It drains the energy or is, you
know, difficult. And uh don't believe that you have to
have these thoughts, these attitudes, this way of practicing. Make an adjustment.
Choose the choose the choose to not make the situation worse.
At least kind of go back to doing what you were doing before you started to do that.
So to assume meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and in a slow comfortable way
take some fuller breaths.
And as you After you breathe in fully,
comfortably in a comfortable way, have an extended
exhale. Ride the exhale to the end.
And then to Keep doing that for a few moments. But
as you exhale, relax your body. Soften
into here.
And then to let your breathing return to normal
and to start the important work
of relaxing as you exhale.
Relaxing, softening the muscles of the face.
Breathing normally, but feeling the face as you inhale, relaxing
as you exhale.
As you inhale, feel the shoulders.
On the exhale, soften the shoulders.
And then as you exhale, inhale,
feeling the belly, softening the belly on the exhale.
As you inhale, feel the thinking mind.
And as you exhale, soften the thinking mind.
As you breathe in, feel how you are emotionally, mood,
attitude. And as you exhale,
relax, soften around your mood, how you feel.
And then finding the settling place, the grounding place
for your breathing. Maybe where the exhale ends,
the inhale begins.
And as you exhale, relax into settle into the grounding place.
As you inhale, allow breathing to arise from that
place.
As you breathe in, feel whatever calm
there might be here. And as you exhale,
let the calm spread. Open to receive more of the calm.
As you breathe in, feeling whatever degree of ease,
easy feeling of being alive that you have.
And as you exhale,
let yourself settle more into a sense of ease.
And now from the vantage point of your ease,
whatever calm or relaxation you have, let that highlight for you, help you see
and feel any way that you are make you make it
worse. Any ways that you strain or
contract, any way you start
being caught in thoughts, ideas that
make the situation worse for you.
And for these few minutes, any thought or idea you have
that that somehow makes you feel worse, makes situation worse.
For the duration of the meditation, you do not need to believe those
thoughts. You don't have to believe what you're believing.
that makes the situation worse for these minutes.
Let go of whatever makes it the situation worse. No matter how small the
movement is, stay close to your ease
and notice when you start losing it.
There's a way that being caught in thoughts,
even good thoughts, is a form of alienation.
Separation from a deeper sense of inner well-being.
That maybe is felt to be in intimately connected
to the inner sensations of breathing.
An easeful breath.
Find find within you where you feel the most ease
or the most calm.
and let go of anything that takes you away from that
for the last few minutes. Breathe with your ease.
Breathe with your calm, trusting
that the best place to be is right in the middle of it.
And as we come to the end of the sitting,
taking a few moments to appreciate
if you can that there can be an inner reference
point of calm, of ease,
of stillness. Maybe spaciousness
that can be an important reference point
for seeing more clearly how you lose those
how they're reference point for notice. Noticing what you start doing that loses
touch with that.
And right there with that information
is where wisdom can support us.
The wisdom not to sacrifice our well-being
for the activities of mind that bring stress,
tightness, agitation.
Don't make it worse.
And in being ready to go into the world of people and work and activities,
communities. How might this
simple phrase support you
to be in the world in a nice way? supportive way for others.
Don't make it worse. If what you're going to say or do is
going to make the situation worse, maybe don't do anything
until you can find what makes it better.
May it be that this meditation practice, mindfulness practice
supports us in not making this world worse,
not challenging our relationships.
May it be that we go about our day caring for
everyone, including ourselves. And in that care,
may we keep in the forefront the idea that may others be happy,
may others be safe, may others be peaceful,
may others be free.
And may we contribute to this.
[Music]
Thank you.
So hello and welcome to this next talk on the insight series
and I've decided that uh it's time to move on to the second insight.
The first insight is is insight into the inconstant nature of our experience.
the impermanent changing nature of experience as we experience it.
And there's a lot of wisdom that comes from becoming attuned, seeing clearly the
impermanent in constant nature of it all. And part of it is the ability
to uh to hold our ground to be present in a non-reactive way to find our
stability in the face of change and this becomes invaluable
when we come to the second insight and in English is usually said to be the
word that for duka is translated as imper is as translated as suffering.
It's a big word and maybe it's not quite the best way of characterizing the word
duka, the poly word, ancient word, but for now
uh what's wonderful about this word suffering is people do suffer.
And the second insight implies that we're learning how to
be present for suffering. Not to turn away, not to close our eyes, not to uh
avoid, but a very honest and clear recognition that there is suffering.
And uh this ability for Buddhists, this orientation for Buddhists to be very
clear, clear clearheaded, clearminded and have be a willingness to yes their
suffering uh is a radical thing to do when many people are avoiding their suffering at
all costs. Some people are unwilling to be present for their discomfort, present
for their distress. They distract themselves. They uh medicate themselves.
They uh run away, escape,
distract themselves. And um sometimes there's wonderful strategies
of blaming and attacking and looking outside.
Sometimes we do things of feeling suffering, but we don't just face it directly and see it. We believe in it.
We got overcome by it. We uh collapse into it.
And what Buddhism is saying is uh yes there is suffering in this world. Be
present for it. See it clearly. See it from a place of stability.
Not in a certain kind of way. Uh attitude that's not for or against it.
Even if there's suffering we're going to fix and try to change, there's ability to hold a place of just being willing to
be present, to see it clearly, and to be honest about it, an honest recognition
that this we have suffering in ourselves, in the world around us.
And then um and then to appreciate
that it's invaluable to see it, to know it. If what we want
to do is to become free of it, if what what we want to do is to address the
suffering uh in a beneficial way. All the ways of
avoiding it, all the ways of being collapsing under the weight of it uh
tend to make the situation worse. And the idea in Buddhism, don't make it
worse if you have a choice. And when there's suffering in the world and there's huge,
you know, challenges in our world, it's always been there. Um and um and it's
very unfortunate that uh the attitude, the beliefs, the
emotions, the reactions we have to what goes on in the world around us, we're actually making it worse.
Um it's bad enough some of the things that go on but then uh we despair or get
angry or blame or or um or
all kinds of ways in which we respond to it that we're adding second arrows.
We're adding to the weight of the suffering. So uh so for example
if um if I'll give a silly little example that
um if someone invites you to their house and they
um for a meal and and you come and just as you come they burn the meal
and uh so they're angry with themselves, they're angry with the food, they're angry with their stove and they're even
irritated that you're there and it's very uncomfortable
and it's an uncomfortable situation. How can we make the situation worse? We
might make it worse by being angry with them. We might make it worse by blaming
ourselves for coming too late. We might whatever. We might make it worse by by
um um running away. We might make it worse by
um trying to fix the charred food. Um there all kinds of ways we make
the situation worse than it has to be. Our contribution is to show up and react
in such a way that we make that we're contributing more suffering to the situation making it worse. It's bad
enough to begin with. Don't add it add anything to it. And so when things are
happening on a national level or global level and people are doing things which
we feel quite distressing and upsetting that they're that they're causing a lot of suffering.
Don't add even more suffering to the world by your reaction,
but do have a clear le level-headed looking at seeing this is suffering, but
I'm not going to suffer because of it. That is a radical thing to do.
That is a phenomenal thing to do to be able to see and be present for suffering
and show up in such a way that we're not going to suffer because of that
suffering. Even if someone is harming us
which that we should stop but we can make it worse for ourselves
for the attitudes the attachments the reactions that we have. And so as we learn to meditate in
mindfulness as we learn to be present for experience not trying to have a good
experience not trying to avoid being uncomfortable. One of the most powerful things about
mindfulness practice is learning to be comfortable with being uncomfortable. A
willingness to be have a stable, clear, honest mindfulness. And we really be
present for what's there. If we only know how to be present when things are
deeply going well and calm and relaxed and peaceful and we're riding on a cloud
of samadei, uh we're not really getting the benefits of this practice. The benefits of the
practice come when we're able to be calm and still enough to be able to look
suffering right in the eyes, say, "I see you." and not add more suffering on top of it.
So even if we're suffering personally inside to learn to be able to see that clearly,
kindly, openly, and don't add second, third, and fourth arrows to it.
This is invaluable and very important. And so that's why we're learning to
track ourselves to see, oh, I'm making it worse now. And as we meditate and get
calmer or more settled, um, one of the benefits of that is not to stay calm,
not to identify with the calm and say, "Oh, I'm such a calm person now. This is great, but to appreciate the calm gives
us a vantage point to see more clearly when we start losing that calm.
When we have a sense of ease, we learn how we lose that ease. And in that
losing of it, that might be where uh we are making the situation worse. That is
where we have left behind our ability to just be present and to see clearly. Oh,
this is difficult and I'm going to be here. I'm going to hold be present and see it and be mindful. Even if I don't
know what to do, at least I know not to make it worse.
So this very simple exercise that maybe is difficult to do and simple to explain
it goes this way. Set yourself at ease. Whatever ease that
you can and notice what takes you away from it.
Notice what caused you to lose your ease and see, are you contributing something
to make it worse that you actually don't have to do? It's extra to the situation.
Maybe you don't have to make it worse. Set yourself at ease and see what takes
you away from it. So that's my recommendation for what you could do for
the next 23 hours until we meet again. And um and this is an entry point now
for this deeper dive into the second insight, the insight into uh suffering,
duka. And in order to do this well, we need to
be able to learn not to add suffering to suffering.
We need to learn well how to stay with our ease, stay with our stability and calm even when we're feeling u lousy.
And that is a phenomenal thing to learn. And that's where you can start finding your freedom. And you might even find a
smile at a time when you're suffering in some way that in the past it uh despared you,
saddened you, upset you. But with mindfulness of it,
it your suffering won't bring you a smile, but your mindfulness might bring
you a smile as you find this wonderful capacity to be present without adding
without making it worse. So, um I hope that you enjoy and or at
least value this turn that we're taking now. And uh remember we're building this
on the foundation of all that we've done now over this year so far. Samadei and
insight. And now there's a dive for the next week or so into this world of um
the second characteristic the second perception the second insight into uh
duka suffering. Thank you.