good morning and welcome to our morning meditation
and in uh addressing the issue
of insight as part of our practice there's a number
of ways of attending to our experience that allows for
insight and as we do mindfulness practice it's useful to uh have a range
of options of how to attend which means how to be
aware and uh one of them is very simply to know our
experience the second is to feel or sense the experience uh experientially
meaning through the body and these two are the kind of foundation
for uh developing insight and what they have in common is uh experiencing things in
the present moment that insight is a present moment experience of
uh understanding and they come from the uh from other attentional aspects as well
present moment experience ways of knowing experiencing being aware but
these two and they are
uh in order for them to uh carry on their function for bringing us
insight they both have to be calm calm knowing calm sensing or spacious
knowing spacious sensing and feeling sometimes I think of it as
giving breathing room to whatever experience we're having in the present moment
so not to be caught up in the experience with judgments and commentary but just
to allow each thing to be as it is and to discover the joy and the freedom in
calmly knowing this is what's happening in calmly sensing and feeling how it
is and how much we are sensing and how much we're feeling uh knowing is a
little bit uh individual for each person but there's a kind of a gentle going
back and forth whichever one helps you helps the most bring the most presence
the most present moment experience whichever one helps to quiet
the thinking mind so to begin
uh to assume a meditation posture that uh helps you to feel
calm helps you to feel
alert and giving some care and some maybe even love to that
posture and then gently closing your
eyes and beginning by knowing and
sensing your body in this
posture almost letting your attention roam around the body
refamiliarizing yourself with the present moment experience of the
body if we're paying careful attention the body is never the same
the experience of the body the sense of the body is constantly
shifting and then
to gently take a few longer slow deeper breaths
as a way of calming centering yourself
here in your
experience relaxing on the exhale
and letting your breathing return to
normal and but with a normal breath continue to relax your body on the
exhale softening in the face
softening in the
shoulders softening the belly
maybe as you exhale to let there be a calming of the
whole body maybe a calming wave through the
body
and as you exhale let there be a calming of the
mind maybe a kind of settling of the mind
and then insight meditation mindfulness
meditation begins to work best if the
knowing and the sensing is cal done calmly calm
knowing as if you have all the time in the world to know
something calm
sensing where the knowing is very simple the simplest recognition of what's
happening in the present the simplest way of sensing it
with your body and you might begin by doing
this with your body
breathing simple knowing of breathing in knowing exhale as an exhale
experimenting with a very quiet simple maybe almost
silent maybe silent
knowing the experience of breathing in breathing out
can the knowing be be done from the back of the
mind so that it's simpler quieter
With the mind a little gathered together
oriented to know the breathing
to know it calmly
where something in your body and mind is nourished by the calm knowing
And then you're also experimenting with sensing the bodily
experience of breathing feeling it with your
body sensing how the body experiences breathing
so the primary locus of attention now is in the body itself
experimenting with a calm sensing or a spacious
sensing of the physical experience of breathing in and breathing out
where the where the calm sensing supports a wider calming of the
body
simple calm knowing
is an antidote to the mind thinking a
lot it's using simple thoughts to be present
calm sensing of the body breathing is also an
antidote to being involved in discursive thinking
feeling any degree of calmness
settleness that might be here in your body mind or heart
and if you do feel some calmness chances are that it's little
bit diffuse
feeling as it should
be breathe breathe with the calmness breathe through it
and as a support for a very simple and direct
present moment awareness calmly
know breathing in whatever way that it is
known calmly sense the sensations of breathing
and in whatever way they appear
And as we come to the end of the
sitting maybe with your eyes still closed to recall
The room you're in the building you're in the location where you
are and the people who you'll be
encountering on this
day or tomorrow
and to know this know all this
calmly to gaze upon the world
calmly with good will for the world
with a good will that's concerned for the welfare of
oneself the welfare of others the welfare of both self and
others together in community
and is concerned with the welfare of the whole
world where the abil where the ability to gaze upon the world
kindly arises out of our calm attention
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may our ability to gaze upon the world to interact and be with
others be filled with this good will may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so good morning and welcome maybe I'll move the umbrella for
a moment
so so welcome to this second talk on
uh insight what the insight is of insight meditation with it following the series
on samadei and that it's uh insight is much
more effective much more penetrating or much more
wise when it's partnered with an ability to be focused stable
settled where all of us is included in a kind of gathered Third
simplicity of attention um so that when we are
attending to something with our attention with our mindfulness um it's not a uh a um a simplistic or or
a very narrow kind of attention but it's something that's uh wide or full
uh and it's um rich with so much so much of who we are coming along to be present
so part of the joy of breath meditation being mindful of breathing
uh doesn't ex doesn't exactly come from the experience of breathing itself but
it comes from the the way in which we have this calm stable settled ability to
really gather ourselves really get absorbed in the experience of breathing
and then there's a wonderful feedback loop between the breathing and how we're
aware of it and at some point in that feedback loop in the inter face between
breathing and awareness um a a wonderful feeling of um of uh
well-being joy delight a richness a sweetness uh arises uh from the
experience of breathing or maybe in that interface and uh the
um Um so to bring together and samadei and
mindfulness and then it's uh very important to understand the basic building blocks of mindfulness that
we're going to be using in order to have insight and the simplest of these
building blocks is the ability building blocks of attention
and the simplest building blocks are knowing and sensing knowing and feeling
feeling the experience experientially in the body and um and knowing can be
nonverbal knowing can be uh very very
simple quiet in the mind verbally knowing can be a little bit more
wholehearted when it's when people use mental notes a label for the experience
saying in as we breathe in out as we breathe out and uh the
um and so breathing in breathing out uh with um uh uh really feeling like it's
known well completely sometimes if it's nonverbal it's a kind of knowing where you really are present
for it so if later someone asked you what was your breathing like you would
have something to say you can give some you can describe some of the details of that experience because you were so
present for it um if you're sensing it that helps the sensing gives a lot of
information for the knowing mind to sense all the different sensations that come into play as we're breathing
and the reason why sensing and knowing are so important or how they become important is when they're able to
support us together with the somebody to stay in the present moment to stay in
the present moment experience of things as close as we can and uh because the insight we're
looking for in insight meditation arises from present moment
experience there are other there are insights important insights we can have about our life our psychology
um the reasons why things are the way they are in our life um that uh can be
really big aha moments uh and we might in ordinary English call those
insights uh and uh being meditation practice can support these personal
insights but the insights we're looking for in inside insight meditation are not
personal uniquely personal to oneself because of one's own life experience
um but rather they're they're called universal experiences universal things
that we can have insight about that we can understand and see that are so universal that um that they really touch
some of the more fundamental maybe we can say universal
aspects of how we operate and how we live that is deeper and more the
foundation from which we have our personal experience in our life and so the art of uh Buddhist
practice is to know when we are addressing you know personal issues that need to be addressed and when it's
useful to uh not mix them up with Buddhist practice too much maybe they're
get they're they're treated elsewhere in reflections journaling with talking with
friends a therapist or someone but to really put aside the uh medit using
meditation as a place to navigate negotiate our personal psychology and
our you know the details of our emotional life the stories of our emotional lives uh in order to get quiet
enough and still enough to begin to feel what's underneath that personal level of our
our life the the kind of the the level what we all have in common that is kind
of the fundamental building blocks for even our personal stories and experience
so the art of this is knowing how to attend what needs to be attended to and
how and um and uh sometimes when we have to attend to the the influence or the
powerful experiences in the present moment that are related to our uh life
story or life life events then um uh when we have the what we try
to do in mindfulness meditation when it's a Buddhist practice when we want to is to have insight about it which means
again staying in the present moment with it making room for it allowing it and
and having the art of really being present of knowing and sensing with
sometimes the analogy that it's kind of like listening listening deeply to a
friend who's needs uh someone to debrief with needs someone to uh talk with about
what's going on and what they need most from um from their friend is just being a
good listener and um so the uh so that sometimes we provide that for ourselves
uh we're not exactly listening to the story we tell but we're we're knowing
what's actually going on in the present moment we're sensing what's happening accompanying ourselves in a deep way
and um so uh when the shift happens from
samadei if that to insight or when we're trying to bring these together
um uh samadei doesn't necessarily mean we're uh uh uh uh becoming attuned to the
details of the present moment uh it's almost the details and how things shift and change um maybe it's not so
important for somati as it is the gathering and quieting of attention
itself so that we get absorbed in the experience with with insight the details
of the experience become important not to be studied and investigated but to um bring into
focus and uh and as uh as as the kind of experiences we have in the present
moment change the focus can be um uh the
aperture can be changed sometimes with breathing
uh the focus can be very precise in a small little area
uh and sometimes what's nice is to have a wide angle lens both of them we allow ourselves to know
and feel in the present moment but sometimes it's a small little area of
breathing sometimes it's the whole um breath body breathing so the um it's different
things for you know different times and so with with mindfulness meditation we're kind of learning how to discover
what is the aperture what is the focus that's useful to help us stay present
for the experience in a way that's appropriate for what's happening in the moment uh and how we measure this by is
what what helps us to stay in the present moment stay with the experience helps us get more settled helps somebody
to grow as we do the insight and we're learning how to know and sense
in a richer way in a rich way and in a calm way and a calm knowing calm sensing in
the classic teachings of the Buddha on mindfulness um he first talks about
sensing and sensing and when sensing he talks about sensing the whole body and
then he says uh uh calming calming the body and as we calm the body that has a
has an influence on the mind on our inner life so that the knowing becomes
calmer the sensing can become calmer and there's a wonderful reciprocal relationship with um uh knowing and
sensing supporting calm and calm supporting a more uh present moment
sensing and knowing so sensing and knowing
um this is uh uh the more we are in this world of sensing and knowing the and the
knowing and again is the very simple recognition of what's happening in the present the simplest recognition we can
have almost like one word rather than an understanding of what's happening where
we know you know the big picture of why something is happening the history of it
and where it's going what's going to happen next um it's very very
simple and um so you might try that through the day you might find
situations where you can um uh center
yourself into to the present moment and try to keep yourself here with your
experience as you're living it as you're doing it and um and know and sense a
place that I uh do this a lot is with driving from driving is that um I let
mostly I try to let driving be very simple and I put aside a lot of my
stories and a lot of my thinking and um and just try to be in the experience of
knowing and sensing with a focus on the driving and there's a kind of a peacefulness that sometimes sets in
because I'm not being distracted and caught up with my preoccupations my thoughts and concerns of my
day and there it's a wonder and I I'm a very act more active driver but I'm also
feel more gathered and more kind of here for the experience of driving almost
like I've entered into a slight samadei or a slight harmony
with the driving itself and my my uh in
a very nice way i'm looking at the rearview mirror looking left and right i'm kind of sensing and feeling and
knowing uh as I go along and sometimes if I do this I arrive where I'm going
calmer than I was when I started so the idea of uh using sensing
and knowing as a way of staying in our present experience in a useful way and
not being caught up in the stress of past futures and fantasy
so you might try it you might try it uh in different activities that you do
today so thank you very much and um and we'll continue this week with this
introduction to insight until we the next week we'll start talking about the specific insights themselves thank you