so I think I have all the computers and screens and buttons
and audio set up for this and as I said I've been away and happy to be back and
be with you all and I've been teaching a two-week retreat for experienced
practitioners and uh it was really lovely to be so deeply connected for two weeks
with a group of people who are so dedicated to engaging in the
practice and um it was uh so I'm still kind of in the momentum of that retreat
it ended yesterday and uh I'm looking forward to
in the fall in September teaching a month-long retreat
uh for experienced practitioners and this has been a dream we've had for our
retreat center at Insights uh retreat center for since we we started in 2012
uh we almost had a month-long retreat in May of 2020 but then the lockdown
happened so now we're fine it looks like we're going to get to it and there was kind of a warm up for me to do the two
week this last time so welcome everyone to back to this 7
a.m youtube and uh they will do a followup
or a second part to what was started in beginning of January which was a series
on samadei and the partner to samadei is
insight vipasana and uh it's sometimes combined
with the um the word samata
vipasana and samata uh here means uh calm and vipasana means
clear seeing in Chinese when they ch translated Buddhist terms into Chinese
they use the characters stop for samata and for ordinary word to see for
vipasana stop and see so this long wonderful process of
stopping all our proliferations all our preoccupations all the ways we're
caught it's a a phenomenally wonderful process to be engaged in slowing down
the mind's preoccupations so that we can see
clearly and as we slow down calm down settle down
uh have some samadei it's remarkable what we can see that's not available if
we're not settled if we're not haven't stabilized the mind and in fact it's a long tradition
of understanding that without some degree of samadei it's inconceivable to understand
uh what's possible in terms of the degree of clarity the degree of
peace degree of well-being that's possible for a human
being and um so to have some degree of stability that allows us to see
clearly so to begin this meditation today and begin the series
on insight we begin with calling
upon whatever delights you inspires you about
sitting down to meditate right now maybe gently closing your
eyes maybe for some of you is simply to be here like me i'm
inspired to be here with you all for this 7 a.m meditation and maybe there's a kind of
happiness or gladness to have this opportunity
some of you have done this for a long time and so maybe there's the comfort of
familiarity maybe there's the confidence of engaging in something that you
believe in or value tremendously or somewhat
and to feel the inspiration the joy
of of simply being here to
meditate and feel it in such a way that the thinking
mind feels comforted or safe enough to quiet
quiet to better feel the sensations in the body heart
mind of
well-being and maybe for some of you there's also a kind of sense of
rightness of assuming your meditation posture
maybe there's inspiration with the posture to be back in a familiar
place maybe a joy that this body and its
posture is a bit like a temple a sacred
place that you have returned to
and in the middle of this familiar
and maybe happy place to gently take a few long deep
breaths not too deeply not too strongly just enough to say hello to your breathing
and for your breathing to say hello to you just enough for there to be a
reconnection refamiliarity
letting your breathing return to
normal and part of samadei is
stability and as you exhale ordinary exhale relax let go
into how the weight of your body rests against some surface chair
cushion floor bed
stabilizing yourself by
grounding your weight on the surface
and is as if the mind itself has
weight as you exhale let that very
light weight of the mind maybe of awareness
itself settle and steady itself
almost as if the mind or at least awareness can settle into your
torso to accompany your breathing
relaxing the thinking
mind and letting awareness enter into the sensations of
the body breathing as if it's a coming
home as if it's coming
into a safe place a sacred
place a supportive place simply to be breathing in and
breathing out
as you breathe in calming your
body as you breathe out calming your body and mind
as you breathe recognizing any degree of
calm that might be present for you
as you exhale spread your
awareness into whatever diffuse
calm there is in your body
and
then with an inner eye an inner
clarity what do you see
what do you see or how do you
see that's easier while you're calm
and if you turn your calm eyes your inner
eyes towards the people of your
life and with calm eyes calm consideration
do you see them in a new way or in a good way
as we bring this meditation to a
close gaze upon the world kindly and
offer to the world your wish for a better world
your inspiration to contribute to a better world
may it be that with your ability to be
calm and to see
clearly that you
can promote happiness in this world promote safety in this world
promote peace in this
world bring greater freedom and liberation to this world
may all beings be happy
safe peaceful and free
[Music]
thank you
so good morning and welcome and
um returning here with the sun beginning to come in through the windows and
um I think in the past I've had a little umbrella or something there in the way
but tomorrow I'll see if I can not have it so bright on my face it's a little
bit much for me even but um I can't complain too much about
sitting in the light the light of samadei the light of
insight and um so welcome to this beginning of a
part two of part one was the I guess we had about 60 talks on samadei and I
don't think there'll be so many this time around but this part two is uh insight and these two are paired in
Buddhism samadei and vipasana uh vasana is a poly word pasana
means to see and v is an emphatic prefix so to see in a special way to see uh
it's often translated is clear seeing and
um and uh and the relationship between samadei and vipasa samadei and insight
is variable different teachers will make have different emphasis
and um one of the contributions uh in the 20th century of Burmese
Buddhism was uh to introduce people to a
way of doing inside practice without the need for a very intense level of samadei
intense level of concentration and um and uh so that
uh and so that was called um uh dry
vipasana because it wasn't uh supported by the strong degree of pleasure joy and
happiness that can pervade the body when there's samadei
however the way that it was taught to me in Burma the so-called dry samadei dry
vipasa uh came along with a lot of concentration anyway it wasn't to the
degree of the very intense way that the Burmese had expected samadei to be
about and um and uh and so I was uh uh blessed by being
able to do the insight work uh partnered with a degree of samadei which um is closer to seemingly
closer to how the Buddha taught vipasana he did not teach the most intense form
of samadei that a human being can can acquire but a a a lesser degree that
kept people connected um uh to their lived experience in their body but in in
a way that filled the body with a sense of well-being and part of the function and
so uh compared to the most dry form of insight where there's no samadei
whatsoever uh uh the um one way to to practice them
is a happy combination of the two where there is some samadei and uh and an
insight and the samadei creates a good foundation for insight because you
cannot have a lot of insight night unless the thinking mind has has uh
settled down um oddly enough one of the insights that we are resting in and is
to rest or flow in the changing river that constantly shifting changing
inconstant uh experience of sensations in the body uh and that's a phenomenal
way begins to loosen up uh attachments clinging we have and introduce us to a
whole different inner sensibility i call it sometimes the deep
mind and um and uh in order for that to happen the constantly shifting changing
inconstant fickle uh the nature of the thinking mind needs to quiet down and so
there's a kind of if the thinking mind becomes still and quiet and uh and uh
then we can start entering into this very deep the deep mind the deep sensations the deep sensitivity within
that opens up a whole different way of being in the world and so part of the function of samadei is to help quiet the
mind quiet the thinking mind still the mind but to do so in a way that's very
welcoming that uh of course the mind wants to be quiet when the rewards the
sense of well-being sense of coming home uh into samadei into a subtleness into
this deep place of sensitivity within it feels so good so right feels like
um um um you know this is the healthy place to be the thinking mind can't
believe this sometimes because thinking mind sometimes is filled with fear and
uh the thinking mind thinks that it has to think its way out of its fear or solve the problems it has uh thinking
mind maybe has resentments sense of betrayal and it's only by kind of
ruminating on them or trying to figure out how to somehow cope with them or
deal with them uh repeat them to ourselves that we can find a solution um
there's all kinds of ways happiness joy success in life the thinking mind kind
of is convinced that that's you know it's going to figure this out for ourselves
um and or maybe there's no sense of an inner life which is satisfying and
meaningful and and uh and filled with well-being and so the only avenue for
happiness success safety that uh someone knows is through the thinking mind
because they don't know an alternative so of course they're going to be enga g engaged in that and not
wanting to give it up samadei teaches us something very different it teaches us how there's a
profound sense of well-being uh that's below the thinking mind below the
surface mind and uh there's a profound profound sense of um of uh stillness and
quiet uh that is is a form of safety is a form of uh happiness is a form of
joy and as sama so that allows the mind to quiet down so that it can then this
that's the stopping or the stilling of the mind the calming of the mind of samadei
samata and then it shifts to being able to see more
clearly and uh and being see it's not just seeing more clearly but it's also
seeing something we don't normally see uh we don't normally see uh the deep
operating systems going on the deep the deep kind of uh um uh organizing
principles by which we organize our life the deep beliefs the deep attitudes the
deep emotions that uh either support our life or undermine our life they're re
usually generally inaccessible by a mind that's preoccupied in thoughts ruminating thinking a lot fantasizing a
lot and so there's a whole different way of engaging ourselves that I believe is
very respectful because it it's a deeper more fully engaged part of who we
are and uh the combination of samadei and insight is that samadei done well is
that um uh uh is a way of becoming fully
embodied and fully embodied doesn't mean that now we're a hedenist feeling a lot
of joy in the body uh uh uh it allows for the insight to be
integrated into the full range of our psychological life our emotional life
our lived life that sometimes is not possible if we don't have a degree of
samadei if samadei is helping us calm and expand ha uh into the whole body
then we're touching all the different places that the body is um connected to
our psychology our emotions the places of tension and holding and the places of
deep sense of well-being and joy and so the function one of the functions of samadei is to help us have the clarity
to have insight but also helps the insight we have to be deeply integrated
into our whole psychological makeup and uh and so going into uh
having insight be able to include all of who we are makes it means we don't have
a bypass spiritual bypass means that we it's really beneficial in our whole life
and as we have deeper kind of deeper and deeper kind of sense of peace and insight the it's good to have the
insight itself be integrated into our full spectrum of our life so the
integration the combination of samadei and insight is a wonderful happy uh
partnership and um and so the the the first part of this year when
we did samadei hopefully uh for those of you who did it will set the stage or not
the stage but set your body in place for uh ability to have insight and insight
in um in a way that's deeply integrated into yourself
for those of you who might be joining now for the first time um uh maybe some
of the benefits of samadei won't be so easily accessible to you but still uh
there'll be that the as we go through this and integrate these two uh you'll
probably benefit uh getting a sense of what's going on here and it might open
up a new orientation for you in meditation that even for a beginner
might be um beneficial so um so this is a very general
introduction to what we'll be doing and uh some of what I just just
said we'll we'll we'll kind of repeat or go into more deeply uh this week and uh
and more and um I'm very happy to be able to um introduce or begin this this
journey in insight it's been a phenomenally
um wonderful process in my life journey in my life to be on the insight journey
and now to share it with you will be uh it's my pleasure so thank you very much