hello from Insight Meditation Center in Redwood City and delighted
that this meditation hall has become so large and encompassing to include all of
you and all the different places you are and for us to have come together this morning to meditate
and uh one of the [Music]
uh emphasises uh I've been giving lately is that
um I'm I'm defining awareness as
[Music] the as the
coordinated coming together working together of all the different attentional faculties that we
have and um and when they're all working in an unself-conscious way but we're
quite present for them all they come together to a sense or
feeling of a spacious open receptive field of awareness and where where maybe our
capacity for spatial awareness spatial reconstruction contributes to a sense of
space that awareness can have for some people so it's not essentializing
awareness into something but rather it's seen as a as a composite of many things
operating together so this is a minor point I want to make but that the more important is that we
have all these different attentional faculties and uh this week I've been
emphasizing knowing sensing and then yesterday
observing and uh clear comprehension there is one more that
maybe nor ordinarily is not considered an intentional faculty but it can be uh
engaged with recruited for the purposes of greater
uh present moment awareness and that is our intelligence our capacity to understand
to figure out to question to explore to consider new options
And um and uh if someone is uh engaged
in finding their way in the wilderness all their senses might be open and one
of the things that keeps them you know even more right there in the uh in the
present moment is the intelligent kind of uh scanning the environment trying to
understand where they are what direction to go what's the wise way to go and there's a lot of engagement
it might seem like that's tiring to apply that to meditation but there is a
natural way of using intelligence to figure out how can I be here in the
present moment in a in a a valuable way
that is relaxed how can I be here in such a way that there's a deep settling and a
relaxing and if uh if we don't ask that question don't engage our intelligence
um with the present moment awareness and how to do it in a nice way uh many of us
will use our intelligence to fantasize better uh to uh catastrophize better to
uh resent better as we review and think about the past we're we're using our
intelligence sometimes for things that keeps us trapped in the world of
suffering in the dharma we want to use our intelligence to bring ourselves into freedom in the present moment and we can
use our intelligence for that purpose and uh the reference point I'd like to
you do use today as a guide for if you want to do this is um um uh I could just
reach out for my cup here i can just kind of grab it and bring it up and
drink it and and without thinking about it maybe
I'm just greedy doesn't matter how I grab it and uh how I drink from it or I
can make the actor drinking the cup a satisfying meaningful beautiful act in
itself kind of like a a uh a Tai Chi movement or maybe in the way that a
dancer might dance and move their arm and the whole expression of art is in
the movements of the hand or someone who go uh practices the Japanese way of tea
and they uh they would uh just the way they would pick up the cup with two
hands holding it bringing it to their their lips and drinking the whole way they're doing
it um has a quality of beauty in it and um sometimes I think that the the
way of tea can be called the way of beauty um and so how can you use your
intelligence to ina to activate awareness of breathing of present moment
of the body what's happening fear of the mind wandering off how can you engage
awareness attention so the very use of it is beautiful and that's what we have
intelligence for and that's an intelligence which uh brings us into the
present moment to be aware beautifully
so assuming a meditation posture but not being in a hurry to do
so assuming a posture almost as if that is itself is an art form or a Tai Chi
movement or
um perhaps in a way
that would express to others that you're really present for
them for the activity you're doing assume a posture that is beautifully
attentive there's an intentionality that's the intention to be here with the
whole body and maybe that means to sit a little bit
straighter a little bit more intentionally not a posture of
completely no intentional muscles operating at all so you can relax as
deeply as possible but a posture that allows for some kind of expression
of beautiful intentionality to be here around which the body can
relax and then to gently close the
eyes in a way that is
graceful elegant or has a deep pleasure to
it just in the right speed for you take a few long slow full breaths
maybe the ex inhale has the beauty of the of a
sunrise in this way it appears or of a flower opening
how would you breathe in can you look and orient yourself towards breathing
in and breathe in a way that is
beautiful and
exhale maybe like a bird that stops flapping its wings
and now glides down to a
landing elegant bird elegant
exhale and as you breathe in deeply and
exhale as if you have all the time in the world on the
exhale gently relax your
body and then letting your breathing return to normal
and be with your
breathing with the exhale relax the thinking
mind any tightness and pressure in the face or
head shoulders or belly associated with thinking
And then how would you
Have your awareness your
attention come together with your breathing so there's something beautiful
graceful with how you're
aware the simple knowing of breathing in breathing out maybe you say the word
in out but the way the mind says
it is like ceremony saying something beautifully
to allow yourself to sense and feel the body breathing the
sensations is there a way to give a lot of time and space and
presence to the act of feeling
so that there's
pleasure in being available to feel or there's beauty
or there is gracefulness
no hurry just like
a dancer who moves an arm it's really in the arm as it
moves as if it's the only thing in the world to be there sensing
inhale exhale in the body as if it's the only thing
with your intelligence recognizing what's happening in the
mind with strain or pushing or being in a
hurry maybe even being anxious how there's a way that that is
not so beautiful and for these minutes of
meditation orient yourself
intelligently carefully lovingly to the beauty of attention
beauty of being aware of breathing of
meditation being mindful in a beautiful
way of the present
moment so that your intelligence your
creativity supports your absorption in the present moment just
here now
for the activity of the mind to be
beautiful it helps to know the quality of mental activity the
mind what it's involved in and
How and can there be a
generous consideration of how to change the
mind so that its activity of attention is beautiful
is satisfying is
peaceful in this simple ordinary
acts of attending to the present moment
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to
consider with some degree of intelligence
consideration reflection
curiosity is the mind is your inner life a little bit more satisfying than
it was before
meditation is there did you learn something about beautiful attention
or did you learn something about way of being with your inner life that's not so
beautiful that maybe you don't want to invest so much time and attention to
perpetuate and as we come to the end here you might consider ways in which
you live your life with attitudes with mental
activity with emotional
states that are not so
beautiful that don't bring greater beauty and peace calm to yourself or to
others and maybe some of those you go along
with automatically and maybe
unnecessarily and maybe instead of doing what's not beautiful you can come into the world
Feeling empowered feeling that it's okay for
you to enter your activities of the day with a beautiful attitude
beautiful mindset beautiful
orientation not hijacked by being in a hurry
may it be that by entering this world in a beautiful way beautiful
tension beautiful consideration that we contribute to the
peace and
happiness for others may it be that we make this
world a more beautiful place spiritually
ethically attentionally with our awareness our presence and our
care may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free so they can live in beauty
[Music]
thank you
so good morning and welcome to this now fourth talk introducing the very
important topic of insight in for insight meditation practice and this week in introducing it
I'm laying out the foundation of uh foundational awareness practices that
uh are used for having insight insight is a
byproduct of a careful present moment attention to our experience here and now
and so knowing how to do that is important and for insight meditation
we're using engaging a wider range of our attentional faculties than we do
when we're doing practicing samadei there's a lot of big overlap
and one of the uh important ones that um with uh some people
would would would beg to differ with me but uh
there's a greater uh usage of curiosity and
intelligence for inside meditation the stance of inside meditation is the
question what is this and sometimes I've just used the word what in sitting in
meditation and um and the what the question what the stance of what is not
looking for an answer but it's more like I I was some occasionally would say to me what is this and uh and it's without
actually moving at all it's as if my whole system attentional system is
opening it the arms wide and stepping forward to be more connected more
present for whatever experience I'm having and this using this question what
what is it and and a a sense of receptivity that can follow from that is
and getting closer letting it be more intimate is um uh is making a choice
about how it's useful to be present and and to track that choice to see is this
a way is this forward leading does this help me be more present does it help me be more centered here does it help me to
uh be more connected and to develop greater clarity of attention and clarity
of knowing what um what's happening in the moment all these kinds of questions
can be done kind of uh you know somewhat without a lot of thought but exactly but
they you excuse me
wait all these questions um are an expression of
intelligence and in one of the attentional faculties we have meaning one of the mental capacities that are
operating that can help support present moment attention that's actually maybe an
integral part of it is our intelligence our ability to figure things out
understand things better question what's going on uh experiment with how we're uh
practicing and uh and many people associate that kind of use of intelligence with the mind getting busy
and distracted and it's too coarse too too much is going on in medit meditation
and that's but that's how we use our intelligence to know how we're using our intelligence so it doesn't make the mind
busy and and activated we use our intelligence to know how the mind can be
more peaceful more quiet more centered more here so I found that asking the question
in meditation what is this with this attitude of opening up and being with
the experience that this actually was quite useful for me and helped settle me help me become
quiet i learned that and the intelligent consideration of how am I being aware
here what's the quality of the awareness of the attention uh can that be more satisfying more
peace producing can it be more beautiful so I did a lot of mental
noting in my practice and I learned to pay attention to how I did the mental noting so the mental noting itself was
deeply satisfying was calming was settling was
supportive of a deepening of the practice i've done a lot of sensing uh a lot of
being my body sensing my experience and there too uh I using your intelligence
and consider how am I sensing is this the best way is there another way of doing it what's the quality of that
sensing and uh sometimes I could feel that my sensing I didn't want to sense something and I can feel the contraction
of pulling away I can sometimes feel like I was straining I was pushing too much trying
to make something happen p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p pushing forward sometimes there was a sense of
being in a hurry and so I learned to uh to look at that and see that and ask myself are
there other ways of doing this can I do it without straining what would that look like can I give it more time
can I somehow find a way to um to uh
uh maybe have it be more beautiful sensing so the knowing the sensing the
the more generic open kind of idea of awareness itself what's the quality of that and one of the reference points for
this intelligence a number of them intelligent consideration is uh does it
support the meditation does it support us to be more calm more peaceful
does it support an inner beauty an inner kind of deep a deep kind of uh pleasure
or joy for being engaged in the practice and um the
um the um so in intelligence as part of the
attentional capacity we have to use our intelligence to be more present and the
word intelligence in English might be a triggering word for some people maybe because we think I don't I'm not
intelligent enough everyone's has enough intelligence for meditation practice
everyone has enough intelligence to find their way to uh freedom from
suffering and um you only need as much uh intelligence to get out of suffering
as you use to get into it and so if you don't have such great intelligence then
um maybe it's not so sophisticated the way you got into suffering and so it's
easier to find your way out so everyone has plenty of intelligence enough to do
this but sometimes in meditation circles we get the message almost like we're not
supposed to use it in meditation because it seems like it's too much mental activity it maybe too much
thinking but uh and so people leave their intelligence at the door when they sit down to meditate um intelligence is
a very important part especially when we engage in in uh the both samadei and
insight practice but maybe even more with inside practice and um and then so
we but then we have to learn to use the intelligence we have um to to support us
not to go in the opposite direction and one of the ways that can help with this
use of proper use of intelligence is to consider that uh if we're spending a lot
of time in the hindrances a lot of times distracted in things uh chances are our
intelligence has been hijacked so that we can better fantasize so we can think
out scenarios of fear and danger and dread for the future
so we can review and creatively review and trying to figure out what happened in the past and um and or write the
great American novel as we're meditating we our intelligence is operating and we
don't want to let it get it hijacked and being used for purposes in meditation that are not useful for us and so um to
intelligently understand where our intelligence is going and to f figure out how to use our capacity to think
well to consider to explore to experiment and to adjust what we're
doing so that it supports the whole process of being absorbed in the present
moment just here and um and I'm sure some of you
will feel like this sounds like a lot of work but as soon as it feels like tiring work uh intelligence is hasn't is not
doing its job job of intelligence is to help you feel like it's not not
difficult work it's not strain it's actually really pleasant really
wonderful and so the reference point I used in the guided meditation was um
something like it's really elegant like a dancer moving an arm
uh and it moving that arm uh it's completely there it's elegant it's
beautiful the whole world the whole world of the the dancers's expression
purpose in life meaning in life everything is in that movement of the arm and part of the reason why it's so
wonderful to watch a really skilled expressive dancer is we can feel that
there's so much is there in this and the grace of that arm moving
for um uh someone who does Tai Chi there's a there's a beauty there and how
things are moving chiang perhaps and in a reference point in
Japanese um way of tea the path of tea chado the sometimes in English called
tea ceremony to do things as ceremony meaning to do things with an elegance a
beauty uh a care where every gesture
um uh you're fully in the gesture and so that has a has an intentionality a
purpose beauty a presence a generosity a care that goes into it we offering it
and um and so to use our intelligence to figure out how can I be attentive to my
breathing to the present moment as ceremony as a dance as a place to
express something profound within us and the primary reference point I'd like to
suggest uh is the idea of beauty to use our intelligence to understand how to be
mindful in a beautiful way so that if wherever we go with mindfulness we bring
beauty with us we are we live in beauty because how we're aware of the world is
beautiful and since that's the only way to be aware of the world is to be aware um you
bring beauty with you everywhere with how you're aware and to and to challenge you a
little bit uh I'd like to suggest that
uh uh being aware in an un beautiful
way is a is not a good alternative the best
alternative in the moment probably is to do it beautifully choose the best choice
the best way of doing it don't choose something that's lesser and undermines you and debilitates
you don't keep sacrificing giving up on yourself by doing something which is not
so beautiful choose beauty and use your intelligence for
that purpose so all these
intentional faculties including intelligence are coming together now so
we can begin to have deep insight and uh that will we'll continue with this topic
for tomorrow thank you