hello and welcome and
one of the approaches to meditation always is to keep it very simple
with the idea that we are simplifying our preoccupation simplifying our what
we're caught up in simplifying ourselves in many ways so that
uh we're able to see our experience
free of the lenses of
pre-existing concepts we have we can see our experience without the filter of
ideas and preferences without the ideas of shoulds and shouldn't and without
expectation that we're simplifying to become fresh a fresh
awareness a fresh perspective a fresh seeing of our experience
even to the extent that it's at almost as if we're seeing for the first time
seeing for the first time and in doing so find it phenomenally interesting
amazing wondrous be and that we're curious interested in
knowing what is here as if we've never known it before
even something as simple as the breathing
but the emphasis is on the process of simplification
not the process of seeing at least in the beginning
so assuming a posture of meditation that's right for you
uh and to
think of the posture as an invitation to become simply here
to be grounded here to be settled here
and the way that the posture could help is by assuming a posture
that allows you to somehow have both an alertness
and an opportunity to relax the larger muscles of your body
maybe on the inhale to feel
the vitality the aliveness the alertness
that's in the body itself
and on the exhale to relax the body the shoulders the belly the face
and to breathing in
a simplicity of being
breathing out relaxing into a simplicity of being here
with whatever is here for you
not wanting it to be different not wanting it to stay the same
just here with this
breathing with it
and it can be complicated to be present if the mind is quick to judge and
comment and analyze
as you exhale softening relaxing the thinking mind
gently quieting your thoughts
and then settling into the simplicity of breathing
or the simplicity of accompanying breathing
and awareness accompanies breathing closely
breathing accompanies awareness
like two friends walking contentedly in a park together
so breathing and awareness content contentedly accompany each other
within the world of our experience
and if you would like in order to stay with
the changing rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
you can gently count your breaths one to three
or one to 10
very very soft count very relaxed calm count
and part of the function of the counting is to help you notice
when you wander off from the count into your thoughts
and then gently calmly begin again
the simplicity of being centered on the body breathing
Each time you exhale
to settle into a simplicity of being
a stability of just being Here
in the midst of your present moment embodied experience
relaxing the thinking mind
the only thing you have to think about is the breathing itself
accompanying The rhythm of breathing
as we continue sitting
feeling into
the way to a simplicity of being and how you can for a few more minutes
just be here in the simplest possible way
with your present moment experience
and noticing how with a shifting changing
river of change of here and now
there is very little orientation towards thoughts of me
myself and mine stories of self commentary about self
because those take you away from simple presence
can you feel see recognize
how the simplicity of being
stays free of the major preoccupations of self
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
consider when and how simplicity of presence simplicity of
being when offered to others
is a gift someone who is troubled
someone who is challenged in some deep way
who doesn't need someone to fix them or explain things to them
they just value being accompanied by someone who can be simple relaxed
someone who can be present for them
where a simplicity of being
provides the right level of accompanyment
or when a simplicity of being is the appropriate way of accompanying
yourself
where a simplicity of being can allow for a simple good will
a simple care and kindness
that gently non assertively without expectation
has goodwill for self and others
wishing lightly openly
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello from Insight Meditation Center here in Redwood City
happy to continue this series on uh the topic of insight
the insight of insight meditation and currently
the topic is the insight into inconstancy the instight into change
and it's not a difficult insight maybe it's almost too obvious that
things change and that things are not the same
but uh still we get caught in permanence we get caught in that kind of believing
this is the way it is and uh to
come to freedom in Buddhism a kind of a deep inner freedom is to we're supported
by staying close to or recognizing in a deep way in a or to say differently not
uh in a continuous way how continuously
things are changing and it's almost as if or it is like that if we see change
we realize deeply we can't cling to anything because as soon as we cling
it's like clinging to uh the um the current of a river you put your hand
into that current you're going to grab that current grab that water hold on tight and you come up empty-handed it
might be a few drops of water on your hand but the current is not amenable to being grabbed and the water just goes
out your your hands and but some people are constantly grabbing grabbing grabbing or they're grabbing within the
current thinking they have it and so to begin seeing and feeling the
distinction between being in the flow of change and somehow being separated from
it or trying to hold on to something and one of those things concepts ideas that
takes us out really far out of the the the flow of the river of the present
moment is ideas concepts attachments to
self independent of whether there is a self or not a self
in a practical way we can get attached to self we can hold on to the self
and it becomes um a trap that takes us out of staying in the changing flow of
the present moment in the fluidity of the present staying fluid and moving with it and uh and knowing how to be
safe knowing how to be uh find a peace in the current of the river
and so uh I've gone rafting and and one of the ways to get trapped to get caught
a little bit sometimes rafting is to get pulled into the eddies usually on the
side of the river an eddy is aware place where the current of water flowing
somehow gets um pushed off maybe the the bottom or the usually the sides of the
river in such a way that part of the current flows backwards and up river to
be then pushed down again and it can go in a circle a little bit like a whirlpool but there's the water is not
being pulled down so it just kind of it's moving around in a circle and the
raft can get stuck there some eddies can be quite strong and some are somewhat large
and um and you can kind of stuck in there every time you try to come out of the EV eddy you're come into where the
current is most strongly going to pull push you down back into it and around and around and um and so the
preoccupation with self is an eddy it's a has a gravitational force that pulls
us into it so if I have this idea that I'm a bad meditator or a good meditator
that's an abstract idea but it's an abstract idea about me i am
something and anything about me is interesting anything about me that's
praise or blame is even more interesting and so there's a pull into that world
there's emotions and feelings that are produced by it there's uh concerns and
anxiety produced by those thoughts there's ways and we get pulled into that eddy and even if we try to come out of
it the force just pulls us back in and we circle and circle and the river is
just a few few feet away keeps flowing it's constantly the water is flowing and
flowing but now we're stuck in this eddy going around and around
and um and and when we try to get out of it towards the edge of it it can feel
it's it gets harder and harder to kind of pull up because there the current the the the force of the eddi is strongest
and um but if we can get free of the eddi then there's the freedom the delight of now
being uh being uh in the flow of the current of the river being carried by it
nicely and then not a lot of rowing is needed or paddling is needed because now
we're kind of in the flow we just have to stay in it and we might from the point of view of the in the being in the
current come close to an eddi but we can see it and we keep ourselves away from
it we know the danger there so there's a lot of way that selfing is one of those
concepts that we get caught in permanence get caught in this is how
things are and when we're really caught in it then uh we're actually
disconnected to the simplicity of life the current kind of flow and unfolding
of life and it can be quite intense the entities we go into where we leak uh the
the the ideas of self the self-concepts we caught in are not just simple ideas
like I'm a good meditator I'm a bad meditator but it gets pulled into the world of of uh fantasize imagination
story making I start imagining that I'm going to go off to some beautiful
natural place and that's what it's going to take for me to be a good meditator where there's peace and serenity and and
I imagine the birds singing and how there'll be people coming and delivering wonderful
uh drinks to me smoothies and and um and it'll just be kind of so comfortable at
temperature and I'm lost in a fantasy this fantasy that's centered on me myself and mine that's more and more
disconnected what's sad is when those fantasies are
negative in nature i'm a bad meditator and therefore everyone will hate me and I can't go to meditation centers because
I go to a meditation center and meditate other people they're going to see I'm a bad meditator and they'll want to reject
me or they'll laugh at me and and we start imagining all these things actually happening and the imagination
affects our emotions almost as as strongly as if it's really happening and we're caught in that eddy and it's hard
to get out of it um but if we know if we have some deep
understanding deep insight deep ability to connect to the flow of
the present moment the changing nature everything is in constant everything is changing including our thoughts and
emotions so we don't get caught in it so we're not in the eddi but we're in the
current that flows down river we just stay in there being carried along
then we're less likely to be tricked fooled by these concepts of self we're
be able to better see the concept selves are a little bit like or very much like
grabbing on to something and holding on and sometimes it's not like an eddy but
you you can't actually hang on to it but you can get caught in its flow sometimes
that what keeps us caught is that um we're still tied to the pier or there's
the anchor hasn't been pulled up and the self is that strong that solid
and um and it isn't that we have to deny that there is a self
at this point in practice there's never any denial um but we see more and more how concepts
ideas of self are pulling us away from the being fluid being
in the flow being somehow adaptable or the somehow kind of appreciating the
lived life of the present moment as it unfolds and changes and shifts in the
present moment and at first this present moment simplicity of being can seem boring too
simple it's much less sophisticated than the elaborate
thoughts fantasies ideas about self and what's I'm doing for myself and what I'll
accomplish and what I'll prove and how great I'll be um but over time we begin
realizing that the eddy of self is kind of very itself very impoverished
very limiting and that the three-dimensional the multi-dimensional
richness of human life has so much there in the simplicity of being because it's
in the simplicity of being that we have we can connect to the deep sensitivities
the deep sensitivities activities of the heart of our inner life to ourselves to
others that that's where something comes alive that is freeing that is satisfying
that's wise and caring so part of the emphasis on the insight
into inconstancy and change is to help us support us from being caught in the
eddies of self so as you go by go through your day
today you might look at this you might consider you might try to notice when you get
involved in the swirl of thoughts ideas stories that
are centered on me myself and mine somehow you're the prime character in
your thoughts and ideas or the or the your emotions are the primary fuel
um for thinking about other people even and uh and how it takes you out of
something it this connects you to something that if you were connected to
would actually give you a much better ability to be wise to be present and to
be caring for the whole world
so um may your simplicity of being
be a gift you give to this world thank you