this idea of using poetry as a support for practice just this recognition
that I think having malleability or flexibility in the way in which we
support practice I would say in which we approach
or engage with anything in life is tremendously helpful can even be
transformational if we're so used to thinking thinking quote unquote that we have to engage
with our experience in one particular way and that really limits
us limits our experiences limits
our um interpretations or ways in which we can work with whatever is arising in
our life so my hope my wish is is for this
these days working with poetry is pointing to another
way than perhaps our usual way of engaging with being with interacting
with our experiences and certainly our meditation experiences our spiritual
life be anything and maybe maybe part of the reason why I appreciate so much this uh
poetry of practice days some of you know that I was trained as a research scientist spent years working in the
laboratory test tubes white uh jacket you know the lab coat gloves you know
the whole thing and uh so I thought that life was just you know one particular
way and had it solved and became good at thinking through things and then it was
just with practice that I realize yes that's valuable what I had been trained
to do but it's not the only way in fact
to have this flexibility to have this malleability is
invaluable not only have freedom in our lives but have a rich full
life so with that as an introduction I'll do a little bit of a guided meditation this morning and to help us
maybe get settled and then I'll drop in a poem and then I'll talk about the poem
uh after the guided meditation so again these poems as they get dropped in you don't have to think
about them you don't have to figure them out you don't have to understand them you don't have to look them up you don't
have to Google them and get the title and all that you can do that later you can do that
later the invitation here is just to experience them and I like this word
Shimmer maybe is there's maybe there's a sentence a word that shimmers for
you and what is that experience like of having some
shimmering some alternatives to this word Shimmer maybe it strikes a cord in
the heart or mind or maybe it uh
remembers you can like remember something about it something like that
okay maybe with a big exhale setting the intention to turn
towards meditation
this exhale allowing some
tightness intention to maybe be
released ah allow a certain amount
of arriving
opening to the sounds that are in your environment
what would it be like if there are not distractions or problems but just part
of the present moment experience
feeling the feet on the
ground this can be such a support in all areas of our life daily life
meditation just feeling the feet touching the ground or whatever they're
touching we are here just
here feeling the pressure against the body where it's connected to in contact
with this sitting
surface and gently moving up the
body if the back is against the back rest to feel the pressure the
contact and feel into the bodily experience lower back and the upper back
is there a sense of
uprightness figuratively or
literally and can we let the arms hang
from the spine relaxing the
shoulders maybe the shoulders moved as a tiny bit back and out very very very small
movement that allows the chest to become more
available maybe less guarded less armored
and the belly our beautiful Bellies can may be relaxed open spacious
and our hands feeling what they are touching
they're warm or cool smooth or rough
and then we'll check in with a
face place we often hold tension or
tightness can we just bring some kindness to the
face some warmth some caring
attention allowing any tension to slip away
and you be in this body this moment just as it
is just this moment
and resting the attention on the sensations of
breathing e
and when the mind wanders doesn't have to be a
problem just very simply gently begin
again with the sensations of [Music]
breathing and you just be here this
moment this experience
e
e e
and to drop in a [Music] poem you don't have to figure it out you
don't have to think about it you don't have to understand it you don't have to like
it and you be here with the experience of it
the poem is called introduction to poetry by Billy
Collins introduction to poetry by Billy
Collins I asked them to take a poem and hold it up to the the light like a color
slide or press an ear against its
hive I say drop a mouse into a poem and watch him probe his way
out or walk inside the poem's room and feel the walls for a light
switch I want them to water ski across the surface of a poem waving at the
author's name on the shore but all they want to do is tie the poem
to a chair with rope and torture a confession out of
it they begin beating it with a hose to find out what it really
means
e e
read the poem
again it's called it's titled introduction to poetry author is Billy
Collins I asked them to take a poem and hold it up to the light like a
color slide or press an ear against its
hive I say drop a mouse into a poem and watch him probe his way
out or walk inside the poem's room and feel the walls for a light
switch I want them to water ski across the surface of a poem waving at the
author's name on the shore but all they want to do is tie the
poem to a chair with rope and torture a confession out of it they begin beating
it with a hose to find out what it really
means
thank you for your practice or sitting
together so this poem introduction to poetry by Billy
Collins I'll say that Billy Collins he was the poet laureate for the United
States in 2001 to 2003 his uh poems kind of use Simple
language and they often have a certain Whimsy to them and I I appreciate them
very much I'll say that um he's currently a
professor and he has been a professor for different universities uh during his career so introduction to poetry we can
imagine is a course that uh he was
teaching and uh maybe I'll read the poem
again and I'll say a little bit more about uh him and uh the the
poem so this poem is called a introduction to poetry again it's by Billy
Collins I ask them to take a poem and hold it up to the light like a color
slide or press an ear against its hive I say drop a mouth house into a
poem and watch him probe his way out or walk inside the poem's room and
feel the walls for a light switch I want them to water ski across
the surface of a poem waving at the author's name on the shore but all they
want to do is tie the poem to a chair with a rope and torture a confession out
of it they begin beating it with a hose to find out what it really means
wow this last slide they begin beating it with a hose to find out what it
really means quite something right a certain like violence of trying to
figure things out I don't know it makes me chuckle because how many times did I uh do this
with my experiences in the world trying to figure everything out it's been using my mind to figure everything
out instead of the senses right that Billy Collins is pointing to listening
water sking on the surface so kind like feeling and waving at the author's name
so uh instead of looking up their biography and figuring out everything and all this kind of stuff I just love
this so I'll say here's a um something about Billy Collins that he writes about
uh his process of writing poetry and he says I tried to create a hospitable tone
at the beginning of a poem because stepping from the title to
the first lines it's like stepping into a canoe a lot of things can go wrong I
just love this idea stepping from the title to the first line is like stepping in a canoe could be a little bit out of
balance so this is a reminder that for this poem the title and the first few
lines are introduction to poetry I asked them to take poem and hold it up to the
light so right this feels like tangible take a poem and hold it up to the light so he makes it accessible
so uh that's Billy Collins but I also want to say something
about a leemon she's our current poet laurate for the United States and 2010
she talks about the relationship between poetry and
noticing which is arguably we could say is what Billy Collins is pointing to as well this relationship between poetry
and noticing and I would say relationship between poetry and practice
right it's about noticing so this is AD leemon she's our current poet
laurate or maybe I should say the poet laurate in the United States not everybody that listens to this is in the
United States so Adon says we find it hard to
settle our our brains down and poetry offers us that silence
that quiet space that allows us to reconnect with ourselves or with an idea or with an emotion it's almost as if
poets are offering a religion of noticing things or a religion of paying
attention and it it's nice that it doesn't have any connotation other than that just notice just pay attention just
be here I'd like to build on this idea of just
be here or just notice because what are we doing if
we're not just being here and just noticing and that is we're often lost in
thought as Billy col says beating the B with a hose which oh gosh it just feels
so painful right trying to get a confession or trying to understand things
so often we have this habit of just trying to figure everything out which is
appropriate and helpful a lot but not 100% of the
time if we have this Hammer we have these beautiful brains these Minds that can analyze and figure things out but it
doesn't mean that everything in our experience is in nail and part of I would say living a
full life a rich life in part of of what poetry offers us and part of what
practice meditation practice mindfulness practice offers us is this
recognition there's more than one way there's things that aren't nails that don't require the hammer of figuring
things out but instead uh maybe they are butterflies or maybe they are blue skies
or maybe it's the soft touch of a kitten that comes up and nudges your
hand so there's this way in which analysis removes us from our experience
we kind of like lose contact with what's being experienced what's being heard what's been seen and what's being
felt felt literally with the body or with our emotions and we want to just um
get in there and think about it it's not surprising that we do this
because we've been conditioned to do this we've been rewarded to do this certainly I've probably many of you just
like me our professional lives were so much about figuring things out and it's feels nice right to have a
problem and then solve it or maybe even just have a problem and think about it and try to solve
it so and maybe I'll say also there's a discomfort of with not knowing like of
feeling confused like why I don't get it like people don't like to have that feeling I don't get it and so they will
do a lot of things to try to make sure that they don't have that
experience so I don't want to say that practice is about never thinking but what I do want to say is
our life practice included is not only about figuring things
out there's a way that we can feel our way into experience
and so we also another trap we can fall into is that with meditation we might
think that uh we have to get rid of thoughts or have to give rid of a all
thinking shouldn't be there there shouldn't be any thoughts or something like that that's a trap
too so I would say poetry and practice are offering us different ways to be
with experience and I'll just say a few things about
practice with thinking that we can maybe there's we can have aspirations or we
can have a even to recognize that there's these different types of relationships to
thinking that we can have but there's this way that there's different more than one way to be with thinking so one
is can we not feel harassed or hanged by
our thoughts or can we not be diluted by our thoughts
so there's there's this way can we have thinking and feel free recognize the
freedom while thinking is happening that's maybe one way that we can have as a direction to go if we're not there
already if our relationship with thoughts a second one is can we develop
the ability to think well that is to reflect clearly maybe even
boldly like you know to have some creative to have some uh original
thoughts as opposed to Simply like being agreeing or disagreeing with what we're
presented with you know by the media or by others or Dharma teachers or you know something like this but instead can we
engage and like ask questions and allow what's being presented to us
in whatever format reading podcast th talks uh social media you know all these
types of things can we develop the ability to actually think things through
and have this commitment wait I want to understand this and think it through as
opposed to just passively consuming stuff and allowing ourselves to be
impacted by it and a third way is can we use uh can
we discern when is thinking unhelpful and when is it helpful because it's both
right sometimes it's very helpful required and needed and sometimes it's not so helpful and can we have room for
both in our life to notice yeah this type of thinking it's not so helpful and
and we recognize it and as best we can let it go when we see so clear how it's
unhelpful often this Letting Go happens naturally and then maybe I'll just say
briefly the Buddha talked about in um in his own path towards Awakening that he
recognized oh there is helpful thinking and unhelpful thinking there's UNH
helpful being um defined as causes Affliction or agitation or
uneasiness in oneself and or in others so what is the
type of thinking that doesn't support greater Freedom greater well-being either for ourselves or for
others and then maybe this simplified way is thoughts of Cruelty or harming
thoughts of ill will thoughts of sensual desire reliably do not lead to Greater
Freedom peace ease and [Music] well-being so when we notice that this
is happening is there a way that we can soften or let go and part of the way is
maybe to recognize the the Dua of that type of thinking the way that our minds
get constricted and there's this closed mindedness and this uh tightness
that gets associated with that there's a lots more that could be said about this but just to recognize that there's
different ways we can have this relationship with thinking can we be
free with thinking not to be harassed by it is there a way that we can recognize
and be able to think well to think through something and have a certain commitment to okay I want to stay with
this and see if I can get to a oh excuse me see if we can get to a conclusion or
maybe there's a way of creative a new understanding so have a commit to think through things and then the third is to
recognize oh yeah when is it helpful and when is it not helpful what are the
topics that are helpful and the topics that are not helpful with our
thinking and I'd like to say Billy Collins and his poem is kind of pointing to there's more than one way we can use
our mind more than one way we can use our
experience I'll read this poem one more time introduction to poetry by Billy
Collins I asked them to take a poem and hold it up to the light like a color slide or press an ear against its
hive I say drop a mouse into a poem and watch him probe his way out or walk
inside the poem's rooms and feel the walls for a light switch I want them to water ski across
the surface of a poem waving as at the author's name on the shore but all they want to do is tie the
poem to a chair and torture a confession out of it they began beating it with a
hose to find out what it really means so thank
you thank you for uh joining me on this uh fourth day where we're talking about
poetry and maybe I'm beating it poem with a hose to find out what it really
means I don't know what do you think thank you thank
you yeah Bob writes many Minds him of years as a Zen student
working with coons trying to figure them out than just being with them thank you B that's ex exactly right there's a way
in which Coons right it can't be figured out
Teresa writes poetry and meditation our cousins very nice very
nice it's kind of a fun way to think about
it water skiing across the surface Bill row writes so right on you still need to
practice but it's freeing to fly wow thank you water SK right like
we're still holding on to the Rope so the poem is like maybe taking us somewhere but there is this uh Delight
right when we water ski I don't think I've ever water skied but I can imagine it looks like it's delightful have fun
looking forward to practicing with you all tomorrow thank you