hello everyone and welcome to
our meditation together And I'll begin
by referring to the idea that often taught in
Buddhism that everything is impermanent And what that means in
essence is that everything is changing Some things are impermanent because they no don't last But some
things are inconstant They're in the only thing that's constant is their
constant movement and change And when we sit to meditate we're
entering into a world of change a world of inconstancy But this world of change and
inconstancy in meditation does not have to be random or chaotic
We are uh putting the conditions together to um uh where the change that
unfolds is a healthy one is a beneficial one That uh the change is
oriented towards being organized oriented towards gathering together
uh gathering together to be settled instead of scattered To be organized instead of
being fragmented to be uh uh centered as
opposed to being desentered or or
um and we can feel this movement inside of us sometimes in psychological ways We
can feel physically that uh we lean towards what we want We pull back from what we don't
want We the mind wanders off we say and it feels like it goes far away The mind
can be scattered The body could be restless which is a lot of movement The
restless body can be uh feel disjointed and not working in
harmony And the body can feel very centered and
collected and settled in itself where the whole body kind of hums as a whole
nice together that uh it's still everything's still in constant but it feels like
everything is changing together in harmony like a well tuned engine which
is humming along very nicely and um or a well centered
wheel which is turning smoothly and nicely It's still changing and
moving And so it's possible in meditation to orient oneself around that
the movement the changing nature of phenomena and to orient oneself to the
movement towards harmony the movement towards a gathering together a
unification a coming into kind of a centered kind of everything has come
become centered and and organized So everything is working together Nothing is scattered Nothing is divided
Nothing is left out There's a feeling of wholeness That's of the whole And we're
coming into that wholeness Coming into that gathering And it's possible to have
a kind of it's very subtle but it's possible to have a feeling or a sense
that it's almost like the gravitational pull the psychological emotional
physical gravitational pull of coming together gathering together
um be uh becoming whole becoming here in a full way
I've been in crowds of people which it seemed chaotic people milling around talking but then the bell rang and then
you see people kind of slowly kind of gather together in a whole circle They
knew to sit in the circle but it was beautiful to watch the coming together and we had a whole circle of people and
a whole different feeling of of being together as a group but everyone had a
sense of where to go to fit into the circle So that sense of everything we
are it knows how to find itself together in harmony partly a gravitational pull
around the center So in this meditation I'd like to encourage you to
see if you can have this very subtle sense Some of it might be physical some
of it might be emotional some of it might be you know mental Very subtle
sense um like the like the subtle feeling of gravity It mostly provides us a sense of
weight and contact against some surface that there's something there that wants
you to come together like on a on a trampoline If you're sitting in the
middle of trampoline weighing it down a little bit all the balls that are on the trampoline will roll down to the middle
We had a trampoline with our little kids that had a lot of balls on it and and so I know what it's like to stand there or
sit there in the middle and have the balls gather So to feel the movements things
are always in motion Emotions are in
motion Thoughts are in motion In a way the body is always in
some kind of subtle motion And to have that motion all that motion
feel like it's coming together to work together So to assume a meditation
posture and think of the meditation posture the outermost form of the meditation
posture as creating a wide large
open space within which everything will fit
Everything has a chance to not be pinched not be cr scrunched
up and not be
forgotten Such posture in some ways maybe the chest can be more
open the spine a little more erect
The belly
relaxed The arms especially around the elbows are soft and
relaxed Maybe pulling the elbows a little bit closer into the sides of the
body Shaking the elbows a little bit to remind them to be relaxed
and gently closing the eyes so the eyes are not searching for
things out outside of you Instead let
the imagine maybe the gaze of the eyes is relaxed inward and
backward So the sense of seeing begins to
participate in this gathering
together and relaxing as you meditate in the beginning is part of this gathering
together So as you breathe in a easy
way on the exhale to relax the muscles of the
face around the
eyes The muscles of the cheeks and jaws imagine that they fall away from
the skull and and relax into the skin
relaxing the shoulders or feeling the pull of gravity
on the shoulders the weight of the shoulders and how there is a very very
subtle Pull for the
shoulders to settle
downward to feel the belly there too Is there any
subtle tendency for the belly to want to relax and
settle Or maybe you feel the opposite the tension pulling in and
up As you exhale softening the belly
And is the thinking mind activated Is there energy
activation agitation movement in the thinking
mind and the power of the moving movement of the thinking mind can be
strong But even there can you feel a desire a
tendency to move towards rest to move towards
calm And as you
exhale to soften
relax The thinking
mind And from whatever degree of calm you can
find in the mind From
there settle your awareness into the body breathing
The experience of
breathing Maybe that place where
breathing comes to rest The resting point at the end of the
exhale
The very subtle movement towards for the exhale to move towards a
place of being settled and calm [Music]
Maybe by allowing the exhale to be a little
longer than normal Not by forcing
it but by relaxing more
And as you
inhale let the body that's around the sensations of
breathing in let Let them be relaxed and
receptive to the sensations of the body breathing in
The sensations of breathing in the body occurs
together with the sensing of those sensations
There's not really a distinction to be made between sensations and
sensing in a certain way The coming together of sensations
and sensing is where the mind and
body become intimate with each other
And if the mind is scattered or fragmented see if you can
gently Bring all the pieces of the mind organize
them to be relaxed and soft to work
together to rest Move towards the sensing of the body
breathing
The sensations of the body breathing can be the center
point around everything around which everything
gathers And to feel the subtle gravitational
pull of unification becoming
whole around this experience of breathing
Feeling any calm or subtleness that's
present And in the middle of the calm and
settleness is there a movement a gathering together a settling
further Is there a centering point of the trampoline which is welcoming all
things to come to settle there at the middle
And as we come to the end of the sitting is there some
settleness some gathering together unification of
being that in and of itself itself needs nothing from
others In and of itself needs nothing but to be at home in
itself be centered in
itself So that as you bring to mind the world that you'll enter into
after meditation the people the work the
activities imagine entering into
it without any
need for it to be in any Okay Because you because you're centered
here And instead of
need there is good
will and care and generosity
emanating from this place of wholeness
where we can care for the world without a need Neediness
May all beings be
happy May all beings be
safe May all beings be
peaceful May all beings be
free And may those wishes
aspirations be the simple expression of a settled heart
[Music]
Thank you
So hello and welcome back to this series on
samadei And this week is a little bit of a review and getting back into the momentum of
the practice after I was gone for two weeks
And uh today the emphasis I'd like to make is talking about the unification
process of samadei And that samadei practice is a
pra practice by which uh the different
scattered parts of who we are Uh scattered energies scattered thoughts
begin to gather together and there's a feeling of unification feeling of of of
some people might call it a feeling of becoming whole where there's nothing
uh scattered There's nothing separated nothing cut out All all of us are
working together And it's a slow process to get there Some people are very
disconnected from parts of themselves They are very connected to certain parts which feels like it's maybe the whole
but maybe they're not connected to their body Some people are not connected to their emotions or some em particular
emotions Some people are so involved in their thinking that almost they don't
know their thinking Um and it is for the the field of
awareness to open and become wider And so this organizing unification is can be
done in two ways One is a feeling of gathering together And the other is a feeling that the awareness is getting
expansive open wider to hold it all So
it's uh um the um there's so there becomes lots of room
for everything And either way there can be a subtle feeling of movement of even
direction towards becoming whole And sometimes that wholeness is a feeling that awareness just wants to expand
outward to include it all And um so rather than zeroing in on
something which is what thinking mind or the anxious mind does or the angry mind
or the desiring mind is it focusing on what it wants what it's worried about
what it's uh wants to push away what it's for and against Here the feeling is
that in the deeper mind the deeper kind of um uh profound kind of place of
existence in us just wants to open up doesn't want to be limited and held tight and it wants to just become
expansive and include it all At the same time there's that can be also feel like
everything is kind of settling together There's a settling process a relaxing process and everything is kind of
gathering into this subtle kind of movement And the difference between this
widening widening awareness to settling is not so distinct
They happen together And um sometimes the expansive
one is called the um mahita the big mind or the expansive mind And
um and um and so so the idea is that
things are becoming unified organized working together not at odds with each other
And um and so this is all part of uh the emphasis in Buddhism that everything is
changing all the time And what's important to appreciate that the change is not chaotic The change follows uh the
patterns and or the conditions is influenced by the conditions we set in place So if the condition is a
preoccupation with thoughts preoccupations with difficult emotions
then that creates a movement towards being more scattered and disconnected Um if the orientation is
towards calm to be centered to be settled uh that moves the change towards
becoming organized uh collected connected everything connected together
And um and so um and so we can contribute to that We set up the
conditions by our what we're oriented towards what our practice is what we're
seeing how awareness operates to allow this kind of movement towards
wholeness And uh but the uh what it needs is a kind of acute sensitivity to
this deeper and deeper sensitivity to the meditative experience as opposed to
heightened kind of preoccupation with um me myself and mine Heightened
preoccupation with our desires and aversions our fears and and uh anxieties
there's a kind of a a shift of orientation from
uh what the mind is gripping onto what it's like to have the the mind
be open the hand be open And it's almost that difference And in some ways the the
hand that's open is unified ready open receptive to what's there The hand
that's fisted together might seem unified in a certain way but the lot is lost in the process and and quickly the
tension that's there in the fist becomes the predominant thing When the mind when
the hand is whole open there's a way in which the whole hand is kind of gathered
or connected or involved together to what's happening And so the same with the mind
the same with the heart this relaxing this opening gathering together And so what I'm emphasizing
today is this subtle feeling subtle sense that we can have of a healthy
direction for the meditation to go Uh that is more subtle and quieter shire
than the pull of our ordinary preoccupations But to start being quiet
enough to listen to feel to sense um this this subtle movement towards uh
becoming settled becoming open becoming expansive becoming connected the subtle
movement that um cares for everything that wants everything to come together
everything to be itself in a settled way It's almost like every way in which we
are scattered every way which we're pulled into preoccupations and desires
and aversions if you feel your way into the middle of the desire the aversion
into the sensation of pulling and pushing and fighting If you feel your way into each
of it you can feel that in there itself has a movement towards
wanting to relax Everything which is fisted wants to
relax Everything which is forceful everything which is tight everything
which is has excessive kind of willful feeling to it everything that is anxious
everything that is insistent everything that's needy in us these are all things
to respect And from this deeper place of sensing you can sense into them and feel
how they want to be connected to the whole how they want to relax and settle
That all things if they're really attentive to it the heart of it you can
feel that they belong to a process of getting organized being connected and
unified returning to the whole if you will
And um and so as the meditation gets deeper and deeper uh this becomes part
of the hallmark part of the characteristics of the meditation it's not a desire it's not a wanting it's
it's inherent in the whole psychophysical system that when it becomes
aware clearly aware of what's here when it becomes settled and relaxed when
there starts to be a kind of a a centered focus centered experience of
here that um everything wants to kind of continue that process of centering
continue that process of opening and um and you can feel the pull
the desire for that And sometimes that desire can uh continue after meditation
in daily life There can be that clear sense of of this is what wants to happen
I just want to meditate more I just want to connect to this more This is what uh
what um what the whole system is about is this coming into whole coming into
the healing coming into the fullness And so there can be this kind
of this this feeling of this is the direction to go in my life even and some
people will decide to go on long retreats Some people decide to do you
know just meditate more Some people will decide to meditate longer That you can
feel inside that after a short period of meditation that what's in here is not
finished There's this momentum this movement this desire almost to continue
this process And um so um the the the or the the
gathering organizing uh the uh process of it all and um
sometimes it feels like it's all coming into a simple simple center where everything gets simpler and simpler Um
the and as it gets simpler just for example just with the breathing at the
same time the mind can feel more and more expansive And sometimes the movement seems like
this more to like more and more expansive like everything is standing in a wide circle but then what's really left is
the edges disappear and what's really left is the center and things get simpler and
simpler So it's a movement towards simplicity also in a certain way because
the mind is not thinking about so many things The mind is not interested in
thinking about so many things It's the mind has been spending a lifetime thinking and wanting and and worrying
And it's done enough of that It's had its chance And sometimes it doesn't seem
to have done much good anyway And there's a strong feeling enough for now
There's a vacation time There's a time to really settle into this other way of
being that is not scattered not preoccupied not desired driven anxious
desired driven or something So the this is the unification
and the word samadei uh that's one of the meanings of samadei It's kind of a gathering together of the
mind in Zen uh 7-day Zen retreats are called
sashines means that means something like the gathering of the mind
So thank you and uh we'll do one more day tomorrow of this kind of kind of a
review and kind of getting into this again and next week we'll return to what
we did before which is the approach um into this deeper samadei what's
called jas and we'll spend another week with the approach uh part of samadei um
and then I'm hoping the week after that we can begin uh at least the discussion of what's called the Janna the
absorptions So thank you all very much