okay so um let's uh let's um I have not had uh use for techquinimity um in quite
a while but um came in handy here and
uh um let's uh let's uh meditate
okay all right
so just on a dime we practice stopping
and what does it mean to stop it doesn't mean that
we sever the present from the past and the
future it doesn't
mean
that we disallow the trace of
memory to arise it doesn't mean we
disavow the concern or fear we might have about the future
to stop on a dime means to feel the convergence of all of
this without being baited into the
mode of fixing and addressing
thing he
Establishing a sense of
groundedness sense of Earth
gravity sense of your belly
it's the stability of
uh sitting in our bones
perhaps
uh gathering uh your attention around
the sensations of your
breathing not by uh pointing the kind of
laser of attention at the sensations but uh
receiving the sensations within a sense of openness
receptivity
and if we can we sense into
the the longing to be free
we let that the force of that longing give us the
courage to get very
simple to renounce to let go
damachand longing longing for the dharma
how simple can we be in this moment
how long is now
how much uh space is there between the breath and the breather
the whole tragedy of human existence Krishna Murray said lies in the space
between subject and object
our clinging and
preference keeps uh reminding us who we are
sort of defensive functions of self keeping tabs
on threat and opportunity
do what we can to uh channel our
uh wish to be free to a sense of
courage the okayess of this moment
let go
we uh melt into uh this breath
and just uh as the meditation ends here uh sensing your whole body and awareness
kind of bathed in awareness
and uh as we open our
eyes not
uh yanking ourselves back into familiar default um position
okay thank you
okay thanks uh thanks folks for your your patience
i'm bellless
and disoriented used to one setup and I
don't have it but I think you can hear me and uh we're practicing
together and um it's amazing that this doesn't happen more it's amazing how
reliable the text been and uh so anyway we'll get that that whatever error it
said said we're um on too many live streams or something
so anyhoozers question from the uh from the
chat line um what are some skillful means when you lose
inspiration in the practice
so first just to say that um we ought to have some measure of
tolerance for the waxing and waning of
inspiration you know every time there's um a period of lower
inspiration is not a problem to be fixed you know one has to bear with the kind
of vicissitudes of inspiration and
um we could say that the path um is a
dialectic between making a kind of comfortable dharma home and the rug
being pulled out from under us and sometimes the kind of it's true the
cozy dharma home phase can last too long
too cozy can be deadening and
um and so the process of um of falling in love with the dharma sometimes
resembles the process of um falling in love with a person
and there is falling in love and staying
in love and we all know people who
uh love falling in love but uh aren't so sure how to stay in
love and maybe partially we need to relinquish the need for intensity and
novelty the kind of hunger for novelty and maybe sometimes we cultivate
the ability even in times of low inspiration we cultivate the ability to
refind why we fell in love initially
sometimes um I've had uh wi with you
know folks kind of struggling with inspiration i I've asked them to
imagine never practicing again no sitting no retreat no
sa no informal practice of mindfulness no contemplation of wisdom and love none
of it then I ask how do you feel now
and they say horrible that's a horrifying
thought and so there's something there we're going to have to keep going it's a
question of how and so we investigate
um what is happening in my relationship with the path and what am I
seeking refuge you know what is the nature of the faith
that's been lost where are we now placing our hope
we're placing our hope somewhere maybe there's
hopelessness you know sometimes we just feel uh flattened by the intensity of some
sorrow some deadness there are we uh comparing ourselves to
some ideal of what's supposed to be
happening and so um we might uh probe okay what got us
into the path initially and is that intention still alive some level every intention we got
into the path with was a little bit naive the dharma is always more than we
bargain for sometimes we've outgrown that intention
you know like the reason we started practicing it's been satisfied in some
way and um you know okay I began to practice
because I couldn't sleep or my anxiety or self-doubt or whatever some existential
curiosity and okay now that's been satiated It's much better now
what and sometimes we actually have to like put that intention down recognize
we've outlived it in order for something new to arise
sometimes we feel uh stuck because we're
trying to ask the dharma to do something it cannot
do the dharma makes no promises about
samsara it doesn't we examine the ways where we try
bartering dharma i'll give you dharma for
samsara dharma may be the only medicine for certain
uh disease but that doesn't mean the it's the medicine for all diseases
so as I often say duka suffering it's an interdisiplinary
problem and there may be some other lineage of wisdom nature therapy 12step
ritual medicine service engagement activism of some kind
it may be something else actually is needed can ask the dharma to be the
medicine for all forms of disease is sometimes we feel stymied
when there's kind of like and this is a little bit of a variation on that theme asking the
dharma to do something it can't do we feel like we we we get um
flattened when there we know there's an action we have to take but we don't
quite feel the strength or courage to do
it and the dharma can kind of stagnate when there's a life move that has to be
made but we're not making it
and maybe our mind's never going to feel ready normally we talk about well we
change the inner life and then our behavior changes right but sometimes
we're never going to feel ready you're going to have to jump before you're ready
and sometimes that action actually kicks up the kind of
debris or the freedom that actually feeds back
into practice the questioner asked for
um for skillful means but this is in a sense tricky yeah
maybe there's some skillful means um but what we're really looking for is
intrinsic interest intrinsic motivation and interest cannot be
imposed from outside can't be imposed from inside either in a
way interest cannot be techniqueified and the lack of
inspiration in some sense is a lack of damovichaya
investigation investigation a lack of um
um py not in the so much the kind of
um samadei sense of janna sense johnic factor of of rapture but like in the
sense sometimes pet is used as like kind of wrapped attention passionate interest
um and that kind of
um arises you know according to many causes and conditions not a decision we
make and certainly can't be imposed from the outside just to get very
interested but once we get very interested in in whatever
uh that has its own karmic
reverberations you may have to learn to love something
new it's not a a decision that can be made i'm now I now love this i now want
to nurture this it's like not a decision but we make gestures repeatedly over
time to breathe life into that new love
that new interest
sometimes practice stagnates and the inspiration stagnates when where our our practice orbits too
much around the self you know it's like sometimes it's just like
ah I I really can't get excited about practice for
myself but the intention becomes very alive okay let me practice for
others and you have to have like a palpable sense this matters this matters this
um uh your practice matters maybe in ways
you can't even fully imagine okay maybe that breaks through some of
the stagnation the deadening sometimes interest comes from
um spiritual friendship you know uh
inspiring practitioners a friend a teacher doesn't have to be a
teacher often for me talking with um uh practitioners you know I I hear
something very it might be little it might be big but I hear something very inspiring you
might not even notice that I noticed it but I have this feeling of like
uh I didn't quite know that i didn't quite know that in that way
i want to know it you
know great is this matter of life and death time waits for no one do not waste
your life zen tradition
says then the uh Tibetan tradition four thoughts that turn the mind towards the
dharma appreciating the preciousness of human
life that this precious life will not
last that our behavior affects our experience
there is karma it's not that our behavior is the only karmic
force but it is one of them and the fourth thought that um the
defects of samsara the unquenchability of ordinary
craving and sometimes we make um the uh the confusion
uh an object the flatness an object and maybe
maybe In deeply allowing
noninspiration deeply allowing confusion a direction
emerges it's Ken Mloud um a few times in my life I've been in difficult
situations situations in which I could not see any way forward
my morning practice sessions I would to the best of my ability rest in the
confusion that swirled inside me i suppose it was the years of effort that
made that resting possible even though uh even though
through all those years those efforts had seemed poulry and ineffective when I could rest in the
confusion it grew quiet and dark quiet of a dark night with no moon or
stars as I rested in that darkness a clarity would sometimes
arise and with it a sense of a direction how or what discerned that
clarity or that direction I don't know but both were
there the clarity didn't illumine anything didn't make anything in the
situation clear just indicated a direction where that direction led or
what I would encounter I had no idea there was a
direction nothing more
so I um offer this for your um consideration and uh yeah may we
um may we uh continue on together
practicing okay thank
you yeah good to be with you hello