good morning dear ones let's start with a sound check let me know if you can hear my voice and let me know if you can
hear the
bell and also let me know if you can see the video
so we'll give that just a moment or two to um get to you and come back on the
chat usually takes a minute
let's get started good morning all my name is May Elliot and I am beaming in from Santa
Cruz California and today we will begin our investigation of the three
characteristics um in our meditations uh will start each day for for the
following uh the upcoming three days um each day we'll start by uh cultivating
some of the supportive conditions for insight um so we'll begin each Day by
connecting with contentment uh then we'll cultivate somadi You by settling with a breath by uh inviting the mind to
stabilize and then we'll open to whatever our Insight theme is for the day uh and the theme for today is Ana or
impermanence inconstancy and uh while I'll be
offering a practice that deliberately cultivates the perception of anich of
impermanence uh know that you can still have insight into a n without doing this
specific practice um there are many practices that aren't even intentionally or deliberately deliberately cultivating
Insight which still reveal insights so for example um you might be doing a
basic mindfulness practice like open awareness also called choiceless
attention and just not noting whatever arises in experience and a practice like this
reveal insights even if you're not looking for them even if you're not directly trying to cultivate them so
even though um uh we'll deliberately cultivate each of the Insight themes in
our guided meditations each day uh know that this isn't the only way to open to
Insight you don't need to go looking for it so uh with that said let's get
started go ahead and find your your meditation posture
connecting with a uh position that is both upright and
relaxed taking a moment to connect with the
body allowing yourself to soften
connecting with whatever is here for you whatever is happening in the heart in the mind in the
body and what you find it might be pleasant it might be unpleasant it might
be neither somewhere in between
and can you connect with some modom of contentment regardless of what you
find even if it's a very quiet
contentment a very subtle contentment
so actively bringing forth this sense of goodness remembering the goodness of
just getting to be still I have this opportunity to train
the mind and the
Heart maybe sensing a a sliver of gratitude
let's place a simple contentment however slight uh will
connect with our home base our anchor whether that's the breath or the body allowing yourself to
land if it's supportive for you you can continue the practice we discussed
yesterday connecting with the moment an inhale begins and coasting on the rest
of the breath almost like a bird flapping in
coasting gliding in the
air
e e
allowing the Blizzard of the mind to [Music]
settle
e
e e
maybe recalling the image of the sun cresting over the
horizon as being like that first moment the inhale
begins seeing the
sunrise
e
e e
having taken some time to open to the breath to settle with the
breath we'll now shift our attention to the changing nature of
experience to a n in
constancy well there are many ways to ATT to anicha but today we'll do it through the
changing nature of the body and the
soundscape starting with the body rather than having a narrow focus
of attention on the breath uh allow yourself to widen the attention almost
like widening the aperture on a camera so that you can take in the whole body
and when you do this you'll notice other Sensations come
into view you might notice that some
Sensations are more predominant than others at any given
moment if you do you know a predominant s sensation allow your attention to go
to that sensation to really sense it and explore
it maybe it's uh in the palm of one
hand so you're sensing and exploring the sensations in the
hand as long as they're
predominant you might notice this tingling
pressure
temperature you'll notice that the felt sense of the body of this sensation is
different then our mental image of that part of the
body it's different than our thought about that part of the
body we're staying with the felt experience the felt Sensations
it may be that that area of the body is no longer as predominant or there's
another Sensation that draws the attention which you in which case you can allow your attenion to shift to the
new
area so being receptive receiving sensation [Music]
allowing the attention to move where it's called
it's fine if the breath becomes predominant and that draws your attention back
wherever you are in the body noticing tingling or
pulsing can you sense the changing nature of the
experience the fluxing shifting nature of
experience
e e
staying with a sensation until a another draws your
attention and seeing the way Sensations arise and pass as the attention
shifts
e e
even though the body is our primary Focus for the
meditation you may notice that emotions or moves or thoughts come
through these other experiences May draw the attention for a
time and if so rather than relating to them as
Intruders or distractions can you include in them in
your perception of anicha and you see them
arise flx and pass away as you return to the
body
e
e e
even Sensations that seem to be ongoing see if you can notice any
pulsation or vibration if so this is revealing some
change some Inc
constancy
e e
you might also include the soundscape
now noticing any sounds that
arise those sounds might be mirror maybe within your own
body breath [Music]
digestion maybe even the sound of the
heartbeat there might be sounds in the room you're in the
sound of my voice or sounds
Beyond maybe outside coming through
through noticing sounds coming and
going arising sustaining and passing
away e
even sounds that seem to be ongoing was there an inconstancy to them
maybe a pulsing a [Music]
vibration or sounds that may seem constant become
inconstant when the attention shifts to a different object momentarily maybe sensing the body for a
moment before noticing that same sound [Music]
again seeing this Inc constancy the shifting of the
attention and the shifting of the object
itself
e
e e
welcome back and welcome to those of you just arriving again my name is May May
Elliot and I'd like to start with a brief story I spent about eight years living
at Zen monasteries and temples which were all in the lineage of Suzuki roshi
and once a long time ago uh Suzuki roshi was giving a lecture
uh and afterwards in the Q&A uh one of the Zen students asked a question he
said something like Suzuki roshi I've been listening to your lectures for years but I just don't
understand could you please just put it in a
nutshell uh could you reduce Buddhism to one
phrase so of course everyone laughed Suzuki roshi laughed and then he
SL everything
changes so this is our one constant Everything Changes this is what uh this is Suzuki
Roshi's Buddhism in a nutshell everything changes so today we'll be discuss
discussing anicha translated as impermanence or inconstancy and this is the first of the
three characteristics that I'll be discussing over the next couple days and as I shared
yesterday uh when we're not when we're not lost in the blizzard of our thoughts
uh when the blizzard settles we're able to see more clearly and what we're able
to see clearly are the three characteristics impermanence suffering and not self in other words uh we're
able to see the changing nature of things we're able to see that clinging leads to suffering and we're able to see
that there's no fixed uh Center fixed core no fixed abiding
self to this being that we refer to as uh me myself
mine so as we enter into this territory um I really want to be clear that these
three characteristics uh they're not things that you need to believe uh they're not views you need to hold about
reality um yeah I'm not I'm not here to convince you that the three characteristics are true um you know as
a belief system or view but rather to support you in seeing them for yourselves that's what becomes
transformational um so not beliefs you need to hold but insights that are
revealed so uh let's focus in on ana um
impermanence so um many of us here about impermanence in relationship to the Dharma this is you know a common
teaching so I'd like to discuss what it is and why it's significant um so
insight into impermanence is often considered the core most important
Insight of the Buddha and it creates the groundwork for the two other insights
insight into suffering and not self the poly word MAA n i CCA means
constant anicha means inconstant so this is you know one of the reasons we can
translate anicha as inconstancy we're having insight into
inconstancy but when we live in the thinking mind the mind that's dominated
by Concepts our reality can seem pretty fixed and unchanging so for example we
can live in fixed Concepts like um my parents are unsupportive
or my spouse is unreliable or I hate my job you know and
there can be this sense that you know this is how my job is and it's always going to be this way it's a fixed idea
but really um there's what's happening and then the story that we tell
ourselves about what's happening so you know two things that are happening at any given time what's actually happening
and in the story we tell tell about it um and what's actually happening is
always changing but our stories tend to calcify our experience the stories we
tell ourselves about what's happening often hold a fixed view so we end up
creating a story that ultimately we feel trapped by and this is how uh as some
say uh we can build ourselves a prison in Paradise know our stories they're
like uh conceptual overlays made up of of thoughts of ideas of belief Bel and
we can feel imprisoned by them at times so when we're not living in our
thought World um when we're not lost in our thought world uh we can begin to get in contact with what's actually
happening what's actually happening um beneath the tick or tape of our narrative beneath the ticker tape of our
storyline and when the thinking might has settled and the mind is clear what we see is that phenomena is arising and
passing over and over and over and this can facilitate a lot of
freedom so there are there are two primary ways impermanence is discussed
in the sutas first there's the repeated arising and passing away of experience um uh
what I think is easiest to refer to as inconstancy and then secondly uh is the
way that things change over time and this latter point the way things change over time is what most people typically
associate with impermanence and what um what most people can very easily
perceive you know it's seeing on a more gross level that things change for good
you know our body looks and feels different when we're 70 than it did when
we were 17 and we're not going to get that 17year old body back um or you when
a loved one dies they're not returning to us uh when we break a teacup we see
its transitory nature so this is all demonstrating this more gross level of
impermanence so some people think an Nicha only refers to the way things pass
away for good you know either dying or ending but the core Insight of the
Buddha uh has a little bit more to do with the inconstancy of things which is
that first type of impermanence that I mentioned so for example
uh if you feel the sensation in your hand and you might notice uh tingling
pressure fluctuation um like a a a kaleidoscope of changing
Sensations so there's change happening there right there's um
flexing a rising and passing of sensation or say we have a difficult
mood maybe we wake up feeling uh sad or depressed and at first glance that
sadness or depression it can seem like a constant everpresent
state um but often when we look more closely we can see um that there's some
fluxing from moment to moment that the mood might be very strong say when the moment we wake up and then uh we have a
sip of coffee and the attention goes from the mood to the coffee and there's a glimmer of pleasure in the mind and
then the attention goes back to the Moon which might be a little lighter now and then maybe um the sound of rain
falling off on the rooftop starts coming in uh so the attention notic is that uh
and then it goes back to the mood again so um this is just like a a tiny little
snapshot of showing the way um uh there can be both a change in the object um um
you know uh and the CH a change in um what we're perceiving so a shift in
where we're paying attention so the um you know the attention goes from the mood to the coffee back to the mood to
the sound of the rain back to the mood and so there's um there's inconstancy in
the object of attention where the attention is going and then in each of those objects you the sound of the rain
is flexing the flavor of the coffee is flexing so um so this is that um um pointing
just to the way that uh there's so much inconstancy in any given M moment the mood itself is changing and the objects
of attention are changing so uh rather than a mood being a monolith it's a
little bit more like swiss cheese like moment after moment there are holes being poked in our fixed P perception of
what's happening so our sadness is punctuated by other experience experiences it's it's arising and
passing so anytime uh we think something is fixed um we're typically not seeing
all the change that's present and on a really subtle level our
experience of the world is in constant you know seeing hearing smelling touching tasting always arising and
passing every moment of hearing there's change emotions and thoughts always
arising and passing so even things that we might initially uh perceive as stable or as fixed
something like pain in the body when we investigate it more closely we often
find that even pain itself is a fluxing kaleidoscope of changing
Sensations so uh why is this important who cares if things are impermanent you
know what's the big deal um well uh when we know on a really deep level that
everything changes uh that everything passes away um we're much less likely to Crave and
claim so if we know that everything will be pulled through our grip we're not going to hold on so tightly and this is
really important know remember the four noble truths first Noble Truth there is
suffering second Noble Truth no sour of suffering is craving third Noble Truth there's an end
up to suffering the release of craving and the fourth the path to the
end of suffering um so I'd like to just zoom in on that second and third Noble Truth the
source of suffering is craving uh craving and clinging so to let go of
craving and clinging is to let go of suffering so this you know this um
inextricable link between craving and suffering so um how does this relate to
impermanence um over time we see when we see closely you know impermanence pulls
everything through our fingertips um we see that if we hold reality really
tightly if we cling we suffer uh when we hold a rope really tightly if it's
pulled through our grip we get rope burn the same thing happens with
anything we cling to with our heart and mind but if we grasp anything really
tightly when it's pulled through our grip because of impermanence we're going to suffer and the heart's going to get
rope burnt and ultimately insight into impermanence it
supports a deep Letting Go it teaches us to let go in other words it conditions
non- clinging so when the mind is steady
and we see change over and over and over the Mind learns on a really deep level
that there's no use holding on when it sees this it learns to let go um and it
also learns not to cling to begin with because it knows better right it knows that clinging doesn't work it knows that
clinging hurts so the Mind heart uh knows this as
deeply and as intuitively as we know not to put our hand into a pot of boiling
water it's like clinging ouch that hurts right so so when we see inconstancy over
and over we learn to let go we learn not to Crave and claim and this wisdom that
develops is liberative now with all this said I want
to acknowledge that seeing impermanence um it doesn't always feel good um it can
even be destabilizing to see the inconstancy of things because when we see this really clearly
over and over we see there's nothing lasting that we can hold on to there's nothing uh reliable in the way that we
thought it was um and while this can be challenging if we've sufficiently
cultivated stability and well-being somebody and contentment uh we're not
going to be as unored by it we're not going to be as UNM mored by seeing the inconstancy of things and of course the
gift of impermanence uh is that our suffering can change too um so our
Neurosis compulsion uh our depression and anxiety also
impermanent you know these aren't immate as rir Maria RKA says um uh let
everything happen to you beauty and Terror just keep going no feeling is
final
because things change UNH wholesome qualities of mind can diminish and
wholesome qualities can grow we all have the capacity for
Change and as we see the changing nature of things over time our impulse to Crave
the next object or experience uh begins to fall away because we've seen for
ourselves how transient they are and through this process our
suffering our Dua can come to an
end so uh today may you be aware of the changing
nature of things and may it condition a mind that is free from suffering so
thank you all for joining me today and I look forward to seeing you tomorrow take care