all right hello everyone let's go ahead and get started today
it's nice to see everyone arriving and I always appreciate how you greet each
other so in today's meditation
um we'll continue with this general theme we've had of settling in and
choosing an anchor of some kind even though that's not an exclusive focus of our attention
and then today the invitation um which I'll describe more as we get into
it is to allow the alignment that we
feel when we're oriented and mindful in the present moment to gain a momentum of
its own and kind of emerge and become less something that we do and more
something that we just orient toward and we're feeling almost that alignment that
feeling of being here as the meditation object as much as whatever our anchor is
yeah does that make sense so we'll um this is a way of allowing the meditation
to start to unfold on its own with less doing from us
so with that let's settle in
starting as usual by finding a posture that feels comfortable balanced
aligned [Music]
and gently closing the eyes
sensing that you are here it's not actually a trivial
introductory kind of instruction there's a whole art to hearness
it already brings in the sense of
can we have humility and dignity together
so we're here we're not shrinking away we're not hesitating
but neither are we asserting self arandizing
we're simply here
and in that we look for the possibility of ease
even within a body that may have some aches and pains or may actually be sick
or injured right now and within a mind that may have some
agitation due to whatever came in previously
that's how it is but even with today's this moment's conditions we can feel
some ease one way we do that is by inviting
softening though softening
the muscles of the face the eyes the jaw
the shoulders
i sometimes feel into the shoulder area like around the collar bone
shoulder blades and the shoulder joint the ball and
socket joint
and then down through the torso heart area
softening the diaphragm so it's not a tight band
and letting the belly spread out and down
reducing bracing in the arms or legs
and as some of the holding in the body releases there's a way in which there's an upward
release through the spine
maybe on the inb breath feeling how the spine would like to draw itself upward
slightly and allowing that if you feel that
Sensing whatever degree it's present a sense of alignment
through the body
things have settled into
a place of as much balance as is available right now
and that too contributes to a sense of ease
and then there's a way to do those same movements within the mind
allowing the mind to be present in a simple way
softening the attention in a simple way
noticing how when we meet the moment with just gentle
mindfulness there's a straightening up in the mind
an orienting
this aligning in the mind is separate from what is occupying the mind there
may be thoughts or feelings but the knowing of that the mindfulness
can be aligned and balanced in knowing that
and with all of that gathered together as well as it's available
then we turn toward our chosen anchor could be the
sensations of breathing
or other sensations in the body
such as the overall body sense or the touch points
where we're sitting where our hands are touching
or it may may be that the orientation towards sound feels more anchoring today
and just taking a few minutes now to sense
can I be aware of both the anchor and this background orientation and
alignment that we've set up
so healing both the object and how the mind is
And the invitation in this sit is from time to time
to return to this feeling of orientation and alignment
if the mind has wandered off or even if it's relatively present
taking a moment to feel the balance and uprightness of the mind
as it reathers around the anchor object or as it continues to notice This
inputs coming in thoughts and emotions and sensations
include also this sense of balance alignment
almost like another object that we pay attention to
as we get more familiar with this feeling of alignment
or orientation in the mind
we may realize that it's not something we're exactly doing
although it is strengthened when we notice it
see if you can let it emerge naturally the way balancing on a bicycle
is done intuitively as the bicycle rolls along
it's not too hard to just shift slightly
to keep it upright
much easier when the bike is rolling than when it's standing still
so there's a certain emergent balance
on a moving bicycle and we can sense that in the flow of the
mind and body also
and as we move toward the end of this sitting
perhaps bringing in or considering that
this alignment is an attunement to the dharma
to a natural way that things are
bringing in our qualities of gentle mindfulness awareness
it's like orienting around the eight-fold path the path we can take through the world
it said that when we are attuned to the dharma it can feel like turning upright
that which has been overturned or knocked down
so there's a sense that we come into uprightness and this can work as we walk through the
world also maybe encountering people or situations
that feel out of balance in some way
and our inner sense provides balance balanced if you will for unbalanced
situations with other people it's also said that those who live by
the dharma live contentedly amid those who are
discontent
even live happily amid situations that are not happy
so bringing our practice naturally into the world in this simple internal way
has an effect of bringing some balance into a world that so much needs that
may our practice support others in that way
[Music]
okay so today we reach the end of our
sequence of animals that took us from the vulnerable quail and the foolish
monkey up through the humble cow and the confident deer
and the the mind gradually sees more and more about itself as we walk this path
and more and more about its place in the wider picture and about what it means to live in the
world with wisdom and some measure of freedom
so today's animal is one that represents a mind and heart that are strong and
fortified with good qualities this kind of mind is poised or ready to
have deep insights liberating insights and sometimes this animal represents a
mind that is free that is already free and uh that is the elephant
the elephant and we're also going to return to the simile that we started with 5 days ago or 4 days ago uh so hang
on for that but for now elephants um the poly word for elephant is hoti
and that's the literal animal with a trunk and these are really impressive
beings really we don't have native elephants where I live but I can
understand how in ancient India elephants would be chosen to represent
strength including spiritual strength they're large they're powerful and
they're smart and we now know and maybe maybe they did then also that elephants are quite
emotional they have an emotional heart that has some um apparently real kind of
compassion and connection to it so when a person's mind is likened to an
elephant there is usually also the implication that such a person has the
ability to train their own mind so in a sense we're the elephant trainer as well
as the elephant so these are some lines from the dharmapata
in the past this mind went wandering where it wished as it liked and as it
pleased now I will retrain it wisely as an elephant keeper does an elephant in
rut delight in vigilance protect your own mind lift yourself from a bad course
like a tusker sunk in mud so at some point we know what to do we
know how to practice we can bring the mind to its fullness its full strength
by training it and taming it and it become it can become like a like a
marvelous tamed elephant strong and useful and not going out to do harm in
the world so there's another word that is sometimes translated as elephant uh but
it's actually a more general term for beings that are spiritually powerful if
you will and that word is naga so you can call a literal elephant a
naga but nagas are also mythical serpent-like beings
we don't have them exactly but maybe sort of like our dragons good dragons that we have um and so the word naga can
also refer to an arant a fully awakened being
so there's a number of sutas also about nagas and I want to read one of them or
this excerpt from one of them it's about how the nagas um uh have their young and
then they get bigger and stronger as they as they grow so apparently um these
naggas go way up to the top of the mountains in order to have their their
babies and it says um the Buddha says based
upon the Himalayas the king of mountains the nagas nurture their bodies and
acquire strength and when they have nurtured their bodies and acquired strength then they enter the pools and
from the pools they enter the lakes and then the streams and then the rivers and
finally they enter the ocean and there they achieve greatness and expansiveness
of body so too based upon virtue established upon
virtue a meditator develops and cultivates the seven factors of awakening and thereby they achieve
greatness and expansiveness in wholesome states so there's this analogy being
made right between the grow there's growth that goes on on this path we
won't go through all the seven factors of awakening today but it's maybe useful to know that the first one of them is
mindfulness so once again we have this as the foundation
where we started and where is always the safe place for us to be and to grow
so like the baby nagas in the mountain pools we may start small but then
there's this continual process of growing and also notice that there's a moving into new circumstances you know
from the pools to the lakes to the rivers and onward to the ocean so
I like to think of it as our life is not really the same as we grow along the
path maybe we're always in the water but it has a way of looking different and
feeling different as we gain insight and then in some way maybe internally uh
we're meant to become large and powerful through practice
so it's helpful as we grow to be aware of this and to actually honor the wisdom
and the insights that we've had no matter how simple they are i mean our
first insight might be something like wow there's a lot of restlessness in
this mind i had no idea I was living with this amount of craziness
great that is a great insight and one suta says that if we encounter a naga
whether it's a baby naga or a bigger one in our mind or heart we should and this
is quoting from the suta leave the naga serpent do not harm the naga serpent
honor the naga serpent so there's a way in which honoring
what's gone on for us in the practice whatever it has been so far supports
this on growing growth in the insights that we're having
another suta points out that the footprint of any animal would fit inside
the footprint of the elephant and in the same way any dharma teaching can fit
within the teaching of the four noble truths so in particular if we start to
understand something about suffering and the end of suffering in a deep way it
informs our whole practice and our whole life everything can orient around what
we're understanding about duca and release of duca everything fits into that
so that's another way that we become the elephant if you will
so now we can return to that same suta that we talked about on Monday with the
quail there was an image of a little quail being bound by a vine and it noted
that even a thin vine is a strong bond for a quail and that was likened to a
person who can't give up even things that are harmful to them they cling even
to unh wholesome ways of being and that's kind of where we start but in
this very same suta uh the elephant is the contrast that's made to the quail
and the so the suta says in the words of the Buddha suppose there was a royal bull elephant
with tusks like chariot poles able to draw a heavy load pedigreed and battleh
hardened and it was bound with a strong harness but just by twisting its body a little
bit it would break apart its bonds and go wherever it wants would it be right to say that for that bull elephant that
strong harness is a strong stout bond and a heavy yoke and the monks say "No
no for that bull elephant that strong harness is weak feeble and insubstantial."
And then in the same way the elephant is likened to a person who is not attached
even to high quality things in their life material things relationships even
wholesome qualities so I'll excerpt of it for brevity um suppose there was a
wealthy lay person with plenty of material goods of high quality and also
highquality family and relationships and they would see a mendicant sitting in
meditation in the cool shade their hands and feet well washed after eating a dectable meal and they would think ah
the aesthetic life or the life of the dharma is so very pleasant so very
healthy if only I could shave off my hair and beard dress in ochre robes and
go forth from the lay life to homelessness and they're able to give up their
highquality lifestyle in order to go forth so again we're lay people that are
staying lay people we're not necessarily going forth into the homeless life but
we are maybe trying to live more in line with the dharma which is not always the
same as how the conventional world is living and this can be challenging right
uh to live in that way so even a strong harness doesn't bind an elephant and
it's possible to release attachment even to things that would be considered good
enough in a conventional life hey you got the job the relationship the house
the dog all those things that should make you happy and we we may have a
feeling like not quite but if we release attachment to those things we can allow
the mind to move on into the deeper goodness and freedom that comes through
meditative development that comes through aligning our lives really with the eight-fold path so we do have
material things as lay people maybe a job good relationships but the attachment to those can hold us
back on our path to liberation so it's important to learn how to release
attachments that are limiting so the weak quail can't give up even harmful
things and the strong element elephant is ready to release attachments even to
high quality things it's a wide range but the elephant is not meant to be a
distant goal we're elephants right now whenever we can open the hand of
grasping whenever you know of course we're learning to release what is harmful but we can even learn not to get
caught up in benefits that we may have like money like good health like family
if we hold those things lightly then we can allow the mind to flow onward into
the deeper freedoms that come from meditation like samadei like insight
so elephants can see clearly what is truly onwardleading toward freeing the
heart and they can positively choose that over other things
so as a reflection as we come to the end of our week it's worth taking a little
time to reflect on what is most valuable to you what about the dharma is most
inspiring and be willing to choose that so the elephant or the naga represent
the strength of freedom that begins to flow in our mind and heart and can take
us all the way to the ocean so thank you for this wonderful week of
the menagerie of animals and I hope in some way it can be inspiring for your
practice as we move along and support each other in our general movement
toward more freedom more clarity and more wisdom and compassion in a world
that needs that so thank you so much for your practice and for living the dharma life in the
way that you do it's so beneficial please don't ever doubt that thank you