so good morning and good day to everyone welcome to
our morning meditation and in the topic of
samadei a word that's associated with it in Pali is the word sama s A M
A and uh I think one of the appropriate translations of this
word is harmony a kind of um
balanced mind that's balanced in the middle of how things
are the harmonious mind and to and for samadei there's a
harmony that's coming into play we're in harmony with what's
happening and it's a harmony that's closely related
to recognizing
the signs recognizing the signs that signify that we're
getting settled calm centered that we're letting
go and so to simply
recognize to let go and recognizing how that feels good the rightness of
it to feel the tranquility to feel the settleness to
feel the stability to feel the
tranquility and to not try to make something
happen and there is a kind of letting go letting go of trying to make anything
happen but there is a a small prioritization for
samadei and that is to take in to appreciate what is good what is
wholesome as we sit and meditate of course there's many things that can be
difficult many things which are challenging but many minds are overly
concerned with those things and meditation is a time
where it isn't we want to push these things away but it's also a time that it's okay
not to be concerned with them preoccupied with them and instead orient
oneself to what is going
well from the meditation if we are a
sailboat and your sailboat is heading directly into the wind and the
waves it'll just it won't go anywhere might even be pushed backwards
and it'll be very rough very unpleasant it's appropriate for the sailboat to
turn away a little bit from the wind about 45 degrees and then the wind can fill the
sails and then the sailboat can go so then the wi the boat is in har the
sails in harmony with the wind so to assume meditation
posture and to gently close the
eyes and right from the start assuming this
posture is there anything which feels
good nice for you to have put down the concerns of the
day or to return to your meditation [Music]
posture to be here for this
meditation and to feel
sense what feels good even if it's just a teeny
bit you're a little bit already a little bit calmer
settled more content just to be this
way let that fill your sails
let that be what you
notice instead of heading into the wind of your
challenges find the wind that fills your sails in a good
way and gently taking some deeper
breaths then relaxing your body as you
exhale a little longer exhale than usual so the relaxing can be fuller
and maybe if you pause momentarily at the end of the
exhale just long enough to let there be some deeper
relaxing letting go in your body
maybe in the shoulders maybe in the belly
And then letting your breathing return to
normal and now feel are there any
further feelings of calm or tranquility settling
with an ordinary breathing on the exhale relax the
thinking mind quiet the thinking mind
and at the end of the exhale have a little pause ever so
slight so that you drop into your body more settle into your body for the
inhale
gently relaxing the thinking mind on the exhale pausing and dropping into the
body
and then let being now centered on your
breathing breathing in and breathing out
what signs what feelings are there now of
calm stability maybe a lightness
Maybe a greater intimacy with your
body if awareness of breathing is your
sail let the good feelings however subtle and weak they may
be let them be there as the wind filling the sail
of awareness of breathing
letting the
mind be simple
the mind is in harmony with whatever feels good in the
meditation
if there's any feelings of
well-being even small feelings of joy or
delight contentment And let
that fill the wa the the sail of your
awareness let that gently fill
you fill your awareness of breathing
as if you're sailing over the breathing the body
breathing filled with with whatever wellbeing is
here
keeping the sails full of wind so the sails don't collapse
the sail of awareness filled with well-being in harmony with whatever
feels good from sitting and
meditating whatever feels good in your body
as the thinking mind gets
quieter the sail of awareness gets fuller
allowing the feelings of well-being
calm quiet to spread through your
body as if your whole body is the sail of awareness
sailing continuously on the inhale on the
exhale the whole
body pervaded
with whatever feels good about sitting in meditation
and taking a few moments to sense
feel whatever feelings of well-being that are here from meditation
to harmonize with those
to open to those to breathe with
And as we come to the end of this sitting no matter how slight it might
be feel whatever sensations feelings of
calm or tranquility
well-being settleness you might have feel it in your
body and it's probably not a specific sensation but a sensation which
is more diffuse or something that spreads or through the
body and imagine that it spreads beyond the edges of your
body the eyes closed the edges of the body are not so sharp
sometimes to feel porousness of how feeling sensations of
well-being expand beyond the edges of the body
seemingly and [Music] imagine that your feelings of well-being
are like radio waves or light waves that spread from you transmitted
from you out into the world just like we don't see radio
waves so we don't see these wonderful waves of
well-being that are carry that carry with them your care and well-wishing for this
world
and may it be that this meditation we do supports
us to spread well-being into this
world by wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of us stay in touch with our own sense of
well-being as a reference point for what we can wish for
others may we spread good will into this world
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this next talk
on this series on samadei
and we've spent some time now on the
approaching the deep immersive experience of samadei this is where samadei becomes
mature or full and uh sometimes the language of
being fully absorbed is used sometimes u immersed fully immersed in experience is
used and um the uh in the in the Buddhist uh
discussions of samadei um it's to uh enter and
abide in Janna jh a na and um I love this expression to
abide to dwell to rest to uh in these wonderful immersive
states And so we enter into and this entering
we approaching and at some point we enter and there's this transition
sometimes it's a slow transition we just find ourselves fully immersed and um sometimes it's a little
bit faster sometimes it can feel like we are just um happily kind of settling into a
body of water and um some people it's a little bit troublesome this image if
they had you know some challenging experience at the water but um it's not
uncommon for some meditators to feel like they're going underwater and very happy and very
peaceful and when they come out of Janna or out of this deeper immersion And it feels like they're coming up out of the
water ahead surfaces and then they can gently kind of let go into the samadei
and they're happily going into this peaceful world the Buddha used the analogy of one one
analogy for being so immersed in samadei as underwater lotus flowers beautiful
multicolored lotus flowers which haven't really surfaced above the water so
they're underneath the water you just see them through the clear water and they're just floating in a very peaceful
clear water peacefully and kind of just immersed in the water touched by the the
gentle water that's unmoving so there's this idea of enter
we enter and for sometimes it just feels like there's a kind of suddenly a flip
like the light the a switch has been switched and suddenly we're we're in a new state some people have the
experience like it's a suddenly a quantum leap um but it's not usually a leap it's more like a dropping and more
like a letting go and it's just oh wow now I'm
here and sometimes it comes with feeling like now we're really here there you know sometimes we gradually go into it
and we find ourselves uh we're not we're not the whole mind and body is not
really going to leave we're abiding we're resting we're fully here with no
tendency to wander off and um and one of the things that keeps
us here now one of the things that's is a feeling of pity the poly word is p i
ti and it's um it's a feeling of usually
it's translated as I like to translate it as joy some people like to give
stronger words for it because it can be stronger uh some people will use the word bliss
um uh but it doesn't have to be strong it could be sometimes uh just
delightfully sweet and um but it's a some feeling of uh of uh sometimes it's
a little bit of a thrill a trill thrill with it i feel like oh this is good like
it's delightful it's like a little bit energized oh this is good now we're here
sometimes it feels like there's a little charge through our body there's tingling and and uh warmth sometimes it's
centered in certain parts of the body that are tingling or vibrating in a nice kind of clear way and joyful way kind of
like you would do if you um uh smiled and uh some people even if they don't
feel joyful and happy just simply making a gentle turning up of the lips of the
corners of the mouth some something kind of travels through the face a little bit that's feels like a little bit of joy or
delight and um but what it is uh the sense of I I just like to call it
well-being a feeling of of the lightness of joy
Some people this pity is experienced more as a light like seeing a white light sometime some people it's
experienced more as um as a pervasive feeling of of um of joy and
happiness and um and uh the idea is to
and it comes from the kind of this I from this absorption just being fully
here uh there is nothing which um is distracting us anymore and all the
different things that we have in our life that are our challenges and difficulties our judgments
are negative conclusions or negative bias have have gone on vacation have
taken a rest receded into the background and there's nothing in the mind that's
unh wholesome there's nothing in the mind which is troubling us in this state
and so without those troubling feelings thoughts uh what's left is feels good it
feels like a relief it feels joy um sometimes the the analogy the Buddha
uses for this is of having um no longer being in debt having paid back a loan
and being free of that burden or no longer being ill free from
illness uh that feels good it feels like oh this finally I'm not sick or not
injured or I can uh uh or uh being freed from prison
sometimes the mind and these difficult thoughts can feel like a prison sometimes he describes it as
being um uh have coming out of a difficult desert journey that was
dangerous and finally come out the other side and it's you're finally safe so now all this unh wholesome all
these difficulties have kind of faded away all the dangers have faded away and now we're fully here and this is good
and um and the idea is to be in harmony with that so some people can still feel
like uh the acquisitive mind the appropriating mind the desiring mind can
still operate and they try to push it and and have this experience be more intense just kind of pushing it and
being it and that's usually not so useful what the Buddha talked about is um
taking the good feelings that come from being immersed being fully here now
settled here take the good feelings and the and let it spread through your body
uh he used a variety of words pervade suse the body and that's really the only
instruction he gives when we get into this first state to the first what's called the first
Janna that's characterized uh many people characterize it by this
feeling of pity of joy of delight of thrill that can be ah this is really
great I'm here wow and flowing along with it but an important thing to
appreciate is that uh entering into these absorptive states of Janna
have a lot to do with letting go in one place the Buddha says that um
um these are known through letting go seen through letting go attained through
letting go and realize through letting go so this kind of letting go don't try
to push anything don't try to make something happen uh don't try to hold on to anything just like it's like you're
letting go into and it's a little bit like for those of you who maybe done some sailing
it's little but like you have to let go of the the sail enough so it can be filled with the wind you have to
sometimes uh uh um loosen the rope that's holding the sail uh in tight
against the side of the middle of the boat so it can feel better and better with u you have to let go so something
can feel let go so it can bellow outwards or balloon balloon
outwards and um and the spirit of this is to is
harmony how can you do how can you stay harmonious in harmony with the good
states and we stay in harmony by not doing anything getting caught by
anything any clinging any attachment any appropriation into self any self-
congratulations and uh and um so at some point as the meditation deepens as we
settle in uh what's valuable is to start feeling the sense of well-being that
could be here even before we go into immersive absorpt absorptive states
it's to uh let there be a reciprocity a feedback loop between whatever little
sense of relaxing peace tranquility you have as a way of uh the gentle wind
that's filling the sail of awareness the gentle kind of encouragement yes stay
here stay with the breath really be here in the present moment don't
overemphasize the feelings of well-being don't at this point try to push them and
make them bigger so much it's just let let them kind of fill your awareness let
them encourage you stay here yes so there's almost a feeling of yes
let go into this let go into this awareness let go into the breathing let
go into now so um the Buddha said that this kind of
pity this feeling of joy that can arise and immersive meditation is not
something to be afraid of and um it's not something to um avoid
and this was maybe one of the great contributions he made in the religions of his time where there was a tremendous
emphasis on aestheticism and and in some places in other places emphasis on ordinary
ordinary everyday kind of joys and delights and pleasures and he was offering something very
different something that was coming up was arising from a very deep place
inside that wasn't an ordinary pleasure but was a kind of a spiritual pleasure
deep heart pleasure or joy a deep pleasure of being in
harmony with the moment with the experience right here and now so that we
enter and abide in states of well-being
so this week we'll talk about this first Janna and uh the different factors that
come into play and um and for those of you most of you you know you're not
going to be in the first Janna but perhaps as you listen to this that um
it's relevant even in in lighter states of meditation and maybe also it's uh
inspiring that what's possible that we have we all have the human
capacity for this and to know this is kind of a wonderful north star that
um that uh inspires you to just be
here to let go into now so thank you very much and um we'll
continue tomorrow