Hello and welcome. And as we
as an introduction to this meditation, I would like to say a few words about
letting go. Letting go is often associated with
Buddhism, sometimes in more dramatic terms like renunciation perhaps.
And um and certainly it's a very important part letting go or release
liberation from clinging. But what is often not appreciated enough
is that um the Buddha rarely talked about letting
go of anything. what he talked about releasing, letting
go re is we let go of holding on.
We let go of clinging to things, not necessarily let go of the things.
And to paraphrase a common teaching of the Buddha in apply to letting go,
he he would have said if letting go
increases what's harmful for you, I don't teach you to let go.
If letting go decreases what's harmful and increases what's beneficial for you,
I teach letting go. And so there's always this understanding that letting go has two for two
purposes. One is to let go in of what is harmful
for oneself and and the other or stressful and the other is to let go so that it's
beneficial. We grow, we develop
but it's not the issue to let go of things. Maybe the English word letting go
implies releasing, letting things go away. But it's uh opening the fist of the
hand. We don't lose the fist. We don't lose the hand. We just just the
the fist disappears. So the idea is not to hold on. And then
there's two ways of that we can let go as I've said before showed before. One
is that we let go and something drops away. The other is we let go of the clinging
and the the grasping but we still can hold
the thing. we can still hold it lightly, openly. And um
so to uh so as we sit this morning,
see if you can let go of the clinging, the grasping, the
holding on to things and then see what happens.
And a lot of what we cling to, hold on to are ideas, our thoughts, our
memories, our beliefs, and we don't even know we're holding on
because we in the grasping we take it as
natural. We think this is how it's supposed to be.
But no, as we sit and meditate, we don't have to hold on to anything, grasp
anything, cling to anything. And we also don't have to reject
anything. The only except for the clinging
except for the holding tight. So in we letting go this way, it's very
respectful. It allows everything to exist in its own
way without our perpetuating it, reacting to it, holding
on to it, pushing it away. And this is a phenomenal gift to ourselves, to the
world, to all the different parts of ourselves to let it be free
of our entanglement with it. And so part of the purpose of Buddhist
meditation is to become acutely sensitive
to how we cling, how we tighten up, how we resist,
how we um become guarded,
how we become defensive, how we become insistent,
assertive. all it all as kind of manifestations of
clinging, grasping, attachment.
So to assume a meditation posture
and right at the beginning of beginning of meditation
assuming a posture that lets the body relax.
Relaxation is a letting go of grasping and clinging
in the muscles.
Gently closing the eyes
and to allow to orient towards a deep
relaxing, a deep softening of the body.
Perhaps taking some fuller breaths to feel the torso, the shoulders, the
belly more fully. And then a longer exhale
to relax, let go, soften.
A byproduct of relaxing the body is that it can relax
the mental tension that might be the cause of the physical
tension.
allowing your breathing to return to normal.
softening the belly
both as you inhale and as you exhale.
If the belly expands as you breathe in, let that be like a gentle massage,
relaxing in the expansion.
When you exhale, see if you can relax the belly still.
On the inhale to feel the shoulders
and relaxing the shoulders on the exhale. Feeling
the face
and relaxing the face.
And then feeling any tension, pressure in the thinking mind.
and with care, compassion, kindness
for the thinking mind. As you exhale,
soften the tension, the pressure.
Maybe you can feel the drive, the insistence
to think.
Maybe there's fear and desire that drives the holding on to ideas and
beliefs and thoughts.
Relax. soften.
Or maybe where clinging, holding on, resides
is in the heart area or maybe deep in the belly.
may be fueled by feelings of fear.
Maybe even a form of assertiveness, insistence.
As you exhale, gently, softly, slowly
release your holding.
Release the force of attachment to anything.
With each breath,
let there be freedom.
and ease. By slowly letting go
of holding
With the help of your imagination,
imagine not holding on to anything.
Nothing sticks. Nothing gets attached. Everything is
free flowing. Comes and goes
like standing sitting in a river and the everything flows. The river
flows right by.
If we try to grasp at the water, we kind of come up empty-handed.
Imagine letting go of everything, sitting here quietly, letting everything
be free to flow, including the freedom of awareness.
That present moment awareness flows freely.
Nothing is let go of.
Only clinging is released.
As we come to the end of this sitting,
I'd like to begin by evoking the idea
that the opposite of
freedom is clinging,
clamping down,
tightening up, freezing,
the heart, resisting,
being stuck in loops of thought.
Bracing oneself against life, against feelings, against
thoughts and emotions.
And that non-clinging is the release of all these things.
letting go, releasing, clamping down, being stuck,
bracing oneself so that we have breathing room.
So we can breathe easily in the midst of all things.
We can have a soft, relaxed belly.
Our hands and jaws, shoulders
can be at ease wherever we go.
So that our thinking is not stuck.
Doesn't overpower us with beliefs and opinions,
projections and fantasies.
to let go of clinging.
So that we have just to let go of the fist. Open the fist of the hand, the fist in
the mind, the fist in the heart.
So our good heart can meet the world. Our
friendly thoughts can meet the world.
Our openhandedness can meet the world.
And may it be by being open-minded, openhearted, open-ended,
we can live in this world for the benefit of all beings,
including ourselves. May our openness
that comes from letting go of clinging be for the welfare and happiness of all
beings. May we freely
offer our goodwill. May all beings be happy.
May all beings be safe. May all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free.
[Music]
Thank you.
So hello and welcome to this series on insight.
And right now we're discussing the insight into duka, insight into
suffering or stress, unsatisfactoriness.
And um my hope in giving these talks now about
suffering that most of you have been along for much of this progression of uh
practice of teachings from the beginning of the year with samadei cultivating a
deep capacity to be calm and centered and quiet, still peaceful, relaxed
and also these talks about um uh insight, the deep capacity to be
present for the changing nature of this world and in doing so to be aware of how
we resist that change, how we stop it, how we um hold on to it, how we uh
struggle with it. Uh, and one of the ways we struggle that Buddhism emphasizes is one way or the other,
we're clinging to something. We cling to how things were. We cling to how we want
them to be. We cling to how things are. We cling to how they should be.
We cling to our beliefs, our thoughts. We cling to identity.
We cling to our possessions. We cling to people.
Um there's no shortage of things that we cling to, we get attached to, we hold on tight. And all of those can be felt if
you're really deeply flowing and inside practice as a resisting or interfering
with a changing, moving, inconstant flow of experience.
It's a way of standing in the river and putting up our hand and telling the river to stop. maybe even putting the
hand in the water to kind of stop it and you can put a lot of effort into
stopping the water and but it the water will flow right around your hand. So
there's something we can feel that we can feel at some point uh in deeper the
practice goes how clinging and attachment um doesn't serve us. It's
actually feels like it's a distraction. It's a interference. It's a it's a
limiting ourselves in a very important way. And so the desire to let go of
clinging is not an instruction, not a thing,
something you're supposed to do, you should do. But with insight practice, samadei and insight, at some point we
know for ourselves, we can feel for ourselves this is not good. Not only that, we can
feel more deeply that the very nature of clinging in the heart of it, it wants to
let go. It wants to release. It's work. It's suffocating. It's tight. It's
painful to cling. And uh and and in the middle of it,
there's a desire to release, to free. And in deeper insight practice is not a
matter of following a admonition you should let go but rather is listening
deeply to the letting go that wants to happen. So in this uh the he talks about
suffering the second characteristic the se second really important insight of insight practice
uh the deep recognition of something about suffering. It's maybe helpful to
appreciate that when the Buddha talked about the suffering that he really wants to address through this practice that he
defined it in a particular way. He defined it as clinging sometimes as
craving. Uh and clinging is a kind of very
um kind of holding on tight um uh much more than is needed.
And uh and there's something about the nature of holding on tight that hurts,
that is stressful, that is painful. And um and so the one of the strong
definitions the Buddha gave of suffering, he he called suffering, the
human suffering that we have, the bundle of clinging.
It's a bundle. It isn't just we cling to one thing, but a few of us cling to a
lot of things. We have a big bundle. And some people keep accumulating bigger and
bigger bundles. Every time we look at an advertisement or see something that we
want, we hold on to that. Um, every all kind all through the day, we're
accumulating more things to cling to, more things to hold on to, more things that we're we're grasping.
And um and the Buddha said that there was five for back in his understanding
five primary areas of this clinging. We can cling to appearances, our own
appearance and others which is a multi-billion dollar industry taking care of appearances in this country. We
can uh cling to sensations to whether things are pleasant or unpleasant, comfortable or uncomfortable. Many
people are holding on to comfort. Comfort means so much more than just
pleasantness. It means security or success or something. Clinging to
comfort and discomfort. Clinging to ideas of things. We cling to
stories. We cling to imaginations.
We cling to the stories of identities. Me, myself, and mine. and we cling to um
consciousness or cognitions that we have. So each of these things just kind of to
it doesn't have to be these five but for the Buddha he puts in these five buckets of bund these five bundles that we're
gathering up all the time and uh and it isn't the bundles is it
isn't the things we cling to that are the issue and this is a very important part of this dharma practice the issue
is not what we cling to the primary issue is the grasping itself
And um and so to separate those two out is so important because otherwise we
think we have to let go of everything. Our possessions, our wealth, our friends, everything. Uh but there's we
don't have to let go we have to let go of anything but we have to let go of the clinging to
those things. And um and in letting go of the clinging we might have greater wisdom. And some
things we see they don't serve us. They harm us. And so we put them aside. But if they benefit from some things, we
don't have to put them aside. Then we can live with them freely with an open hand without clinging.
But this deep movement of letting go of the grasping, the clinging, the holding on, the tightening is really the
emphasis of Buddhism. So in um yesterday I talked about the three kinds of suffering the uh the
we're here now the word duka can be understand pain we understanded as literally as pain there is duka duka the
pain of pain like physical pain they're just pure and simple physical there is the the the suffering the pain
of things changing they're not being what they are people die, get sick,
things will fade, things break, societies change.
And uh and then there's the the um the suffering of the mental formations,
the mental constructs that we have. And the third one is really the primary
concern. We can have mental constructs, mental clinging, grasping towards physical pain. We can have mental
grasping and clinging to a relationship to how things are changing or not changing. And we can have mental
grasping and clinging to our clinging to the constructs we've created.
And so it's this it's a third one which is a primary concern
and they make the first two easier. If we're not grasping, clinging, resisting,
physical pain can be a lot easier. I'm not saying it becomes easy but uh it
removes the second arrow. If uh we take uh if we don't cling to
change then change becomes easier. It's not always nice. It's not always welcome
but it becomes easier to find our way. And one of the remarkable things
is how our hearts, our deep inner psychological life generally knows how
to work through how to find its way with grief, with loss, with change, with
what's coming new, with adapting to the new way of living. Uh if we give it a
chance, give it time. But if we cling and resist, we don't give this deeper heart
a chance to find its way. We interfere with it.
And then uh mental constructs are so much nicer and easier if there's no clinging.
And we learn to let go of those constructs which have that harm us not
for no other reason because they involve this tightness and resistance.
So the core suffering that the Buddhist practice is meant to address is the suffering that comes from
our mental clinging attachments that we have. And as I said at the beginning of
this talk, um, uh, the function of deep
mindfulness practice, deep somati practice is to help us become our own
teacher, that we can feel and recognize
that the uh uh uh how we shortch change
ourselves, how we harm ourselves through our clinging, our attachment. But even
more important, we can feel that deep inside,
deep in the heart of our clinging, our attachments, sometimes our fears, sometimes our
strong desires, sometimes our our very clinging to identity, to me, myself and
mine. There is a wish, there is a feeling, there is a movement
towards freedom, to letting go of that clinging. And so we become our own teacher when we
recognize that the wisdom of non-clinging
and the deep request that even clinging asks of us that our
inner life asks of us. Let go release.
Put down this burden. Free yourself from all this work
of clinging, the yoke of clinging, the bondage of clinging. Put it down.
Let it go. Become free of this suffering.
So um the insight into suffering
is invaluable. So we can see that in the heart of suffering
is a desire for freedom which is an invitation.
Let go of clinging of holding on.
Thank you.