okay folks So uh so welcome It's um I always happy happy to see um your
names and be practicing uh
together So um finding uh yeah finding a posture
Just landing in your body as a bird lands on the earth
Just breathing into your body as if to uh deepen the sense of gravity
And just as we we begin scanning through
uh the the hindrances just to see what's here
So the two poles of energy of agitation restlessness on the one
hand kind of dullness sloth the other
And the two poles of of desire of wanting not
wanting seeking sense pleasure experiencing aversion ill
will and doubt
kind of lack of confidence in our contact with
sensory
experience The dharma
Feeling buried behind layers of
fog And so each of these five we just uh get a kind of pulse
check It's okay Whatever you find just bring that into awareness in your
finding
Just appreciating how profoundly intolerant we are of unpleasantness
But to be judgmental is just kind of uh the architecture of our nervous
system is unpleasantness even quite
modest signals to us that um something about the universe is off its rails
And sloth is unpleasant Restlessness is unpleasant Sense longing is unpleasant
Illw will is unpleasant Delusion unpleasant Doubt unpleasant
We bear with
it and blessing it with our awareness
and pay attention to whatever you feel drawn to pay attention
to Maybe the cycles of your breathing maybe your body more
broadly maybe uh your body experience from the
perspective of emotionality and affect urgency and motivation
Maybe you're anchoring to sound Maybe the anchor is
everywhere nowhere Just wide open to all sensory
experience
But every so often may be fruitful
to check the ways in which our attention can become a kind of
appendage of our wanting
And so [Music] we do a kind of pulse check the ways in
which greed or aversion creeps
into the meditating mind
How much can we
relax and offer a kind of unmixed attention
an attention that bows rather than grasps
We're practicing surrendering control
And we think wait a second no I have to pay attention I have to let go I have
to do all these
things Surrender and control does all of them
You really don't have
to create goodness
Just let it find you
Greed hidden delusion is a making of measurement
Just put down all all
the yard sticks
[Music]
Okay it's nice to uh nice to practice with you Um I know that
sit was better for me having been with you all than it would have
been left to my own devices
SA So for whatever
reason this morning I went back to um
my notes that I had saved from the kind of very first Dharma talks I'd given Um
these are about 17 years ago
and it's kind of a fossil record of my wisdom and
delusion you know and that's kind of interesting to look
back and hindsight of course 2020 as they say
but um we know with certainty that um
uh the present will become the past And so until
time stops some humility is uh is
necessary And um it was curious to see some you know kind of detect some
measure of uh confusion in those notes A kind of
angular rigidity but also uh some continuities
themes that preoccupied me then remain with me
now And I had looked uh uh back at a talk I'd given on a classic line from from uh
Jack Angler who's a I think transpersonal psychologist and Buddhist
uh writer teacher and he he as I as I recall it he
got this question about somebody with psychosis highly unstable sense of
self and uh so the questioner are asked like okay are they given this this very kind of
amorphous sense of self are is that person close to um understanding a nota understanding
not self and uh angller's reply was you have to be somebody before being
nobody and the implication is you have to have a solid sense of self before you
can shed that self and many years later
um um he uh Engler was interviewed and was asked where he stood on that quote
you know and he said yes um well I don't see it as quite that linear exclusive
anymore in a general way I would still stand by it that you have to be somebody
before you can be nobody although it's a provocative way of putting Yet what I
had in mind when making that statement was that if you're going to go to the depths of the Buddhist mindfulness
practice which is what I was talking about it requires certain psychological
capacities what in the psychoanalytic tradition would be called a certain
basic ego strengths And those ego strengths form around some stable sense
of sense of who we are some stable sense of identity I still believe that's
true So I get that the the
deconstruction needs to occur from a place of
strength And I I've recently suggested that there
are kind of two dimensions Insight into not self gives us power insight
into self makes us safe And I think all that's fair enough
but it strikes me that there's some confusion
um involving our language about you know quote
self and uh the philosopher Vickenstein famously says phil philosophy is a
battle against the bewitchment of our intelligence by means of language
And the word self self in the in the phrase self-love it's not exactly the same as
self in the phrase no self not self
anata and selflove is is not the celebration of a permanent selfexisting
entity that is me That's not what self- loveve is Self-
loveve is not a kind of deeply emotionally charged story about the
essence of my being
And self-love is um maybe better thought
of as a kind of forgiveness Self- loveve is forgiveness It's understanding and
honoring one's very peculiar conditioning and
sensing our innocence And so to love oneself is not
to cher cherish or elevate a self or
claim ownership over something
In other words self love is an expression of of
non-clinging Maybe we even say um selflove is the
first mini taste of the emptiness of
self Self- loveve is the first taste
Self-hatred is clinging Self- agrandisement is
clinging Self-love is the beginning of unclenching the
fist the beginning of insight into not self
The kindness we can show to ourself um the love we can show is a function of
metaccognitive clarity Metaccognitive clarity In other
words we're we're not fused We're not
wedded We're not reifying um some some story some self story
In a person with um psychosis that that Angler was asked about there may be a
kind of diffusion in their sense of identity but
often very intense emotions bound up with the self story If you ask
somebody schizophrenia about their self view uh they're you're likely to get some
very charged material and a not uh not self is not
about diffusion It's not about being um confused or oblivious to one's traits
to one the continuities in one's personality It's about um
flexibility and as we drain
the self story of attachment and
aversion we begin to get freer We begin to get freer
And that doesn't mean we can't aspire towards
excellence It doesn't mean that we're confused about our
traits Uh but we know that it doesn't attach to
me Life is um is happening Life is
happening and gains and loss All of it is
happening It's just not happening to
you
Exactly Self-love is the beginning of metacognitive clarity with respect to
traits and characteristics Anata is a dramatic deepening of that
metacognitive awareness It's the
unbinding of his that had previously been grafted
into the model of
self That which um felt like the origin of our
light becomes illuminated
What um we sensed before was something like
I'm the spotlight and now but the spotlight
itself was in the dark and now the spotlight
is a wash in luminosity
The philosopher Letha be in ordinary waking consciousness
representations that are bound to the self-model including our deeply held
often unconscious beliefs about ourselves and our lives typically do not attract explicit
critical attention or reflection They are experiences reality
itself or as that with which we see the world rather than part of the world that
we see When the binding of these stimuli
into the self model is disrupted we disidentify with them a
very straightforward sense rendering them opaque
They're no longer experienced as part of me but as something separate an object
or an appearance in consciousness to which I can attend with some sense critical distance and
suspension of judgment
You get the sense of uh yeah what had been grafted into to me
the place from which I see becomes something else that is
seen There's a kind of unbinding process It's it's along the same continuum of
metaccognitive awareness that begins with selflove
Okay I'm conditioned like this Okay that's okay It's okay Oh I I I aspire to change
this to grow Okay that's okay Self
love And the self that is loved
is easier to forget than the self that's hated
And forgetting the self dramatizes the
importance of
love The self rearises
recongs but we know a little bit more deeply how innocent it is
offer this for your consideration and uh you wish you all a good uh good week
Yeah Stay safe Wish you well Thank you