The Poetry of practice so I've been these days taking
poems that have uh been written perhaps for a general audience and then kind of like pulling out some Dharma teachings
from them maybe that was the intention of the poet maybe it wasn't but uh there's I kind of like
this idea that we can find teachings we can find support for our practice ice everywhere right whatever you know life
is offering us uh and I'm choosing specific poems to
support that but today I'd like to do something a little bit different as we end our time together on the Poetry of
practice and I would like to share a poem that is by somebody who is a
Buddhist practitioner who is practices in our tradition here and is using
poetry to express her practice who is like explicitly she's
not a poet right she's a practitioner and a way to like that's a
straightforward you know using you know clear language um
to express practice and what I think is a beautiful and inspiring
way it's um one thing to like take the dorm out of the Poetry but maybe for
this last day were putting the Poetry in the Dharma you know pretending like they're
different poetry in Dharma but maybe there's some way what you right you know of course there that uh distinction is a
little bit too artificial or heavy-handed but there have been times
when I've I've been on some long Retreats I've jotted down short little poems just as a way to I don't know like
I felt like that could express something that uh was being experienced or known or I don't know
what it was exactly just these short little poems and it's not uncommon right there are a number of uh practitioners
who put together poems and uh publish little books of them I know some people
have uh sent me a number of people have sent me Po books of their own poems that
they've that are associated with their practice so today as I've done in the
preceding days during the guided meditation I'll drop in a poem and then
um talk about a little bit in the D afterwards and again you don't have to
like these poems you don't have to agree with them you don't have to understand them you don't have to do
anything you we just allow them to be heard and it's that simple it's that
simple and of course that's what practice is right it's just meeting what each moment brings as best we can and we
can do that with these poems as well so just
um taking a meditation
posture that expresses Our
intention to meditate and to
be present for whatever each moment
brings tuning into just the experience of the body as
a whole like inhabiting the body
bringing a sense of aliveness sense of presence to the bodily
experience in general
nothing in particular needs to be happening or just
allowing the mind and the body to get on the same page so to speak
as I've done the earlier days feeling the body resting on its
sitting surface
feeling the
contact there's a way in which the Mind might have a feeling of flying
around and a Dreamscape and the body is here
here e
noticing if there are any areas of tightness or
tension and then just gently resting our attention
there maybe in the same way that we put our hand on the back of
just slightly touching someone's back as a way of support
or
consolation care
notice if there are any any feelings
sensations of well-being maybe a certain amount of
okayness this might be a small part of your
experience it might be your dominant
experience whichever it is can you rest attention there
is there a location in the body is a feeling of
okayness well-being dare I say contentment
and we let that experience get as big as it would
like this is an allowing this is not a doing
and can we abide in this with this as
this sense of well-being
okayness even if it's just a small part of your experience
staying here in this
moment e
you find the Mind wandering just very simply
gently begin again either with a feeling of okayness
well-being or with the sensations of breathing
e e
tuning into the bodily experience feeling
embodied and is there a way you can just abide
in the body in this
moment
e
e e
drop in a poem poem is called My
Religion by Aya M My Religion by a
madeand to live and die without regret that is my
religion to taste the cup of the sacrament of this moment now my only
moment how otherwise to spend it for tonight I may
die to abide in the fragrance of goodness in the world enduring
awake to bring no harm to myself or
anyone to be a cause for kindness and compassion a joy that defeats
despair to smile with courage through life's storms and trials trusting the
inherent principle of love to pray to live and die a simple
way
e e
read this poem
again my religion by I
am to live and die without regret that is my
religion to taste the cup of the sacrament of this moment now my old only
moment how otherwise to spend it for tonight I may
die to abide in the fragrance of goodness in this world enduring
awake to bring no harm to myself or
anyone to be a cause for kindness and compassion a joy that defeats despair
to smile with courage through life's storms and trials trusting the inherent principle
of love to pray to live and die a simple
way
e
e e
[Music]
thank you thank you for practicing
together so as I said at the beginning of the guided meditation that rather
than I'm taking the like the Dharma in a poem uh today we're looking uh the
Dharma being expressed as a poem Dharma practitioner somebody describing her
practice uh with this in poetry which you know sometimes it's like we can't
find the words maybe it's not so clear I know I've been in I've um offered
practice discussions and I've um been a student in practice discussions where the practitioner is like can't quite
find the words exactly how to express what's uh happening and so maybe like
poetry is a way in which we can you know it's a different way to
express we can use it you know some to recognize the to point indirectly
to what's being known or what's being
experienced so this uh poem is called My
Religion a maid and d and maybe I'll before I read the poem
say a little bit um about the the person who wrote it so she uh this person was born in
Canada um maybe I'll say a little bit about her name so her ordination name so she's a
Canadian um Mid Andi is her ordination name a means sister so this is something
that's um given to uh nuns in our tradition the um instead of like biku um
she would is a here and midan Andi her name means we could say it's like maida
is wise and anandi is a joy wise Joy or
the way that poly works it could also be the joy of wise fullness or uh the joy
of wisdom wise fullness I made it up a new word there but um I don't know I love
the these two qualities wisdom uh sometimes it can be translated as intelligence but I like wisdom and joy
so the happiness of wisdom or I don't know this a beautiful name a beautiful name so she ordained as a 10 precept nun
in 1988 this is quite some time ago with under SAA
upand and then when Burma closed their borders uh she left
and went to uh England and practiced there in aan charage at amaravati some
of you might know amarati this arano Aran Amar over there and then um it wasn't until 2007
maybe almost 20 years later that um she received full ordination and that was in Taiwan and
then in 2008 she returned to Canada so there a inspiring woman I would say who
had this dedication to practice that ordained even before full ordination was available for women and now she's the
founder of Sati sarinia this is a Hermitage a monastery
for women in Canada in Eastern Ontario so here's somebody who's
dedicated her life to practice and I'll just say Sati Saria we could translate
that as maybe these are two words like sey mindful Seria we could say is a
friendliness friendly mindfulness being mindful of friendliness or I don't know
there different ways we could uh translate that so here's somebody who as I said
has dedicated her life to practice and something that I appreciate so much in
the sutas we see that the Buddha he was taking the words of the dominant
religion of his time it's would have been brahmanism kind of like a Proto
Hinduism and he used words of that dominant religion and then redefined
them uh for what he was teaching so he was using words that people would have been familiar with but redefining them
we find this all throughout the sutas and here I am is doing the same thing so
this is a subtle thing that maybe if you didn't know about the sutas it wouldn't appreciate as much
but when I read this I just loved how she's conflict um I'd be finding a way
to bridge between the dominant religion which I would say is judeo-christian in
Canada and the United States and uh her practice so here's this poem called My
Religion by I am Andi to live and die without regret
that is my religion to taste the cup of the sacrament of this moment now my only
moment how otherwise to spend it for tonight I may
die to abide in the fragrance of goodness in this world enduring
awake to bring no harm to myself or anyone to be a cause for kindness and
compassion a joy that defeats despair to smile with courage through
life's storms and trials trusting the inherent principle of
love to pray to live and die a simple
way I don't know I feel really touched by this you know there's the real
Simplicity of the words that she's using kind of like supports this Simplicity of
she wants to have her life to be and I like how it's kind of like a list of
things to do this to do this to do this so she has this uh Clarity and this uh
simplicity so maybe I might say we could summarize this as
purpose maybe I could say presence maybe presence Integrity compassion
presence Integrity compassion for this to be one's religion
what a beautiful thing what a beautiful thing to move through the world this way so I love this uh this opening
stanza is to taste the cup of the sacrament of this moment now my only
moment taste the cup of the sacrament of this moment this way of bringing
something uh maybe Divine or something uh bigger than
oneself or to uh maybe um something that
is feels holy to this moment to taste the cup of
the sacrament of this moment I know I feel touched by this just recognizing
the preciousness maybe of each moment because later right she says um for
tonight I may die just recognizing that you know why put it off like why think
that you're going to be mindful later why are you going to be present later you might not have a later we're not
promised anything so why not test the Divine the
holy I'd say maybe the beauty the grace of this moment and to drink the cup or
to taste the cup of you know to taste so it's not that we're thinking about it
it's more that we're experiencing it so presence and then Integrity to
bring no harm to myself or
anyone I would say can you imagine what a world it would be if all of us decided even to do one
of these no harm to myself or no harm to others
like to have this commitment to do either of those how the world would be
different how the world would be so different because there's a way if we have this commitment to not harm others
means that we also can't harm ourselves or to not harm ourselves or not harming others also right there's a this as our
practice deepens we start to see how you can't separate harm from oneself or others there's a way in which we can um
think that we're not going to harm others and then we end up harming ourselves because we're bending over
backwards and allowing boundary boundaries to be crossed or something like this when we're trying to not harm
others but if we like really have this as a guiding principle of one's
life then we start to see how it's just this non-harming in general and we can't
make a distinction between ourselves and others in the beginning there is there definitely is but as we go deep deeper
and deeper and more and more um flavors and colors our life we start to see oh
yeah this commitment to not harm impacts
everybody and instead this idea of to abide in the fragrance of goodness in
this world fragrance of goodness the sense of
that goodness is maybe something um like not so tangible you
know sometimes maybe you uh walk into a home and somebody is uh finished baking
cookies or in a bakery and it smells like fresh baked bread there's just the scent of even if you can't quite
precisely put your finger on what it is this fragrance of
goodness this way in which maybe you have a conversation with somebody and you feel maybe
um it doesn't have to be big up brightness but it's not this like oh oh
uh and you felt like you had to protect yourself and maybe in a subtle way or you had to make them feel better or
there was a lot of work in the conversation or something like this this way that sometimes we um when
we meet a moment there is this subtle feeling of this this is there uh
allowing this more openness this more ease
more spaciousness is more freedom or is there not and I would say the goodness is this
uh what allows the most openness the most freedom to abide in the fragrance
of goodness in this world there is goodness the media wants to tell us
otherwise other people want to tell us otherwise but there is goodness I'm not
denying that there's Badness I'm not denying that but I feel like I want to overcome
this negativity bias that so many of us have and also point out that there's
goodness and then this this uh presence integrity and
compassion she uses this word compassion explicitly to be a cause for kindness
and compassion a joy that defeats despair recognizing there is
despair but to act in a way that with kindness and compassion and to create
the conditions in which others can have kindness and compassion this brings a joy that defeats
despair can we treat ourselves with kindness and compassion and treat others
with kindness and compassion so a an mid
and her religion presence Integrity compassion
I feel inspired by this may you feel inspired by
this maybe there's a way in which there's a if not
a actual poem maybe there's a way in which there can be um maybe some unspoken uh just a
sense of possibility and some actual experience
of presence in integrity and [Music]
Compassion maybe with some Simplicity simple uh in there sprinkled in there as well right so here's this poem
again my religion by a
madeand to live and die without regret that is my religion to taste the
cup of the sacrament of this moment now my only moment
how otherwise topend it for tonight I may die to abide in the fragrance of
goodness in the in this world enduring awake to bring no harm to myself or
anyone to be a cause for kindness and compassion a joy that defeats
despair to smile with courage through life's storms and trials trusting the
inherent principle of love to pray and live and die a simple
way beautiful so thank you thank you for
joining me these days on the Poetry of
practice it's been a pleasure practicing with you all this week I'll say that some of you might
know that tomorrow the Sati Center which you can find at sa.org there is
a an offering by um it's terrible his
first name I think it's John brim is that his first name Mr brim is who's
written a few work few uh books the last one being the Dharma of poetry he's
freely offered there's something at the sa Center uh tomorrow so uh you might
want to look at that might be uh fun and interesting I think he's calling it The Poetry of not so you know I wish I had
the specifics uh right here in front of me but um you can find it at sa.org and
for those of you who live in the area in a couple of weeks uh on Saturday I
believe it's the 18th I'll be doing an in-person poetry of practice day long
this will not be online nor will it be recorded I'm sorry to say so it's one of
those things that uh if you're there we can practice together it'll be um some poetry and a lot of mindfulness and
silence as well as a poetry so thank you thank you
again and may you find some beauty some poetry in this
moment whatever the moment is bringing in