so uh for today I want to um kind of tell you a story but also um
uh offer you the teachings the Buddha gave uh for the monks at Kosambi uh it
had to do with the conflict in Kosambi uh we sometimes might naively think that
the Buddha was so so great wonderful teacher that there couldn't have been any conflict in his among his disciples
in his time everyone was must have floating on clouds and got along really well but uh there was uh definitely uh
just because of human nature uh conflicts within his monastic community that in his own lifetime in the
monastery where he was living even and so this happened in the in a
town called Kosambi and um and uh it had to do with a very
minor monastic rule and uh it's so minor that you think is this really worth the
level of conflict that uh arose and um uh they had you know they
had an outhouse and the way that people clean clean theelves because they didn't have toilet paper back then was they
used water and they had these dippers for dipping water and it was very important not to um leave any water in
the dipper when you're finished and u maybe because mosquitoes or I don't know
why and um and so there was someone who was an expert in the monastic rules
there were some monks who specialized in this and um and the this expert was
criticized or was accused of having left some water in his
dipper oh these monks
And um and so there was this and and uh he insisted he hadn't done that other people said insisted he did and so there
was two factions in the monastery the factions were against him and the fact that they were for him and they couldn't
get an agreement and eventually somehow maybe the majority or something voted to
expel him from the monastery but that even created more conflict in the community and uh there
was all this arguing and the Buddha was there in the monastery and he said cool it you know you know you should get
along and let let maybe let go of this but they said they said to him something like um you know just leave us alone
venerable sir we'll take care of this and they don't even listen to the Buddha
and so so they they were continuing to argue and it was noisy in the monastery and so the Buddha he had tried to
intervene they didn't listen to him so He left he just he just went went off to
go someplace else and uh but then the the town's
people got wind that the Buddha wasn't there and that there was this conflict so they started stopped supporting the
monks there and um and support means feeding them because monks are not they
don't cook they don't they can't even keep keep food overnight they're not allowed to store food so every day
they're dependent on what's offered to them and as they go walk for arms so
people stopped feeding them so that got their attention eventually they started to starve and so um uh they went to the
Buddha to apa to apologize and say you know we you know please forgive us and please come
back and and um so he came back and um and um and so but they were
still kind of you know a little bit challenged by it all but uh so he said
um so this is the description of the how it went now on
that caa occasion the monks at Kosambi had taken to quarreling and
brawling and were deep in disputes stabbing each other with verbal daggers
this is not this is like serious um they could neither convince
each other nor be convinced by others they could neither persuade each other nor be persuaded by others so they're at
a standstill um so
uh someone went to the Buddha and sat down explained what happened um and uh I
think and what it says here the Buddha called them to come visit to him so he had gone someplace and so the monks all
went to him and he asked them um monks is it true that you have taken
to quarreling and brawling and are deep in dispute stabbing each other verbal daggers and so they're supposed to be
honest for your monks so so they said "Yes venerable
sir." Um and then the Buddha said "Munks what do you think when you are quarreling and
brawling and in deep and deep in disputes stabbing each other with verbal dagger daggers do you on that occasion
maintain acts of loving kindness by body speech and mind in public and in private
towards your companions in the holy life that's a beautiful expression asking
them and we can ask ourselves that you know there's people quarrel in
families sometimes there's things fall apart people quarrel in communities they
quarrel in work they quarrel quarrel in politics they quarrel a whole nation is
at a standstill with with each other and um with verbal daggers for each other
it's not uncommon that we get this standstills around this tension and problems so what do you
think when you're in opposition with other people for whatever
reason um are you stabbing each other with verbal daggers or do you on that occasion
maintain acts of loving kindness by body speech and mind in public and in private
towards your fellow citizens how do you how do you view people
and um and it's a call to always always have goodwill whether this word meta should
be translated as loving kindness or not is a open question for some people loving kindness is a little bit too high
a bar and a little bit too idealistic and maybe uh maybe maybe it is unrealistic
but goodwill maybe is more realistic that you can always have goodwill uh even for your enemies you can wish them
well because then they'll treat you better maybe and um so
uh so to um uh so this is a really high
kind of teaching of Buddha very important teaching the Buddha to always maintain loving kindness um and and uh
one reason is that it antidote to having ill will is the antidote for ill will and
ill will harms the person who has it and uh why would you want harm
yourself and that's one of the remarkable things that happens through this practice is as we settle on
ourselves more and more deeply in the present moment become more embodied more connected to ourselves in a deep deep
way we we're become acutely sensitive to the ways that we harm ourselves by what
we do with our mind our speech and our body acutely aware of the tension that
builds up the way we close down the way that we do even some kind of sometimes I felt
like violence to ourselves by having hate by having greed by having all these
ways in all you know in all directions including towards ourselves towards others and we we feel how we're harming
ourselves and why would you harm yourself and that's the big question in Buddhism when you really have settled
deeply deeply leap on yourself really connected and sensitive to what's happening which is a hard thing to come
to because we're so distracted we're so busy you know chasing after doing things
and thinking about important things and that we don't we're often somewhat alienated from
ourselves and this this uh becoming deeply connected then provides us this
important information about how we self harm and it's remarkably
uh powerful to see this and it's it goes against kind of the grain of how we
normally think when we spend a lot of time blaming other people or blaming the
world or the weather or something but as we get more and more deeply connected we can feel the movements of
uh illwill the movements of greed and ambition the movements of even sometimes
anxiety and doubts how it kind of begins to twist something inside or close
something inside uh that uh irritate something inside kind of harm something inside and so to
discover um that good will is not something we have to do but
is what is left when ill will has gone away that's like a treasure to discover
so for the Buddha he put a lot of emphasis on the importance of goodwill and loving kindness and so he starts
with this addressing the monks who are quarreling when you're quarreling do you have goodwill
and being committed to being honest they said "No venerable
sir." Um and then he goes on and um says "Well
when you're quarreling and brawling in this way what can you possibly know what can
you see that you take to quarreling and brawling
what is it that you what is it you're which you deeply have insight or see clearly or what's triggering what what
do you value what's so important for you that you want to quarrel and brawl what's happening when you hate someone
or challenged by them or really so it's a it's a it's a request to really look
deeply what are you going on in you at that time
um um and uh if you keep doing this living this way
uh it will lead to your harm and suffering for a long time
and I'm struck by you know how many huge conflicts we've had you know in our in
our world over the last hundred and what 200 years or something that we're still
living in the legacy of it the harm that was done by these major wars continues to this day
um you know I was uh my parents-in-law uh were in the concentration camps in
Germany so I knew them until they died and knew the impact of that up until I
think my my father-in-law died about I think about 11 years ago and so
up until that time right up to the day he died I know that the effects of being in those camps was still with him and
the people who went through uh uh all kinds of things their Armenian genocide
in 1910s and 20s they're still living with it uh we're still in this country
still living with the the challenges of the civil war that uh goes on and
someone would argue some people would argue that the violence that happened for the Americans American Revolution is
still with us in some deep way that uh it wasn't all good the American
Revolution and independence that somehow that act of violence that was horrible
um there could have been another way like
Canada maybe got independent a little different kind of way and um so this idea of of
um of being connected to ourselves and uh this value of loving kindness instead
of violence instead of hate uh is one the Buddha was championing so
um so then so then the Buddha had this is his core teaching in this
text then the Buddha addressed amongst us there are these six memorable
qualities that create love and respect and conduce to helpfulness to nondispute
to concord and to unity what are the six
uh so uh these memorable qualities sometimes they're called um uh six
principles of cordiality which seems a little bit dry uh one translator
translates in the six principles of of uh goodheartedness someone else tried to
translate it as six principles of amiability when's the last time you'd said
amiable but good-heartedness but I love this idea that they create love and respect conduc to helpfulness
to non-dispute to concord and to unity this is one of the primary principles of
uh Buddhism is don't create divisiveness look to see how you can create concord
and unity so there can be conflict there can
be differences of opinion there can be but how do we live in conflict how do we live in challenges with loving kindness
with looking for how can we come together rather than be torn apart and
we're always going to have difference of opinions does that have to tear us apart and for the Buddha that no so
there's six principles um so he said and three of
them have to do with this goodwill so it's kind of nice and the idea is to do them in in public and in private and um
I think private means so no one knows about it isn't that nice you don't have to get any
credit and then maybe it's even better you know to do do acts of kindness of
love of care um uh without anybody necessarily knowing that you're doing it
um maintain bodily acts of loving kindness both in public and in private
towards one comp one's companions in the holy life so he's talking to monastics in their monastic
environment this is a memorable quality that creates love respect conduces to
helpfulness to non-dispute to concord and to unity that's the first principle the
second is maintain verbal acts so first do things with your body make a
gift cook a meal and offer it to a friend uh the inside world aid that
we've started up again i think it's this Thursday is starting up is Thursday right uh is um starting up um making uh
bag launches for homeless and they're going to do it here in uh they're going to make them here in Redwood City um uh
we we we discovered that there's a small group of people connected to the Catholics workers here in um in uh
Redwood City they have a little house and they're going to let us use their their space to make these bag lunches
and um and I love that fact catholic worker and Dorothy Day were very important social workers or caregivers
of this country and um and so they're still live and going here at Rubid City and we're getting to use their space so
there's information on the inside world aid website about that if you want to go and help make
sandwiches so that so uh you know bodily acts of loving kindness then the second
principle is maintain verbal acts of loving kindness both in public and in private
third one is maintain mental acts of loving kindness both in public and in
private so I don't know what a mental act in public would be versus private um
maybe just what maybe it means like when you when you're out and about you should uh you know in in the society just have
have good thoughts of goodwill and the private maybe means when you're meditating when you're alone think well
about people then too so the fourth one is um um
uh you use things in common oh again a monastic uses things in common with
their virtuous companions in the holy life without making reservations one
shares with them any gain of any kind that accords with the dharma and has been obtained in a way that accords with
the dharma including even the contents of their bowl so that means the food
they get so the idea is so that the fourth way to conducive for for conducive for loving kindness and
imiability and good good-heartedness is to share without reservations what you have uh even the contents of your bowl
of food even your food that's quite something because they only get one meal you know one meal a day or you know and
um and you're just lucky if you get enough food back then and even if you don't have enough food share with those
who have even less always be sharing that's a the principle always share so
we have a little extra in this country so supporting Burma would be nice
um and then um um the fifth
principle a monastic dwells both in public and in private possessing in
common with her companions in the holy life those virtues that are unbroken
unblatched unmutled liberating commended by the
wise and conducive to concentration ation so here there's a call to be
ethical and live in such an ethical way live by the precepts live with the virtues in a way that uh is uh
un unblenmished that somehow is just kind of a purehearted
uh connection to being ethical and this was a huge surprise for me when I
started doing this insight practice the first time this was in Thailand and my I
kind of stumbled into it i didn't quite know what I was getting involved in and um and so kind of accidentally my first
introduction to this practice that we do here was on a 10-week retreat so and uh so that was kind of
that got so that was long enough to get my attention and one of the things that
happened surprising things happened in that those course of those 10 weeks was I got so settled and so connected to
myself so at peace with myself so there was so little inner conflict present
anymore that uh there was I I started to feel something inside which by according
to my earlier life based on principle I wouldn't have appreciated they didn't
trust uh it was kind of like they didn't trust this kind of words the language
concepts and that was the concept of purity and I started feeling this
amazing sense of purity within and uh and I I could feel that if
I had certain thoughts that were not so pure uh how it was a kind of violence or kind
of darkened or colored or you know shut down this place of purity that felt so
healthy and good it felt like home in a way and so this idea of of uh of um uh
virtue which is unblatched unbroken that in ourselves
it's quite a remarkable experience to have as a reference point for how to live a
life and that's some here it's called liberating and I wasn't liberated spiritually in
the deep Buddhist sense that during that 10-week retreat but I certainly felt free from a lot of the kind of inner
conflict the the way that greed and hatred kind of uh were a kind of
u loss of freedom because they kind of become compulsions that are difficult to
put down they kind of drive us and so there's a kind of freedom from living with a deep sense of virtue
but the most uh uh uh surprising thing around this description it ends with the
virtue that is conducive for concentration and that's meditation in
order to be able to sit in deep states of meditation to have this deep connection to oneself this deep feeling
concentration is also a feeling of wholeness we're completely comp uh feeling whole and connected in some deep
inner way um uh virtue is essential you
have to you can't you can't be unethical and expect to become whole in the way
that concentration makes you whole and uh a feeling of wholesomeness or wholeness
so the idea that virtue that's conducive to concentration and I love this term
because there there's a safety mechanism built into this that um any attempt to
be to live an ethical life that makes you more agitated that somehow takes away your
capacity to get deeply settled is probably not going to be ethical and not
a few people think they're living an ethical life but underneath it there is hostility there's hatred there's there's
fear there's anxiety there's shame there's embarrassment there's all these complicated things that we have
guilt that uh that doesn't help concentration doesn't help for this deep
sense of peace that concentration can provide and so um uh so the connect to
connect ethics with concentration I think is a wonderful safeguard so that our ethics is really the right
kind so uh and then we come to the sixth one um a monastic dwells both in public
and in private possessing in common with her companions in the holy life that
view that perspective that is noble and liberating and leads one who practices
in in accordance with it to the complete destruction of suffering this too is a
memorable quality that creates love and respect conduces to helpfulness to non-dispute to concord and to unity so
this is kind of what Buddhism is kind of the teaching of the Buddha is all directed towards it's directed to
towards something in you that is
conducive to love and respect to being helpful becoming
helpful person to non-dispute to concord and to unity is that so
bad that this is kind of like the the kind of over and over again this is what the Buddha is pointing towards as
possibility I think is really useful not to forget this that this is the kind of orientation or this is the litmus test
for practice and for Buddhist teachings how does it support our ability to do these things over and over again how not
to succumb to ill will how to live with goodwill how to live with a a kind of
virtue or kind of ethics that is conducive to your own well-being that
conducive to concentration and virtue is really good for the world around us if you live
ethically uh the only people who might uh be suffer a lot are the newspapers
the news channels because most of the news is about people being
unethical and um the um and then
sharing you know the sharing with the with others this the fourth quality and
now there's something about a view a perspective that's liberating and uh that frees us that
that also creates goodwill or creates helpfulness and unity that we create a
view that frees us from greed and hatred frees us from
the kind of clinging and resistance the kind of obsessiveness and compulsivity which gets in the way
of goodwill gets in the way of caring for our community around us it gets in
the way of caring for the people who we disagree with is that
possible and that's that's the idea so I don't think that this teaching here is
about monks not disagreeing over a monestic rule i think this is uh it's
you know rules are difficult to interpret and understand but it's even if you have a
disagreement never give up your loving kindness and hopefully it's a you know
religious people speak in hyperbole sometimes so you have maybe hopefully what I'm about to quote we can
understand that just said in an exaggerated way so that to really stress
how important it is the Buddha said "Even if
bandits are sawing off your limbs maintain goodwill."
And uh when I was in uh and there was a uh a teacher uh
Indian teacher named Manindra Gi when um some of the westerners went to practice
with him in the 1960s um I think there was a a woman who was
somehow little bit accosted on the publicly in the street and I think she fought off or got cut got cut got cut
got cut got cut got cut got cut got cut got cut got cut got cut got away from the person but she went to the to the man and said you know what should I do
if I get accosted in the in the on the streets and he said with all the loving
kindness you can muster hit the person overhead with your umbrella
and um but but that goes that goes along with um one of the rules the monastics
are supposed to live by one of the rules is that they're not allowed to hit
anyone to strike anyone physically fight with them but there is one
exception they're allowed to hit out i think the expression is strike out
against someone for for for two caveats two
requirements they have to do it with loving kindness in their hearts they have to have a do with goodwill they
cannot have ill will for someone when they do it the second uh they do it only for the
purposes of escaping them so you know you don't have to stand
there and just not do anything if someone's hitting you attacking you're allowed to do do what it takes to escape
uh but there has to be goodwill and that's a high bar right i mean how many people can do that when they're caught
in their fear or something but it is possible i've known people uh because the people
I know because that's my circles I know mostly is uh I know uh practitioners who
deep practitioners who have in fact been uh something has happened someone like
was robbing them at gunpoint or something and they somehow they knew how
to not succumb to fear not to succumb to ill will and they kind of something they
were surprised themselves by what came out of them that's uh that uh settled
the situation made the whole thing go away one friend of mine looked at the person and said um your mother would be
ashamed of you and that was enough another person
who um uh was out in the desert and this man
accosted her was with a gun and um didn't want it wasn't going to be a good
scene and she said um you're you're no Christian give me that
gun and that was enough and then she threw it in the bushes and ran so I'm
not suggesting any of these things you know as a strategy you know to try to do it but somehow they knew what to do in
the moment that uh that settled it and I knew one person one friend of mine who
did not stay calm uh being held up in San Francisco and um
and he was the one that ended up in jail because of his ill will and what he
tried to do so uh so the six principles of goodwill
six principles that lead to love and respect to unity and concord that begins with loving kindness
in body speech and mind publicly and privately
six uh uh that includes uh sharing generosity giving uh even down to your
last food in your own bo own bowl without reservations supporting the
people around us this is one of the deep principles of Buddhism and then virtue and the and
it's not just any old virtue any old ethical rules but the ethics that really
does something to your heart does something to your inner life so that when you sit down to meditate it's easy
for you to get settled to get concentrated and then uh to have a view
to have a perspective that understands that uh it that uh clinging
to anything grasping to anything craving to anything is
harmful and then the and the practice the purpose of the practice is to let go of that clinging to let go of all
craving and clinging and it's those people who have no clinging clinging and
craving who become second nature to live with
goodwill to live with caring for people to be helpful for this
world to be concerned with the welfare and happiness of everyone the unity the
concord that we can live in and it's a high bar it's not easy
when there's so much divisiveness in our society and so much is at stake and uh
so much harm can get done and so there's a lot of tempting
reasons to succumb to hostile anger there's a lot
of reasons to get succumb to fear and anxiety and distress
and the Buddha was teaching something else for us he was and I find it
tremendously inspiring and encouraging he was in uh he was teaching
that in some sense that the world begins by you and if you want to live in a
better world begin with yourself live with live with goodwill publicly and
privately live with sharing not with hoarding
live with virtue live with ethics not with causing
harm any ways through your behavior and understand something
profound about a perspective that frees you from all harm intentional harm
making any greed hatred that causes harm to yourself and to others live with a
view that it is possible to be free it is possible to be have profound peace at
heart to be transformed into someone who lives for the welfare and happiness for
the world not because they should but because it becomes who we are
so thank you that so those people in the past the
ancient world how could they be live in conflict with each other shouldn't they known better time with the Buddha we
certainly know better now don't we one of the things that disturbed me
about um watching things like Star Trek when I was younger it was supposed to happen you
know thousands hundreds of years into the future I I was just str so struck by how
um ethically naive they were i was so surprised that you know
that by that you know in a few hundred years that we hadn't kind of become ethically and psychologically
sophisticated and capable of caring for each other in a deep profound way
so anyway we live in this world where these teachings are so important and
maybe we'll always need them six principles of
goodwill so thank you