okay folks so um we should uh we should practice
together so finding your posture
finding your belly
just live in your belly for a moment
sense of gravity the earthiness of your body
really taking your
seat what did the the budha mean when he
touched the
Earth just let your body find
out right
now e
I'm so used to living in my heart heart and my head
that the attention almost drifts up like a helium
balloon out of my belly out of the [Music]
bones to my head and heart but we just stay grounded in your
belly sit in your bones
know yourself as
Earth breathe yourself down into the
ground may stay open but very stable
oh
e
e e
just sensing um a AFF effect in your
body kind of uh circuits of emotional activation
and just bathing those circuits in uh
awareness
patience
for
for e
it's like we have a certain unannounced vision of how our life is supposed to
unfold and uh affect in the
body it's the way we assess our progress towards that
model of our
life but we're invited
to put down Notions of what our life supposed to be what it
is to put down Notions of what it is to
meditate and to breathe
let me just use everything is a way of becoming
more Al
live
e
e e
just for now
pleasure and
preferences become uh very much beside the
point not forever but for now
and you don't have to perform
awareness for
awareness depends on certain
conditions but none of those conditions are
you
e
e e
budda knowing
dum
e
e e
for
[Music]
e
okay so the uh the the Buddha's path began
with a a recognition that something something about his life was
unsustainable unsustainable and as the story goes before leaving the the
palace he was living in a kind of [Music]
Illusion and then he realized that pleasure couldn't go on forever
and there's a kind of recognition he saw the Human Condition was inherently
unstable ruled by
uncertainty and this recognition generated some
fear as the the illusion of a governable
permanent pleasure crumbled and and he uh sought security
instead in relinquishment and in a way you could
say he sought security by being infinitely vulnerable
to the world and perhaps um the ambient
anxiety of 2025 of this moment is is something
along these lines some some we're intuiting something
similar uh but not about the individual but about our
society that we as a human species are
not on a sustainable path
and uh just as the the Buddha's pleasure was unsustainable so too
maybe conditions the trajectory of of uh
us and it's not that human nature is getting worse not that over the last
whatever 100 years or something we've deteriorated we have actually
gotten better in many ways it's just that greed and hate and
delusion scales more efficiently than
Dharma and technology has functioned not only but in part to scale greed hatred
and delusion
and our our bewilderment grows as we
um flooded with ideas and opinions but ceased to
care about evidence and overconfidence is what um what goes
viral so we're we're a kind of
caricature of of a the dun and Krueger effect the dun and Krueger
culture they write um the skills that engender competence in a particular
domain are often the very same skills necessary to evaluate competence in that
domain those with limited don't knowledge in a domain suffer a dual
burden not only do they reach mistaken conclusions and make regrettable
errors but their incompetence Rob robs them of the ability to realize it I was
angry when I wrote up these notes just full disclosure you
know and uh as I offer the talk I was sort of
recognizing like oh yeah anger always imputes an
agent and um maybe in certain moment and
reflecting on this theme I forgot something uh empty phenomena rolling
on let me continue my
rant Renee um Desta said that um freedom
of speech is not freedom of reach
ignorance now reaches
everywhere and there are
likely massive labor effects of of AI and new
technology disparities of um wealth or heartbreaking and the kind of emerging
economy is likely to exacerbate that Gap not heal it
and the rise of authoritarianism not just in this country um but many places
the the confidence of conmen mistaken for actual
hope and of course La is on my mind
and climate change and the kind of shrinking of livable land or
at least insurable land and all this just
um yeah it just seems like it's not
sustainable I don't feel apocalyptic or something or feel
like something so IM imminent but it just feels like this is not sustainable
and then we sense our near nearly complete powerlessness in
the face of the scaling of greed ha and
delusion sometimes our heart gets frenzied sometimes it
collapses sometimes for me it Sparks a kind of
um dabbling with a certain kind of nihilism just of
like not nihilism in the sense the Buddha used it but just the the sense of just like get me out get me out of some
sorrow and on the one hand it's a very good thing to have confidence that you
can be very happy even amidst very difficult circumstances practice
engenders that confidence happiness independent of
conditions it's a reasonable way of talking about
Freedom shinen yangang would often use a phrase like
that but still I don't even want to flirt with
nihilism you know and so
um sometimes we do say step step out of the realm of Hope and fear that's often an
instruction we say to hope is to hope for the wrong thing TS Elliot I said to
my soul be still and wait without hope for hope would be hope for the wrong
thing wait Without Love For Love would be love for the wrong thing and so yeah
step out of Hope and fear but sometimes times and today was one of those
times I need hope I need
hope but the time scale of My Hope might need to
expand I need to expand Beyond the Horizon of our
lives and maybe
you know maybe our love can't quite dispel misery right
now but uh nevertheless let us steadfastly
plant seeds wisdom and compassion they've been
planted through time we are enjoying the
fruit of that now and so I want
to to be uh part of a group that is
committed to love to nonharming to heedfulness
care even if that fruit is not
born now even in this lifetime we do need the momentum
of goodness to continue
and I want to be part of a uh an endless
stream of wisdom and compassion that predates the
Buddha continues after
us do doing no evil engaging in what's
skillful and purifying one's mind this is the teachings of the Buddha of the
buddas plural from the dhap doing no evil engaging in what's
skillful purifying one's
mind I go back in moments to the fundamentals when things get
staticky maybe that's clear enough maybe just that is enough let us do that even
though it feels insufficient let us do
that this from um uh local San Francisco paper I saw today
um in December uh Rangers from the US Forest servants uh
encountered an unexpected climber a goose attempting to Summit Mount
chesta Forest Rangers Nick Myers and Eric Falconer of the mount chesta Avalanche Center were on routine Patrol
when they came upon their first uh their first attempted Ascent of Mount Shasta
by a goose found at about 10,000 ft uh Meer
said the first step was to catch it I didn't think I'd actually catch the goose but as boys being boys we
tried rescue proved more challenging than expected with the goose initially
trying to escape at first the goose tried to fly away but couldn't its head and eyes were
crusted in ice Wings battered flopped its way down the slope we chased after
without success Eric and I were about to give up but I said I'm going to try one
more time and I ran up from behind and Dove on top of it and caught it honestly
I was surprised I caught it and my next thought was what do I do what do we
do now and that's when we're like well I
guess we try to take it down the mountain I tucked its wings and stuck it
under my arm like a football I expected a big fuss and fight as I started the snowmobile
and began riding down the mountain uh this is when uh I began to
to feel uh real connection of the spirit with the goose as its demeanor
relaxed and tucked its head into my jacket the goose most certainly
understood uh we were helping it as it warmed up in the truck it got a
little feisty but nothing
crazy started to talk angry but
um tender
now and um
um as I wrote up the notes sort of cried and unusual way for
me and uh tears kind
of affirming the necessity of care
stewardship of love spiritual friendship k
offer this for your consideration