welcome uh welcome folks good morning to uh most of you good afternoon to
some um yeah happy to uh be with you the chat's fun
um so um I'm your your sub and uh yeah
happy happy to be with you i know a lot of lot of these names very sweet u
grateful to uh Gil for for having me um
so let us uh yeah let us let us practice together
so finding um finding a
posture balances alertness and uh deep relaxation
because we have so much
fidelity to the last
moment and to all the ideas and models of self and
world can feel like freedom is very far away in this moment
perhaps not so far
we might begin by
just forgetting everything we know about ourselves
ceasing to turn yourself into an
object to be assessed that is the beacon the
orienting point
it's hard to forget ourselves it's hard to simultaneously remember
the emptiness of all points of identification
but we
train this clears out some fresh
space for you to just breathe
to just be a body rewarded
by oxygen expelling what's used up
enjoy it
this sense of self accumulates sort of behind the radar of
awareness like dust on a shelf
sense of pressure to prove something to perform something to be
something we relax
we uh [Music] receive each breath like a gift and
a surprise
feels like in each moment we must take
care of all our future
selves that all those future selves are depending on this self
now it's a lot of pressure
as we come to be less intimidated by Anicha
uncertainty feel less responsible for all the future
iterations of
feel safer to relax into the uh open space of
uh this moment this breath
we can be precise
without tension
sometimes useful to notice the beginning and ending of
the inhalation the beginning and ending of the exhalation
and then the bottom of your
breath it's a sense of
release surrender
then it begins
again so many opportunities to begin
again so many opportunities to soften to the moment
all phenomena are
friendly from the perspective of dharma all phenomena are friendly
even though some hurt
okay good to uh practice with you
um so there are uh a lot of lists in
Buddhism and uh they're really so um so
profound and uh sometimes kind of marvel at the the genius of how the different
factors fit together and um work for our um growing
wisdom and uh compassion
and there are lots of kind of spiritual factors that don't show up on on the
lists and um I kind of made up a list uh
a couple years ago and now kind of uh rethought it a little bit and revised
and Um and so the theme this week is like basically my fake list you know
Matthew from California's fake list not seven factors of awakening or five
johnic factors or something it's just but things that have been meaningful to
me on my path and uh offer for whatever it's
worth so I was
um talking to a yogi after a retreat and um and they said something like you know
I'm I'm suspicious of I I kind of asked like how was the
retreat or something like that you know i was like uh you know was I a little
too playful or something you know cuz I remember trying to be relaxed you know
and um they said like no I'm suspicious of teachers who lack a sense of humor
the lack of humor usually means they haven't reached deep into the mystery is
what they said and sort of stuck with me because for a long time I thought dharma
practice was serious business and dharma teaching that's even
more serious right um but I'll
uh I'll tell you how I got my nickname uh Captain
Buzzkill was awarded to me by my brother and
uh younger brother and I have a lot of joy in my life but not much excitement
uh you not cuz I'm like trying to be all Buddhist and be present and
uh you know trying to like be in the m it's not like that some of it's
temperamental some of it's probably practice a lot of joy when things come but not look so much looking forward and
my younger brother lives on excitement kind of you know um and looking forward
to things and he was telling me something he was excited about and I you
know I was kind of just misattuned and I sort of you know reminded him of like
the first noble truth and wanting is always different than getting and and he
was just like you know who you are you're Captain Buzzkill and still years
later as I've told that story sometimes yogis from sas far and wide just come up
to me and call me captain so
um today on the fake list the first factor uh humor and
playfulness and there's this sense that the the intensity and poignency of life
is somehow incompatible with laughter and play and
humor and it's not and one of the kind of gifts of
dharma practice is how quickly even strong forces can move through us
opening us to a very different moment even a moment of grief followed by peace
or joy and the seriousness the seriousness
is is some of it may be sincere but it's often driven by ego the
ego is by nature serious it's uh the ego doesn't think it's
funny but it is it's very funny
when experience um becomes more light a
little less bounded by the self story spacious there's a lot more room
for lightness for humor and it's always like curious
um like it's amusing to hear when you
know like the senior teachers uh the agon in the Thai forest tradition when
they laugh is very funny to me when they laugh
because they laugh at things that I don't really think are funny you know like a tomato is it be like well but
that didn't work out too well did
it very funny it's almost like
um yeah we have to be able to laugh at ourselves the uh writer George uh
Saunders says "Humor is what happens when we're told the truth quicker and more directly than
we're used to." That's a very useful humor is what happens when
we're told the truth quicker and more directly than we're used to and the dharma is like that sometimes it just
sneaks up on you and there's nothing to do but laugh
humor and um and playfulness they're so um they're kind of a central part of uh
kalana mitaa spiritual friendship often you know and
um and my my kind of dharma friendships you
know you know fellow practitioners teaching colleagues and it's like we
laugh a lot a lot um Freud said um those who share a sense
of humor share a whole lot more and and it you can kind of sense that when when
when two people find the same thing funny it often testifies to something
deep about their mind maybe what's not even conscious
something that is is deeply shared and to meet in that is um is
beautiful uh Nietze said that um maturity is
re-acquiring the spirit that um a child has at
play and what are the characteristics of playing how can dharma practice be
sometimes a little bit more like playing well the characteristics of
playing are there's nonvigilance we cannot play when we're
patrolling when we're patrolling the boundaries or something
like that when we're keeping tabs on every potential
threat we play in the absence of
self-consciousness you cannot play if you're trying to look cool or smart or
whatever trying to look anything play is the absence of a kind
of self-consciousness and so this inclusion of our whole being we're at ease with ourselves and in a kind of
flow and play is intrinsically rewarding we're not getting anywhere in our play
some people it's hard to tolerate that not getting anywhere it's important
psychoanalyst um Winnott says psychotherapy takes place at the overlap
of two areas of playing that of the patient and that of the
therapist psychotherapy has to do with two people playing
together where playing's not possible the work done by the therapist is
directed towards bringing the patient from a state of not being able to play
into a state of being able to
play a state of not being able to play into a state of being able to play
and a lot of that can be said for dharma too for a practice where can we
play where can the self-consciousness de dissolve where can sense of just aimless
exploration just delight uh where can that be and then
where can we not play can we play with our foy balls and
play in the zones of clinging or even play in zones of
shame play i want to play everywhere
and as the the egoic framework becomes less of an
organizing kind of system you know as we we come to feel less and less like we
orbit around the self story we open to more humor and
play and we come to play even with the conventions of self
in other words we become the joke and it feels very good you know sometimes I've
been you know I like like making fun of myself and maybe that's like
subterranean self-hatred but I I don't think so i think it's just there's kind
of um there's some some delight in playing
with the conventions of self you know
it's like part of how I relate to my defilements is through
humor you know and and sometimes you can sense like oh the mind could go more
than one way it could go into shame or pain or
defensiveness or humor and we just play play with the conventions of self play
even in our places of pain or
wounding okay yeah some lightness there
we move from a state of not being able to play to a state of being able to
play and become progressively less defensive less rigid our
holding our fidelity to who we think we should be
some years ago I went to this um it was like a breathing workshop with a couple dharma friends fellow practitioner you
know practitioner and was not a Buddhist practice and I got into a very curious
mind state that I had never been in until then and have never been in since
then it was not in the It was not in the
progress of insight it was not in you know it was not a Janna it was very
strange so it was a 90minute session we're all in the dark people's heads are
all pointed towards the center of the circle and uh maybe an hour in I start
and and I start to hear um the woman next to me
crying and uh in this kind of very poorest state
it's like it was not felt totally effortless to just
attune to that and to join and I start
crying that is not so you know uncommon for me i cry most times I give dharma
talks or uh you know practice much but
um okay I'm crying but then also there's something about it that just I'm
laughing deeply you know it's kind of like this
sense of zooming out to the cosmic wildness of it all and I'm just I'm
crying and I'm laughing hard and beneath all of it it's like
um miles under the surface of the sea and it just abiding perv peace
uh pervading all of it and it was like those with three very
distinct mind states totally
co-occurring crying laughter peace not blotting one another
out so
um humor playfulness on the path
uh offer this for your consideration okay nice to uh nice to be
with you i wish you all a good uh good day and um
uh see you uh see you tomorrow thanks uh thanks all okay