so good morning and welcome and
uh and to begin with the
meditation one of the really useful things to notice to
support dipping into samadei is the way that the discursive
mind the mind that thinks a lot thinks about things has conversations talking
about things in the mind uh living in images and visions of what the mind
can produce The way that that keeps us kind
of separated from the body it keeps it uh keeps us somehow uh in a part of the
brain mind that's activated more energized in a way that is not uh
usually so relaxing or calm or um it can
be um we're living in our thoughts and living in the activated energy that
keeps discursive thinking going rather than settling deeply in And discursive thoughts can uh be
mesmerizing They can be in captivating They can be have a kind of authority
like this is really important to be thinking about And our sense of self of who we
are is often closely maybe uh unconsciously but closely connected or
associated with the mind that's dis having discursive thoughts partly because a lot of the discursive thoughts
have to do about me myself and I and so what we're learning to do in
meditation especially samadei is to uh become become
attuned aligned with something different than that Uh a place that's maybe deep inside
maybe in the torso in the chest or in the belly where there's a feeling of
settling a feeling of being more grounded and connected to ourselves
And one way to kind of move into this more grounded connected sense sense embodied sense rather than a kind of
disembodied version of the preoccupations we
have is um to start feeling
uh whatever degree of well-being there is in the body
And of course there's a lot of feeling of distress feeling of discomfort
emotional challenges There's a lot of ways that we feel the opposite of
well-being that we then prioritize So but not to
ignore it not to deny it not to betray our unhappiness in any kind of way but
to care for it deeply It can be very helpful to not focus on it directly to let it just be
there as part of the atmosphere part of the weather in a sense and uh and for somebody to begin
feeling even the ways that you sense of well-being in the torso in the
body Um and that can be a sense of
calm And even if it's just like you know 2% calm next to 98%
turmoil allow the turmoil to be Don't stir it up even more Attune yourself to the calm Or
there might be a feeling of settleness or a place of settling that's in the torso in the body
that's not in the just mind that has all this discursive thinking Settle with the
settling Calm calm yourself with the calm And there also might be a feeling
of satisfaction or contentment or to or
joy delight or some kind of feeling that's
pleasant kind of pleasure in being embodied in the
body instead of activated in the activated thinking
So to assume a meditation posture and as I like to say
that no matter what the posture sitting standing lying
down to give some care to how the body is
positioned as a beginning of entering into an embodied
connection to
yourself And to support this turning inward into the the pleasure the
goodness the calm in the body to gently close your eyes
And it's even more to begin connecting to your
body coming into your body more Take some fuller
breaths deeper and fuller in a comfortable way
but fuller and deeper enough that you're intentionally connecting and
engaging the rib the diaphragm the breathing in the
torso and feeling as you breathe in the expansion of the
torso And then see as you exhale you can slow the exhale just a
little bit So it's still comfortable to exhale Slow it and extend it
longer Letting there be a feeling of fullness as you breathe in
like a full balloon And then a releasing relaxing as
you exhale as the balloon lets out the
air It gets smaller comes together
Breathing in relaxing as you
exhale and then letting the breathing return to
normal But feel now the more subtle way in which there's expansion
As you breathe
in and a releasing relaxing as you exhale
And as you come to the end of the exhale let there be a small maybe even
infantessimal pause
And in that short pause feel whatever sense of stillness
or calm pleasure there is in your
body Maybe connected to breathing
And as you breathe in and out see if you can drop down into your
body out of the discursive thinking
mind like you're lowering yourself into a very pleasant pool of
water and feel whatever is
pleasant whatever pleasure well-being
calm settleness you can find in your body your torso that's breathing
as you breathe in as if the expansion the breathing
in is breathing through or with or into
The calm and the pleasure however small
As you exhale see if you're exhale exhaling
into that calmer groundedness
settleness Feeling the rhythm of breathing in and
breathing
out Letting your
awareness stay connected to breathing riding in the on the breathing
So there's a sense that awareness is being
massaged or awareness is doing the massage
Breathing in and breathing
out As you exhale letting go of your
thoughts thinking
So there's more room in your awareness to feel the pleasure the
calm that might be here
And if you find yourself having discursive thoughts
conversations See if you can
feel how unsatisfying it is for the
body to have this form of thinking How there's more energized
activated kind of a pulling away from the
body And how more satisfying it is for the
body to be settled for awareness to be
settled in the body breathing
Taking a few moments to feel whatever it is that might be
pleasant comfortable in your body
Whatever might be more settled maybe deeper than any ways in
which you feel uncomfortable Deeper
within than any place that you could be having discursive
thoughts Finding the place where
breathing the influence of breathing the atmosphere of
breathing is pleasant enjoyable
Maybe as there's a sweetness or a glow in your
body which offers the atmosphere in which breathing the
breathing body expands and contracts
For a very short time maybe only 20 30
seconds entrust yourself to that which is calm or
settled in your body No matter how
small give yourself over to it Breathe with it
And also spend a few seconds letting your thinking mind
become quiet The kind of quiet you might do if you were going to listen to a sound
faint sound far in the distance Let your thinking mind become
quiet to listen to
feel the most subtle feelings of
contentment tranquility
And then as we come to the end of this meditation
imagine that your tranquility your settleness your
calm can radiate from you out into the world
that to some degree it radiates beyond the edges of your body into the room where you're
at the place you're in
Almost as if the whatever empty space is around
you receives your calm your
well-being And whatever feeling of settleness or calm you
have it can spread outward beyond
the building you're in
Beyond the neighborhood you're in just beyond going outwards and
outwards and that you can and on that can
ride your well-wishing for this world
May your care and love and well-wishing for the world be
carried on the wide glow of good will and
kindness May all beings be
happy May all beings be safe
May all beings be peaceful May all beings be free
And may how we are settled on ourselves tranquil in
ourselves be the way that our good
will can be with us as we encounter
others May all beings be happy
[Music]
Thank you
[Music] So hello
and welcome to this con continuation of our samadei
series and we've had a break for a week And so I hope that the meditation today
was a little bit you know kind of getting us getting you a little bit more back into the the flow of what we've
been doing these last months And uh for the topic of this week
the focus will be on the second Janna When I was here the last week I was here we uh discussed I discussed the first
Janna and um and the second Janna is uh
kind of a deeper form of well-being a deeper form of pleasure and joy and
happiness And uh one of the characteristics of it
um um is that uh
uh it is a sense of well-being joy and happiness pity and suka that's born of
concentration born of samadei and um born of the state of
meditation that comes in the first Janna the joy and the happiness that's there is born of from
seclusion from being separated from uh the preoccupations the concerns of
our everyday life being separated even more importantly Being separated from unh wholesome
thinking to be caught up in the hindrances in greed or ill will to be
caught up in in uh kind of a rigid dull mind to be caught in
restlessness and regrets to be caught in doubt is unh wholesome And so there's
this delight and joy and happiness when we're no longer caught in the unh wholesome no longer caught up in the
mind It's uh the difficulties of the mind and um and uh so part of like and
and they and what's fueling the first John sense is uh vaka and vichara two of
the johnic factors of this massage of applied attention and sustained
attention So there is some intentionality there is some giving ourselves to over to the meditation in
the first Janna and this joy finally I'm here Oh it's so good to be
present and I've been so distracted so caught up in my mind and my thoughts and preoccupations Ah this is good and then
but in order to stay there there is a kind of gentle uh massage of applying
and staying applying and staying massaging in this um in the in the
second Janna the need to kind of keep applying and sustaining attention is no
longer there Um and certainly the applying coming back and connecting again connecting again is no longer
needed and also there's a little movement of the mind to stay to ride be
here that is little bit intentionality involved also is not needed because now
we're settled we're kind of rooted here we've arrived ah and the mind is not
going to wander off in the second John in the first is that first Janna There can still be some thinking mostly
thinking about the meditation and um the thinking is all wholesome There's nothing unh wholesome about it It all
helps us helps us to get connected and be in the practice In the second Jonah uh there's
no real need for thinking anymore and the mind now has a lot of space a lot of quiet
Some thoughts might arise but there it's hardly anything to pull us away or we
don't get caught in them or involved in them and there can be mostly feeling of a lot of empty space beautiful space
clarity in the mind and um so I want to read to you the the the
the classic description of this second
gen with the stilling of applied and sustained attention
A practitioner enters and abide It's in the second Janna consisting of joy and happiness
born of concentration born of samadei calm with calm inner clarity and
unity of mind Free of applied and sustained
attention free free of thinking and examination free of this kind of so
there now there's almost no thinking and so it's characterized by an inner clarity
Sometimes the word that's translated as clarity is translated as assurance sometimes as um
confidence and um uh but one of the meanings of it can be clarity the
brightness and uh for me this represents the quiet of the mind of uh thinking has
just about stopped and uh and so because there's uh so little thinking that um
certainly no discursive thoughts anymore or no conversations within our inner mind the uh it's feeling like the oh
that now awareness the mind has a lot of space lot of clarity like the fog has lifted the smog
has gone away and we can see across the vast terrain see the mountains in the
distance because of the clarity and um so um the um
um and uh and so this is what I said earlier that one of the characteristics
of the second genre there's a real switch now that now we're really here
we're settled and um and it feels like we're really arrived we're not easily
slipping off we don't need the with the first genre it's very hard to you really
feel established too but there is a kind of intentionality of staying there stay
here be here stay here and c and Right along ride along Be here And with the
first Janna uh this is where some people get in trouble because there's a little
bit of intentionality involved This applied and sustained attention that
um that uh if there's uh there can still be some striving some pushing some
trying kind of tightening down and uh and so people sometimes are pushing it a
little bit And so the joy and the happiness that can arise sometimes gets pumped up or gets uh pumped up and gets
to be too much or gets pumped pumped into some particular bottleneck in the
body and that some energy can build up there too much There's a lot to do with
striving and striving itself is a tightening Something gets tightened when we strive And so the energy of uh the
joy and the happiness gets somehow uh gets compressed or gets blocked or gets
somehow uh uh gets interfered with In the second Janna uh uh the the
joy and the happiness can get strong um and more likely it gets even stronger in
the second and the first But now uh it's less much less likely to uh go arai lima
much less likely to be too intense or too tight or too strainful or get
bottlenecked or get kind of blocked or something Uh because now there's uh the
intentionality of staying there We're not pumping it up anymore We're not um uh you know um blowing on the flame to
let it become stronger We're just allowing things to be there And in fact uh I'll talk more about this tomorrow
The metaphor or the simile for the second Janna has to do with a uh floating in a
very peaceful quiet uh uh clear lake Um
that is a very comfortable and very clear The water is completely is is uh
is somewhat still but uh there is this gentle movement of an underground spring that
refreshes us So the feeling here is there's still some in the in the when
it's too intense in the first Janna um there's a lot of movement almost of the joy and the pity in the second uh
there's still this movement but it feels refreshing It feels delightful and it
has no obstacles to it And this idea that this underwater spring uh in the
lake just has no obstacles as the refreshing water spreads through the
body So I'll talk more about this tomorrow uh but um the
um the one of the ways I want to emphasize here that one of the lessons of this second Janna is uh to be able to
start see clearly the difference between being really you know dipped into the pool of
water dipped into the samadei versus coming out of it uh into the thinking
mind and how discursive thought um uh conversational thinking Uh it puts us uh
as as sometimes as fascinating and pleasurable that some of those can be
There is a kind of uh disconnect with ourselves in that process Disconnect with the wholeness of who we are the
fullness of us that's embodied and present here And that part of the
movement towards this deeper settling of samadei is to learn how to relax the
thinking mind and trust this deeper place of well-being of subtleness of
calmness in the body with the breathing and um and uh and so that the
thinking mind is not reinforcing
um some of the unh wholesome tendencies of mind The thinking mind is not repeating itself over and over again the
same stories and ideas that keep us disconnected from the possibility of a
deep kind of uh inner settleness Deep kind of place of being at being calm
deep place of just happy to be alive happy to be present for this moment as
it is independent of
um you know the concerns about the world around us It's not a turning away from the
world uh in a resisting way or escaping
way It's a way of starting to cleanse ourselves deeply so that we can come
back into the world in a much better space much better
way So we'll go through this different aspects of the second Janna this this uh
this week And I hope I'm not expecting you to be dipping into the second Janna
Uh some of you might be familiar with it already but um uh some of the individual
characteristics of the second Janna can be present in even uh lighter states of
meditation and uh becoming familiar with them can give you a new orientation for
ordinary meditation because you can start feeling these qualities characteristics are present in subtle
way in a way that maybe you ignored before They never knew to pay attention to it And the more you start feeling
these wholesome beneficial qualities within the more engaging it is to be to
meditate and dip into this uh this inner world of
meditation So thank you very much and um look forward to continuing tomorrow