thank you hi everyone and yeah Happy New
Year I feel like I always celebrate two new year I grew up in San Francisco so we always celebrated Lunar
New Year too
um and happy Black History Month yeah good
answer yeah so really good to be with you if um you
were here with me last time you might remember that I'd like to start off not
with the dhama talk but with questions about your formal meditation
practice you know not all of us meet with teachers or get to go on Retreat
and ask questions about practice so how's it going on the cushion these
days what did you notice maybe this morning or at
home are there any places that are sticky or confusing or you don't know
how to work with something if you've been practicing for a while and something new is
happening Happy to answer any questions like that from a few brave souls
okay hi hi uh my name is Angela I did
not I don't I'm not even sure what Dharma means I trained with uh transcendental
meditation for a few years now back in Boston and my question is how important
or is there an importance in Transcendental Meditation we sit in a chair um and I have tried to sit on a
pad but I just my body and I'm not sure if that's part of the practice so my question is what are your feelings about
that or what comes to you when I ask those questions yeah it thank you you
know it's a really good question and this is for just a reminder for folks um
one the Buddha offered four postures sitting standing walking and lying down so all of those are completely
legit postures and uh sitting on a cushion on the
floor is not um better than sitting on a chair so
and it's so good to to remind ourselves of this because sometimes our bodies cannot sit on a cushion and it's painful
for folks who at some points in their lives have to transition to a chair cuz
then sometimes we have to learn how to meditate in that posture right so thank
you for the question I'm glad you're taking care of your body
yeah
yeah good morning my name is Melody um I have fairly long practice maybe 15 years
or so but just recently my mind has been very very
busy like just chattering chattering chattering something it's about something
good but um because I think it's about a creative process that's going on and so
it keeps going back to that back to that and so the way I'm I'm working with it is I sort of
gently step alongside it for like a second or two or three and then I gently
come back to here and now and that's I'm doing it all the
time and um more than usual so in some ways it's really H H uh helping my
awareness practice but I just wanted to know if you have any thoughts about that yeah is there any frustration or wanting
it not to be happening yeah there was there was some of that
but but uh but I I I resolved that
yesterday by doing some dhama reading and so forth and so I'm it's more I'm
befriending it at this point great so it sounds like it's it's not a problem it's just what's happening right and we can
notice oh when causes and conditions change in our lives content changes doesn't
it and so also maybe
noticing like the content happens in the mind the creativity um so a couple ways of
working with it is what you're doing kind of like walking beside it and then at some point maybe putting it down
maybe actively um but also we can check out like oh what does it feel like to be
maybe excited in the body or enlightened and then rest with that instead of just
coming back to maybe your anchor like rest with the uplift of it yes that's
what I'm doing the energy the effort that you know something wants to be born
of this and so be open for that right be open for that and then and then you know
also watch like oh it's a little bit of a hook like I'm gonna you know figure out the
next step on my creative process you know it's like of course and that's exciting and and we can it is valuable
to set along around set aside time for dedicated practice so sometimes when I
have a lot going on I just remind myself okay right now we're just meditating we
can think about that in 20 minutes all right yeah thank you for your question
and maybe we have time for one more about your practice anything up
questions Okay so
I just want to say out loud what a gift you have in this
community just that there's I don't know something like 50 folks here or more
today a lot of other communities haven't bounced back like this since the
pandemic there's like 15 20 so it's really wonderful to be in a
full room really
wonderful yeah oh yeah one online question yeah yeah
sure the question is from Eve um they ask how important are retreats
to the practice I'm not at a place in my life where Retreats are an option and my
practice is mostly daily meditation yeah thanks Eve it's a good
question so Retreats have their time in place you know and
and um I'm a retreat teacher
so I see value in retreats and there's lots of value in daily
meditation practice right daily dhama practice daily like I I do emphasize and
and really focus a lot on us expanding our definition of
practice because so often in this lineage there is this
preferencing much like the cushion right the preferencing our idea that it's all
about Retreat practice and and meditation practice but but the
Buddha the Buddha laid out many many things for us
to cultivate and and so keep doing what you're doing
yeah yeah keep doing what you're doing and you know if the time comes in this lifetime to go on Retreat then great and
if the time doesn't come to go on retreat in this lifetime not a problem yeah people have very very very
deep daily life dhama practices
yeah so thanks for that question
and it's a good inquiry for today for all of
us how maybe in these times to integrate these
practices and to remember um the value of in our
daytoday bringing in these teachings of the
Buddha and so maybe I'll start with Howard Thurman
who in here knows who Howard Thurman is raise your hand just a few
folks um it's Howard
Thurman yeah he uh was like a Christian
Mystic um [Music]
he was a teacher of Martin Luther King when Martin Luther King went to grad
school he was was one of the first people who
influenced Martin Luther King around practices of nonviolence and he went I can't remember
what decade um but he spent maybe five or six months in India both lecturing
and um learning and meeting with people like
Gandhi and I think it's so helpful I marked a couple pages
um sometimes when things are changing very rapidly like they have over the
last week or so um we have a very short
memory but U maybe Howard Thurman wrote this 50s or
60s he says remain at peace accustom yourself to remain at
peace in the depth of of your heart in spite of your restless
imagination and so I've talked to a lot of students this week and some of the imagination is going to like some of
it's not imagination it's actually happening and there's an overlay of extra worry
yeah and so Howard says peace anywhere seems to be wishful thinking during days
of turmoils within and violences without Peace of Mind peace of heart peace of
Home peace of country peace of world peace of Cosmos it does not matter which
the same sense of pinpoint unreality
pervades there seems to be a vast stiring of energy malignant and unstructured that catapults to the
surface all kinds of disharmonies conflicts and
disorders and he goes in to name all these places including the United States
always there is present a turbulent quality the out of hand aspect of the
common life accustom yourself to remain at peace in the depth of your heart in
spite of your restless imagination so it's a
reminder right that this is this is this human
life these vistit toes and I think it's so helpful like
to remember how can we find our Center in the midst of it
all again and again and again and again right and this is what our practice trains us to do doesn't it like notice
the mind getting caught up and come back notice what's happening in real
time in our hearts and Minds right
noticing if were caught in grief and
despair and then knowing how to meet with that with a lot of kindness right so for some
folks that's the practice right now it's some grieving
practice for some folks it's practice of being with anger or
rage and someone yesterday asked me you I kind of give this big
question around you know I'm feeling so much anger so much rage
and um I know that I'm supposed to have compassion but how can I have compassion
you know just really upset um and then I gave like a classic
teacher answer um but we misunderstood each
other and then and then they were upset with me which is
okay I'm like oh we missed something you know and then kind of moved on but
really the Miss was that I was saying to start where you
are start with incapacity and and grow that capacity to
meet the harder things and and this person thought I was saying saying I no be compassion for
with all the folks who are causing harm like maybe you're not there yet right
can we know we're not there yet and then be compassionate for what that feels
like for ourselves for our anger cuz that's suffering isn't it like for most
of us I mean you know there is
um rage that sometimes feels good and also it's painful isn't it it's
or what's underneath it is painful it's a response to something
right so I'm just going to give lots of tips today about how to be with things
right now and one of them some are from the DAP it's not Gil's version
I was going to bring his but I couldn't find it so this is there are other translations out
there so this is one translation so this is in the the uh
chapter 8 the thousands a single word of Truth which
calms the mind is better to hear than a thousand irrelevant
words so maybe there's one word that can bring you back that can remind
you uh about what how Thurman was talking about peace like remaining at
peace what's that word for you maybe it is the word
peace a single verse of Truth which calms the mind is better to hear than a thousand IR irrelevant
verses so I think this is pointing to you know maybe there's a chapter in a
book dama book like that's helpful for for you to remember a reference to come
back to again and again and again I bet some of you here have quotes
on your walls or reminders on mirrors you know maybe we need to expand
those you know put them in our wallets just post them everywhere
yeah it was so nice walking up I walked I parked down here and um you know on the on the side it says Insight oh yeah
insight and then that reminds me like oh these teachings like what builds to
Insight you know if we think about the 8old
path there's this bucket of um CA like our ethics like and
then there's this bucket of concentration and this bucket of wisdom arises just
like [Laughter] that I'm going to read a couple
more reciting a single verse of Truth which calms the mind is better than
reciting a hundred meaningless meaningless verses so maybe that means yeah we say
them out loud or chanting maybe some of you have a chanting practice that's supportive to
you they're just all
reminders and this is these are more more towards how to live our lives a
single day lived with conscious intention and virtue is of Greater value
than a hundred years live devoid of discipline and right
restraint a single day live with conscious intention and virtue is of greater value than a hundred years live
devoid of discipline and right
restraint and then it repeats [Music]
um and it says devoid of discipline and wisdom
so isn't a single day like how we
[Music] spend how we
spend our [Music] mornings can start to really pay
attention how we spend our afternoons our evenings and are we bringing ourselves
back we get lost get
confused like what we're here for what the possibilities are
more
reminders you know I love that the Buddha gives us so many ways to integrate these practices into our daily
lives and maybe we can just for a
moment make an intention so I'm going to give many different
ideas and maybe one Sparks you so I'm just going to say some
words because I I I think that what can happen when things are are chaotic in
our world is that we can get
overwhelmed and have a lot of doubt and then not know what to
do like or or not think that we have any power to do anything and is that
true it is not
true and we all have um
influence you know in our own
ways and so maybe because we have these
practices um we're the ones in our families or in our friends circle that
can remind people of other possibilities when they're lost and
caught in despair
worry right or we can be the
steady or steadying presence
right just by listening to them like I hear your worried sometimes sometimes
people just need to say I'm so worried they just need someone to
listen or maybe you're the one who says let's go on a walk
together or I know this really cool Meditation
Center all right so here are the here some
words generosity are there ways that in your daily life you can
practice generosity and here's the
thing when I say are there ways you can practice this what people's minds go to
is external did anyone go to internal okay all all right we have one
Advanced practitioner right so everything is both
externally and internally and both and we can't REM we can't forget to remember
ourselves right so what does that
mean wise speech
the Sila piece how can we practice doing no
harm in thought word or deed how can we practice doing no harm
in thought word or deed internally externally and both you
know and so internally that might be oh being a little softer like noticing the
harsh critic you know it's Tough Enough out there
y'all no one else is going to no one else can talk nicely to you like
internally like you're doing that so
yeah renunciation there's something to be let go of right
now for some folks it's news light right now
right wisdom is there a way to
cultivate
wisdom and one of the ways I think about wisdom or insight it if we call it
Insight is are there ways right now to
cultivate our intuitive knowing and really deeply listening to
ourselves which is not so easy sometimes because sometimes we don't like what we hear like
oh I said so the other day I um was talking to one of my best friends I
think just yesterday just getting caught up we hadn't talked in a
while and then I started complaining about one of my
siblings who I complain about a lot they probably complained about me a
lot too and I could tell my best friend was
so irritated with me because I complained about the sibling a lot I was like
oh there's something in me that knew like oh I need to stop complaining about this
sibling and so we can notice like oh what are we complaining about that hasn't actually helping
anything but I wouldn't have you know like I mean this is why
friends help because they can reflect us back to ourselves but like oh this is
some intuitive wisdom like oh the felt sense of what it feels like to
complain without
action energy could can notice like how are we spending our time and
energy are we spending it complaining are we spending
it like avoiding that which maybe should be met with some
care which is the definition of suffering
right other options are patience and we practice patience like
you don't have to choose all of them I'm just naming a whole bunch and if one really resonates with you maybe that's your thing for right
now and we have to have so much patience in this life and in these practices don't
we because uh
it took a while to get ourselves into this
predicament and we're not going to get ourselves out of it overnight
either so both we have to have patience like the upside is then we're practicing
patience so we're cultivating
patience truthfulness oh this is is a hard one truthfulness maybe it's not so hard for
you but maybe it's a little harder if it means um
putting yourself in a risky situation I'm I'm a classic people
pleaser there's folks that can relate I want people to like
me um I'm getting better it's like it's okay if you don't like me
um but but this truthfulness sometimes means that people won't like
you if you're being honest and if you're saying it out loud
or sharing it if you're standing in your truth if you're standing in your power and that's
okay it's not so easy all the
time but it also means truthfulness with ourselves
like really being honest with ourselves also not so easy not so
easy determination to me this is like this willingness to show
up show up for our hearts show up for our mind show up for our community show up for each
other and then these ones that we know the Brahma bahara
loving kindness more
friendliness Compassion or our kindness meets
suffering mudita let's not leave this one out
happiness for other people's happiness in all the places where Joy
can be had and it's not all suffering is it
you know newer folks to practice I know not anybody in here sometimes think the teaching is life is
suffering is that the teaching no there is suffering but life
is not just suffering although sometimes it can feel like it
is so remembering those places that uplift that bring joy you know yesterday
I called friend who has it was um they have a four-year-old they just turned four like sometimes I just need to see
this this four-year-old being's light so I facetimed and you know they I
don't know they they just take me out of any worry I'm like all right this
four-year-old's got it we're in good
hands and then Equanimity find finding some balance in the middle of
things not so easy not so
easy so how do we remember how do we
remember when our hearts are heavy there's a lot of worry in the
mind when we don't know which way to turn or what to do or what's up or what's
down like can you just remember one thing not one thing I tell you to
remember but one thing that's sparked in your own
heart whether it's to be more loving be more honest be more
truthful remember peace the possibility of Awakening even
right wisdom
Insight anybody care to say a word I'll repeat it you can just say it
out loud anything came to you like oh that's mine I'm going to work on that one
Victoria
um I liked the quote from the DAP about a single day I don't remember the characteristics
but of mindfulness and discipline it's better than 100 years
without because I waste most of my time h
yeah I know I I know better well and and I hear you and it is good it's such a
good reminder it's a single day you know what if it's this day always you know
this day that's a practice day and then a you know just a wholesome day spending
time and watch the mind being judgmental include that too like oh I can say it
cheerfully okay yeah don't worry about that okay great great I'm just saying the quote
got me yeah okay thank you thank you yeah yeah yeah it's a good it's a good
quote a single day live with conscious intention and virtue is of greater value than a hundred years live devoid of
discipline and right restraint and what chapter in The dood is that it's eight yeah the thousands
yeah yeah um generosity really um
yeah I really appreciate that uh kind of holding that in awareness and there's something around generosity of spirit
too that comes up for me and um kind of entering into the meditation and you
know being here today I was having a lot of kind of physical and mental tightness and I noticed just kind of a
settling and an opening up and um with that opening up this yeah this feeling
of generosity towards everyone in this community and outside of this community and it feel so supportive of some of
those other things like mudita and so just really appreciate um yeah kind of dropping that
into awareness today thank you yeah thank you so generosity of spirit yeah
yeah and the generosity that like created this place right it is all built
on generosity yeah yeah if you weren't here I wouldn't be here
here if we weren't here like the teachings wouldn't right that's all it
goes yeah the generosity of the Buddha to share these teachings with us the
compassion of the Buddha to share these teachings with us
yeah any other Sparks or words that were
supportive it's going to be your word today this week this month
patience patience yeah
patience um I was kind of sparked by no
complaining don't complain and I wonder what is the like
that's the negative of it like I can see where
complaining kind of releases some of that Rage or you know helplessness or
frustration um in little things and in big things you know but what's
the positive the flip side of it yeah to me it's a motivator to take
action so you know I can complain about myself sibling or I can just have a
difficult conversation with my sibling right um or or I can choose something
else like the birthday's coming up you know so I can express
love right yeah but I think that's really helpful yeah yeah yeah so we just have
about five minutes and I'm done talking but maybe there's some
questions um about practice in general about expanding
practice I'm about a step behind you because I'm still on the what sparks oh
yeah what sparks yeah please um for me is uh truthfulness I'm going to be
visiting a friend in Florida not my favorite place but she's a dear friend
and the other day she said you know I I said something about hurricanes and climate change and she said oh you know
the the jury still out on that and I thought okay I'm going to be go spending
time with my dear friend and so it's that for me it's finding being true to myself but not picking a fight that is
not going to be helpful for anyone yeah yeah yeah and
and um to not seow more division it's like oh where can we meet where can we
we meet you know like we can know for ourselves
um when we're stuck in a position you know there's no amount of anybody
telling us anything that's perhaps going to convince us otherwise you know so it
is good to find those common places to meet
or yeah yeah just a couple couple more
minutes yeah here and then
here so um actually I really appreciated your
quoting um uh Thurman I I I recently um
read one of his books and uh recommended by a guy that I'm working with whose father actually just wrote a a biography
of his um but yeah he's so so that that resonated and I appreciate the fact that
that he came out of a different tradition you know he was he was a Christian and but yet there's a some
level there's a lot of overlap with our practices um I guess the only thing that
that Al also say that that came up for me and you didn't it wasn't prompted by any one specific quote or thing you said
but um I find myself more and more
um you know kind of overwhelmed by the the neurotic egotism of the times we
live in in this kind of preoccupation with ourselves and everything and and contrasted
with um the truth of nonself and that we're all
connected yeah and so I often find myself when I when I when I'm I'm outraged and seeing what's going on I I
I think of that and and realize that I think a lot of the stuff that that we feel is coming from that connection with
everybody else that's that's experiencing other
stuff yeah yeah and how do we balance that right yeah and then there was one
person right behind you this is a question on the practice
how does the practice look like and feel like when you're not formally sitting
yeah it's all of these things everything that I've said so it's it's oh can I be
patient while waiting in line or for waiting for my family to come out to the car right can
I find ways to be generous with my spirit maybe smile at another right can
I find ways to when the critic comes to meet that critic with some
kindness right uh can I notice when Joy is happening and be with it
fully so these are the ways we integrate these practices into our daily lives can I notice if I'm about to say something
or do something that might callls harm to another or to myself and not do it or
can I at least reflect on it afterwards and vow to not do it again
right these are the ways that we must integrate these practices into our daily lives and
and then in our more formal practice maybe we notice some settling because
we've practiced these wholesome uplifting qualities of heart and mind
right does that answer your question it does uh in in the in the
sense of practicing the virtues but I'm also wondering about the uh
observing the nature of mind while you're doing things all the
things that you mentioned yeah yeah yeah
um so I think it's helpful to build in some pauses right um so just I if if the mind
is not like knowing what's happening when it's happening throughout the day to build in some pauses um or cues to
help bring you back like it could be every time you walk through a doorway
like you just take a beat and take a pause um or every time a plane flies
overhead you pause and you send meta right but it's it's get the Paw in
there you know and or right when you wake up in the
morning you know you lay with yourself and with your breath and you know when
you're about to be upright right you're sitting up you know when the legs are moving out of the bed and feet are going
on the ground you know when you're standing up and make these habits and this way you're bringing in
moments of mindfulness throughout the day is that helpful okay okay so we have
to stop how really appreciating being with you today and so
we want to dedicate the Merit of our
practice our practice of
meditation of mindfulness our practice
of letting the teachings land in our hearts and Minds practice of showing up
for each other and for ourselves in this community may the benefits of our time
together first be of benefit to ourselves and then for all beings everywhere without exception may all
beings be safe and protected from all internal and external harm may all beings be peaceful and happy as possible
may all beings be healthy and strong and may all beings live with ease
[Music]
thank you all for your kind attention and for showing up so good to be with you