hello and welcome and for today's guided meditation as a
way to support the teaching afterwards I'd rather than some
instructions I'd like to offer you um Hello and welcome like to offer you a
um kind of an analogy or
metaphor today um the coming down here today I biked down to IMC and uh I was wondering about
the weather uh in one direction to the north the clouds that I call them clouds
were uh very dark and seemingly heavy and there was kind of a a cool crispness
in the air like uh crispness that was like Christmas like Christmas confusing
myself um uh a cool crispness in the air
that um uh it indicated to me that rain was coming so I was looking at all this
trying to make sense of it and I looked at my phone for the weather that they provide on the app and uh it said it was
cloudy through the morning and then it was going to be um sunny in the afternoon and uh and I knew
that in the last week or so we've had a lot of fog strong heavy fog coming in
from the coast and I thought maybe that today was just another uh you know rather intense version of it so I
decided to bike down some years ago my wife and I were at about 10,000 ft elevation in the
Sierra Mountains high up beautiful place we had lunch in this beautiful little
lake and we're just resting there um and uh we could see even higher peaks a
little bit to the west and um and the the sky was uh
completely blue and free of clouds and then there would be um we
would watch and kind of directly above some of the highest peaks they would
form a little cloud you know it was one of the littlest clouds I could imagine
there being in the sky a little puff would uh appear high high up in the
sky and um and then uh it would dissolve and not be there and then
another one would form and dissolve and disappear and it was kind of like magic
it was almost like watching something um uh arise out of nothing
and then disappear into nothing so I knew that what was happening was that uh the the again the coastal uh
weather uh was blowing moist air towards the Sierras and it would be pushed up as
it close to Sierras and at the highest peaks it would be pushed up the highest where it was cool enough for the
moisture to to form little cloud and then probably the wind was blowing it to
the further to the east where it was warmer and it would um or something and
it would um uh the cloud would disappear again so I kind of knew what was uh you
know you know the unseen world I knew something about but what was remarkable was that
uh was this watching the arising of the cloud and the
disappearing and um and the vantage point of being at ease peaceful calm
um watching the the birth of a cloud kind of understanding the simple air uh
atmospheric conditions that were operating and uh and being delighted and
amazed by it and the contrast of today with all the clouds and I could probably
construct an atmospheric explanation for what we have but uh my mind was
concerned about is it okay to bike down to IMC you know do I need to maybe it's going to rain and my bicycle will get
wet and what will I do and and how do is this these clouds clouds are going to
rain later and it was all this world of predicting and thinking and wondering
what to do that was very different world than the world just watching the child
being born and disappear and um and meditation is a
little bit like going from one the first the complicated ated world of many
things and many conditions coming together and predicting and wondering and analyzing figuring out and kind of
kind of conceptualizing about it to a kind of quieting and stilling and and to
be able to observe a single thought
arise and pass a single sensation come and go and we start seeing the the
simplicity of the details of our experience and uh and but the idea is
we're there resting after uh being at ease comfortable
peaceful kind of like we were my wife and I were kind of just resting on an
edge of a lake looking up at the sky so so this idea of meditation is just
there to become still enough quiet enough in the present moment
enough and oriented not towards the big concepts of today tomorrow is it going
to rain or not going to rain but right now in such a way that in the present
moment we see the birth of a thought and because we're not going to
participate in it so much it fades away the birth of a
feeling the birth of a perception of a feeling some feelings emotions seem like
they're have a constant presence but there's the perception of
it and simple simple perception that arises
and comes and goes there's the breath the inhale is like that cloud
that is born and then ends and then gets born again
so assuming a meditation posture and gently closing your
eyes and to become
established here and now in this
body taking some fuller breaths to feel your body on the
inhale a full feeling broad wide feeling of the
body and on the exhale relaxing the
body settling in
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and for three breaths relax your body as you exhale
and then for three breaths on the exhale quiet soften the
thinking mind
and then to settle in to the simplicity of
breathing not the complex thoughts about breathing
predictions about breathing or judgments about it but at the most basic level of
breathing seeing watching the beginning the first
appearance of inhaling the
inhale coming into fullness then ending
and the exhale
begins goes through its full
movement and then fades away
and this very simplicity of watching the coming and going of inhale and
exhale
it might highlight how much thinking there might be going
on how much conceptualizing complicated
ideas be amazed that the mind can do this
be amazed at a mind that can be clouded filled with clouds of
thought and then come back to that simple place in the natural
world where you're watching the natural unfolding of
breathing in and breathing
out amazed at the comingings and goings of
perception of breathing
there's that complicated world of thoughts and ideas past and future
and there's the simple world of what appears in the
present the
perceptions something is heard something is
seen something is
felt some new thing or old repeated thing is thought the thought arises
How can you settle back relax into the present
moment to watch the comingings and going of perceptions and
thoughts by watching the new every new perception as it comes into
existence and then something else and something
else and all this can be seen in the comingings and going of
sensations of breathing
if you're simple enough with your presence just here for the comingings
and goings of perceptions you might
notice there's a perception of something a feeling a
hearing and then there's a thought about
it or there's a thought that
arises and that conditions some feeling in the body
that things arise in awareness based on
conditions that come together for its appearing
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to appreciate
that the desires we have can condition how we see the
world and if you desire kindness
compassion if you desire to support the well-being and happiness of
others if that's the wish then we see the world differently
we see the world in such a way that we care for it more
and one possibility of meditation is to be more deeply
connected to the heart's
wish to bring greater peace safety compassion
love into the world for the benefit and well-being
of
others may it be that our meditation
practice is a condition for wishing for the welfare
and happiness of everyone
wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may these
wishes condition the eyes by which I see the
world may I see the world with love and care
[Music]
thank you [Music]
hello and welcome to the next talk in this series on insight
and this week I'm talking about five different categories of insight that
um um can be experienced that uh fit into this at least for the Buddhist idea
of insight the first day was personal
insight this yesterday I talked about um seeing um the difference
between appearances and the recognition of the
appearance the naming of it the remembering what it is and how one has a little bit more to
do with the senses the sense doors the sense contact with the world and the other has to do with how we understand
the sense contact how we recognize it as something and um and if we have these
two uh completely joined together as if they're the same thing then we can't see
either one clearly and things become kind of solid and have kind of a solid
existence so if we don't see uh so if um some food appears in front
of us someone offers us food and um and
uh and so we see food but we don't just see food we see an offering but we see
we see it through the lens of um oh uh this is something I don't like this is u
this is one of my least preferred dishes and uh and now the whole thing is
tangled up together as one big knot of the food the offering not my favorite
food i don't really want this they should have known better and how what am I how am I going to deal with this what
am I going to do here and um and you know it's becomes this
big knot um but if we can see each step along the way oh there's there's an
offering there's food and a recognition of food there's an offering recognition
of offering there's a rising of uh not preferring
this there's that thought and then uh uh there is that impulse to want to do
something about it and um and then we see that impulse clearly
and because we see it curly maybe we don't do anything about it we don't grimace we don't uh show our distaste we
don't we just kind of graces gracefully gracefully maybe just receive the the food so to be able to see the component
parts of what's happening the experience and our relationship to it that's more
of a mental world uh gives us a lot more freedom to be wise and careful with what
we do in um in the next insight is um that
uh can happen sequentially it can that really is highlighted because of our ability to see difference between a
sensation and recognizing what it is an experience and then the relationship we form to it is that
um is to see conditionality insight into uh the
conditions how one thing arises and something else that's a condition for something else arising i've sat minding
my own business in meditation very quietly and um and so I don't know why
at the moment but there's maybe some thought arises i'm sure it arose because
previous conditions I didn't see but uh thought arises and now uh maybe it's uh
concern about something that was difficult with someone and I can feel fear arise in my belly that thought
arose and that was a condition for fear in my belly uh there's no so then
there's no mystery if I didn't see the thought arise I just feel the fear in my belly uh and I just kind of keep
ignoring it then after a while I don't know what the original condition was that stimulated
it it can go in the other direction sometimes there's a a s sensation in the
body and um and uh the um so so I had a little tinge in
my back this morning so that was a little bit of pain and I've had back problems before so um I could see that
based on that there started to be thoughts about how do I be careful with this do I have to do some exercises do I
have to kind of go through the day a little more carefully here and so there was a and there was a cause and effect
relationship or uh this arose then that arose and um and so at some point when
the mind gets quite quiet and settled and the mindfulness gets clear in the present moment the that gives us a
vantage point gives us a a a vantage point from which a vista point to gaze
upon the present moment and being able to see the uh the simplicity of a
condition and the and what arises from that condition what that condition uh
evokes for us and things aren't a mystery anymore things aren't glued
together entangled caught in knots and um and we see that nothing has some
inherent existence nothing has some permanence or weight just because it's
there in our mind which it tends to have if everything is knotted together into a big ball of judgments and fear and
concern and history and past and present and all seems to be kind of in a big
knot but to see oh with this comes that with this comes that and then there's
more space to leave it alone to not act on it to not uh take it on as a as a
truth or as a as a something that has to be dealt with it's just we can see more
clearly and some people when they come to this stage this form of insight um
it's not required exactly so we don't go looking for it it's um it's really comes
from being settled but some people found it's really eye opening for some people
um it they feel tremendously empowered they feel tremendously like now they can
imagine what freedom is like because uh they see the space between a stimulus
and a response uh they see that uh stimulus is one thing response is another a stimulus
might a stimulus might uh it doesn't have to go into something else because
at some point as we see the these things things things these things arising one after the other one condition leading to
another at some point we don't participate it we don't get involved we don't act on it we're not we don't come
under its influence and so this morning when I felt my back pain uh I wondered
about it and uh spent some time thinking about it that was the condition for those thoughts was the back pain and um
and uh and then I thought you know I don't think that this uh level of pain which was very slight warrants much
concern uh at this point so I think I've done enough thinking about it so I think
I'll put it down if the pain is there again I don't know if I need to really get involved in those thoughts so I
might want to think about it but I have other things to think about or I would rather just be present for what I'm
doing at the moment so I just leave it alone so this is called insight into
into intercond conditionality and uh and kind of uh to
get to drop into it in a deep way it's kind of like entering into a different world uh a world where nothing is really
solid nothing is absolute in our direct experience and we can even see that uh
the impersonality of certain things that um that uh uh uh a certain sensation
arises and with that comes a thought and uh and it just kind of the thought wafts
up like the cloud I saw in this kind of being formed in the sky and then disappearing or as um a rainbow appears
and then it disappears that um there's a there's a
um a sight of a bicycle that's kind of shiny and new that's the sense
experience more or less and then with the mind there's a thought maybe I
should get a new bike and we see that the seeing of the the bicycle conditions
the arising of the thought if I hadn't seen that then I might have come I might
have just galloped off into thoughts about the new bike and uh and and but
because I could see so clearly the new bike the bike should I get the thought
should I have a a new bike I could just leave it alone i could my wisdom could operate and I could say you know I don't
need a new bike i have a perfectly good bike and um and uh let's not uh gallop
off let's not get swept up in those thoughts um and so there's a sense of of
freedom there oh and the thought should I get into a bike that is u almost like not my
thought it's almost like I didn't plan to have that thought i didn't um uh it
wasn't my wish to have that thought why exactly that thought arose from the different conditions in my psychology I
don't know but I don't have to take ownership of it i don't have to make it
something that um um make me out of it it just there was seeing a bike there
was a thought about maybe I should get a new bike and it just like it comes and
it goes it's just like a cloud in the sky that comes and goes a rainbow that appears and disappears that
um uh that um things are just things come and
things go and uh and then it's much life is a lot simpler and
easier and so so as I said before that this is a for some people uh this
becomes a very clear and strong insight that uh it they feel wow some people
even start feeling that this is so clear and powerful that they think that now they have tremendous wisdom they must even be
enlightened because the clarity by which they see this and they see that they
kind of begin seeing everything through the lens of conditionality that X X
arises then Y arises X occurs and Y occurs and um so but it but the
condition for it for this really to go go strong is the mind is deeply
settled and um and concentrated this is why samadei is so helpful and supportive
that we drop into a deeper samadei and stillness and capacity
really be here in the present moment content and happy and full the
distracted mind is no longer operating and uh and now uh we're just in this
vantage point of ease and relaxation we're just watching the experience
coming and going and one of the things that insights then is this insight into
conditionality and this uh sets up the stage for um the next one uh next
insight the insight into ins one's called comprehension or insight which
involves understanding and that'll be for tomorrow
so I also feel that you know this entry into insight is a little bit more is more
seemingly more intellectual more conceptual and um and some people
associate meditation so strongly with the experience of getting calm and settled maybe samadei that's kind of
exciting but uh but this is maybe seem now seems too heady and all that and um
but remember that the purpose of samadei is to be able to see in a new way and
these are the new ways that people see and to really do well it's not
intellectual it's not in the head it's actually the opposite it's to be really centered here and these become
revelations this is what gets revealed to us not something we have to think about or figure out or reme even
remember so uh the insight into conditionality is uh phenomenally important uh in the
in the in the teachings of Buddhism and all forms of Buddhism and for in our
practice it becomes an insight that's something we see clearly it's not a
philosophy so thank you very