hello and welcome to our Monday beginning of the week series of
meditations and teachings overall we're doing samadi over this extended period of
time and in thinking about samadi
um many people consider somebody the same as concentration and that is the same as
some kind of mental laser focus of the mind that happens from the control
tower another way of thinking about it is that the word samadi
is uh can also be understood in the very related words
samati uh can also be understood as um a subtleness to be settle deeply
settled and so in meditation in Buddhist teachings there are four dignified
postures for meditation and I love it when it's called
dignified there is walking
standing sitting and lying down but the kind of the the
representative for meditation is the sitting posture and the posture here we
have of the Buddha here next to me and
um and uh there's something that happens there in this posture if you if you
stand or if you sit in a balanced way rooted
upright in this kind of posture it allows something to settle to
relax the body then with time begins to relax the tensions the shoulders which
are tight the belly which is tight the upward kind of swirl of agitated energy
begins to settle and there's a feeling of subtleness a settling into the body
deeper in the body sense of gravity lowers the sense of being rooted and
grounded increases and um and that is not the
same thing has this laser focus of the Mind One Way of I understand it is that
it's kind of like a trampoline and if you lay down in the middle or sit in the middle of the
trampoline the trampoline settles and sags takes the weight receives it so
when we sit in a good way everything kind of settles down and that settling
point the lowest point of the trampoline then um is a little bit the center then
or the grounding the root for samadi and this can be done in any of
the four postures and uh but it takes some care to allow the posture to support
that to assume a posture which is aligned
or kind of where the in whatever way our body allows us
to do it that our body is
somehow um kind of in harmony with itself
or set up in a way that allows for something to settle there's not unnecessary tension or holding in the
posture and then there's a settling that can happen and then we can become
whatever degree of subtleness we have we can become aware of what makes us
unsettled and when we feel unsettled when we lose that whatever degree of modum of subtleness we
have it's possible to become aware that we now
become uh fragmented we now kind of become we're prioritizing or the energy
and tension and activity is going into some part of the body
mind that um kind of stands out at the expense of the
whole but if we allow that to settle if we relax that then there's a
sense of settling back into the more the whole of what's here and to recognize the way in which
becoming unsettled there's less of us there less of our
wholeness there and when we return to a sense of feeling of more the whole of our body
mind and heart that allows the body mind and heart to settle
more not because we're making it settle but maybe because we're finding
that place at the center of the tra trampoline where something can rest
the mind can rest the body can kind of be at
ease so when I did Zen practice the instruction was to uh place
the mind let the Mind rest in the Hara in the in the rest in this deep
place about two Ines below the navl and let just that was a place where
things were rooted and settled and not to not to avoid everything
else but allow everything else to settle in the center of the
trampoline so to assume a meditation posture that's right for
you st sit walking standing sitting lying
down and move a little bit in the posture wiggle sway back and forth forward and
back twist a little bit and and then see it to come into
some kind of Center some kind of
midpoint where things seem most aligned
and sometimes it can be that the aligned posture can help it feel like the two
lungs as they breathe
breathing the experience of breathing has a
midpoint in the front of the Torso perhaps parallel to the spine spine
and where sensations of breathing arise and
settle and that AR rising of the inhale the exhale which can be a
settling and letting go it's kind of like a
like needing bread kneading dough kind of a gentle kneading of the
body to soften it and settle it and support a
settling that you're not focused on doing
but that you're attuned to
doing and so if you haven't closed your eyes you might close your eyes to better
feel
sense the sensations
that come and go as you breathe in and
out perhaps relaxing on the exhale
or if there's nothing to relax on the exhale let there be a
calming a calming wave through your body
and there maybe a similar kind of kneading the
mind the thinking Mind by as you breathe in to feel the
sensations and energy activation of the thinking
mind and as you exhale to calm Cal the thinking
mind
soften
for
for for
centering yourself on
breathing as if the place where the inhale
begins or some other place deep in within the
body is the midpoint on the trampoline
is a place where everything
settles and you don't have to do the settling as much
as keep a light connection to that
point maybe on the periphery of attention
so that the feeling of that be that settle
Point allows things to settle into it allows the rest of your
body mind and heart to be
reassured there's a home base on which to
rest
for
for e
there can be an inverse relationship
where the more we are thinking the less were centered and
settled in the body and the less we're
thinking the more we're available for the settling into the
midpoint the center point of the body the grounding
Point shift your priorities from
thinking to
embodiment
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of a
sitting to perhaps return now settle more
on the grounding Point within the settling Point wherever that might be for
you maybe it's the place where the exhale
finishes if you let the exhale extend a little bit longer than
usual by letting go more can you in that few extra
moments relax and settle deeper into your
body and as you inhale have the bottom of this inhale
bottom of the sensations of your body as you breathe
in feel as if it's resting
on that settling
point and as if you're grounded or settled or
rooted deep inside
now bring to mind the daily life the world that
you'll be returning to after meditation the people you'll encounter
today maybe thinking of the strangers who you'll pass on the
street meet in places of Commerce and
and to from this subtle place to gaze upon
others with appreciation born of a sense of
kinship we are all family in some way or other
and in this rooted place where no one needs to know what you're
doing to wish others well and may it be that this meditation
we do allows us to see and take the
time to appreciate others and wish them well
may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free and may our ability to be settled on ourselves
allow us to contribute to the welfare of
[Music]
others thank
you e
so hello and on this Monday morning where we begin the second week
on the theme of
samama and um last week was more of the preparation for it and this week is
still preparation uh sometimes I think of um
the Buddhist practice meditation practice especially as being uh kind of a
pyramid where the preparation for meditation or
this beginning meditation is um creating the very thick
foundation for the pyramid and that the pyramid is
represents how much time we spend on different things in meditation and we spend most of the time
on setting the foundation and so in a sense we're all beginners we spend a lot of time with
beginning practice and then as we settle
in and the mindfulness gets stronger and the concentration gets [Music]
more uh unified then we kind of slowly go uh add
higher levels of the pyramid until we maybe occasionally get to near the top
but that's where we spend very little time and um because if you spend too
much time on the top of the pyramid it's a little bit like turning the pyramid
upside down and uh and have it's standing on a the point and it's not
going to be stable then it's going to want to come fall fall and then it'll create a new Foundation once there's a
wide base again so in the teachings of the Buddha
the preparation for samadi the mo the the proximate uh
preparation for it is to um settle the
hindrances the these are five states of
mind that inhibit or block or hinder the settling
and the unification of the whole self into this present
moment and um and so somehow learning to settle these or uh not be caught in the
hindrances so they hinder is a big part of being able to go into samade
and so the five hindrances I want to just be very simple I've T taught them
before some of you know them well and I want to just give a simple uh
label for them uh the first hindrance is to be hindered by
desires the second is to be hindered by aversion the third is to be hindered by
a sinking amount of energy just kind of like a fading like a draining away of energy or freezing of it the fourth is
to be overactivated with too much energy and something and the the fifth is to be
confused so I'll talk more about these but for today I want to focus on these first two because uh to to have a better
appreciation about why the hindrances interfere with samade uh you have to appreciate and be
able to recognize how each of these hindrances generally puts us into the world of our
thinking and this is particular with uh uh desire and aversion there's
something that we want or there something we don't want we want to get away from or push away and so there has
to be a a cognitive concern of the mind uh a story an idea thoughts an
imagination sitting and meditating their eyes closed we're imagining somehow what it is we
want and so we've gone up into the head into our thoughts ideas
imaginations images that we create that we're swimming in and caught in when
there's a strong desire or strong aversion and also as we get pulled into
strong desire and strong aversion there's not just a cognitive part of it
but there's also a motivational side we get pulled into the motivation behind it
there can also be a an emotional side to it that um that it sweeps us into the
emotionality or the authority the the
the the sense of urgency or power strength of the desire of the
aversion and this being pulled into this world that little uh complex of things
associated with desire and aversion uh then it
limits the wholeness of attention it limits how we can be what we're aware of
caught in a strong desire and um we can hardly notice anything else around us
but the object of our desire uh caught in strong hatred and we
notice nothing really except for the object uh of our
hatred and so the attention is now radically limited and the Buddha talked about this
that um that greed and aversion is a limitation and we put put us under we
put ourselves under severe limitations the stronger those are and one of the ways to feel those limitations is that
uh we're no longer in in touch with the wholeness of who we are we're not really
aware of the greater capacities for feeling for emotions for Sensations for
embodiment when we're caught in the grip of these strong things and so it's possible to feel when
we get caught in the grip of Desire or ver verion how it maybe maybe for some
of us pulls us into our head pulls us into our thoughts it uh maybe creates an
activated energy in the body that now uh focuses the energy of the body the
activation of the body in a particular area at the expense of really feeling settled or complete or or in the
fullness of the body and what we're looking for in um in
samade is a capacity to settle into the whole body to settle down and be rooted
and grounded here and so the hindrances are the very thing that gets us
ungrounded they can be very compelling and they can be very even desirous to
have them because of the strength of U motivation the Sens of energy and
aliveness and Authority they have like they almost can give a life meaning and purpose that uh can feel really good to
have like now I know what to do is to hate this people or this thing but it's at a tremendous expense
of alienation from oneself being more and more disconnected to Who We Are
and samadi is to be connected samade is to be the opposite of alienated from
ourselves but to be deeply connected at home here in
ourselves and so rather than being at war with the hindrances and feel like
they're bad to have and good preparation for somebody
is to remember everything is to be included everything has a place and so rather than being CAU in the desire and
aversion to see it clearly and recognize the effect that has on you recognize how
it limits you how it alienates you from parts of yourself and recognize how it
uh put you into a very narrow domain of awareness of cognition of concern and so
much is being left out um and uh you kind of have blinders on
almost and and as you see the limitations of this that is the beginning of opening up to something
wider and then you might be easier to uh make room for a settling to feel that
settling place and as we breathe maybe breathe with the hindrances but breathe
from that subtle Place uh let the subtle Place receive the energy the activation
the tension of desire and aversion and um and remember that uh the process of
suade especially in the beginning has a lot to do with a
settling and uh and the settling point and each of you will have a different
settling Point uh grounding Point Place of rooted within in the center of your
body perhaps and whatever that might be for you um in Zen sometimes we in Zen
you're taught to meditate with your hands one t t on top of the other the thumbs touching like this and sometimes
the instructions is not to put your mind in your Hara in your belly but let your heart rest in the in the curve of your
hands the palm of your hands and uh that becomes a settling point for some people
it's the sitting bones against their cushion the contact Point uh some people
it's something deep in the belly some people it's in the area of the solar plexus or maybe in the
heart and some people it's the whole body is the grounding place but uh when
you feel settled when something goes ah and you're relaxed uh you've been busy and
activated and preoccupied maybe tense or something and then finally you can
stop and something releases and lets go where does that is there some place
in the deeper place of subtleness might feel little bit amorphous might not be as so
clear as the clarity of the shoulders relaxing but uh see if you can start
finding a a place inside that is the Gathering Place the settling place and
be careful with it don't focus on it directly don't zero in that laser focus
on it almost like you have like more like a peripheral attention to it a
gentle soft attention into it a as if that is what allows it to kind
of smile allows it to grow allows her to feel
safe and um
so practicing with the hindrances is invaluable part of this Foundation the
foundational part of the pyramid that we're bu building and so if you have if
you have maybe you might have occasionally today some of the hindrances of desire and aversion
don't see them as exactly as unfortunate and be aversive to
them see them oh this is an opportunity now to practice with the foundational
elements of of samadi and as I've said one of the key
things to do is to notice how these hindrances now for today
um U aversion and desire how they limit you how they narrow the focus the
attention that's where attention can go how they contract you how they uh keep
you caught and uh and how so much more of who you are the totality the all your
capacities for uh as a human being many of them are left out now and left behind
and so is your way in which you're aware of the your environment it's very significant to see
the effect of the hindrances and know them well this is what's going to have help
uh the whole complex of the hindrances to settle and to return so you can
return to the the settled point the settling place the grounding place
within so um so today uh please uh uh notice when you
get caught and the language is caught in desire and aversion and notice how it
limits you and if you just do that in the course of the day you're uh you're
doing really well and it'll really supports this laying down the foundation for the where we're going in this course
on somebody so thank you very much and um I
look forward to tomorrow with you