so good morning and hello and welcome to this meditation session that's part of
an ongoing series on samadi and um samadi is the means in
Buddhism in the ear to see things clearly as they
are and to do so with equinity to do so
with a nonreactivity so because reactivity prevents us from
seeing things as they are and the primary thing that we want to see is
ourselves or see in such a way that um we see what's there we see the world
clearly but uh we don't uh get caught in it we become
free and so for some of us it's an indirect way of uh finding our equinity
with the world it's also an indirect way of responding to the world soat is not a retreating
from the world it's a strategic stepping away in order to come back into
Health psychological spiritual Heth and what's remarkable about the
whole process of Buddhist Meditation and Buddhist um uh kind of uh spiritual life
is that uh we have selfhealing properties we have there's a
movement towards homeostasis or a movement towards Health to wholeness
there's a movement towards no longer um living in a divided way or no
longer caught uh in our reactivity and our fears and our Ambitions and conceits and
it's remarkable what opens up for us and it's remarkable how we start allowing
and trusting the self-healing the self growing movements the onward leading
nature of this practice and it is onward leading if we
allow trust a deep process of connection
to ourselves here and now so part of this with suade is uh
somebody is a process of becoming whole a process of unification of gathering
ourselves together uh to allow this process of the whole of who we are to come into some
kind of healed holistic State and so uh as we develop as we
settle in and calm down and be more really here grounded in ourselves
grounded in this place grounded right here uh meditation practice becomes less and
less concerned with accomplishing anything with uh uh attaining anything
with proving ourselves or making something happen for ourselves
because more and more we see that that movement of mind takes us away from the
whole takes us away from really allowing this deeper onward leading process to
happen and so the Paradox is that the fastest way from A to B is
to be fully at a to be fully here in this
experience uh with what's happening now uh uh to not not be interested or
with accomplishments and attainments and getting anywhere in meditation is actually a way in which the whole
system uh unfolds and actually moves into some of the deeper places in
meditation so it's almost like giving up attaining anything is the way to make
progress in the practice so the when we approaching
somebody uh there starts becoming more and more a sense of deep con contentment
deep happiness deep Joy a deep kind of peace with just this moment here
here that uh is feels compelling feels like it has its own life that begin to
unfolding and in with that comes a sense of of um of unification and what this
means one one of the things that can mean is we have a sense that awareness now becomes more whole more inclusive
more Global and we might be very centered on some point on the settling point in the
breathing but that it's not focused it's not tight there's a there's a open soft
relaxed feeling of being centered at ease resting there and the same time a
soft wider focus a sweetness a joy a
delight a contentment that is not so specific but is more
diffuse and as we're more content to be here there's a more emphasis on the
diffuse awareness then there isn't a tight narrow you know focused attention
but that diffuse awareness that spreads out is nicely
centered and the attention is kind of centered but not um uh not uh tight not
straining to be with something and it there might feel a great intimacy but there's a feeling
it's in a wider container or wider field that could be feel quite
spacious quite bubbly quite soft quite warm a glow
something so this broad awareness inclusive
awareness so with those introductory words to assume a meditation
posture and um and to enter your
posture maybe with your eyes
closed and as if you're kind of lowering yourself into a refreshing pool of
water that you would take a deep breath and on the exhale lowering yourself into
the pool of your
body settling the
body breathing in deeply so that awareness of the body spreads through
the Torso with the expanding rib cage and
belly breathing in deeply and also feeling the more subtle sense of movement and expansion in the back rib
cage so the experience of breathing is
three-dimensional through the whole
torso and then a threedimensional settling on the exhale
and maybe a TW steps exhale exhale as you normally
would and then exhale a bit more by relaxing
further the diaphragm the belly
and then letting your breathing be
normal and for a few moments here with your eyes
closed feel or sense the edges of your body
some places where there's contact with the chair or the floor the hands contact with
body there's a very clear sense of Edge and other places there's no
contact maybe the edge feels more
diffuse more continuous with the space around it
and then within the the skin of your body this bag of
the body be aware of the global Sensations on the
inside almost as if you can imagine
a large spacious room within you or large Cavern or a open
space and as you breathe that you're breathing within
sensations of breathing are moving through the wider space of this body
and that as you exhale a calming of the body like a wave
that travels through
and so the experience of the body breathing is occurring within a wider
field of the lived body the general sense of being in a
body as it sensed or felt right now maybe a soft a few sense of
a vibration energy glow
hum where there's not an awareness that fixates on any particular
thing like the space in a room doesn't fixate on anything it allows all the
objects to be there as they are
or as if you're gazing into the space of a room into the space of an Open
Sky the attention doesn't land on any object but the peripheral awareness
knows in a general way what's around
and within this Global body as you
exhale soften the thinking mind a gentle calming of the thinking
mind
as you're exhaling calming and letting go of
thoughts let go in into the body breathing like
you're like a leaf settling from a tree onto the forest
floor Awareness on the exhale is
settling into the floor of breathing the settling Point
Within for
a panoramic sensing feeling of your
body without any
strain as you saw soften relax calm the
body settle into a panoramic sense of being
present with breathing at the
center
e for
if the whole body is like the ocean the breathing is like the
waves lifting and falling on the surface of the ocean
and as you breathe like waves through the
body also feel whatever pleasure that's
present especially any pleasure wellbeing
that comes with a
meditation
for
e
e e
and as we come to the end of this sitting
gently softly as you exhale
let there be a calming settling throughout your
body as if there's a wide soft
awareness that pervades your body and that breathing in
is a movement that travels through that field of calm or
space particular Sensations that travel through the wide field of the
body in a sense the body is like an antenna all the sensations that we feel
in the body are there because we have the
ability to sense to
feel like an antenna
and as we get ready to open the eyes and begin the process
of returning into this wide
world the wide world is a field of
connections wide Network before there were wireless
networks there were Wireless people networks of
relationships and connections and interactions between people some
wordless every communication we have with someone else is part of this human Network
whether we're writing or speaking
or sharing a space with
people we're designed to be in relationship in this human Network that
we're all part
of and to offer into that wide feeli and network of our
Humanity some equivalent of a smile as if a
smile brings brightness to the whole
field as if a smile is reassuring and calming for the
field a f a smile of friendship smile of
care a smile of
respect may it be that this practice we
do disposes us to spread smiles and kindness and
warmth and and Care into this world may we bring a
brightness to the this human world human Network may all beings be
happy may all being be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
thank you
so hello and welcome to this next talk on samade and we're now at the point of Sam
where we're at the phase of the approach the approach phase the approach
approaching somebody and uh the classic way of talking about this is that is a
gathering together or maybe we can say a coordination of five different factors
come into play and having these somehow in in the field there to be coordinated uh creates
a kind of Honor W movement onward kind of opening or settling or or
strengthening of the state of awareness meditation that we're in and so to kind
of gently not try to make anything happen but to allow the coordination to
happen and then to kind of gently feel where that onward leading spot is and
just rest with it that almost like you're allowing yourself to be pulled
long so these five coordinated faculties of ours that come into play that become
a little bit more pronounced and they have to identify every single one but
the tradition says these are the five things that are starting to become in coordinated and working
together and um so the first is these two uh the applied and sustained
attention the connecting attention and the sustaining attention and so there is
uh we're not just resting still on some focus of attention like they're
breathing there is a kind of gentle kind of like a wave like movement of connecting and releasing connecting
releasing connecting wondering away coming back there's a kind of gentle massage that's there stay here stay here
and sometimes even I've had the very sense sense of a little voice in the
back of the mind that said says it's telling me stay here stay here with us stay with this
stay now now sometimes I've used the word yes for this
yes yes and there's a little bit wave a little bit kind of like connecting and
sustaining and I like the yes because that speaks to the next thing that other
five coordinating faculties so the first is the connecting attention the second is sustaining that attention
and um and uh in a very small kind of relaxed kind of nice way like
yes um and the second the third is some degree of Joy some degree in which the
mind is is getting lit up mind is saying oh yes yes this is
good yes this this is nice and it's not necessarily verbal like that or but it's
as if there's a kind of a of a bright a kind of a maybe a teeny bit of a thrill
or a teeny bit of of a pleasure that feels delightful and wonderful that
comes with this feeling like um like uh you're now on the slide and it's so
great to be sliding along and uh now you're in the field now you're kind of
nicely connected and it's almost as if this connecting and sustaining attention
is like um you're like a cat being petted and that just something is kind
of just feels so joyful happy thrilled but then there's also and this
sometimes is less clearly felt but there's also a deeper feeling or or
embodied feeling that maybe initially can be described as
contentment um I often think of it as happiness uh and it's as less of the
mental brightness and thrill that can be there the mental yes this is great but
now there's a more settled ah and it's then it becomes easier to kind of this happiness is a a place
where it's easier to happily be calm happily be settled happily to be here
not needing anything else happy to just be arive and be
present because just being alive is enough and so it can it can be feeling of content contentment it can be a
feeling of coziness a feeling of sweetness that's settling calming
reassuring uh it is a kind of happiness that brings a sense of confidence like this is the bright place to be this is a
good thing and um and uh so there's the connecting
attention sustaining attention there's joy there's happiness and then the fifth of these factors coordinating factors is
um sometimes called one-pointedness but that one pointedness is too easy to uh have the idea that
we're tensing up and straining to be really locked into something and
sometimes there is a feeling of being really clicking in and really being present in a very clear way but we're
not the one who's doing it it's the it's the system that's doing it so the mind could be quite relaxed so the metaphor
or the example I like to use for this is that say we're just staying with the
breathing and the breathing is let's say the breathing is like a way of coming and going rising and passing and um and
then someone says you should concentrate on the breath and so then there's a mind here and the concentrate every
everything in the mind gets tense and focused like a point and then it goes and kind of points and tries to pierce
this breath that's kind of is a moving flowing thing and u and sometimes that
can create strain and headaches and all kinds of problems to do it this way another way of doing it is um is to let
the mind be very soft and relaxed to calm the Mind calm the body relax
everything so there's a feeling of spaciousness and open like the hand now is open not collapsed on itself and then
you bring these two together and so this is the holistic kind of broad uh wide
sense of being aware because the the mind is quite open and spacious the body
feels quite open and kind of pervade with a kind of a hum of just being alive
or the hum or vibration of all the different little sensations of the body
kind of singing together and um and the open mind that
there's no tension in the mind and the the breathing is still moving and what
you do is you bring this together so that the the um maybe the breathing gets quieter and
quieter and so the breathing and the most sensitive part of the Mind meet and
join and so there's a resting a coming together so there's a kind of a sense of
being right centered on the breathing the the massage of the breathing staying
there the connecting attention is kind of like connecting sustaining
Falls away connecting sustaining to the most sensitive part of the of the of the
mind so there's a lot really s centered there but it's not focused it's not
preoccupied and there's all same time a broad field all around it that can feel
sometimes like just like space sometimes it can feel like a sweetness a pleasure a joy a a holistic kind of sense of
being here in the whole body and but this is soft and relaxed but and so this
begins taking prominence and sometimes what will happen is is this here this connection will uh become stronger and
stronger and everything around it becomes softer and softer and maybe parts of the body seem to disappear The
Wider World disappears because and we're just sitting right there on the
breathing so uh so that's the one pointedness that the one Gathering the
one settling the set settling place the Gathering Place the sensitivity place
that we really feel oh this is it and um so then when these when these uh five
factors are coordinated then there's a kind of a gentle there might be a gentle gentle
gentle feeling of onward movement and one way that I felt
it is it's almost like there's a place maybe in this breathing Maybe and whatever the where the where the sense
of Joy or the pleasure maybe is the strongest with all this it's almost like
the Dharma up ahead with a string and it's gently pulling you here here and so
there's a some place inside that feels like oh here is where the slide is here's where the world is opening up
here is where to relax into not to rush into not to uh uh but it's a place of
approach and as we are approaching um this feeling of being content being holistic
being whole being unified becomes a little bit stronger and stronger
everything is here together there's nowhere else we'd rather be there's
thinking mind is quieter and quieter to the degree to which we're thinking uh
it's thoughts about the meditation his thoughts about ah here it is here's the
in breath here's the whole whole feel here and present and it's nothing more
sophisticated than that just the most simple kind of thoughts about the experience and then in the process of
that uh you there might be a feeling there there's something operating here which is not
you it's something operating here that U that you can trust something an onward
movement a a deepening settling a deeper opening um and this
and and this is something that if you have any role at all to it is to trust
anything at all it's kind of to let go let go into that place where into
that onward leading feeling where either it's onward leading because it feels like the pleasure the joy is going to
grow if they're onward leading because it feels like this is where the the center point is that you want to kind of
really rest and follow and be with allow yourself to be pulled by that
string allow yourself to be carried on that slide allow yourself to open that
door allow the the uh the
the you know like if you have a parachute on allow kind of the the the
floor of the airplane to fall open so you can start floating and flying in the
space with the that parachute so there is this kind of so
onward leading so this coordination of all these things and that coming into a
wholeness this way is not exact not something you can engineer and plan for
but you can feel the symptoms of it you could feel the joy feel the pleasure
feel the the the goodness of it all the sweetness of it all the contentment of
just being fully here and trust it trust it and allow for it don't be the
engineer don't don't be the Constructor and the maker of it don't be measuring
and trying to am I there yet just trust to be the fastest way from A to B is to
be fully at a and as we're at a at this approach stage then the
Dharma will know what to do your job is to trust the process not be
in a hurry not to try to make it happen and maybe the biggest thing you can do
is to let go into trusting the process rather than making the process and uh
however long it takes so um we'll have one more talk on
this approach point and um thank you very much