e
e e
hello from Redwood City
clearly getting lighter earlier now starting to get light outside the
windows here and um and in Buddhism it said that the
dawn is the um
Harbinger harbinger of
wisdom because with light we can see clearly
so yesterday I said samadi is Simplicity today I'd like to offer a
different aspect of samadi that samadi is
subtleness to uh um becomes settled and um the kind of
subtleness that creates a foundation to hold all
things that uh tripod for example uh when
it's well placed with the three legs then it can hold whatever telescope that
is going to be on it that you can't really do if you the
legs are not spread apart but they're all bunched together so it's basically one leg then it's going to wobble and
it's not going to uh stay up by itself and maybe you have to hold it but even your hand is
not so steady to hold it still so a steadiness to create a steady
Foundation that can hold all of who you are that allows us to see turn on the
light to include everything because as I keep saying some
body is a unification of all things in a certain way so so a
subtleness and so to uh
use are the different elements of meditation for the purposes of feeling
settled becoming settled it's closely related to being
relaxed to settle and be relaxed it's related to
um um being fully invested fully engaged fully
interested in here and now this process
here and to engage in that process of being here in a settled way in a relaxed
way in a in an enjoyable way and of course the mind will wander off consider
that to be part of the process it wanders off and then the task is to
begin again it's almost like a massage the mind has to be massage enough to settle
and wondering off and then coming back is a gentle kind of relaxing massaging
of the mind so it eventually settles to be here
so to assume a meditation posture that allows you to feel somewhat
grounded into the surface that holds your
weight whatever surface it is if you're standing the soles of your
feet if you're sitting on a cushion or chair or couch it's the
the seat of the chair the seat of your cushion is against your bottom if you're lying
down it maybe in a bed or on the floor it's a
full extent of the B your back
perhaps in contact with the floor the bed and allow that to be kind of a
grounding for your weight
as if this surface receives your
weight to provide a grounding a
settling closing your eyes taking some long slow deep
breaths with the exhale relaxing the body softening the
body and as you do so settle into this grounding
settling into this place where you're
meditating and then letting your breathing return to
normal and for now can you find a settling point a grounding point
maybe deep in your body might be the lowest point in your
body or the most grounding place in your
body for the end of the out breath if you follow your exhale the
physical experience of the body releasing Contracting settling
the diaphragm lifting as you
exhale maybe the belly expanding as you
exhale or the bellet gently pulling in as you exhale
at the end of the exhale the last place of clear
Sensations in the body from
where the movements of inhale begin maybe spreading
outwards as the Torso expands
for some people there might be the image of a balloon
that as expands as it fills with air so the Torso expands as we breathe
in expanding in all directions and as the balloon deflates
as the air leaves and contracts pulls
in so the exhale the
body settles back in
back to the settling
point and maybe even the image for people who
visualize a balloon expanding and
Contracting will keep you simply with experience or breathing
and as you breathe
in you might gently
say the word one but see if you can say it in a
way that doesn't activate the mind or agitate the
mind but is part of quieting and settling the Mind into the
breathing especially when you say to as you
exhale long pronunciation of
two the two as an invitation to now settle the
Mind down towards the settling point
maybe imagining or feeling or
allowing these numbers one
two do not arise in the mind so
much in the brain but in the wider
mind as if it's a rising in belly itself
to rising from the settling Point without any tension or
pressure the numbers just float up as an
invitation to feel the breath to be with
it
for e
usually there's a little stronger feeling experience of the body as we breathe
in allow that strength to
support being
attentive and letting there be a settling as you
exhale the body can subtle and sometimes the number two
saying two with the
exhale can be a way of staying
connected and settling the mind as
well
e
e e
e for
seeing as you exhale if you can
ride the whole exhale
stay in touch from beginning and
end in a way that the whole
exhale settles quiets the
mind the awareness into the body
for
e
e e
staying close
to the entire length of breathing [Music] in the entire length of breathing
out may be supported by
counting inhales and
exhales the counting keeps you settled here
with the body's experience of
breathing
for
e
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting maybe if it's possible to settle the
heart maybe as you exhale to allow the Heart
Center to [Music]
soften to
relax and to settle almost as if it's gently being
invited by gravity to come to rest in
itself with every exhale settling the heart
settling the heart so that it can be supported by the deeper
settling place
within the place where breathing comes to a settled
point or the place where the body feels most
settled let that hold receive the settling
heart and what if if it is this settled
heart that can
that can love most
easefully a settled heart can have good will
kindness can have care and respect for others
a settled heart doesn't sacrifice
itself for anger or resentments
frustrations fears
settling the heart so we can gaze Upon This World
this suffering
world with an attitude of care of
kindness an attitude that we would like to
spread kindness
support so everyone's heart can settle everyone's heart can
settle so the best quality of heart can grow in all
people may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all
beings be
free and may we stay close to this aspiration these
aspirations by staying close to a settled heart a settled
body a settled mind
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this series on
samadi and
um slow samama slowly moving into it and today I want to mention that
sometimes I think of samadi as settling as a subtleness samadi is
subtleness and when we sit down to meditate it's often good to start with
the idea of Discovery to discover how we are how are we right now and one of the
questions you can ask is given how I am
what needs what is unsettled that maybe would be good to
settle now if it what's unsettled is something ideas about things in the
world something outside of ourselves we maybe won't settle those things the problems we have but we could
settle what needs to can be settled is the mind's agitation the heart's
activation around things that are feel unsettled and this is where meditation
comes into into into highlight for us is how it when we come back to notice where
we're unsettled inside then we can ask now let how do we
settle this and there's many answers at different for different things one of
them for when it's hard to stay focused on meditation the Mind wonders awful
lot one thing to become settled about is
that that's happening and that we can fold the distracted mind into the
meditation in this way to think of it that what we can do is offer a massage
to the mind that there's a natural process a
cycle of um wondering off and returning wandering off and
beginning again and that cycle provides a massage that we don't know what's being softened
and needed and relaxed but to appreciate that there's a cycle that our job is the
coming back our job is to wake up again is to be connected here again and we
know we're going to wander off but it the but be relax and settled this is a
process so that as soon as we notice we' wandered off we're relaxed and at ease
and know oh good come back be here uh show up here
again and um and that we're kind of going along going
along and if we're counting the breath the INB breath and the out breath uh
you're less likely to wander off so much because you have a reference point or
you're more likely to notice if your Wonder off and so one of the values is counting is to
notice when this massage is operating so you can be part of it more intimately
more closely so count one for the inhale and if you're counting two for the
exhale and you don't say to you might be really drifting off if you're able to
say to for the exhale um you might then see that you're not really there it's
become mechanical it's become automatic because you now you're drifting off in thought and that gives you the clue that
I'm drifting sooner than you would normally or if you don't catch it at all
during the exhale you might catch it on the inhale oh I'm I I've drifted off in
thought and then the one saying one is
the settling word one or two is a settling word and what I
mean by that is you want to be able to if you do the counting of the breath to do it with
a tone of voice loudness energy in the mind of saying the word or imagining
you're saying the word in such a way way that it just feels settling to say it
like if a if someone comes to you who's really upset maybe hurt maybe angry
maybe something that you would maybe change your voice uh to be available
clearly and you're the settling it's okay I'm here with you it's okay now and
so something can kind of begin to relax and settle and then um different times as we
discover what's going on for us and in some ways meditation is continual process of discovery we discover what
can be relaxed what can be settled and now sometimes what's being settled is the
body and um and uh sometimes what's being settled is the muscle musculatures and activity
of breathing itself maybe in the exhale we're really settling and relaxing those
muscles that get engaged when we breathe in and um so that when we breathe in U
there's maybe less extra muscles engaged in that process there's an easeful
process of breathing in and breathing out maybe what could be settled would be
the mind and um sometimes uh saying counting
the breath um we're there with the breathing but since the words are a
little bit mental uh activity is to say the words so that
there's an um there's a settling and expanding of the mind just um that the
Mind opens up to be wider bigger um the shape of the mind is
arbitrary but if we're caught up in thoughts caught up in preoccupations the mind gets tight and sometimes shriveled
sometimes constricted and um but to say these words why
one so the Mind expands two so the Mind
expands and then after a while go back to just the breathing but to stay close to that
rhythm of breathing through it all the rhythm of breathing is the is the
ultimate massage the ultimate reference point for this process of settling
connecting receiving the experience of the moment receiving the inhale relaxing the exhale
settling and um one of the interesting things about counting the breath if
you're doing it and I recommend that you try it for a while for this
week is that um the uh the amount of energy or or
effort or uh strength of that inner voice that does the counting
uh you have to pay attention that as you get more settled and relaxed in meditation uh you have to uh turn a dial
in the mind so the you're saying one two
the count a quieter um if you say it too quiet
before you're ready the mind can drift off too too quickly so you have to kind of adjust the volume in such a way that
it you keeps you present but it helps you to settle without agitating you but
as you subtle you might have to turn the dial down to quiet even
more so um I want to repeat a little bit some of the choices you have for how to
count and I apologize if offering you too many options um makes it
um you know makes it confusing but different people find different things are
useful uh and I find at different times different ways of counting are good
um sometimes uh just counting one with either the exhale or the inhale
all it's enough I find it very nice sometimes to just count one for the inhale and two for the
exhale sometimes it's nice because it engages me bit a little bit more is to
count one for the inhale two for the exhale three for the next inhale and
then be quiet for the the next exhale would
normally get to count four and sometimes I can't help myself but to somehow in the back of the mind is say the number
four but the idea is to kind of little bit not do it so there's space for some
real deeper connection some space to allow some deeper relaxation and opening
and uh and I find it kind of delightful if my mind back of my mind I still want
to do the number four and um it's I kind of appreciate how effortless it just
arises by itself and uh and kind of the kind of not counting the on the four uh is a
protection from the counting getting automatic it's kind of a refreshing to start again at one so that's very very
simple another way of doing it is to count to 10 so five inhales and five
exhales you get to 10 and then you start over uh another way is to only count the
exhales um or to count the same count for the inhale and the exhale one one
two two so probably I shouldn't be giving you so many options um but if one
of them you know Sparks your interest keeps you
engaged you'll learn a lot about yourself by counting you'll learn a lot about the forces of distraction you
learn a lot about how you're practicing because sometimes we uh the the inner
voice of does the counting um is provides the evidence that we're straining or we're hesitating or we're
seeing it as a work the whole meditation is a work and we're kind of like you know it's kind of like a burden
kind of and so we can see a little bit through that voice unnecessary attitudes
and then see if through the voice you can change the attitude change so it's simpler easier cleaner how you're being
here with the experience so
um so to um uh count the breath and uh and then
uh tomorrow I'll give you a little bit more U discussion about how this
counting really supports this process of samama body in a deeper deeper
way so um may you continue with this for a while and again as I said yesterday I
really encourage you to um if you have the time the inclination to add a second
meditation in the day so that uh you can practice this more on your own so you
bring that with you for the next day to a little bit more of a foundation or a little bit more of momentum to go along
with what we're going to do here over time um so thank
you
e
e e