hi thank you nice to be with
you we've been uh we've been sitting with our eyes closed I'm just taking you all
in what a treat we all seem to have made it um
Beyond daylight savings time um many of you know me uh as the
co-managing Director at uh imc's Retreat Center over the hill the Insight retreat
center and last night uh Gil and bruny are there teaching uh 40 or 45 yogis and
there was a there was a very long spiel about the clocks changing because the
the uh the Yogi's minds are quite still and quiet and I was I was pleased by the care that
went into the clock's changing announcement and the giggles that were coming out of the meditation Hall
so the the topic I want to talk about today is how we reg regard experience or
how we relate to experience um my own route through practice has
been a rather winding one and I think that may be true for for
many or all of us that uh the content of our lives and the and the steps we take
through this life there's so many each of us has our own challenges each of us has our own
strengths um but there's something there's something that the Dharma offers which is
um at least in theory can be applied to All Things how we regard
experience one of the reasons that this practic is uh maybe a
little mysterious isn't quite the right word but maybe uh let's say let's say
deep multifaceted is we have so many instructions uh I was I was doing I I
like to count uh I was doing some counting depending on how you look at mindfulness of breathing we might have
16 instructions or four depending on how you want to look at them Sati patana if
you look through the the mind the foundations of mindfulness suta depending on how you count it maybe
there's a dozen Maybe 13 and then the majima 119 mindfulness
of the body there's another 10 there's some overlap in all these but it is your mind
spinning with instruction but rather than rather than
take these as um sort of scattering one way we can gather them all together is uh Joseph Goldstein has
this great piy quote that there's only ever six things going on
there's uh sight sound smells tastes
touch and then mental activity that's that simplifies things
no down from 30 30 something but in the practice we have
these we have these sort of let's say traditional or time honored ways of applying our
attention uh it in very specific ways that help to grow the path to grow the
grow the steps of the
path just to strengthen this point about Joseph Goldstein and the six things aan
cha the uh Thai Forest teacher said that actually where practice
happens is where the Mind meets a sense object maybe in other words we could say
that's where attention meets sights sounds smells tastes touch and mind if
any of you have read Gill's book uh the issue at hand there's this lovely little uh thing I think it's in the
preface where um he talks about it it's so much it's so much more maybe skillful
or easier to pay attention to the the the point of contact with experience I
think he uses this metaphor of uh walking on a rocky road and that every every step that's
like a oh ouch little rocks ouch ouch uh and rather than trying to sweep the road
clear of rocks we put on shoes we put on shoes and in a similar
way uh rather than trying to sweep all the Rocks away from our six sense spaces
if you will taking really good care of this point of contact so how we relate
to experience
so I want to tell some stories uh that sort of illustrate this the the first the first illustrates the
fact that in our in our mindfulness practice there are two qualities that are being cultivated in
Tandem and uh sometimes these are translated as Serenity and
insight there's the there's the calming the stilling of the mind and then there is the clear seeeing
familiar territory and these are these work best when they're developed
together so why is that first story
is when I was a when I was a young boy seems like forever ago I was given a
telescope and I was delighted I was something of an astronomy Enthusiast when I was a a little one
the the trouble was um I couldn't figure out how to set up the
tripod uh and I it did not occur to me in my young boy mind to ask for
help poor little one so uh instead of instead of asking
for help uh I decided I'm just I'm going to my gray telescope I'm just going to
try to hold it and you know it seems reasonable enough right so I'm I'm out on the I think I'm
on the porch and it's night sky and I can see the astral something that I want
to look at maybe a star and uh I I kind of point the telescope at the at the
star and I put my eye down to the viewfinder it looks still enough but when I look down in the viewfinder
there's just nothing it's it's a haze it's like hazy nothing I can't I can't
see because the telescope isn't still and this is how this is how the
the functioning of uh uh Serenity and insight work the tripod is the serenity
of course and the Insight is the telescope if I had had this a stable
base I may have been able to see all sorts of things but when these two qualities
develop together um they begin to unveil all sorts of layers of our
experience there's this lovely verse in the damam that something like for for one
with Insight no for one without insight there is no
meditative absorption and for one without meditative absorption there's no
Insight but with both one is quite close to nibana was quite close to the goal of
the bre practice this ending of greed hatred and delusion our various practices can
emphasize one side or the other or they can emphasize both but when they're both mature we can really fly really
fly they also have um suring Serenity and insight that they not only have
meditative implications but I think it's worth mentioning that they have ethical implic
also maybe we can take the point that the the more clearly we see inside
ourselves and and outside uh how different our actions
become I was reading in the in the sutas this morning and uh and found found one
I hadn't seen in a long time which said uh said something like a
mind without delusion uh uh is a whole wholesome
mind and what one does with a mind without delution is also
wholesome and that's it seems simple enough but that's an import that's an important shift from just the mind
without delusion is wholesome to what we do with that mind is also
wholesome so there's there are these ethical implications to Serenity and
insight so talk about the just one other way uh there is the the what of our
experience and the how of experience the what we might say these are the sights
sounds smells tastes touch mental Activity six sense
bases and then the how of course is how we relate how we
relate and it's a fascinating thing to to to look at what sort of what sort of
perspective or what sort of attitude what sort of how is the mind taking up at any
moment and then how is that influencing both how I'm seeing and um how I relate to
others the how is important of course because it conditions so much of how we
suffer um and some of the some of the stories I want to tell I think I think we'll get into that but uh one one very
innocent example about the the how of experience um is any it do we have any
coffee drinkers in the maybe you'll be able to U relate to this I know when when I wake up in the
morning often when I right before I go to bed I think ah coffee's coming in the [Laughter]
morning H and then uh wake up in the morning and uh alarm sounds is it time to get up
okay maybe a maybe a thought has arisen but things really kick off when at the eye door when I see the coffee
grinder and then I start you know all that happened was a little bit of contact at the eye door but all of this
proliferation starts oh my perfect cup oh oh I hope I have enough of my
favorite dairyfree creamer uh the desire the craving the thinking all of this all of this gets
going all on the basis of just all all that happened really was I saw some I saw a coffee grinder
so uh that's innocent innocent
enough so a couple of
stories last September I was sitting a three-week retreat at at IRC something
really special I think we do this is my asside to again share that
I'm just having an upwelling of what an amazing Community IMC and IRC are uh this is not what I wrote but um uh we
had a um we had a volunteer appreciation event sometime last year and uh
uh there it was stunning I I was sitting right over there it was stunning to see
just that as an expression of how many people make the make IMC I don't even
want to say make IMC possible like they make IMC you make it it's amazing are IMC
you're doing IMC what a what a cool thing all right back to them back to the
story so um last September at at IRC sitting this Retreat and little
little did I know that um must have been shortly before the September Retreat a new a new neighbor
moved in and the the neighbor uh four
legs tail and barks barks Barks A Lot
Barks A lot so I did a I did a lot of my meditating
in my in in my room with the windows open and it was uh at the ear door bark bark bark
bark bark bark bark bark sometimes okay that's the what of the experience and the how sometimes I would hear the bark
I would hear the bark and what would happen annoyance agitation you feel the feel the
sensations in the body mindful mindful
um and then based on that uh based on that agitation that aversion these
thoughts started coming some of them were I wonder how long a dog could bark
before it gets tired there must be a
limit um and then it was uh gosh I'm the
director there are 40 people here I wonder do I need to go over there and like have a conversation with my
neighbor about their dog um I didn't choose to do
that uh let's see just to say all that happened was a
sound and all this scheming started happening and other times other times
the bark would come up mindfulness would know and uh there would be absolutely no
reaction whatsoever completely neutral not intentional on my
part and then still later sometimes sometimes the bark would come I hear the
bark and who knows who put this reaction there it would be what what a lovely dog
I just love this dog I cannot wait to meet this pup who's moved into my
neighborhood is full of meta it's remarkable interesting thing about all
this uh this first story is that um it didn't deliberately cultivate the
different responses it was just mindfulness and and conditions coming together so uh
what does that mean it means our reactions to things are not stuck they're not
fixed uh they they are they're they're both changeable and they are changing if we wait long
enough it's kind of like the
weather so a little bit of a a different location Second Story was um uh tasahara
has anyone been to tasahara yeah yeah so the Zen Monastery that I I
moved to California for
um loved being there it's just beautiful out in the out in the Ventana
Wilderness kind of in a in a in a valley with a little Creek Running by and the
cabins are built along the creek very very cool place to practice and I was working in the kitchen uh at this time
so
this [Music] uh this story is about deliberate
cultivation The Last Story shows that some sometimes things change on their own this one needed a little nudging
because this was a very stubborn habit I'm working in the kitchen and occasionally I would I would um I would
drop something like a whisk or a bowl or some food or something uh maybe I drop a
glass and it would break and I would notice any anytime I would drop something the mind would have its
response more or less G G I was I was agitated at the fact that I had dropped
something seeing this happen enough times and uh just knowing it wasn't
really shifting Shifting the pattern I was motivated to make a change because I
noticed that not only did the G make me really uncomfortable I was I was making my own suffering worse
with the adding agitation on top and then it it wasn't doing any favors for
the the mood of the kitchen and the people around me so I I was having an
effect so I decided to to try something completely different which now I know the Buddha calls replacing the
peg where anytime I dropped something I would uh I would deliberately in my mind go yes
and some sometimes I would do this out loud uh and it sounds really silly but
it it it totally worked it really worked so so uh it came to be that in that in
the kitchen I would drop something yes what a rise Pleasant Sensations rather than agitation that led on to
upset and the the the training the the mental training of replacing the peg was so effective that now um I'm not
encouraging you to break anything but e even if I hear someone else drop something my mind will go yes and and
the pleasant will come the pleasant will come it's a much better condition for a happy mind um I told this story U maybe
three years ago at tasahara when I was not working in the kitchen and uh the K the the folks who were working in the
kitchen for that practice period picked it up as a practice so it's spreading
so that's replacing the peg um again it's it's a it's a kind of
light-hearted story but it m it makes a really important point that if we choose to we can deliberately cultivate a
different how to experience um yeah it's not it's not
necessarily not necessarily to force anything out of our experience but just bring some other conditions in
so this third story it's a it's another Retreat story and it's uh it's it's more subtle
we can say it's um it's in the sort of place where the
Serenity and insight had some momentum it's been a it's been a long retreat by the time this happens in the the story
what I and what I came to notice in the the the the Stillness and the
clarity was that there was a very subtle almost
invisible um attitude it was kind of like a tiny little seed that was
coloring uh every aspect of experience that uh I hadn't even known
it was there but it there was like there was just a slight Distortion to
everything and the clo as I as I tuned into that little seed what I saw was that it was a very small seed of
fear and that that that fear was it was pervasive it was like everything that arose at the eye there was a little bit
of fear every sound every thought you know every sensation in the body that the the entire how of experience was
fear it was really really subtle but there's something in those in those
meditative spaces where I mean seeing something so small can be so
powerful and can constitute a shift you you can imagine what a what a
change comes if you put a say you put a giant lever at just the right place and
you can move it just the tiniest bit just and the and the whole world
changes so in in this case the the how of fear just by being known
with mindfulness and uh Clarity with Serenity and insight something allowed
it to let go nothing really
happened that's anticlimactic story but um sometime later sometime later that
day there was this total unbidden uh Vision it was like new eyes
that the world the world could be seen and known without fear it's somehow it dropped away on its
own without without really doing anything and then this big upwelling
that I did not ask for of beautiful confidence came and just to see that for a moment
oh that that that confidence was a that's a different option for a how for
how to relate to experience it sure didn't last forever
um but it was it was enough it was enough to to show and to show this
beautiful possibility and also for the the body and the mind to get an imprint like oh this is possible this is
different so it's another case where it's not exactly like um confidence was cultivated it
wasn't exactly a deliberate cultivation in that way but uh as you hear Gil talk about all
the time we're putting the conditions in place for something to unfold and in the way we're talking
about it today we're putting Serenity and insight or we're talking about the how of experience the how we relate to
experience really taking care of that and then that that making way for for
the unfolding of something rather beautiful or freeing or easier
so mindfulness it's a pretty easy relationship to experience let me say that a different way it's not
easy but it's sure not complicated it's a very simple relationship to experience Boo
and alio has a as a real succinct way he puts this he writes that one task of
mindfulness is to remain generally aware of the process of
experience without reacting to specific sense
objects that sentence is a little complicated one task of
mindfulness is to remain generally aware of the process of
experience without reacting to specific sense objects
to put that uh as I've been saying in a in a in a more simple way we have these
six sense objects the what of experience and one task of mindfulness is simply to to know
them to know them without reactivity so all three all three of
these stories kind of say something about that how and what's possible for
us um if there's some curiosity about
practicing with the how uh practicing with the how we relate to experience um borrowing from auta and
the samut Naya there's some uh there maybe some some
Reflections or things you can look toward in your in your own meditative experience one is are there thoughts
present maybe you can get to know the how how am I relating to experience by seeing are there thoughts present
and a secondary question uh asking yourself are these
true second thing of Leaning into the third Foundation of mindfulness is there
an attitude present so thoughts
attitude third um am I knowingly or unknowingly
cultivating something in my third story Maybe I was I was unknowingly conditioning
fear uh and in the Second Story I was deliberately cultivating a more uh Pleasant response to dropping
stuff am I knowingly or unknowingly cultivating something and then fourth how simple is my
seeing how simple is my relationship to experience or how complicated is it
so I might say that the um this practice has a
trajectory it has a movement an onward leading movement and this uh unification of
Serenity and insight it uh it reveals both our our
what of experience and our how of experience um and then moves onward
through these VAR deep insights these Notions of uh uh seeing things as they've come to
be um then ceasing to be enchanted by those
things the the gradual fading away of craving and then knowing a mind that's
free that's amazing that is pretty amazing it makes me so glad that this place exists
another Gil ISM related to
Liberation more or less says something like it's not us who become
awakened but with Awakening we we liberate all things from
us yeah that that makes that makes once huh that's a very different how in
relationship to experience
there's a really there's a really um seems like a to me a an
interesting relationship in the sutas that I don't think we talk about all that much but occasionally the um
I think it's called the ruler of the dvas Saka comes and asks the Buddha a
question that's always that gets my attention and uh Saka in this
case comes to basically ask what why is it that some some
beings uh are liberated and others are not that's a good
question in my opinion and what what do you imagine the
Buddhist response might have been I could imagine any number of responses but I was delighted in turning this
theme in my mind that the the Buddha the Buddha talks about eyes and sights ears and sounds
nose and smells tongue and tastes body tangibles mind and mind
objects and more or less says uh the beings that grasp on to
those objects are not liberated and the beings
that uh don't grasp that's the difference it's the the
relationship to experience
um last night last night at at IRC there was this there was this very short Q&A
it's kind of a part of the process of coming out of retreat and um I won't share share the details for
for the person's privacy but there was someone describing something really beautiful they had seen they had seen in
themselves a certain letting go over the course of the retreat they had seen a way that they had been causing suffering
for themselves and that um it was a seemingly wholesome value that they had
but they realized that they were grasping after it really hard
uh and the response that I heard was oh
um instead of holding it like this
you can hold it like this so still keep it
close that's an important value but you can you can you can hold
it close with these Open Hands maybe that's in the same
family so this trajectory
I want to close with some in these verses from the the the book of eights
theava that um I think I think as you hear them
um maybe maybe maybe it can be maybe it's something inspiring to me it's it's
uh it's both inspiring and it it points to the ethical implications of what we're doing the sort of beauty of a free
heart and how a person like that lives in the world uh inspiring maybe because that's
that's the the possibility that's available for us at least in Walking The
Path uh two little bits of explanation before I I share the verses is there are
some there are two there are two very strange Clauses in here if I don't explain there will be question
marks uh one is that it it describes a sage a free person as someone who is
fake less faithless uh I did not understand this
uh until I read the commentary uh and uh the the
understanding is that perhaps it's a person who has gone beyond uh gone beyond having to have
faith in something else because they've been they've been so freed of greed hatred and delusion that they know it
for themselves that the faith doesn't have to be out there does that make sense
and then the other related piece is that they don't free themselves from
Passion because the work has already been done so these uh these verses describe a
stage a free person not clinging to the
Future nor grieving the past they see seclusion in the midst of
sense context and are not Guided by
views they are neither clinging nor deceitful not greedy or
stingy neither impudent nor offensive and don't engage in malicious
speech neither addicted to what's Pleasant nor given to
arrogance gentle and intelligent they are faithless and don't free themselves
from Passion always equanimous and mindful in
this world they don't think of themselves as equal Superior or
inferior they have no swollen Pride depending on
nothing having known the dhma they are
independent they have no craving for becoming and not becoming
I say they are at peace they who are not concerned with sensual
Pleasures they have no bonds and have crossed Beyond
attachments maybe it's enough to just say I say they are at
peace I'm wishing for that for for all of us now and in the future
um maybe to to close with a word of appreciation which is uh as as I've said
in the beginning the middle and now the end uh there's something like arriving
at IMC there is something lovely about being in being in
the field and maybe it has something to do with this that we're we're oriented
toward not grasping or oriented toward not being
malicious or oriented toward peace or being wise about
that and maybe there's something we're doing here that that can uh support us in what's not an easy
world uh not only support us but support us to uh
engage and do that beautifully more like
this so thank you for your attention I think we have a just a few
minutes for um questions if you like or comments
Beautiful Stories thank you I'm curious if that dog you mentioned had Buddha
nature nice nice he didn't say [Music]
thank you so much that was a a beautiful offering I really appreciate it um in the last reading there was a
line that I'd like to know more about which was something to the effect that
to not give up passion but shortly after talking about equinity and um maybe you could talk a
little bit more about that right right I think that's the the line they are
faithless and don't free themselves from Passion and then right after it says always equanimous and mindful in this
world they don't think of themselves as equal Superior or inferior right
yeah uh the the way that I make sense of that that that particular line is it's
the the the same Principle as the faithless point that they they've they
have already freed themselves of when a when we use the word passion here I think I think Gil is translating
Raga which um which is like it's not the sort of passion that
we think of as as a inspiration or even vow or resolve passion it's like
um uh sometimes the Buddha will describe something like the the senses being overtaken with a
fever it's that it's that sort of thing the mind the the mind and the the senses
com yeah just overtaken um sometimes also has this
this uh tone of relishing yeah so that that's I think that's an important distinction when we
we use when we use the English word passion because we we end up losing if we throw if we throw out everything
that's involved in the English word passion we're we're we're losing so much but we're also kind of
missing the distinction I don't know if that's what you're asking though yeah that makes
sense yeah yeah great
great you related to that question so the resolve and inspiration how does
that connect to the yeah to me very isn't it right on
the okay but I think everyone heard me yeah yeah so to repeat the question
maybe for folks online um uh um how does the passionless relate to fa Faith or
can you say it again I got it wrong yeah when you mentioned resolve to me Resolve seems very faithful right and so excuse
me so the faithless how does it connect right right right right thank you for the question um I think um have to
consider it in sequence so uh I think I think
the yeah we have faith in our in where we're headed like when we we put our
energy into resolve because we have faith or confidence that the practice is working this is good but please keep
this up may you all have lots of faith in uh in yourselves in your practice the
way um the way we talk about faith in the faith in uh Buddhist
practice there's this interesting turn where it goes from what they call Bright Faith to uh uh kind of like confirmed
faith and the the mo the move is based on having seen greed in the mind and
then at a later time that greed is not in the mind and then that bolsters your faith
that oh the the practice is working oh look I'm not I'm not consumed with this all the time same for hatred and
delusion anyway uh I think the principle holds that we we we need to have faith in the
fact that the the practice work works and then once you have once you once the
the path has been fulfilled uh you don't have to believe it I think that's I think that's part of the point kind of
like when you arrive at the Grand Canyon no one has to tell you about it anymore or you don't have to believe it's there
because you're looking at it does that make sense
cool there's a question online um the person asks how to attend to how I am
with the moment without too much selfing how to attend to how I am with the moment without too much selfing if they
were here I would ask them if they could say a little bit more about what they notice about the
selfing um I'll see if they respond we'll see if they
respond yeah yeah maybe to try to respond in some
way of course it it can seem uh it can seem like a whole lot of doing and a
whole lot of meing meing me doing the doing if I'm like
tracking uh oh did they did they happen yeah they responded making more of a story
focusing on the story of me making more of a story focusing on the story story
of me yeah it's it's hard to know it's hard to know exactly what's what's meant so
I'll I'll try to respond in some way
um I think there there are two things that I I'd like to note one of them is that
um when we practice when we practice mindfulness say we're practicing mindfulness of the body we're staying
very close to the six sense doors let's say it's actually a great simplification
of experience it it allows them allows the mind to settle on something something
much more simple than our um the the novel of me um or like focusing on like turning
turning to the sight of a glass of water is much more simple uh much more
simple in terms of experience a story about it and part of how part of how
mindfulness practice can work is that by by staying very close keeping our attention very close to the body and
doing that in a way that's steady maybe it's kind um it um it actually softens all
that gripping that creates the self story and then there's room for something else to
come yeah I hope that was semi adequate uh for for what was uh actually needed
great so we're just at time and I want to thank you for your practice this
morning in your attention and uh for being and doing
IMC may we uh may we all have such a beautiful place to practice take care