[Music]
so hello from Spirit Rock i'll be here one more day
tomorrow and uh
delightful kind of comfortably cool kind of foggy cloudy weather the
the clouds the fog should burn off today and we'll have a beautiful blue sky
and um and I'm here for a meditation
retreat so maybe a little bit more than usual i
am kind of I don't know maybe I could say in
love with what it's like to be alive when
I live living close to the world of this this unified
harmonious collected movement in
meditation and I've been reminded here because of one of the co-teers
uh Kairo Jewel Lingo who's a was a nun in the Tiknadhan tradition for 15 years
and before that lived in spiritual communities
about growing up in uh Italy and having and just enough contact with Catholic
monasteries there and um to feel the same kind of
unification coziness warmth kind of centered in my body
um in those monasteries as she has felt and as I feel
here so when we come to this third Janna one characteristic that's
important to keep in mind is that there's no discursive thinking and many
of us understand our life make sense of our life through the thinking mind through having
conversation explaining things to ourselves um understanding connections between
things and it's inconceivable that we could have a rich valuable safe life
without negotiating it through thinking a lot
as we come into the third Janna uh the thinking mind kind of goes
offline however it's not going into a trance uh there's actually a greater
clarity it's kind of like the without the thinking mind the discursive
thinking mind the conversational mind commentarial mind without going quiet and becoming
peaceful there's actually a greater sense of
clarity greater sense of clear knowing a greater sense of u kind of a
certain kind of healthy intelligence that the mind is capable of even though
there's very little content so one of the ways to um kind
of appreciate this thana whether you go into it or not is um the
goodness of nonverbal thinking
most of the knowing most of the conceiving that we have through the day
is not done verbally or in images there's a
deeper there's a deeper uh kind of capacity that humans and
probably animals have to know that does not require a lot of thinking
i suspect that some of you saw the turkeys going by a little while
ago there's an intelligence in them but I suspect they're not thinking
about all kinds of things i don't even know how much there's a past and future
probably some but um so many of the kind of thoughts that
you have um would be inconceivable for a
turkey but the turkey knows
sees and and knows enough to stay alive
so I'm not saying that you be like a turkey but I'm saying that it's kind of built into us that we have a a kind of a
nonverbal knowing a nondiscursive non-con
conversational knowing that in the
uh is called clear recognition
sana and even sati mindfulness or awareness
is a kind of silent awareness more than it is labeling
or verbally recognizing what's happening it's a silent
recognition so this idea of a noble silence is part of moving into the Janna
this beautiful clarity and intelligence so for this sitting perhaps
um you can kind of attune
yourself to how there is a nonverbal clarity nonverbal awareness of
experience that is a doorway for a deeper
intimacy so assuming a meditation posture
kind of maybe rocking back and forth a little bit swaying back and
forth kind of feeling into your posture to feel how to align
it center it have the chest a little bit more open
maybe adjust the head a little bit so there's a lifting at the very back of
the head it's tipping the head forward slightly and creating a little bit more
stretching little bit at the back of the
neck and a good part of the feeling into your posture and adjusting it is
probably happening with a nonverbal
knowing or a very rudimentary verbal knowing very very
simple that's coming from a different place
inside then discursive thinking about stories and events and what should
happen and then in your posture let there be a few
deeper inhales and in a relaxed
way extended exhales
relaxing as you
exhale allowing for relaxation as you exhale and so there's a knowing
nonverbal knowing maybe a kind of
feeling of subtle places in your body that release
relax soften you don't have to think about
them it's enough just that they're known without any comments
allowing your breathing to return to normal and on the exhale
continue to allow the body to
relax no commentary needed
and see if there can be a silent
awareness of your body of the tensions in your
body of the softening in your Ready
and then centering yourself on your breathing maybe if it's possible center
yourself on the grounding place the settling
place deep at the beginning of the inhale and at the end of the exhale
let there be a nonverbal
knowing silent awareness at the end of every
exhale of that settling place grounding place deep within
and as the inhale begins allowing the inhale
to arise spread through your
body where the sense of allowing
is silent no words images
needed receiving the sensations of breathing
in allowing the exhale
and allowing which is also silent it's almost like an
opening up the door window to allow the sensations of exhale
allowing the exhale to
unfold and maybe without discursive
thinking there's no right and wrong with however way you're breathing
there's no project it's
simply a quiet silent knowing of
breath knowing of breathing
from some deep place inside that is
content to rest in a silent knowing silent awareness
[Music]
a silent
awareness that is a bit like being
surrounded by refreshing water pool of water
[Music] floating and thoughts are let go like
bubbles floating to the
surface resting in the
body in the bodies Silent awareness
if there is thinking maybe you can feel how the
thinking has tension in it or
pressure maybe you can understand that here and
now the thinking is not needed
there's a better alternative to trust the
meditation to trust the silent awareness
[Music]
maybe arising out of the body
and if there is anything that's pleasant
delightful about resting here and Now in the
body allowing
receiving whatever is happening into this
nonverbal
knowing this silent awareness that can include
everything no thinking needed
a silent awareness the nondiscursive nonverbal way of
knowing is a way to leave ourselves
alone to not be a project to not be something to judge
it's phenomenally generous and kind to hold ourselves in
awareness without anything extra as if we're our best
friend who's silent silently accompanying
us not commenting or judging or trying to fix us just we know we're not alone
so to sit with this silent awareness of
ourselves as being our own
friend heat
and then learning how to be a friend for all
people the value of accompanying the
world without discursive thinking without
making anything into a project without
judging a silent awareness that has an intimacy a
friendliness a care that allows so much to be
communicated more than words could ever do
to trust the love the kindness the
friendliness that can be there with silence silent
accompanyment with clear
companionship and as we end this
sitting to let the silent awareness spread our goodwill out into
the world may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may others feel
recognize that we're showing up with a simple
friendliness care and kindness for them and for all
beings whether we agree with them or not may all
beings experience profound
well-being so thank you very much and again there's no bell i will
bow in appreciation thanks thank you
so good morning and welcome to this next talk on
samadei and Um and this week we're exploring the
third Janna that is um basically the second and third
are recognized as a form of noble silence and um silence of course in our
society could there could be a dictionary of silence uh all the different meanings what's
conveyed in silence many of it which is not kind and uh sometimes is
offputting but this is called a particular kind of silence called noble
silence um a sil a silent treasure a treasure
silence and um that where it feels cozy it feels
wonderful it feels like um nothing is needed and there's a remarkable thing
that happens when discursive thinking stops conversational thinking stops rumination
stops not not just a few times often for many
people rumination obs obsessing about things with the mind storytelling telling
ourselves stories repeating the same idea over and over again commentating judging
uh having thoughts which are mean or thoughts which are scary or thoughts which
are filled with desires all these limit us all these narrow the
window narrow the wholeness they divide us they keep
us not really deeply in touch in a holistic way with ourselves from the
inside out there's in fact even though thinking can be quite pleasant at times
or quite compelling seemingly very important
uh involves a tremendous sacrifice tremendous loss and um oddly enough sometimes the
people who are most worried about the Buddhist teachings of renunciation letting go which these
janna have a lot to do but letting go in the meditation
The people who are most worried about it most troubled by it are the ones who are
most involved in their thinking mind discursive mind and there's good reason
for that because that's the mind that tells us uh stories about all the things we need and
should have or don't have and all the ways that um you know we've been offended or
hurt and of course thinking is valuable of course some of the things we think about are true
enough but it's unfortunate if it disconnects us from the wholeness of
who we are and some of the deeper capacities of knowing and intelligence
that we have that uh are waiting for us are there kind of below the level of
discursive thinking below the level of conversational thinking
and um and so going into this third Janna it can feel very silent in there
but it's not a silence that is being silenced being ignored it's not a
silence of being disconnected there's a feeling of like
almost a feeling of of uh to be alive is enough someone on this retreat that I'm
teaching ask me very very sincerely and a question of what's the
meaning of life and sometimes if someone asks that questions it's not really
asking for an answer or it maybe too philosophical or something but there was
such a sincerity that this was really important for the person so I was
careful about how I responded so there was an example I was using a kind of
discursive thinking conversation to think about that but it arose from that silent place inside it wasn't arising
from fear or ambition it was more kind of the place where creativity or
intuition arises maybe so I thought about it for a while
and I lived with it for a while and the answer I came back with is that the
meaning of life is to discover the expression of
life what is it that's wants to be expressed what is it that's flowing and
growing and knowing from deep inside that um you you can never know if
you ask answer the question what is the meaning of life with a philosophical answer uh with a answer that even is
logical or um somehow rational or
somehow conceptual um it's like asking someone
um you know if they're involved in some wonderful playing of music or doing a
dance or or maybe just going with for the walk
with a friend in a delightful walk what's the meaning of friendship what's the meaning
of playing music what's the meaning of dance while you're doing
it it's not needed in fact to assign
meaning to it during the activity takes you out of the activity and so to drop in and let the
expression of the music the music making of the dance of the friendship that the
expression of it that is the meaning of life so in the in these deeper genres it
can feel that way there's no need for meaning we're so fully alive so fully
here so fully quieted the discursive ruminating
mind that tells us otherwise it's part of the delight for
it so um so and and it's also very
satisfying to go through this uh process of feeling a lot of joy and happiness in
the first and second Janna and then having the joy quiet and then uh
inviting this very deeper happiness with this deeper embodied happiness again is
not a verbal it doesn't have a verbal source it doesn't have a source from
ideas many people's emotions and sense of happiness and sadness is so dependent
on the thinking mind and whatever direction thoughts go that's the way we feel
and here there's a whole different source for happiness for joy that wells
up from deep inside and um that exists deep inside
that just feels satisfying feels like this is being alive and
uh so uh I want to read the metaphor or the simile for the third
Janna and uh it uses uh in this metaphor uh a pool of water that's cool water and
you have to appreciate that maybe imagine that it's one of the warmest days you've ever been in hottest days
you've ever been in because this was the these metaphors were uh created in India
in the hot climate of India it was um in the Buddha's enlightenment Buddha i
think I was there in June it was the hot season it was the hottest season boy
there's no one else there it was so hot and um and the Buddha didn't get enlightened in the peak of the hot
season but he was he was getting close to it when he was sitting under the bodhic tree there
and um and in the context of a very hot day it's just a delight to go into and
soothing and satisfying to go into a cool pool of water and so it's in that
context you'll see that coolness is used uh as part of the metaphor and lotus flowers are used and
lotus flowers can be quite beautiful and so it's a it's a metaphor for something that's quite beautiful in ourselves in
our experience so the third Janna is like a pool filled with blue
lotuses or red lotuses or white lotuses where some of the blue red and
white lotuses would be born in the water would grow in the water would be
nourished by the water without ever rising up above the water above the
surface the cool water would fill pervade saturate and permeate those
lotuses from their tips to their roots so no part of the blue red or white lotuses
would not be touched with cool water
so the practitioner pervades and saturates and permeates
this body with happiness
freed of joy so that no part of the body is not
touched so a couple of things about this simile i just find it delightful this expression
um the uh this body is permeated with happiness freed of joy have you ever
heard of such a thing um why would you want to free yourself from
joy and because there's a happiness which is better
uh sick pure happiness in a very deep embodied satisfying way uh lacks the the
excitement the thrill of uh of joy and of course that thrill and
excitement is quite wonderful at first um but if it goes on and on and on and
on it's exhausting it's tiring and so to be able to drop into this deeper state of
happiness and the metaphor is one of being immersed in the water cool
refreshing water when I was young we lived by the
seashore and uh excuse me I lived by the seashore and I spent a
lot of time in the summer not only in the water but under the water uh I I had
a snorkels and mask and I would dive under the water maybe to about six feet
or so five six feet and flip myself over my back and try to stay down there as
long as I could uh and there were gentle waves coming in uh in the sea that I was
at and I'd be underneath looking up at the waves coming into the shore and it
was so delightful to be down there there was this wonderful silence there was
this wonderful being kind of enveloped uh hugged it was kind of like being all
cozy in a nest perhaps or cozy in a nice
uh comforterfilled bed or something and
um and uh the world was had disappeared down there um the world of expectations
the world of needs the world of comparing myself to others and wanting
things to be different the world was so still and quiet down there so satisfying
um and it felt I felt more alive on my back under the water looking up than I
did almost any other time no part of my body was not touched by this wonderful
environment of the water so as we go into these deep absorption absorptive
states many people will actually use the simile of dipping underwater briefly or
a while uh when they're in these deep absorption and then if they come out it
feels like they're surfacing out of it and uh there was a time in my practice where I would go into these
deep states and that I needed to felt like I needed to just kind of make sure
everything was okay that I wasn't straining or things were that I knew the
time i knew my environment and I would surface out of the water and check out
what was going on make sure everything was good and then I would dip down back
in and then in this state everything we experience all the
sensations whatever we it goes on feelings any feeling goes on uh is
seen as beautiful is seen as kind of wonderful like lotuses each thing is distinct each
thing is its own thing floating in this water so you might feel sensations of breathing and it's just delightful like
it's its own lotus floating in the water you might even feel
some happiness sensations of happiness different parts of the body
anything and uh and there's a silent knowing a silent awareness nonverbal
knowing of all this it's tremendous clarity and now you don't you're not
thinking about it but you know it you come out of it you might think about it some but not in this state
so uh I hope that this metaphor and these words give you a feel a sense
maybe through your imagination of what it's like and um and if uh the idea of
being in a pool of water is not welcoming for you maybe there's some other way another metaphor that you have
that can be comparable um one of the first times I experienced this kind of thing was uh going into a
thousand-year-old chapel in France and um and just it was on top of
a m little hill and being in that chapel I was
enveloped by a kind of goodness a kind of peace that was new to me
so the second Janna thank you
um I hope that
um you somehow go through the day exploring
considering feeling into the ways in which you can have nonverbal
knowing the ways that awareness mindfulness can be silent and that you
find that very satisfying so thank you very much