as Martha said um I was just asked to uh give this talk uh yesterday uh because
Anushka was feeling ill and um so um so
I just want to send my good wishes all her good wishes to Anushka that she feel better soon
um so um so the Buddhist said I teach one
thing and one thing only suffering and the end of suffering
and um and in the practice um he points out to the um these three roots of suffering
that we all have uh greed hatred and delusion and all our afflictive mental
states arise from those three qualities uh from u greed you know that
includes all the hatred and all the um all the minor irritations we have um I I
mean uh aver did I say hatred okay I think I said the wrong word so greed
includes all the desires we have obviously and hatred all the you know
huge variety of ill will that we have in the world you know and uh delusion is
kind of our obliviousness to what's really happening at any given moment um
which anybody who's looked at their own minds um has found a lot of that right
um and so um you know these deeply
influences in everything we do how we respond to each other how we react in
the world um but but the one thing is that within each one of these
forces is the seed for transforming into wisdom it's like the desire that we have
that the greed we have is that same force that says God I want to be free of the suffering so within each one there's
that seed um the the thing that pushes away everything you know I hate that i I
don't want that that's irritating that's the same seed that allows us to see how
to how to train the mind in being wholesome um and within delusion is the
the quality of you know you walk in you know nothing matters you know everything
you know you know step on the puddle you don't even notice your feet are wet um and you know that that leads to has the
seed for equinimity for a very um sweet state that it notices the puddle but
doesn't get upset about it if we made a mistake so in each one of those roots is
also the healing of that root and today I'll focus on um the root
of uh hatred and the transformation of hatred into
wisdom um so I'll start with you know um a
metaphor that many of you have heard I know uh but I but it's um it's so um
makes a point that I really like to use it uh in Buddhist psychology you know we
often call the um these three personality types um uh greed hatred and
delusion uh as the desire type the um aversion type and the delusion type and
it just means that in our personalities those forces are a little bit more prominent and the metaphor we use
um is um you know um imagine that we're going to a party of um you know some
wealthy people and uh the desired type walks in and there's this awesome view i
mean really beautiful beautiful view and they're just like wow this is amazing
but within moments the mind says um I want that and you know I want to buy a
house just like this where I can have that kind of view and maybe I should change my my job and get a better job
and make more money and and and you know that view is no longer appreciated or
seen right um the aversion type walks in and they see the stain in the corner on
the carpet um they you know they look over at the food food trays you know and
God it's just full of junk food you know and and the music is just oh you know
how could they pick that kind of music and don't get me started on the guests you
know and um the the delusion type walks in kind
of oblivious to everything and including the fact that there was a huge sign at the door that said "Please take off your
shoes." And um and everybody else took off their shoes and they're all in their stockings feet and and they just walk
right in with their shoes you know so these are like these stereotypes or these personality types it's way
oversimplified but we all have all of them in some way or the other just
sometimes some personalities predominate one over the other um
um so you know these um these uh roots
are referred to as the torments of the mind you know and um they're ready to
torment us incredibly quickly and um and I'll give you an
example you know um early in my practice um my husband and I had been discussing
you know we went to dharmat talk and we're discussing the topic of letting go of attachments
um you know and we've been kind of discussing different aspects of letting go of attachments over a couple of days
and um and you know I woke up the next morning and I was in a really good mood you know and I was really looking
forward to my fresh cup of coffee and um I had in my hand and I was just about to
take a sip uh when my husband just grabs it out of my
hand and like that you know I went from a great mood to really pissed
off and and um you know and it's like all three defilements showed up you
right I wanted that coffee desperately i was really angry and I was really
completely delusional and not seeing the huge grin on his face right he didn't
mean it you know it was he was just teasing but he sure that was his way of continuing the
conversation about clinging um so um so you know the
the first step for for really uh
creating this transformation is recognizing aversion
hatred ill will all those different forms when it shows up
and it's amazing how often we don't see it i mean if we're really angry we kind
of know it um but uh it can take so many forms like just
resistance you know just a simple resistance you know walking into somewhere we don't want to be resistance
resistance we're not happy right um uh we can have uh very strong emotions you
know like like getting pissed off over the coffee or you know something's just not warm enough the coffee just isn't
warm enough we have all these little things that aversion shows up and those
of you who just sat for the last 35 minutes probably had a little bit of version show up at some point you know
where you know maybe the breath wasn't quite to our liking and instead of just noticing oh that's a rough breath you
know we're like you know okay let me make it better let me fix it there's something to fix you know so these these
habits of mind of resisting what's unpleasant are very very strong in us
um and you know half of our lives uh I
don't know if it's half but a really large months of our life uh includes
unpleasant experience right how much of the time do you go outside and the
weather is perfect you know you're dressed just right there's no chill it's not it's just just the right temperature
you get more of that in California but um but but still You know it's like uh
oh I I should put something warmer on you know just these little very let me turn on the air conditioner you know how
many of us just turn on the air conditioner for the minor minor unpleasantness sometimes uh or turn on
the heat when it's just just minorly unpleasant you know we're so in the habit of trying to always find the most
comfortable um and um Oops excuse me
getting trapped here um you know so if we look at our at our
life you know one of the things that I I learned um on retreat um you know in
retreat when we go on on the inside retreats we usually have like a work
meditation and um you know my first several retreats my work meditation was chopping vegetables which is really I
really enjoyed that uh but the next retreat was cleaning toilets you know
and it's a oh what a bummer you know I just wasn't happy about it but it was
one of the most wonderful practices because you know you're committed to being mindful to doing the job
mindfully and it's very very different if we clean a toilet resentfully we
clean it like okay let me do it and try to get it over with as quickly as possible um or you clean it mindfully
and to the point where wow this is really fun i'm enjoying cleaning the toilet you know I didn't think that was
possible um and it completely changed my relationship to the things we do at work
you know it's not that there wasn't sometimes an unpleasant smell you know or um or it was awkward or there was
something I didn't like about it but there was a way that we can show up for
that that doesn't darken our hearts that doesn't contract us you know we can be
doing the same activity and do it happily or do it miserably
so um so ill will can be described as an
unfriendly or hostile disposition it can be towards anything
anything at all you know we often think of it as towards people you know hatred towards people but um since we hate
ideas right there's lots of ideas these days we hear on the news that that
hatred can arise um we hate um uh
emotions that we don't like we hate uh physical sensations we
don't like and we can hate objects um you know an example um
um you know this is like decades ago um someone gave me this um uh uh a potter a
potter gave me um a a head you know and it was like kind of ugly and devilish
looking but it was kind of interesting you know and so you know I put on the mantle you know and um another friend
came over and picked it up and go and they dropped it and broke it
they were so repelled by it you know they had so much aversion that they
dropped it but we respond to objects that way too it's a m you know we can you know hate anything
right um you know another way that
um you know the verse of mind tends to um uh focus on what we don't like right
on what we don't like what what we disapprove of um but also it tends to
give that too much meaning so we can notice the stain on
the carpet but but we add we make it really important you know we can notice a chunk
food i mean you know no matter how how quantumous we are we still notice the chunk food yeah but we don't have to
contract our hearts around it and one way of of uh an example that that for me
is very uh poignant of how we do that you know when uh we're teenagers you
know and and um uh you get a pimple a little pimple on the face you know just
this one little pimple and you look in the mirror but what you actually see is 95% pimple right you know and I know
that from experience and um you know so we
overemphasize the the what's wrong with things the unpleasant
um you know for some of us aversion arises most easily with physical pain
um but I've seen minor discomforts be just
as irritating as as pushing against them um you know an itch you know uh have
have you I hope you've all had the the privilege of experiencing a really
strong itch and living through it you know but also living through it
mindfully mindfully you know with like oh that's unbearable well let's see if
it is unbearable you know and really not scratching it just hanging with it and
watching that strong strong sensation that feels unbearable
uh move through us and that's really the heart of the practice you can do all of the practice
of working with hatred in this in that way with that we can do with an itch and
so we can't do with an niche we're going to have a really hard time doing it with anything else anything really big so can
we do it with an itch before we try to do it with um maybe some political
figure we have less and friendly feelings towards um
um the other thing about anger is and um maybe some of you have experienced this
is that anger can sometimes be a motivator and um it brings up a lot of
energy right and so sometimes people get you know not only anger but aversion and
you know the the whole when I say anger I mean the whole realm of of u kind of
hostile energy that we might have and um it can motivate us to do things uh but
it's not a healthy source of energy and it actually ends up exhausting us it's
hard on our bodies and it's also not a sustainable
energy uh but we might be in the habit of using that to get our
energy you using stress to get our energy uh it's a little bit like um you
know when I was in school I'd wait till the last minute to study you know because I'd be so stressed you know my
my all the hormones were going through my body i had lots of energy to study uh
not the healthiest energy to study but but that's so that's what I got used to
but we can get even better energy much better energy from
inspiration from um enthusiasm inspiration really wonderful feelings
uh but so so there is another source for that strength in us uh besides that I
mean anger makes us feel strong when we feel weak you know which can be really helpful when you're um you know fighting
the tiger right you know you want that extra physical strength but when we're
um just living a life you know living in a city like this living uh you know with
family and friends and work and and you know we uh we don't need that level of
um anger to get our energy
um so the way we practice with this in meditation is when those feelings arise
any feelings of aversion of irritation um there's usually a story
there's something that irritated us or something that we're angry about and we
turn our attention away from the story not rejecting it pushing away but just
shifting the attention to how we feel in the body that's also happening in the moment what's happening in the moment
what is it like to be angry you know what at this moment it's not always the
same at this moment it's not an intellectual thing okay I know what happens when you get angry but it's in
this moment what does it feel like in my gut what does it feel like in my body you know um some people you know their
hands just tighten they grasp their knees some people their bellies get really tight uh some people a lot of
things get tight um so what is the experience like in our bodies you know
what's the experience of sadness in our bodies what's the experience of any strong emotions we have in our bodies um
so the story you know we don't if we don't need to feed that story we feed
the body that's being present with what's happening
um you know the stories are a fuel to the unh wholesome
emotion um Joseph Goldstein said um aversion is transformed by interest you
can't push away what's happening and take an interest in it at the same time
right um it's another example
um you know some you know um many years ago um a friend was supposed to pick me
up from work and they forgot about me you know and I'm standing out there you
know it's getting to be dusk you know and and uh they're not showing up and of
course it was the days before cell phones and you know so I couldn't text them or reach them you know and I was
really angry you know I got really really angry and um you know and After
my anger subsided a bit then I started um you know uh thinking about okay you
know arranging to get a ride home you know and I found a a place to make a phone call and I took care of it and by
the time I got home I was pretty mellow you know I forgot all about it i started you know putting around the house doing
stuff um but when my husband got home much later uh I told him what happened
and and I got just as angry as when it had happened just retelling the story
retelling the story and you know and then really consider how often we retell
stories about our childhood or regrets or um you know or or things that just
happened um you know how often do we do that in our minds we tell the stories so
when we see that we're telling ourselves a story that's triggering these unh wholesome feelings
um you know it's it's just a habitual story you know this is just as real this
is just as authentic the story is not any more real than than what's happening
in our bodies right now um so the instructions are simple drop
the story go to the body
um you know and uh even though I know I mentioned the three three personality types humans tend to have a negativity
bias you know where uh we have the tendency to notice what's wrong with things and that's part it's what helps
us survive you know if we're out for a walk you know and to see a beautiful
sunset and we're uh really enjoy you know enjoying it and there's a tiger you
know we want to focus on the tiger not on the sunset right that's dangerous you
know so we're we tend to have that that little bit of a negativity bias uh but
it often kind of bleeds into the rest of our lives where uh we keep noticing we
meditate and we know you know my focus on what's wrong with our meditation what's wrong with us instead of how am I
right this moment what's happening right now you know but um um how the kind of attention
um we give this uh negative experiences we have is what is what transforms the
practice you know so we can give very kind attention I like the term affection
of curiosity you know so when anger rises it's not pretty right it's not pretty to
see anger to see hatred in ourselves but what happens when we give it affection or
curiosity ah this is what anger is like oh it hurts it hurts
Um and and this is actually a tool for developing
wisdom and um the ability to see what's
wrong it's also can also be used it's it's a it's an important aspect of the
mind that sees what's wrong it sees the tiger it sees the sunset it sees the
difference it's not oblivious um so in in pi we called
wisdom pa
um it refers to the deep understanding of reality a very deep deep
understanding of reality that's not an intellectual understanding but it's an understanding and insight that comes
from from practicing deeply and it's an understanding that
frees our hearts that actually allows us to be really at peace with our lives and
be at peace with the world um one aspect of wisdom is the ability
to see in any situation what's what decisions we make
that are going to be helpful and move us towards happiness and what decisions we
make that are not helpful and move us towards further suffering that seems intellectual it seems pretty obvious
right but it's actually it's amazing how often we make the the choice of moving
towards more suffering the habits of mind that makes continuous suffering
that feed our suffering uh like doom scrolling right it's not a habit that makes us happy and
yet a lot of us are stuck on those little devices um supporting and and strengthening or
ability to be to suffer ability to be unhappy
um subversion tends to divide things um what I want what I don't want what I
like what I don't like them and us um you know when we give too much
attention uh to what's wrong than to other aspects of them um uh it's a very that that
dividing of things creates more tightness and contraction in our hearts
but the same ability to see the differences between things can also
mature into what we call discerning wisdom so instead of saying that's what
I like that's what I don't like that's what I want that's what I don't want we
change the quality of that to oh this is helpful and this is unhelpful and that's
huge that that little bit of difference is is huge it's a heart that's at peace
you know it's like yeah we're in a difficult situation challenging situation how can I help what can I do
to help right now and uh you know we're in a uh you know
and we drop what's unhelpful um you know we may not like
the pain in our back i don't know they say one out of four people have chronic pain in any given moment so I know that
some of you have experienced some pain this last sitting uh but we can see that
when we pay attention we can see that our resistance to it or aversion to it the bad mood
um it doesn't help at all so the pain can be there and we can
have give it kind attention and it actually improves the sensations of pain they found that when
the mind is at peace uh the the sensations of pain are decreased
um and a different aspect of aversion um again this is a personal story in my
very early days of practice and I was at a board meeting you know and board
meetings you know um well I won't say anything I I'll I won't go
there my favorite thing to do um you know but I always was really good at
noticing what was wrong with a plan you know people bring up plans that always notice all the faults in it you know and
um And I wasn't shy about expressing my opinion and um but it seemed to me that
my role often was um to burst someone's bubble you know people come up with
these enthusiastic ideas great ideas that were really full of holes right and
and of course you know I would I would say give those holes and you know and
you know didn't make me very likable um and you know I felt resentful about it
contracted righteous you know and I rarely left those meetings feeling
good um but as I got to become more familiar with the inner workings of my
mind I began to see that you know it's really good to be able to see the holes
in things it's really able to see what's wrong with things i mean this is it may
not be a tiger but uh but that's going to fail if we do it that way right uh
but I didn't have to do that with a contracted heart i could do that with uh
with a lot of kindness and equinimity and um and and with time you know I
learned uh to express myself it it was useful uh but it also made collaboration
fun you know which I'd never gone to a meeting or been involved in something
like that that was actually fun you know and I love collaborating with others now it's it's really great you know
different ideas pushing back and forth no not that way this way but it but done
in in with a really friendly open heart
um okay
you know in inside practice we call that tool that we use to to u noticing what's
helpful and not helpful investigation and you know we often talk
about investigation in med in inside practice you know investigating the moment investigating the breath um and
for instance um you know the really obvious practical thing is you know it
shows it the the difference uh between when the muscles are relaxed and when
they're tense right you know it's the investigation of the moment that lets us
see um I remember when I first start meditating I you know I first time I
realized I'd been sitting for like 15 minutes with my shoulders like this you know maybe some of you have had that
that insight right the insight into how we hold our bodies um you know and you
know sometimes the tension in the face you know the frowning and the all these habits you know and so we slowly use
that tool of investigation oh what's really happening here oh that's not helpful i can drop that oh that's
helpful i I can do more of that um you know in particular you know how
many of you have gone distracted right um you know in meditation right and so
sometimes you know I've gotten really lost and then I kind of see what I'm getting lost in you know it's like a
fantasy I'm really enjoying you know I go I want to keep going so I I caught it
but I keep going right I'm so seduced by it you know and you know and the
investigation said you know says well you know here I am meditating what am I doing let's go back to meditation you
can fantasize anytime you know and it's like oh okay you know that attachment but that's
the practice it's like that's what we address the root of all our suffering is that clinging that clinging I just got
to keep going in that fantasy just got to do it you know that's what we're addressing in practice and that
flexibility of dropping the story and going and going back and doing it in a
kind manner it's like not putting down on ourselves that we just got distracted uh that we just spent the last 20
minutes of the meditation you know um you know planning a vacation you know and so yeah so we're
back home great wonderful kind attention that's what the clinging does you know
it's it's uh what we see how our minds work um and it's really easy easy to
investigate the quality of our minds at any given moment you know are we having
a kind attitude or an attitude of ill will for a really long time longer than
I want to than I want to say um I every time I came back to my breath
when I was distracted I would feel like I had just failed and so my attitude was like I
blew it i blew it back to the breath i blew it and it didn't never occur to me
that that that journey between waking up
and getting back to my breath was really essential it was reinforcing
uh something really unh wholesome in me and I started taking that journey waking up oh great i'm awake and I'd come back
to the breath with just a lot of kindness and in a warm field of course that's what the mind does that's why I'm
that's why I practice because the mind wants to you know play or or you know u
delve in the mud you know of the mud for of the things we don't like or or whatever things you know take us away
um so there are two aspects um um two ways that we primarily develop
wisdom you know there sometimes we call them two wings you know one of them is
the idea of letting go when something unh wholesome is happening and the other
is the idea of um cultivating whatever's wholesome and just by meditating daily
the the practice uh we learn to develop some calm and some tranquility
and calm and tranquility allows us to see um you know we have so much more
room to see when aversion and when these uh any of the defilements show up any of
these torments of mind show up and so we're able to see them and and it takes
the nourishment out of them in a moment of calm any moments of calm and peacefulness are moments where we're not
feeding those roots where those roots start um you know
shrinking and the other the other u side is the side of letting go and you know
the the standard metaphor is if you're holding on to hot coal you're just going to drop it because you recognize it
right you know you don't have to think about maybe I should drop the hot coal what do you think is that wise or not
you know we're just going to drop it and and the same thing with in our minds what happens often we just don't
recognize that we're holding on we don't recognize that we're how tight we're
holding on um and so we can lean in the direction
of letting go and um but we can't force ourselves
to be calm and we can't force ourselves to let go
we can you know maybe with a muscle we can go okay I can drop it but um maybe
you've had this experience of in meditation where um uh you know the
teacher says let go and nothing happens you know uh you know we're just
still all tied up in knots you know and um I remember uh you know uh early in
practice one of my sittings you know I just had an argument with a friend you
know right before coming to a group like this you know it was just like I was like really agitated you know and um and
I spent the first part of the sid you know I'm just thinking about all the justifications and and all the things I
should have said and that I can still say and and and then the teacher is doing a guided meditation and they're
going relax the body relax the you know and and it's like you know how do you
relax i can't let go how do you relax when you can't let go how do you let go when you can't let go you know and um
you know and I I practice with this you know many many times but but as I
continued to practice with it I saw that I could incline my mind towards letting
go it wasn't going to let go instantly but I could incline in that direction
and what it meant was that um when sometime you know when I had a
choice of uh spending the next five minutes rehearsing my arguments I could
choose not to do that right you know and still there'd be this tightness in my heart this you know but I'm just
inclining the mind and I saw that the part of the nature of the mind is that
um a lot of the work of the mind happens underneath And uh the experience for instance if
you've seen um maybe you've had the experience of um having to get up really
early in the morning and um much earlier than usual and setting an alarm clock
and then waking up right before the alarm clock you know you know it's have happened to me many times i stopped
setting alarm clocks um and um and the
subconscious is is doing the work the subconscious so when we incline the mind
you know I we can begin to trust that that's enough sometimes that's what we can do right now that's what's happening
right now and um you know we c as I said we can't force ourselves to let go you
know we can do some things you know but you know the the metaphor a flower
blooms in its own time you can't pull the petals open but they'll open if we nourish them if
we water it we nourish it and we nourish it with our intentions you know we nourish our
hearts with our intentions my intentions to let go of suffering my intentions is
to let go of the anger of the story you know so I can see it clearly so I can
respond with an open heart with an easeful heart
um so wisdom arose arises naturally when we pay
attention you know everything there is to know that's important in our lives is
right here it's right in these bodies and these minds and these hearts and by
paying really close attention and developing our attention um we can
release um you know uh release the these roots these things you know and allow
them in their own time to free themselves um you know as we settle the minds in
meditation we start seeing things much more clearly instead of being filtered
by preconceptions by our ideas by our judgments you know we start really
seeing the process of how our minds and bodies work um but what's really the
deeper aspects of this practice is that as mindfulness becomes more penetrating
as we train the mind and where we're really able to see the nature of reality
um you know we can see intimately how experience comes and goes we all know
that everything in life is impermanent right we've known that for a long time nothing lasts right um but this is a
experiential level we can get to where we it's like deep in our bones when you
really see that nothing nothing nothing lasts uh there's nothing you can hold on
to right you know and um you know in the intellectual area we still try to hold
on to everything right you know we're going to keep that relationship we're going to keep that you know keep the
food the fridge full all the time you know the whatever it is that that we we
grab on to um and it becomes clear that no
experience we ever ever have is going to give us lasting
happiness you know it's going to give us any kind of sense of lasting satisfaction
so our experiences in our life no matter how wonderful the trip is no no matter
how how wonderful the relationship is no matter how wonderful uh the the vista is
you know it's never going to last give us lasting happiness so to
look for happiness in the conditions that change all the time that won't
fulfill us to keep looking there is the recipe for suffering for continued
suffering and um you know and then we can still see or might see our
limitations or imperfections but we don't have to believe that they define who we are
they're just part of the changing landscape of our lives and we can begin to know a
happiness that doesn't insist on things being just
right that doesn't insist that things be the way we want them you know and that's the fruits of
this practice you know the the being really at home in this world in our
lives um and the last thing you know this this kind of wisdom comes from here from
within from ourselves even though a teacher might say some wise words you
know the dharma the books talks everywhere we get you know there's tremendous amount of wisdom but still it
all comes from here from developing our own hearts and minds with the practice
from freeing the heart and mind so thank you very much for listening