it's really fun to read these greetings from all over the world welcome everyone
welcome to Friday I've really been enjoying this week of practice with you in finding
support for the beautiful Som teachings that Gil has been offering
us and uh also a little bit more time for silent meditation in the morning for
Discovery throughout the day to help build the cultivation of this
practice so uh today one aspect of this
uh of mind that may appear in this cultivation is
spaciousness exploring a bit about how spaciousness uh matters in the
development of somat or may enter in uh one way that it
is uh experienced is giving plenty of room and time for this
development not crowding it with our expectations of what is supposed to
happen or when and it you know our expectations and our hurry actually will
get in the way it's pretty much guaranteed that expecting something to happen the way you've heard it from
someone else um is or or being in some kind of hurry to acquire or attain
samadi or the janas or any meditative State uh that pretty much guarantees
it's not going to happen because that striving tenses us up and makes it more
difficult it's a little bit like sitting a 2-year-old child down to rationally
explain why they shouldn't be upset and why they should calm down when they're
in middle of having a tantrum a 2-year-old's brain is not
developmentally ready to be rational when they want what they
want so when you're doing a cultivation of some it's also a kind of cultivating
developmental Readiness in your practice for a collected settled mind
and you can't force that development before the mind is ready uh the mind is going through
phases of showing you how it needs to uh
be seen the conditioning that may subtly be causing dissatisfaction and suffering
that you haven't yet seen where there's stress where there's resistance the Mind
needs you to see that before it can settle into some
another way we might think of spaciousness or experience
spaciousness is through a physical and a mental sense of just how vast and
all-encompassing the mind can be the Mind Body can feel very expansive
and receptive to any experience that comes
along it's as if the Mind had been like a crowded room there are so many people
you could only get a vague sense of them or get to know just a couple of people
as contrasted with an empty room where uh you and another you might
enter the room and another person might enter and you might be able to see them and get to know them with much more
clarity so the key I would say the most important thing of all is not trying to
make anything happen instead being present for what
shows Itself by paying attention remaining aware or returning to awareness again
and again starting with the breathing in a very clear way not just
some vague sense of things but very clearly so with that as a few opening
comments said let's settle
in allowing plenty of time plenty of
room for arriving here in the sense of how
the body is right now
paying attention to what wants to be known and seen in the body
time to both allow for relaxation where that can happen and for
softening around or bringing any ease that's
possible to any area of of
chronic
sensation room for recognition too of how the body is showing
us what is happening emotionally perhaps what's going on in the
mind acknowledging
it offering all of it perhaps some deeper longer breaths
allowing the inhalation to bring energy into the
body in the exhalation to release anything that wants to be released
and settling into whatever is normal breathing for you right now
gently bringing the attention to the arising of the
inhalation following it through the body
allowing any pauses that
happen and following the release of the
exhalation noticing how quiet how still the attention can
be while following this beautiful cycle of the breath
and if it's supportive bringing in counting of the breathing in whatever
way you've discovered helps best to keep you with the breath
present with the movement of breathing the
sensations very very softly in the background
the counting as a support
allowing such a light touch with all of
this that perhaps you can feel the extra
space the room that you have for
it e
the breathing arising from ample spaciousness around
us
and releasing into that vast
space
e
e e
receiving what ever is arising
perhaps coming up alongside
any else that's showing up for a few
moments and gently returning awareness to the
breathing to the support in the background of the
counting everything can be received
everything respected there's plenty of space for it
all
e
e e
and in the final minutes of the
sitting from any
Stillness calm
Simplicity steadiness spaciousness that's been here
with us May there
arise nourishment for everyone in this
s and for the worlds of people and beings around each of
us may there be
safety May there be health
wellbeing may all beings have
ease peace freedom from
suffering allowing that to arise from the Stillness and flow to all beings around
us e
for
there can be a sense of spaciousness in this cultivation when
the mind is finally quiet it shows us by contrast how much
is usually crowding the mind vying for our attention
and with spaciousness can come more equinity there's room for any experience
to be received to be understood as things as they've come to be in this
moment a natural result of the causes and conditions that preceded
and knowing that that can change so we have another opportunity
today to notice as we continue to practice and cultivate mindfulness the
partner Sati the partner of samadi this mindfulness in daily life
can show us when the mind is more relatively more
spacious and when the mind is getting constricted or tightened around
something we can notice what preceded that state of mind if we check in from
time to time during the day with our state of
mind just seeing um by paying clear attention we can see that the contracted
mind is not the automatic result of a busy schedule it's possible to be quite busy
to have a lot to do and maybe you've had the experience at times of settling into
a very pleasant state of focus or flow with what you were doing by contrast you may know from
experience that there may be a time that you have plenty of time on your hands
and yet the mind is still ruminating planning worrying
doing active very busy so discovering what actually leads
to spaciousness or to contraction is a little bit of a journey
to look forward
to having spaciousness in meditation and during
the day gives us a little more Breathing Room a little more ability to step back
to pause and to receive what's happening with some level of
respect it's really helpful to do this in moments when we uh stop during the day and find that the mind is getting
constricted or a little too close to something one recommendation I've heard
involves uh deliberately introducing more space into
meditation or even daily life uh for example if one is stuck on a pain in the
body you know feeling really tightened around it and just keep keep coming back to feeling the pain suffering from the
pain it's possible to introduce the idea of more space around it so for example
think of that pain in the context of the space in the entire building you're sitting in or from a th000 feet above as
though a eagle were flying over and looking at the pain at times when I've
really found uh persistent pain difficult I've backed all the way out into space and looked at it it's an
interesting experience to take any thing that we're tightened around and see it
from that perspective so today one invitation throughout the day might be to notice
stop and notice what the quality of mind is and what preceded
that and to feel the effects in the body also uh to continue to check in
during the day with any sense of calm with the breathing with any Stillness
within as a support as well and uh there will be again one
final 4M silent sitting on zoom and you can find the link on the IMC calendar on
the homepage find the zoom link and find the pass password there I just want to
thank you for a delightful week of practice it's been really great to be with this beautiful songa and I wish
everyone here freedom from suffering and a lot of freedom spaciousness and joy
throughout the day be well everybody bye