good morning and good morning to all of you
uh it's it's really lovely to be here and I have a few friends that are here
and it lifts my heart but it doesn't diminish the affection I
feel for all of you that I don't know who are here spending
this time meditating together and practicing the dharma it is a delight so
I want to be sure to mention that because perhaps the lifting that I feel
from my friends makes it more likely that I see that I share an affection for
all of you and it is that that I want to talk about today
how how do our views the views that we have
influence our experience and what does that mean how does that affect who we
are how we are how we practice whether we suffer
so in uh in wise view one of the first
factors of the eight-fold path one of the one of the goals is to be
able to see clearly that's the only part of that biography I really like
um that that that that is my goal in life is to be able to see really clearly
and if we're going to see clearly it's crucial that we see the color of
the lens that we're looking through it's crucial that we know what our
prejudices and biases are how how we are viewing the world
why we have views is influenced by how we're seeing how we're looking where
we're looking otherwise we are subject to delusion so one one
piece that uh got me started on this idea was a a briefing that I got an
email i get a lot of really horrible emails but one of them every day uh
during the week I get a briefing from Nature magazine and it has a list of you
know the latest things that people have found in all realms of science it kind of keeps me from forgetting entirely
that there's something else going on in the world besides news and so in this scientific news today there was an
article or this week there was an article about the coffer illusion some of you may know what this is but
basically it's an optical illusion and it it was done by a man in uh San Francisco actually created by a man in
San Francisco uh that is made up of a whole series of
well most people see squares
the estimate is 97% of people see squares when they look at this i saw
squares when I looked at this but some people see circles
some people see circles now the article was about there are lots of theories about why people see squares or circles
the article was about some psychologists who have been linking this to
conditioning visual conditioning of how how we raised so so if you see squares
their theory is that you see that because you're used to assembling your
life your your buildings your streets everything's kind of on a grid we like
we like we see preferentially squares structures that are at right
angles to one another but they tested some people in a village
in Africa who who live in huts round huts and they
have round corral that they keep their animals in and they see circles
now after staring at the illusion for a while I was able to see the circles and
now I can rapidly go back and forth between them but I always see the squares first
you put it up in front of me I see the squares and I look and I can find the circles i know exactly how to do it now
my mind knows how to make that shift and I can go back and forth at will
now what's interesting is that one of the things I noticed when I was
first reading about this was that I wanted to be able to see those circles that I wanted to be somebody who saw the
circles i wanted to be in that 3% i noticed that trend toward exceptionalism
i want to be exceptional i want to see the circles
interesting to see that this is what our practice is
in order to see what is guiding what we're doing we na need to be able to
understand what are our mind habits what are the things that we typically default
to where do we go when we look at somebody when we see something now I'm
speaking mostly of optical illusions but it can apply to anything it can apply to
I feel unsettled right away i need to know why I'm feeling unsettled excuse me
i want to know why I'm feeling unsettled what I can do about it how can I fix it
it takes a lot of practice to just stay with unsettled
because it's uncomfortable and we we don't like that we want to be comfortable
now what I want to emphasize is there's nothing good or bad no judgment applied
to any of this the fact that I see squares doesn't mean
anything about me except I see squares in fact
there are no actual squares or circles in the illusion they're just sticks of different lengths
arranged on a page and it's called coffer because the squares appear to be
indented like you could put something in them in into the little recesses of the squares
but they're just sticks or light or shades whatever you call it the reality
of it there are neither squares nor circles but the perception is that there are
squares or circles and and the predominant perception is that there are squares
it's really crucial to understand how that affects our experience
not just because of that page but because everything that we experience has that feature
of being influenced by where you're coming from and what you're looking for
and what you're familiar with we are conditioned by the familiar
that's a large part of seeing actually we can't typically see things that we're not used to seeing
it's quite difficult we miss stuff we just miss it
so I'm going to read you a quote by uh Andrew Alenski who wrote a book called Untangling Self that's where this is
from the truth is we like our preferences and prejudices
we like defining ourselves in terms of what we like and don't like
it's precisely desire's entanglement with the sense of self that makes this all so difficult to unravel
fortunately there's a relatively easy and accessible way to counter the powerful forces of desire the
cultivation of equinimity every moment of mindfulness is also a
moment of equinimity it is not a disengagement from the object of awareness but rather the full
and complete engagement with it it is engaging with the breath or with
the feeling tone or with a thought without also either wanting it to stay as it is or wanting it to be different
than it is end of quote so the truth is we like our
preferences and prejudices
we define ourselves in terms of what we like or don't like you know we're
constantly saying "Well I'm somebody who does this i'm somebody who believes this
and you're somebody who believes that." Because we have ideas and prejudices and
beliefs about other people based on totally arbitrary things they could just
be sticks and we're seeing squares
or you could be frowning and I could decide oh you don't like what I'm saying
and you're really frowning because your knee hurts
but I don't know that and I interpret what's happening to you or with me
andrew Olinsk's quote emphasizes the importance of willing direct experience
with this is what's happening really this is what's happening when I
feel myself when I feel the energy of forming an opinion about something can I stop very key pause and say is that
what's happening or how I'm interpreting it then what can I look what can't I really see
in this moment as opposed to what do I believe about
this moment
so it often involves this bias we have of
how we see involves judgment judgment of me judgment of you you know so so I
mentioned the thing of exceptionalism seeing that
I had this urge toward wanting to be different wanting to be separate I could
decide oh there's something wrong with you you have to be important i can form
all sorts of opinions about that unless I'm also able to see that I really like
being here in this group with this group i happen to be sitting up here but
really it's with you that that lifts my soul lifts my heart
but if I'm focused on oh I got to worry about whether I'm conceited or whatever
the judgment is you have about one yourself or about others you can become derailed from what's actually happening
you get kind of stuck in a rut and find yourself going down a tunnel this is my
conventional way of thinking this is how it is
and what we're really doing is seeing what is familiar
seeing what is familiar
so I recently spent some time with my sister who uh is closest in age to me i
come from a large family and I really love my sister and uh
maybe three days into her visit I found myself wanting to tear her apart
i could feel the anger and I I turned around and I walked away and I realized
and I walked away because I didn't want to say something hurtful so I wasn't totally out of control i could I could
see anger is here and consequences are always bad so I'm I turned away and as I
walked away I thought about how this was actually an automatic response based on
a long history of life with my sister and thinking oh she's always that way as soon as I heard she is always or I am
always as soon as I hear that message in my head I immediately know that I'm lost
in some delusion i immediately know I'm not seeing things as they are
because the truth is I turned away because I loved my sister not because I
was angry
seeing clearly requires you to really notice what's going on and be brutally
honest about it it is neither good nor bad the fact that anger arises
is not bad it just is what we do next determines whether it's
skillful or unskillful
one of the places this shows up most clearly is in the realm of righteousness
this is how it should be it really should be this way and it's
not this way and the dissatisfaction comes from the sense that there's one
right way that this can be
and one has to ask oneself if they're just not seeing the circles
am I just not seeing the circles
one of the the difficulties of unraveling the case of
of reacting from a sense of familiar seeing what's familiar noticing what's familiar
is that we ignore that the conditions are always changing
so conditions are such that today this is happening
so maybe at noon I don't want to be down at Market Street in San Francisco because
it's going to be really really busy there and there going to be a million people there and I might not be able to
find my way on another day that is totally untrue
the conditions are always changing in every moment for everything that is occurring any experience you have you do
not repeat that experience there are some conditions that are different and so being able to recognize I'm acting
from a conditioned response or I I can see the tendency toward a conditioned
response gives us the freedom to stop and say "Oh
am I seeing clearly am I really seeing what's happening or am I just seeing
what you know is easy to see it's easy to see
one place this plays out very strongly is in the case of expectations
we may we plan something and in fact this is what the anger with
my sister was about i had a plan for how how the visit was going to go we were
going to do X Y and Z and we were going to do it in this order and it was going to make everything perfect
except you know her grandson didn't want to do that
and he was there too and I found myself just being irritated
by that but but I'm trying to make this perfect for you
can't you see this act of generosity it took me a while to see that it was my
selfish grasping on my expectation of how
delighted they were going to be by this thing I planned that I failed to see that they were actually delighted by
something else
and the suffering was being caused by my expectations
not by anything they were doing or even anything I was doing it was all based on
I have a plan this is how I think it should go this is what this is how I'm this is what I'm
offering it comes from a very generous place and turns into something not quite so generous
not quite so generous when we are disappointed over the
outcome of something the first thing we want to do is establish blame it's your fault it's my fault
no you just see it and when I saw that my expectations were getting in the way
of everybody being at ease I thought "Oh well it's just
expectations i can let go of expectations
the mind locks back on the expectation no it's just an expectation step away
from it again step away step away
we can't really recondition the mind willfully overnight
we can only increase our ability to see when the mind habit is occurring when
it's showing up when it's arising we condition ourselves to watch
and then we say "Oh that's what's happening oh I see that."
The other thing to keep in mind is the tendency of us to see things from
our point of view all the time because you know that's where we're looking from right
but can I see you if I'm only worried about me
so there's need for balance in our view as well when I feel jittery when I feel
irritated when I feel delighted I too have a tendency to say "Ah it
means this it's about that." And then I look at who else is in the
room and see what does their experience look like what does it feel like for them it
helps me get more in touch with what's really happening
but if I'm only focused on me
I can't see what's actually happening
because I'm leaving out a large part of the experience
seeing clearly requires us to be open to all the aspects of experience
to be open which can be you know scary
it leaves you a little vulnerable guess what that's a good thing
because it means you're taking it in you're actually taking in what's what the experience truly is
so many of our assumptions are
biologically socially conditioned
we're conditioned beings but we're not determined by those
conditions we can see oh this is happening
we don't decide to have that conditioning it's just there
we don't decide well what we do
is we reinforce what we believe we re reinforce ideas that we have about
ourselves how we are how we should be instead of what's happening now
what's going on in this space in this time with these conditions what's happening now
we've all had the experience where uh everything is going beautifully
and we say "Ah now I've got it i know just how this works
this feels so good and we feel locked into the experience
because it's a pleasurable experience when we feel like we're in the flow you know we're in the flow we're just moving
with things it's really easy and
we ascribe meaning to that oh this means that now I've got the answer i know how
to do this cool i'm never going to be angry with my sister again right
being affected is not the issue noticing something is not the end point
the next thing we do is say "Okay I notice that I'm affected how am I being
affected what do I notice what's going on in me how do I use this information
that I've just received that things are not the way I thought or they
are the way I thought how is this affecting me what what do I feel about
that so rather than getting caught up in the
story about it so let's let's take the case of being angry with my sister
instead of worrying about why I'm angry or what I'm angry about or what all the
details of the story I can notice that it makes me uncomfortable that I'm
irritated that I'm hot i can change the focus based on what I see that
disentangles me from the story so that I'm not reinforcing the view
not reinforcing the need for blame i'm over i'm in a different realm now
still with this what's happening but now I can feel what does this anger feel
like what and the in in turning it around so that I'm not reinforcing why
the anger is there explaining the anger whatever the feeling is just being
present for that allows me to say "Oh that feels not good i don't want that to
continue." It increases the possibility I can step away from that anger i'm not fighting
the anger i can see it and say "Okay
anger is here but it's not me i don't want to cultivate it here's how I'm
feeling i'm my stomach is upset i'm looking at the actual things that are
happening and not trying to interpret them i'm also not denying that it's there
that's delusion but it's not the only thing there
and I can look up and I can see in the the particular case of where this
argument occurred i looked out at the at the waves and the
beach we're on Santa Cruz Beach and said "Isn't it a beautiful day
it's still a beautiful day
you don't we don't have to take some emotional content piece of experience
and make it the entire experience
we get washed away in waves by an emotional experience
but we don't have to be and we and like waves we can see them come crashing in and they go out again
they're not who we are
so while the programmed mind establishes what it is that's going on
we can say is that true and what else is happening is that true and what else is
happening and what is actually happening that's led me to this conclusion
what's actually happening
how is this affecting me and now what am I going to do the skillful thing is not to have these
biases never show up the skillful thing is what do I do when they show up
what do they do what what do I do with this whatever the bias is
maybe it's a bias toward optimism
my husband really likes to see the good in everything
so when he's frowning and he's trying desperately to find the good
you know he's suffering
because he doesn't want to see the stuff that he doesn't like to see none of us
do we don't like pain we don't like discomfort
and we tend to think it means something so Sylvia Bourstein tells this wonderful story she um I don't know if she still
tells it i heard it 20 years ago or something but she uh was trying to get a
hold of somebody at Zen Center and they exchanged emails this was before the world of texting and telephone calls and
they just didn't seem to connect so one morning she was calling Zen Center and she she asked for the person and whoever
answered the phone said "Well he's not here." And she said "You know it just must be that we're not meant to
connect." and he said 'N no it just means that he's not here
now I particularly like this story a because it's humorous but really because
it it makes it really clear what it is we're talking about here it's not life or death it's that we tend to form
opinions and implications when actually this is the only thing
that's happening just this just this thing is happening
we have to take out the have to take into account the nature of our attitudes
you know what's my mood today uh how how am I feeling physically did I
have a night where I couldn't sleep and so I'm really kind of short
i have attention deficit i'm not actually listening to you i
heard the first two words but after that
we can develop a sense of the energy of how we are in the world
in order to to make these quick determinations of what's actually going on
we have to pause we have to have some something that we look at look at the
energy am I leaning toward this am I leaning away from this am I
lifted by this am I depressed by this learn to follow the energy of what's
happening it keeps you from getting lost in the story for one thing there's a tendency then to convert that into this
is what this means like you know we're not expect we're not meant to meet
but if we develop a feel for what our preferences and expectations are like
what does it feel like to to find myself leaning toward an expectation i've got a
plan and to feel yourself moving ahead to the next item on your plan you can
kind of feel that leaning into part and say "Maybe I'll just stay here
maybe I'll just stay now
become sensitive to the the energy flow of your attitudes your your
uh responses your experience
become familiar with it that's part of what we do in meditation
when we're sitting in meditation and watching what arises I can't seem to sit here today i feel
like I'm going to jump out of my skin feel what that feels like know what that
feels like there are many times where we're standing in the kitchen and we feel like
we're going to jump out of our skin or or we're driving down the freeway to know that and say "Oh that's what's
happening." If this is the jumping out of my skin feeling and not everybody on the road is driving
crazy
find yourself free of blame don't let the view of this has to be
someone's fault or someone's doing or someone's responsibility
mine or yours and just be with the experience of this is what's happening
know that the views of mind habits are very strong learn yours
learn the ones that come up most often they're tendencies they're not you
just as sometimes I really really really want to be alone just as strongly
sometimes I really really really want to be in a crowd not as often crowds
but get a feeling for what what pressures you
get a feel for it notice oh there's pressure here i'm feeling pressure
there's stress there's stress here i'm feeling this not I am stressed but I'm
feeling stress i'm feeling some pressure i'm feeling anxiety
anxiety is here instead of saying "Oh well of course I'm
anxious i'm always anxious under these conditions." No no no these conditions didn't happen before
oh what's happening that anxiety is here what am I actually feeling what am I
uncomfortable with what am I delighted with
how can I have more of this in my life what did I just notice that lifted my
heart ah because every time you notice something that lifts your heart it makes
it more likely that you'll notice something again later
feel the energy note this is how it's affecting me this
is affecting me this energy is affecting me this experience is affecting me but
it is not me
this is the wisdom of wise view i see it but it is not me it just is
what's happening it's just this it doesn't have any untrust truthful any
unconventional meaning
what we're in search of here is truth truth what's true
if we know the patterns and behaviors that we are prone to we can learn to see
them and say "Is is that coloring what my experience is now
or is I is it something that I need to pay attention to?"
And remember that what we think we are is just a point of view
what we think we are is just a point of view and then any given day we might
think we are something entirely different
there's a role of the people that we interact with
in seeing ourselves clearly when we notice how people react to us
we can form assumptions about them or we can say "What are they reacting to
what are they seeing what's going on with them
what's going on with them just as much as I'm interested in what's going on with me what's going on with them
because our practice is really relative to other people you know it feels like
it's all about us but it is really about all of us as opposed to me
suffering in the world arises because I want to be liked because I want this
because I want that i have all kinds of desires things I want to have happen things I don't want
to have happen how attached to those things am I
earlier in the week I had I ran across something that I I wanted I wanted and
it was too expensive i've been following it for a year waiting for it to go on sale it finally went on sale and I
wanted that i wanted that and I said
"And it's on sale this is great just what I was waiting for
but you know I really don't need it."
And when I heard my say self say "I don't need it," I thought "Well you're just arguing with yourself now you're
trying to be as you know trying to be a good person yes and
I don't need it i really don't need it
i took it out of the cart it's been there for a year
waiting to go on sale it was interesting for three days it's
been on sale and I kept watching what does it feel like to want
pretty soon the want was much bigger the understanding the want was much bigger
than the item I mean the item just kind of disappeared but what was interesting
was how strong that wanting was for something I didn't even need
would have very little impact on my
almost none and how strong that wanting was
not because I'm a bad person or because I am I don't know any number
of things that you could say about it but because I'm human I'm also subject
to wanting and not wanting and to be able to watch that feel that
understand what that feels like to see when you're in the grips of that is a
very important part of practice how we cling to something
to be with that in a nonjudgmental way
so all of that wanting the thought would arise oh you're a bad
person for wanting ah that's I don't need to go there what I need to
do is understand what the wanting is to to really feel the wanting doesn't have anything to do about who I am it only
exists under these conditions
the way that we are with these uncomfortable things that we see is by
not assuming that they're us they just are they're just there
so I have lots of other things in here I could have said however
what I want to leave you with is that awareness of what's happening
is impacted both by the views that we bring into the moment and the
mindfulness with which we see them
wise view comes out of seeing things as they are recognizing the tendencies of
our mind habits seeing them nonjudgmentally
the space we want to occupy is the space of neither wanting nor pushing away the
experience just see the experience
don't label it as good or bad that just gets in the way
so I'm going to read you a uh a pros poem by Steve Cohit
uh and it's co called Mount Baldi this is a spirit up before dawn to
meditate all day with a saffronroed Thai terraada Buddhist monk who explains the
incomprehensible dharma in all but incomprehensible English then jabs a
finger in the air and nods triumphantly and at the bell propped upon my purple
zafu in half lotus I set grimly to the task of reigning in the hyperactive and
incourageable mind that screaming brat who's flying up and down the supermarket
aisles flinging from the shelves everything in sight i liked Malt Mount Baldi in the Zeno
there and Terraata mindfulness practice and that grinning sensei with his fractured English and I liked as well
that shapely dark lubricious fellow meditator three zafuss down her lovely
face and arched cross-legged body lust longing random fragmentaryary thoughts
and drowsy bits of memories and momentary bouts of wakeful consciousness
and sudden bursts of joy one moment quiet ecstasy and utter peace the next
the wish this week weekendl long retreat were long since over with my back felt
stiff my knees achd then Sunday after lunch with an hour's freedom for myself
I wandered off alone and scrabbled up a nearby hill and found a perfect rock to
sit upon and looked around unbburdened and relaxed amazed by everything those
few spare pines the skies soul-wrenching blue and at my feet a tribe of ants
systematically upending grains of sand and far away that winding strip of highway with its antlike string of
trucks and cars and then I saw her in a clearing some 50 odd feet below where I
was perched that gorgeous raven-haired young meditator that seductive bodhicattva wielding a long crescent
sword and practicing her katas cutting through desire the hundred,000 permutations of the
wobbling mind wonder pleasure dreams desires and memories
i simply watch and let them be they too luminous transparent perfectly apparent
perfectly themselves that all things rise abide are changed
and pass away mindfulness practice at the Zeno at Mount Baldi 6,000 ft above the sea
exquisite world of craving and delusion
there he was on a perfect rock unbburdened and
relaxed amazed by everything those few spare pines the sky soul-wrenching blue
and at my feet a tribe of ants systematically upending grains of sand and far away that winding strip of
highway with its ant-like strength of trucks and cars and then I saw her in a
clearing some 50 odd feet below where I was perched that gorgeous raven-haired young meditator that seductive
bodhicattva wielding a long crescent sword and practicing her katas cutting through
desire the 100,000 permutations of the wobbling mind
wonder pleasure dreams desires and memories i simply watch and let them be
they too luminous transparent perfectly apparent perfectly themselves
that all things rise abide are changed and pass away mindfulness practice at
the Zeno Mount Baldi 6,000 feet above the sea or here at IMC
exquisite world of craving and delusion may you all see clearly thank you