Hello everyone and welcome to this guided meditation session that's part of
a larger series of exploration of what the insight of insight meditation
uh points to and um surprisingly the topic for now I think about seven
seven sessions has been the second uh insight not that we're not surprising
that we're doing it. But surprising that we would spend seven days, seven
sessions talking about suffering, insight into suffering,
the bu the ability to recognize something profoundly important about how
we suffer, how we feel distress, how we get
caught in stress, how we get caught in emotional unnecessary emotional pain.
unnecessary emotional reactivity, unnecessary
uh attachments, clinging, resistance in our life.
So maybe this will be the last uh time on suffering before we move to the third
insight. And um and so but uh one of the very
significant approaches to insight meditation is when
we're able to see our suffering, understand, recognize our suffering
in um highlight or in contrast or together with seeing the first
insight, seeing change, seeing inconstancy and uh non-ontinuity and and
impermanence of the experience. all the ways in which change happens
and one way or the other suffering what Buddhism is calling duka
the very the thing that the kind of suffering the kind of emotional pain
that that Buddhism is addressing one way or the other
involves A a
freezing of the mind involves a tightening of the
mind. Involves a holding the mind tight and steady, tight and caught in
something where that caughtness feels like there's continuity of attachment,
continuity of pressure. And it's kind of a solidification in the
mind, a kind of a stopping of the mind. It's a kind of um preoccupation of the
mental activity that's gotten glombmed on, stuck into some concern, some
preoccupation, some thought, some idea, some emotion that we have.
And in doing that uh there's a semblance feeling that we're now no longer moving
along letting things flow in the river of change. that we've somehow
picked up a bucket of water and we think the river is the the water
in the bucket and it's a really heavy to carry that bucket and if you have to carry that bucket all the time uh the
the burden of that the suffering of that the tiredness of that
uh will gets more and stronger and stronger until we return the water to the river
where it belongs. And then the water flows. Then we can float in the river. We don't have to
carry the water. The water carries us. And so to begin recognizing where the
mind has stopped around thinking, stopped around some preoccupation.
Of course, it hasn't stopped completely. is maybe chewing, ruminating on our concern, but there's something has kind
of gotten solidified. Some people like the idea that it's gotten frozen because then it can thaw.
Some people the idea of being it's now become um there's a kind of a permanence
a kind of a continuity just like if you held your fist tight
all the time in a certain way the continuity of that tightness
is more prominent than a a hand that's fluid and changing
and moving and being with things as they are.
So to begin appreciating how the mind seizes up,
it could be very very mild with the lightest of thoughts that we
just kind of get get involved in. We can feel this little kind of
tightening or it can be quite strong.
And then to allow the mind,
the concerns, the attention, the the the to set it free, to make it loose,
to flow, to not hold on to anything, not reject anything.
Oddly enough, not accept anything or reject anything.
Finding that a third option, neither accepting
nor rejecting, but flowing with all things
without having to believe anything or not believe anything,
without needing to act on whatever arises.
and maybe also not needing to not act unless it's going to cause harm, unless
it's going to it's going to continue the way we get locked in.
So to assume a meditation posture and to
maybe kind of sway back and forth a little bit, you know, shake, move
the shoulders, rotate the shoulders. Kind of sitting down to meditate and
maybe rotating your head.
kind of letting there be movement and flow and that kind of loosens things up
a little bit in your body. Flapping your should your elbows.
Kind of tapping your fingers so that shaking your fingers so they loosen up. The hand loosens up.
And then gently closing your eyes
and feeling whatever feels loose
in your body. Whatever feels kind of light
in your body.
Wherever there's a sense of ease in your body, even if it's just a little
square centimeter somewhere in your body, feel the ease.
Maybe feeling the pleasure of
maybe the lips touching.
Maybe a small half half smile in the lips
and feeling into your body
deep within where the breathing begins
to Feel a place of stillness
and ease. A stillness where nothing is held.
A stillness that's more like the still quiet air
of a dawn above a still lake.
And there arises from within an inhale.
Maybe the inhales come quickly, forcefully. Maybe they come slowly, gently.
Maybe you can have a feeling of receiving the sensations
of breathing in, allowing them to appear.
Receiving the inhales
and allowing the release of the exhales. Close.
And as you exhale in an easy way
with the kind of ease that where there doesn't have to be success.
As you exhale, relax your body.
Soften different parts of your body.
And as you inhale, feel any way that your mind, your brain
is tense, solid.
Maybe locked in in some way
tight in a fisted fist in the mind,
caught in anything at all, even the slightest thoughts.
Feel that pressure, tension,
stress.
And as you exhale, soften the mind.
Soften the tension, pressure.
And as you're aware of the rhythm of breathing,
let that rhythm carry to your mind a gentle massage.
carry up to the mind
kind of
flow of awareness. That's like water
softening, dissolving
whatever is hard in the thinking mind.
Whatever is tight in our preoccupations.
Feel the fixations of the mind. no matter how light small they are
but don't become fixated on it. And that's the role of breathing
to keep us help us be aware gently softly
neither accepting or rejecting anything.
Just holding the fixation in the flow of
awareness, massaging it,
softening it,
melting
If you have a concern that you're
caught in preoccupied with, you don't have to let go of the concern.
Let go of the tension, the pressure.
behind having the concern.
Feel that tension. Feel that pressure.
And notice how it creates a solidity or a hardness.
That keeps you from flowing
in the changing river of now.
And then as we come to the end of this sitting
to notice now
is there any way that you are calmer than you were at the beginning.
Is there any way that there's a deeper place of ease
or stillness
that is a bomb is a medicine
for any way in which the mind might still be tight,
hard, Tense
under pressure.
And with whatever calm you have,
see if you can not be troubled.
by any mental tension, pressure,
preoccupation you have.
Let the calm.
Appreciate the changing
nature of tension and pressure. mental
hardness and solidity.
Hold it all lightly.
And in doing so,
identify more with the calm and the lightness
than with the heaviness or tension or pressure.
Be the calm. Be the lightness
that knows what is not calm.
And then without accepting or rejecting any part of
yourself, can you gaze upon the world
kindly? Can you gaze upon the world calmly?
Gaze upon the world with generosity, wishing well for everyone.
As you would wish well for yourself, wish well for others.
May all beings be happy.
May all beings be safe.
May all beings be peaceful.
May all beings be free.
[Music]
Thank you.
So hello and welcome to this
series of talks on insight. The core recognitions
that uh arise from doing mindfulness practice. the core recognitions that
help set us free, loosen us, liberate us from clinging and suffering.
And one of those deep recognitions, deep seeings, deep revelations is a deeper
understanding of suffering. And it's a big word. We've been talking about it now for a number of days.
And um and but one important aspect of it is to
appreciate that uh whatever it is that Buddhists are talking about when they
talk about suffering that it comes with tension. It comes
with a holding on tight. It comes with a sol a solidification of some inner parts
of ourselves. The mind, the heart, the inner life gets frozen, gets stuck, gets
uh locked into something. So there's a whole series of words that can be used
that are near synonyms. Maybe some of these words work better for others.
But um uh if um if I am angry with something
and I need to express that anger to other people or believe I have to and so
I make a fist in order to express myself and I pound my fist into my other hand
and um and um you know insisting that
the English language has too many letters to keep track of. It's too many letters. We should have fewer letters.
And um and uh yes, I can be in a campaign to
change the English language. Uh and but I could be suffering if I'm
trying to do that and trying to get everyone on the bandwagon and insist how right I am and how important this is.
And there might be good reasons for this kind of idea.
uh but I'm suffering because of it. So I could be looking at my suffering and
trying to understand why I have this idea. What's the philosophy behind it? What's the linguistic elements of it?
what's the real right count for letters and maybe you know just caught up in the
ideas of it and I don't notice that I have my hand in a fist
independent of whether I solve the issues of the number of letters in the English language
I be I just relax my hand life becomes so much easier without that
fisted hand without that tightness and contraction and eventually spasming of the hand. It I can separate out the
concern about letters with from the tension in which my hand
is in. So in the same way we might have very good concerns we have
much more important than number of letters things that we're attached to things that are really precious and important
for us and we're suffering because of it we're stressed because of it we are
burdened by it we feel sometimes oppressed by some things sometimes we feel fear and that's the um sometimes we
feel ambition sometimes we feel disappointment and uh hurt and many many
things that we feel. And if we're kind of concerned with the subject of the
suffering, then we might be caught in a maze of
concerns and he said, she said, they said preoccupations.
But instead go look and see where the tension is. Where's the pressure?
Where's the locked in? Where's the the the tent the the tightness?
Where's the uh agitation? Where's the
clinging, the craving? Where's the leaning forward? Where's the pulling
back? And um the deeper way to really address
the topic of suffering in this insight is not to stay with the details and
complexity of the subject of what we're concerned with, but rather to really
take responsibility for the relationship we have to that subject. But in doing
that, don't think even more. The art of mindfulness is to learn to feel, to
sense, to experience the sensations of
that come with suffering. the tightness, the tension, the pressure, the clinging,
the locked inness, the shutting down, the turning off, the
um the giving up, the all these different
kind of ways that can feel like, oh, there's where the holding is. There's where the dropping away, you know, kind
of pulling back and escaping is the desire to run away. Feel all that. So
that and that then you start feeling where we're resisting change, where
we're standing against changed, where we're kind of solidifying,
tightening up, making something more constant art artificially.
Artificially in the sense that it's an artifact of the mind,
of our attitudes. that are holding on tight.
So the art of mindfulness is to take a deep look at where the solidity is,
where the incon where the constancy is, where there's the continuity that comes
from holding on tight comes from a physical
uh a physical and even in the mind it can feel physical or almost physical.
the the pressure the the the tight constellation the narrowing of uh
happens in the awareness of the mind around some concern some preoccupation.
It can be that um that the weight of something we talk about the weight on our shoulders. The weight of a
responsibility is not in the responsibility.
It's in that you know the ways in which we have phys almost physically tightened
up solidified locked in gotten frozen around something.
There's a wonderful story of Ajang Cha, the famous uh Thai monk who was a
teacher for many of the early vipasa teachers, inside teachers
uh and uh who was going for a walk with someone and said pointed I guess to some
really big boulder and said to uh and asked is that boulder heavy and the
student said oh yes it's really heavy. And um and Ajan Sha said, "No, it's not
heavy. It's only heavy if you try to lift it."
And so what are we? So the burdens of the world, we're holding up the burdens
of the world because we're trying to lift it. Maybe it's not necessary to
lift anything, hold anything. And the benefit of this is that when we
tighten up, when we contract, when we get fixated,
when we cling to things and crave for things, we're actually narrowing
the our intelligence, narrowing the scope of our heart, our emotional,
mental sensitivity. We're losing touch with the wide range
and scope by which our understanding, our wisdom, our care, our love can
operate. And it's counterintuitive because the preoccupations we have can be so
important and we need this. We need to protect myself. I need to have this. I
need I have to take care of this. I have to criticize myself. I have to figure out something else.
And that insistence is part of that tightness. That insistence is part of that sense of physical pressure.
And so but it has so much authority.
But to learn over time that we are wiser, more caring, more open, more intelligent
when we don't get locked in, when we don't get caught.
and the and when we're free. And so this insight into suffering in
Buddhism is very much supported
by really being mindful, really seeing and recognizing
the actual tension that's there with our suffering.
So, you might have some cause, like changing how many letters there are in the English alphabet,
but pay attention to how you're insisting that things should be different and how they have to be a
certain way and how you're going to, you know, really change the English language, change all the dictionaries in
some way. Pay attention to how you're making that fist.
Don't tighten up. You can still make effort to change the English language,
but at least don't compromise your hand. Don't compromise your compromise your heart. Don't compromise your mind. Don't
compromise the the quality of your inner life.
Your inner life is precious. Letting go of tension. letting go of
pressure to allow the inner life to to grow, mature, free, develop
um in beautiful ways. It is possible.
And um so this insight into suffering
is such an important part of not suffering.
So thank you very much and I believe that that's will be the end of the
discussions here about uh suffering. Maybe we've suffered enough now. Um but
there's one more area of suffering that uh that is so important that it is
considered the third important insight to have uh and that is um into this uh
perplexing topic for many people of not self
and um and that'll be the topic uh when I start up this up again unless some
reason there's revelation happens once is suffering some more.
So, uh I'll be away for two weeks. Uh next week, uh Ying Chen is coming and
she's a wonderful teacher. She's been here before on YouTube and I'm very happy that she'll be with you the
following week. um in the way things are working out. Um we're going to do a
replay of the of right near the the the beginning of the year when we were doing
samadei. Samadei is the foundation for insight and I thought it might be go
nice uh while I'm away to go back to the beginning. And so uh we're going to uh
do a rerun and play the third week in the samadei series that had a lot to do
with uh developing samadei around breathing. And uh hopefully that's a good foundation for when I return after
that to pick up the insight into not self.
And finally um uh maybe I've said this enough. I apologize. But uh for those of
you who would like to study more of the things that I I'm going to be offering in the fall, I have three programs in
the fall. Uh one is this call called Anua
which is uh a 11-month program on um
looking at one's uh practice life, dharma life, spiritual life through the lens of um the parameies, the
perfections and 10 spiritual themes that come out of the world of western world
of chapency, spiritual care. The other is uh the chapency program itself. It's
a beautiful wonderful program that we offer both online and in person and uh I
do the inerson part and uh this is for people who want to be involved in in uh
volunteer or professionally in the world of spiritual care
and then um uh the um third is through those are both through Sati center.
The third is uh offered through IMC and that is um called the equivalence of
ethics and enlightenment and it's a program it's a eight ninemonth program
uh looking at the foundational teachings of ethics in the teachings of the Buddha
and how it applies to our life um and appreciating that ethics and enlightenment at are not really two
different things and um and they are integrated deeply from the beginning and end of the path of practice.
So um u may you
uh be uh suffer wisely over these next
uh two weeks and uh when we come back we'll uh continue this series. Thank you
very much.