uh good morning to uh many of you good afternoon Scotland and
uh London and um yeah happy to
uh to practice with you very sweet seeing the
uh chat
community okay um let's uh let's practice together
one way of talking about uh duka usually rendered as suffering is
that um life is
um a little bit too much at
least often too
much a little overwhelming just to to be
human and so in meditation it's just a
way of doing much much
less being open to how life flows through us
settling and tranquilizing so that we can uh
meet life as it flows through
so relaxing whatever can be
relaxed area around your
eyes be so much tension just in uh unconsciously
in muscles around the eyes
your
jaw softening releasing thing
so my friend uh Pam Dun says just let your whole face fall Ah
And your shoulders hang loosely
hey wherever your shoulders hang after a deep
breath just let them Rest there
your belly be
soft
any subtle tension or
holding bracing in your belly soften amen
if you're sitting just
letting your hips pelvis sink into the ground
your feet be open your hands be open
sense that uh energy can run through unimpeded
and now that which we already know how to
do
breathe becomes
uh objective
awareness you already know how to do this
now we just uh delight in
aliveness simplicity life becoming simpler
there's hunger for oxygen we breathe in that's uh quite
pleasurable the little tension builds up and then we expel
uh what's been used up that too is quite pleasurable
so for a few minutes just uh just enjoy Hey
In subtle ways we're embedding this um present moment within
a kind of matrix of predictions and expectations
the sense of the energy just leaning
forward sense of uh knowing thinking that we know who we'll be in the next
moment what our life will be the end of
this practice period the end of this
day the ways in which we predict uh
continuity and expect ourselves in the next moment the next moment
we practice diving into the present
moment in a subtle way as that expectation ations are
modeled by our
mind we prune those back by having deeper
fidelity to this mind moment
you stop predicting yourself
and samadei it's a kind
of dissolution of the predictive architecture
craving is always about one word next
usually what we envision being next is me
in meditation we
uh soften
the expectation that I'm next me in the next moment me
reborn exactly as I was
please stop making that hypothesis
we fall into the present moment
[Music]
we often associate uh
disorientation with um unpleasantness who likes getting lost
you know maybe a few people but I have never had the taste for that exactly i
associate disorientation generally speaking with
unpleasantness but here um in in dharma we actually develop some
appreciation for it and those moments when you you know
right after you wake up or something before you've remembered who
you are some elements of
um practice are about a climatizing to
disorientation and was alluding to that a little bit in
the uh the instructions and
awe awe awe this is a um beautiful
feeling pleasant but maybe a little disorienting the sense of the
mind broadening and it's like we're not
accustomed to so much space but awe is the the feeling of a
kind of simultaneous expansion and
contraction in you know we're like infantessimally small and
vast and there's sense of like oh yeah this smallness is partaking in the
vastness
this is um psychologist Decker Kilner um awe is the feeling of wonder and
amazement at being in the presence of something vast that transcends one's current
understanding a is part of a family of states that includes elevation appreciation and
admiration the majority of all experiences occur in response to nature
other people who other people who display virtuosity or
magnanimity art and music religious experiences and ideas similar to other
pro-social emotions like gratitude and compassion a reliably predicts increased
sharing assistance and generosity
maybe you're in nature in the mountains and that kind
of stunning austerity of the world just stops you and this sense of
like I don't know time can be felt in a different
way you know it's like you just see the the the rocks and the the you know the
trees and the landscape it's just like yeah time can be
sensed or virtuosity you know I was like
saw um a video of Simone Biles doing a floor a floor floor exercise the gymnast
like the most like kind of the best gymnast in the history of the world you know and it's like and
what she was doing it was like I was really like the response was like I cannot believe we're both homo
sapiens she and I were both like the same species i was like I just felt proud to
be like part of the same species somebody who could do that it's like science
fiction you know or goodness goodness you know like
it's usually called moral elevation the moral beauty that we can witness that
can fill us with awe it's a lot of it happening it doesn't get reported so much but it's
like you know I don't know much more goodness than we could
ever estimate greed hate and delusion of course must fill the pages of the the
papers um but um the amount of just simple
ordinary goodness is
staggering and awe breaks us out of um
claustrophobia i associate suffering with
claustrophobia you know and often we don't realize how small our life has
become you know and it's natural suffering is inherently
selfabsorbing you know I'd like to live
uh to live with a sense of life as a problem just puts all the focus on
what's what's in front of us you know and because the feeling of self is
a feeling of specialness it's um it's hard to treat ourselves as
just another person and so a lot of how we work with
our mind is about broadening and awe is like a sudden
dramatic broadening we learn to live in more and
more awe we develop awe for
um the path and the lineage you know and uh there are times when you
know there are times when it's like oh yeah I'm a meditator d whatever then
other times where it's like the gratitude is so overwhelming that it just becomes awe
like how on earth Did
Sidartha Gautama like of Lumbini you know 600
BC speak so directly to Matthew of
California 2025 AD you know to speak words that are
relevant across space and time amazing
i remember early tastes of the path you know kind of like have shared this moment with Galen
Ferguson you know Tibetan teacher and uh after a weekend retreat on the unity of
shamata and vapasha you know the unity of um
tranquility and insight and I didn't know what was happening but you know it was kind of
like you know beginning to fall in love with the dharma and I go up to him afterwards and kind of crying and sort
of messy and trying to say something but kind of just wanting to hug him and you
know and he's a kind of a little bit buttoned up you know uh didn't know
exactly what to do with me um but he was so gracious beautiful and um you know he
just said something like yeah sometimes peering out over the vastness of the dharma
ocean can be a lot can be a lot
awareness becomes a kind of object of awe like
how close the distance from suffering to
peace might be in the lockedin feeling of duca the
claustrophobia of duca feels like well no way out of this
until I get circumstances right till I get straightened some way
and um and then we start to appreciate like wait a
second maybe there's a lot of peace much closer than my mind
suspects maybe it's just one moment
away and it's not always like that but sometimes it is and when it's like that
we say to ourselves okay I don't want to forget
this we're encouraged uh to reflect on the kind of preciousness of uh human
life awe awe we could say at having been
born and we're we're thrown into the condition of living and it feels so
self-evident that I should exist you know but it's super
wild you know it's wild there's something rather than nothing nothing says we should exist
nothing says the dharma should have been offered as I say like all all the time before
you were born plus all the time after you die is almost precisely all the time
there is and yet here we
are on
YouTube and wonder wonder like a sense of awe in the face of
possibility how might I live in
um existential psychotherapy the failure to grapple with uh kind of core
existential themes is thought to be produced symptoms you know lead to pain
and one of them is around uh the openness of possibility the
weight of freedom you know
how might I live and we've perhaps been too taken
taken in by convention by all the kind of models of happiness profered by
society and everything that we consider well
this is the natural way this is customary this is the right way this is common sense
empty labamasa like attachment to right usually rendered as attachment to rights
and rituals which is shed at stream entry
um attachment to rights and rituals um but it's also in a deeper
sense the ways in which fidelity to
convention to making what what is empty seem
uh concrete and it's sometimes it's like oh
yeah my entire life is sila paramasa entire life is
convention and it's not to say we should live a totally different life but we should
realize we're just making this up
totally okay how might I live and even if I do
live and I do live in adherence to
convention at least it looks like that but not
inside and so we recognize the groundlessness of all uh convention and
there's a lot of wonder awe how might I
live i remember at a uh at a retreat uh New Year's Eve uh a retreat
that fell over New Year's Eve and it was a couple weeks of of retreat silence are
sitting and uh and we ring in the new year with chanting and then have a
silent dance party and it's midnight or you know it's after
midnight and uh I'm sitting in a chair out in the Santa Barbara
stars and some of the light from those stars you know looking up you can see a
lot it was it was a good night and uh knowing that I'm looking at
some stars that are now gone you know literally looking at the past and amidst the the vastness of
space and time i remember thinking like "Oh my good like here I am this like
unimaginable vastness and I'm worried about my butt hurting from
sitting you know hard hard to take uh much seriously
amidst the vastness but as the self grows smaller
the world gets much bigger the less clinging the more
life the less clinging the more life and then there's
uh a lot of love a lot of joy a lot of
cheerfulness you know to
uh sense into that openness maybe we call it the openness
of life sense how vast the love might be
so we we live in some sense of
awe we actually don't acclimatize to it
totally is not old
hat uh for this uh for your consideration yeah sweet to uh to be
with you thank you for your attention and uh we'll uh keep going tomorrow okay