so good morning everyone and welcome can you hear me all
right so this morning I'd like to talk about a
very important kind of concept in mindfulness in general and and give a
kind of a Buddhist take on it and that is the difference between uh
stimulus and response and uh people teach mindfulness often
emphasize this distinction and that um and and so I
will as well with um emphasizing the wonderful opportunities that are
available in really knowing how to identify this distinction
and and kind of in what's in between the stimulus and the
response and in the process this discover something about equinity there an angle to understand
equinity and how to have it so as as I understand it the usual
teachings on stimulus and response is that response is different than a
reaction and uh a reaction is something that happens kind of as a habit kind of
an automatic pilot there's a stimulus and then without even any reflection any
consideration there's automatically um a some kind of um activity we do it's
called reactivity meaning activity that's in response to something with
acting so uh so that could be we say something that we later regret it just
came out of us like that it could be an expression of an emotional expression that comes out of us so quickly that
again maybe later we regret it and um it could be that it's a um
something that um in activity we do we you know we do something we do do
impulsively with our actions we push send on our computer uh when we had U we
saw that there was this lovely thing to buy and the fact that we don't have
enough money in the bank account for that doesn't matter just you know this is this is going to be the solution to
my and the world's problems and so you know it's a kind of automatic pilot and working on habit
addictions are often this way and um and sometimes the reactivity
is within ourselves that we our mind um reacts in such a way that we create an
interpretation a further thoughts further judgments further bias comes
into play um and so in the mind might spin out in stories and ideas and create
universes of interpretations that happen very quickly in Rapid succession and we
don't sometimes it can be so quickly we don't really even see the all little steps that go in go into this creation
of interpretations ideas and all that when I was in um practicing in
Burma uh I've been practicing on retreat for some time and there was this very
simple uh little experience that I had that was a big aha for me and that is
that um when I went into the the meditation
teachers uh Little House cabin that he had for my practice discussions with him
and meetings with him uh I had to pass go through the front door and on just on
the on the right going in there was kind of an Al Cove that was filled with Buddhas and stuff you know it wasn't
actually an altar to bow at or something it was just like I don't know why it just it kept a lot of look like Buddhist
kind of things there statues and stuff and so for you know many days I
just walked right by and gave it almost no thought at all and so I was been
practicing for I think a few months by that times my mind was very quiet very still mindfulness was very strong and um
and I walked in and I looked to my right and as far as I could tell I think there
was a new Buddha there I saw it as a
Buddha I saw as a very distinct movement of the mind that it was really Pleasant
to look at okay and then I saw as a distinct kind
of event in of itself I want it
and in the past uh maybe the I wanted would have happened so quickly that it
had Authority it had meaning it had like this was the way the universe should be or something I never gave in any thought
I just like that was suddenly there but to watch the sequence of recognizing
what it was and then having sense the experience of it being Pleasant and really what I
could see what I want was more of that Pleasant more than I wanted the Buddha
statue and um and so then I um I um I
said wow it's possible to have this freedom in this sequence it's possible
to see the uh stimulus reaction stimulus response so clearly that I didn't have
to respond I didn't have to act so usually in the stimulus response distinction the way I like to think of
it the one hand there's reactive responses and the other there's considered response there's wise
response and so the idea is there in that Buddha I just my response was
wow and I just left it and I didn't think about it again for
a long time and until I discovered that uh someone
had actually bought it for me and and uh and I'd left it there for
that Abit to bless or do something and um so then many months later was handed
to me I didn't say anything to anybody about this little event so I have it at home
now and um so um in the way that this funny way
the world works so uh so so mindfulness has a lot to do with
uh adding the pause between stimulus and reaction between stimulus and response
so if all you do is something happens say that it's it's something as
simple as your what happens is you breathe
in and maybe the inhale is
unpleasant and I've had an unpleasant breath and immediately had a judgment
about it so automatic this is the wrong breath I'm a bad meditator it shouldn't be this way and there's a whole Cascade
of these automatic pilot kind of thoughts which are kind of a drag to
have but I can be so caught in their mesmerizing
enchanting you know truth of these kinds of you know judgments that I don't even
feel that it's unpleasant but it's actually not unpleasant but it's continues to have
each of those steps and judgments uh is just kind of draining kind of little bit
kind of impactful in a negative way on me it's unpleasant to kind of experience each
step and um and so it just Mak it simple as as uh you know an unpleasant
breath alternative is to feel the unpleasantness of that breath and take time to be mindful of it
give everything time it could just be two seconds in mindfulness practice we
give everything time we give everything a chance to be there before the
reactivity before the Judgment so so I would we would train ourselves we would
develop the capacity to feel the unpleasant breath and really feel it
take okay this is an unpleasant breath let me just feel it before I judge it
let me feel feel it before I'm pushing it away before I'm trying to fix the problem so feel it or let me observe it
let me just observe what it's like to have an unpleasant breath and maybe because it comes and goes so quickly uh
that pause is extended where maybe for the next 10 inhales I keep looking at
what what is this like what is it like to have an unpleasant breath and become the world expert in tense breaths of
what my unpleasant breath is like I discover things about it I discover where it's unpleasant in my body I
discover maybe where there's a holding in my breathing and tension uh I might understand there's an underlying fear
that's operating that's part of that that holding I start discovering so much
by taking time to know it to observe it be with it and
um and then I can decide wisely what's my response to this and one respon I
have to noticing I have an unpleasant in in breath is I think of it you know it's
just a massage I'm just massaging the unpleasant I'm just massaging the place
where I'm feel held in my breath where it's tensed tight and um I'm little bit
contracted or up my chest it's just a massage let's just hang out let's just
let it be there let's not fix it or do anything about it I'll just every inhale I'll feel where the tension is where the
holding is and my inhale again and again and again and I found that this is
really a wonderful thing to do to not make it a problem but just to kind of meet it be with it care for it this way
um and to allow something inside to unfold relax unravel on its own
rather than me having to be the doer and sometimes the reactivity that I
have like just something as simple as the unpleasant breath is I'm I I'm operating kind of in
this automatic pilot that I'm the one who has to take care of everything I'm
the one who I'm the victim of everything and I'm the one who has to address everything every moment in my
life but I've learned slowly that I don't have to do that it's kind of a lot
of work to do that every moment of your life and it's good to kind of take a
vacation and uh and mindfulness meditation is a time for a vacation from
being the one who's in charge or thinks they're in charge of every moment of your life like you're the victim you're
the person experiencing things you're the person has to do things and fix things and make something happen and
prove yourself and have a good experience to show your neighbors look I
had a good experience in meditation I went on Retreat and boy did I have a good experience some people are
experienced collectors just just you know all these
things so so as we pause take time to be with
something uh it just nice in itself it makes room so the reactivity doesn't
ride so close to the stimulus and in that time there's time to discover something that's going on
find out deeper what's happening what's going on one of the things we might discover is the nature of the
reactivity so it might be it takes a while to discover that it's unpleasant
breathing and um and there's a second unpleasant thing that happens and that
is the idea that it's wrong to have it happen the reaction of this is like
California Buddhist California where there's so many Buddhists then to have it but good
breath looks looks like deep really
relaxed and shouldn't be controlled there should be no tightness and you know this is some an embarrassment to
Buddhist Buddhists everywhere and so so I'm right so I have
this unpleasant breath and the reactivity immediately in my mind is these kinds of judgments these kinds of
ideas so then the choice is let's take time with that pause let's hang out with
that let me see that operating let me feel what it's like to have those thoughts those judgments let me see them
operating let me see them Bubble Up and and maybe they maybe they're constant
but chances are they're not constant they might look constant chances are I
me they're happening for a while and then I'm thinking about lunch or I'm happening for a while and then I feel my
exhale which also is not right and so then I have different
thoughts about that and uh and so but after a while I
just see wow that's a judgment it takes a while to just see a judgment as a judgment and as I see
judgment as a judgment I no longer believe it automatically I no longer
think I I don't have to live under the Yoke of that judgment I don't have to invest so much importance in it let me
just let it float up maybe it needs time maybe needs to
maybe it's lonely and needs to be seen so let let it just float up that judgment come and go see it and I'm
leaving it alone and then slowly maybe that relaxes maybe slowly I see something
about that judgment maybe I see that that judgment uh comes comes from some kind of beliefs
that I have maybe so that judgment comes with a certain kind of
uh self- understanding that I'm carrying with myself but how I'm supposed to be in the world I'm supposed to be a
perfect Buddhist whatever that is and so there's a whole universe of
things that start being discovered in that pause in the taking time with
things and um and so mindfulness is the
practice of pausing not necessarily in the
activities you're doing if you're going about your da life but something inside of you giving yourself a little bit of
time to know to feel to observe what's actually happening without laying over
on top of it judgments reactions wanting it to be different fixing it just let's
get to know it let's be with it so just that it helps with equinity
just that allows you to not be equinity is the ability to be present without
being on automatic reactivity automatically kind of getting worked up and and and but just kind of have a
steadiness okay let's just be with this without getting caught in the
reactivity and um so I mentioned two things that are important I think one is
that we start seeing what's happening more clearly the second is we come to a place
where we can choose how to respond one of the responses is to choose to be
mindful of it rather than being reactive let's take time with it let's get to
know this let's get let's investigate this let's discover this
further so this is all very nice and uh it can make for much wiser life it can
make for much w a life that we really start understanding yourselves more and more deeply and one of the things I've seen
of people who do a lot of mindfulness meditation mindfulness practice they grow in self- understanding because they
start seeing how these things operate the operating systems and the more we can see and understand the less likely
we are to be working on automatic pilot more likely we we're able to kind of step
back and have more choice on what we act on and so Freedom has a lot to do with
having choice and so we're giving ourselves Choice by pausing and knowing and recognizing what's happening
inside and then there's a opportunity for wisdom to make wiser choices of how
to live and maybe this example of breathing unpleasant in breath is
so such a minute mundane silly kind of example but what i cho I chose it for
that because it is a very small ordinary everyday kind of thing you most of you are breathing in all the time
regularly and so it's an ordinary thing but even right there there can be um uh
a developing growing the capacity to have this mindful pause mindful take
time to really know something and feel something but let alone when you're
driving uh driving is thing we're in the freeway is that not a few people have reactivity to what happens around you
some people are driving reactively because they've already
gotten in this mode have to hurry have to get somewhere they're already upset with everyone else and so the the very
way of driving is driving tense and so they're already kind of ahead of themselves by this force of
some reactive decision that they have and so even there we can say wait a
minute I'm tense I found it fascinating to watch
sometimes my right foot waiting for the red light to turn
green my right foot I I blame my
foot it has this kind of like Restless energy like you know let's
go judging my foot and blaming my foot is just one more way in which we don't
stop and look more deeply because it's not the foot there's something deeper in me that's that's gotten attached to or
afraid or eager or ambitious to get go somewhere need to get someplace quickly
so I'm living in the reactive mode and most people are doing that much of the
time what mindfulness does it gives us time to pause long enough that we can
think we can consider and we can see where there's Choice and then we can hopefully Choose
Wisely because we know something different so this is all fine and good
maybe this is kind of ordinary teachings on stimulus response but there's another
possibility that this allows and that is in that
space between stimulus and reaction and and even a a growing
possibility of a space between stimulus and response where we leave things
alone there's the opportunity for something to settle inside of us it's
opportunity to some begin to feel something deeper about ourselves that
arises from some depth inside that reactivity does not exactly where reactivity comes from
inside of us as may be different people experience it more differently uh I often think of it as
being kind of surface reactions sometimes it's from the neck up it has a
lot to do with goes on the mind and thoughts and ideas sometimes I think of it it has to do with the muscles
muscular system of who we are where reactivity is like want that get that push away that make something happen in
the world and um and so it's kind of more the surface and when reactivity is
strong it uh blocks our awareness of something deeper if we're constantly
living in reactive thoughts constantly living in a swirl of of thoughts and concerns and fears and angers and
resentments and betrayals and all this kind of world it it kind of
fills the attention so there's no space in the attention to
feel or sense something that's deeper that's Shyer that's not screaming for
attention so this opportunity to have a space between stimulus response allows
for some deeper connection to ourselves where in
Buddhism Buddhist teachings is the is the location out of which wisdom
comes it's location out of which Love Comes it's a
location out of which peace comes it's a location where a sense of well deep
well-being that's very nourishing can course through us coming from some deeper Place rather than these what I
call surface kind of places that and it takes time to settle in to relax some of
it has to do with relaxing the tensions we carrying in their muscle the tensions we have in our body I would
propose are all products of the reactive mind and the more tense we are the less
we can feel that which is below the tension Les we because or less we feel
how those muscles feel when there's no tension in them they might be totness in
them sometimes but there's no contraction no tightness they're not held in place
and the muscles then can start being part of a system of nourishment of
feeling nourished feeling goodness feeling warmth feeling kind of like the
these deeper wells Springs arise from within that feel like they're feeding us
supporting us in these good ways and this is one of the Miracles I
think of mindfulness is that that mindfulness makes room for some deep
sense of being alive to Bubble Up Inside that uh feels like just to be alive is
enough that feels like this is deeply satisfying in a way that a life of
Desire life of fixing it life of getting ahead a life of conceit life of trying
to prove oneself or get ahead or get behind or whatever we trying to
do it will never do for us because it those kinds of ways all too easily uh
are like uh are are um are never going to be
satisfying if we live always wanting something if that's the habit of
mind we can get something but the Habit is still there
as soon as we get it we want the next thing we want the next thing they want the next thing and it's kind of like
what I discovered sometimes if I stay too much surfing the web I'm just I'm minding my own business
kind of reading a few websites you know I'm
innocent but I've clicked on enough clicks that I can feel that now there's
a kind of a drive a desire and urge to click for the next thing I don't even know what the next thing is but there's
kind of an automatic kind of Wan thing to do do do so so it can be so even if we succeed
sometimes it can still be unsatisfying uh to build up uh to be
preoccupied with uh conceit is one of those things that limits this deeper
place inside that can well up that can't well up if we're somehow caught in the world of self-
preoccupation so this stimulus response allows for this upwelling of something
which I feel you can't really appropriate as your
own I mean it's not not anybody else's but the very movement this is who
I am you know let me show you who I am um that doesn't work because that is
this kind of uh suffocating or this tightening up or covering over of
something which doesn't really lend itself to being claimed as mine it's not anybody else's but you can
go along with you can be supported by it you can be guided by it you can choose to feel it and know it and tend
to it you can choose to know it and study it find out when it's wise maybe when it
doesn't seem wise when it's appropriate when it's useful so the stimulus response
distinction when it's really lived out in practice when mindfulness allows for
these longer pauses before even a response something really precious can
happen and that's one of the things that can happen in meditation for example and one of the great values of
meditation is that in uh in the minutes that you're meditating it's one of those
few times in life when
hopefully you don't have to say anything to anyone
you don't have to decide what to buy you don't have to move your body decide that
you know you don't have to there's so many things you don't have to do you don't have to you know plan your
menu for your meals for the next month you don't have to solve The World's
problems you you just have to be there and uh and then and all that that
allows you the option to let the gap between stimulus and
response be forever and what that means we trust
just being mindful of what's Happening pausing and knowing it without needing to
respond so if I have my uncomfortable in breath um I would just feel the
uncomfortable INB breath that's all I need to do if there is a thought this is a bad
in breath this is the wrong in breath I just can see let because
sometimes these reactions are some of these automatic parel things can just happen on their own anyway but I can just see that
oh and with time that ability to have this extended pause doesn't necessarily
stop some of the automatic ways in which the Mind might react to things but it takes the
power out of it the strength out of it it's just like it just this thought bubbling up oh this is a bad breath this
is a bad in breath just a it just like you know it has as much substance as a
hologram or something it doesn't really exist it just kind of comes and goes it's a cloud that comes and goes and
empty sky and uh and it feels like I don't have to get involved in it or do anything with it I just have this long
pause in which whatever happens inside of me uh doesn't require any response
doesn't require any judgments and has to be any different just let everything be liberated from
myself we free everything that happens within us from our reactivity our
judgments or what has to happen doesn't happen we just there if any but if there
is Choice it might be the choice of how to continue being mindful how to
continue to be aware to feel to sense what's happening as opposed to making an
anything happen fix anything without thinking about things and analyzing things just being present
just being there so meditation is a time to learn that and the more we can extend
that time the more there's a possibility to start feeling something deeper inside
show itself there's a deeper relaxation deeper calm deeper um subtleness that
happens that that brings us to a place that's below or
or very different from the place of reactivity the place of
automatic pilot that many people are living in Buddhism they glorify this
kind of way of being by calling it uh being awake uh and the other way they
sometimes call being asleep even though PE reactive people sometimes are hyper
awake hyper alert you know but you're not really they're not really here and
present for our life in a full embodied clear
way and uh it's a world of difference to live a life that comes
from this deeper response inside which is not the response of Me
Myself and mine there's this deep Wellspring inside
that can respond to the world that is not planned not thought out not
connected to our usual understanding of who I am not connected to our fears and our
Ambitions we have layers and layers of wise responses that can Bubble Up from
inside that can uh help us find our way a through this world that it helps us be
equanimous because we start seeing that the alternative to that
is not so desirable the alternative to this resting or being with or connected to
this deeper Wellspring inside uh diminishes us it Narrows us it
brings tension to us it brings tightness it brings suffering to us agitation to
us and and probably not a very good basis for wise choices about how to live
this life but this but if we settled in this deeper place a place where it's almost
as if we're not the one responding but it's wisdom that's responding chances
are we make will make much better choices for how to go through our life and it'll feel much more much more
have much more Integrity to it much more sense of being connected something more holistic within us than we can ever do
from the surface reactions that we have so to end this talk with
the uh you know to again to say this there's this very important distinction
between stimulus and response and what we're doing in mindfulness at least in mind meditation
is letting that gap between stimulus and response become longer how long it is depends what
you're doing if you're driving in the freeway probably shouldn't be very long
but if you're sitting in meditation maybe you know that you can actually give a lot of time and that g
the advantage of that is then you discover more about the depths of you who you are that you can't if you're
always responding even if you think it's wise so those are my thoughts for today
and now it's your turn to
respond how would you like to respond respond do you have any questions or comments
or on now right okay so as usual you've been a fly on the wall in my house and
of delivering just what I need to hear I don't know how you do that um
because we're we're all in certain certain ways we're kind of the same yeah
we so much so so much of how we our minds operate is a lot of but I so much
want to be unique
um so H how does this work in a
conversation because when I get triggered or reactive it's often when I'm talking to somebody else and I was
trying to imagine how to pause without looking like like I was uh not
understanding had gone to sleep rude whatever I just couldn't imagine how this works in a in a conversation
because that tends to be where I am frequently triggered I I see seems like an
important issue I think I'll have to think about that for a moment
[Laughter] let's could could you say that
again you know I'm a shrink we're always saying to people tell me more about that
but I'm not talking about those kinds of conversations no no I mean yes so maybe
for you there the danger for you is you start sounding like a shrink but uh but there are ways days of
slowing a conversation down that uh people don't feel like you're going slow and it's probably you know just just
just say even just a nod and say oh yes um and people will allow you a few
seconds and you can ask you know can I can I can I pause for a minute um and
then if you can't if you have to respond with something right away I don't know you say
something inconsequential so you have a chance to somehow your system to process
it okay I'll try I'll put in a plug for a mindfulness
teacher uh named orang Sofer um he wrote a book called say what you mean and he
has a couple of classes uh that you can do asynchronously but you can get a
partner and practice the bringing the mindfulness the non-violent communication and things like that into
your conversations so great yeah so Orin Sofer is great what he does he's made a
real specialty of mindful speaking and um and probably one of the things that's been most it's very hard
to to practice mindfulness and speaking so that I think it's often very diff you know it's a difficult place and uh so I
don't want to give the impression that it's easy but the probably the one thing that's
been most important for me in learning to do it is to stay connected to my body
mindfulness of the body the uh just feel feel the impact it has in my body feel
the impact it has um in my emotional life my emotional body and give time to
really know that because um to speak without being in touch with myself is
often not so useful so a kind of thing General thing of how i' like to live my life is to
have 50 if I'm a conversation with people is to have about 50% of my attention on what the person's saying my
partner in conversation and 50% on myself and uh and uh I've learned that
if I have a 100% attention to the other person without tracking what's going for me I don't really listen that well or
I'm listening for sure but um I'm not processing it because I don't see what
my reactions are my emotions we I don't see the filter through which it's going and um and if I have 100% of
myself um which is happens more often I like to admit like I have you know someone's
talking and my mind goes off into thought then I I'm no longer have to say to can you repeat that please because I
wasn't tracking but the idea 50/50 to really be there and then to also to feel
my body to my emotional body to see what thoughts arise the belief Bel arises to
ATT track both at the same more or less at the same time I think has been invaluable for living a wise life so
this 5050 guideline I also want to share something
briefly my uh I taught a 4-week mindfulness course online as part of a
program and my cousin uh lives in Boston and drives for ride shares and was
saying he was struggling with get getting angry and reactive and driving
and so he was practicing some of these type of um mindfulness of of that and
non-reactivity and uh he said it was really great and that he saved a lot of
gas money
also I've got a yes uh Gil during your talk um I found
myself remembering I cannot count how many times in the past I've um um in
conversation with other people when I feel like I've been at my best and when I feel like I I haven't been and um uh
and the ones the times when I haven't been I find myself going over and over and over those occasions so I how could
I have said that better or or been more um you know um more like an a mountain
posee instead of Leaning forward you speak a little louder you begin to f away oh
um thinking over and over again how how I could have uh said things better
instead of uh leaning forward or leaning back uh we're getting some feedback so
um and so uh but the one thing I want to say is when I've been at my best I'm a
lot happier and when I haven't been at my best you know I'm just not happy so
so maybe recognizing that kind of happiness will be is my um um my
teaching moment on on on how to be yeah it sounds great and uh mindfulness
practice has a tremendously important role for when you're at your best and
when you're at your worst both both are great times for
mindfulness okay thank you thank you and everything in between
so is this on can you hear me okay um so I find sometimes uh I get very reactive
as you say in daily life when you're interacting with people and when I sit I I don't feel anything and or there's
this big ball of stuff you know and I can't figure out what the under lying
thing is and you're probably going to just tell me to keep sitting with [Laughter]
it or not you know what you're raising is a
very important topic and it probably deserves more attention more
understanding than uh it's appropriate for me to give an appropriate response and uh you know to
say something that quickly just sit more seems to you know premature without
understanding a lot more what's going on for you but um generally uh the the kind of
generic kind of one generic kind of way of responding is that whatever it is including the big sitting quietly and
you nothing's happening the reactivity is not there but a big kind of swirl of something
Amorphis is um uh maybe there's something there for you to discover
so to bring a deeper attention to that or what's happening there and and it might be that if you feel your way into
the emotions that are present that that might be a doorway to understand something deeper about
you thank
you Gil thank you so much uh for this beautiful invitation and remind
Remer um I'm struck by how many times um
I have heard or I have offered a teaching like this to um to sit with
reactivity to notice it to invite the opportunity for response and yet this
morning felt like so fresh like the very first time I'd ever heard this and um I
just I wanted to to say how beautiful that was and and to thank you so much great that's nice to hear nice thank
you thank you for that talk and I just have a question
um how so sometimes when when I recognize a
reaction uh emotion especially like anger for example I can sit with it and
and and and try to try to just be with it um sometimes it
becomes a rumination a what sometimes it becomes a rumination rumination yes so
how can what what kind of what suggestion do you have to to um to avoid
you know to to to be able to sit with the different reactions emotions but not turn it into a
rumination yeah so it's a uh I might not be responding to you in the way that you
asked the question or what you're hoping to hear but I was struck by your use of
the word rumination to me that's a very significant word it's what cows
do and for you to for you to identify it as rumination means that you have a
certain Insight you have some you have some clarity or some wisdom about the particular kind of particular kind of
thinking that you call rumination what is the wisdom what is the benefit of seeing it as
rumination because you seem to identify that's what it is so what benefit comes
from having that kind of clarity I'm going to have to think about
that one but but the futility is one of the things that came up one of the I think
futility is one of the response that came up first ah so I I'll leave that for you to discover but I want to I want
to say that for you to have enough under self understanding to recognize it as
rumination you're seeing it as seeing that way of thinking is not not useful for you fule maybe even and um and
that's beginning of wisdom that's actually a good sign that you're seeing it that way if it's in fact not useful
for you and um and maybe to appreciate yourself
rather than focusing on the rumination as being the problem it is something to address and to learn about but begin to
appreciating yourself as the one who's now beginning to be mindful of it and beginning to kind of separate yourself
from it a little bit and beginning to see it and maybe we want to emphasize that movement in you rather than trying
to deal with the rumination which is what people want to do means you're still caught in it but just let's
appreciate for have you appreciate what's beginning to happen to you the
very fact that you can recognize it as rumination and recognize that you do it a lot and recognize that you're caught
in it you're beginning to separate out and becoming freeer let's emphasize that
movement so you begin feeling what that's like for you and do more of it and more of it and the day will
come two things will happen maybe can happen one is this the movement of
freedom of awareness the mind this this Clarity the freedom of mindfulness of rumination is so strong it's more
dominant more living thing in the moment than the
rumination and you in a sense you more you're living in the awareness now more than living in the rumination and that
feels good the other is if you use the metaphor of the hand for this movement
of you know first you were caught and then then you started to become a little bit separate separate until you were
free of it in a sense at some point you can go like
this and take that ruminating mind and just hold it gently and see what happens and maybe
then it begins to relax thank
you great so it's time to stop and I'm happy to stay up here and if you want to
come up and um if you're willing you uh it's you know you don't have to do this
but if you want to say hello to someone next to you that would be nice before you leave some people might be new here
today and uh and then you know but thank you for being here