so good morning everyone and welcome or good day for those of you on other time
zones and um
so in this ex exploration of the
the first of the three major insights of insight meditation
I'll continue talking about inconstancy change
and impermanence the coming and going of experience
and for meditation one of the really important milestones in meditation
is coming to a really clear understanding clear insight
if you may if I may of
how much time we spend thinking
how much time we spend viewing our experience ourselves what's
important through the lens of thoughts and thinking most thinking is about
something and so we live in a world of aboutness
rather than living in a world of immediacy a a world of sensation sensing
and even if we are sensing and more or less in the present moment and feeling deeply what's going on even there
there's subtle conceivings valuing prioritizing
selecting of the experience that goes on even sometimes subvocally or sub
subconsciously almost in us that gives us a kind of kind of uh holding on to
experience a kind of momentum of of preoccupation momentum of of um
raifying or solidifying some concern that we have
and uh and the most extreme versions would be to um be lost in thought about
something that just seems insurmountable seems permanent seems like this is the
way it's going to be forever and it's terrible or wonderful or something
and so to see how much the time we spend there so that we could can experience our life
in meditation in a very different way it's almost like a paradigm shift
from see looking at our life through the lens of our concepts
to feeling our life through the flow of
changing sense experience
and uh and to relax the thinking mind to soften the tension that is behind a lot
of thinking we go we do the momentum to settle and relax the body relax
what's going on so we're not forcing ourselves to enter into the world of
change but we naturally settle into it and feel
it and become it and one of the insights that's possible
as we stay close to the world of the phenomenal world the world of direct
experience of everything including thoughts is to appreciate how much
under the surface of our projections and raifications
how much
Things change arise and pass and in the passing
there is a hint of freedom
a freedom from preoccupation a freedom from being
entangled with experience reacting to experience
a freedom of simplicity a freedom of a heart and mind
that is unpreoccupied and that when something ends
that absence of something is overlooked in the dharma we don't overlook the
absence that follows the ending of something we appreciate the spaciousness
the peacefulness the stillness that might be found there so in this
meditation notice endings
and the absence of what just ended not because it's sad or because it's you
miss something but the experiential in the moment
space silence openness stillness
silence that might be there even if it's momentary momentary
so assuming a meditation posture
and right as you close your eyes there's a ceasing an ending
of being involved in the visual world of sight
in settling into a meditation posture there's the ending of a certain degree
of movement and moving around
breathing and settling into your posture there's the ending of certain
large tensions or holdings maybe if the shoulders relax
the belly relaxes
can you readjust your arms and hands to allow something to relax and soften
feeling the rhythm of how the body expands and contracts
as you breathe
the movements of the belly and diaphragm as you breathe
maybe the movement the tingling of air going in out through your nostr nostrils
and kind of with a gentle massage of that rhythm of breathing
on the exhale relax your thinking mind
soften
Maybe as just quiet your quiet your thinking mind calm it in a quiet
way of thinking it's a way of letting go of all other
thoughts gently on the exhale
quietly on the exhale whisper to yourself the word yes
yes to letting go of thoughts
yes to letting go into the body
and as we're sitting here meditating
a lot of things are no longer happening for you in this
moment there's more things that you are not thinking about
more things than you're not clinging to than you're preoccupied with
they appreciate the absence
when something is not present a degree of freedom is found there
peace spaciousness
gently calmly stay close to the comingings and goings
of sensations thoughts feelings
appreciating the moments of absence
when awareness is not feeling or sensing
something that was being experienced
At the end of the inhale There's a momentary absence
of the inhale that allows the beginning of the exhale
but between the inhale and the exhale there's a momentary
absence stillness spaciousness
being free of any sensation of breathing
the end of the exhale same thing
when you're very quiet you'll see that thoughts are not
continuous
there's little gaps and pauses and little moments when the mind is
distracted by sound or sensations
moments where awareness is free
of what we were thinking feel
those moments
in the coming and going of sensations experience
with a going of it you might feel
how the then there is a non-involvement with what was
at any given moment there's what the mind is involved in
and there's a vast spaciousness
of all the things it's not involved in
expand your sense of awareness into the spaciousness the peacefulness
of non-involvement
at any given mo moment
there are things that have passed sensations and sounds and thoughts
were shifted
we're no longer the center of attention
let go of what was
let go of what is not in the direct experience
of the moment
so there is more space and openness
for what comes next
and as we come to the end of the sitting
maybe you can appreciate the opport opportunity that endings
provide as much as there might be a loss
in the dharma there's a greater benefit in the freedom in this peace
in the openness freshness
that's there with the absence of what was
if we can let go of what was a moment ago
endings provide an opening into freedom
and as we in and openings and endings
ending of preoccupation ending of projections and agendas
even if it's temporary allows us to meet others in a fresh way
open way may it be that this practice we do shows
us teaches us how to be present for others
with a fresh awareness an open awareness a peaceful awareness of what is
so we're not preoccupied by what was or what we carried with us
into the meeting
may endings support deeper connection deeper care
for this world because we know people better
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this 15th talk on insight
and this week has been a um
a exploration of the topic of anicha the poly word a n i ca
and it's usually translated as impermanence which tends to emphasize the ending of
things that things will stop and cease and no longer be there the poly word
more literally means inconstancy meaning that uh things are not constantly there but they come and go
and some things are obvious the um meals come and go days come and
go daytime comes and goes mornings come and go uh meditation sessions come and
go all kinds of things come and go and they return the next day they return the
next hour the inhale comes and goes but and it's but it's always there in a
sense so it's in constant and um and a lot of the deeper insight
of meditation a lot of the wisdom ordinary wisdom of being a human being
appreciates that things are impermanent that things do sooner or later stop and
disappear and to learn how to be wise about that compassionate about that
and there's also this deeper truth that's not seen as clearly is the
inconstency of things one reasons we don't see it so obviously
or live in it so much is we tend to be focused so much on one thing there's a
tremendous raification tremendous preoccupation that mind has
the preoccupation of the moment can can um can feel like it's constant
the And the uh the metaphor that's used for this kind of illusion of constancy that
involves a very busy and active mind is um it's called monkey mind and this is
the mind that is u a monkey is swinging through from branch to branch in the
forest in the jungle and um before it's let go of one branch it's already
reaching to grab the next one so it's always one way or the other involved in
grasping reaching for and take holding on to and um and it might let go but be
uh of one to grab you know in grabbing the next but the preoccupation is
already in the grabbing of the next doesn't notice the letting go
and uh and so what the in a sense what the mind is involved in is always with a
grasping so grasping can seem like it's constant but in fact it comes and goes
and when we sit down in meditation and start and calm ourselves and get clear
and clear with the mindfulness we start seeing um among other things uh the grasping
mind and how it reaches and wants but we see the gap between it we see the
arising of a thought rather than seeing thoughts as continuous we see that
thoughts come and go we see that sensations come and go and with a deeper
and deeper calm samadei of meditation there's a shift to in the direct moment
of being just here in the direct experience now here just here and and
it's we start entering into the river of change there's the river of inconstancy
and that can be very satisfying and it can be very absorbing to be in that
but there's a pos an opportunity there that we see moment to moment things are
coming and going and um moment to moment uh in that stream things arise and pass
and seeing the passing of things seeing the ending of things uh gives for all
the loss it might entail also provides opportunity
and one of those opportunities there's number and that is that uh the mind
unless we're involved with memory and caught in it the in the moment what's
not there uh creates space and openness in the mind unless the mind reaches for the
next branch and um so
as you're thinking about something and a particular
thought ends And before the next thought begins
between the ending of one and the beginning of the next
without using thoughts to answer the question who are you
what is awareness like between thoughts what is awareness like
between ex beginning of the end of one experience and the beginning of next
there might be if you might feel a degree of peace a degree of spaciousness
stillness a degree of non-clinging non and so at some point in practice we
start be beginning appreciated appreciating the ending of things
or we appreciate the endings and it can be disorienting because in the ending of
something we're so used to having something that we're orienting ourselves to or holding on to or some way of being
that we are this is who I am but in the flow of arising and passing and uh some
people then get disoriented well I'm if I'm not there you know if if I don't have a thought
telling me who I am then who am I if I'm not holding on to something or
preoccupied by something then how am I going to be safe and so there's a kind of a beginning of
exploration a beginning of of uh of um finding a certain kind of peace comfort
letting go in the the the the certain
kind of freedom that's there with the absence with things it's kind of like as
things arise and pass we see in the passing that right there there's the
opportunity not to cling right there there's nothing to cling to there's nothing to resist nothing to do
nothing to push against nothing to be
and so part of the emphasis part of the what comes along almost in a natural way
nothing we have to do about it is as we start settling more and more into the
impermanent inconstant nature of direct experience
and the I'm going to underline direct experience not uh um thought about experience
if we're if we're thinking about experience the thinking gives all kinds of other uh impressions of what's
actually happening it can give an impression of more constancy more solidity
so it's not the continu continuity of thinking about experience it's the continuity of the direct experience kind
of under underneath the thinking level and we start to see there's freedom
there there's freedom in floating along in the current of change and there's
freedom in the spaciousness and the openness of um when when things end
and um so in the teachings of the Buddha there are some places where uh he emphasize that when something uh uh when
the hindrances for example when greed or hatred aversion desires
when um doubts when anxiety and fear when these things kind of uh come to
some kind of end um uh don't just go on to the next
branch don't just go on to the next clinging take a few moments to feel the
absence of that feel the goodness of that feel the
spaciousness or some of the characteristics of that absence
so monkey mind doesn't take the time to feel the simplicity of being
when we certain things have been put down we just go on to the next thing to
cling to and be involved in and meditation is one of those times where
we're beginning to appreciate very deeply all the things we've put down all
the things that we've let go of in meditation settled away relaxed into and
the absence of those things uh is a freshness the absence of those things there's a kind of freedom there and one
of the things to appreciate one of the things that's remarkable in
how it leads to greater and greater freedom is to appreciate the ending of
things the absence of things how things are not there even if it's momentary or
maybe it's more extended um and and then it gives you the opportunity to be careful
not to reach for the next branch not to fill yourself with more presence of
things but appreciate the absence and ab and so absence is a little bit
can be more expansive and spacious so that when we go through our lives
and we are we do know something we do feel something and sense something we're
not locked into it but rather we feel it in a wider
uh field atmosphere of calm of peace of freedom of non-clinging
and so rather than being a monkey swinging grabbing one branch up to the
other we come become more like a graceful soaring bird
where the vast empty sky holds our wings up as we float fly through and see
all the changing things in our life from the vantage point of all the space that's here as well
so I hope this um discussion about um seeing endings seeing the absence of
things seeing the uh is understandable to you and it gives
you an appreciation of of u not just uh the
the negative part of absence not just the the beginning of something new but
something in that ending of something that allows something expansive to be
there and as that expansive freedom is there then it's much easier to be with
the challenging parts of impermanence and change and this life human life
so thank you and um so we'll continue with this uh series on insight in a few
weeks i'm going to be away on vacation uh for this next week
and uh and I'll come back and uh be here again on the 30th Monday i think
I'll still be in my vacation place that time but I'll teach that morning and and
then I'll be back here at IMC the next day so thank you very much and I look
forward to coming back in in a little over a week