so hello again from Spirit Rock Meditation Center and uh this is the
last morning I'll be here for this time and uh it's been a
wonderful time with my three teachers Tueri Salah and Darra Williams
and Kyra jewel lingo and
uh and also with the retreatance here and all of spirit rock it's a
wonderful place to practice as you see in these wonderful uh kind of rolling hills behind
me we're nestled into these hills and spend much of the time when we have to
go between places outdoors and as you can also see these days if you've been following the
weather changes quite a bit and that's part of the joy of uh being at Spirit
Rock being outdoors and um I've been here many many years over you know guess
I've been coming here for 35 years and no matter what the weather is I'm happy
hot cold stormy so welcome to the meditation and
Um and uh one of the characteristics factors that come into play in
meditation that stands out in a highlight uh in the third Janna is
equinimity uh it becomes even more significant in the fourth Janna but it already appears
here and uh together with mindfulness with sati
awareness and clear recognition clear comprehension
sajana and um and uh equinimity
and one of the meanings of the word upa
equinimity is to have kind of an overview a bird's eyee view of our
situation how we are at the moment the current experience that puts it into a wider
context that allows us to hold it in a spacious way hold it
generously hold it without getting caught in any reactivity the reactivity of being for
and against the activity of translating the experience into a
story a prediction of the future without the reactivity that wants
to assign meaning to the experience
or the orientation to measure the experience or relate the experience to
uh ideas of me myself
mine this is who I am
just this wide spacious overview with no inclinations to have
thoughts about who am I what am I where am
I because the overview the broad perspective the spacious open
perspective feels so complete
so satisfying that none of the
reactivity is needed we see that we feel that we know that for the time of the
meditation we understand there's something much better to do in this wide
aquamus overview uh that sees and knows
but allows each thing to be itself and the metaphor for the third Janna that we
talked about yesterday is um lotus
flowers and in a certain kind of way everything becomes a
flower it's seen that way in this kind of aquinomous open
expansive view of a third so to assume a meditation
posture and while you're sitting establishing your
posture see if there are small adjustments you can make that soften your posture
that settles your
body and oddly enough maybe there's a way
of being well aligned in the posture that allows for a deeper
relaxation if we relax everything
seemingly we can't relax the most
so and if you haven't already to gently close your
eyes taking a few deeper
longer inhales and exhales to begin entering
into the body meditating
and letting your breathing return to normal
and to orient yourself around the
body as if it's the body that's meditating as if it's the
body that generates awareness
maybe through the way the body can sense
sensations the broad fields of sensing in the
body and in that broad field of sensing in the
body there's the movement the sensations of breathing
and perhaps with every exhale let it be an
opening a widening of awareness through the
body open to possibilities open to what's there
and with every inhale also in
opening the awareness wide broad field of sensing field of
awareness open to possibilities open to what's here
without the need to think about it in
fact appreciating that by
suspending thinking discursive
thinking you become more open more sensitive
through the field of
sensations and the vast space around sensations around your body
the space of awareness within
which the body meditates
letting go of thinking as you exhale and letting go
into the body the field of awareness
open to A spacious field of
sensing
awareness as you inhale letting your
thoughts float away
and again open to the spacious
awareness of what is here and now as the body
meditates the body senses
And the mind the quiet mind
provides an openness to the vast space all
around the sensations of the body meditating
[Music]
just like the sky is not disturbed by a cloud that
drifts through it
so the field of
awareness is not disturbed by whatever is known
the feel of spaciousness around all
things does not react to
anything everything is like a cloud drifting through or like a flower lotus
flower floating in the vast
waters of the body's lake
one of the qualities of the third Janna for all the
Janna is to abide to dwell here
to rest in whatever goodness whatever is
good in this meditation
and to consider that whatever that's good in
this meditation
As you enter the world making contact
with things of the world the people of the
world it makes a difference to contact them through
this field of goodness it's very
different than encountering the world and people through our field of reactivity
and judgment
may it be that all that is really good in you
the goodness the calm the peace the
love is in the forefront of how you encounter the
world may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may all beings be loved
loved by the goodness of our
hearts and if it helps you to love
more no one needs to know you're loving
them but you are with your goodwill your care
compassion may all beings be loved
so thank you and again without the bell end the
sitting with a bow
so hello everyone and welcome to this next talk on the samadei series
And it's um the third talk on the third Janna
and um as we go deeper into absorptions
deeper into a unified concentrated absorbed
state the experience of our body begins to change
and one of the ways that I unders I've come to understand this at first maybe
through my own practice I started to feel that the these immersive
states I would leave my karmic body behind and that one of the bodies we can
experience is our karmic body and that's the body that we feel
and sense sense that is a product or a byproduct of our
reactivity the ways we've reacted to the world the way that we have resisted
tightened tensed by the world and now you might want to blame
the world for the ways in which you are tense or afraid or
um uh contracted and that's
okay but still it's something which the mind the inner life is doing the
contraction the tension the holding on the resisting and um and it's very deep and
it should be have tremendous respect and care and carefulness around this karmic
body we have this body that's conditioned uh
by the regularity or the frequency in which we think the same thought over and
over again if you re repeatedly think that you are somehow
inadequate it becomes kind of a self-fulfilling prophecy because if it's
repeated enough it's just depressing it just kind of drains us and so that draining the drain body I
would call the karmic body if what you love to do is to watch
horror movies and uh the excitement and thrill and livveness of being
afraid and you do that enough and in fact you tell yourself horror movies in
your own mind then that you have a a fearful body
the fear body is predominant some people live in their fear body
and that's I call a karmic body it's a body that's
somehow been shaped by the reactivity of the
mind and um as we go through as we settle and get
more and more focused concentrated unified relaxed the the the
the ways in which the body is tightened up tensed up knotted up held tight
become rigid the fear body the anger body the the desire body
the grief body that things have gotten so conditioned that we're kind of like
living almost like we become that body but that begins to loosen up as we go
deeper into meditation we kind of that falls to the side that no longer is operating for us
and um it's not a loss of who we are it's like taking off a coat that is o
become overly heavy or overly hot as the weather warms
up we no longer need it and uh and sometimes this uh leaving
the karmic body behind um the body feels very different and the
third third gen Janna one of the ways of understanding it that it's a happy body
happiness body that uh it's it's saturated the
body is filled with a kind of happiness where the karmic body is no longer
operating sometimes I've called it the adam the diamond body the
adamantine body because it feels so clear and solid but transparent all the
way through like a jewel and um and sometimes the the in going through the
Janna the posture of the body changes and uh sometimes it gets very
aligned and sometimes you can actually feel the body aligning itself with the
concentration it's almost like there's an energetic force in the body that kind
of lifts the spine opens the chest and um you feel very present and I call that
kind of the karmic that I call that the the diamond body and um sometimes some people might
call it kind of an energy body that happens because all that's left is this tingling flowing vibrating field of
energy seemingly And um so as we leave this karmic body
behind we're leaving behind our con the ways that we've we've been conditioned
by the world by our own behavior our own thoughts by the influence of
others and um and
um and it can be very healing it's one of the reasons why these Janna are
prescribed sometimes because they have such a deep there's such deep medicine
for the heart the mind it touches kind of the very deep subconscious places
that are very hard to otherwise contact and so the usual instructions that or at
least that I'm familiar with or at least value a lot when if you're fortunate
enough to begin to go through these jas uh do it slowly don't be in a hurry to
get somewhere uh because the idea is to allow yourself to be reconditioned to
allow yourself to feel the goodness of it the he the healing of it allow your
def to kind of uh get a very different message into your heart into your body
than the message of danger or the message of being left out or the message of not
good enough it's all these messages that we live with that are not so healthy for us and to be able to have this other way
of receiving a different healthy message is one of the values of these deep
states so uh in this um happiness body of the third genre
karmic body conditionality the conditioning we have the reactivity we have really settles
dramatically then there's a lot less orientation
potential for being reactive and what what comes what
becomes clear what stands out and highlight instead is
equinimity and the equinimity that is not for or against something that's not
wanting or not wanting something the equinimity just allows each thing that
arises to be there like the sky allows a
cloud to be in the middle of the vast
sky uh or like a vast sky allows a bird
to fly through it and the sky is not disturbed it's not for against the bird
it's just vast kind of space and non-reactivity openness to whatever
comes the metaphor of u Buddhism it's often that of a path Buddhist practice
and uh a path is a clearing in the forest that's open so we can walk
through it and uh so the path is to a great degree defined by the absence the
openness the emptiness that's there above maybe the physical trail that's
there but the path includes this open space and a path in the woods the open
space is not disturbed by you walking through it so the mind so awareness so
this happiness body allows everything just to be there in the quiet aquinomous
mind in uh and for me uh very closely associated with this is the feeling of
spaciousness as if there's lots of space around each individual thing
the for the Buddha it seems to be rather than space it's kind of similar but it's
the vast space that's underwater in a lake and um
there the space has a kind of viscosity it has a certain kind of kind
of you know little bit of weight little bit of physicality to it that you feel
the contact of the water against the skin and um maybe the refreshing
comfortable temperature and stillness of the water and um and so it's not just simply
empty space but in the third Janna it kind of feels like it's you know this
wonderful soothe kind of texture
or viscosity or soft
butter of spaciousness in which we are as breathing or
being and um and so one of those characteristics
of that spaciousness
this vast water is um is a feeling of
contentment happiness kind of a deep but it's physical the body just feels like
it's maybe almost like the body is beginning to disappear getting very soft
or has no boundaries but the body is kind of saturated or filled with
feelings of pleasure and some people some translators prefer to translate suka in the third genre not
as happiness but as pleasure because it's so
embodied and um and for me at least pleasure just doesn't seem to capture
how good it is how wonderful it is so I prefer happiness but for some people
happiness is too complicated a state and so maybe pleasure is
Or or maybe contentment is um is um the middle way for these words
deep deep contentment or satisfaction so
equinimity not equinimity from understanding something but an equinimity of uh being larger than
everything the awareness is large and spacious and open that uh it's has room
for what's happening here and now giving breathing room to all things so you
might today as you go through your day find times through the day to give
breathing room space to what's happening and notice how it's a thinking
mind maybe the reactive mind that narrows the space of awareness narrows
that makes sometimes a claustrophobic mind that's much more
um affected uh troubled by what's happening and
maybe by giving breathing room and opening up expanding outwards you get some of
the benefit peacefulness or happiness or at least
equinimity of a spacious open wide awareness may your day be one
of we'll continue this series tomorrow uh tomorrow I'll be at IMC
And I think I'll miss a little bit being here on this rolling grasslands
outside and u and so thank you very much
[Music]