if you look there underneath that tree the closest tree branch there's a little little in
the picture here for me but a very big white egret that's up in the grass
hunting for something and that egret's been living here at Spirit Rock
for for um some for a year or so so it's well
known it's been given a name and uh yesterday it was
about right next to where I'm staying here so maybe it'll come into the
picture later
someone asked for the name uh the is called Paul
so hello everyone and welcome to Spirit Rock Spirit Rock Hillside that is
um and I think uh behind me uh in this direction is up
in the hills there is the Spirit Rock meditation the actual meditation hall
from where I'm teaching a retreat today this this week and uh one of the ways
that Spirit Rock is designed is that um uh you have to be outdoors to go between
almost anything and so there's a constant going outdoors and experiencing
the land the sky the weather the turkeys
the different animal yesterday there was a beautiful day before yesterday there
was a really beautiful healthy looking coyote stalking the hillsides up here
and uh and now I showed some of you there was this white egret that's been
here so uh welcome and for the meditation today
um and on continuing the exploration of samadei
uh the descriptions of the janna each of them has a is different but they all
contain a similar wording and that is one enters and abides in these states of
being and so this idea of it's entering it's not staying apart it's not staying
up in the head looking down but it's dipping into it's entering um and one
way from that I understand this or helps to understand it it's entering into an embodied
state but an embodied state that is not
exactly our physical body but rather the the sensations in the body that are born
from the meditation from being settled from being connected
being unified calm clear just as if you get angry you can
feel new body sensations in your body and if you enter those difficult sensations maybe you'll be more angry
so when we start getting kind of more and more involved with meditation then
there are these uh samadei sensations that we can enter
in abide in which I take to be rest in enter and rest in them so this resting
is very different than pushing or wanting more or trying to have something happen um it's closer to enter and be in
them a kind of sense of beingness resting in them um abiding in
them and then one more step that uh is not in exactly in the text but it's my
interpretation of the classic instructions and that is to
open to some of these sensations direct experiences that come
with meditation that have to do with u
well-being joy happiness uh delight contentment
and um open to it so that it seems to have more space in the body so there
it's an embodied opening so we enter into the maybe very
subtle at first sensations that seem connected or associated with
meditation and rest in them and open for them to become more expansive to open up
to spread throughout their whole being so to
enter abide and open so assuming a meditation
posture
and and I recommend that you close your eyes
and with your eyes closed to feel and
sense maybe some of the leftover or
associated experience of feelings of delight or awe or openness in seeing the
hillside sides in the sky behind
me if that somehow had an influence on your body
your heart your mind let that be
there however subtle it is and the art of entering into
it and if it just simply assuming your meditation posture if it's
familiar there there's a contentment there is
a familiarity there's a
relief there's a lot of some kind of good feelings that can
be assuming our meditation posture feel those in the
body and enter into
them or lower yourself into them in the
body rather than associating yourself with the efforts and the
choices and the strivings of the mind the brain up in the head up in the
control tower drop down into the
body into the middle maybe like it's a
lake of whatever subtle small
mild good feelings there might be
and if it's uh accessible in the middle of that
or deeper deeper underneath it or around it become aware of your body
breathing aware of the expansion and contraction of your torso as you
breathe and that the impulse to breathe
in is inside the breathing itself the breathing body
enter into your breathing to feel that impulse
the movement the expansion of breathing in
as you exhale let that be a settling into your
body entering your body like you would enter a refreshing
lake to the water
as you exhale relaxing any tension or pressure in the thinking
mind letting go of your thinking
and doing so by letting go
into whatever good feelings there are in your body even if you
feel off or feel uncomfortable anywhere in your body
for now see if you can drop yourself into that which is pleasant
with a very modest idea of what that
is breathing
naturally maybe some point in the cycle of [Music]
breathing there's something pleasant [Music]
Enter and abide in
[Music]
[Music] and if in the course of this meditation you get pulled into your
thoughts notice how that might be pulling you away from an
intimacy of your body and those sensations wholesome sensations of just
sitting here let go of your thoughts and allow yourself to enter
settle into the pleasant enjoyable
sensations abide in those as you breathe breathing through it with it around
[Music]
it and open the body open the heart
open up so that the pleasant sensations the
good feelings the joy can spread through your
Buddy in these three steps rest enter abide and open
done very very gently kindly
softly as if you have all the time in the world
at each
step encouraging the thinking mind to be
quieter letting go of thoughts in
favor of a more intimate
Connection to the goodness of this moment in your body
enter abide and open
maybe an opening of all your senses nothing left
out but you abiding at the center of it
all abiding in the center of all the well-being that's available
letting it spread through your body
[Music]
and if during the time of this
meditation your body feels more subtle more calm
If you feel a greater contentment or ease in any
way if there's a joy
enjoyment in your body of meditating however small it might be
Enter into it drop into the embodied experience of
it letting your body feel it sense it more fully
abide in it rest in whatever good feelings wholesome
feelings there are sitting here
meditating and open to those feelings
open beyond the edges of him so they either expand
spread or so that there's no
boundaries no edges to the good feelings
enter abide open
[Music]
and then opening your body your heart your
mind beyond your meditation beyond where you
are out across the lands
cross the hillsides the forest the trees the oceans the lakes the skies the
clouds and allow your good will
allow a kind of inner seeing that sees all
things with kindness with [Music]
care a care where we want to care for what cares for us
so much on this earth is constantly caring for
us providing oxygen food
may it be that the way the purpose the
dedication of regular meditation practice
is to contribute to a better world starting with
ourselves that brings forth a better us
brings out the best in us so we can share that with the
world spreading kindness compassion support care for the whole
world may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free thank you and with this bow I we
end this meditation
[Music]
so welcome to our next talk on samadei on the last
talk on the second Janna and
um most people who experience the second Janna feel that it's much more
satisfying than the first Jonah and um there is maybe a little bit
of evaluation in the mind with the first Janna kind of a sense of relief of not
being caught in the thinking mind the desiring mind the aversive mind anymore
and um the um and um so there's a abled ability to
kind of just be in the experience itself in a deeper way it's not in
reference to what we've left behind and how good it is to no longer be caught up
in the hindrances and um and so things get the thinking mind the act the active mind
becomes quieter and quieter pe more peaceful more open and there's virtually
no thinking uh and uh one of the ways to kind of
move into this or enter into it is to begin appreciating the difference
between ordinary thinking uh conversational thinking commentarial
thinking um thinking with words and uh or images and begin
appreciating that there are nonverbal ways of knowing we could know
without there needs to be thoughts that tell us so and so when we get into these deeper
states of samadei uh there is a kind of a knowing there is a deeper place inside
that maybe even guides us a little bit because it knows stay here enter here be
present um and um this is good but
there's there's no there the the ordinary verbally thinking or vision
vision making kind of thinking that goes on for some has gotten quiet it's taken a wonderful
delightful vacation finally it could rest and um and but still there can
bring a deeper knowing that somehow keeps us connected here in the present
moment a kind of nonverbal knowing and
um and uh it's that kind of knowing that recognizes the the joy and the happiness
that characterizes the second chamom so the pity the poly word and suka the poly
word that I translated as joy and happiness and uh people other people who
um practice jannaas um sometimes they're not happy with me using the word joy uh
and happiness because they feel like generally that's too modest that it should be something
more like rapture or um and bliss
but as we get into this uh deeper especially in the in the second Janna it
becomes um important to uh open to the joy and the happiness when it's there
the joy and happiness of being fully engaged fully involved with no distractions with the with the practice
itself it's such a wholesome feeling feels like there's such a rightness being here and now and that
they it feels so complete like this is good this is a this feels more deeply
satisfying than a lot of things that people can experience in life and um and so there are these two
things uh joy and happiness and um and it and as this
second gen matures matures means we become more familiar with it the joy and the
happiness spreads it becomes more fully embodied uh we open to it more that um
uh we start seeing the distinction the difference between the joy and the
happiness until this point uh we talk about joy and happiness but maybe we
don't really see they just kind of mingle together and there's no real difference between them but as
everything gets quieter and calmer um and the thinking mind becomes even
quieter and softer And the excitement of uh that um very subtle but excitement of
of um of of you know entering into these states begins to abate uh we can start
seeing the difference between the joy and the happiness and one of the common
ways to uh see it is um that the joy is a little bit more
mental whereas the happiness is more a little
bit more physical now the physical sensations of the joy can be quite
strong some people kind of are a little bit confused to hear that it's it's more of the mind than it is of the body but
the uh there's a kind of a mental um excitement you start feeling there's a
there's a mental uh thrill a mental kind of uplift energy excitement ah this is
good oh yes ah not that we say those words to ourselves but there's a little
bit kind of energy like that and um and that energy is a higher level of
activity of excitement than the happiness and the happiness
is almost like a very deep contentment in the body it's a very deep sense of
well-being that um uh the mental excitement or the mental activation of
joy is is no longer there and now and and with the mental activation of joy
the sensations in the body tend to be a little bit more stronger more active and
sometimes quite active quite strong like big waves of bliss that kind of wash
over us sometimes um it feels like a lot of lot of
movement um but with the happiness the movement and the it feels like a gentle
hum or vibration or or warmth or it might still feel like there's a flow but
the flow feels very harmonious within us and um there isn't any of the subtle
maybe not so subtle excitement of the joy and um so as the second genre matures uh
there's a being able to distinguish these two uh becomes very useful in
terms of moving further um into the third genre which we'll discuss I'll discuss with uh next
week and um and so uh learning to feel
the distinction or the difference between joy and happiness becomes part
of the task as we go deeper into this meditation into the Janna's and
um and uh but either way don't be in a hurry uh it's best with Janna's never in
a hurry um take all the time in the world to become familiar to feel it to
look around uh to spread whatever goodness there is to enter
into to abide this idea of abiding is means we're not in a
hurry and um and opening and opening so that um
uh and the quote from the classic traditional
teachings so that the p practitioner fills pervades saturates and permeates
this body with a joy and happiness born of concentration so no part of the body
is not touched and this um expression this body
um uh is is not referring to kind of the
ordinary physical body we might think about but rather the body
uh that we experience in meditation itself in a kind of way um the the experience
we have of our body is very much conditioned by our mind uh except when
there's the physical pain of the body is quite intense they would acknowledge
that that was not mindmade but so many of the sensations
in our body have a very close strong conditioning very strongly conditioned
by the quality the characteristics of our mind our posture shifts and changes with the moods of our minds the
preoccupations what we kind of the negativity bias we have sometimes brings us into parts of our body where we're
reacting to them or pushing them away or have aversion certain emotions um and
attitudes cause a lot of tension in the body and so as we meditate and the mind
became softer mind becomes more relaxed not no longer preoccupied no longer
caught in things then um the body responds accordingly and and it's you
start feeling a very different feeling in the body and it's almost like we have two different bodies we have the body in
ordinary life and we have the body the samadei body that uh kind of glows and is
luminous and light and open and um has a very different
sensation and so to appreciate enter into this kind of different body even
when just the feelings of it are just beginning to happen and uh enter into it
help it support you to um be willing to put down put to rest the ordinary
thinking mind enter into the state the feelings the sensations enter abide rest
in it resting in it so it can kind of spread so it can kind of you can
appreciate it you can be nourished by it you can let it registered in a deep way
let it recondition you in a nice way and then open to the goodness of it open to
the joy and the happiness to of it and then next week when we start the third
Janna um we'll talk about this distinction between the joy and the happiness becomes particularly important
uh because the joy will fade away and we'll be able to enter and abide uh in
the happiness of meditation of the Jonas so
um so in the meantime uh you might want to over this weekend
um keep these three uh steps in mind maybe throughout the day as much as you
can maybe have a sticky note that you put on something that reminds you um
enter abide and open and just see if you
can do that in ordinary life everyday life uh maybe when you drive someplace
and you arrive don't get out of your car right away sit there a little bit and um
relax enter abide and open
if you're standing in a in a line in a supermarket uh don't
read the you know the headlines on the news that's there rather stand there
maybe with your eyes closed but looking down enter abide and open with what's
happening here for you and maybe being attuned to what is good and right right now that you want to be attuned to if
you're just in your thoughts thinking a lot enter and abide and open through the
weekend and then we'll go further on Monday so thank you very much and uh
I'll still be here at Spar Rock Monday Tuesday and Wednesday and um you'll get
to see these wonderful uh hillsides here to
see a little bit the my view out of my I'm sitting outside my little room and
this is these hills and behind that forest there up that up up further up
there are the two spirit rock meditation
halls so So there's actually
96 people in the retreat probably like 110 people living here you would know
that from all the all the grasslands
so thank you