greetings friends it's uh it's a lovely afternoon here in Tuscanyany and it was
nice to uh start with the bells with the church bells so hello hello hello good
morning good afternoon bonjoura bonera whatever time zone you're in
wherever in this beautiful world of ours you're in
um as I say that I think of the the um the lyrics what a wonderful world you
know it's a challenging world it's a beautiful world it's 10,000 joys 10,000
sorrows So wonderful to be with you in this
moment in time as we come together in this um community in this beautiful community
that we have that we've come together as as maybe you've been coming uh to this
teaching for many many sessions many weeks many years or if you're new
welcome welcome welcome let's welcome ourselves let's welcome each other i so
appreciate the spirit of of welcoming and welcoming each other as we as I see
in the chat all the good mornings and good afternoons and um all the greetings
so so so continuing with our theme this
week the theme of SA um one of the triple jewels one of the
most important aspect of practice community friendship spiritual
friendship noble friendship good friendship kalana mittita good
friendship and we've been practicing in those aspects the past couple of days and
today I want to continue with this theme and today I want to explore the theme of
ethical empathy which is the foundation um of of friendship of kindness of meta
of compassion which is putting ourselves in someone else's shoes
whether it's in friendship whether it's in challenging situations exploring
those so with that um I'd like to invite us into a um
meditation as always we'll start by settling
arriving landing um in our bodies with the breath
and um and then I will share some reflections for us to drop in to drop in
into our bodies uh to work with so so with that um let's let's begin let's uh
assume our uh our posture our meditation
posture and arriving oh by the way before we start um internet can be a
little um uh how should I say it a little uh choppy here so I will be
opening my eyes down and just to make sure I'm still uh on Zoom and YouTube
and if for some reason it it goes down I will restart it so just so you know that
it might be challenging so here we go okay let's get started let's get started with our
meditation arriving arriving and landing children playing outside i don't
know if the the sound is carrying through so arising arriving arriving
every moment arriving and landing arriving and landing in this
body in this moment in time
so here here I am here I am on this
earth feeling feeling your own presence the sense of
presence this ineffable and yet
profound
quality of our own presence
arriving arriving each moment
arriving arriving and landing in this body this moment in time
feeling feeling embodied as the basis of our practice
and it's not a heady topic this embodiment it's really
earthy how is how is the body feeling can we infuse
our feet with our awareness as our feet are touching the
earth can we infuse our feet with knowing that they are being
sensed can we infuse our hands with
awareness allowing sensations to rush in to be known to be
gently intimately known
infusing your sitbones with awareness
infusing our sitbones how we're sitting connected to the
earth allowing sensations of contact touch hardness
softness to be known simply to be known
being grounded Earth
allowing allowing the breath to move through the body infusing the body
can we feel the sensations of breath in breath out breath in the
abdomen our hands and our feet our shoulders in our
chest can we allow the body to relax and really
release when we are tight in our body we tend to get tight in our thoughts in our
mind so relaxing the body supports relaxing of the mind mind
heart so soften drop what is not needed just check in what's not needed
right now can I release it and simply humbly humbly be with the
breath receive the breath
now I would love to invite you if you would to drop in a
reflection again not into our head but in our heart heart
space and inviting inviting a good friend a benefactor
perhaps someone you've been inviting the past couple of days or someone
new someone who's easy to invite into your heart
space and sit and sit with their goodness with their kindness with their
compassion with their wisdom their
loyalty generosity generosity of heart whatever
aspect and whatever person comes to your heart this aspect of their being doesn't
have to be every aspect of their being but this one particular aspect
sitting with them in your heart
space feeling their presence
receiving their presence in your heart space as if you're sitting with them
having tea receiving your heart's face their
presence their unique
presence rhyming the heart rhyming the
heart and now as if you were swapping place with
places with them as if you were them it's so random
who we get to be who we get to be born as but as if you were
them embodying their presence their sense of kindness
wisdom whatever it is embodying them embodying their
heart their mind shining your awareness out of
their eyes out of their being in
this exploration don't make it too heavy see what it feels like even a second of
it can be opening
what might it feel like to be them with sense of kindness generosity
patience [Music] perhaps
friendliness don't think about it let it be embodied feel into it don't think
into it
feel into how this shifting of places might soften your heart expand
possibilities of ways of being
again not a heady thinking practice just feeling
into another being's presence as if you were them breathing in their kindness
breathing out their kindness
breathing in their brightness breathing out of their
brightness just to get some
flexibility space in our heart in our way of being
and now coming back swapping places again coming back to your own
presence your own your own felt sense of the body breathing in breathing out your
own brightness kindness from your heart center goodwill
friendliness embodying this world this life as you tend to do this body as you
do this being who is
me appreciating your own being this being who is me
this body this life this heart my challenges the way I'm
stretched my aspirations feeling into
them in breath out breath with kindness gentleness
there be appreciation goodwill for the way that I am a friend to myself and
others
allowing your heart to rest in the goodness that there is goodness not a
time to be critical release that if it's coming up resting resting the
goodness and there is always goodness
the last part of this practice period another invitation if you
wish I can support expanding our heart a bit more
if you would invite yourself to swap
places with someone that you've had a bit of a challenge not number
10 scale of 10 1 to 10 but maybe four or five
so when you've had a bit of irritation challenge swap
places seeing the world through their eyes their circumstances their
difficulties how they see the world expanding your
heart again if it feels too challenging or too much of a stretch and you get
triggered come back come back to yourself to your body or your benefactor
dear friend but if it is possible imagine inhabiting the
world as them the challenges they have the the limitations the
conditions the way they think and see the world all the experiences genetic
educational familial
upbringing and how perhaps you cocreated the challenge the
difficulty
together putting oneself in the place of others the foundation of ethical empathy
stepping outside of ourself out of our self being the the
self being the center of the world and for just a minute just a
minute not forever just for a minute entering somebody else's world
reality to expand our heart expand our
capacity doesn't mean we're going to condone the wrongdoing at all not about
condoning not at all or condoning the harm at all
but just to gain
perspective or the freedom of our own heart to gain perspective
and now letting that go coming back to your own heart body
perspective wishing yourself well appreciating yourself for having done this practice and if available wishing
this other person well with whom you've had a bit of a an
entanglement and of course wishing your friend benefactor whom you brought in earlier
well with gratitude may my practice be a cause and
condition for freedom for well-being for awakening of myself and
all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings know their own
goodness including myself may I know my own goodness may I flourish in my own
goodness and kindness may I be able to expand my
heart for the benefit of all beings may all beings be well may all
beings be
happy ding
ding
ding thanks everyone thanks for your
practice pause for a moment
so dear community dear
Sana I think you heard the bell i hope anyway that was my hope at the end of the practice to to do this toggle that's
needed to hear outside uh sounds including bells and bird song
etc it sounds like it did come through beautiful so to continue today
with our theme of [Music] uh of uh SA
community so Oh yes and two bells both the church bell as well as my verbal
bell because I don't have my handy uh Tibetan bell with me yeah
so so we're continuing with the theme of um sana community kalyan namita
um beautiful friendships as part of the path as as
the entirety of the path not just a luxury but uh 100% of the path as the
Buddha said not 50% as ananded thought
So yesterday we talked about friends of the heart
suadia the helper the enduring companion in the times of happiness and
sorrow the good counsel and the compassionate friend the four different types of friend we also talked about the
upakaraka mita upakaraka mita and I was the sadayita the opakarakamita
um who's the uh friend assistant companion who points
out your faults with kindness celebrates your progress and reminds you of of the
dharma in challenging times so today I want to switch to the
topic of putting oneself in the place of another and that was an invitation that I I brought in to their guided
meditation to explore that to to try that on for
size and um different themes different points I
want to cover today one is um that empathy empathy is the foundation of
ethical restraint and the Buddha teaches in the Vama Suta in Samutan Nikica
557 where the Buddha is teaching lay people about the foundation of mor moral
conduct in terms of mutual experience and this is what the Buddha
says what is displeasing and disagreeable to me is likewise
displeasing and disagreeable to others knowing this one should not inflict it
upon another so in this teaching the Buddha is teaching the principle of moral
reciprocity it's the natural ethics based on uh not commandments thou shalt
not but it's the felt understanding it's a felt embodied
understanding that and and it also predates its parallel which is the
golden rule do unto others as you wish them to do unto you it's a little more
poetic than that but essentially that's the golden rule so it's not theoretical empathy but
it's really embodied momentto- moment felt sense ethics if it's displeasing to
you if it's uh disagreeable it's likewise difficult
disagreeable to others of course it is and simil in the similar vein the
Buddha teaches in itaka 27 that all tremble at
violence all fear death comparing oneself with others one should not harm
or cause to harm the same way the sense of trembling of the heart that wow this
is painful all of us all of us have don't desire or or that we we don't
want to be harmed so again this is the ethical the the felt sense basis of of
ethics and and there is of course research and modern research that
suggests that um there are uh that that we feel we literally can feel another
person's pain if we allow ourselves that are um that there are areas of the brain
again not to limit our the found the the wholeness of our experience just to the
uh firing of some neurons i'm not trying to do that not being reductionistic and yet both there there
is research supporting that different areas of of our brain which which um
activate when we are in pain when we witness another people's another person's pain when we allow ourselves to
witness some somebody else's pain those areas specifically the anterior insulin
and the anterior singulate cortex they do activate during these empathetic
experiences and feeling the pain of others as if if it were as if it were
our own so so it's that this Buddha's call to
ethical empathy is um is supported is is
is because we are able to if we allow ourselves to feel somebody else's pain
and not cause harm another aspect of the teaching here
is um recognizing that selflove is a gateway to universal love loving others
and sharing our love so self love is so important it's not luxury it's not
selfish it's a foundation of universal
love and in Angutra Nikaya 557 in the Sacha
Suta the Buddha uh instructs that just as one is dear to oneself so to all all
beings are dear to themselves so he says "I am dear to myself and so are others
dear to themselves therefore one who loves themsself should not harm
another." That's powerful right i am dear to
myself and so are others dear to themselves therefore one who loves
oneself should not harm another so love yourself love yourself deeply love
yourself appreciate yourself be kind to yourself and similarly be kind to others as the
kindness to ourselves as the foundation of kindness to others so this sentence
this statement this teaching is so profound so profound i want to underline
it some more it bridges self- concern and universal ethics showing that
nonharming naturally arises from self understanding and self-care
self-love and the commentary the commentarial literature also emphasizes
that reflection softens the view of beings as other this othering that we do
that it softens that and this particular teaching this way of being cultivating
this way of being loving ourselves therefore loving others not harming
others it reduces what's called
selfcenteredness a conceit mana so it reduces
self-centeredness and mana conceit instead of increasing
it and of course as many of you know and have been practicing meta especially
during happy hour this is a foundation it's the foundation of of loving
kindness practice meta practice that recognizing that all beings want
happiness just as I do just as I want to be happy and not suffer everybody else
also doesn't want to suffer and doesn't want to be um just wants to be happy and does not
want to suffer so another another teaching I
want to bring in is that there's also this teaching on
pre-action reflection pre-action reflection to prevent harm
and in Angutra Nikaya 853 in the
Udai the Buddha teaches reflecting thus
would this be agreeable or disagreeable if done to me one should abstain from
doing it if it would be disagreeable isn't that great so this is
just taking it one notch higher this is a really practical invitation so the Buddha again says
reflecting thus would this be agreeable or disagreeable if done to me one should
abstain from doing it if it would be disagreeable so the Buddha is teaching uh that before
reproving or any action towards others one should internally check the ethical
response of the action or the ethical resonance of the action is really
feeling into like is this agreeable disagreeable would this be hurtful unheardful should I do should I it's
just this moment pause that the Buddha is teaching in the sutas how beautiful
is that so internally checking the eth
ethical resonance of the action before taking the action and this is an
application of yono wise attention yo
manasara wise attention and if shifts the mind from reaction from reactivity
to reflection so the purpose of this is not
pacivity of course but it's compassionate clarity is so that we act
so that we act with discernment and empathy rather than ego and projection
and reactivity and and the practice of sati mindfulness
essentially which is the bread and butter what we practice essentially leads to to being able to to t being
able to take that reflexive pause before action to take that pause like is this
is this a wise is this unwise is this going to cause
harm and um this is what the Buddha advises so I want to end with three
reflective questions for today so here's the First reflective
question how often do I actively imagine another's perspective before acting or
reacting how often do I actively imagine another's perspective before acting or
reacting here's the second reflective question what would it look like to integrate this reflection more fully in
small daily moments what do it would be like and here's the last and third
reflection can I recognize that others fear grieve and long for safety just as
I do just as I do just like me just like me just like
others just like me so today we've explored putting
ourselves in the shoes of another which is again this basis of ethical
uh restraint ethical uh empathy ethical care not in a heady
way but in a practical in a practical way woo how would it feel to me if somebody just opened their mouth and
said something like this or did something like this do I want to do this taking that mindful pause with yoni sa
nasikara and again selflove being the the corner store of care and love and
ethical treatment for others and look at that we have bells today right in time
so so thank you all for your practice thank you for your care for
your goodness may your goodness May your kindness may your ethical care
ring in all [Music] directions thanks
everyone see you tomorrow [Music]