hello and welcome and as we
begin I'm reminded of a story told of the Zen teachers Shinrio
Suzuki Roshi in the maybe in the 1960s when he came to United
States and he was asked by someone by student um or someone interested in
Zen if I practice Zen will I become enlightened
and Suzuki Roshi uh answered uh if your practice is
sincere it's almost as good and uh and this idea that sincere
practice is as good as or almost as good as awakening i think a remarkable
statement and to be sincere I I understand is to give
oneself kind of wholeheartedly to the practice with a
certain humility a certain uh giving oneself
over to it but without straining or without conceit without
trying to attain awakening even though that's the purpose of it uh a sincere engagement with the
process just for its own sake in this moment i think of sincerity as being having
very closely related to honesty an honest understanding of how
we operate what drives us what our challenges are and to hold that with a
certain humility a certain
non-reactivity and that in the end uh there is a learning to give up give
away cease all the efforts in the mind the
heart the body maybe all the efforts that are not
needed all the reactions all the judgments all the trying to make
something happen build something up try to avoid something try to fix something
anything that's extra to the radical
simplicity of presence of attention
here and one of the ways to appreciate this is to
appreciate that way in which practice
attention can be effortless it's not something we have to
put effort into but something that we align
ourselves with or open to or allow to move through us
that we have this capacity as human beings to have
mental emotional processes operating that don't seem to require
any active intention active effort on our
part they just there just as if the heart beats the
diaphragm moves as we breathe the good part of human life
we're not actively working on having the heart
beat mostly we just let it do its thing it's a kind of effortless in the sense
that uh it takes no uh effort of choice no effort of mental
effort and so practice becomes that when it's sincere and one way of understanding
this path of janna is a deeper or fuller experience
of effortlessness and when we come to the fourth Janna it's kind of remarkably satisfying
because of the clarity the amazing clarity of
awareness that's there without any effort without any personal effort
without any choice so to assume a meditation
posture and to gently close your
eyes and to begin appreciating a certain kind of
effortless quality of practice it helps to relax deeply
so first sitting here and feeling
sensing a global experience of
yourself as if whatever way you are right now is fine
there's no need to add judgments or preferences reactions to how you
are but to allow there to be a global awareness that for a few
moments it's all
okay and into that global awareness to experience it all in a fuller more
expansive way take a few long slow deep breaths
in the long exhale relaxing holding and tension in
the body the energy that goes into being
tense is extra it's not really
needed so softening relaxing what you can
and then letting the breathing return to normal and for maybe three more
breaths see if you can allow a
relaxing of the body on the exhale
and then sitting quietly with this simple global
awareness of your body in whatever way that's easy for you without making any special effort
for
it and in that global
awareness can you find maybe in the middle of it the place a settling place a
grounding place within or a place deep
inside that has a kind of feeling of being home or a center of all things
that takes no effort for it to be there it is just
there and perhaps feel that effortless
quality of the centering place
the grounding place may be at the end of the exhale
and as if there's a resting place deep
within that's waiting for all of who you are to join in the rest in the
effortlessness is there any tension in the mind
and be aware of mental tension in an effortless way don't make
it a problem nothing to fix or change
back up step back to where you can gaze upon it
effortlessly that quantumously just known and that's all
and then to return to your breathing and while you might have some
effort in staying with the breath breathing in and breathing out returning
sustaining notice that part of awareness knowing
mindfulness that seems has seems to have the least effort in it
maybe it has a receptive
quality a quiet
stillness and appreciate the interface the interface
between Effortless
attention and breathing
and as you're sitting here is there any feeling of
comfort pleasure maybe with the edge es of
breathing maybe just beyond the breathing
sensations a kind of simple pleasure
well-being that exists effortlessly maybe with its own
hum and the awareness that knows it receives
it without effort almost like a wind will a breeze
will blow through an open window with no effort on the part of the
window
and then gently very
gently open yourself to the simplicity of effortless
awareness effortless
attention effortless knowing that is
perhaps nonverbal it requires almost nothing of
you so that
awareness settles into itself by
recognizing a certain clarity of awareness openness of
awareness effortlessness
And in that effortless awareness might there be some quality of
peace awareness aware of itself
awareness aware of its own clarity
clarity like the clarity of unobstructed space
as you sit here in the most
gentle almost effortless way you
can don't do anything
no I don't do anything with the
mind if you find yourself thinking that involves some degree of
effort see if you can find the place where that effort is not
happening where you can stop meditating to just
[Music] E no conscious effort
and as we come to the end of the sitting to
consider how an open window allows the breeze to come in
effortlessly
an open window will not
break if a rock is thrown at the
window and an open window
[Music] allows the radiance the
light of our love our care for the world our
goodwill to shine out the window unobstructed by curtains glass tinted
glass so we sit here at the end of the
sitting with an open heart
allowing the gentle breeze of the world
suffering to light the warmth of care and
compassion so that our heart open heart can radiate its goodwill out into the
world spreading the medicine of
care far and wide may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all
beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so good morning and or good day and welcome to this next talk on samadei
we're talking about the fourth Janna and
um it's not something that people will experience often and regularly in life
and maybe occasionally it's experienced in very particular circumstances
something like this but even in meditation it's not something that is easy to to enter into enter and
abide and um but one of the ways maybe to get feel for it is through the
imagination and through some of the characteristics of it which might appear
in ordinary life and one of those is um there's a a
deep effortless quality that is highlighted in the fourth
Janna before entering into samadei there is a kind of effort that's being done in
practice sincere effort and hopefully an effort that you enjoy doing that you
find a way that it's enjoyable and satisfying you look forward to you know
just like you would forward to certain kinds of activities that are fun to do like playing an instrument or maybe
cooking if you enjoy that or sometimes we put a tremendous amount of effort into
uh you know some sport or something um go for a hike in the hills and it takes
a lot of energy but there's a pleasure there's a joy there's a kind of
um maybe a kind of effortless quality in the sense that we're not
uh having to work hard against ourselves so as we to really enjoy the practice
and then to begin finding a way that to a deeper settling deeper uh uh quieting
calming and uh while being deeply centered and unified and really feel
like we're fully here in the present moment here centered here in this time
and place and um and then as we go through
the deepening samadei um uh slowly the there's sometimes
sometimes with kind of big jumps but slowly there's a transition from how
much effort we have to make and how much effortless effort there is how much
there the practice rather than we doing the practice the practice is doing doing us and so to go along with that to feel
that shift so we're not overriding the effortless part overriding the way the
practice practices us um u because we think it's always up to us we're pushing
and striving and doing there's an art to knowing when to let up and just enough
but to stay really present uh not so much that the mind drifts off but not too much so that
there's a strain and so this art of kind of knowing how to make this shift gradual transition until there's less
and less effort from us needed because there's no wandering off we're just here
we're entered and abided we've arrived here and the Janna the four Janna are
one way of understanding them yesterday I talked about progressive stages of
calming another way of understanding them uh it's a
progressive entering and abiding in an effortless awareness less and less
effort is needed and until we get to the fourth Janna and uh it seems like there's
really no effort at all and uh it can seem like there's no
effort in the third Janna for example but uh from the point of view of the fourth Janna there's still a little bit
orientation of the mind towards the happiness towards the the the good qualities of it and uh and so um uh in
the fourth Janna kind of uh the joy of clear recognition the joy of the
happiness of awareness the happiness that's a little bit activated energy
quiets down even more and so there's this kind of deep feeling of
effortlessness but it's effortlessness that seems to leave what's left is a
broad un un um bounded
uh sense of awareness of clarity of knowing of um sensing of just being that
uh maybe has very little characteristics to it it's almost and it's like that the
awareness is aware of itself uh it's kind of like um
uh you know uh I'm you know I'm nearsighted and um and so if I uh kind
of I have complicated eyesight now but uh uh without my glasses um I
don't see so well and c certain distances it's all blurry and um and uh
but uh when When I put on my glasses uh it's everything is clear and I can see
in certain certain directions certain distances and uh and uh the seeing it's
kind of like the seeing sees its own clarity well it is
the object that's there that I see clearly but there's a feeling that uh
it's not like it's not so much about the objects there's almost a feeling that the the eyes themselves now have cleared
there's a the eyes see their own clarity almost and so the the the uh the
awareness knows its own clarity knows its own purity or maybe there's some deep deep
nonverbal knowing that knows these things it's a
no deep knowing of uh something very of what is really special this effortless
awareness that's clear it's unruffled there's no waves there's no judgments
and so there it's very aquamous and um and uh it's not reacting
to anything and not participating anything so a lot of things disappear
because part of what the mind is is an uh alarm system we're alert and vigilant
for all kinds of things for what we are afraid of what we don't want what we want and the kind of that kind of
vigilance falls away it's a feeling of deep deep safety
uh generally the Janna are very hard to experience unless somehow we provide our
whole psychophysical system with the reassurance of a deep kind of safety in that
time because that's another way of describing the Janna is a progressive state of feeling more and more safe so
safe that the idea of safety and danger disappears entirely and we're just there and with
this clarity with this purity with this feeling a very clean um very still very
quiet um there's no thoughts at all though there might be still a little bit
just in the faint kind of nonverbal knowing that um you know really you're
not involved in it just it's just just kind of floats there a little bit gently
quietly it has no power there's no energy behind it and um and the mind
feels very clean as I've said and one of the characteristics of it in the
description in my translation I said um uh disappearance of mental happiness and
mental suffering it's hard to know how to translate these two words from Pali
Duman and sudan sumanasa and um basically it's kind of
means good mind and bad mind and it might mean something like u a really
elated mind or deflated mind a u uh
happily aroused mind activated mind or u unhappy
uh mind and so the emotional tenor quality of the mind um uh is neither elated nor
depressed neither inspired nor dispirited neither sad
nor you know inspired and it can seem like that's an amazing dullness amazing blandness why
would anybody want that oh well to be in it it just feels like this is really good it feels so pure
so nice so clear uh so peaceful uh that maybe describing it as
a profound peace that we it's almost as if that's what's all that's left and
maybe we're still there in some kind of way with some kind of attention but the
degree to which there's any self-centeredness or self-involvement has almost almost if not entirely kind
of disappeared and um and uh the effortless awareness and
effortless peace uh that we abide in we feel safe in we
feel comforted in and um a you know like
uh wrapping ourselves after a nice refreshing
uh bath in a wonderful bath towel that just sit and be completely content and
happy as we sit there wrapped in the clean clean towel clean body refreshed body
everything vibrating with a open clear
um a quantumous mind awareness so I'll read you the the
description of the fourth Janna letting go of pleasure and
pain with the disappearance of mental happiness and mental
suffering one enters and abides in the purity of a quantmous
awareness of the fourth Janna once it's pervading this body with
a pure clear mind so that no part of the entire body is untouched by the pure
clear mind by the clean clear
mind and um and uh this is a mind which is
unpreoccupied with itself unpreoccupied with self un preoccupied with desires
and aversions unpreoccupied by fears and
distress and um and this makes the
mind phenomenally ready for a
transformation because as soon as the mind is preoccupied by something
uh it can't it's the hard for it to shift and change and be ready for what
comes so um so the fourth Janna so we have one
more talk on uh this fourth Janna and the
Janna in general and I'll kind of bring it to a kind of conclusion tomorrow
and uh and talk a little bit about what follows the Jonas so thank you very much and um may
this day be a day that you feel the the preciousness the joy
the deep satisfaction of the way that your heart
and mind can be effortless as it moves through the day
don't sacrifice the depth of who you
are by making too much effort let the mind be at ease thank you