so good morning everyone and welcome can you hear me
okay so last week I talked about mindfulness of speaking and so to follow
up this week I'd like to talk about mindfulness of listening and uh listening is such a has such so
much overlap with mindfulness that um sometimes I think
that if you can't be mindful
listen and and or if you can't meditate if you can't learn to meditate learn to
listen there's a little story that I made up the once of this person who
lived next to the who was visiting ing from another country for a year and was living next to the monastery and she
started going visiting regularly and was taught to some introduction to meditation and did some meditation and
really was taken by this but then her family was going to move back to her home country uh where there was no
Buddhism and no meditation so uh she went to the abbs of
the monastery and said what do I do when I get home who is going to teach me to
meditate and the AB said um ask around
for the person who's the best listener and then ask them to teach you
how to listen so to listen well as a as a form
of mindfulness or substitute for mindfulness but ideally you do both
learn to be mindful and learn to listen learn to be mindful as you're
listening learn to listen as you're mindful the
um um there's tremendous value in listening
some people it's been said that some people have trouble listening because it involves a lack of
control and I suppose it does you don't control the people around you if you just listen
um but uh uh we certainly can uh acquire a lot of control of ourselves mastery of
our ourselves if we learn to listen so I have two quotes two quotes
here about listening and um uh I think they're kind of wonderful
one's a poem and once both of them are poems and um and uh the idea of the
person is um one has a person being really small
and one has a person being really big so I include both for
equal equal opportunity equal representation in case some of you don't
like the idea of being small and some of you don't like the idea of being big
we'll start with the big this is uh from Walt Wittman very important American poet
this was his uh song is he's called the poem called Song of the Open Road
so it begins kind of with exclamation from this hour
freedom from this hour I ordain myself freed of limits and imaginary
lines listening to others and considering well what they
say pausing searching receiving contemplating
gently but with an undeniable will devesting myself of the holds that
would hold me devesting of the clinging that would cling to
me i think it's a powerful step for me for listening listening to others and
considering well what they say pausing
searching receiving contemplating gently but with undeniable will
devesting myself of the holds that would hold me i think it's a great Buddhist uh
little paragraph there or lines of a poem but it's together with this idea of freedom freedom uh celebrated like
that's the beginning could be very self-centered uh especially in individualistic culture
that America has often been um it could even be more so expression of our
individuality sees the day for oneself but immediately it's it's there's some
lines in between I didn't include but um then in this poem includes just a deep sense of
listening So after this listening to others he writes I inhale droughts of
space the east and the west are mine and the north and south are mine i
am larger better than I thought i didn't know I held so much
goodness all seems beautiful to me today imagine if
listening in that spirit listening that you're better and
bigger and have more goodness in in you than you know so this is the one about being
big listen and here's the one about being small and this is by uh the po
poet May Sorton it's titled "Can I Weave a nest of
silence." Isn't that evocative can I Weave a nest of
silence it refers to a small bird named the Phoebe
the Phoebe sits on her nest hour after hour
day after day waiting for life to burst out from under
her warmth can I weave a nest of
silence weave it of listening listening listening
layer upon layer but one must first become
small nothing but a presence attentive as a nesting
bird pro-offering no slightest wish toward anything that might happen or be
given only the warm faithful
waiting contained in so contained in one's
smallalness beyond the question the silence beyond the answer the silence I
thought this was a great poem to represent meditation sitting you know sitting and um the Buddha did
liken doing Buddhist practice like an egg sitting on its
eggs and incubating them he uses language of uh that not his his word
it's a modern word but gestation that having something be working and growing
developing and being born from within as we do this practice so I thought in that
spirit this poem about uh the the bird sitting on its nest with its warmth
justestating something letting something develop the eggs develop until something gets born and now May Sartin wants to do
the same through her listening can we is does a listening
well does it give birth to something new does listening a well justestate
something allow something else to happen in you and in the person you
listen to there people whose job is to listen to
people's stories and um uh uh they are sometimes
referred to as midwives that they are um they uh hear things into birth in their
listening things come alive and are born in people in your listening to yourself can
you listen to yourself to sit quietly and it would be different if you use the
metaphor of listening for mindfulness than if you use the metaphor of seeing
for mindfulness for some people seeing is much more active and in fact I know some
people who actually engage their eyes when their eyes are closed in meditation you know they're trying to look and
stare at their breath they're trying hard um it's a little bit harder to do that with listening listening has to
almost be a letting go of effort to listen well there can be an act of choice to listen but uh there's a kind
of giving up control or giving up it's almost like you have to let go of effort
to listen really well your listening can be directional but still it's not you
have to kind of allow it to come there's less interference and that's part of the
power of mindfulness when there's no interference and we can just feel without any attachment know without any
attachment just there and to not be in a hurry to wait
uh to uh be small to build a
nest and I like this very much that uh that part of meditation especially in
the early years of being a meditator um we're kind of beginning to kind of
create something wonderful inside a nest a a tenderness a softness a presence a
capacity to be present and here where the body begins to soften and relax
there's a yogic body that comes into play that slowly gets formed by meditating day by day by day and the
body itself shifts and changes the heart shifts and changes the mind shifts and
changes when less and less uh preoccupation the mind doesn't wander off so much in thought is something
begins shifting and changing when we're not so uh uh writing our concerns our preoccupations really tightly you know
really want something or don't want something or reacting liking and not liking drifting off in distractions not
drifting off in distractions racing off in distractions and uh and so the uh with
the idea that we're building a nest as opposed to doing it to have an
attainment i'm going to get this i'm going to be a really good meditator i'm going to get the attainments of Buddhism
full enlightenment i'm going to get the Janna i'm going to get this i'm going to get that
but what if what we're doing is building a cocoon building a nest building a womb
gestating something that's a little bit more the Buddha's understanding of what we're doing in meditation the Buddha did
not present Buddhist practice as something we engineer something we
construct something we build um he presented Buddhist practice all through
language and metaphors that uh were creating the conditions for something to
be born something to arise something to grow and um and
so creating creating the conditions for something to grow can be represented by
this metaphor of the nest it can be represented by um you know being so
still and quiet and warm incubate it bring warmth tenderness to all that you
are there's a um wonderful story from the
Ramayana that I sometimes I've quoted a lot um the Rama is in the forest with uh
companions and um Rama hears a very faint voice in the forest and he asks
his companions do you hear the voice and uh they say no but he hears the voice so
he kind of tries to figure out where it's coming from starts moving in that direction and then very faintly he hears
the voice is calling his name Rama
rama and he asks companions do you hear the voice no we don't hear it so he goes
closer and closer and as it gets closer it's a little bit louder and louder but still very quiet and finally he comes to
the source of it and the source is a very big boulder and uh coming out of the boulder
is this voice Rama Rama kind of inviting him perhaps to
come closer so Ramba takes and puts his two hands on the boulder and immediately
the boulder um transforms itself into a beautiful
woman who long ago had been um uh uh
someone had cast a spell on her and turned her into a solid boulder but
someone like Rama had to come to dissolve her and so she wouldn't be so
petrified and uh and so what I how I interpret
this wonderful story was Rama listened only he could hear what is it only you
can hear what's calling you what's calling you
inside what is it that's solid or petrified in you that's waiting to be
touched waiting to be somehow held recognized and so to sit in mindfulness
as a listener to yourself what is it that what is it that's speaking deep
inside that doesn't have words doesn't have a voice but this idea of listening
deeply deeply it's a little bit different than looking some people if
they're looking for their depth looking for the answer inside um people are
really active searching searching around looking around all the different places where can I find it there must be some
place here under behind the navl you know and in the back of the
heart you know no it has to be in the base of the brain where is it
um but you can't do that if you're listening listening you have to just be quiet quiet still listen feel sense in
some deeper and deeper way so what is it that calls you and um
and uh and I love the language of being called because that's been so much kind
of how I've been operated in my adult life um called to meditation called to
practice meditation uh and with the things that began happening to me when I meditated was
basically say come here this is good this is the right place to be this is where peace is this is where harmony is
this is where the the wholeness your wholeness resides come here and let this
wholeness grow and so I then went from meditating
every day to going living near a Buddhist center to becoming a resident of a center to going to live in a
monastery uh all all of because I felt this inner call to become go into this deeper and
deeper listening to what was calling me and eventually there was a call to be of service the call to be a teacher or
to somehow support people in the suffering of the world in Buddhism in Mahayana Buddhism they have this um
great bodhicattva great celestial kind of being called
suffering of the world uh sometimes it's called the one who see Yeah who hears who uh who hears
the suffering of the world so this metaphor of hearing uh is there and and of this wonderful
there's statues of of uh of a loadhara and we have actually one that's in the
museum in Kansas City we have a big photograph they have a beautiful one there it's up on the top of the steps
above if if you're brave and sign a liability form we take all full of
risks you can go you can go up the spiral staircase and uh and see this
that the wonderful photograph of that Kansas CityWin and it's in the pose of in the
pose of repose uh it's sitting in a very relaxed posture the one who hears the cries of
the world who um is relaxed at ease who listens well
and maybe we can only listen well if we're relaxed and at ease and to the
suffering of the world is it okay to be relaxed at ease listening to the suffering of the world some people say
absolutely not you have to be distressed you have to be angry you have
to be distraught you have to be you know show that you really care by being all
worked up that is not creating the nest that's
not creating the the place of some deeper wellspring of growing and
maturing and responding to the world actually it mitigates it if we're if we
are caught in distress in anger distraught over the conditions of
the world which is easy to do it's actually maybe in a certain way very
logical to do that and but and then we
are um held by what would hold you
which to paraphrase Walt Wittmann but he said devesting himself of the holes that
would hold me and um so how to listen well so
there's also a story in China ofwan yin there where someone asks a Zen master
um what's it like to be Quan Yin what's it like to listen to the sounds the the
the suffering of the world and the Zen master says "It's like adjusting your pillow in
the middle of the night." Isn't that weird but the idea is that um uh we're
uh the I think the assumption is that the metaphor means that you're you're
kind of half asleep and you adjust the pillow unself-consciously
you feel something needs to be adjusted and that simple relaxed unself-conscious adjusting of the pillow that's what it's
like to be compassionate there's a need but there's no distress there's
something but and responding to that need the
um um so um how do we listen well to others
one way is to try to listen without the filters of our own judgments our stories
our interpretations of what's going on and that's one of the values of mindfulness the more mindful you become
the more you're also tracking yourself you're tracking uh whether you're
actually responding to them in your mind and stop listening to their what they're saying and I don't know if I'm just
weird but I've known myself to do that that uh what what did the person
just say i I'm just impairing my my my answer and um and that's not healthy so
the idea to recognize that's happening to no listen stay listening stay present
hear the person out and um and to to be able to track yourself and know how
we're kind of and sometimes occasionally I felt this tremendous power this urge
to speak like it had you know it was like hard to keep my mouth shut
sometimes interrupting other people because of that power that's there mindfulness is supposed to protect
us from that unless the situation requires action but to track oursel to
see what's going on but listen mindfulness also provides us with a lot of wisdom a lot of understanding if we
can track ourselves as we listen we can understand the reactions we have to what
we hear we can understand the beliefs that are operating or the thoughts that come up the judgments that come up we
can feel recognize the emotions that are coming up and uh the tensions that are
coming up or the softness that comes up we can kind of track what's happening inside of
us um that doesn't make us a worse listener it can actually make us a better listener so all those things
don't interfere uh so we can listen better to the other uh and also if we listen to
ourselves while we're listening to others um it turns out part of who we are is in this wonderful natural world
we're not a singular independent thing who we are is partly co-created all the
time in the world and so if we're tracking that and being present for it in ourselves we're actually in this
we're watching and seeing the co-creation that happens if we only paid attention
ourselves which some people are capable of doing and uh uh then we don't hear the
other person but if we only hear the other person then we don't hear
ourselves and some people feel we're obligated to listen to someone 100% we're supposed to be a good
listener turns out we can't be a good listener if it's 100% with the other person
and so what I like to the idea is that the mindfulness helps us to have the attention 5050 50% here with oneself and
50% with someone else and so I want to offer the alternative to these two poems
one poem is about becoming large and the other about becoming small for me the
wonderful delightful alternative is to disappear
that's there's a third option and so when the attention is really
present 50% to the person 50% to what's all in here
um then the imag as Walt Whitman says the imaginary
lines disappear the imaginary boundaries between self and other kind of
disappear and so this usual understandings and sense of self disappear that often interfere with
listening well and it's just such a pleasure to disappear this way and are
you going to be unsafe in the world if those kinds of imaginary lines that separation in you as person uh is no
longer there how are you going to take care of yourself i suggest you actually can take care of
yourself better because you're tracking your feelings your thoughts the
impact the concerns the beliefs you really see what's going on what's here
you get all the right information that you need you just you haven't just you just don't package it into an identity
that this is who I am i'm supposed to be this way um and so you're able to then
in the conversation to respond appropriately and take care of yourself um because you have all the information
from the other and listening to the other person you hear them well so it's not a dangerous thing what I'm
suggesting but it's a great relief isn't that nice i mean it's kind of a drag to
be small and it's kind of a drag to be big
but it's not a drag to disappear then there's no resistance
anywhere so to listen well and then one way to listen well to
others is to uh uh let them know that you hear them
uh uh active listening often means that we we kind of in a very simple way not
you don't go you don't repeat everything they say but even with one or two words uh demonstrate that you've heard what
they said and uh even simply as saying um yeah um like you know oh Gil you were
talking about listening today well then I know you heard you
you and uh and something different can happen and uh so it could be very simple
but help people understand know that you listened more powerfully help people
know that you understood them people have a tremendous need to be understood i would venture guess that
you have a tremendous need to be understood if you have a need one of the wonderful
I think maybe pops psychology principles that I like is if you have a need offer
it to others give it so if you have a need to be understood understand others
it's it's the alchemy of that is very fascinating the what you know if that's included in the nest of something that's
growing it's really fascinating what can happen but you know just simply it might
be that people feel like wow the person's really interested in me maybe I
should ask them how they are and so then then they initiate it
but if you say to them you never you you never listened to me you never shown interest in me and you then they get
defensive and then they're not going to listen but you kind of do this iikido
move you know you know understand them and
um so as a way of finishing these words I'd like to uh
reread this one's one part of Walt Whitman's
poem listening to others and considering well what they
say pausing searching receiving contemplating
gently but with undeniable will devesting myself of the holds that
would hold me so may it be that listening is one of the ways that you're
able to start letting go of some of your attachments and clinging that listening
is an antidote to holding on tight that you begin letting go just
like meditation is meant to be an antidote to holding on tight helping you to let go so if you can't
meditate now you know what to do practice listening
instead and listening you can practice all day long when you're with people or with yourself listen to yourself
well so those are my thoughts and uh with this fresh on your
mind and uh maybe inspired by it or want to want to try it quickly how about if
you turn to one or two people next to you and say something about what arose
for you in listening to this talk what inspired you what was interesting to you what what protests you have what you
didn't what you didn't like about it and um but but give the other people one or
two people with you um a chance to practice listening to you but as you
speak be sure that you're listening to yourself as you speak and don't speak
for very long make it really brief because mostly this is a listening exercise so you want to just get over
your talking so you can get be doing the listening part and as you listen to them listen to
yourself that 50/50 so have a you know friendly conversation and those of you who don't want to be part of this you
certainly welcome to go have tea you're welcome also to sit quietly in here and then we'll take five minutes or so just
to kind of come back and have a few more words so um just make sure no one's
sitting alone uh look around you and then uh I'll ring a bell when it's time to stop
so what did you learn about yourself as a listener in that exercise anything
were you listening anybody want to offer something
i do but that's Yeah but people online need it
a lot of work for somebody i've found out that I'm not nearly as good of it as I think I am
that's it that That's progress
i also found out I'm not as good as I thought and I like to give advice
so what in recognizing that was that also progress definitely good definitely
[Laughter]
well I'll just I'm just a quick one i find for myself if I'm excited all my
energy goes out i mean any kind of strong emotion if I'm angry it's like
the idea of bringing it back to myself is challenging
it's funny that you spoke before me because I was kind of going to say something similar just that the
eagerness to speak can be distracting and it's nice being able to witness it
and let it go so that we can drop in with one another in a more still and tender way that was very nice to hear
that you see that see it that way thank you
there's There's a next Oh go ahead
no a quick comment i just find that I get so interested in hearing more and
learning about the person that sometimes I ask too many questions
now I finally understand what tune in and drop out means
um I have just one little story to share which is I think one well it's one of my
favorite things about becoming a meditator i've not I've only been meditating about seven or eight years I
want to say but when I was an absolute beginner um
I immediately fell in love with loving kindness and found it to be a very
lovely thing to carry around during the day and I was very mindful of that in
the beginning that was the one piece I I could carry and all of a sudden at work
at least once a day someone would stop when we were done discussing and say "You're such a good
listener." And I've never had that happen prior in my life and I was very
good at it then because I was so mindful of this new thing it doesn't happen
nearly as often now i don't know if I just went on to more complicated
meditation concepts that I'm trying to master but it was the most delightful
gift from my practice pro it might be my favorite thing and it really is a shame it doesn't happen very often I have to
confess but um it was a gift well you know it's invaluable to always be a
beginner another thought
not not the tune in dropout kind but um I was thinking it's
easy to really tune into listening when I'm speaking with strangers not the
people that I know in life ah that's fascinating
there's so much history and complications and all kinds of things with people we know maybe it's but they
might be the most important p people to listen to well thank you all very much i hope
this was nice for you and uh this topic of listening is really central to a
mindful life and may you mindfully listen and listen
mindfully so thank you