so welcome everyone to IMC and for those of you online who are also attending
welcome and um so uh I think I think it's my
pleasure to uh talk about mindful speaking
one of the one of the joys of this work that I
do is when people come to me and say "Well this mindfulness meditation is good but how do we apply it to life how
do I integrate into the rest of my life not just in meditation?" And one of the really
significant ways is to practice mindful speaking and uh in fact uh I think that
mindful speaking is um just mindfulness out loud now if you practice mindful
mindfulness by yourself internally you're just recognizing what's really happening there in a truthful way and
learn and learning to tell yourself or recognize it what's happening not only
truthfully what's happening internally but also beginning to recognize it in a
way that's useful beneficial it benefits you to recognize it in a way that's kind
that's supportive of you it's certainly possible to know what's going on inside and treat it as bad bad and unwelcome
news and one more reason to be critical of yourself mindfulness is turning that
around and using mindfulness as a way to start having a positive relationship
with oneself so that something different can happen than that couldn't happen if
we're critical angry upset we're caught in greed and all kinds of things
so the same thing in our external world we're learning how to be mindful mindful
out loud one of the reasons why mindfulness of speaking is so useful is uh it's
useful to understand yourself better uh it's a way of looking and understanding
tracking what you're saying and why you say it uh many people speak uh without
really much care to what they say uh there's a kind of a little quote that
goes around sometimes that says that uh many people take more care in how they
dress than what they say but uh what we say has a much bigger impact on our life
and our so communal life than how we dress and um and so to start seeing what
am I doing here when I speak what motivates it uh why am I saying what I'm
about to say this it creates a tremendous useful
window into your inner life why am I saying this really is that the reason um
you know you might say well the person asked me a question so I'm just going to you know I'm just answering the question
that's why but then if you look more deeply well I want the person to like me i want the
person to see that I knowledgeable and I know how to you know and there's all these different motivations that are
operating at the same time and so to stop and take it have the ability to take a deeper look to track what's going
on as it's going on another another area that mindful speaking is
useful is that uh uh if you pace your day and so that your day you'd go about
the day at the speed of mindful speaking
how fast would you do things uh how fast would you speak uh
maybe maybe you want to speak fast and furiously but if you want to bring
mindfulness into your life then you might want to consider the speed in which you speak
and and you know any speed is fine for mindfulness practice provided you can track it while you're saying it you can
track it before you say it you're kind of tracking you know the impulses you know what's inside of you and you can
kind of then live more wisely so there's a lot of self-standing
a lot of development and growth of mindfulness that's uh that happens if we begin practicing it in our social life
communal life around mindfulness of speaking another reason for mindfulness uh of
speech is so that we can create good relationships with people around us with the world so that we can create a better
world um because speech is uh uh has a big impact on uh on other people and
ourselves the world we live in and uh rather than creating more animosity more
hurt more uh conflict can we speak in a way that does the opposite that uh
creates more concord that creates more friendship that creates uh more healing in this world more unity rather than
divisiveness and so if you're able to track your speech then you can kind of begin seeing is this really what I want
to say is this the best way of saying it is there a better way of saying it so in the Buddhist tradition there are
guidelines or signposts maybe that um
are presented offered to track what you're saying and the questions to ask
yourself and um and this could be as you're speaking but um maybe a place
where it can be even harder to do this and in speaking is in emails or texting
or something where it doesn't have to be as quick socially you know s long
periods of silence are kind of awkward but uh you know to be silent for 10
minutes not respond right away it's not such a big deal to take it a little bit
while maybe even to compose something and not send it and say come back five minutes later and you is this what I
want to do what's the impact is this what does this express here and then you can ask yourself these questions
uh uh is it the right time to communicate it is it
timely is it uh truthful does it express the truth uh is it uh uh uh beneficial
to say what I'm about to say to write what I'm about to write and is it uh is
it kind does it come from a place of goodwill there's sometimes a fifth one that's
offered and that is um I don't know if I really know what the poly word means but
some translators translated as gentle uh it's possible it means
beautiful it's possible it means polite but you know so uh most common
translations is it gentle gentle speech is it polite speech is it
um but there so the first one is it timely is it the time right time for
something and uh that goes for me very closely connected to this idea of is it
effective is it is it useful to say what I'm going to do because some things are important to say but the timing of when
you say it is really important people might not be ready to hear it they might not be able to process it and respond to
it um if you say it you know uh turning your head as you leave as you leave hey
by the way you and then you off you're running to catch the bus or something uh
there's no processing there's no chance to kind of work with it and interact with it and clarify it or hear their
response or see what the response is so is it the right time to say something
uh I receive emails sometimes that uh maybe it was in some ways maybe um it
was not the right time because email is not a good way to communicate the nuance
of attitude and emotions that's behind what's being said and I've kind of uh
misread an emotion either didn't see the emotion in it or saw emotions that
weren't there so is it this the right time to communicate what I want want to communicate maybe a phone call is better
maybe there's another way maybe a wait there are sometimes that I have waited a
long time to have an important conversation with someone because I felt that they were closed to having it and
it was it didn't make any sense to it's I had every right to say something you
would think but being right doesn't mean it's going to work
and so uh is it the right time so to to ask yourself that question and that's a
difficult question to ask for some of us because the impulse to speech is can be
quite strong and where I see it is uh when I'm ready to speak before a person
has stopped speaking i don't know if any of you have that issue you know I'm just sometimes you
know I'm not just like you know just can't wait sometimes I I you know don't in a social conversation or something I
I don't really hear the second half of what they're saying because I'm in my
mind I'm telling them what I feel is important to say and so uh so um
um so to take time
listen so then uh and um so that's one question slows you down is ask ask the
question is this the right time the second is is it the truth and that has a
multi-layered kind of analysis consideration
um what is the truth uh is how you feel the truth
uh maybe it's true as a feeling but maybe it's not true as a judgment
And that that line between an emotion or feeling we have and it being the truth
about a situation out there the lens through which we see it is a kind of ambiguous world and sometimes what we
say we're saying what's true um um you know I feel that you're
awful and that was true statement right i had this feeling but actually it's a
judgment and uh and maybe it's welling up quite powerfully as a powerful
impulse inside something's really uncomfortable or strong inside but you
know you know you have to be very careful what we say is that really true what might be more true is say uh
hearing what you have to say I'm feeling quite uncomfortable I feel unsettled now
I wonder if we can talk about it um that's getting closer to the truth
but then you ask the question is it timely to say that if you uh maybe not
maybe some people just they hear that you're uncomfortable makes them so uncomfortable they shut down or so
uncomfortable they leave they don't want to you know want to bother or they
can't is it is it true
um is all truth right to say some people feel that
they justified to say something if it's true but that's the uh next guideline is
that um uh is it beneficial does it benefit is it useful
is it strategic is it effective and so um I
mean I I've thought about this sometimes in political discourse people can be right maybe they they believe they're
right the people they have a right to say what they're going to say they have justice on their side so of course they
should speak up but is it effective what's the impact
it's going to have is it is it beneficial the impact and a lot of
political discourse uh in all kinds of directions uh people feel it's true they
feel it's just to say it but it's received in a way that actually is
counterproductive and you might you know be yelling and screaming and because feeling you have every right to say
something and maybe you do but the question is is it effective is it
beneficial and then you can ask yourself your question and beneficial in what way
how are you trying to benefit from the situation if it's simply to make yourself safe
that's certainly sometimes important to do but is that the only thing that's necessary to do or important to do what
about the relationship you have with the other person how about c can you create a a friendly relationship a mutually
supportive rel relationship and so then the other guideline is is that is there meta is
there goodwill in the communication we have and um and goodwill means that we
also care about the other person's welfare we want them to be happy and
that's a high bar to because they don't deserve it
they've you know they've they've disrespected me they they're in the wrong they really messed up and caused a
lot of tr trouble and you know they were mean so of course they don't they were so mean they don't deserve any goodness
for me uh they've they've now forfeited all rights to receive anything good for
me and I'm going to give them peace of my mind people don't think that way I don't
think but sometimes they operate that way because we don't stop to look at and
think what are we doing here what's going on here the impulse to speak sometimes is so strong and unexamined
so the Buddha keeps emphasizing examine what's going on when you speak look at
it and so can you can you have goodwill can you aim to create a healthy
relationship here can you somehow break break through the meanness or the
closeness or the hostility that might be here it's not an easy thing to do but um but
maybe it's better than making the situation worse sometimes the best way
to deal with all these criteria uh somehow to cope with them is is not
speak just be silent and one of the guidelines is if if speaking is going to
make it worse maybe don't say anything some people will protest but but but you have
to speak you know you have to fight for the good cause you have to set things right you have to have to you know but
maybe if you're making situation worse maybe you don't speak maybe wait and
this is where mindfulness of speaking comes into into play in big time the
mindful speaking also means knowing how to speak at the right time the first
criteria which might mean after After you've paused for a while after you've
been silent for a while after you say "Can can I take a breath or two can we
pause that was a big impact on me before I speak can can we just take three breaths together?" Or "Can I take three
breaths?" And then I'll try to respond just some kind of pause and I've done
that in difficult conversations with people where I was triggered and um and
I thought to myself you know Gil uh right now you're not going to say good things you're not capable of it and I I
asked and I asked permission i say to the person I'm having this very difficult conversation with "This is
difficult and uh could we pause for a while can we just sit here and breathe for a little bit?" And um and
um last time this happened the person was very gracious and said yes i think the person trusted me with that maybe
thought they were they were going to be treated better and so I took about two minutes
three minutes to get my breath back get my senses back and then I could continue in the conversation but instead I was in
you know it was not going to work so sometimes not
speaking and then can we speak with goodwill can we care about the other person's welfare as well and one one
reflection I do sometimes is that uh when someone is
hostile mean they're hurting chances are that their meanness
and hostility represents some suffering they have does that justify that they're
mean or hostile no but to know that means
oh they're hurting of course I want to care for them they're hurting i don't
want to make it worse can we find another way to have this conversation can we talk in a way that uh uh uh
fosters some kind of mutual understanding some kind of mutual care for each other some kind of friendliness
friendship for each other and then the last criteria is to
be gentle or to be have beautiful speech kind speech and I've said it already but
beautiful speech polite speech um some people say this is the opposite of harsh
speech uh and um so I don't know what you think the opposite of harsh speech is but uh harsh speech is speech which
uh just a tone of it is harmful so can you do a tone of voice which
is makes space for people that uh is not doineering not not filling the space but
makes room for a dialogue to go on so um
um so of course you don't have to do any of this if you don't want but if you
have the question how do I bring my mindfulness practice into my social life my community life this is a really
effective way it's not easy for most people some people for some people it
seems like mindfulness of speaking is the most difficult area of life to be mindful in because uh when we're talking
we get pulled into our concerns our emotional life our impulses our desires
there's so such a complex world that we get pulled into that um in relationship
to other people that sometimes we we're not really tracking ourselves very
well but the benefits of doing it are immense huge uh we learn about ourselves we
learn how to stay balanced in ourselves stay healthy in ourselves to stay closer to a place of
well-being we don't give oursel we don't give up on ourselves when you're mindful of speaking tracking
it and you uh we um create better relationships in the
world relationships then which are um that uh have a feedback loop where they
come back to benefit us the more we can develop friendly relationship other people the more that we can um
um I had a conversation recently with this person who many years ago I had that difficult conversation where I had
to ask can we pause and um and
uh and I was pretty angry so you know it was kind of difficult time and uh she
said "Gil you've always been so supportive of me and so accepting of me and I just feel your love for me." And I
said "But but but we had that time." And uh and she said "Yeah yeah
that you know that didn't matter you know your your your good intent was there." Um so anyway so so somehow you
know that relationship continued and is now a warm friendly relationship in a
nice way so um so mindfulness of
speaking so that's the topic and so now you get to practice it so for those of
you who want to stay and those of you who don't want to be want to stay and don't want to be part of this can just sit quietly and uh or you know get some
water and just hang out until we come back but the invitation is for you to of
go into small groups of maybe three people uh and uh just look around you
and you make your groups and no one's end up left alone because sometimes everyone goes to the you know to their
left and their right and then you know they're just sitting there and like so everyone you know look for the make sure
everyone's included and um and then maybe you could offer some words uh of your own
experience or inspiration for mindful speaking what have you learned so far or
in what way are you inspired by these words today or other ways to uh find a
way to be attentive to you more carefully attentive more deeply
attentive to speaking as you speak okay so we'll do that for about 10 minutes
and then we'll ring a bell and we'll come back as a group as a whole and have a few more words and in here and then
we'll stop in time for the potluck so thank you
please so how much mindfulness mindfulness was
there of speech you can it's possible to talk about
mindful speaking and not be mindful while you're talk while you're doing it but it was very nice it felt like a
nice happy set of conversations to witness from here this place any uh
questions or comments about this topic yes so if you could uh use the
mic just that people online can't hear
um I I have a question we were talking about um feeling the need to feel the the
silence in conversations um because I I feel the need to do that like I'm doing a little
closer um but so I I feel like I can Oh yeah
yeah i can be mindful but um it like those awkward silences and pauses in
conversations are where I have trouble like taking a step back yeah yeah yeah
so some people are not com a lot of people are not comfortable with silences and uh so you might have to
contextualize it for people you say you know uh uh you know we've been talking
for a while now and I need to get my bearings i wonder can we be quiet for a little bit or can I can I excuse myself
for a moment or the the the really sly thing to do is to is to say uh excuse me
I need to go to the bathroom and uh and no one's going to ask you what
you're doing there and what you're the reason you need to go to the bathroom is you want
to pause in the conversation and then you've gotten the free pass to have you know two three minutes five minutes
alone to process so so no it is hard to in these
conversations yeah okay and also it depends where you do the conversations also um sometimes
if you invite the person to go for a walk with you sometimes in walking it's
easier to be have longer pauses than if you're sitting kind of facing each other or something um yeah i'm thinking like
the context of like a new social environment where you feel pressure to speak to somebody you don't know and
could you hold up oh sorry i'm gonna I'm doing it again i'm feeling in in the context of that
environment I will go into those situations and be like anxious and then
say probably say too much or like overshare because I'm filling the space
yeah yeah yeah so yeah i mean I don't know what to
suggest i mean it's a social world is difficult world to be in so you it's not an easy to say this is what you can do
and the expectations and the cultures can be so different and people are anxious people are everyone's nervous so
everyone's trying to cope so it's hard to know but there's a few things that
sometimes are helpful and that is um show an interest in them and uh and so
so you can be quiet because you you've asked them questions and they're talking
and uh and people appreciate that your interest and then you don't you're kind of off the hook for a little while so
you can kind of process and and maybe as you're listening to them perhaps and um
and uh and then there's also active listening where you not only ask them questions but you also um affirm what
they're saying or you kind of uh just say something like oh so you you're new here you know they
something or you so so you know there's there's things you can say that might slow the conversation down uh so that
you you're you're not on the on the center stage like you feel
like you have to say something that uh about yourself or something wise just
ask them that can help yeah that that did help thank you
okay thanks Kil um it's great and smooth when you talk it's easy that it it it
will work but in reality when it comes to family it never works
so right um I think um for me uh what somebody's working is
um just accepting them and just accepting the way they are right um with
family friends and everything else is so easy yeah uh just accepting and then not
thinking about myself too much it's like oh my god Gil said this and you know I
think that helps but the relationship does change there's nothing I can do about it so I don't know if you have to
say something sounds like you're finding your way with your family how to be with them the the
relationship changes you know even if I'm quiet right so yeah yeah yeah i don't I don't feel like I can really say
anything because every family is going to have very different dynamics and and and uh and different capacities
and so you've been you're working with it for a while so you know it sounds like you're finding your way but uh but
you might for yourself internally ask yourself those questions is this the time to bring something up because
imagine sometimes you bring it up and um is this the time you know is this is
this uh effective or is this going to be useful to say this now and is there a
better more useful time or more useful way of saying it so you might have more agency around when you speak and how you
speak than uh what other people contribute and and expect so and
sometimes you know sometimes uh you can plan what you're going to say and you
know it's usually not best not try to memorize it but you can think it out ahead of time so if you have kids maybe
when they're at school think about what you know how you know you need to talk to them about cleaning their room and so
you know when do you do that and what's a good time to do it and when when do you when do you think you can get their
attention in a way that they really can take it in and uh oh you know if I make
their favorite cookie and uh and lay it out on the
kitchen table in a nice way so they have to come and sit to the kitchen table to eat their cookie and it might be there
there's a little bit space to say something here by the way you know I want to I know I've been brought brought
up this issue of the room your room but I want to let you know that um uh it
kind of it kind of hurts me to have this never taken care of so you kind of
create the conditions for the conversation that maybe is u so there's there's a lot of uh thinking ahead
sometimes thank you
i mean don't ask me these questions as if I'm the expert probably no one
is it's a work in progress for all of us
uh my question is um how to not have a checklist approach you know it's it's a
lot of work to constantly ask these five questions to myself like in every single
conversation cuz I've been trying to practice it for a while and is is there
a simpler way like just being with the body or being with the breath or I don't know like something
practical i I think that's a very good question and the idea that this being
more centered in your body mindful of your body uh usually creates more space
to see what's happening in the mind see what the impulses are and so you can be wiser about it and uh and just your your
innate wisdom might operate just fine take care of the situation it might
might also be though if you give some time reflecting and thinking about these five categories maybe one at a
time that after a while they become second nature and so they operate just
kind of they're not part of now you don't have to go through the list it's just that as as you give yourself more
space to be present they're kind of there in the background and it's kind of obvious after a while that you're
oriented that way makes sense
thank you so so one more in the back
this is kind of a follow on on on on that but uh I mean I obviously not
obviously I see the you know I can resonate with the value of right speech
and thinking about these things but it also when I think about doing it in the
midst of a conversation it feels terribly artificial like it am I going
to Yeah yeah yeah yeah you I mean to slow
down the conversation said wait wait wait I have to go through my five lists my
criteria yeah that that's kind of artificial uh but as I said these things
can become second nature after a while and so you don't have to think about them it's just like they waft up it's
like you can see oh this is not kind you know and and it must be probably I
should be quiet until I can a kinder thing comes up to say um or this is not
true you know so it becomes second nature after a while hopefully and then
um as as was just said um just just uh being grounded in your body being
centered and being present here for your own experience goes a long way to create
uh the kind of natural the kind of space for kind of a natural wisdom to operate that uh if we uh if we're losing oursel
in a conversation chances are you've lost touch with your body
thank you yeah and the body gives us a lot of information about what goes on
interpersonally the tensions in the body the postures of the body the agitations in the body the warmth in the body the
the softness that comes in so a lot of different things a lot of information there that informs us about what our
relationship to what's going on and the more we can take that in the wiser we'll be in the in the
conversation okay well uh I'm very confident that you'll have lots of
opportunities to practice and so just doing a little bit
of it can go a long way don't don't you know don't tie yourself in knots uh by
all these all these criteria but just just starting starting to open up this door of mindfulness of speaking is a
powerful door it's invaluable and in the process you'll learn a lot about yourself and as you learn about yourself
you'll be wiser about the things you say how you say it so everyone's welcome to
stay for the potluck and uh whether you're brought anything for it or not it
it's just an excuse for us to get together and and be friendly and get to know each other so uh so uh I don't know
it'll take a few minutes to do the final setup and then there'll be some
indication that we can start to serve each other and serve ourselves and then uh please please um I think there's a
circle that's formed yeah the fo's formed and there's some blessing or the food or something that goes on so um
probably in about 5 minutes or so so uh in the meantime you can talk and hang
out and thank you