okay welcome folks um good to uh good to be with
you so
um many years ago Gil said something like um it's not you who gets free it's that
you free everything else
and um that resonates with that the line from the um maim andaya that I shared
some weeks ago only when when there is what belongs to a self is there
self it's not you who gets free it's you free everything
else so we uh practice in this
Spirit how much might we
free so finding a finding a
posture e
so if you're sitting stretch up towards the sky with the spine
give everything else to the Earth
just arriving with your breath
just letting it all take its place amidst awareness
what's excluded often haunts us
and yet to include is not to be entangled
with to be entangled with is just another kind of
exclusion excluding the fear or the stickiness or the whatever
so we
include
and let our life flow through awareness
not clanking into any
whirl pools of
clinging so we
breathe
e
e e
and how how much of experience can we free
to free our images and
sounds to free our pain
Tranquility to free our feelings our
whole Rich affect of life to free our
thoughts not to be free from thought but to free our thoughts
what a strain possessiveness
is so much
tension and owner
ship what can be freed as we
breathe
e
e e
what whatever tastes like self whatever
tastes like
me like I am
this we let go
the whole play of uh
appearances rising and
passing becomes uh
personal e
and we I
move out of the position of protagonist into just a kind of another little
incidental subplot the Majesty of awareness
don't take a stand
anywhere
e
e e
there's more safety and openness than there is
in insisting upon continuity
assuming that what comes next to
me
e
e e
in uh greed and virion
fear these
forces maybe uh intrinsically create the
impulse to
control great delusion always has an owner but in
equinity the self thins out
just resting for these last few minutes
e
e e
[Music]
e
okay
um so I'm uh at a
uh at a stoplight uh this morning and uh I had uh just seeing the
uh Dylan film with uh with my parents a couple days ago and was
listening to one of his um early songs um M take this badge off of me I can't
use it anymore it's getting dark too dark to see feel I'm knocking on heaven's
door and was thinking about
uh my friend uh Ann Buck uh died uh this
week I think 93 50 years of Dharma practice and um
while she was uh in in the hospital um her house in the Palisades
um burned to the ground uh it's a place I i' had spent decent amount of time and
um yeah tragedy for sure um and in some moods she might have
said um something
like a better view uh of the
Moon and earlier earlier in the morning I was
flipping through Timothy Snider's book on um resisting
autocracy and um was surprised how many of the chapters the maxims are
essentially about fairly ordinary CA and emotional
Clarity and I'm at the stoplight I'm sipping a a
good cup of coffee and
um yeah enjoying and I heard somebody say um
when two molecules of hydrogen and one oxygen are coming
together I think they don't know they don't have any idea that they
could become water and um and I'm aware of all of
this um amidst all of this I'm
uh happy very happy and
then this person dressed head to toe in
fluorescent psychedelic confetti riding a bright pink bike
pedals past me I'm like okay this is life
here and so we um
we do our best to live the
Dharma and you didn't um come to
a uh memorial service here and I don't want to impose
my private um loss but I imagine Anne Buck's life has some meaning for most
any Dharma practitioner and I I knew an from
Retreats with uh shins and yang um starting in I think
2003 and cumulatively we probably sat many months together often next to each
other close to each other and uh you really get to know a
person in the silin and sometimes I I'd sort of feel
like like i' I'd sit next to her kind of draft you know like um the leader of a
you know like one drafts behind the the lead Rider in a bicycle race or
something they're breaking the wind kind of and um I remember one time we we both
arrived early to a a two we Retreat year end
Retreat casad de Maria and and uh Santa Barbara and uh we were both we kind of
both sort of caught each other greedily looking
for the best spot in the room you know we were there early like before registration opened I think and um and
we said to each other like first we cling then it's time to let go
and I remember the first time I got kind of a big gulp of freedom I remember her
saying afterwards like I saw you I saw your eyes I knew what was
happening and we um we taught some um dayong retreats in LA
and we would always like plan really carefully and orchestrated and have an
outline and it was kind of like whatever we did it would just get really teary in
the room you know and perhaps it was meaningful for
you know um yogis to see two people separated by almost 50 years who love
each other and um and she was fierce she was kind
of fierce so when she said it's okay to really love yourself you
know you you knew she wasn't playing she was a restaurant tour I
think owned a few restaurants ran some restaurants and um and I'm not sure I
would want to have been her Sue Chef I can say that but when she
said it's okay to love yourself you did did what the woman
said and um ever since um I moved from
LA to the Bay Area she uh you know about 12 years ago
or so she she suggested that um we chat each month on the phone
just about life and practice and you know I thought you know I thought maybe
still think we were speaking as friends but I don't know I kind of suspect in
some way that um she wanted to just quietly support me
offer her blessing try to ensure I didn't do anything especially
stupid you know and we would have these like very lovely free flowing conversations about kind of whatever was
important uh but the Dharma was stri through all of that and
her yeah her confidence in the Dharma seemed to me seemed
unshakable and somehow yeah the path would just Infuse
everything we would discuss and just sort of feeling like oh yeah she's
sharing her mind and
um and greed hate and delusion just kind of looks so silly in the the
mirror of that openness and that kind of made whatever
life was for each of us us somehow okay
enough and there was something about her her home um the view
from her backyard which is quite striking now in ashes you know I
looked on the whatever the was tracking it you know hoping home was
okay and um but uh you know
the Cal Fire has photos of each house
damaged or okay and it's just
ashes um but that view that view a month ago
just a month ago that view reminded me of her of her mind in a way I know she
likeed to sit out there practice you know it's very gorgeous view some grass and the kind of Hillside
Santa Monica Mountain Hillside and um overlooking the water
the Pacific and an had uh had practiced with
shinen and young um to whom we both feel like we
owe our life in some ways maybe but also
withe and and with sometimes just kind of very simple way just remark how much
kind of ready access she had to a mind that uh you know classically
described as intrinsically empty naturally radiant ceaselessly responsive
and she would ask you know like how easy is that for you how accessible is that
for you there's a lot of safety in that that
guides you through disease macular degeneration
through family pain pain of the world that uh keeps you keeps you
well and as she entered her 90s is I would um I would call at our appointed
time and I was never certain how she would
be and I could hear her aging and um I would help her sometimes with a
word or ignore it because it didn't matter
and uh still till the end the the kind of emotional resonance the the presence of
dhma was fully intact and uh there's something precious
about uh kind of spiritual friends who
can uh hear the hian tone of one's
heart and um know there were many many received her
her blessings and so um it's worthwhile
to reflect on life and death the gifts
of of fearlessness you know uh to reflect on that that question
I posed uh maybe a couple months ago how
How would our love look were we little less
afraid um for Andrew Wood by uh poem by
uh James Fenton what would the dead want from us
watching from their cave would they have us forever
howling would they have have us Rave or disfigure ourselves or be strangled like
some ancient emperor slave none of my dead friends were
Emperors with such exorbitant tastes and none of them were so vengeful
as to have all their friends waste waste quite way in sorrow disfigured and
defaced I think the dead would want us to weep for what they have
lost I think that our luck in continuing is what would affect them
most but time would find them generous and less self-
engrossed and time would find them generous as they used to be and what
else would they want from us than an honored place in our memory a favorite
room a hallowed chair privilege and
celebrity and so the dead might cease to grieve and we might make
amends there might be a pact between dead friends and living
friends what our dead friends would want from us would be such living friends
okay thank you