hello and welcome to this meditation session and as a beginning I'd like
to tell you of a study that I read about many years
ago where they took um some teenagers from deep in Metropolitan
New York grew up kind of in a uh without ever leaving New York and then living
kind of I think they were people living somewhat poor lives and and um you know so their range of
experience was quite small and they took them to some place like the jungles of Costa
Rica uh to go out with the people who had spent their life teenagers who had
spent their life living in that environment and the locals in Costa Rica
would point out birds and different things happening in the forest and uh that stood out
jumped out to them it was obvious to them that they could see them and but the the teens from New York could not
see them they didn't have the ability they didn't know where to look and how to see
and and so the story points to the idea that we get accustomed to a particular
way of what we're familiar with and we maybe pick up what's familiar but
there's a lot that we miss as a result in meditation uh that tendency comes that
we come with our familiar world of thoughts and concerns and even the way
that we uh think of ourselves uh can be uh kind of set in
our ways so that we're not so sensitive and attuned to notice other aspects of
our experience to uh to become skilled in
samadi is to begin to become sensitive and expand the range of what we're aware
of so we can be aware of the subtle shifts that go on the shifts that uh uh
show us the path of Samar the shifts that uh open to a deep deing absorption
deep deepening mind state of samadi and so part of that is the
evidence that samadi just beginning maybe the first kind of beginning of
things that lead to a state of samadi if we spend our time preoccupied with what
to have for lunch preoccupied with the argument we had before preoccupied with
um kind of a negative selft talk or maybe positive self s talk
even that um if that's the normal way of seeing the lens through which we see we
might not have the Mind quiet enough um or capacity to sense sensitive
enough to start listening to the finding the rare animals in the forest the birds
in the forest like I think some people who are going bird watching and want to listen for the
cries of the bird might make their thinking mind
quiet to have a and everything become still inside of them except for their
listening for that quiet bird song So in meditation then when you sit
down to meditate to be start becoming attuned to
the subtle shifts that happen that um
the subtle shifts that that they have um in
um uh in your
uh uh in what happens to you as you sit down to meditate and in the course of
the meditation what are the subtle shifts and they not so subtle shifts that that are the evidence or the
Gathering Together that repes represents somebody and um
and uh and so when you first sit down uh you might come along with a lot
of your concerns but is there a feeling of goodness or rightness or heness in
your body as you sit down does something already begin to relax and soften taking the meditation
posture and if so uh feel that a align
yourself with that attune yourself to that as you begin to relax
intentionally what are the what's the what's the impact the influence that
relaxing has on the parts of the muscles that relax around the muscles and the rest of
you in what way does beginning to Center yourself here on the body on the breath
begin to quiet your mind begin to shift the direction of where
your concerns are where your attention is going as you settle in more are there
subtle shifts of things becoming calmer or more centered or more
grounded to pick those up to see them as the the as the traces of the path to be
followed not to hold on to them not to push anything but to the more we can feel all we have to
do is see them and feel them and sense these the evidence of samade beginning
to grow for that be contribute to the Gathering and more important to
contribute to the mind the attention wanting to be here in this process this
process of somi starts feeling very inviting uh it because it's uh enjoy
able it's Pleasant there's a goodness and rightness to it we're following the evidence the path the
trail of something that uh feels really
good and before we last thing I'll say is that this being skilled in the
evidence of suar however subtle it might be is
um is um the Buddha sometimes calls being skilled in the
beautiful and there's something about samadi the evidence of it that maybe we can start appreciating as a certain kind
of beauty even though it's only maybe 1% of our
experience that's where the trail is that's where the path is not to push other things
away but not to leave it out to become attuned
aligned encouraged guided
supported by this subtle evidence that allows you to get more and
more settled so to assume a meditation
posture and closing your eyes and now feeling
ing the subtle shifts that's happened for you in assuming a meditation
posture is something
subtle is there a goodness or a rightness in beginning to
be connected to oneself simply from taking the posture
gently slowly taking some deeper
breaths and as you exhale soften relaxing in the
body and as the body relaxes is is there a subtle influence
or effect that has in parts of your body that feels
good
to let your breathing return to
normal and is there already just sitting here
quietly in your own body heart and mind
some subtle shift that's happening that you associate with
meditation that feels
good and to be attuned to that aligned with
that almost as if the way you're going to pay attention
the way you're going to be aware
somehow takes on qualities of the caling that you feel in
your body or pleasure or the
goodness and with a normal breath to on the exhale to relax more
fully in the body in different parts of the body in
the whole body
relaxing and into a subtle Place deep
within the settling spot the grounding
spot the centering spot Within maybe where the exhale
finishes and the inhale
begins and is there some glow or Radiance
or softening
caling that's spreading a little bit beyond the edges of your
breathing in some parts of your
body some evidence that the process of meditation
is
beginning it doesn't have to be dramatic or could be very subtle and
quiet but notice it appreciate its presence
and
to settle into the sensations of breathing
as if awareness and
breathing are
gently absorbing each
other as if in the meeting of breathing and
awareness something good begins to
happen and awareness it's very light
as light as a butterfly that lands on the
breathing as light as
sunlight that shines its
beauty on the experience of
breathing
e e
sensitive to the subtlest of shifts
that come with
meditation not searching for them but in a relaxed way sensing
them so that part of the shifts is it shifts in the
mind the Mind becoming soft
lighter and where this the sum total of the shifts that we
feel gently guide the mind guide
attention to be intimate with the experience of
breathing e
and noticing any pleasure that is also a symptom evidence
of the practice of
meditation
e
for
e e
as we approach the end of the sitting maybe letting go of focusing on the
breathing letting go of your thoughts and becoming aware
of the general Broadway in which You've Been Changed by this
meditation is there a broader embodied feelings
being calmer more settled some broader feeling of
something that's Pleasant settled
relaxed a greater intimacy Here and
[Music]
Now to feel the broadest widest
sense widest evidence of a shift in the course of the
meditation a shift that is good that feels
good feels satisfying feels Pleasant
even if there are other things that are troubling and difficult that to allow that to be as it
is but to attune yourself to the more subtle way that in
the body heart and mind there might be some subtle way
that of pleasure of calmness goodness intimacy
quiet and if there
is with the lightest possible
touch allow the rhythm of breathing to gently move through do it
to touch it to
recognize the broader feeling evidence of how things have
shifted in a good way
and if you stay connected to whatever that's been
good that has shifted in the course of this meditation imagine imagine yourself
settled in that allow yourself to be settled in
that as you now turn your attention your
thoughts out into the world that you'll encounter
today and to en allow yourself to encounter that world of today
from this subtle place of meditation the goodness of it the subtleness of
it so there's room for Good
Will care
generosity respect for all that you you encounter
all the people that you learn about
and almost as every individual that you talk to talk about read
about see in person or on a
screen that you imagine them being settled and happy
imagine that possibility for them and wish it for
them may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this next talk on
samadi and um this time I want to discuss the topic of the
evidence of samadi the evidence of becoming more
settled calm absorbed connected to the meditation
process and um in uh in the language of the Buddha there was a word for this
evidence the symptoms and uh it is nimita n i m
TTA and it's um one day two days two T's
um maybe it's one t but nimita and it um it
um it is um sometimes has kind of come down into the present times in the
meditation traditions of Buddhism to uh refer to only one example of the the
symptom of meditation and um I don't not going to bother you with what that one
example is because it it's really an example of what comes out of a very particular way of practicing
meditation uh in the ancient world there was just lots of symptoms for what uh
evidence for what happens as we meditate and um and so that whatever it
is whatever the symptoms are what shifts and change um is uh meant to support the
practice and uh one of the words that uh I associate with this is uh Beauty and
the Buddha called talked about the becoming skilled in the beauty of
Samar because these symptoms that we have this evidence are have a beauty to
them or a pleasure to them or rightness or goodness to them they have there
sometime sometimes they they feel healthy there's a healthful health healthiness that comes along with
them and uh um and the idea is to be sensitive to them and include them as
part of the range of what we're aware of as we
meditate and um and generally what I suggest is not to take them as the focus
of meditation don't get preoccupied or caught in them and uh even though they feel good some people are pumping them
up trying to make this stronger but the idea is the symptoms that feel calmer
more subtle um often is associated as we get deeper into with uh different Sensations
feelings emotions even that are quite Pleasant like joy and happiness and um
and a lot of pleasure physical kind of sense of pleasure that flows or radiates from the meditation
itself and so rather than focusing on them or being preoccupied with them or
drawing conclusions for them or congratulating yourself for them being there the idea is to take them as a as
cheerleaders and say continue what you're doing what you're doing is good and uh and let them be there on the
edges supporting you guiding you and sometimes what you can feel is that as
like with the breathing with the Rhythm or breathing you can feel that as you kind of Follow That Rhythm and get more
absorbed and more intimate with it you can feel that it has a growing effect on
the evidence on the nimita on the effect that the wider effect that it has on
your body mind and and heart and uh so there can be tingling in
the body there can be a sense of wonderful delightful humming or vibration there can be a feeling of
things becoming body becoming lighter and softer translucent um the body seems to become
uh uh the in in the inside of the body can start see feeling like it's like a
vast wonderful kind of Cavern or uh Great Space feeling more and more space
is one of these evidence of of the Mind entering Sadi Sometimes some people will feel
that the mind seems to become very quite expansive that the narrow mind the contracted mind is often a sign of
preoccupation being caught in something and as we're less caught the mind starts feeling more expansive and that's this
evidence the sign um sometimes the people use the word sign quite a bit for what I'm
talking about the symptom the sign the evidence and uh sometimes there can be a
strong Sensations flow of pleasure sometimes it has a flowing feeling in the body sometimes it has a pulsing
feeling in the body and sometimes in intense ways it can feel like a cascading waterfall or breaking waves of
pleasure that rushes through the body so it can be strong but it's it doesn't
have to be strong and in some ways it's can be more useful if it's not so strong
some people push it and try to make these things strong but uh the just well
enough that it supports the mind to get quieter supports this the a seeing or
following the trail that's open up opening up in front of us as we meditate of a trail or onward leading to a
feeling of um of of mean each person can choose their own
word to describe this a feeling of coming home a feeling of intimacy a feeling of being uh deeply calm and at
ease feeling of being peaceful a feeling of kind of being absorbed gathering together and being
really here in a wholehearted way in a wholebody way and whm minded way this
feeling of being complete and whole right with her our
experience and um sometimes this the symptom can be uh the inner eye or the
eyes it can seem like SE light sometimes it can be white light some people will see
different color lights sometimes the lights are colored lights are shifting and changing in different kinds of
patterns or something and uh again it's best not to get focused on those things that can be
quite entertaining or interesting if it's colors um but the idea is to always let these things these symptoms be in
the periphery as saying is almost like encouragements yes this is a sign that
the meditation is going well um let's not get involved with the signs let's not get preoccupied with them and let's
kind of just stay keep the hold the course hold the course don't get distracted by
them and some of the signs and symptoms will settle away over time and disappear
to be replaced by by others some might get stronger before they settle away and
disappear and uh and generally the the momentum and movement of somebody is a
is a movement towards more calm more peace uh more Simplicity greater and
greater Simplicity that feels very very satisfying to to have and so uh these signs symptoms um
Can Ur uh start occurring at the very beginning when you first sit down
especially if you're used to you have a familiar and comfortable posture to sit down into when you meditate the
familiarity the regularity of assuming this posture means that almost
immediately uh we are um um we can start feeling something is
beginning to shift shift in a good way and we a little calmer the body softens
and relax um there's a feeling of things the body not being aligned some people don't
really live in a really good aligned posture in ordinary life but in
meditation it can feel so good to kind of take that kind of a posture that's upright and aligned and anything that
feels good about the posture then about relaxing centering oneself on the
breathing kind of resting in the settling place like grounding place um
uh any way in which it feels good for the mind to be attentive and this is
where the art of samade has a lot to do with the art of learning how to use our
attention in a way that we enjoy that feels nice if we're jerking the mind around if
we're pouncing on them ourselves because we're wondered off and that's not good
and we're then uh straining and bearing down to like we desperate to be
concentrated that's not a beautiful that's not enjoyable that's not a a pleasant way of being aware but to find
a way that's Pleasant to be aware so the Mind wants to be aware in the present moment so the mind is more interested in
being attentive to the present than it is to be preoccupied in thoughts so all
of what I'm describing can be understood as being the symptoms and signs that the
meditation beginning to uh create a good context a good feeling in within and
sometimes it could be subtler than some of the difficult feelings that we have and it isn't that we want to push
the the difficult feelings away or condemn them or something but uh to feel
some any of these subtler signs of calm or subtleness or goodness or um
receptivity that's there that um that becomes a way to hold what's
difficult that's a way to relate to it that's a way of caring for it in a nice
kind of container and a nice attitude so that uh it itself the difficulties we
have are being tended being uh cared for
being nurtured be uh by Love by Care by kindness by uh
spaciousness by allowing them to be there in a soft accepting way and there's a kind of a sense of the beauty
of it or the calm or the pleasure of meditation kind of maybe allows what's
difficult to soften by itself to be felt in a different context so we're not so
caught in it or troubled by it so
um um so the signs of meditation the nimita the evidence of it of what's
Happening there's an art to learning how to gently
modestly um use them to support the Gathering Together the unification the
settling the onward leading nature of meditation as we start entering into the
world of samade where we're entering into kind of a new space a new way of
being uh for the duration of samadi so thank you very much and uh may
you um I'm very fond of this idea of the word Whisperer like a horse
whisperer and um and so may you be the whisper of your
samade and um May you respectfully care and listen and sensed to the things that
are often overlooked so that you can settle more deeply into the
practice so thank you very much and we'll continue tomorrow