so I'm happy to happy to be back here after
being uh gone for a week i was at the Zen monastery in down outside in the
mountains of um Big Su near Monterey Tasahara and Tasara has a river going
through it the Tasara River and one of the
you know one of the fairly well-known saying is the idea you cannot step in the same river twice but the uh full uh
uh quote goes something like you cannot step in the same river twice because
it's never the same river and never the same person that the person's also changing all the
time buddhism uses a a central metaphor in
Buddhism is a river flowing in a river
and so for this meditation I'd like to offer you a image
uh for sitting in meditation that uh emphasizes the constant change
the river of change that we're in river of time river of change that's all
around us so the image is that of a big solid
boulder sitting in the middle of a river and the water of the river just flows
right by it just flows and flows and flows but the the the the boulder is
solid sitting there and that someone goes to meditate on
that boulder and feels like the boulder solid
and everything is allowed to just flow by every thought every feeling whatever
is happening is allowed to flow to be in the river we don't pull any
water out of the river we don't um
we don't do pull a bucket of water and hold on to the bucket we just let everything flow in meditation move and
flow through the variation of this is that the boulder
is you and you're sitting there like the
boulder but the boulder also is not made of rock
but it's made of ice maybe a big ice block fell off a glacier into a river
and that slowly over time not only does the river wear out the ice
it melts the ice it melts the ice
and eventually all the ice all the water of the ice melts
and joins the river and now instead of being
the boulder you are the river
in this way we sit in meditation in the stream of change
everything's changing constant change
except for in some way or other we freeze our
experience through our thoughts our attachments our preoccupations
and the meditation is to allow for all things to flow and move in our
experience it's the nature of perception experience
even the nature of thoughts themselves to constantly be shifting and changing
and flowing and that doesn't have to be
a whirlpool doesn't have to be an eddi or rapids
it doesn't have to be a stagnant river everything can flow can flow together in
the same direction harmoniously and we flow in it we ourselves are
constantly changing we also are the river of of change
so to sit in meditation like a boulder
feeling solid in your seat in the place where you're meditating
and to gently close your eyes
and to settle into being here in a solid grounded way
taking some fuller breaths deeper breaths
and relaxing on the exhale
releasing to the pull of gravity on the exhale
without Losing a solid posture
letting your breathing return to normal and for two or three breaths more
softening the the body on the exhale
softening the thinking mind
as if what is solid and tight or contracted in the mind thinking mind
can melt can soften Amen
do you feel for some people the emotional center
maybe in the heart or the belly wherever it might be
soften softening relaxing
sometimes the river is a river of tears
sometimes it's a river that's gentle gentle
flow through our body
and then to feel the sensations of breathing
the inhale comes and goes
the exhale begins and ends
the changing sensations of the inhale are sensations in the body
expansion and pressure movement
a feeling of fullness
and imagine that your the sensations of breathing the experience of your body
breathing that you're gazing upon it
from your boulder but watching it flow by
as if sitting looking at a river the current the
gentle waves the ripples
as the water flows on and on
or watching the waves lap up on the sand beach
and recede with the kind of gaze that would you
that you would use relaxed
watching a natural process of change in your own body
watching their river the waves of breathing
except for sitting on a solid boulder
let everything else
be in the river of Change every perception
every thought every feeling
is flowing moving
Some things like a river the river is always there
but the flowing of the river is also always there
the river is the flow the change
and then allowing the boulder to dissolve in the water
maybe the boulder is made of ice
so nothing is held out of the water nothing's held away from the flow
all of who you are
is part of the changing nature of the present moment always
changing shifting flowing
every p perception changes
thoughts change
sensations and sounds
maybe the sensations of breathing are the central current of the river
stay in the current in the middle of the river change
all things are changing
just as in the present moment the sensations of breathing
are changing
so in the present moment all experiences
all sensations thoughts feelings
in and of themselves are shifting changing
flowing
don't hold yourself out of the river
let all things melt into the flow of change
and as things change
to be soft soft without resisting change without pushing
the change
finding a way to be in harmony with the change that's about to happen
which is bringing this meditation to an end
just the river is taking a different bend
it's always flowing
to take a few long slow deep breaths to feel
more connected to your body
maybe feeling a little bit more like you're on the boulder again solid and
grounded here
and appreciate that one way or the other all of us
are involved in a constant process of change
sometimes what's new appears sometimes
what has been disappears sometimes what's here grows old
or matures and ripens
and in this tender changing world
to be each other's companions in the river of change
so we care for each other we help each other float and move and
be known may it be
that we are each other's companions with care with kindness with love
in this flowing and changing world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be at peace
in this changing world may all beings be free
as a river flows freely without any obstacles
may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and welcome back to this series on insight
that is following the longer series on samadei
and um so after a break uh for this last week I
want to pick up again and now do a series of talks on the first primary
insight of insight meditation which is uh insight into the experience
of change of inconstancy of impermanence
and um that things are constantly shifting ing and changing and arising
and passing appearing and dissolving and disappearing
that this is a really central aspect of human life
and becoming wise about the changing nature of life is something that a lot
of wisdom traditions maybe all wisdom traditions uh emphasize
and Heracitis is the one who said you can't step in the same river twice but
even more wisely u the rest of the quote goes uh you
cannot step in the same river twice because it's never the same river and never the same person stepping into it
and um the um
um so even you are changing just as the river is constantly changing and
shifting and we often have ideas
that don't change with the changing nature of reality we have ideas that
things are going to be this way forever uh and some things will never that
disappear will never come back but the art of
and the power of mindfulness practice is to appreciate that in our direct
experience what we're experiencing is constantly coming and going
and uh and the nothing stays the same uh in experience in what we sense and feel
and and um the nature of all the different aspects of the human being
that come together in the moment we're always a change and to a great degree
the world is too there's a a Sufi story that I like of uh
a man who had a ring made and uh he went to a Sufi master and said "Can you
inscribe something on this ring that uh whenever I look at it um I will be wise
or will support me in my life." And so the master said "Yes please leave it here." And when the man returned in a
week to pick up his inscribed ring uh uh in it was written on in it was on it was
written um this too will pass
this too will pass and um so Buddhism is not unique in
emphasizing the changing nature of the world and in fact I've met people who I
thought were more wise than uh many of the Buddhists I've known people who have
been in the middle of uh life's challenges in the middle of uh all the
changing nature of life and death and change and war and peace and
um poverty and wealth and just has been people have been through it all so much
different things that and through it all they haven't been become become bitter
they haven't become despondent they haven't become afraid somehow or other
they've come to the point in their life where they understand in some deep way
and wise way that everything is changing all the time and to expect change not to
be surprised by it certainly there can be sadness certainly
there can be grief certainly there can be joy and celebration by what changes and moves along in our life the uh but
um but to to really appreciate so that there's a way maybe of stepping into the
change be stepping with it being with it flowing with it being in harmony with it
um not fighting it unnecessarily not um
uh pushing for change faster or not
holding on to things so they don't change these are not universal ways of being
but given how much things are always changing there's a way of being wise
about that and not foolish there's a ways way of being in harmony with that
rather than out of harmony with how things are always changing
in uh Zen Buddhism a person who's a novice monk a monk in training uh is
referred to in Japanese as an unsui and uh the word unui is made up of two
characters two words cloud and water and it's pointing to the idea that uh
someone in training in Zen um should go wa go through the monastic life like
clouds and waters fluid and flowing and moving around not resisting anything
uh but um somehow adjusting and sh and and reforming a cloud is constantly
reshaping itself with what's there and a water uh is constantly kind of going to
the going to the the lowest point always flowing around things and with things
and being lowest point being the point maybe of peace or freedom that something
inside of us is in the flow towards freedom from holding tight freedom from
being contracted freedom from resisting tight because those things are a lot of work those things involve a resistance
we don't have to accept things as they are uh we don't have necessarily accept everything that's changing part of
Buddhism is to appreciate how deeply things are changing but um they're not
chaotic and especially in our own direct experience for ourselves what's moving
and flowing and throughing us and what's growing in us we we we're not internally
chaotic through dharma practice we slowly learn to uh to come into a kind of inner
harmony and to shape and develop so that the river that's flowing through us is a
harmonious river or the the what's growing within us becomes u uh beautiful
and supportive and healthy there's a metaphor in Buddhism of again
of the rivers often used by the Buddha but one one metaphor is the analogy is
that um high up in the mountains when the river is still small and a creek or
a stream and it's going over rapids and going over boulders and um the river can be
quite noisy and when it's a waterfall it's a big roar
and um but when the river finally uh gets big enough and comes down into the
plains and is wide and big and the river becomes silent and it flows harmonious
so in our own life as we begin dharma practice um the dharma is flowing
through us um kind more like a high in the mountains and uh it's having to deal
with boulders and rapids and waterfalls and u blockages and things and and um
and it's uh sometimes it's chaotic and sometimes it's um you know waterfalls
and rapids sometimes It's uh noisy and challenging
but we stay in the river we stay in the practice and as we bring our kindness we
bring our uh clear attention as we bring our samadei as we bring our goodwill as
we bring our nonattachment all these things grow as as joy grows as
seeing things more clearly grows as um a sense of tranquility grows
equinimity grows uh the sense of The dharma river we we are becomes stronger
bigger and it begins flowing silently it still flows but it's a silent flow
and um and so we can go through
this world as a powerful
peaceful flowing river that can meet anything
that comes anything that comes our ways with wisdom with compassion with clarity
maybe with a skill and the ability to welcoming welcoming it into that
peaceful river welcoming into the flow of love and care friendship that we
change the world through the flow of love the flow of
peace the flow of the river of caring for each other in this world
we don't we're not a boulder we're not the rocks that are tumbling in
the river banging against each other we become the river we welcome
everything into the river maybe we're helping the ice b the ice
boulders to dissolve so this introduction then to the theme
of impermanence uh I wanted to emphasize that um it's
not a unique wisdom that Buddhism has uh I think I'd
like to propose that all wisdom traditions have contended with the same experience that we live in the river in
the world of change things are changing all the time and that there's an
ordinary even everyday way that we can become wise about how things change that
doesn't require deep meditation doesn't require deep insight it just in it requires
um ordinary sight that we see clearly and we stop and reflect and contemplate
the all the change that we see here so that
we can be in this world in a wise way may it be that our exploration of
impermanence ana the poly word may it be
that uh it's a way of supporting this world to become more peaceful and caring
may we care for all beings without exception thank you