and this morning um we're going to meditate together before we start um if
you take a moment to either silently reflect on or share somehow what you noticed in your
practice yesterday anything at all related to the
themes of connecting with wisdom with
abundance
kindness relating to the moment
And when you're ready taking your seat whatever posture you're
in settling in to your space for
meditation perhaps taking a moment to look around or listen to the
soundsscape allow a small smile or sense of connection with
yourself with your body
beginning to allow the attention to move
inward noticing the sounds around
you the silence between the sounds
noticing the warmth or cool of the
body the weight of your body on the chair or cushion or mat
and connecting the [Music] tuning with the internal world of this
body all the little sensations of aliveness
scanning through your
body maybe a gentle sweep of the attention from the head to the
feet inviting the eyes to relax in their
sockets the area between the eyes and the brow and behind the eyes and the
head to soften and spread
eyes closed but perhaps as if taking in a broad
vista allowing the tongue to soften
and sweeping the attention down through the neck and
chest noticing the sensations of the body breathing
allowing the mind to be soothed the heart to
rest in a gentle rhythm of in and out breath
allowing the whole core of your body to
relax softening the hips and buttocks thighs and hamstrings
noticing softening the shins and calves ankles and
feet and taking in the integrity of the whole body
allowing awareness to fill
it and settling onto each inb breath and outreath or whatever anchor of
attention object of attention feels most imbalanced
in connection today
if the mind the attention is pulled
away by thoughts images wants or aversions
gently staying in your
seat returning to mindfulness
awareness noticing any leaning towards or leaning
away and when it's possible returning to simple
balanced awareness
if the mind becomes entranced seeing how
graciously appreciatively it's possible to
welcome the return of mindful awareness
in the last few minutes of our meditation
together the invitation is to open
up your awareness to know the
knowing include the quality of mindfulness itself in the
knowing take a step back open the lens of awareness
allowing everything that's known just to flow
through allowing your heart your mind
to be
bright nourished by the knowing itself
and then as we draw this meditation to a
close The invitation is to
appreciate recall any moments of
embodiment mindful awareness
contentment any moments of
simplicity goodness
kindness and in your heart offering the benefits of that
outward to the others in this world those your life touches directly and indirectly
and those unseen far
away may all beings be safe happy peaceful and
free and may our practice here together be a cause and condition for
greater love liberation and peace in the world
[Music]
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
so sa today we continue the series on inspirations for
insight stories and wisdom from the myths and stories of the Buddha's life
and others around him but before I start I'd like to make an announcement which
is um that the Sati Center for Buddhist Studies
many of you know this organization kind of a sister organization to
IMC they are um they've opened their applications for the Buddhist chapency
training program about a week ago and um there are two versions of this program
there's an in-person version with Gil and two other teachers and an online
version with myself and two other teachers both are wonderful i went
through the first and now teach the second um so for your consideration if
you're looking for a way to bring your practice into a um deepen it in an
engaged way a way that helps
others so I'd like to sto start today's um talk
today's inspiration for um insight
with a story so um that
story is the night the very night of the Buddha's enlightenment
awakening and um some of you were here last yesterday and heard the kind of
pre-story of him receiving nourishment and kindness and deciding on the middle
way and then he made the determination strong determination that he was going
to sit under the bodhic tree until he awoke and so off he went and he did and it's
kind of the culmination of his hero's journey from a mythic
perspective he's sitting and as he's
sitting Mara the um mythic figure the namesake
literally means death who symbolizes the life denying forces mara comes and
brings his armies it said brings every force to bear sense desire ill will
horrific visions of all kinds and the Buddha observes this play
of just intense arising of these images and
of the hostility and of the desire unmoved
so Mara then shoots his army shoots volleys and volleys of arrows at the
Buddha and in this myth they're converted to showers of flowers raining
down on him instead of piercing him offering this sort of beautiful
fragrance that's associated in the ancient texts with
virtue and then finally Mara is not getting anywhere with all of this so he
taunts the Buddha with one last kind of attempt to undermine his
practice his awakening and he says "Who are you to wake up who are you?" He
taunts him with doubt and it's said that in
response the Buddha touches the earth beneath
him and in some versions of this story the earth shakes in response i think of
this as as earth as my witness and then when he
awoke he awoke completely it said that it's the end of ignorance and this is
canonical here freedom from all forms of suffering and a knowledge of the karmic
effects of actions of living beings action and result where people how
people are impacted by their own actions after his awakening the Buddha
went to another tree and it said rested under it stared at it for a full seven
days enjoying the bliss of samadei and
freedom so powerful evocative myth right it's the culmination of this hero's
journey an embodiment of courage
determination restraint and a peaceful victory you'll notice there was no
combat but instead he stayed in his
seat so that's the story and
um want to invite you to take whatever feels inspiring in it to you into your
heart and mind i'll offer a few reflections in the next few minutes of some wisdom I found it holds for
approaching the experience of insight one lesson I take from this is that the
mind can experience insight the heart can experience freedom even when the
most difficult kinds of memories or images or
hindrances are present in fact that can be the moment of very strong insight
i've seen this in people I support and I've seen it in my own practice as well
as we covered yesterday the exact same experience can be challenging and
difficult can be distracting or discouraging or it can be a penetrating insight
the difference lies in how we relate to experience and what mental
faculties are implied here so I talked a lot yesterday about how we relate to
experience and that will be a little bit in this talk as well but first I'll kind of focus a little bit
more on the faculties of mind so the first things that you notice in
these mind in his mind in this story is
that if we kind of depersonify Mara and his attack all of the mental hindrances
are t that are talked about in the Buddhist teachings are present sexual or sensual desire which is by definition a
lifegiving force here is utilized as a distraction and then there are these
horrific visions ill will of being shot at and fear of all
kinds the Buddha meets these rather than becoming entranced by desire or pulling
away or pushing away in fear or disgust or horror he holds his
seat even though all hell was breaking loose he stayed present he didn't give in he
didn't give up but he also he didn't actively engage in fighting there was a
non-contention present in other words if we consider the Buddha
in this story as our inner capacity potentiality for awakening awakened
awareness which is on a continuum with simple
mindfulness he was mindful simply present and that kind of simple presence
of mindfulness not leaning towards or away is a powerful support for
insight and what supports the capacity of this mindful awareness
what we do each time we sit noticing it attending to
it appreciating it not being critical when it's
gone and sometimes reflecting after meditation what
conditions you might put in to help it arise more often how much interest might
be able to be brought to bear to help the mindfulness be more continuous more
steady more balanced mindfulness too awareness too
is conditioned and appreciation helps it to arise more and
more often so now we come to this image of the
army's volley after volley after volley of arrows transformed into
flowers the way an aware wise heart and mind can metabolize difficulties into
wisdom so what might this look like there are different
ways i'll offer a few most of you probably know the simile of
the second arrow get hit by a first arrow those are the slings and arrows of life it hurts there's pain there's grief
there's loss there's the arising of things we don't want on a personal familial or societal level that's the
first arrow the second arrow is all of the ways our minds and hearts make
things worse when wisdom is present it's possible to
see the arrows the many ways the mind can make things worse as conditioned
processes of this mind and this
heart in other words while in some ways life's difficulties might feel and be
intensely deeply personal on another level what we experience inside is not
personal its universal qualities tendencies of heart and
mind so instead of taking things personally it becomes possible to
connect with this process and with the flip side of
wisdom compassion care
just like me everyone suffers sometimes that compassion recognizes the
universal human experience so in short rather than being wounded by
the arrows of the life denying forces of the mind seeing into them with clear
mindfulness how they're formed how they're conditioned how they're common among humans and other beings too
some this perspective this capacity can transform
difficulties into inner beauty
flowers and as we draw to the close of sort of unpacking this story just as it
was for the Buddha in this story doubt tends to be the most difficult hindrance
for people who are you who am I to
experience bliss who am I to experience a moment of insight
mara a classic way in the um stories and
teachings of the Buddha is to simply say "I see you Mara i see you." To look
doubt in the eye and doubt the doubt
there's also the power of being grounded in your own
seat your own place on earth touching the
earth there's a simplicity and an integrity in us being part of
nature we are nature everything that unfolds in our minds and hearts is part
of natural processes interacting there's honor in that
so to review factors of mind that are helpful at the moment of insight and
difficulty are recognition of a strong simple mindful awareness that doesn't
lean towards or away not entangled recognizing that what arises is based on
conditioning nature and rather than reacting with blame or shame and even if blame or
shame are present to bring compassion clear seeing to the process of what's
happening
so in other words the way our minds and hearts metabolize or relate to anything
in our inner lives can transform how it lives in us the very same
experience can result in protracted difficulty or in profound inner growth
sometimes both first one and then the
growth so friends please stay grounded in your
own place on this earth these next 24 hours if you're walking you're earth
walking if you're sitting earth sitting and notice for your homework
your assignment should you want to accept it where are there moments of mindfulness
awareness where you're not leaning in or leaning away thank you for your kind attention