all right so good morning my name is May uh the the talk today is going to be on
vdana or feeling tone um and so to for those who aren't familiar with it uh uh
I'll spend some time in the meditation um inviting you to explore vaydana in
your own experience and that will aid in your understanding of the dharma talk as
a whole to have a felt sense of it um uh so if you're not familiar with what
vdana is just a very brief introduction to it uh vdana is typically translated
as feeling tone and it refers to um this spectrum of pleasant unpleasant or
neither uh so all of our experiences have a feeling tone so on um in life
there's extremely pleasant we might think of vdana on a spectrum so uh very
pleasant on one end of the spectrum um very unpleasant on the other end of the
spectrum and in between we might say it's neutral neither pleasant nor unpleasant so in this sit today we'll
explore vdana uh as it relates to body sensations uh to sounds uh and maybe even visual
sights so that's what you can expect uh we'll start by settling in uh just
sensing the body being with the breath uh and sitting in silence for a while before we uh we get into feeling tone so
uh so why don't you go ahead and find a posture that feels supportive for you to sit in uh a posture that is uh upright
and relaxed
and just take some time to settle in with the
body you might connect with your home base for the meditation uh for a lot of people that's
the breathing for some it might be the soundsscape or a global sense of the body
sitting taking some time to settle with your home base with your
[Music] anchor landing in the present moment
having taken some time to settle in we'll now shift our attention to
vdana to feeling tone and we'll start by exploring it in
the body and we'll do this with a couple of body
scans and we'll start at the top of the head and do a slow scan down to the feet
and for our first scan uh we'll be noticing any
sensations that register as unpleasant
it might be very slightly unpleasant moderately unpleasant it
could be very unpleasant and when we meet these
sensations seeing if we can do so with a sense of ease and relaxation
scanning down the forehead feeling the
jaw maybe there's some tightness in the jaw that feels unpleasant
sensing the neck the
shoulders the torso sensing anything that might
register as unpleasant
it could be tension or tightness or
pressure sensing the
arms the wrists and hands
and the hips and legs
sensing anything
unpleasant when you finish just coming back to the breath
we'll start another scan now at the top of the head uh going at about the same
pace uh noticing anything that's
pleasant and it might be ever so slightly
pleasant i'll allow you to go at your own pace sensing maybe it's an area that feels
relaxed or spacious
maybe an area of the body that feels like a nice temperature just a little
pleasant maybe a softening
a slightly pleasant tingling maybe in the hands
making your way through the body sensing for anything
pleasant that's fine if you don't find anything it may be that there aren't any pleasant
sensations sometimes we'll catch just a little pleasantness in the body
when you finish your skin coming back to the breath
and beginning another scan of the body from head to toe uh this time
noticing vdana feeling tone that's neither pleasant nor unpleasant so this
is vdana that we might call neutral and often much of our experience
is neutral sensation that doesn't feel
pleasant or unpleasant so going down the forehead the
face in your own time your own pace sensing neutral sensations
neither pleasant nor unpleasant
often neutral sensations are less interesting for the mind so we tend not
to pay attention to them so it can take some extra energy
uh to stay with them
and you finish your scan landing with the breath again
now letting go of the breath and we'll shift our attention now to explore
vaydana uh in the soundsscape
so resting in this uh vast field of
hearing we can hear sometimes we can hear sounds within our own
bodies sounds within the
room and sometimes sounds outside the room maybe traffic or a bird
call so we'll see if we can stay with this field of
hearing and as we listen we'll be attuning to feeling tone we'll be attuning to this sense of pleasant
unpleasant and neutral so as you hear a sound uh see if you can have a soft
mental note in the background that acknowledges the feeling tone of that
sound so even as you hear my voice you might notice if the sound of the voice
registers as pleasant unpleasant or neither neutral
and you may find that it changes when you hear different sounds vana isn't
fixed it comes and goes
maybe just a soft background note
neutral unpleasant
neutral
neutral neutral
our task with vana is just to be with the feeling tone as it
is if it's pleasant we don't grasp hold of it and
try to get more if it's unpleasant can we be with
it without aversion without rejecting it and if it's neutral can we stay with
it without zoning out without getting lost in thought
we can release our focus on the soundsscape and we'll shift now to do a
little experimentation with the vdena of thinking so thoughts and emotions also
have vdana
so to experiment with this you might bring to mind uh someone that you love
or that you care about so that might be a mental picture
of them or just have a felt sense of them
and now notice the vadena associated with that thought or
that sense of the person
And often we find that it might be pleasant maybe a little pleasant or very
pleasant to think about someone that we care about
to notice an unpleasant
thought you might think about something on your to-do list that you're not so
excited about not getting lost in thought about it just just bringing up maybe the
headline or a mental image of doing the task
it may be that just the idea to-do list
registered as unpleasant
so noticing the vena whatever you're seeing in your mind whatever that task
is that thought it's an
idea it might be you might see words in the mind it might be a
picture so noticing the feeling tone of the words or picture in the mind related
to this task so this is just the
vdena of the thought the idea that doesn't mean that the task
itself will actually be that
way but it may be that the the thought has unpleasant va
So letting go of these images down coming back to the
breath the
body reconnecting with a sensation that's neutral or pleasant
[Music]
good morning again and I know Hillary has an announcement or two good morning uh welcome to our
Sunday tea after the Dharma talk please stay and have some yummy appetizers and
some tea and just mingle and get to know each other a little bit better
um I also want to give a deep bow of thanks to one of
our teachers Camille who is here today who has been teaching um the Dharma
Rocks with her husband Tom Tim for a number of years now and uh we are going
to miss them but they are having their first baby so we will have a derm baby
coming uh in August so do you want to just wave your hand thank you so much we
really appreciate there's nothing better than raising uh someone up in the dharma
i I probably very few of us have had that that blessing so thank you and
that's a good segue to uh mindful parenting next Sunday is it 11:15 or
11:30 11:15 and Melody is one of our teachers here and that's for parents who have
kids of any age it's really a great support so thank you very
much so many of you have heard my little speech that everything uh at IMC and at
our retreat center is offered by donation and all the teachings are are
free there it's never a charge so if you're inclined to make a donation there's a donation box near the front
door and you can donate online and our teacher this morning is May Elliott i'm
reading from a her audio dharma bio so I I hope it's accurate she's a dharma
teacher in the terraic tradition currently serving as the co-director of Insight Retreat Center she began
meditating in 2004 and spent eight years training as a Zen monk at San Francisco
Zen Center Temples may is a graduate of Insight Meditation Cent's four-year
Dharma teacher training and is dedicated to supporting practitioners in walking
the path of awakening she offers teachings that cultivate kindness
clarity and virtue through deepening meditation and daily life integration
more information is available at
www.mmayeliot.com good morning May thank you for our guided meditation thank you
Martha uh for those who are sitting in the far back can you hear okay yeah okay
great and if you'd like there are seats up here you're welcome to stay where you are but there are some seats in here if
you'd like to move in uh so I'd like to start the talk this morning with a very short poem it's a
very short poem at the very the beginning of a very long book uh the book is the Vudi Maga uh fifth century
commentarial teachings by Buddha Gossa uh and in it uh it references Goa
so that's the Buddha goes like this a tangle
within a tangle without the whole world is tangled in a
tangle gota I ask you
this who can untangle this tangle
uh so when I was a kid um maybe seven years old or so uh my
parents took me to the Grand Canyon and um uh for those who might not be from
the US or familiar with this area this fly really likes the Grand
Canyon um hi little friend um so uh for
those who aren't from the US the Grand Canyon is uh probably one of the geologic wonders of the world um it's
really extraordinary um but interestingly enough uh one of my uh
like key memories from that trip was not of the Grand Canyon but of the gift shop
uh there was um uh there was a little toy in the gift
shop uh that consisted of um two pieces of metal and each metal was kind of like a little loop and the loops were hooked
together kind of something kind of like this and they looked like inextricably
linked like they couldn't be decoupled like they couldn't be taken apart but if
you keep mo ke kept moving them um if you did it for a very long
time eventually they would decouple um so I
was just like obsessed with this toy totally fixated on it um it was like the
highlight of the Grand Canyon trip um so um so I was remembering that toy and
that experience and I was thinking about how many times in my life um I've been
totally fixated on some inner puzzle some um you know some story or complex
life situation uh and I'm really just obsessed with trying to figure it out
trying to to find the solution to figure out the right thing to say or do and in
being so captivated by this inner puzzle uh I'm missing the um the majesty which
is my life and I think that this is something that a lot of us do we get caught we get
so caught in our um we get so entangled in uh our inner challenges our inner
puzzles uh that we don't even notice that the Grand Canyon is right there
waiting for us that the full beauty and awe of our life uh is somehow missing
we're not quite seeing it because we're so fixated on these
puzzles so uh of course that toy is long gone uh but I'm still really interested
uh in how we get caught how we get caught in these puzzles uh how we get
entangled and then how do we become unentangled how do we become unentangled
so the Buddha talked about entanglement and this very process of learning to be
um to be free of entanglement to be free of suffering to be free of stress in our
life so today the focus of the talk is on one of these gateways to
unentanglement and more specifically uh the talk is on vana or feeling tone uh
so for those of you who weren't here at the beginning of the meditation I'll provide a little recap for you uh so
vdena uh it's typically translated as feeling tone sometimes it's translated
as hyonic tone um hyonic tone or
effective tone and when I say feeling this is not talking about an emotion or a body
sensation it's referring to uh the pleasantness unpleasantness or neutrality of experience uh so I had
mentioned the spectrum so we can think of vdana as being on a spectrum with one
end of the spectrum being like the most pleasant thing a human can
experience and then there's like very pleasant and then quite
pleasant pleasant uh a little less pleasant slightly pleasant you know
neutral a little unpleasant etc all the way to the most unpleasant
thing a human can experience you know it could be the emotions associated with the loss of a loved
one or uh severe physical pain you know so so this is that
spectrum of va so one of the most famous sutas uh
the sati patana suta which uh is uh forms the basis for many of our I should
say most of our meditation instruction in the west um the satipadana
foundations of mindfulness it goes over four foundations I'll just mention a couple uh one is the body one is the
mind and one is vdana so it's really interesting to me
that the Buddha only gave one foundation to the the the body only one foundation to the mind and vana gets an entire
foundation to itself so what's up with that like that that caught my attention
like this this must be important if the Buddha gave an entire foundation uh the Buddha said you know there's four things
to pay attention to and one of them is vana so um so why is that the reason one
of the main reasons vdana gets so much airtime from the Buddha uh is because it
plays a critical role in why we suffer it plays a critical role in how we get
entangled uh so one of the teachers that the the teachings that the Buddha offered uh that best explains how we get
entangled is dependent origination uh it's also known as dependent arising uh
also known as the 12-fold chain the poly is paticha
samupada uh so uh this teaching uh at first glance well even after first
glance it can seem very complicated uh uh very hard to understand confusing uh
but very simply uh the 12-fold chain uh it's just a description of how we get
caught in suffering the cycle of suffering it's often depicted as a wheel the 12 links kind of going around in a
chain we just go round and round the circle circle of suffering the cycle of
suffering um so uh so I appreciate that it's called the 12-fold chain because
awakening is sometimes called or referred to as freedom from bondage so
when we become awakened it's kind of like we become unchained kind of unhooked um but what's
amazing is it's actually possible to break the chain to break this cycle of suffering before full liberation so
that's what I'm interested in today in this talk that we can actually break the chain we can we can uh stop entanglement
from happening um uh here and now and we
don't need to wait for um for some future enlightenment uh so in the talk uh today
I'll be talking about just four of the links and of those four are just really zooming in on two of them and what's
nice about the four I'm going to mention is that uh you don't need to know anything else about the rest of the
chain for them to be useful and applicable and what's also nice about them is you can experience them in your
life um they're not theoretical so um let's go through them
and maybe I'll just say all of them to begin with uh so um the six
senses contact vdena craving and that's the
order six senses contact vdena craving so uh six senses so you're all
familiar with the five senses eyes ears nose mouth
body and then the sixth in Buddhism is the mind so those are the six senses we
can all experience those next link
contact so if you can see me right now that's a moment of
contact if you can hear me right now that's a moment of contact so contact
refers to when a sense gate meets a sense object and we're conscious so
those three things coming together so there's a working eye there's a sight
and consciousness is present consciousness is just the the basic awareness of being awake all sentient
beings have it so it's basically saying as long as you're not under general anesthesia
um and you have a working eye and there's a sight contact is going to happen or as long as you haven't fainted
or as long as you're not in deep sleep contact is going to happen at the senses uh if you have a working sense gate and
there's an object so contact is happening all the time it's very simple
like I said if you can see me and you can hear me that's eye contact and ear contact and there's also mind contact
the mind mind as the sense gate meets an object the object is a thought or an
emotion so that's mind contact so um so there those are the first two uh links I
wanted to share uh Six senses contact now we have
vdana so every moment of sense contact has vina has feeling tone we normally
don't notice it but every sound every body sensation every taste every thought
every emotion has feeling tone it's registering as pleasant unpleasant or
neither so um when we see something that we
perceive as beautiful maybe it's art or nature uh or something like that um it's
probably because that that sight object is pleasant that moment of sight contact
is pleasant if we hear a song that we like um it's because that song registers
as pleasant um for most people if they hear a chainsaw that registers as
unpleasant now every body sensation has vdana so um
as you may have noticed in the meditation one area of the body can be feeling pleasant while another feels
unpleasant um much of our experience is often neutral at the sense
gates and as the mind experiences emotions sadness might register as
unpleasant joy might register as pleasant sometimes anger can be
unpleasant sometimes we can have that sort of like self-righteous anger that can have a little pleasantness in it uh
right so be really interesting to explore the field of vana uh and not only interesting it can
be very useful um so and that'll that'll the utility of it will start to become
become clear as we explain um as I explain the next link
so six senses uh when we have the six senses we can
have contact every moment of contact leads to vdana and uh for the untrained mind the
knee-jerk reaction to vdana is craving that's the next link craving so um to
highlight the relevance of craving for you I want to remind you of the Buddha's four noble truths i'm just going to
mention the first two uh first noble truth uh there is
suffering second noble truth the source of suffering is craving so this is
really radical right the source of suffering he's not saying the source of suffering is unpleasant vana we usually
think that unpleasant things are the source of suffering but that's not what he's saying he's saying that it's
actually the wanting and not wanting that's the suffering the rejection of
experience or the grabbing hold of experience that's our suffering so the craving and of course the the other side
of the coin of craving is aversion so wanting and not wanting so why why are
those suffering like why does that why is that suffering so the secret message
behind craving and aversion are that this moment is not
enough if craving for something else is present um or aversion is present it's
saying that this moment needs to be better or different more or less in
order to be content in order to be happy so inherently within the wanting and not
wanting there's a sense that this moment isn't okay um that I need something different
in order to be happy so it can be hard to see that because we're so fixated on
the object of desire what it is we want to get but really embedded in that whole process of mind the whole wanting and
wanting wanting and not wanting system is dissatisfaction so that's why craving
is duka that's why craving is suffering so um so returning to dependent arising
these links here so I had said the knee-jerk reaction to vdana is craving
so what happens is we experience pleasant vaydana we immediately want
more that's that movement from vdana to craving we experience unpleasant
vaydana and we immediately want to get rid of it or we want less of it that's the aversion right we want to fix it or
change it or destroy it or get rid of it if we experience neutral vana uh
we're usually bored uh it's not interesting to us and so um we go into
delusion delusion is like getting lost in the thinking mind in the narrative of
um I me and mine so we check out um we go into selfing uh so so this is that
that movement through the chain so six senses contact vdena
craving so um so we can see this in our experience it happens really fast but
I'll share a short example of um of this kind of sequence occurring that I
noticed some years ago uh so I was having a snack at home uh it was um some
nut butter i think it was like almond butter or something like that and I'm sitting in the kitchen eating my nut
butter straight out of the jar delicious my favorite uh and I should mention nut
butter is like a high ticket item in my family like it is a coveted item so So
I'm really enjoying my snack i finish I put it back in the fridge i'm about to close the door and then I realized there
was something just like a little strange about the way that I put the jar in the fridge and I realized I didn't just set
the jar in the fridge i kind of like moved some things out of the way put the
jar in and then moved those items back so you know how a dog will take a
bone in the backyard and dig a hole and put the bone in and then cover it with dirt
that's what was happening so um so you know I could have
been hard on myself about this like oh come on you know you've done you know renunciate monastic training focusing on
generosity and you know giving things up and um but fortunately I was just amused
when I saw this um and it was just interesting to see this is just what the mind does this was just the chain of
dependent origination and action six senses in this case there was a
mouth there's a moment of contact the mouth made made contact with some almond
butter i was conscious you there's consciousness present um I wasn't under
general anesthesia um I hadn't fainted you know so so there's a moment of
contact that contact was very pleasant and that pleasantness led to
craving and clinging and I did not want to share so so that's that chain that's how
that occurs and this is happening all day long for
us so there's this uh this classic suta uh called the dart or the arrow it's
samutanikaya 36.6 um some of you may know it as uh the
teaching on the second arrow uh it's a really very commonly taught suta uh
however a lot of people don't know that it's actually about vana so um so I'm going to read you a
little section from it when an untaught worldling I love
this phrase an untaught worldling refers just to an untrained person a person who hasn't practiced the teachings of a
Buddha who hasn't done the introspective training so when an untaught worldling is touched by a by painful vadena they
worry and grieve they lament beat their breast weep and are
distraught they thus experience two kinds of vana a bodily
and a mental adena it is as if a person were pierced
by an arrow and following the first piercing they are hit by a second arrow
so um so the first arrow so let's say there's uh we have knee pain so there's
some unpleasant vana of the knee pain that unpleasant vadena that's the first arrow but then uh when we grieve and
worry and lament when we go oh my gosh my knee hurts how am I going to afford
seeing a doctor what if I need surgery what if I have a limp who will love me if I have a limp um that's the second
era So um so that description of the first arrow and the second arrow those are
those two links of dependent arising that we've been talking about that's vdana and
craving unpleasant knee pain that's the vdana the uh the aversion the fear the
worry that's the craving specifically that's aversion right so that's that
movement and within that movement is the movement from freedom to
suffering um because remember vana pleasant unpleasant neutral is not
the source of suffering the Buddha said cravings the source of suffering so
that's that shift that shift from ease to dooka right there
so um so one aspect of training as a Zen
monk is uh being trained as a ceremonial instrumentalist so you become kind of
like a Zen musician um and in uh residential Zen training uh there are a
lot of ceremonies like a lot of ceremonies and there's all different
instruments uh so there are drums there are bells of all different sizes i
remember at Tasahara there was one that was like almost big enough to take a bath in um there are
um there are let's see um uh a variety of kind of like I don't
even know what to call them uh like what an English translation would be there's one called the makugio that's like a red
lacquered fish that you hit with a mallet um there was a large wooden hanging fish um and you hit it right in
the eye with a mallet so all these different instruments um and sometimes the
instrumental parts are quite complex um which is kind of a vulnerable thing for
a Zen monk who didn't choose to move to a monastery to be a musician
a lot a lot of Zen monks don't really have a lot of musical tendencies um including myself uh so so sometimes
this was challenging and of course if if you make a mistake the whole assembly hears right
so so um during one ceremony at uh city center San Francisco Zen Center uh the
former Abbis Blanch Hartman was um was officiating so that means that she was
the the main priest for the ceremony and she was making all of the offerings and things like that and um the Doan the
instrumentalist who's playing the bells um uh needs to be hitting each bell at a
very specific time uh choreographed aligned with what the the abbis is doing
in the ceremony and so the whole assembly knows exactly when the bells are supposed to happen they've heard it
a million times uh and on this particular day the Doan was um a woman
who was moving right along until she hit a bell at the wrong
time she hit the bell and immediately she
winced that sort of that facial expression that's like the universal
expression of damn it so she hits the bell wints the abb
looks over because she hears that the bell is wrong and then of course the ceremony continues um so at the end of the
service the woman who was playing the bells went up to Blanch and she apologized for hitting the bell at the
wrong time and Blanch she responds she
says "Mistakes on the bells are inevitable but the
face the face was [Laughter]
extra." So the unpleasant sound of the incorrect
bell inevitable that's the first arrow right the
wse that's extra that's the second arrow the wse is the second arrow so that wse
of aversion that movement from vana to
craving so what is our alternative how do we break the
chain so how do we keep suffering from arising
so the key is learning to rest in vdana learning to experience vdana
without reacting to it so can you be with the pleasantness
of experience without chasing it grasping for more
and can you be with unpleasant experience without aversion without
rejecting it without trying to get rid of it or get away from it so this is our
task and what's worth noting is um when we think about the chain we still have
six senses uh they still make contact with objects and vana still arises
vana is a benign force even after Buddha the Buddha's enlightenment the Buddha still
experienced Vdana he still experienced pleasant and unpleasant he still had really bad back pain but what he didn't
have was craving and aversion that's what's different about
the liberated mind it doesn't have craving and aversion so you don't need to get rid of what's unpleasant in your
life you don't have to chase what's pleasant in order to be free you can just be with what is
without anything extra and that's what's
freeing so that's that's how we become
unentangled tell me go how to untangle this tangle
so um for many people
uh it's difficult to decouple vdana and
craving and I might say uh that it's a victory just to start noticing vaydana
at all and so that's where I'd like to suggest you start
uh start uh in terms of uh the practice of decoupling vaydana and craving where
we start is just starting to be mindful of vaydana in our life so starting to identify it so that
second foundation of mindfulness vdana so you might start by noticing it
in your meditation practice you might uh spend a period of medit meditation just noticing vana kind of how we did today
um where you see if you can notice uh pleasant neutral and unpleasant
sensations in the body uh see if you can notice pleasant unpleasant neutral uh
sounds uh try opening your eyes and seeing if you can identify pleasant
unpleasant and neutral visual objects sights uh it gets really interesting to do this
with emotions and moods and particularly so with thoughts if you can catch them
it's really easy to get lost in thoughts and not be able to see them clearly but if you can see them clearly you can
begin to see how much the vdana of thoughts uh controls our life has so
much power over us so getting interested in vdana starting to notice it um becomes a gateway to
wisdom we um maybe I could say we get wise about vaydana when we become
mindful of it so I I want to say a few things about the way that we get wise about vaydana
so you can see how this can affect us so one way is that we start to see that
vdana is impermanent that it's really transitory that it's always changing you
know we think that vana is fixed um you know we we chase some object you know uh
ice cream is always pleasant or maybe more dangerously um
exerson uh is always terrible or even worse um x- type of
people uh like I always hate x- type of people you know we have this sense that
maybe there's some some unpleasant vdana associated with certain people that we don't like you know that's and that's
how they are it's always unpleasant so that's assuming that vdana doesn't change um and we have a lot of
assumptions about vaydana not changing but as we begin to examine it and it
experience it in our life we see that it's almost vaneta operates almost like uh raindrops on a pond just coming and
going coming and going even within a single mouthful of food um the vdena
will change there'll be like a peak of pleasantness in the chewing and then it just kind then it becomes a little more
neutral and then we swallow and oh the vet is gone so check it out for yourself um
when we begin to see that vdana is impermanent we start to see how feudile
it is to grasp it why grab hold of something why chase
something why spend sometime so much time trying to fix or reject or get rid of something when that vana is
impermanent when it doesn't last so that starts to undermine our
tendency to move from vayana to craving right that starts to make it so seeing
seeing clearly that things are impermanent that vdana is impermanent it starts to allow us to break the chain it
starts to allow us to just rest in vdana you know why get so entangled in the vdena with craving with wanting and not
wanting when we know it's going to change anyway i can just rest here
some of you may have had the experience of getting uh a new toy maybe a new article of clothing uh or maybe a new
gadget uh maybe a cell phone maybe something bigger a new car or something like that uh and being really excited
about it for like two weeks and there's like a like fever
pitch pleasantness associated with that experience and then something happens we
often don't even notice it but that new item just kind of fades into the background of our life like it kind of
just becomes normal and we don't really notice it anymore and then we need a new toy in order to experience that fever
pitch pleasure or a new experience so all that's happening with that first item is that the vdena went from very
very pleasant to neutral and so that example um uh is to
express that one vdena changes but also another way that we get wise about
vaydana uh is that um we begin to see that vdena
is not inherent to the object like a new car like
um pleasant vadena is not embedded in the new car it's not fixed in the new
car uh shockingly pleasant vadena is not
embedded in ice cream like it's possible to have ice
cream that's neutral it's possible to have ice cream that's unpleasant um it
changes and it's not fixed it's not embedded in the object it's not inherent
to the object so all of this undermines the tendency
to cling seeing this undermines the tendency to cling
so one area where you might see this for yourself where you might be able to see that capacity to um to rest in vana
without clinging is to start noticing noticing things that are just slightly pleasant or slightly unpleasant because
we have a greater capacity to be with them without reactivity so just in your
life notice if some there's maybe um a food that's just slightly pleasant and
you might notice there's no craving with it oh interesting i'm not craving for a second helping oh okay i'm actually
seeing how I can experience something pleasant without craving so then you
just get a little taste of what's that what that's like to see the two decoupled to see vana and craving
decoupled for a lot of people um they're so used to those two forces coming to
happening at the same time that it's hard to see that they could be separate so you can play around with it with
vdena that's not as strong uh because it's more obvious there another place you might notice um
or maybe I should say another practice you might play with um is noting
practice we did a little of that in the meditation uh this can be helpful for uh both recognizing vaydana and also uh not
getting hooked by it not getting entangled with it um so you might just notice um uh when when v when you're
you're attending to va you just might use a soft mental note um pleasant
pleasant pleasant or unpleasant unpleasant maybe a phone rings during
your meditation and normally you'd go "Why does the phone always ring during meditation it's so distracting i wish it
wouldn't do that." But instead you might just note
unpleasant unpleasant unpleasant so this is one way that you
can just uh incorporate another tool to noticing vana and not getting hooked by
it
maybe just um I want to say a little more about how
wholesome it is to rest in vana when we do this uh it's a little
like a foretaste of enlightenment so one definition of
enlightenment um is the complete uprooting of craving
aversion and delusion the complete uprooting of craving aversion and delusion so when we
can rest in vdana when we can just be with pleasant unpleasant and neutral without craving
without aversion and without delusion that's a mind a lot like the
liberated mind so don't miss it don't miss that mind uh
enjoy it and know that it's possible it's possible to break the chain here and now to rest in something very close
to freedom uh not full enlightenment it's not full enlightenment but it's
like a taste of the peace that's possible so this this is how we become
unentangled so I I'm going to end with a a poem a
piece of a poem i'm not going to read it all it's called in this passing moment by Hogan Bay and I share it because part
of our task with vana is to choose the vdana we have right then rather than
trying to get better vana choose the vena we have rather than
trying to get rid of the unpleasant and get the pleasant
in this passing moment karma ripens and all things come to be i vow to choose
what is if there is cost I choose to
pay if there is need I choose to give if there is pain I choose to
feel if there is sorrow I choose to grieve
when burning I choose heat when
calm I choose peace when
starving I choose hunger when happy I choose
joy whom I encounter I choose to
meet what I shoulder I choose to
bear when it is my death I choose to
die where this takes me I choose to
go being with what is I respond to what
is this life is as real as a dream
the one who knows it cannot be found and truth is not a
thing therefore I vow to choose this dharma entrance
gate may all Buddhas and wise ones help
me live this vow let's sit together
thank you for your kind attention so we now have a little time
for questions or comments um and please just say your
name before you before you share we have a mic i don't know martha there's somebody in the back
here thank Oh Kurt thank you very much of course thank you um two quick
questions how do you spell Vana and what is the uh how can
we find what you just read that I choose to I choose to those are my two
questions great so vdana it's spelled v as in victor e d a n a vdana typically
poly v's are pronounced w's so I could argue that it should be pronounced but um in the west we usually
say vana so for consistency we'll stick with that um the poem if you want to uh
note the title it's called In This Passing Moment by Hogan Bae and this is
recorded so if you just go to the IMC website you can hear that title and look it up and then you can see the full poem
too great thanks
I'm going just bring it over here
good morning my name is Mizu and I'm so happy to be here i have two questions
also um the first one came to mind as you were reading the
poem um so I'm asking the question sort of backwards um the questions two
questions um the first one is what is the feeling tone or vdana
of accepting what is yeah so uh was everybody able to hear the question
great so what is the feeling tone or vdana of accepting what is so
um typically uh acceptance registers as pleasant uh sometimes
neutral and I should uh I should say that remember that vdana isn't fixed um
and it's not consistent uh so there isn't one consistent reliable feeling tone associ associated with acceptance
however there are trends uh so typically it's it's uh pleasant or neutral and you
might imagine a time for yourself where there was some sort of clinging or holding on or struggle and then that
shift to accept acceptance often acceptance is a state of non-clinging right so non-suffering
and that's pleasant non-suffering is very pleasant yes I thought so thank you
I just wanted to clarify that for myself um and then the second question
uh is about vana still as it relates to duka and going back to the story of the
arrows there's a first arrow and then there's a second arrow
So the vdana isn't an arrow at all the
Buddha actually he he uh to clarify he was saying the vdana is like a first arrow like we do there are painful
things in our life we can experience extreme physical pain and that's like a
first arrow but then the reactivity the wanting and not wanting that's the second arrow so it kind of goes along
with the phrase uh that you may have heard uh pain is inevitable but
suffering is optional okay so then the last question I'm sorry
um just to get into the full clarification of duca then is duca only
then the second arrow and not the first arrow which is vana so typically uh
typically when we're talking about duca we're talking about the suffering that's optional yeah so one k could consider um
physical pain as duca also um as uh
sometimes the the Buddha would refer to duca as uh sickness old age death uh
these things that are very you know first arrow very primary um but
typically when we're talking about dooka we're referring to that optional type a second era yeah because that's the
that's the dooka we have some say over that's the type that's optional
yeah so I think we should probably stop there but if anybody has any questions
after we close you're welcome to come up and we can chat a little more so thank you so much for coming today and uh
you're welcome to stay for tea and treats take care everyone