good evening welcome
welcome I so appreciate meditating together there's something just really wonderful about it no matter what's
happening there's just I don't know so thank you for
that so I had the great Good Fortune uh these past few days last week to be
doing some hiking in uh Southern Utah and and it was just so beautiful it
was just so wonderful and U there's a number of reasons why I thought it was wonderful
but you know part of it is just being away you know being away from being on
screens you know being out hiking or some of my usual responsibilities but
also just to be outside with a trees and rocks and
nature quote unquote and um and I noticed though even
though there was like so much appreciation and I don't know just so much happiness about just being outside
and walking you know so simple just uh
walking but I noticed that I felt a little bit more of this
ease when I was on those Trails when there was less people like when there
was a lot of people and then crowded on the trails and stuff like that it was I
was so happy to be outside happy to be doing that but when I was on a trail where there weren't so many people there
was another little set of certain set of uh ease it maybe a
little bit easier to tune into maybe some of the beauty or the
quiet the Simplicity this sense of maybe this
naturalness too for me there was a maybe when there weren't so many people I'm
just right now thinking about it maybe there is a certain amount of ease that could
arise I tend to be more of an introvert maybe some of you that are extroverts are being that doesn't sound fun that's
okay too right we don't all have to be exactly the same but maybe there's this way that uh
being like outside in a way that feels easeful
is similar to being inside when there's a big storm going on rain or hail and
wind or something like that and you're inside feeling cozy maybe there's a fire in the fireplace or hot chocolate or
something like this a feeling of coziness or maybe there's this feeling
that when you're in a like at a setting which there's a lot of people a conference or maybe a big a party or
wedding or something like this and maybe it feels like sometimes it's really loud like oh wow this is a lot and then you
step outside maybe you just feel like you just need a little bit of quiet before
you go back inside or something so I'm pointing to this idea of like you know separating ourselves
sometimes doesn't have to be all the time but removing ourselves like
separating our our El from whatever is
happening even we might say that this is part of what Retreat practice is is
about is to kind of like separate yourself and that's a big that's part of the power and the potency of retreat
practice is that we're away from the usual distractions there's no electronic
devices on Retreats and there's no so few decisions to be made and things to
take care of but I even when I was on I've done a lot
of retreat practice and when I was on Retreats I was also like trying to figure out where can I be away from all
these people so it's kind of funny it's just something that I would do and uh
and what I'm just remembering a friend of mine unbeknownst to me also had the same idea kind of like oh I want to be a
little bit more isolated a little bit in a little bit more quiet place and I I
would think like okay well after lunch I'm going to go in the meditation hall because nobody else is in the meditation
Hall after lunch that's usually a time when people are doing other things resting or helping take care of the
dishes or whatever it might be and I thought it was funny that a good friend of mine I would like find there also
like oh you're here and then I think oh well maybe I'll do Walkin meditation over here nobody goes over there and
then I'd be over there oh there's my friend you know so just this recognition that some of us just have this uh
tendency not everybody has that I'm just sharing some of my own
experiences but I'd also like to say that the Buddha talked about this or he
pointed to this this idea of you know sometimes not all the time sometimes to
like be a little bit more separate to be a little bit more
isolated from what's Happening and can imagine that in Ancient India from what
we know from primarily from the Buddhist literature is that people lived in large
groups right commonly right big family groups multiple Generations living
together or the monastics live in monasteries a lot of the time and they
also didn't live in monasteries they also were would be wandering and would be off on their own too so I don't want
to say that's exclusively what happening but there's a number of times
in which the Buddha would give kind of like this instruction you know don't delay the there are the roots of trees
there are empty Huts go meditate the roots of trees being in India there was
be trees that have these really large root systems that would be kind of above ground and' be really big so they' kind
of like big a big root here like a big root here so you could have your own little space or something like
this so his encouragement on occasions to go
to sit meditate be separate from
others so there's a poly word that's uh no that's this denotes this and no need
to remember this poly word don't worry the word is via and the reason why I'm bringing it
up is because there's a few different ways in which we could understand this word and um I'd like to talk about that
tonight this idea of separating or to to separate or being
separate or separation something like this I like this idea of maybe thinking
of VCA as like being independent of what is
unhelpful being independent of what is unhelpful it's kind of you know clunky
language but maybe we could understand it of not being Tangled Up in
entanglements being uh separate from difficulties
being separated from difficulties so just this way in which
maybe we can find some distance between and not get lost in what's unhelpful
and one of these examples could be as just as I described as finding a place
that supported a meditation practice and sometimes that place might be you know
separate from others out in the woods and in your room here at IMC maybe it's
we're not all separate from one another but maybe you're separate from what's happening at your workplace or your home
or whatever it might be on the freeways whatever it might be
so in the same way like there might be like this physical separation is finding a location that is more quiet and
settled but there also can be this mental separation creating the
conditions that are also allows for this more quiet and settled finding a place
in the heart and mind that is quiet and
settled maybe being separated from these difficulties that of course they arise when we
meditate when we sit down it's not always uh unicorns and rainbows you
don't need me to tell you that so the classically there's this or
traditionally this idea of being separated from mental difficulties points to the
hindrances these are this uh five obstruct ctions difficulties things
that are like getting in the way of being even more settled of being even
more having some calmness these hindrances these group
are five are said to be the doorway the gateway to samadi samadi we can understand is like
the sense of collectedness with a sense of well-being the sense of being unscattered
undistracted and and with a sense of well-being like oh yeah this just being
here so I'll just say a few words about these hindrances for me when I first learned
about them I was like so happy it made me so happy because it felt like such a
relief that thousands of years ago somebody was talking about the
difficulties I was having in meditation this meant like oh this is just a human
thing this is just what happens when humans try to sit down and meditate it doesn't mean that any of us are failures
it doesn't mean anything about us as meditators it just means that we're meditating so there's this way we with a
really broad brush we could say the hindrances are these we might say energy
states or forces in the mind there's this uh typical list of five the
first two relate to what I like to say kind of like pushing or pulling this can be uh show up in so
many different ways but there's this kind of like pushing like get away from me I don't want this you know get
away aversion maybe there's some little bit of hostilian there to a little bit of ill wh like just get away or there
can be this pulling I want more I want more give me more I need more of this
experience and more of some experience that I'm thinking about so this is we could say is desire so this a pushing
and pulling and sometimes when we meditate you can see sometimes people are lean forward a little bit if they
really are in their meditation practice and they really were wanting something this can be uh shows up in our
body as well as what the mind is happening I haven't seen aversion show up as much
as people pulling back but there can be this sense of like oh ew I don't want that you know like that that's kind of
the feeling so those are two of the entrances pushing and pulling we could say aversion and desire
also there's also uh two more entrances that are related to the amount to the
sense of a settledness or energy so one is this feeling
of not enough energy this feel right kind of like this
falling asleep isn't obvious when you feel like you're going to fall asleep this is not so uncommon in meditation
practice and then the other one is like oh my gosh if I have to sit here any longer I'm just going to go crazy
there's this sense of you know I just want to jump off of my seat and do
anything go organize the sock you know something like this that feels like it's more important or more urgent so there's
these two that low energy and high energy low energy is given the
expression sloth and torper and high energy is given the expression
restlessness restlessness and worry and uh I've given a whole series
of Dharma talks on these I'm just doing a broad brush right now I know I say
this some often when I'm giving DH oh I should give a whole series on these and uh I often don't do that even though I
have that idea but I think maybe I will I'll spend a little time these are good things to really
explore so that's four and then the fifth one is this sense of velation like
I don't I don't know maybe I should do this well I don't know maybe I should do this over here well wait wait maybe I'm
not sure this kind of like this indecisiveness this vacillation this
hesitation not really engaged and and um sometimes that shows up as like okay I'm
going to be mindful of the breath oh but my knee hurts okay I'll be mindful of the knee oh I really don't like this the
knee okay I'll do M I'll do loving kindness practice oh but this is hard okay well maybe I'll do visualization
practice so or just you spend your whole meditation practice going from Bing Bing Bing just jumping from uh practice to
practice that is um this vacillation this hesitation to really just settle
in um is often called doubt and there's a lot that can be said about doubt I
think I gave a talk not too long ago about it so there's this way in which these
hindrances these five uh desire ill will sloth and toror
restlessness and worry and doubt they they are operating whether we are aware
of them or not but it's maybe helpful to think of them as as a Spectra it's not binary
either you have them or you don't they're just um can be really subtle and sometimes
our meditation practice as the Mind does start to uh settle down we start to see
oh yeah there's a little bit of restlessness that was subtle that we hadn't noticed before or maybe there's
this desire that we hadn't really noticed before and so part of meditation
practice is just to see all these uh the the obvious versions and the not obvious
versions of these hindrances we don't have to take them
personally just means that we're humans sitting down to meditate but they they don't happen only
in the meditation happen in all of our lives so these are obstructions that happen in all these different
ways so then this idea of separation and VCA as being a doorway
into samade settledness with a sense of well-being is that as they start to
soften these hindrances these five Universal qualities everybody has them
to some extent unless you're completely awakened I don't know what a completely awakened
person has I maybe imagining they don't have these as this separation this seclusion
happens then there's this way in it can be just
this sense of maybe ease and contentment
just a real sense of a deep sense
of that kind of a feeling so separation from these hindrances is of
what we might call a different type of a
via this mental V mental separation separating from these
hindrances but there's this also way in which we vea or even this word separation we could say is like to
separate or separate there's this way like separate
is this recognition oh there's can be more than one like there can be put
things in this pile and put things in that pile we can't separate it's not just one thing and in this case what's
being pointed to is can we separate can we distinguish can we
discern what is helpful from what is not so helpful I talked about this uh VCA as
being like this independ dependence from what is unhelpful it helps to know what is not
helpful and this uh we learn right with practice sometimes
um it's obvious and sometimes it's not so obvious and so we could say helpful
helpful for what we could say helpful for finding greater happiness Finding
finding greater peace ease and freedom what's helpful for Crea in
suffering oh you know just it's helpful to know these types of things too right what leads to
suffering reading all kinds of news right before meditating probably not so
helpful right then there's just the mind is going or something like this and
right and you learn that maybe if you find yourself do Doom scrolling oh yeah right I'm supposed to go meditate and then you meditate and you realize the
repercussions of the Doom scrolling or whatever it was you were doing I think we've all have uh done our
share of these types of things I remember that uh early in my
meditation practice when I I would be like driving to The Meditation Center to do something just like what we're doing
tonight A sit in a talk I would like play the radio like really loud and sing along and you like
in my car but then when I noticed it's as soon as I sat down all those songs
just showed up again in my mind and I'd be meditating just Oh no just these words of the songs I'm trying to get rid
of them but they would stay or something like this so I stopped listening to the
radio when I was uh before as I was driving to go meditate just to see if
that could help not have all those songs playing in the mind while I
sitting so there's this idea of you know via as to separate what's helpful and
what's not helpful we can say that's part of a Right View part of uh the
Noble eight-fold Path I'll just say briefly that kind of
again broad brush of that is knowing what leads to suffering and
what leads to the ending of suffering and to use that as a
perspective as a framework as we move through our days through our lives just
this sensitivity to oh yeah this is causing suffering this leads to suffering and
this this one isn't this doesn't for me spending time hiking
didn't lead to more suffering it brought a lot of uh
happiness so there's this idea of a discernment but there's also something else that this uh this
separation or distinguishing or something like this that the Buddha
talks about and that is to notice the contents of the Mind what is present in
the mind and what is absent in the mind some of you might be familiar with
this it's the third foundation in the Sati patan suta if you don't know what that means perfectly fine it's just this
um pointing to how there's these UNH
wholesome Roots we might say some of these foundational like really I like
this word roots often unseen and underneath but they're like allowing all kinds of stuff to sprout
up greed hatred and delusion are the classic traditional
Roots greed hatred and delusion you'll notice that I talked about the hindrances like for that desire is an
expression that we we could say the root is a desire and it shows up as a hindrance as I'm sorry greed as the root
and it shows up as a hindrance of Desire we could also say that there's
this uh this hatred and maybe shows up as a hindrance of ill will but could also be anger it can
also um be disdain for others it can
also be um a certain amount kind of arrogance you know so there's these roots that give Sprout to all kinds of
things that turn out to not be so helpful and then delusion we can say there's a number of ways we can talk
about this but delusions is sometimes just being disconnected from whatever is
happening so the Buddha points to can we notice when greed hatred or and or
delusion is present but often it's not it shows up in so many Myriad of ways
it's maybe not so obvious to us so this is there is this way in which
can we get to know when it's greed is
present hatred is present these are strong words delusion these are strong
words nobody wants to say oh yeah I had a lot of greed today I had a lot of hate today
like nobody wants to say this I was diluted for some time
today but there's this way if we can recognize the way these three different
Roots show up in our lives the experience of them this can be
transformative because this is part of the key of finding more peace finding
more freedom finding more ease is getting to understand like what is it
that isn't peaceful what's that experience like for example what is the experience
of like really wanting something like really really wanting something and this
can be a fantastic practice in your daily life on the cushion just recognize
oh I really want my coworker to you know do something or not
do something and I know sometimes I would find myself please let XYZ happen
you know not rain tomorrow or you know whatever it might be please don't let it rain tomorrow please don't let it rain
tomorrow you know there's this sense of you know really wanting something but it
can be fantastic to just notice what is that experience
like how does it feel in the body
could be this little bit of Leaning forward but there's also this tightness and there's this oh I really wanted this
to happen there can also be the certain amount of energy associated with it this the mind it can be like maybe repeating
please make this happen maybe we don't have a clear understanding of who we're
asking or saying to this but there's just this sense I really want this please let it
happen it's uncomfortable it's uncomfortable able these expressions of greed hatred
or delusion it's uncomfortable to experience them in some ways there might feel nice
that there's energy associated with them but uh in the big picture it turns out to be agitating really
agitating and it's uncomfortable to recognize that we have these within us
because what happens is it's this little it's a kind of like a delicate uh
experience maybe to say oh yeah okay there's a lot of hatred you know
aversion it will and then often what happens the next beat and I'm a bad person because I
have that this is often what's happening so it can be really helpful to
discern differentiate separate discernment from judgment
can we make this distinction between these two discernment is
helpful it is this clearer cleaner way in which we're seeing Oh yeah this is
not so helpful this is helpful if we want to clean dirty dishes
it's helpful to use soap rather than just adding more grease to the to the
dish water right this is something that's obvious there's not a lot of judgment about it like oh yeah I grabbed
the wrong thing and didn't add soap to it okay but when we see something in
ourselves can we just have the same type of discernment oh yeah
that's this is uh maybe a cleaner way clean using D soap I don't know
sorry this is a discernment is like a just a clean way of noticing this is
helpful and this way it leaves us room for this greater
perspective for this maybe seeing the big picture and we can start to see
oh yeah yeah okay I could see how that's not helpful and it just feels kind of
clean or I can see how I thought maybe it would be helpful but now it's
not in contrast to judgment which is this quick reactive and kind of this
closed way and it has this value Laden quality to
it and it's often associated with the inner critic this inner critic that shows up and might say something like
well why did I even bother trying to do something I I can't do something new I can't even meditate I don't even know
why I'm trying or I can't change the way my life is
going it's I'm useless I can't do it this means that I'm because I'm having
these hindrances or whatever experience this means that uh I'm
just lazy or I don't know these things that uh we we say about
ourselves so discernment is maybe Forward Thinking is open and it
recognizes maybe that things didn't turn out the way that you had hoped or the way that you had planned but then
discernment like considers oh how did maybe there's some Alternatives here and
so there's like a Way Forward whereas judgment is like this is bad I'm bad and
then it's kind of closed loop of just these stories that just perpetuate it
it's this way that we kind of like gets bogged down and mean and nasty the things that we
say to ourselves can be really awful sometimes or this uh judgment can also
be towards other people but that inner critic sometimes the
Judgment of other people often we notice that but the inner critic often is under
the radar because it feels so familiar it feels like oh
yes and then there's a sense of shame we hope nobody knows this about us it's
just really toxic and painful so part of this VCA this
separation is for us to maybe not to get
bogged down in the inner critic but maybe to like separate to be able to
notice oh yeah the inner critic is here it's telling me that I'm a terrible
person it's reminding me of all the things that I've done wrong [Music]
it's uh discouraging me from trying anything new or trying to expand my
capabilities in any particular way so I'll here I'll just say here's
something to do if you find yourself bogged down lost and weigh down with
this inner critic if you have this feeling of uh
this is really strong or present and is pushing you
around you can just ask yourself how am I feeling right now
that's it that's all you have to do how am I feeling right
now I feel awful okay how does awful feel how am I
feeling right now this awfulness I feel stuck I feel like it's heavy
I feel like nothing's ever going to turn out I feel terrible but then you can say well how
does that feel like how are you feeling right now is away it starts to
feel um maybe it turns your attention towards the uncomfortableness of the
situation but then it also is a way in which it brings mindfulness in how am I
right now I'm
feeling confused not sure what to
do and then there's this way of which bringing mindfulness in is can bring a
certain amount of disruption of the
momentum instead of like maybe just to keep on checking in like how it feels in
the body and how it feels in the mind is a way that instead of this uh um
inner critic running the show if we can kind of like say yes but how am I right
now is this this movement towards how we are with some
care with some kindness is a way that interrupts not only the momentum of the
inner critic but it's also inserting some different energy some different uh
flavor it's introduces some care how am I like it's like with care like how you
would ask somebody that you could see like oh my goodness how are you is this you know way to connect with
and see how they are so when you find that this inner critic is up and
running way that we can just like tune into the
experience not in in with care maybe I should say this with warmth and care as
best you can as best you can because often what will happen is kind of the aversion will
have a certain momentum and it'll start like how the
how the F am I I don't know right we could have this you know
this uh aversion will kind of follow us uh into
that so there's this way inner the inner critic can get us spog down whereas this
discernment allows us to just see things yeah this is not helpful and maybe it
helps us to see here are things that can be done these are issues to be looked at
or situations to be managed or something like this so discernment has this movement forward whereas this judgment
in particular this inner critic has this sense of uh being stuck and so part of
this separation is to be able to distinguish discernment from judgment
and then can we separate ourselves from the judgment and allow that discernment to still be
there between what's helpful and what's not helpful and I mean we do this all the
time often right with judgment that and discernment that we're kind of flitting back and forth without um even
recognizing that we're doing that but it can be helpful to notice and
to tune into okay what is this is there a way that I can separate what's helpful
from not from what's not helpful here
so this VCA with the mind I talked about knowing the contents of the mind and
also in terms of what's present but also what's absent this turns out also to be
not kind of tricky like to notice what's not there we often dwell on difficulties
or dwell on things that are uncomfortable and we Overlook some of the beneficial Pleasant states of the
mind that are there also might be they're just a small amount but they are
just um often ignored or dismissed but when some of these difficulties start to
diminish when we start to become maybe a little more separate from
them they we can start to really notice and feel some of these uh beautiful
states of Mind here's a very short poem from
analo some of you might know analio B analio he's a premier I would say maybe
the foremost uh uh academic who kind of like studies uh this tradition and he's
also a premier you know meditator and uh
he's written books and books and books both on the academic side as well as how to practice so p and alio and uh here's
a very short poem
such Joy it can be when the mind is
free even if only
temporarily such Joy it can be when the mind is free even if only
temporarily I kind of love this it's kind of this Whimsical fun playful way to think about it but just he's pointing
to the power of uh what it can be like when we notice some of the absence of
some of our difficulties if there was a strong sense of really wanting something and just kind of like seeing oh yeah
that faded away I didn't satisfy or uh or maybe you did and that then the
wanting went away but this sense of noticing when some difficulties are are
not there can be really helpful and supportive so this idea of VCA this
separation to and to separate is both like separate ourselves physically move
ourselves into a place that supports some ease and settledness and also mentally to
separate ourselves often What's called the hindrances and then this whole idea of
just to even be able to recognize that things can be separated and maybe put
into helpful and unhelpful as well as to notice well what
is going on in the mind what is present and what's not present what's helpful
what's uh not helpful and then I uh made this this uh
clunky little expression of being independent of what is unhelpful I kind
of like this idea of Independence you know this you know it's a way of feeling like okay I've doesn't
mean I don't know what's unhelpful but and I can interact with it and maybe be
with it but I'm independent of it I can separate myself if need
be so thank you and I think I'll open it up for some uh questions or comments
thank you
does anybody have uh something they'd like to
say is sloth and torpor different from feeling sleepy while I'm
meditating so there's a um two different ways we can Define feeling sleepy one is
feeling sleepy due to lack of sleep and there's one that's feeling sleepy as a
way in which the mind kind of does is like trying to avoid something so it
kind of uh shuts down or it just hangs out in this foggy place so it can't be
with what's over there it's very common both because we're sleep deprived so but
and we often want to avoid things here's how you can tell the
difference if you're doing a meditation period And if the and you're feeling
like oh my gosh I can't stay awake and you even find yourself you know doing this type of
thing if like the Bell Rings into the meditation period you're like oh great okay now I got to go do this I got to
take care of this I got to do this if there's all of a sudden energy returns it's not due to lack of sleep it's due
to just the way the mind is uh wanting to not be with some uncomfortable
experience and it's okay this happen to everybody this I've done a my a lot of this myself
so anybody else have a question or
comment thank you um when you were talking about VCA
initially um after your uh hike in the
in Utah um it sounded more like um it was
related to taking Refuge oh very nice and um so I and then when you were
talking about it further and it became more about discernment it seemed somewhat different
but is there a relationship between VCA and taking Refuge are they like the
Opposites of one another or in furtherance of taking Refuge just not
not sure how to yeah yeah thank you Nancy for this this is a nice
idea um so one way like I kind of like
think about it is uh sometimes you know taking refuge in the Buddha Dharma SAA
but we also use this word refuge we kind of like create Wildlife refuges right
where Wildlife we separate them from other things out there that are going to eat them or poachers or whatever is
going to happen and we put them uh in uh you know in an enclosure of some kind or something like this so in
the same way I would say they're kind of they're related this way of uh yeah I'm separating and orienting
towards what's
helpful Diana we have we have one question online uh what is the difference between
VCA and renouncing yeah so there's a uh a
similarity but uh renunciation is more about uh
Simplicity and it's more about
um yeah I would say it's more an emphasis on Simplicity and of course there's uh a relationship between um
separating out what helpful and unhelpful and just being with what's helpful and renunciation so there there
there's a relationship but I would say there's a maybe a distinction maybe renunciation has the
goes up maybe a step further it's more like maybe letting go of what's
unhelpful whereas I'm just pointing to uh recognizing that you can make a
difference or or dis distinction or discernment and um and to do so maybe
renunciation is you could say maybe it's the next step after
N I think is the poly word for renunciation they don't have any similar
atmology but thank you for the
question yes we're we're at time so I'll answer this one quickly but if you have can ask it quickly I'll be I'll be quick
um the word that came to mind for me or a couple of different words was
Solitude um which to me has a very positive con ation um and then also I
was thinking about protection and I know that the the Buddha um every day would
take time out from meeting with people and take time out during the year to to
be um to be separate and that that that feels like that's a way to be more
balanced is to take time away um to kind of recharge one's one's
batteries and Solitude um and I I value that a lot and Nature's a great place to
do that yeah thank you thank you via sometimes gets translated as Solitude and sometimes as seclusion also yeah
yeah thank you okay wishing you all a lovely rest
of the evening and safe travels home if you'd like you come up and talk to me otherwise I wish you well thank you