so good morning everyone and Welcome
to our meditation time together and I'm going to sneeze I
think wait a minute and maybe at
best so for this meditation today I'd like to say
that in that somadi involves a unification Gathering a coming together
of everything all of who we are uh engaged in a single
activity and all supporting engaging the activity of being present here and
now uh without being distracted and that most commonly it in
is gathering unification in the present moment around a Center Point a settling
place a gathering place that doesn't exclude things but
allows all things to have supporting roles and coming together and everything's kind of gathered and
collected here for the same purpose the same direction the
same and um the um and one of the parts things that that
gets unified gets collected that comes together could be understood to be uh
continuity of attention so uh time is not just place but there's also
the idea of the continuous movement of
time and of course time doesn't move maybe there is no time really in some
kind of philosoph iCal way or experiential way there's also we live in
time and and so what it what it lives what what I'm mostly focusing on now is
the uh unification also inv involves a
continuity of staying present here and now without losing it without wandering
off so we stay in time and I love this expression staying
in time because it kind of has a musical
Association and um the um uh being in time in all kinds of ways but living in
time being continuous with the way the present moment flows through
time and so sometimes I think of um uh mindfulness and meditation concentration
as a writing the wave of the present as the present moves
through the the you know this
um River of time and we're riding the current and we have to stay in the
current and be riding on it continuously if we fall off the wave if we get spun
out out of the current of the river like into an Eddy or something then we're still we we've lost the present
moment and for me this idea of catching the wave and staying on it catching the current and flowing along and then fall
off get back on and ride it again catch and sometimes I TI I connect that to the
exhale as the place where I get on again and ride is carry as much as I can so
the continuity of attention that's done without strain
that's done without Force done without um apologies done without about
disappointment when we fall off just get back on and then uh see if you can not
so much work at being present but ride the present
moment ride continuously stay on stay on
and some of you know my scooter analogy we can ride the scooter as long as the
momentum of the kick is there and as it momentum goes down we do a gentle kick
again to keep it going so so rather than a wave or a current of the river the
idea of this kind of gentle pushing casually pushing moving the scooter in
in the present moment so I I'll guide you with this so assuming a meditation
posture
and and assuming a posture that you think will allow you
you to be alert in your
body in such a way that you can allow the body to relax
deeply almost like you assume a posture that
supports the way the muscles of the body want to relax anything extra
any kind of muscles that are apart from the simple ones that are
used to hold us in the posture we're
in and to gently close your eyes and then
gently calmly as if you have all the time in the world not forcing it or
being being in a hurry take some comfortably
deeper in breaths feeling the expansion of the Torso as you breathe
in and if see if you can breathe in in a way that's not too deep but just a
deeper full or in breath that stays enjoyable it feels nice
so maybe because of how you do it calmly and slowly or how there's a gentle
stretch opening or maybe it feels very nice to
feel bigger with the
inhale and then allow the exhale to Exhale longer
than normally would not by forcefully exhaling more but at the end of the
exhale relaxing relaxing the
body maybe relaxing into the settling Place deep
inside so these calm slow deeper inhales will you ride the
inhale like a wave all the way from the beginning to the
end a continuity through
time and kind of feel what that's like to
ride the inhale continuously or to aride the awareness for the
duration of the
inhale and with the exhale relaxing the body
settling and then to let your breathing return to
normal and for this ability to ride the present moment continuous awareness
through time it helps a lot if you can be
relaxed because continuous present moment
awareness is what we do what the mind what our system does if we don't interfere with it we
don't override it with thoughts and ideas and intentions and wants and
aversions
doesn't have to be a forced phenomena it maybe is more of an loud
phenomena allowing it to operates we don't interfere with it so to relax
deeply as you exhale relaxing the muscles of the face
as you exhale relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the
belly maybe you can release and relax the whole torso so the weight of the
body helps you to settle more
and on the exhale to soften the thinking
mind relax the
mind and if there's a lot of thinking
can you dial the thinking down a little bit so thinking is calmer a little
slower
quieter can you switch your thinking from thinking about other
things to having thoughts about
meditation thoughts that a naturalist would have simply recording and knowing what's
Happening Here and Now
and then not directing your attention
anywhere but allowing attention awareness to be available to whatever is
occurring in the present moment at any sense
door with the emphasis on appreciating or
feeling what it's like to not be directed but instead to be
available open receptive
and then with that kind of open receptive awareness without moving the mind or
without in a certain way directing the Mind open the mind
to welcome or feel the gentle breeze the gentle
sensations of breathing in and breathing
out and begin Now by being aware of the experience of breathing
by noticing whatever is easy to feel and experience regarding
breathing not think about it but sense what comes into
awareness around breathing in the easiest obvious way
relaxing any sense of directing your
attention but more like opening the window so the wind
the breeze comes in
not so much that you're doing awareness like
swimming but that you're allowing the current of the river to come up from behind and carry
you along
and let the current of the breeze the wave of the
inhale let it carry you carry your attention
continuously for the length of the inhale
monitoring yourself enough to stay there with the full
length of the inhale
and then to do that with the
exhale the inhale is the wave that rises you
up and the exhale is a surfing on
it the inhales the gentle push of the scooter and the exhale is carrying
Along being carried moving along on the scooter
following the exhale to the settling point the grounding point the centering
Point letting the inhale begin there and then bringing all this
together allowing yourself to be aware continuously of breathing in and
breathing out around
if you wonder off simply Begin
Again maintaining a continuity of
attention through time without
Force but with a kind of intentionality a sense of purpose
that's soft
relaxed while being committed to keeping you in the
current of time of
now
e
for
for e
and as we come to the end of the
sitting to take a few moments to feel into your
body whatever is there that feels more
calmer more settled
whatever in your body it feels comfortable or
Pleasant having spent these minutes meditating even if parts of your body
are uncomfortable feel the places where it's
comfortable or Pleasant where the body feels more
subtle or
peaceful even if it's just the very small place in your
body and allow your mind to relax and
appreciate the presence of some AUM of good feelings in your
body that to that degree your mind can settle more
relax being here and
now whatever way you feel
emotionally in a better place than you were before
and every whatever way your mind is more at
ease or maybe taking time to remember a time in your life
where you were quite subtle and
peaceful at ease and what that was like for you for
your body
and knowing this for
yourself wishing this for Others May
others be comfortable in their bodies May others be at ease in their
hearts and their minds
May others be peaceful and quiet at
home with themselves with their hearts
here and may it be that the degree to which you know these
things can be a source an
inspiration to somehow have it spread from you out into the
world that if you can stay in touch with it maybe it can spread maybe it can be
support others to feel that way too may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may we somehow or other contribute to
that certainly may we avoid making the situation worse
[Music]
thank you [Music]
so good morning and welcome to to this 20th talk on
samadi and uh the topic for the last four days has been related to the
unification the inclusivity of
um of um samadi and um that we want to bring our
body everything settle together be here supportive for uh the center of
attention in the present moment centering it on something like the
breathing and um and part of this unification bringing together being
whole is involves time that we're
also uh uh living in time which the only
way to live in time is to live in the present moment in the way I'm talking
about it uh uh
to uh to be continuous through time with awareness and um in a way where
awareness is not hijacked by preoccupations and concerns where
awareness is not pulled away this way and that by desires and aversions fears
that were settled and um and one way to think about this that uh works for me is that
that of um uh maybe even like riding a slide or being carried in an fast moving
River that's quite safe but you have to be really present to be in the current and flowing down in a canoe or a raft
or um surfing body surfing board surfing
on a wave going there's a variety of things that we do that we get carried
and flow skiing for some people maybe Sports um more sports that are more
active where as we're doing this the the sport um part of what can be so
enjoyable about it is that uh we're no longer caught up in our preoccupations something about what
we're doing brings us into the present moment into the present moment activity in a continuous way and um and uh and if
thoughts are operating they either have re SE it in the background they're not really relevant or they're support
supportive characters in the event and so rather than thinking being the main
actor they're a supporting actor for this being engaged and involved in the
activity so excuse me I don't know if you I was able to turn that off fast enough before my
sneeze and um so so the representative is on like a
slide you most people when they go sliding down especially a long slide that's not too fast um uh you know that
their preoccupation or other things goes away we're just in the in the in the
slide and um the um and uh it can be nice it's
very nice and I think there's something about our whole system that likes being fully present and engaged in certain
activities it could be a craft it could be reading a book partly because we're
not being pulled out of the present moment we're not being pulled out by fear aversion desires
preoccupations um and uh and so the awareness our ability for present moment
attention has not been compromised by the preoccupations of our mind and and
it turns out that if without the mind the ruminations the stories that we live in some of them almost
subconscious the beliefs we're operating under without those kind of in place
then natural capacity just to be aware in the present the natural capacity for attention as it moves through our body
more complete as it's kind of more uh inclusive of all the different attentional faculties we have
the happier we can be the more pleasant it is the more goodness it feels there the more rightness it feels to be really
here and um and uh so part of what we're learning in in uh in process of suade is
learning the art of staying with our experience continuously through time and
in the beginning it means that we're continuous for a short time and then we do it again and continuous for a short
time and slowly as we relax and settle slowly as the preoccupations of the mind
kind of lessen that ability to stay present is able to be more extended so
not by force not by holding ourself there with a great force little bit there's there has to be some intention
some oomph some commitment to being present open relaxed and there
um uh and um and uh so that we don't
easily wander off in thought but with time we're not feeding the thinking not feeding the preoccupations and it's able
to stay in that that flow of the present longer and longer and uh maybe in the
beginning it's just maybe if you're lucky you can do the whole inhale and then the whole exhale but over time it
becomes multiple inhales and exhales and this is where counting the exhales
useful some people count the exhale and the inhale and uh but the counting kind
of is a encouragement to stay present uh and to encourage encourage me
to stay into in the experience of breathing not staying the count is just
a small piece of what we're doing it's a almost using count that you're imagining yourself
counting and um and uh it's kind of like a pointer stay there and the value of counting to 10 is that
the mind has to be a little more alert to the process of counting in the present
moment and uh and as we get into it this if as long it's not forceful or tight or
contracted but the sense of settling and opening and inclusivity of all with the
center point on the breathing staying on that Center Point um staying in the
really feeling that we're resting in the canoe as the current of the R carries us
um if we're um there's a natural process of goodness
of brightness of pleasure or comfort that can happen some of it because the
tensions we carry inside of us have a lot to do with how we think about things
and if we're not thinking so much um then uh natural Comfort or well-being or
sense of relief can be quite nice quite nice and as we get deeper into deeper
into it um there's more and more pleasure that can arise with samadi so this process of this week of
being inclusive uh being oriented being settled being um here more and more
fully with all of who we are in a sense is and then today continuous through
time is a Prelude to beginning to feel the the pleasure or the joy Joy the
Delight of samadi we're making room for that in the body we're making space for it through
time we're making room in the mind for some deeper process to begin
unfolding and um and so continuity of attention is very
important and uh so that's what I'd encourage you to practice and um and
maybe even look for the ways in the daily life that you have where you can
relax the scattered mind the preoccupied mind enough to just simply in a very
simple way um the um the enjoy your everyday attention
awareness of what's Happening going for a walk in a park and just enjoying the present moment of being with the the
trees the landscape the people uh if uh and uh and kind of
cultivate this ability to be more continuous in the present moment here and now with
this maybe uh spend less time being on your device
which certainly in the present moment with the device but generally the kind of attention when we're looking at a
screen uh does something very different to the brain it actually en encourage is
a brain which is destructible courage is a brain which is caught up in its thoughts not that uh where the whole
system the whole body comes alive with awareness so I'll end with a
um a delightful image at least for me it's delightful I hope you enjoy it uh
of this idea of staying continuous being carried in the current being carried
kind of on the slide of the present moment maybe the slide of the
exhale um or being is um
uh good number of years ago I uh came out to my car on the street while it was
raining and uh it wasn't raining super hard but it was definitely raining and the windshield of my car was you know
all wet and there was a little bird it wasn't very big that uh would stand at
the top of the windshield and slide to the bottom Hop Off fly up and slide down
again it just over and over again and it was just sliding down that there wasn't any food involved there wasn't
any searching for safety or searching for a partner as far as I can tell it
was just enjoying sliding and so if a bird can do that
then um I think it represents a very for me it represents a very
deep um maybe a way in which we creature with brains have
been shaped to find a certain kind of
delight in being fully in the present moment with some experience of being
open relaxed being carried along and may it be that until we come
back on Monday that uh you allow the the flow of
time of the present moment to carry along your present moment
awareness and may it bring you delight and joy so in in meditation for these next
two days see if you can work on this topic work on this capacity we have of
having attention be more continuous through time so thank you very much