so uh so welcome folks um yeah good to uh good to be with
you so uh we'll do that that uh thing we do
together so uh finding uh finding your posture
and so natural to predict that the next moment will be a great deal like the
last to expect me the next moment
some level our highest priority is not being startled by a niche
that can uh deaden our experience
of our life
relaxing whatever can be relaxed
we're just practicing being alive just
available to uh experience moment by moment
just being uh kind of internally caressed by your breathing
sort of sweeping soothing movement
your breathing unifying your Buddy
to the imperfections of this moment of our
lives we We don't have to say yes to those imperfections forever
but for right now we can there's always something
wrong is something we might tweak or adjust or fix or dial
in just stop being baited by Mara
moment by moment
each uh breath just
uh becoming secluded
if there's a thread of interest
curiosity kind of passion to know something
anything just follow that uh thread of
interest we can't manufacture interest when it's not there but when it is
there it's maybe the most
trustworthy intention for practice
we're practicing
noticing new phenomena or familiar phenomena in just slightly
new ways
the poetry and aliveness of not knowing or not quite
knowing
we expect to find ourselves in the next
moment we're invited to put down these kinds of expectations
what does it mean to uh cease
reiterating the self as we
breathe feel to our body sense the my
head the mind comes uh infused with
uh Buddha Dharma
we uh forget ourselves to
remember the path
[Music]
okay so um some years ago maybe
it's 201 18 I think
um Gil and and some others um were uh
kind of in the spir uh system were asked to write some brief reflections on um on
CIA ethical conduct and
um and I I wrote you know they just asked for a couple paragraphs so wrote
something and one of the SA members was was um asking about those those words
and so I thought to uh go back and uh revisit them so I'll just um read what I
wrote and uh and then say say a few
words so um I said um make make of yourself a
refuge for all beings the Buddha enjoins us to cultivate this radical heart a
cultivation expressing not only sila but samadei and pa
too to be safe for others entails a path of self-discovery humility
sensitivity and willingness to be softened by one's suffering goodness ripens through a
process of letting go and letting go involves a measure of grief we grieve
the harm done to us and the harm done by us we grieve the human condition the
indivisibility of life and suffering this process is
autobiographical idiosyncratic and
universal to be mindful of goodness brings love to be mindful of pain also
brings love that asymmetry is the
miracle the more attuned we are to our heart and its instant karmic
reverberations the clearer our ethical life will be the more unified the mind becomes the
deeper the love will be boundless nothing but warmth the effortless care that is the
face of emptiness we learn unwaveringly hatred is never the last
word to see more is to love more sila expresses the entire
path and then we begin again the story we tell about love is
never final new questions complexities and debts
arise might I owe more than I suppose the ego complicates
everything i want to think of myself as a really good person and I don't really
want to change my behavior ethical development stagnates
when we rationalize our preferences it's conceivable that goodness entails much more than even we
good people are accustomed to giving just because the
saint is extremely rare doesn't mean that anything less strictly speaking is
justifiable can imagine in the notistant future a major reconfiguration of our
ethical obligations to non-human animals to the egregious suffering of the most
vulnerable around the globe and to future generations this is a time for radical
hearts i don't usually feel up to the task but I am steadfast in keeping a
relationship with my own sense of moral
incoherence from that relationship I hope that I evolve and contribute more
of what I owe to the welfare of others the path
unfolds then at some point it's time to die that final gesture of letting go
which is both deeply poignant and also not such a big
deal your life was made complete by what you gave away
so you might was asked to write something about sila but uh
might enter uh the doorway of wisdom find your way to sila and
samadei uh likewise there there are those people who committed to love and
service to sila who uh maybe without knowing their
existence just quietly find their way into more and more wisdom and
stillness and this is part of why dharma talks not you know they they
just don't tend to stay on one theme you know if you like sampled 5 seconds of a
thousand dharma seed talks it would be hard to know what the topic was you know
in each one because it just weaves together you cannot talk about love
without talking about wisdom and so to to be a refuge to cease doing
so much harm uh that that that entails a a a
measure of clarity and attunement of sensitivity and humility of
tracking the ways our being uh ripples out into others
and there must be a kind of you know I' I've been kind
of circumambulating this theme for a long time you know but uh being wrong
that book uh Katherine Schultz wrote many years ago um but graceful
gracefulness gracefulness about having been wrong is
just indispensable in our moral evolution and our our evolution as
practitioners and the this process this process by which
we we grow this process by which we recognize uh some measure of uh
um that uh we were wrong in some way
that process um uh often feels like uh
like something like grieving and uh the growing pains of dharma feel like
grieving but um we need not be uh so afraid of pain when
we've acquired the taste for purification
and it's amazing to feel we actually get a sense of it happening inside us almost
alchemically i don't know how to say it exactly but unpleasant vena un you know the
intensity the imperfection of life becoming the brahma vharas becoming some species of
love and it strikes me that um something like solid liquid
gas pain grief
love it's one dharma talk for 100 people the dharma said to be universal right
but almost a kind of infinite number of constellations of upaya skillful
means and what is wisdom for one is delusion for
another and the way that delusion often manifests is not doing the opposite of what the Buddha says but delusion
expresses itself when we reach for the wrong teaching when we try maybe
to fit our practice into someone else's mind into some
ideal so much of practice is uh a kind of sensitive improvisational
uh way of being and so you're you're not
assimilating to some Buddhist culture you're
finding your belonging within the dharma
idiosyncratic and yet feels exactly like
home this love can um stabilize can linger with us is never far never
far animates our daily rhythms and I don't know you know I'm a
I'm not a my sleep is not lucid you know I'm a dumb sleeper
kind of I know some people are dream yoga and various things and lucid
dreaming yeah beautiful right that's not my experience i don't know if I could
train myself but but if you woke up in a dream a lucid
dream it would be I presume very easy to love to love
almost recklessly the sense of being conscious of being in a dream and to
feel as I imagine I would that love is utterly
costfree and what happens if we wake up in our life and it becomes
more dreamlike what uh shape would your love
take the story we tell about love is never final story we tell about love
evolves and we're suggestible where
um the you know when in bachelor's rendition it's like it's hard to hear
the dharma when you love your place and you know loving one's place I would
say is part of it is is being a person of our time of course we're all people
of our time but we're incredibly suggestible morally speaking even When
we call ourselves radical we take on many of the dominant values
culture and so part of our practice is developing kind of deep moral
imagination this line from um theologian Hesshel
that uh quotes sometimes uh the prophet the prophet is human yet they employ
notes one octave too high for our ears they experience moments that defy
our understanding they are neither a singing saint nor a moralizing poet but an
assaulter of the mind often their words begin to burn where
conscience ends
uh the philosopher Parfett said um we're
separated you know in in a kind of philosophical inquiry into
identity came to the the sense of um that we're separated from our future
selves by time separated by fellow humans by
space and why does the separation across time matter so much more separation
across space that sounds harsh maybe but um the
phrase that came to me is that the ego makes liars of us
all just liars that's not to inject a measure of self
you know the dharma selfconquering the ego or something like that i know it's
strong language but the truth just seems absolutely meaningless to the
ego and in a sense it's only when we wake up to
uh uh love we only wake up to love when the homelessness of ego is realized
grieved released
and this um seems to me
uh for me it's the only way that my life feel uh might feel complete the
end you know it's like otherwise even a thousand years would feel like I'm being
robbed of something so what what would be complete
for your heart what would be a complete life the sense of this this life was enough this life was
enough and uh so we practice completing our life we
practice dying before we die offer this for your u
consideration so thank you for your attention
and um
um yeah I'll see you uh see you next week and I I dropped a uh a line for um
uh questions um in the I think the description i just chatted it in too and
so it's uh it's there if you have questions it's uh it's the it's the it's
questions comments complaints the uh Dharma customer
service desk is is open at that Google form so um uh yeah maybe I'll take a question
next time but I I wish you all uh all well thanks very much