so welcome warm welcome everyone and delighted to be here subbing for Gil
while he's on vacation My name is Don Neil for those of us who we haven't met in person or um virtually
And just want to say a few words before we start the meditation for those of you who are already here that um this week
I'll be covering we'll be exploring the five elements which is both a contemplation and a
practice that is intrically related to the experience of insight especially as
um it is put forth and experienced in the um
classical Burmese Myanmar tradition that Gil and I have both practiced in
So with that as an orientation the invitation once you've finished all
of your greetings and warm hellos is to settle back into meditation practice
and noticing
how it is to be in your body this morning
Maybe taking a couple of deeper slower breaths
and allowing awareness to come to the forefront
Allowing this moment to come to the forefront this embodied
moment
[Music]
Noticing the weight of your body on the cushion
or chair or mat
Noticing the support behind or beneath you
whether it's firm or hard or soft
and yielding
Noticing the texture of any clothing on your skin
or on whatever surface you're contacting Is it rough or smooth
tuning in also to the heaviness or lightness in your body
Right now I'm feeling a sense of weight my hip points
A little bit of pressure against the back of the chair the back of my body
Noticing for yourself this feeling of being held
rooted in your place
held to the earth by gravity
Noticing too any feelings of lightness
Perhaps lightness in the chest or belly as air comes in
Perhaps a lightness in the heart being with Sana or taking time for yourself
to practice
Then attuning to other dimensions of the felt sense
of being here
Perhaps a sense of moisture or dryness in the air
against your skin or as it enters the nostrils
and becomes breath
Noticing any warmth or cool heat or cold
on the skin or inside the body
Perhaps a slight chill of air or warmth
of clothing or a wrap
When within this field of felt sensations
noticing the movement the aliveness
of this body
Perhaps the movement of the abdomen or belly diaphragm
This air breath goes in and out
or the play of sensations at the tip of the nose or the top of the lip
shifting and changing
and settling anchoring
the attention
in the felt sense of the moment
If distractions arise
allowing your meditation as the Buddha invited your meditation to
be like the earth
not allowing thoughts stories
to proliferate through the mind but returning to this body
A sense of weight integrity
sitting like a mountain
from time to time Reconnecting
with this experience this embodied moment
Noticing there are places of density
weight softness lightness
even within the breath itself
Sometimes on the outreath there can be a sense of settling
drawing the attention inward and downward
like sediment settling the attention
the heart in the body The moment
Allowing the attention to stay close to the felt sensations
shifting changing [Music]
Rooted in now Grounded in now
In the last remaining moments of this meditation
The invitation is to notice
any ways that there might be more settledness
grounding perhaps lightness or spaciousness
And at the beginning of this time of practice together Feeling
into that
And then from that place whatever unfolded
noticed with appreciation and kindness
casting your internal gaze outwards to all of those your life touches
Wishing that just like me just like you
they be happy as healthy as possible
peaceful
That just like you just like me
may be free of suffering
May all beings be safe peaceful and free
[Music]
Thank you for the sincerity of your practice
So good morning and a warm welcome to our online sit together
This week um as I mentioned to those who are on a little bit early I'm covering
um we will be exploring together the topic of the elements in Buddhist
practice sometimes four elements sometimes five elements I'm um offering
a teaching on the five elements and um
to say that this is both a meditation practice and what's called a
contemplation And by contemplation I mean there's a number of different kind of um
exercises that the Buddha gave for us to consider and frame our understanding of
felt embodied experience And those um both the practice and the
contemplation the imaginative exercise help to prime
the mind for insight or deepening of insight So this week is offered in
support of Gil's unfolding series on insight in practice right now
So four or five elements are earth water fire air and sometimes space And I just
want to name this is a bronze age framework So what does it have to do with us now
so there's a number of reasons that it's still relevant First as many of you know
maybe all of you know we still have elements those are not necessarily called elements anymore because we now
have the periodic table of elements and even beneath that there's a quantum level of elemental experience So we
think of them differently but the basic notion that folks had in and before the
time of the Buddha that we are made of the same stuff as the world around us as
the earth still holds It's just a bit more sophisticated now perhaps
So this contemplation and meditative practice is a way of pardon unearthing
this felt experience and it's one of many cases where a
skillful means or a framework is introduced by the Buddha for developing
insight into inconstancy in nature and
not self or selflessness anata So I have an anecdote about this from my
time as a um practitioner in Myanmar Burma I was practicing with a contemporary of
Gil's teacher there upandita Um my teacher was Sid Jonica
and um I was practicing within the framework of the progress of insight the way that um
the rough framework Gil is using in his teachings right now
and um would have one-on-one or very small group meetings with the sciat
every day to see how things were unfolding And in the course of these practice
conversations in the course of my weeks there of practicing in one of these practice conversations
it came up that um the elements were apparent
and it happened just after the insight into anata
It was an organic arising that came up in one of these small group
conversations and seeing the shifting changing and
personal nature of elements and embodied practice could actually be considered
another form of seeing each That's what came up in the discussion And then later
I learned maybe that same trip or maybe shortly afterwards that the form of practice we
were doing the mahasi method it's called with which really involves noticing the movement of the belly the abdomen with
the breath was actually considered by the person who developed it for lay people people
like us say mahasi to be elements practice a very classic mindfulness of
the body practice from the four foundations of mindfulness
I'll say more about this as the week unfolds But to say that it's central
and it's not necessary if it doesn't resonate for you yet it is central It's
one of the central practices in that foundational text of our tradition
So as I said this is one of many forms of
meditation and contemplation which involve shifting and changing our
perceptual process our perceptions And among other things this shows how
the heart and mind shape our experience of reality for the purpose of cutting
through forms of clinging that amp up or even cause increase
unnecessary suffering duka in our lives
This week we'll explore both the contemplative and meditative dimensions of this practice
of elements practice especially how it can support insight including a practical perspective and of more of a
poetic or mythic perspective according to um
well actually it's not even according to the commentaries I'll talk about the commentaries in a moment but at the
introduction to many many of the Buddhist discourses there'll be this just kind of toss away line This body
composed of or comprised of the four elements or the five elements It's just
kind of taken as a given this notion that
we are the same matter the same stuff as the
world around us And that wasn't just a kind of
lifeless sort of quantum physics of the time though it was a material
observation Of course there was also this cultural soup in which the Buddha
lived and taught that was um kind of prehindu pre- breminical
and the idea in the ancient texts of the brahinss the aananishads
was that these different materials these different processes of earth
water fire kind of had a certain sort of aliveness
So it's about that felt sense of aliveness in the poetic sense
in the um so the first four elements
are experienced as objects of meditation Objects of meditation on the body The
first foundation of mindfulness In other words touch
sensation interosception the feeling of what happens within our bodies
and they have the power attending to them has the power of bringing us here
Now according to the commentaries they have
each element has experiential qualities and functions
So they're ways of noticing the experience of the body in the moment as
a process In other words direct experience
of embodied change in constancy
So elements practice can be a skillful means for experiencing that river of change and for disidentification
desentering from our attitudes or imagination or cultural projections about our bodies I don't like my skin
now that I'm over 50 or I don't like my hair or I don't like my belly Those are all thoughts
Instead this is the lived experience of kaya the body the aliveness
and our fundamental belonging to nonsparation
from nature the earth itself
So with all of that as context and introduction thanks for hanging in there with me We'll talk a little bit about
the earth earth element to start with a just a nod to a sort of
more mythop poetic perspective as I talked about the last time I was
subbing for gil on YouTube the night of the Buddha's awakening
he was assailed by the forces of mara life denying forces of
um doubt and ill will and the like And in some versions of this story well
in all versions he touches the earth You can see the touch earth mudra on many Buddhist statues
And in these myths some of them the earth shakes earth is
my witness I belong I have capacity to awaken
And in some of these stories it's described as the earth being her She
bears witness to him
So earth can be inspiration for meditation
as it is in that myth or as in one of the discourses the teachings in which
the Buddha advises his very own son Rahula to take inspiration from each of these
elements Take inspiration Make your meditation like the earth
you said and I'll say more about this in later talks because the same is true for
water fire air space We too can take the earth as inspiration
for our practice the strength the solidity
the integrity the settledness
We can also attune to those qualities associated with the earth element
Are we feeling in this moment sensations of heaviness or lightness
hardness or roughness softness or smoothness
attending to their changing nature if you want to feel into right now what
heaviness or hardness might feel like on a more material level in the body the classic instructions are to notice the
teeth kind of put them together Notice your nails Feel into the way our bones our
skeletons hold us up There's an integrity there
Then there's the function The function of each element And the
function of the earth element is that it is the basis from which all else grows
on one level the base for the other elements In the samuta nikaya the connected
discourses the Buddha likens the mind to the earth element that it's the ground
for the other experiences This is picked up by the waiter Tibetan
tradition and I'm quoting here from um it's actually from a a wiki on um
Tibetan Buddhism The mind's ability to serve as the ground for all experience
is the quality of earth So essentially the Buddha's words but a
little bit more um contemporary in their saying
So it supports earth element supports
all of the seeds of our minds All of the cultivation for good or for ill of our
minds I'll close with this poem attributed to
patachara These are poems based on the awakening
songs of the women in the terriata by Patachara
And she says "Farmers turn up the soil plant seeds
and wait all by itself Water pours down from the
sky and turns the earth into food After all these years sleeping on the
ground waking before dawn and begging for every meal
where's my harvest late one evening I was washing my feet
After another long day of sitting and walking the water poured over my feet and onto
the ground I let my mind go and it flowed downhill with the water
towards my little hut I went inside
sat on the bed and lowered the wick of the lamp all by itself The flame went out
and she awoke In some versions of that poem there's
talk about settling the mind with the flow of the water
And this this awakening poem sets us up for tomorrow's topic water
So your assignment homework assignment should you choose to accept it between
now and tomorrow is to notice notice in the felt sense of your
experience how sensations of heaviness or lightness
change roughness or smoothness density or soft spaciousness
Notice this in your day Maybe a few moments in formal meditation or informally through the day and see how
it connects you to the moment or doesn't Thank you for your practice