welcome to everyone arriving nice to see you
so let's go ahead and start
so sometimes occasionally
you may experience uh a mind that has a lot of restlessness in it
and I'm saying that a little bit tongue and cheek because I think we all know that one
and other times the mind may seem to be kind of uninterested in meditation
so we may have restlessness or disinterest can't quite be there and
sometimes we take that to be that itself to be the problem and we try to change
how the mind is we think it should be some other way but sometimes when we do that all we're
doing is letting go at a surface level and it turns out there's actually something underneath that's driving all
those thoughts or all that resistance and so there can be times where we need
to see the that underlying issue before the mind can settle down so there's
restlessness and then sometimes a little investigation can help and sometimes there's some kind of emotion maybe some
kind of discontent or some kind of desire that's often what drives
restlessness so and if you're feeling very calm and
peaceful that's also great but with that little introduction let's
let's sit together and have a chance to look more carefully at our minds
so settling in now for a to a a posture where you can
stay sitting for half hour or so
just allowing the attention to come inward sensing the body
in whatever posture you're in knowing that you're moving into a
meditative mind space
in a natural simple way
and starting by feeling into the body
not what it looks like in the mirror but what it feels like right now to be in a
sense in the body
sometimes it's easy to connect first with the contact points
the place where you're sitting resting on just feeling your weight
the solidity and stability of sitting on a chair a cushion a bed
and allowing yourself to be supported
and sensing into the balance of the body sometimes I even rock back and forth
slightly or forward and back slightly just to sense that really that middle
balance point as well as possible and inviting the
body to settle There
inviting some softening in the face in the shoulders
in the belly arms and legs
and tuning into the sensations of the breath
which are certainly happening in the present moment
so this is a way of inviting the mind to connect with the present
the simple life force of the body
breathing in breathing out
it can be helpful to invite some further softening on the outreath
and bringing up consciously the quality of mindfulness
a simple present moment attention
that doesn't judge what's happening as good or bad right or wrong just sees
clearly
it's easy enough with the breath because there really isn't any right or wrong way to breathe
just notice how the breath is
And now noticing the energy in the mind
as we settle in we can just at a top level
check in is the mind more on the side of being a little
drowsy or dull
more on the side of being a little bit energized or
jumpy restless
it's as simple as you know taking the temperature of water putting our hand in is it a little cool a little warm
and just noticing that it's a natural quality of the mind that
the this kind of energy changes
throughout the day and even from minute to minute
so continuing to stay with the breath as the primary object
but in a sense also being aware of the tendency of the mind
toward being a little agitated or a little dull
or perhaps it's perfectly centered at this moment
that happens too
but just resting with the breath and having some curiosity about
the flow of the mind in addition
It may be that simply paying attention
to the energy level of the mind
helps it to find some balance balance
it's a little bit like the dynamic balance of riding a bicycle
you're never completely balanced on a bicycle but always making very slight
corrections back toward the center
it's possible for the for that to happen in meditation too
with the right balance of conditions we stay with the breath and
a little agitated but then that settles out a little dull but then
that returns to balance
and sometimes not sometimes the mind is really determined
to not stay present and if that's the case
it can be helpful to notice next time it happens
what did it feel like what does it feel like when the mind is
continually moving away is there something else
there right before it goes off or it gets dull
continuing
to breathe along with the flow of the mind
and as we continue to bring mindfulness to the mind
the flow of the mind A gentle reminder that
mindfulness is not deciding what should and shouldn't happen
it simply is being with what is happening
so mindfulness has kind of an inherent aspect of contentment
being okay with what is actually happening in the
present
whereas the moment where the mind gets caught in a thought
or a desire is kind of a moment of discontent in the mind something else would be better than
this present moment seeing a contrast between
the discontent of restlessness and desire
the contentment of noticing and being with how things are
at this moment
can we be content with a mind that is sometimes restless
and sometimes not
once again we feel the ease and the safety
just being mindful
nothing is a problem if we're aware of it
and as we move toward the end of our formal sitting
beginning to have a sense of
what it means to be okay with things as they are
the dharmapata says contentment is the greatest wealth
it doesn't mean accepting terrible things
somehow validating things that we don't agree with but that very base level of yeah this is
how it is at this moment and when we do that with our mind which
is sometimes discontented restless restless or dull
we can then carry that into our day
as we move through tasks that we enjoy tasks that we don't enjoy so much
just managing the mind well through all of those changes
staying with things staying with interactions
that may not be to our liking but we can be content to know yes
I'm present i'm going through this it's such a gift to ourselves and to others
to have this gentle awareness of the mind
so wishing as we go through our day
may all beings find some degree of internal ease
may they learn to be with the ups and downs of the mind
and I will walk through the world in that way in order to support that
process for all
may it be so
[Music]
okay so this week we are exploring the
dharma through animal simileies as I mentioned yesterday
and they're designed to kind of move us along uh a path that the mind follows as it
progresses from you know being relatively unprotected to becoming
stronger and wiser same path that we walk as we walk this path of insight
during the insight practices that Gil has been emphasizing in his series
the Buddha often taught via simileies and they're they're very very rich and
they're not they're not only mental they're not meant to just be things that we think about but they can actually be
kind of visceral you know felt in the in the body so that's the invitation perhaps as we
go through the week is to feel how you can connect with what we're talking
about literally in your own body and your own experience so we started yesterday with the quail
and that was about how when we get caught up in the five senses we allow
mara the forces of distraction or difficulty to gain access and bring us
duca suffering stress whereas if we stay mindful which is our ancestral home as
it said in the four foundations of mindfulness that keeps us safe even if
we are in a minds you know relatively weak like the quail let's say
so today
we are moving on to the monkey that's the animal for today and interestingly
there is a nearly identical suta to the one about the quail that features a
monkey instead uh so it's kind of a nice transition and you know we won't read
the whole thing but it um it says the same kind of thing is that there are
places where neither monkeys nor humans can go and then there are places where
monkeys can go but not humans those are places that are safe for them and then there are places where both monkeys and
humans can go and there monkeys can get trapped apparently and so um one kind of
trap features a tar pit apparently and the monkey gets caught by grabbing he he
gets stuck in the tar with one paw and then trying to free himself from that he
grabs it with the other paw and then that one gets stuck so then he tries a foot and that gets stuck in the other
foot and finally the mouth and so in a sense um we again have these five right
five things getting stuck the five sense bases and um that happens because the
monkey doesn't realize he's attracted to this apparently there's something sweet in the tar and he doesn't realize that's
what's happening and so continues to stick and stick and stick in more places
and so this is um uh the emphasis is not so much on weakness or vulnerability
ability like the quail but kind of foolishness you know not realizing that
uh the monkey is catching himself so um so in these contexts the monkey
represents in a certain way the forces within us that attract us to what isn't helpful and how we get caught again in
that the quail was portrayed as weak and the monkey is really more portrayed as foolish
uh in allowing allowing himself to do that because monkeys are nominally intelligent right um but maybe not using
their full potential in those cases so there's more to this monkey simile if
we then look to other sutas we start to get a richer sense of what the Buddha is
suggesting here you may have heard the phrase monkey mind um often people use
this term for restlessness in meditation and there are two references to monkeys
as a simile for the mind in the sutas and they fill out this idea kind of nicely
so the first one is the monkey mind of consciousness uh leaping from object to
object and maybe that's kind of the the way we often imagine it it's really it's
not just restlessness there's a little bit more to it so this this foundation
of the foundation of restlessness as well as of things like desire and aversion the ways where the mind tends
to go off of staying calmly in the present moment the foundation is
discontent of not being okay with just this moment of needing to seek something
else and then going from thing to thing like a monkey swinging through the forest i have I feel like we can all
understand this image pretty well from our own mind so I wanted to say a little
bit about the actual teaching where it comes from um the monkey mind suta is in the samuta
nikaya and it says that it starts out saying that uh somebody might not have
any problem letting go of the body the idea of the body as a self um but it's
very difficult to let go of the mind or the intellect or consciousness buddha
uses all three terms and then now I'll quote from the suta uh why can't they
let go of that for what reason because for a long time this has been held to by
that person appropriated and grasped thus this is mine this I am this is
myself therefore the uninstructed person is unable to experience disenchantment
toward the mind unable to become dispassionate toward it and liberated from it
it would be better for such a person to take as the self the body composed of
the four great elements rather than the mind why is that because this body is
seen standing for 1 year 2 years 3 4 5 or 10 20 30 40 or 50 years even 100
years or longer but that which is called mind or mentality or consciousness
arises as one thing and ceases as another by day and by night and then
here's the image just as a monkey roaming through a forest grabs hold of
one branch lets that go and grabs another then lets that go and grabs
still another so too that which is called mind or consciousness arises as
one thing and ceases as another by day and by night
and then the teaching goes on to say that we can observe uh dependent arising we can observe that the the mind too is
impersonal and should not be identified with uh as a self because the way it
flow is is actually just conditioned it's not really about me and mine it's
that one thought triggers an association and that brings on an emotion and then
that emotion triggers a body sensation and then the body sensation is unpleasant and so we have another
thought about the unpleasantness of that etc etc etc there's this flow to the
mind the Buddha isn't really saying we should identify with the body as itself but he's saying it makes more sense
right the body is a little bit more stable more constant in some way than
the mind which is continually continually changing so now we're getting into more detail than we had
with the quail so monkey mind is not just a criticism of restlessness or
anxiety or you know mental movement it's actually an invitation to investigate
how the mind moves from one state to another continually the mind is leaping
about but it's not doing so randomly there's a flow of conditions and when we
see that it helps us not to not identify so much with the stream of thoughts or
emotions and that is the way to really let go of all that restlessness doesn't
mean it goes away necessarily but it allows us even in that moment just of
observing it we're stepping back from it and instead of being right in that
swinging monkey from branch to branch we step back and say "Wow look at all that
restlessness look at all that proliferation of thought." There's a dharmapata verse that says
people delight in proliferation of thought but Buddhas are free of proliferation so that's one of the
qualities of the Buddha is the mind doesn't go off and we start by just
stepping back and being able to see wow look at my mind going crazy at this
moment or really getting caught up it's fascinating to just watch that and have
you know have have some some ability to be aware of it and then the second monkey simile I said
there were two is also worth talking about it's along the same idea as this
momentto- moment flow of monkey mind but it's on a longer time scale so in a
different suta the Buddha comments on some practitioner's tendency to move
around from teacher to teacher from technique to technique from tradition to
tradition never settling in on one practice and really going deep so in
this case he says having let go of the last they lay hold of the next and the
implication there is the teacher having let go of the last teacher they lay hold of the next teacher following impulse
they don't get past the snare they grab on and let go like a monkey grabbing and
releasing a branch so it's this is a verse so it's a little
bit more poetic than the pros I was reading before but in this text the
Buddha is pointing out that there are people who engage in spiritual practice by looking externally this teacher's got
it no this teacher's got it oh no i'm not with them anymore or this practice oh this is it i finally found it no and
then 3 weeks later oh I'm on to the next practice um people are kind of looking
for a particular experience or a philosophy from the outside that they can hold on to and claim that now I've
got it now this is success now now my mind will is pure something like that
there's some idea or ideal that they're looking for and if if that's the
attitude in how we're seeking teachings and practices we're bound to be disappointed
and so hence uh the person goes and seeks the next thing the next thing like the monkey swinging on it's the same
idea can you see that it's the same idea as the mind in moment to moment like in
meditation thinking this thought then that thought this emotion getting caught up in this it's just on a longer time
scale so there's a way in which the Buddha says just look at this tendency that we
have to not be willing to be with one thing not be willing to just stay in the
present um so but instead to be able to watch oh why is the mind moving from
this to this to this is there something underneath where it's a little bit discontent
looking for an ideal looking for an experience this isn't it it must be somewhere else
so my my addition to the monkey simile I think you get the the idea now of what
this represents is that monkeys have large brains and a lot of potential capability but they don't always use it
well they have this slight foolishness sometimes about how it gets directed and
there are ways where that may be happening for us too we have great potential in our human mind but to open
this up we have to learn somehow to navigate our hindrances um the
hindrances can be seen as ways that we hold ourselves back that we don't use our full potential and so we have this
very humble training of just watching the very first step is to be able to see
ah this is what the mind is doing flowing from this to this to this there's a discontentment there's a
grabbing there's a pushing away and daily life mindfulness having some continuity throughout the whole day
really helps us develop that even further than what we do in meditation so mindfulness practice is not always um
all that glamorous but it um it is something that we can stay with and if
we stay with it it continually goes deeper and deeper we don't need a lot of different techniques back to the four
foundations of mindfulness and continuing to stay with that looking inward looking inward continuing to
watch the flow of the mind we'll start to see the patterns and be able to
settle down and just see how the mind works and be content with uh the flow of
life as it is things do change by themselves we don't need to continually
keep seeking them so some of our early insights to tie into the insight theme
are insights into the hindrances and our tend tendencies toward certain kinds of
thought patterns and emotions not always fun to see that but really great um
self-nowledge is rarely good news is sometimes said but it's also said that when we are willing to see uh those we
can have a real sense of sorry if there's some background noise distortion in the zoom because of that um when
we're really able to see that then we're doing the practice you know then we're starting to settle out of the hindrances
and settle in to the four foundations of mindfulness our protection and our place
of refuge so the monkey as a a way an invitation to investigate and
see the flow of the mind then we'll move on to another animal tomorrow as we
continue our journey through insight thank you so much