okay nice to see the new year wishes shall we uh go ahead and get
started with what we all do together it's new year but what we share is this
meditation practice so I feel like we should just
jump right in and we'll talk afterwards so as you're
arriving please uh find a posture where you'll be comfortable for
a little while and settle in so that we can start off this year with some really good
energy among ourselves and sending out into this world that needs it so
much if you're comfortable doing so I invite you to close your
eyes allow your attention to come
inward settle ing back from the screen finding a balanced and
upright or if you're lying down a straight back
posture maybe really sensing your feeling of
presence almost rootedness like where your body is placed your seat on the
chair or the
cushion having a sense of groundedness of stability
connection to the room that you're in or the place that you're
in just being here
and then from that place of clear presence softening softening the
face softening the
shoulders the [Music] arms down through the Torso and the
belly softening even in the legs and the
feet so inviting a sense of clarity and presence that is at ease
in some way
and then inviting ease also in the mind so letting the mind be at
rest be okay with the condition of the
body with the conditions of the environment maybe it's chilly maybe
there's some
sound but it's okay we're
here so you may notice that it took a little bit of energy or effort to orient
the Mind collect it bring it here maybe still some effort is needed to
be stable or willing to be
present but as you find your
balance maybe tuning into the breath or
sounds Sensations in the body some simple anchor that can keep you
present maybe it starts to feel like there's a little bit of
momentum maybe you can begin to feel
like it's more like being on a skateboard or a bicycle
and as things get slightly out of balance you just add a little bit you
know you move to the right or the left or you push again on the
skateboard but generally the motion is already happening we just do enough to
rebalance so sit quietly for a few minutes now with this intention of
seeing if we can establish some momentum and then get into a position where what
we're mostly doing is rebalancing the mind
for
for for
the art of learning to rebalance the
mind has to do with noticing in what ways it tends to fall
away from the present moment at this time cuz sometimes that's different
you know on a given day the Mind might be really obsessed with the
future thinking about what's going to happen tomorrow what do I need to
do so then you set up a little check in the mind okay every time I'm thinking
about the future I need to watch when the mind starts going that way and then I'll
bring it back other times the mind is
get concerned with the future but it's more with that pain in my rib cage
today and then we have to watch when the mind starts going in that direction so
it's very situational very attuned to how things are
now so how's your mind right now today
what are its top three ways of being
distracted can we notice those when they just start and rebalance
[Music]
for
if the distractions of the Mind are not seen as
problematic but instead seen as normal opportunities to
rebalance it can be really enjoyable to just Cruise along with the
mind like riding a bike through different kinds of
terrain sometimes we're pedaling harder sometimes not as hard sometimes there's
gravel sometimes it's smooth and it's all just part of the bike
ride for
and as we find that we've gotten the hang of being present with the mind as it's
just starting to drift off
we might have the feeling that we could back off from any
doing any sense that we need to be managing even actively
rebalancing the Mind feels more like a ball rolling downhill or a stream
flowing toward the
ocean you can release some doing and trust that the mind will be
with the unfolding of experience maybe it will still drift off
but somehow it will naturally come back the way a stream may move back and
forth but is always flowing down toward the
ocean so seeing seeing what it's like to let go of some of the doing of
meditation
for for
for
e for
so noticing how is the mind now
has there been an effect [Music] from letting go of some of the
management of
it maybe that meant it drifted off a bit more or maybe
not and maybe there was a different feeling in it to not be continually managed
by the cognitive mind there's something of an art to
interacting with the mind how much energy or effort we put
into working with it so to speak so just noticing that there is
that range and there is that effect sensing how it was for you today
in this meditation
and as we are going to be coming out in a couple of
minutes and then after that moving into our lives
that's also a time when sometimes we're very active
in staying present being with the situation actively seeking to shape it
in some way and then there are other times where we're more just letting it
unfold still present but with a very light
touch having some trust in the unfold of it or otherwise sensing
that we don't need to be so active this is also an art
form and it also has an effect on situations when we're trying to manage
them versus not other people too so considering as we go
out May the way that I bring energy into my interactions into my work into the
tasks I do for Others May that energy
be rebalancing may it be helpful
beneficial just the right [Music] amount that things are kept flowing but
not over contr controlled
with the wish that that helps things to go smoothly and helps other people to
feel welcome and connected so that our
presence is a joy and a benefit in the
world and can bring goodness to this world
Okay so Happy New Year to everyone in the way
that we measure time very nice to be joining you with
this outset of 2025 but we're also right in the middle
of our week of talking about uh letting go and cultivation and specifically some of the
Dharma topics that support doing these actions
effectively so we've noted earlier how these are not opposites they're not
opposites but they're actually intertwined letting go in cultivation or intertwined almost like two sides of the
same hand right um and we've also talked about some internal factors that can
help any of them either of them to succeed we talked yesterday about willingness capacity and knowhow as
three important components in in our efforts to let go and to cultivate
So today we're going to look at the topic of wise effort or right effort which is not about right and wrong um
but it's really more about uh Effectiveness or appropriateness of the effort or energy that we bring to our
lives to our endeavors and it's a very important factor this is actually the sixth factor
of the eight-fold path so the Buddha singled it out as an important area for
investigation it's quite integral to both our practice on the cushion and to
our everyday life uh sometimes it's a little bit of a uh I don't know people feel a little bit
down when they hear this topic of effort because it's been associated with other
things in their lives but um hang in there there's some uh interesting sides
to it all along the path actually were accompanied by this issue of effort and
the teachings on it tend to focus on what we're doing and what we're making
an effort to do which fits in perfectly with our topic actually um the
definition of wise effort on the eight-fold path is to let go of and if
possible prevent UNH wholesome mind States and also to cultivate and if
possible to maintain wholesome mind States so it's totally about this uh
theme we have of how can we let go of what's UNH wholesome and cultivate what's
wholesome but an equally important Dimension is how much effort we need to
apply in any given situation and that's a little bit more what I want to focus on
today um in our and I and I there's a a
kind of a a reason for that there's a wide range of efforts that are talked
about in the Buddhist discourses and I hope maybe uh what I say today will
expand the range um in your understanding of how the budha talked about effort or energy in our in our
life so many of us have had introductory meditation instructions you know where
we go and take an introductory course or start working with a group or a teacher
and most often here in the west those instructions will encourage relaxation
ease acceptance words like this um and actually you know we can practice just
with those for a very long time so these are W these are important instructions
to start with often because we're very you know driven or ere efforting in
certain ways and so it's like okay let's just start with ease with acceptance
with being still um and that's good
and yet we also know from our own experience I think that it does take some effort or energy even to accomplish
relaxation right if we sit down and do nothing while we're sitting uh we'll probably think for the whole session and
the mind will become tired or agitated from that thinking is actually pretty
energetic and tiring so we have to put in some kind of well-directed effort in order that the mind can settle
down and find ease so even with that first instruction we find that there's
some subtlety to this issue of effort or energy and we'll need to put in some
kind of effort in order to settle down and experience the deeper benefits of
meditation so when should we ease up and when should we bring in energy and to relate it to this turning
of the New Year how can we apply ourselves appropriately to any change
that we might wish to make in our lives so I hope we can set aside maybe
our associations with this word effort about pushing or striving or what a
teacher told us in school one time to make more effort or something um and
let's try to kind of take a a fresh start on it a fresh start for the for the new
year so what I want to do is walk through several quotes from the
discourse of the Buddha that span a wide range about what he said on effort so
that'll maybe give us the idea first of all that there is a wide range but also that he didn't teach uniformally about
this topic there's a lot of different ways that he did depending on the context depending on the person
depending on the situation so I hope it will spark some reflection and a sense that there's a
need for discernment in this area so um some of what I'll say applies
specifically to sitting practice but some of it also applies to the to the Practical wider world that we live in
and anyway what we do on the cushion of course influences how we act in the rest of our life so we're starting at one end of a
spectrum um so we'll start with the end of applying more effort and a lot of
effort in fact there's probably no way to study the early Buddhist teachings
without hearing that there is a strong EAS emphasis on making effort so the the
qualities and factors of effort and energy um appear in the most lists that
the Buddha um gave So This this term Vira or some similar term uh appears the
most often in the various common lists that he taught and so about the Buddhist own
quest for awakening he made this declaration I want to read
it gladly would I let the flesh and blood in my body dry up leaving just the
skin tendons and bones but if I have not attained what can be reached through
human firmness human persistence human striving there will be no relaxing of my
persistence from this heedfulness of Mind was attained Awakening from this
heedfulness of mind was attained the unexcelled freedom from bondage okay so that's quite powerful
language um maybe at the top level we could say that the instruction to relax
and accept Everything Is Not the Only instruction um but of course this degree
of striving that the Buddhist talking about here is quite extreme and you know
we wouldn't do that on an ordinary everyday basis but but you may recall
that there maybe you've encountered times in practice where there were very strong physical Sensations or very
strong emotions coming and we did have to bring forth a pretty strong effort of
attention in order to meet them mindfully maybe we weren't able to in that moment but I can think of times
where I had just enough capacity that I could I could with maximum effort meet
what was arising that was pretty strong and powerful and that felt really good you know it actually felt like yeah I've
got some strength of attention here and I'm just going to be with this and it's like oh and you feel the the power of
that and the way that it slowly transforms what's there uh or we can it
can be the other way we could be caught by a powerful wave of sleepiness or toror and the mind is really fading and
there's a sense of no I'm I really want to stay awake I really want to stay present I had a time on a retreat where
I was falling asleep every day after lunch it's fairly common but for some reason
on that Retreat I was very determined that I wasn't going to fall asleep and so I stood up uh during about halfway
through each of the after lunch meditations I stood up and I felt very
tired it was took effort actually to bother to move my body to stand up but I
felt like that was what I wanted to do really wanted to stay awake so there are
times where we bring for forth a fair amount of effort and it feels good feels right for that
moment so that's one end of the spectrum it is there in the teachings and then there's also a broad
middle range where the Buddha talks about balanced effort and many of you
may have heard a suta called the Sona suta where he's teaching a monk named Sona and um poor Sona had been doing
such vigorous walking meditation that his feet were bleeding he' walked and walked and walked and
walked cuz that's what he thought practice was about and his he cut his feet on the ground and um the Buddha
teaches him that it's about uh tuning his effort like one would tune a musical
instrument cuz Sona had been a musician before you know he said if the strings are too taut can you play your
instrument and Sona says oh no I can't it sounds terrible says well and if the strings are too loose can you play it no
that also doesn't work so the Buddha says right we have to tune our efforts so that our mind will be in tune and
playable like an instrument and so then we have to put in the right amount of persistence not too
much but not too slack and then of course Zona finds that balance and and
finds Awakening so there is that um there is that need for balance and then another
image he gives for the balance is a Goldsmith or to purify gold so from time
to time he blows on the fire so that it revs up sometimes he sprinkles water on
the fire so it cools down and sometimes he it looks fine and so he just watches
the gold purifying and it's the same way with our mind that's what I was encouraging in the meditation is to kind
of watch how the mind goes off and do what needs to be done to rebalance it so
there are a lot of teachings also about balanced effort so that message is more like the effort
is not formulaic or uniform we need to apply sometimes more sometimes less
always looking toward the balance point but then there is yet another
farther out on the Spectrum the other end of the spectrum sometimes it's appropriate to
apply no effort at all that any effort would be uh disrupt dtive to the
practice so I want to read a very interesting verse from one
discourse the Buddha says one Insight is that effort is the
basis of all suffering the other Insight is that by the complete Cooling and
cessation of effort no more suffering is produced every form of suffering grows
out of effort eradicate effort and no more suffering is produced
wow right obviously that's not a general instruction and it's in a specific context that he says that um this word
that's being translated as effort um pbod translates as instigation it refers
to the kind of inception of energy the movement toward doing something and this
word that is translated here as suffering is of course Dua but duka can also just mean stress so we could say
one Insight is that uh moving toward doing something creates
stress and by we by the complete sensation of the movement toward doing
anything no stress will be produced right so there are times in
practice not all the time but times where things are flowing along so
smoothly or in meditation the mind gets so still that any movement creates a
little bit of tension any effort to do anything introduces a little bit of
strain a little bit of duka and so in that case the mind will actually let go of intention itself which is a very deep
kind of surrender so maybe we've come full circle and relax and accept is actually
the deepest instruction as well as the initial top level
instruction so the teachings on effort span this
amazing r right from unremitting striving human
striving such that Awakening can be achieved through balancing our effort
all the way through don't do anything if you do anything it's going to disrupt this flow this perfect smooth
balance so there's a need for wisdom then in how we apply effort and how much
particularly so I hope this maybe is an inspiration to
um being inspired to really tune in and listen to our own mind and body at a
given moment we have to look all the time where are we at what's going on
with me and with the surroundings how much effort is needed how much energy should I put forth to be present or to
change what's happening or to redirect my mind well maybe I don't need to at
all maybe trying to do all that is just going to mess it up and I should just let things
flow so um this also points us eventually
toward something that points away from our s you know there's sort of less and
less emphasis on personal effort where we need to sort of consciously manage everything and more a sense of intuition
of okay what needs to come forth here or what shouldn't come forth maybe everything's unfolding just as it should
life doesn't necessarily unfold because we are doing it it's actually already unfolding the question is what we're
doing in response to that how we're being with that you're already on the river what are you doing with the ore in
your boat that's the question we're not creating that flow we're being with it
in a certain way so in a sense the fruit of learning balanced effort is
forgetting about effort um it's kind of like when we learn a skill or a craft at
first we are painfully deliberate making sure we do each
movement with our conscious will and then later it flows naturally without we
really having the sense that we're doing it even though we are doing
things so this is not necessarily easy or simple but it is something that comes
about through this um clear seeing of how we are okay so to wrap up um it's
clear that the appropriate amount of effort could be seen as an act of wisdom that's what I've been pointing toward
but as a preview for tomorrow we could also see uh this balanced effort and
this appropriate effort as an act of care love and compassion and kindness
are related to how much effort we're putting forth all of these are behind
acting skillfully so tomorrow we'll talk a little bit more about the uh the
affective side the heart side of our efforts to let go and to cultivate in
the new year so I hope to see you then be well