i guess it helps if I turn the microphone on Good
evening Welcome Welcome Nice to see you
all So I'm going to start the talk tonight with this uh kind of playful
silly whimsical poem and uh unpack it a little bit
because it actually allows us to point to a few like classical
teachings And I'm wondering if we can turn down the volume just a tiny bit It
feels just a little bit loud And oh can we make it just be a little bit louder i'm sorry Jim I'm always doing this
right okay Thank you Okay So this poem is called The Cookie
Thief by Valerie Cox The Cookie Thief by Valerie
Cox This poem rhymes which is kind of unusual these days right so here we go A woman is
waiting at the airport one night with several long hours before her flight She
hunted for a book in the airport shop bought a bag of cookies and found a place to
drop She was engrossed in her book but happened to see that the man beside her
as bold as could be grabbed a cookie or two from the bag between which he tried
to ignore to avoid a scene I think I said the wrong a wrong
word here The first one is she was engrossed in her book but happened to see I think I said happy to see happened
to see that the man beside her as bold as can be grabbed a cookie or two from the bag between which she tried to
ignore to avoid a scene She read munch cookies and watched the clock as the
gutsy cookie thief diminished her stalk She was getting more irritated as
the minutes ticked by thinking "If I wasn't so nice I'd black in his
eye With each cookie she took he took one
too." When only one was left she wondered what he'd do With a smile on
his face and a nervous laugh he took the last cookie and broke it in half
He offered her half and he ate the other She snatched it from him and thought "Oh
brother this guy has some nerve and he's also so rude why he didn't even show any
gratitude." She had never known when she had been so gied with relief when her flight was
called She gathered her belongings and headed for the gate refusing to look at that
thieving ingra She boarded the plane and sank in
her seat then sought her book which was almost complete As she reached in her
baggage she gasped with surprise There were her bag of cookies
in front of her eyes If mine are here she moaned with
despair Then the others were his and he tried to
share Too late to apologize she realized with grief that she was the rude one the
angry the thief
this playful poem It's kind of funny right like the
story and uh for me it feels a little bit like it was the night before Christmas when all through that right it
kind of I think it has that similar uh rhyming scheme maybe and uh proity I'm
not sure So here is this uh woman at the airport
and she has a view about what was happening that the person next to her was a thief was didn't show any
gratitude and she was getting irritated and he was rude and ungrateful like all
this stuff about this guy that's sitting next to her I don't know Can you just imagine
what this feels like when you realize oh no But then all that was needed
was one piece of information Just one piece of
information and like completely rethinking everything realizing oh everything that I was so
sure about and created such a big story
about one little piece of information realized everything was
wrong But she was so sure she was getting so irritated about this person
and just like things uh just evaporated as soon as she had this piece
of information And I've had something not exactly the same right i didn't take
cookies related to somebody but maybe there's a way in which we do this Something for me that I've told
this story a few times And now I'm like forgetting the
details but the the gist of the story is you know waiting for somebody We were
supposed to well this has happened to me more than once but waiting at a restaurant
and my friend isn't there And just kind of like the impatience and like making
up this story Oh I can't believe this person doesn't respect me They think they're so important
and how I don't want to be here and how dare they leave me waiting and be late
Like all this story making that's happening when somebody is not you know
meeting me at the time that we had decided to and then only to discover finally when this person does get into
contact with me that there's a reason why they couldn't contact me earlier and it was a perfectly legitimate reason
when they realize oh right of course I probably would have done the same too I would have been late to not be able to
contact you so just you know this for me just recognizing how I was just really
holding on to this particular story and then poof it's just go on with some more
information I'm sure all of us have different versions of this
story So we might say that having this idea this notion this view this belief
about how things are and being pretty confident about it
and then realizing oh no actually it wasn't that way at all This is a word that feels a little um
uncomfortable but it's in the kind of like the Buddhist teachings we use this word
delusion Delusion often just associated with ignorance just not knowing the
whole picture not knowing everything Maybe knowing a little bit of it but uh
not all of it So but also delusion sometimes in the Buddhist teachings also
kind of get expanded to like this lack of attention like just not paying attention to what's happening maybe
being you know busy with thoughts or just simply not paying attention Or
there's also a way in which delusion can be uh understood as
confusion as this uh like what like not really a what's like feeling disoriented
or like what's happening or yeah I'll say delusion and sometimes that's associated with some
bewilderment too And I could imagine if I were this woman at the airport and I
was thought I had some cookies and somebody was taking them I think I would be confused and bewildered and like the
usual social norms aren't uh being uh followed So this idea of uh
delusion sometimes ignorance sometimes just not paying attention sometimes confusion
Those of you who are familiar with this some of the classic Buddhist teachings will recognize or know that uh delusion
is also one of what's sometimes called the three poisons or often um also the
three unh wholesome roots Greed hatred delusion
So everything that's humans do that is unhelpful unskillful
unhealthy comes out of greed hatred or delusion Kind of like the Buddhist
getting down to just three a list of three like from which everything uh everything that's unhelpful arises
So I've talked about the hindrances and the hindrances are like have sensual desire and aversion of them that's
definitely part of uh coming out of greed hatred and delusion But there's a way in which we could say that
everything that's uh not so helpful and uh at one time I kind of got confused
about all these lists Okay there's these and wholesome roots There's hindrances
There's this word clatas There's these uh now I forgot what they're called Oh
there's taints There's like all these lists of all these things that are unhelpful but we could just simplify it
just to these three Come out of greed hatred and delusion And there's this way in which
delusion like we don't know when we're in delusion if we did then we wouldn't be
deluded right so sometimes I um I've given the teaching because I use this
for myself when I was practicing and somehow I would get confused like have
entering into maybe some new meditative states or something that I hadn't experienced before there'd be some
confusion but then there's this recognition just to say oh this is
confusion then there's a moment of clarity and the confusion is dispelled just to say oh This is conf
confusing Is it really a way to kind of help be grounded so there's this way in which when delusion is operating we
don't know what's operating In fact we would say that delusion feels like
truth And in this poem right this person was really convinced that the other
person was the cookie thief But the truth is maybe I mean maybe
there's a a few different ways in which we might uh want to talk about truths
but one is
that most of life is uncertain We like to think that we know
We like to think that we have the truth and that we know the whole picture and all this kind of stuff But there's a few
things we can point to that the part of the Buddhist teachings are that things are always
changing So even if we felt like we understood exactly how something is
maybe it's different in a meaningful way now than how it was Or maybe there's a way in which it's
arising and passing or flickering and it's uh it's uh seen to not be as solid
as we thought it was there's this changing quality and we feel like okay
it's like this oh no wait it's like that or it's like this or there's this way in
which things are uncertain not only maybe do they have this flickering or
unreliable uh quality but things
end right this is also one of the basic truths that uh or the Buddha is pointing
to is some of these uh characteristics of phenomena is that they're changing
and that they end And so they can't be these lasting sources of
happiness Instead they often can cause a certain amount of
uneasiness some way in which it makes us feel
uncomfortable And we don't like uncertainty Humans don't like
uncertainty Probably all living beings don't like uncertainty because there's risk It highlights our vulnerability If
we can't predict precisely what's going to happen next it highlights how you know we might be in danger We can't plan
or assume things in the way that we like to that we want to It makes us feel more
comfortable But the truth is right we don't really know There could be an
earthquake in the next moment right i'm planning to finish this talk you're probably planning to stay here and then
just happily drive home at the end or something like this right we don't know what's going to
happen And so because humans don't like
uncertainty we make things up We just create stuff because information
feels better than just recognizing the the unpredictability or the fact
that we just simply don't know to recognize that we can't control things So we're making it up as we see in this
story and we can also see this in um individuals who are losing their memory
This is well established that they often can't quite figure out like now how did
that get there they don't can't remember exactly that they put it there So they
make up a story about why it's there and they believe it and they're describing to somebody else oh yeah that's there
because I was thirsty so I put the glass I took it out of the dishwasher and put it there But you know maybe they forgot
that uh somebody had returned the glass to them and put it there and they're making a story for it to make
sense I don't blame them I can It's got to be pretty scary if you're losing your
memory and little bits of things are falling apart But you know it's not just only
people who are losing their memory that are making things up We saw in this poem
Rachel had she created this whole persona of this very gracious and
generous person She was thinking he was awful a
terrible person And turns out he was so nice He took the last cookie and and
broke it in half and shared it with her He didn't yell at her he didn't a big
huff and get up and move off of there and or something like this or I don't
know there's all kinds of things that might have happened right so there's this way in which
people often have an idea so I gave an example of losing a
memory and the poem is about trying to explain why somebody's uh taking cookies
from the same bag he's taking cookies from But um this is you know happens so
often This was highlighted for me when I Well maybe I'll just say this Um I've
had a number of conversations where I've seen like people they have this strong belief and they just say "No it's this
way." And then if you poke a little bit at their logic they start coming up with all these ideas that really don't make
any sense but they're just trying to support what they said initially they don't want to back down at all or look
at things differently or admit that what they said wasn't quite right Or maybe
people this is like um well established this idea of uh
confirmation bias too Um when we have this view that we will discard
information that uh seems to contradict it and we will like seek out information
that promotes our favorite view and or just interpret or just simply only
remember little bits of information that support our views
So there's this way in which we navigate this truth of inicha this truth of
impermanence this truth of changeability of phenomena by clinging to
views We cling to views to help us feel better to help us feel more comfortable
about the uncertainty help us feel better about
impermanence And for me I was a little bit fascinated like this poem is uh playful and fun but I was I was
fascinated at the end She didn't stop to ask herself why this person was taking
the co her cookies or did ask him or anything Instead she just immediately
boom made up this big uh story about this uh other person She just made up a
story this person's a cookie thief and maybe it's not said in the poem but
maybe she thought oh he doesn't even deserve to be spoken to or she had this you know this uh righteous indignation
like she know knows what's actually happening and was uh behaving from that
perspective from that view and there's this way in which we are clinging to
views and maybe discarding alternative ones but clinging to our ones
which of course is really encouraged Our media is built on this That whole all
our media probably mainstream media and social media is all about they're
wanting you to have a view They're wanting you to take a side It's all about this for you to set
up an us versus them me versus you thinking
It's a incredible industry People are making lots of money to try to make sure
that you are taking a side I heard this uh from Matthew Bren
some time ago and uh I loved what he said He said when when there's this
conflict why don't we take the side there'll be pressure to take side Are you with me or against me are are you
part of the us are you part of the them why don't we take the side of not
suffering take the side of freedom Take the side of ease instead of us versus
them Can we see oh here's where more suffering is and here's where less suffering is Such a great way to
consider it and to think about it And that might even be a way not might this is often a way that I think about the
four noble truths the truth that there is suffering there's the arising of
suffering there's a sessation of suffering and there's a path leading to this sessation of suffering This could
be like a framework in which we could use instead of us versus them to be saying uh suffering and not suffering
So this way of uh clinging to views is a way that we are navigating uh
impermanence and na but it's there's something implicit in
here that we often don't even recognize
but there's a way in which we're offering often assuming that we have
omniscience that we know everything It's so clear We're the good guys They're the
bad guys You know what we're doing is good What they're doing is bad I'm the
one who knows and you are the one who doesn't know or you know something like this There's this way in which we're
assuming omniscience and kind like batting away other ideas or batting away
other information or not even having any curiosity about anything It's so much
easier just to slap on this label which is completely 100% fabricated Just slap
on this label I'm good Slap on another label to everybody else You're bad It's
not that simple And we all know that We know it's not that
simple But there's this way there's this uncomfortableness sometimes with this uncertainty or there just
uncomfortableness with conflict And so there's this way in which we just
want to take a view And this is another way that delusion gets described is
clinging to views Clinging to views is
delusion It's a come it's a and we could say in the classic Buddhist teachings as
well as that you know clinging as a source of suffering the
source of uh a lot of difficulty and it's amazing the things that we can cling to and it's amazing
the things that we have views about we have views about ourselves and as I've
been pointing to but we also have views about what does it mean to be a self
What does it mean to be um disconnected or isolated or distinct from everything
else and is that really true we have so many of these views
And then this here's another idea from Matthew Brun that I think is really great and that we can see in this
poem is he said that views are
channels into which our greed and hatred
flow Views are channels into which our greed and hatred flow
So we're making up views about all kinds of things just to help us orient to the
our experience help us understand the world But the ones that we hold on to
and cling to are being fueled by greed and or
hatred These words are like terrible words like greed and hatred None of us want to feel like we have greed or
hatred but there are strong words and there's a way you know just like I need
more or get that away from me You know these are the few different uh ways we
might understand uh greed and hatred And this is what's uh fueling our views And
we might say that clinging to views is delusion So here we are these root defilements
So how can we work with delusion by definition we don't see it when we're uh
in the midst of it when we're lost in it One is just like in this poem it's by
meeting other people If I there it's like reflected back to us you know our thoughts and our
views Sometimes we have some ideas and uh if we don't share our ideas it can they can get a little weird you know if
they're not like uh shown some daylight and shared with others I know this has happened to me
many times but um and it's happened you know when people like accusing me or I remember
this was some years ago I won't say the details but uh somebody saying dad I
can't believe you did that because of x y and z and I'm like Wow that's very
creative that you came up with X Y and Z It was actually had to do with this some
you know completely different I'm sure all of us have had this where like people made assumptions
about our actions and project onto us things or and we're doing this to other people all the time
So one way to work with delusion is be not only to meet other people talk share
some of our views meet other situations but here's the second that part of that
is being willing to learn Being willing to learn from
others being willing to learn from our experiences Of
course be willing like when we get some new piece of information like a bag of cookies and are when we're on the plane
and to rethink like oh yeah I'm actually the cookie
thief And then just to maybe like well how did I um not notice that and for me
it's noteworthy that in this poem she's reading a book while she's just like
grabbing cookies So she's not paying attention at all
disconnected from her bodily experience and lost in some other fantasy or
whatever the book is about We don't know And this is often when the delusion is
happening is right when we're not paying attention to what's our experience And
we could point to specifically our bodily experience There's a way in which um
when we're lost in thoughts which views are that um you know we can talk
ourselves into and out of just about anything and everything like why it's a
good idea to eat so many cookies while waiting for the plate for example or
something There's a a way in which if we're disconnected from our bodily experience
then our thoughts they can just run rampant and create the whole stories and
fabricate whole entire worlds right that have completely disconnected from what's actually
happening here But there's this way if we can feel into our bodily experience that
maybe she could have felt the irritation and the discomfort and really
like wow this is actually really uncomfortable that this person is taking my
cookies and maybe just address him with kindness Uh or you know or maybe
officially offer him so he no longer has to be a thief and then he re or you know like would you like some cookies these
are my favorite I I guess you like them too Or you know or maybe it was been an opportunity to connect with this person
and they could have had a funny laugh together and they could have been embarrassed together like "Oh my gosh I
can't believe this happened This is what a story Oh I'm so sorry Let me buy you
some more cookies or maybe can I buy you a coffee to go with your cookie?" And you know maybe they would have had fun
to you like connect while they're waiting for the plane I don't know Right That was a whole story I just made up
But there's this way in which to work with delusion is to be maybe with our bodily experience If she had noticed the
irritation and but was still like you know connected to the chair or the cushion she could have turned to him and
said something different So this is another way to work with delusion
I was I'm I think maybe I'm going to stop here This
idea about delusion and
views this poem Maybe I'll read this poem
again There's this I don't know I was touched by this
idea that um maybe part of the reason why this poem is uh funny and uh playful
is maybe we can recognize ourselves in our in it or maybe we could feel this
internal horror like that she can't apologize or maybe we've had some of this experience too like we did
something that turned out to uh we thought it was one way and turned out to be completely
different The Cookie Thief by Valerie Cox A woman was waiting at the airport
one night with several long hours before her flight She hunted for a book in the
airport shop bought a bag of cookies and found a place to drop She was engrossed
in her book but happened to see that the man beside her as bold as could be
grabbed a cookie or two from the bag between which she tried to ignore to
avoid a scene She read munched cookies and watched the clock as the gutsy cookie
thief diminished her stalk She was getting more irritated as the minutes
tick by thinking "If I wasn't so nice I'd blacken his eye
With each cookie she took he took one too When only one was left she wondered
what he'd do With a smile on his face and a nervous laugh he took the last
cookie and broke it in half He offered her
half and he ate the other He offered her half and he ate the
other She snatched it from him and thought "Oh brother this guy has some
nerve and he's also so rude Why he didn't even show any gratitude." She had never known when she
had been so gied with relief when her flight was called She gathered her
belongings and headed for the gate refusing to look at that thieving ingrate
She boarded the plane and sank in her seat then sat her book which was almost complete As she reached in her baggage
she gasped with surprise "There were her bag of cookies in front of her
eyes If mine are here," she moaned with despair "Then the others were his and he
tried to share Too late to apologize she realized with grief that she was the rude one the
ingra the thief It's fun right to hear this poem
again when you know how it's going to end These little uh these little uh foreshadowings that gets kind of dropped
in there that you can interpret So just an encouragement So often we are holding on to our views and
I've gotten this uh from Gil a number of times I think uh as a demonstration so
often we're like holding on to the these views That thief he's taking my
cookies But of course we need views because things are impermanent and we need to know how to navigate the world
And so you may ask well Diana what do you do you hold views like this with an
open hand This is completely different than
like this and maybe even shaking it Right just holding views with open hand
This willing to learn something new from what we encounter from what our body is
telling us from situations that we experience And then you know the views
can change and morph when we're not holding on to them so quickly
So with that I'll end and open it up to see if there are some questions or
comments Thank
you Thinking about um making up stories I was
uh with this five-year-old that I'm very close to I volunteer with her anyway And
she I forget what story she made up but about this person that she'd seen or
interacted with and it was so you know it's so easy to give advice versus to see it in
yourself So you know I'm going "Oh sweetie we don't know anything about that person or how their day was or you
know trying to encourage her to be more open-minded and and uh and that kind of
triggered me to to think about uh stories I make up even just little
little ones and how uh you know prejudices
that uh you know just maybe little ones with strangers Oh look at that person I
don't know whatever story I make up So I like I like the continued idea of of oh
that's just a story I made up Okay maybe I can just you know Yeah let that let
that go Yeah that's I find myself sometimes using this when I'm like in my uh when
I'm talking to somebody Well here's a story that I have that it's due to blah blah blah But you know just even saying
here's a story that I have just lets people know this is my current thinking It might be different later And maybe
I'll also offer that um what comes to mind of years ago
So before I really had to practice but I was um feeling like you know I had been
wronged about somebody had treated me poorly and I had made up this whole story about it
and all this kind of stuff and uh um and my friend she said well let's make up
other stories with the same facts Okay so all we know is X Y and Z And I'm like
no this is what happened you know this person really did it because of blah blah blah you know all this stuff that I
didn't know but that was such a great thing And then we had fun like let's make up all these different stories that
would account for the exact same facts And so that's useful for me to keep in mind And maybe it could be fun for
children too to like oh let's make up all kinds of story The UFOs came and
they uni unicorns uh touched this person and they did I don't know We could make
up anything So it's funny to me that I can with a
lot of behavior I can see it more clearly in other people you know kind of
judgmental or whatever that and then I go oh yeah I do that too wow
thank you Lena that's exactly right and that's part of the I would say the characteristic of views when they're
other we see them in other people they think idiosyncratic irre rational a little bit odd but
ours perfectly logical reasonable appropriate Yeah it's
funny Thank you very much for the talk Um I'm thinking about what you said
about if if she could drop into her experience that it might help shift her
views and wondering if you can just say some more about that I'm curious Yeah So
for example the agitation maybe she could have felt like some of the tightness maybe in the chest and the
shoulders going up and grinding the jaw in this kind of way like you know the kind of like this this little bit of
anger And then she could have realized oh yeah okay this is actually kind of
odd and irritating that somebody's taking my cookies and then could have maybe done something that maybe spoken
to him But there's this way in which we're so disconnected from our bodily experience We're just running with the
stories and never there's nothing to consider that we should do anything
except believe them Is is is that helpful yeah it's
it's reminds me of like the concept of being grounded Yes When we're in our bodies then we um are more grounded and
that that helps our balanced thinking Yes Yes Perfect Yep
Okay I think it's kind of this kind of related to the last question Um a part
that I wasn't um sure I was getting was in the talk uh you mentioned like we
make views from uh or they're channeled through uh
hatred or greed um is the thought that like
uh probably by being more in tune with our bodies like looking for places where there's greed or hatred and that will
uncover some of the some of these views that are most likely wrong Um is that
kind of the process or maybe I'm misinterpreting the No [Music]
Um so we have to make views in order to orient ourselves in
the you know to help understand things right because we're not omnisient So we we make
views and the ones that we make like which ones do we choose to make are come
out of we would say some of this our greed and hatred our conditioning but
the ones that we um the ones that are causing problems are the ones that we're really holding on to and I would say
greed and hatred um support the the clinging of the view as well as the
content of the view and the the content of the
view may have some may the greed and hatred may be minor but it's the real
clinging that and so it's where the real delusion and the suffering is views I
mean we have to make views because we don't know everything I don't know is this helpful what I'm saying it is yeah
um I think uh part of it it's hard to live without views So I don't want to throw entirely Um but uh the idea of the
content and the clinging I think I need to be able to separate those Um I was
thinking a lot more about the content and how to unpack wrong views and um but
maybe clinging is also a signal Um yeah Yeah Thank you and thank you for
giving me the opportunity to highlight that distinction It's the clinging to views and you know the views when we're
making up stories they are going to you know be a reflection of
our our inner life our conditioning our biases and those are they coming from
they're they're colored by greed and hatred and delusion
Well thank you It's a really good story Um the other thing that I noticed about
this poem is that we try to live with the problem rather than address it Oh
properly because she doesn't want to make a scene So she's uncomfortable with
conflict whereas the conflict could be dealt with in a gentle way rather than
making a scene Yes I think she just didn't want to deal with the issue which
we do We just put up with the neighbors whatever or our co-workers whatever
instead of addressing the issue So we we suffer we choose to suffer Yeah Yeah
Right This uh con like not wanting to have conflict and the things that uh we tolerate when we actually would be
better to just address Yeah Yeah Yeah Yeah thank you for highlighting that Hi
how's it going good Um I just want to say Jim did a great job uh last week while you're away Oh great Y
Thank you Jim Oh great Great I I was teaching a
retreat I I knew it would be in good hands
Any other comments or questions before we close for the evening
okay So I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening and safe travels home Thank
you Thank you