good evening welcome welcome
so tonight I'd like to continue on this series I've been doing on this whole
idea of crossing the flood so there's a
this is a metaphor that shows up in a number of different places uh in the sutas over and over again and the
general idea is that we find ourselves what we call like the near shore just
here wherever we are and then there seems we come up against
what seems like a flood of water you know just something that's like feels
overwhelming or just sets us off balance or too much
something that we feel like oh my gosh how do I get to the other died
there's so many things in life right life brings us that it's maybe not so uncommon or unusual or to have at least
once if not more in a person's life like "Wow I don't know how I'm going to do
this." And in the way that this metaphor goes
is we're sitting on the nearshore see the flood and on the other side is
the far shore that which you know for different people means different things but in general we
could say that's where peace and ease and freedom
lasting happiness this type of thing and so there's the question well how do
I cross the flood how do I get over to the far shore to
the other side and the as I said in the polycanon this
the Buddha gets asked this a number of times like how did you do it how does a
person in general do it how do we get across uh the flood
and one translation from one response that I really like it has a little bit of a I don't know it's a poetic feeling
to it the Buddha's response is by not
hurrying and not ting
terrying is not a word that's usually in my vocabulary but I like this it's like
not you know just uh not doawling not stopping or not you know just doing
nothing not hurrying not tearing
so these two extremes we might say and it seems like so often we have uh one
way in which we prefer to meet difficulties like okay I just got to power through or I'm just going to maybe
put my head down and push maybe that's hurrying or maybe hurrying we could say
is a way in which we kind of got disconnected from ourselves and from everything else and uh we're just like
okay I'm just going to do the minimum to get so I can get to the other side of it i know somebody I used to work with that
was like this that uh everything that he did was done really quickly i appreciate
very much and oh wait this isn't quite right and oh
wait now that you did that it doesn't work with this other thing and you know but he he just had this feeling like he
just wanted to get off his plate as soon as uh possible
and not tearing there's this way in which sometimes when we encounter difficulties we feel stuck
and we're just stuck and we don't really do anything
maybe we've put our uh head in the sand a friend of mine
recently said that she was uh describing she said "I just ostriched." And I was
like "What what is that?" took me a while to figure out just put your head in the sand and pretend like it's
nothing's there or whatever the difficulty is uh not to be there or something like this
so these uh two different ways and what's uh interesting for me I think is
interesting is that Buddha isn't saying exactly what he did he's pointing to what he didn't do
these extremes are going too fast or not doing anything and so there's a way in which maybe
there's some room for us to explore for ourselves well what first of all maybe to explore do we have a way in which we
usually are meeting difficulties do we have a way in which we just want to get through it as fast as possible because
it just feels uncomfortable so we'll make decisions or we'll yell out or
blame others or you know something like this just to no longer be experiencing the discomfort
or are we more of one that uh tends to kind of like get stuck so first is maybe
just to ask ourselves is there a way in which we tend one way or the other chances are that's so
and then maybe with that question is to can we lean a little bit more towards
the center it'll be uncomfortable because the usual
way of doing things is the most comfortable way but can we just recognize are the way that we often are
doing things and maybe do something more not on one of the extremes
and so with the Buddha not saying exactly what he did allows us to interpret maybe there's a third way we
have one extreme another extreme and maybe there's a third way and then what might that third way be
i'll offer some ideas here one that occurs to me is to tune into to
be sensitive to what's needed maybe a certain amount of hurrying is needed
sprinkling some hurrying here some tearing there and you know and maybe a
mixture of both or something like this but a third way is to not just follow
our usual habitual patterns but instead become sensitive to what
what would be best here and a willingness to maybe stretch
ourselves what what is this situation what is this experience calling for
what would be uh the most helpful in the big picture in the long term instead of
just our usual way and then there's another way in which we
might interpret the third way is something that's balanced something
in the middle the middle way is we could say is part of the third way i'm not going to talk
about that tonight that's uh that's a whole another topic worthy of its own
dharma talk but is is there a way in which to be balanced and one way we
think about this is with equinimity this equinimity is this uh not being
thrown off not being pushed around but instead to be able to
remain balanced and then we might say well that sounds nice how do we uh be
equinimous how do we practice with equinimity one way is to just reflect on our
experience for example let's just say you came to a
place like IMC and let's just say it happens to be something like a Monday night and kind of like you know the
evening after dinner let's just say that you come here for a meditation session and uh it could be you sit down to
meditate and the mind is really restless but there's chances are if you have been
meditating before you know oh this is just kind of what it's like at the
beginning of a meditation session it's chances are doesn't always happen often
does that things will mellow out that there'll be a little bit more settling and the body will have some a little
more ease a little bit more relaxation but so when you're sitting down and you
realize oh okay I'm feeling a little restless or agitated there's a certain amount of equinimity with that you're
not all of a sudden like oh okay I can't meditate now and just get up and walk out but instead you have this experience
maybe even seeing the bigger picture like Oh yeah okay this is not uncommon
and this is what happens so sometimes when we feel like there's
crossing the flood when we feel like we are coming up against some difficulties whether I was talking about overwhelming
but maybe it's not something overwhelming is there a way that can um help us to see the bigger picture
sometimes seeing the bigger picture means if it's a we find what the difficulty is
is some difficult emotions or some ruminations that we just can't get out of our head and we feel like we're in a
loop about something really uncomfortable or either anticipating a
really uncomfortable situation or rehashing something that happened or trying to figure it out something out
whatever it is sometimes seeing the bigger picture is to recognize oh yeah
okay these are thoughts that are there's a lot of rumination going around but what's happening in the bodily
experience that's kind of like expand the awareness to include the bodily
experience including feeling the feet on the ground if you're seated feeling the
pressure of the chair mat or cushion against the body and there's this way in which getting
embodied and grounded really helps us to see the
a little bit bigger picture because otherwise we're just stuck in the the
rumination the the circling that's happening in the mind
so this is another way to like support equinimity often when we're offbalance
not always but often it's what's happening with the mind so can we expand
to include the bodily experience and this helps us to not necessarily
fall into our preferred hurrying or tearing
so when the Buddha said this to this person or this who asked how did you
cross the flood he said by not hurrying and not tearing and then this uh
individual said "I don't have it in front of me." Something like
"Yeah but how really how did you do it?" And then the Buddha expands it a little
bit and he says "When I terried I sank
when I hurried I got swept away."
I love this at first the first 10 times maybe I've read this I didn't really
occur to me until more recently this idea that Buddha is saying trial and
error he's learning from his mistakes when I tried I sank when I hurried I got
swept away so it's not like it was clear to him exactly what to do how to cross the
flood he was finding his way he was having to be sensitive to what's needed
he was having to figure it out be present for the experience
so in the same way this practice isn't asking us to be perfect it's not uh
asking us to know exactly what to do every moment
instead it's asking us to just meet the moment
as best we can can we be present for what's arising in
our life as best we can and then we have a sense of what to do
next or what direction to head but there's something more about this
idea of uh this trial and error maybe a
little bit like as I was saying earlier for equinimity
is that we have to be willing to as soon
as we encounter some difficulty for example sitting down to meditate and maybe the mind is really restless there
has to be a certain amount of willing to hang in there a little bit trial fail
and error means that the very first time you make a mistake you don't don't just
leave and like okay that didn't work i'm abandoning this i'm not going to try anymore anything like that
it's this willingness to hang in there and try something else
this willingness to be sensitive and to explore okay maybe I tried um really
really being present for this uh experience of the
posture like uh being seated feeling the pressure against the body with the chair or the cushion like really really tuning
into and feeling um that experience but then we find ourselves getting really
tight as we're straining to really stay with that experience
and then instead can we recognize oh maybe there's a way instead of like
going out there and really straining that we can be more receptive
just receive what experiences there are to receive instead of going out there
and probing and trying to really glum on to our experiences can we receive them
this uh I'm doing this with my hands it's it's more of an openness and allowing whatever's to be known or to be
experienced to be known or experienced instead of like straining and pushing
receiving or maybe there's this way that um we
just show up for the practice in whatever way that means for us maybe
it's like you know all I can do right now is sit for five minutes five breaths
five moments but this idea like you know what I'm going to show up as best I can and this
is all I can right now to this way of showing up just for
ourselves for what's happening in whatever way that we can at that at that moment
so this diligence in terms of you know not abandoning ourselves not abandoning
the meeting the difficulty
and then there's this way maybe with this diligence this trial and error of hanging in there maybe this willingness
to just ask what's helpful right now what what's needed right now if we're
allowing it to be known to ourselves for it to arise whether it's uh something
that we want to
sometimes it is helpful to just drop in the question what would be helpful right
now sometimes what it bubbles up and it becomes clear if we're being sensitive
to the moment then we just know but maybe it's sometimes helpful to just drop in what would be helpful right now
and then it's the asking the question more than finding the answer but
sometimes just asking orienting this way can be enormously helpful
helpful to find out what's helpful and then this third thing that we need
like this idea of that when I terried I sank when I hurried I got swept away is
also it requires a certain amount of maybe this uh sadda is this word in poly we
could say that it's uh to have a certain faith a certain confidence
a certain maybe heartfelt uh connection that this
is a way forward whatever whatever way it is that we're approaching the difficulty
i talked about equinimity is like maybe we have this uh we're stuck in our mind
and then I said well maybe we could bring it into the body but then also the heart maybe the heart to pay attention
to the heart like what what feels like heart felt or you know um
to bring some tenderness into what the experience is
to bring some care and compassion and love into this experience
and then the sutas there's another suta quote
when uh somebody asks the Buddha well how does a person cross the flood
and he's no longer speaking about what he did but speak just giving instructions for others
and he says by faith you cross the flood
and by diligence you cross the deluge deluju is also could be like ocean or
sea just a giant expanse of water and this word faith is a sensitive word i
I'm not so comfortable saying it sometimes in this
setting because it can feel like oh just believe and everything will be fine
but is there a way can we have like faith that
everything doesn't have to be figured out right this moment
a certain type of trust a trust that
being present for one's experience that alone is helpful
trust that things change they do change it's not always pleasant but it's also
can work in our favor when we're these difficulties
and then faith also has this heart quality so what is it that uh uplifts the heart
that allows us to have some openness to meet difficulties meet ourselves
maybe with some compassion meet others with compassion
how did you cross the flood by not hurrying and not tearing
and I think I'm going to end there could end a little bit early tonight but I'd
love to hear from you all
do you have some ways in which you meet difficulties some habitual ways some patterned ways
what does a flood feel like for you what does it mean to you to have faith
trust confidence to help cross the flood
what does it mean to have equinimity to have balance
what is a third way between two different extremes
if we can I'd love to hear any comments anybody has about this we can cocreate
the this talk here
one thing that comes to mind for me is to be the eye in the storm so in other
words you know all this stuff is going on around you to you through you
whatever in your life but you're just the eye of the storm you're just like
unchanged by it you have that equinimity on the inside so nothing out there is
pulling you too much this way or that very nice that came to mind for me do you have a a sense what helps you to be
the eye in the storm uh inner stillness so in other words if there's a lot of
noise out there it's not necessarily in there so you can be still even though
there's all that noise nice yeah yeah and we all have this stillness we just
don't always aren't in touch with it or Yeah yeah thank you thank you
anybody else
thanks for the talk um I for me I found it hard uh to work
with the metaphor maybe I just haven't thought about it much but nearshore far shore and um it's both kind of abstract
but then it's trying to be concrete and so uh I kind of thought a lot about the
teachings of impermanence as a way to work through it and specifically the
idea that like oh today we've identified a far shore like we've created a goal
and to think about like why do we think that that's the far shore and if you think back like we probably all had
different far shores and identifying ourselves on a certain nearshore right so depending on the day or season of
life or whatever different far shores aka goals maybe um and so impermanence
kind of helps me and just go oh like it's what I see today nice and like if you adopt a posture where you're like
well that might fade um or the shore I'm on might you know
fade but you know can keep moving and recognize there will probably be another shore or kind of surrounding It nice
doesn't work much i don't know if with an island metaphor no I appreciate that very much the
changing nature of it thank you thank you that's great today's far shore maybe tomorrow is
nearshore or today's nearshore maybe tomorrow is far we don't know right
maybe yeah yeah i love it anybody else
um for me there's a big difference whether the turbulent river is
um occupied by another person and it's a relational situation
or whether it's my own individual uh project or situation
when it's my own I can pace myself and pause and
when it involves other people it's like there's a real force just
yanking me to go forward and to change that tendency
i'm very conscious that that's something I would really like to intend to change that to
have the courage to just be present
and be with it instead of this impulse to
rush in or say something or do something
have you got any uh recommendations for this dilemma
can you tell me do you have a sense of what what's underneath that impulse is is there um
I feel like when it's just me and my own situation I have a certain amount of confidence
and trust but when I look at the other person
faltering and showing me a need or a disturbance
But then again it's different whether I'm wearing a professional hat or it's family for example and as a professional
I could do that because you have like a little discipline you put on every day
but in familial situations that's where it's really tough
and I feel it's really important i'm still sharp enough that I could attempt
this you know it's not too late it's not too late
yeah one thing that when we're seeing others uh struggling let's say and we
want to help them it really brings up acutely
our powerlessness to control others
that's really uncomfortable to feel like oh I care about you i want to help you i
want to support you and we might have a sense of what would be helpful for them but of course you know they're going to
do what they're going to do and we don't like to think of ourselves as wanting to control others but there's this way we
often or just the powerlessness is so uncomfortable of course I don't know if
this is exactly what's happening with you but I just want to highlight that this is
often what's underneath when there's some uh difficulties with when one
person is struggling and the other person really wants to help
yeah I see the power part i definitely see it um
but it's very hard to perceive these delineations when it's happening
you know I it's um it's kind of like when the weather suddenly changes and you realize oh it's going to hail you
know and down it comes and there's no warning um
and so that's the difficulty for me is to
um particularly in very well ingrained habitual familial patterns
that's definitely I think I've heard it mentioned many times in different sort of these are the really tough
tough areas and they're beautiful places to practice because they are tough areas and it's I would say in some ways
meditation practice is fantastic because I mean let's be honest sitting still for
30 minutes is sometimes really uncomfortable like we don't want to and it's just uh building up the capacity to
be with uncomfortableness is absolutely a way forward because just feeling like
yeah wow this uh this doesn't feel good whatever it is and just saying like but
uh having some equinimity seeing the bigger picture like oh yeah okay I've sat through physically difficult or
mentally difficult situations it doesn't matter the particulars of what made it
difficult it's uh really does a tremendous amount for our capacity to be
uncomfortable it's lifech changing in so many ways
yeah and I can kind of hope that the compost process of meditation might loosen it up a bit does that make any
sense to you yeah yeah compost right things get uh changed yeah somehow they
get loosened yeah i'm sure it does yeah thank you you're
welcome you're welcome
maybe right behind you you know when you're talking about the the nearshore in the far shore I was
thinking of another another metaphor I heard years ago which is you know you're
you're in a in a room and you want to figure out a way to get out of the room
you're not I forget what the the motivation is but you can spend a lot of time moving the furniture around and
think that something's going to be different but really the task is to get
outside of the room and you're looking for instructions like how do I do it and
the the metaphor was well there are instructions but they're on the outside of the room
and you know I I what I've always taken away from that is
um it's almost like there's a a narrative and a story that we think will
guide us through but you may not know what that is in the
moment it's only after you've sort of navigated whatever that challenge is
that you say "Oh well this is the story I'm going to tell myself." But again
it's a story it's a narrative um but you don't know what it is when
you're in the middle of the on one side of the river I guess
interest so let's see if I understand so this um the instructions are like the
narrative but we don't know them it's only retrospectively we look back
and we can piece together and knit together a narrative from events that happened yeah or perhaps the guidance
that we were looking for to change our situation but we don't need the guidance
then when we're outside the room right so
that's kind of a cruel thing right that sometimes that like oh now I see yeah
yeah that's an interesting idea the instructions are outside of the room so
maybe maybe that's the metaphor there is to stop looking for instructions instead I'm using this language like be
sensitive to what's needed maybe that stops you don't have instructions so
tune in to what's the next thing to do yeah and it also goes back to what you
were talking about a couple weeks ago that you know you're um
I forget how you described it but you said something like you're in place B and you're trying to get to place A but
the only way you're going to get there is to be completely present here that's
exactly right
thank you thank you
anybody else have something they'd like to share or say
so the instructions reminded me that at one time I was trying to learn to ski
and for years I tried and tried to make nice smooth connected turns and it never
worked and one day an instructor gave me a particular instruction and I skied
down with nice smooth connected turns and I said oh great these are great instructions and it took me a while to
realize is that it had nothing to do or very little to do with the instructions it had a lot more to do with a couple of
years trying trying and failing and more
or less that's what I'm doing here very nice very nice we tend to think like oh
if only I had those instructions years ago dismissing that oh no no no we needed those years of trial and error
and practice yeah yeah yeah great thank you thank you
you know as far as doubt is concerned um
there's a Joseph Goldstein used a phrase which I
loved uh he said uh watch out for doubt masquerading as wisdom
and I loved that because uh in my case especially you know that it'll have the flavor of this is how it really is you
know oh my god maybe it's all maybe you know it has this certain I
know what's what's really happening you know it's got that flavor um but for me if I can catch it it helps
but I could be stewing in doubt for let's say let's say I'm stewing in doubt for 10 minutes and struggling i don't know what's going on after 10 minutes
let's say I catch oh my god this is doubt then I might stew another 10 minutes oh okay doubt i'll work with
doubt i'll work with doubt and after 10 minutes the thought might come oh Joseph Goldstein said that and then it helps
resolve it you know and then I went oh my god wait oh wow okay now I can and he also said like what does doubt feel like
in your body and then I like oh this is what doubt feels like i can stay and stay and then it shifts right but even
with having that tool sometimes having the right thought come seems important i
could still in 20 minutes even though I know this kind of thing helps me if that thought doesn't come that go said this
and it's helping me I can still 20 minutes goes away until that thought comes you know so I struggle with that
part there's all these tools but if it the right thing needs to come at the right time that's right that's right but
the right time you're defining is when you want it yes it's coming at the
perfect right time for it right it doesn't necessarily match your preferences but uh it arises when it
arises yeah you know and when it does it feels
like and when the resolution happens the first thing that happens is I should have thought of this 20 minutes ago you
know that's the first but not hurrying
and not tearing right this idea hurrying like oh that should have been 20 minutes ago
thank you Jay
okay today was a
yeah today was a day that I didn't have a opportunity to prepare a talk and uh I
scribbled some notes here and I said well we'll see what happens
and I don't know it's just lovely that together we I don't know I felt like we created something together
so thank you thank you
if you'd like you're welcome to come up here and talk to me otherwise I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening and safe
travels home thank you