okay welcome uh welcome folks good to be with you
um I fell asleep when I meditated a little while
ago and uh so I it the theme didn't exactly
emerge with a tremendous inspiration but uh we will find our way
no matter what condition our minds are in and
um find your posture
maybe you relax absolutely everything as if you were going to
sleep except the brightness of the
mind and a
luminosity let me see how deeply we can relax everything else
staying tethered to the light of the mind
maybe just being here
together tethered by electrons and
love maybe that's enough to support the brightness of your mind
whatever it feels like needs to be done you need to
do uh just relax that too
they sense all the busyiness and complication of clinging
conniving and strategizing
sense the taxing quality of willfulness
what's left in the wake of letting go
what brightness is not governed by you your
willfulness clinging
we just keep relaxing until we're wide awake
the sense of self is experienced as a kind of knot of tension
deeply can that be relaxed
more safe we feel the
less entranced by uh clinging we
become the more our mind flows out all directions
like a hangail snagging on fabric the
attention snags on
phenomena we keep
relaxing softening
widen Hey
The experience of um being
you is a kind of reiteration
arises ceases but then uh rear arises
again and creates the impression of um continuity
how deep does a nature run
if the self is uh done by
grasping we're invited to become
uh deeply unafraid deeply unattached
see how much of the self melts becomes porous
fluid is enlarged
[Music]
okay it's good to uh good to sit with
you so I remember um long long time ago
uh I was returning from from a retreat and uh was telling a friend about a a a
dissolution experience a kind of prolonged experience of the self um
having no trace whatsoever and kind of uh melting away of of agency and
boundaries and center you know sense of centerlessness everything everything was
the background there's no foreground background is like everything was
background and um it was exquisitly
peaceful and as I'm describing it she's laughing saying this sounds
horrible you know and um when um people describe a kind of
emptiness is descriptions often echo uh some unsettling kind of
psychiatric symptoms and uh de
depersonalization derealization characterized by feeling
kind of uh very detached from one's feelings and experiencing the one's
surroundings and objects and people as um people often say unreal or distant or
artificial or lifeless and yet the person experiencing
that is their their reality testing it remains intact they're
not having um psychotic symptoms
uh but it leads to huge distress and impairment and
uh almost everybody with that has co- co-occurring depression
anxiety conditions and here's nega describing
the uh the positive dimensions of emptiness says whenever there's belief
that things are real desire and hatred spring unendingly
unh wholesome views are entertained from which all disputes come indeed this is
the source of every view without it no defilement can occur thus when dependent
origination is completely understood all views and afflictions vanish
utterly so that sounds good but I've often thought that there might
be some overlap if you were neuroiming a brain on emptiness and a person
experiencing derealization I would imagine there'd be some
overlaps and I I don't want to say that they're the same
experience but the they kind of rhyme a little with
each other and so then the question is what
accounts for the difference between uh nourishing and terrifying dissolution
experiences
uh the researcher uh Aviva Burkovich
Ohana and uh meditation teacher Steven Fuler and some of their
colleagues published a paper that I I just saw yeah I think yesterday and um examining that that
question and it's more complex study I'll post the study in the uh YouTube uh
description um uh and I won't go over all of it but
want to speak to some elements of it so
um as uh as animals like knowing what's going to happen next is of paramount
importance i sort of say that often and um and that um our our brains are
continuously generating and updating models of self
and world and uh these these authors and we we we
start to get more sensitive to that that's what I was alluding to in the SID a little you know that the that kind of
sense of the reiteration of the model that creates it's like happening fast
enough that there's um a sense of
continuity and the uh the authors argue that the basic experience of phenomenal
selfhood phenomenal is in like the subjective experience of self the
experience of feeling like a self this arises as a function of those
modeling processes you know and even the the sense of existing
existing emerges from some of that predictive
processing and we we usually uh consider the
um the sense of self as the cause of things i choose to do this i choose to
do that i did it myself did it but in Buddhist psychology the sense of self is
an effect of things not a cause the
self is uh I might say an effect
of fear an effect of
fear the consequence of
fear and there's no greater fear than
death and death denial um is considered a kind of uh
transdiagnostic construct so across many different forms of psych psychological
distress there's elevations of um death
anxiety and of course anybody with even without any you know elevated psych
psychological distress is likely uh a lot of feeling of course around
death and this um this fear term leads us to associate death with the other not
with self and in a way it can sometimes have the sense of like this subtle
default assumption of
immortality so what what does death um threaten seems to threaten
everything but the very foundation the sense of
self is a target that is put under direct threat
by the prospect of mortality
and Andrea Steven Levine asked the question in the the title of a book who
dies who dies and this sense of self is it's not the
only part but I think it's a part of what makes death so
terrifying and it feels like death pertains to to me the kind of me inside
me it pertains to the seat of subjectivity the center
and in in kind of dissolution experiences that comes
under threat you know the there's a kind of sometimes a fear of non-being the
Buddha described um bavatanha the craving to become
craving to become the kind of perpetuation of meanness or the perpetuation of a
something into the future and dissolution
um is the extinguishing of bhavatanha
and so what the the researchers found um
previously and you know prior study was that the depth of
dissolution was not correlated with bliss or terror so it wasn't like if you
partially melted it's bad it's unpleasant and if you fully fully melt
it it's good what the researchers found was
that higher levels of death anxiety led to more
fearful dissolution experiences derealization
depersonalization um that was negatively valued unpleasant fearful terrifying
anxious and when one's um
relationship with death is deeply unsettled the dissolution experience is
sensed as a kind of attack a mortal attack the sense of self
and so in dharma practice we contemplate
endings mortality groundlessness we place a niche
impermanence at the center of all things and
then dissolution maybe uh doesn't feel like it threatens as
much
there's still
loss but that sense of like the kernel of one's being perishing under the tides
of change and mortality that can
shift and there's still a goodbye but a
different kind of goodbye and Levine writes death
somewhere I think in in a year to live that that book um death is perfectly
safe letting go is um kind of rehearsal dying
concert and
uh don't mistake what I'm saying uh I I
don't I don't think it's my view but I don't think
even enlightenment is a perfect consolation for
death not perfect in other words maybe grief is a
kind of irreducible part of the
universe to my mind it can't be can't be refined
further but the dharma really helps and it helps with
um the most fundamental problem for all
animals and maybe this
um bolsters our courage
In this period of um moral
decrepitude I don't know how I'll be asked to
spend my modest courage but I do know that I'm being
asked to develop it
maybe so okay offer this for your consideration