welcome welcome back to our week of finding the supports that uh enable us
to cultivate samadi so we've been taking just a
little more time for meditation in these mornings and more time in silence and then also uh the opportunity
has been to practice stronger mindfulness throughout the
day and to investigate to discover what things
enhance and what things detract from a feeling of being settled in the practice
an ability to come to some state of
collectedness so we're allowing for not having to
know not having to know when we'll experience anything particular in
practice including sady and not having to know uh not having to push ourselves
in that direction what we're doing is very simply and very steadily coming back
again and again to what we've been doing this week is focusing on the
breathing uh being very attuned being present with the inhalation and the
exhalation and using counting of the breath in the background or in the periphery of awareness to
support keeping the Mind steady keeping the Mind present or bringing the Mind back to
presence the other day I read this brief excerpt from the samadi suta that I'll
read again here wise and mindful you should develop immeasurable
concentration that is concentration based on immeasurable Goodwill
compassion appreciation or equinity so these four
qualities these Brahma vihara support the heart and mind coming
to a place that is set steady settled in coming to uh
Stillness and in cultivating somadi the suta goes on to say that as a
result of samati based on these forms of wholehearted
goodwi when wise and mindful one has developed immeasurable
concentration five realizations arise right within
oneself it goes on to list these five realizations and this morning i' just
like to highlight the first of them um as inspiration an interesting look at
what may arise as we cultivate samade as we do this practice of following the
breath and of perhaps counting in the background so here's the first
realization the realization arises right within oneself that this concentration
is blissful in the present and will result in Bliss in the
future so that's interesting first of all it's a realization so it's something
that will come with the practice we don't need to try to make it happen and in fact if we try to make Bliss happen
that's pretty much a guarantee that it won't happen that kind of striving um or pushing just is
counterintuitive but think about what the word bliss uh canotes for you or what it brings up uh for me it really
feels like kind of a steady glowing form of happiness or a
warmth it's not uh roller coaster ride excitement it's
really quiet and steady
so we can as we meditate we can be available to notice any kind of steady
happiness any kind of warmth that arises with the practice and we can
certainly appreciate the steadiness of of coming back to this again and again I mean it's wonderful that I've seen many
of the same names all week long and seen the same people in the afternoon sitting
that there's a steadiness of coming back to this again and again and sometimes we
can see as this what Gil was calling sweetness as this kind of bliss or kind
of steady warmth of happiness
arises and if that's not what's happening there can be some leap of
faith or trust or confidence that practice has worked so far in the ways
it has worked for you and that what we cultivate ultimately will grow so this
cultivation of samade will take us in the right direction it's going to take us towards freedom from dissatisfaction
stress and suffering we don't have to be so worried about what's AR what's already Arisen or that
we need something to arise the idea perhaps is to enjoy or
relax into what's already here and the way that it serves
Liberation it's important um not to uh fall into treating this practice
as a grim kind of obligation or to get so hardened around it that we're pushing
pushing pushing um but instead to just relax see what kind
of uh qualities are there see when diffic difficulty is there don't shy
away from it meet it and appreciate that it's the mind showing us something
that's important to be healed to be seen
so simply noticing with kindness and appreciation whatever is
here and perhaps noticing a bit more today about what might develop in the
way of steadiness as we do the practice or as the practice does
us so um settling into
meditation and the ways that you know bring you some relaxation some
ease understanding softening around things
that are present and are going to remain in this moment
bringing whatever appreciation is here for getting to do this practice in
this beautiful s of support around the
world of being able to come back again and again
and
grow appreciating whatever peace or calm is already
here even that the body is relatively still
encouraging the mind and heart to come to [Music]
Stillness and perhaps radiating or quietly whispering in the
mind appreciation for yourself for this
practice for all around you including this
s May our hearts and minds and bodies be well as we
cultivate these
practices may we enjoy the freedom from harm that's happening just in these
moments of sitting
together may we be peaceful
may we be free of suffering and appreciate the extent to which some
freedom is already
here for
gradually coming into the breathing to presence with the
breathing as it arises from the
quiet present as it courses through the body
and as it leaves the body following the entire out
breath appreciating the
steadiness the reliability breathing in
and breathing
out if it's helpful to further steady the Mind by counting breaths or half
breaths one to 10 one: one Whatever method works for you in the peripheral
using the counting in the background to
support present awareness in the [Music]
foreground
e
e e
as steadiness develops noticing any peace that's
here appreciating any quiet level of
[Music] Happiness even just the thought of
appreciating the steadiness of following the
breathing allowing it to steadily nourish
you
e
e e
in the last few minutes of the sitting perhaps noticing the steadiness
steadiness of the practice steadiness of the
breathing with some
appreciation perhaps appreciating any pleasantness that came with the comb
and radiating that appreciation to those around
us the steadiness of the presence of others in our
lives and how our well-being is so intimately
interlined may we all be well
our safety our inner and outer freedom from harm is
interl may we all be free from
harm appreciating the ways others look out for our safety as we look out for
theirs
appreciating the way we create peace for one
another appreciating the way we can be more and more free of
suffering and radiate the wish to all beings around us may we all be free of
suffering may we care for one another to that end
[Music]
e
we can offer ourselves a lot of ease and steady calm
happiness in allowing ourselves these periods of time to be
untroubled to let the mind and heart rest
as we turn our attention towards this collected place of
steadiness and actually turn aside from
agitation busyness struggle consciously turning aside to
come to steadiness in this practice and there's such benefit too in
allowing ourselves to hang out with and appreciate any Pleasant feeling any feeling of
happiness it nurtures and reinforces our ability to come to
somadi to enjoy the freedom from
distraction and this learning that we can step aside from what is unhelpful
UNH wholesome unsettling and that's that's very
powerful actually leaning into or learning that we can turn towards what's actually helpful
what's Pleasant uh what's steadying and what brings somebody is a
superpower if you ever watched yourself as you took up a new sport or
skill um perhaps you noticed that tension didn't help so if you learned to
swim and you found that you were fighting or tense you'd learn that you
know you were more likely to thrash or sink or if you uh took up
skiing uh and the first time you fell you struggled mightily to get
up any number of skills that if we are fighting or for tense when we begin we
quickly learn that when we're able to relax it's so much
easier if you think of a hen sitting on her eggs she doesn't sit there and you know
urge the eggs to hurry up and hatch she doesn't fight with the process she
doesn't Peck at the eggs she just shows up day after day hour after hour and
nurtures the eggs with her body warmth we're nurturing this practice and
the steadiness of it in a similar way
so we'll we'll find that the practice will grow as we're able to take pleasure
in it as we're able to find something about it that we appreciate even if it's just a thought at
first today um as we practice again there's this opportunity to strengthen
mindfulness in daily life and perhaps one way today is to notice sources of
steadiness in you and in your life maybe from others noticing with appreciation
friends Partners colleagues who steadily show up who are there no matter how
things are going we very steady um and noticing what's
challenging what leads to a lack of subtleness what leads to upheaval is equally useful what the
things that show up that are tough are Pointers they are little Buddhas showing us the way that we need
to heal that we need to uh encounter ways we've conditioned
unhappiness so uh there's also the invitation to come back for a few
minutes at a time throughout the day to any sense of Stillness come back to the
breathing and to join uh the afternoon 20 minute sitting I'm offering on Zoom
if you'd like uh if you look at the IMC calendar and click on it you'll find the
zoom link and the password but most of all uh enjoying
today's practice enjoying the mindfulness that shows up at points throughout the day enjoying any
increased sense of calm or settledness that you're taking into this day from
this practice thank you so much for your prce practice
together may all beings be free of suffering