so welcome and uh I am
uh sitting here up in the hills above Lake Tahoe in California
where I've been on a vacation for
um almost a week going back hiking in the hills here in the mountains at
fairly high elevation and um this is our last morning here and
uh driving back to the to home in Redwood City and we'll be um
we'll be broadcasting from IMC tomorrow again so um
welcome so this is different than how it usually is
that and so it kind of speaks to the theme I'm still focusing on which is change
and in constancy impermanence and so surprisingly there's a new place
new situation and um and
the central focus that Buddhism has on ana the poly word that's usually
translated as impermanence that more literally means inconstancy
and uh is in the family of words like change buddha has this these three
expressions he uses together in constancy
change becoming different and um
and change has uh three important characteristics
and as we become wiser about impermanence change things becoming different in
constancy it's useful to keep in mind these three aspects
uh one is that um uh change means that something that was
will no longer be another thing it means is uh things that
uh were not happening are now happening so change can be welcome and unwelcome
something that is uh unfortunate can come to an end and we celebrate perhaps
or it's a relief things that are fortunate and wonderful come to an end and we're sad
the ending of one thing means the beginning of something else and the beginning can be unfortunate the
beginning of something that's fortunate and wonderful can happen and
and sometimes there's what's in between that things don't change fast enough or
they change uh too slow but they stay constant for a while
they are that way for a while and so all these ways impermanence is not just a
depressing word it's also makes possible the all the important changes that uh
happen in your life that are useful and important and wonderful
and um not having change sometimes is the unfortunate thing that we need
change in order to grow a child grows with change we grow with
change and so it makes it makes a world of difference in Buddhist practice
whether we situate ourselves in the middle of the change in middle of the
changing world and even though our thoughts and ideas can emphasize that
things aren't changing or some aspects don't change
um there's always change here in the present moment and it's possible in being attuned to
change to find a degree of freedom
a freedom where we don't hold on to anything we don't resist anything
a freedom where we surf or float
with the changes not but not randomly
uh it's not chaos there's a gentle way
appropriate way that we steer the boat the the raft that goes down the river
the river carries a down river but we keep it in the current
we can influence the change that happens we create the conditions for it to be
different so we meditate
and in meditation we learn to situate ourselves in the
change and to understand where the rudder is
that keeps us going in a good direction keeps us flowing
keeps us in the current rather than leaving the river
to be in the land of thoughts and ideas memories and futures
to stay in the river and not get caught in the eddies or the sandbanks
here now and one of those places to find the current is in the breathing
to breathe to breathe
that we be with changing flowing sensations of breathing
so to assume a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
and with your physical body as an antenna
as a sense apparatus sense and feel
the body's experience of breathing
and as you breathe
feel the sensations of change in your torso the movements of your rib cage
the movements of the belly
the movements of the diaphragm
and then in a gentle way that's just right for you
taking some fuller inhales
just a little fuller and a more extended exhale
so that you begin entering into the full physical experience of
breathing as if your whole body is participating
breathing in and breathing out
remember the extended exhale
to relax in your body
to soften
and letting your breathing return to normal
not so much following the breath or watching the breath
but allowing your awareness your sensing your
sensations
to participate participate
in the changing shifting
rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
as you exhale relaxing the thinking mind
softening the thinking mind
quieting your thinking and if you like in the quiet thinking
think the kind of thoughts that keeps you
participating in the changing shifting rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out
very quiet soft thoughts about breathing
that supports a quieting a stilling
entering into
The everchanging sensations of breathing
one breath at a time
and your contribution
is to notice how thinking takes you out of
the flow of breathing
the flow of attention participating with breathing
place yourself in the rhythm of breathing
so that the mind doesn't get fixated on any idea thought judgment
feeling everything's allowed to
move and pass through
with awareness attention
staying in the river of change
as if mindfulness awareness
as a rudder
that you gently move in the river of change
to stay in the flow the flow of breathing in and out
so awareness itself doesn't get fixated anywhere
it flows along like a boat flowing on the surface of a
river
there is an art for you to have awareness awareness
mindfulness participate with breathing
gently flowing along with the breathing
awareness massage by the breathing so awareness stays soft and gentle
relaxed and so the awareness of breathing
allows the breathing to settle and quiet
there can be a very satisfying and healthy way of breathing
that comes with this careful caring attention
to breathing
what keeps us alive
allows us allows us to live with caring attention for what keeps us
alive
as we come to the end of this meditation
just as caring for our breathing
can allow breathing to care for us
so we care for the wider world so it cares for us
and is sitting here in the forests of
Northern California
in the midst of this natural world
for which our human lives depend without which there would be know human
life and may it be that
we use our awareness our attention
our compassion and kindness to care
for what cares for us
as we end this meditation may it be
that our ability to be have a heightened attention to the present
supports us to care for the natural world
that we live in and the natural world that we are within us
may all of life be supported
to move through its natural cycles freely
and caringly may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and I don't have a bell today to ring so I I end this meditation now with bowing
to all of you thank you
so hello everyone and welcome to this continuing series on
insight And uh today is uh the end of my
vacation up in like on the hills of Lake Tahoe
and uh I'm glad to have you along
uh so in this series on insight
uh I've been doing a while now and many talks on the first insight usually in
English called impermanence more literally meaning inconstancy
and um this emphasis on insight can sometimes lead people to believe that
mindfulness or insight meditation is meant to be a form of um uh thinking
thinking about things but in fact the deeper insight that uh is being
developed in insight meditation certainly has a cognitive side to it but
it involves a deep um samadei
a deep subtleness and peacefulness and quiet and focus of the mind
we have um in um and so I'd like to talk a little bit
more about this insight into uh impermanence
before we move into the second insight which is the insight into duka
so um uh the deeper insight into change into
impermanence uh arises when the insight practice
um uh becomes uh co-joined
with samadei so the first part of the year the emphasis the series was on samadei
and I hope those of you who came along with it that you had some feeling for the possibility of a deep quiet focused
silent mind that's a state a state of being of being collected unified in a
quiet peaceful way and they and um this kind of that sense
of samadei this state of unification of settlement of peace
um uh usually get uh gets unified around something like around the breathing
around loving kindness around something that allows everything to settle
and um one of the things that can we can get unified around is unified around the
experience of change especially if that experience of change uh initially is a
very simple one and that is the function of breathing um and to enter into the
current of changing flowing moving sensations the with time the minute
sensations that come into play with one inhale one exhale is a ripple of
sensations that are coming and going and of course we don't have to look for the ripple i want to look for the subtle
sensations but as we are staying more mindful of the changing nature of breathing uh
staying in the present moment with that this allows the mind to get unified
around breathing for deep jic work the in the samadei
gets organized or or around something that's more stable the the the changing
nature of what's happening is less important than the stilling of the mind
for insight practice the stilling of the mind together with the changing nature
of the object of attention in this case the breathing um uh come together in harmony they come
together and work together and so insight begins to the deep
insight uh of insight meditation begins to be come into the forefront when the
mind gets very uh still quiet absorbed unified around
the experience of breathing at least that that's the way I was taught when I was in Burma uh at some
point as we get absorbed into this world of change as we get unified around it it
no longer is limited to the experience of breathing it could open up into the
whole field of changing sensations in our experience and sometimes that opens
up to something that's called choiceless awareness uh where we're not we're not choosing
something like the breathing as the focal point for seeing change but rather
we're just allowing change to show itself to us uh in whatever way that it it shows itself there might be a sound
then a sensation in the body and then a feeling then a thought arises and all
this stuff happens in a way but but not that we're chasing it not what we're following it but rather that we're in
the midst of it uh settling quieting becoming unified
just this what is possible is to um sometimes with
the choices awareness of opening up too quickly to include everything uh some sometimes it's too easy to um limit the
quieting and settling unifying of the mind it's uh sometimes too easy to
mistake kind of a kind of cognitive awareness of everything from the deep
non non uh thinking mode of being and um and so
the idea sometimes people find it very helpful just to stay with the breathing and all the insight that we need to have
for insight meditation can be uh found or can arise from being with a changing
shifting sensation of breathing um and uh so as a as a mindfulness
teacher inside teacher my preference is to encourage people to stay with the
breathing as as long as that's compelling as long as that's an easy place to be and just to flow so because
it works as a great place to develop this unification of samadei so that
samadei and insight are working together hand in hand
some people like to um um well so that's that's my emphasis and
then uh however uh if anything becomes more compelling than the breathing like
say there's a strong sensation in your body elsewhere or a strong feeling or a
strong uh emotion or a strong s a sound outside
then uh in a whether it's a relaxed mind as possible uh fold that into the the
mindfulness the awareness let that become the uh focal point or the
organizing center for this unification so it isn't so much to go out and really
um understand the sound if it's a loud sound it is to take it in that also as a
changing flowing part of the present moment
and then there's a knee pain and you do the same thing with the knee pain uh you
don't you don't start thinking about the knee pain but rather uh that becomes the
place where to stay with the changing flowing sensations getting so the
samadei is arising uh in relationship to change the
relationship to things constantly shifting and moving and becoming different than it is
the um and in the process of doing that uh a meditator might go through similar
uh stages of samadei as we do in pure samadei practice there might be
comparable to going through u the um um
the approach concentration approach somebody and the approaching johnic like
states there's kind of johnic deep absorptive states that go through the
quantum leaps of deep joy deep happiness deep peace contentment to deep
equinimity as it as it works in samati practice it can also happen in insight practice
because the the it's the change the the the flow of inconstancy of impermanence
comeings and goings of things that becomes the the uh resting place for
samadei the home base the grounding place for our experience of being
attentive and um so in this way it isn't that
We're looking for change trying to understand it and with cognitively
evaluate it or cognitively believe in it or focus on it but rather
uh awareness is flowing in it uh unified in it almost as like we're be awareness
is becoming the change uh the changing shifting flow of the present moment so in this regard I like
to sometimes think of um um now as a river the river of now we're always in
that river of now but it's a river because whatever it's in the now is
always shifting and changing and the more we can rest in the river of now the
more we'll see it as a river we'll see it as a constant shifting moving of
sensations thoughts experiences arising and passing
coming and going flowing along uh sometimes only through very minute
little shifts and changes in the texture the quality the tensity of what's going
on but to stay with it in such a soft
settled restful a awareness that the whole psychophysical system that we have
can get settled peaceful quiet settled
into this flow of change until in at some point with deeper insight oh all
there is is change and at some point even it doesn't really matter in deep
inside practice what's changing it just simply that feels so nice for the mind
to be just kind of absorbed um in a samadei state of how much just
the change the flow the current of the river becomes the delight not
necessarily the kind of water we're in or the details of the experience it's just that
things are flowing becomes deeply satisfying partly because it's deeply
freeing it's deeply freeing to uh to uh not have the mind latch on
to anything not to have the mind caught by anything reacting to anything wanting
something judging something but rather having the mind at ease resting flowing
along in this current of the present moment
so thank you very much and um very happy to be able to be here and very grateful
to my friend who allowed u my family come up here for our little vac for our
vacation and uh and I'll be back at IMC tomorrow
morning and I look forward to continue then thank you