hello and
welcome welcome to this
meditation and one of the part of the art of meditation the skills of
meditation is to have an infinite
patience and the closer we get into
samadei the more patient we need to be not patient because it's not going well
but because it becomes more and more important
to simply set the course and
to stay on the course as if you're going to do this
forever you're settling in and less and
less orientation towards accomplishing doing
anything less and less orientation around having desires for something or escape from
something less and less trying to make something happen
this orient this way of practicing is useful all along to a certain degree but
it becomes more and more important the quieter stiller the mind becomes because
the slightest little desire slightest little pushing and wanting um agitates or
interferes with the samadei itself
so to assume a meditation posture
and taking a little bit of time to be careful and
caring about the posture you'll meditate
in almost like like a ritual of arriving here
part of that ritual might be to gently close the
eyes and as they close to have the gaze turn
inward the gaze turn inward as if there's a homecoming here
and gently in a way that feels really nice
for you take some fuller breaths with the
whole torso just enough to feel
like full or satisfied with breathing
in and then a longer than usual exhale slow
steady steadying yourself in your
seat in the place that you're meditating
breathing in relaxing on the
exhale and letting the breathing return to
normal and for a few breaths more let your attention travel around
your body to places of holding or
activation and on the exhale gently
relax it might feel good to pause at the end of the exhale
sometimes the body can relax more in that
pause a pause at the end of the exhale gives you a chance to feel the global
body a bit more and allow more letting go in the body
and then letting the breathing return to
normal and with a normal breath on the inhale
feel the thinking mind feel it if possible with patience
acceptance just to feel it and know it as if you're saying
hello and then on the exhale to relax the thinking
mind
feeling the thinking mind feeling the whole
mind on the inhale and on the
exhale to settle steady the
mind on the
breathing orient the
mind towards the
breathing organizing the mind for the whole mind to
be centered on breathing in and breathing out
as if there's a light from the back of the
mind that directly settles on the breathing
feeling the body's experience of
breathing and feeling it being aware of it in a gentle steadiness
not fixating the mind but a gentle massaging of breathing
in the body awareness with the
breathing a gentle flow and
orientation feeling whatever
sensation feeling there is in
breathing that feels sweet
pleasant enjoyable
it might not be with the sensations of breathing
directly but it might be a feeling of being cozy or at
home around the breathing like the body around breathing is a nest where
breathing settles and moves
and as we enter samadei there might be the kind of
subtle sublime feelings that come with quiet creativity
a kind of cozy feeling of intuition
maybe a kind of subtle sublime feeling of listening to very reassuring
music that [Music] somehow touches us deep inside
breathing in the middle of it all holding the course
steady content to be with a breathing as if
forever in infinite patience
remembering not there's no need anymore for desires or
aversions simply accompanying breathing
And to evoke a little bit of pleasure or joy
delight in this steadiness with breathing you can turn up the corners of
your mouth just
enough to elicit some pleasure
joy lightness
openness to support the
patient accompanying of each breath
there can be something satisfying with sitting meditating
quietly without desires and without diversions
a cozy
patience to accompany breathing
continuously
taking a few moments to
feel deeply within deeply within within whatever
else you normally feel is there something that feels
satisfying that feels sweet or
beautiful that feels cozy or an at homeness
or maybe a sense of ease or peace calm
gently let yourself feel
receive the influence of this deeper sense of
well-being however subtle it might be
and imagine that it has no edges that in some way the
well-being deeper feeling is open wide to the whole world
an open transmission on
which can travel your goodwill out
into the world and may these words represent your
own goodwill your own well-wishing for
others and may you
cherish your capacity for
goodwill may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may we each stay close to the deeper place
within from which good will can flow
may this practice we do help us spread well-wishing
goodwill and friendship out into the world
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to the continuation of this series of talks on
samadei i think we're now on the 40th talk and
um what I hope is that these guided meditations that go along with it and
these talks um more than teaching you techniques
more than teaching you how to do samadei practice it's pointing you to
feeling something meaningful and satisfying
within the normal state that people live in is involves some kind of
tension some kind of stress it might be a low level and it
might not be recognizable by people that they're living with stress and tension because it's become normalized
it's expected it's just how it is to be in the world how it is to be a human
being and the person might have a reference point for something that calls stress or
being tense that's some kind of serious level or quantum leap above their normal
state but still often people live in this normal state and what that means is
that um the thinking that comes from tension also has become normalized also
seems just as this is how what it is to be a human being and uh and we're supposed to do
this or we may even be almost invisible that we're constantly chattering talking
having conversations remembering reviewing
planning and um but to enter into samadei is to drop into some place
that's below any level of tension or stress that we can experience
and in a sense uh we are now in samadei
um dropping below the stress level of our life the tension level sometimes the
stress and tension kind of start continues to be there in the body and heart or someplace but is now moved a
little bit to the periphery because we feel at the center or underneath it all
a place where uh there is no stress there is no tension there is no operating
on clinging desires pushing desires needy desires
that are there without any kind of uh hostile aversion
pushing away wanting it to be different it's it's like we're dropping into a
much more of a na can be a natural state of who we are when there is no tension
when there is no stress at all in the system and um and this gives rise to deep
feelings of satisfaction relief
well-being joy and each person is going to experience this
differently but sometimes it comes along with um the kind of feelings you would
have uh if you were peacefully creative maybe writing poetry or reading
poetry or maybe um you know uh peacefully
quietly involved absorbed in a very simple craft or very simple playing of
music where there's some kind of almost emotional feeling that wells up or is
there that feels susive and spread through the body and um and it isn't that we can so
much make this happen in somebody but um it begins to show itself because it's
there almost it's almost like it's always there is underneath the tension underneath
distress and uh it's kind of like the a uh treasure house within that's waiting
to be opened and it's important not to think that the treasures are too you know
fantastic not not don't important not to look for peak experiences and dramatic
uh you know feelings of samadei but uh it's actually better to have it be be
kind of very deep contentment a deep satisfaction a deep aha this is good to
be here like you've gotten really cozy in bed and now you're safe now it's good
nothing has to happen nothing has more has to be done nothing has to be said
and now this is good and to be able to recognize that uh
so we can move towards it or settle into it in meditation so we can recognize
that this is important this is valuable it's a treasure uh because sometimes the
orientation is so strongly towards safe towards uh thoughts and uh tension
stress that often driven by the desire to be safe because we're afraid the
desire to want something because we feel like uh insufficient in some way or we
just want more pleasure or something um and to have and to no longer be
attracted to that no longer be hooked into it or to to be mesmerized by
desires and aversions um and to settle
quietly into a much more deeper sense of contentment deeper sense of satisfaction
and um at some point because uh uh we start seeing that having any we start
seeing that desire or when we see that desires aversions thoughts are actually
agitating the mind keeping us separated from this deeper place that's satisfying
deeper connection to breathing and the underlying kind of
um peace or this joy or well-being in which breathing
occurs we see that thoughts and desires are agitating it then it's easier to
just let those go let those become quieter kind of let the mind become
stiller and quieter uh let the heart be more settled
um but we might need to see the the that certain kinds of activities of the mind
are not so satisfying or maybe a little bit alienating a little bit uh keeping
us away from something deeper satisfaction so that it's easier just to let it float away there comes a time
when the desire to not have those desires is too much to have and so it's
almost like we just learn to leave it alone we have desires we have aversions
we have thoughts and there comes a time when there's a just feels like the best thing to do is just leave it completely
alone don't be involved it recedes the periphery it's not being reinforced
maybe it floats away maybe it's kind of quietly in the background but in the
foreground is where the action is the action of contentment the actions of
deep satisfaction deep immersion in this lake of
samadei and um and in this space of samadei there can be pleasures there can
be pleasantness there can be joy there can be strong sense of happiness
sometimes people feel rapture in these states and um but the idea is to somehow
be at ease in the middle of them don't push for anything don't try to pump
anything up just try to be at ease and allow make it space allow it to be there
let each thing of these well-being kind of have space breathing room to live the
way it wants to live sometimes these states get stronger sometimes they fade away
um don't have an agenda but be hold it steady and uh and what happens with uh
as we go through this approach stage the steady staying here becomes stronger and
stronger or sometimes it feels almost like we're clicking in and when there's a kind of a shift boom and now we're re
now we've really arrived boy are we ever here now with this experience and it
doesn't feel like there's any movement to get distracted or wander away
sometimes that is a very slow steady movement of like that we slowly um
settle into we don't see sometimes it almost coming until we find ourselves in a state where we're now we're
really here and um and you know there's if there's thoughts it's only thoughts
that are pleasant pleasant nice good thoughts about what's happening in
meditation about the experience here and out that supports us to be with it and
um and very very quiet and and and to some people have the experience we're
locked in to this now sometimes it's just really like there's um um we're at
rest where now we're really rooted here and now and
so the kind of the fruition of this approach stage is
because we're so patient so willing to just stay here and be here for as if forever that the desires to be anywhere
else begin to fall away and um and the familiarity with just staying here with
the breath staying one breath after the other inhale exhale riding the breath
staying with it continuously in an easeful way at some point we're we're rooted
we're there we're we're we're not not going away for a while and
um and then in without exactly desire
um we're allowed to enjoy that and this is where the art of enjoyment is an art
it's the enjoyment enjoy it in a way that helps the minds be
quiet without thoughts with less thoughts calm and um and then just just oh just
stay there and you can feel that having thoughts takes you away from it but
you're allowed to be there in that well-being of deep samadei it's actually
part of what we become rooted in or connected in it supports us to be right there in the
practice so whether you understand what I'm saying now and you any reference
point your own experience or not um I think it's good just to hear these words
hear these descriptions uh so that you can um recognize it or
appreciate it or be inspired by it uh so some characteristics some qualities of
this can um actually be there all along in your practice in your meditation even
times when you are much more restless and filled with thoughts that this is the orientation this is the the
simplicity of it and um and so we'll continue on
Monday and on Monday we're going to start going into uh some of the
characteristics of when the samadei really becomes clear full samadei which
in the our tradition is called Janna and um and I'm not expecting you to be in
Janna but uh some of the qualities characteristics of it are useful to know
even even when you're not in Janna but in the meantime if you have
feel like any kind of ongoingness momentum that's happening from you from this samadei uh series I
would recommend that you be sure to meditate this weekend through the next few days next two days so that there's
some continuity through the next two days that you can pick up with or
continue into Monday when we start again so thank you very much and um I
appreciate your attention your being part of this journey with somebody and
um and I look forward to continuing thank you