so welcome again and
uh what i started to say is that uh this meditation
practice leading to deep insight has more to do uh when
we um what we don't do than what we do
there's a lot of uh uh ways in which we are so actively involved in our minds
and our thoughts that it interferes with the natural capacity for
insight and one of the kind of the core principles almost of buddhism is that we
have a profound natural capacity profound natural abilities that uh we're learning to get
out of the way of and the analogy would be if you were going to go canoe
comfortably down a comfortable safe uh nice
slow narrow river maybe maybe a stream a creek and um and uh so there's a few
things you have to do you have to untie the canoe from the dock
um and you have to release your hand from holding on to the dock and then you have to somehow stay
in the middle you and you don't want to reach out to the side and hold on to a branch coming down uh you want if you
see a sandbar up ahead you want to avoid getting stuck on it so there's a few things we have to do but there's a
natural capacity if we stay in the middle of the river to float and carry
on same way with u this meditation practice uh and the the world of insight is what
opens up when we let go of the dock we untie the rope we allow ourselves to
flow in the river and uh the way that we get grab
onto branches and get caught on sand bars is by thinking a lot and thinking
and living in concepts living in attitudes are what
kind of solidifies or raifies or makes the world solid makes the self solid
solid rather than the self being fluid and moving and constantly shifting and
changing in a free liberated way um through the conceptual world and through
our attachments and our fears and our resistances and our wantings we kind of
solidify and it's hard to see the change we form that big tangle that big knot
where uh experiences sensations direct contact
with the world uh is entangled with our concepts of it entangled with ideas of
self entangled with our attitudes and our desires our aversions and so things get all uh globed
together and so it seems like there's something solid here and permanent and
this is the way it's going to be forever but we let go we untie the rope
from the dock we learn to trust deeply and it's almost like uh it's what
we don't do it's a lot of letting go not because we're letting go into nothing
we're letting go into this natural capacity to flow and to move and to flow
into a really good direction the metaphor of the flowing in the river is used in buddhism
uh to go from small little streamlets and creeks that flow into bigger lakes
into bigger rivers into bigger rivers and finally flows into the big ocean and
so this idea that the flow of impermanence the flow of the changing nature and the river of change um it's
not just that itself is not a static thing uh that if moves on to better and
better but the cost in a sense of doing this is is is to let go is to let go
untie from the dock of concepts and ideas of past and present and also to
untie ourselves from or let go of holding on to the branches of self the
branches of ideas and philosophies and and of self that we might be carrying
along so it's a lot about not doing and when we don't do we'll feel and see that
the river is flowing will flow with it so the insight are what comes deep
insight comes when we're no longer holding on to
something so to assume a meditation
posture if you get into a canoe you kind of have to be in a good posture of
balance in the middle upright can't be leaning one side to the
other you can't can't sunbathe laying down in the canoe if you want to
stay flowing in the river and tracking what's going on
so to take a good posture and to close your
eyes and without doing anything else as you're sitting as you're in your
meditation posture can you
feel the hum of sensations the vibration of
life can you sense or
observe the way that so much is changing and shifting in you as you just sit here
doing nothing being
still even if you're preoccupied with thoughts the thoughts the images the
words are coming and going and
shifting rather than looking at the content of
thoughts now notice how the details of
thinking belong to a world of change changing words changing sentences changing
images and whatever degree of change you can experience here
now in the middle of it all from deep within begin
a comfortable fuller
inhale and a longer easeful exhale
with whatever sense of ease you can
have easefully take just a bigger fuller
breath that keeps the ease
and a long longer slower
exhale that settles you into an inner
ease and then letting your breathing return to normal
right there in the breathing the body's experience of
breathing you can observe change shifting
you might not see the changing sensations of breathing if you
hold your breath but if you allow the natural
rhythm of breathing there'll be a natural shifting and changing flowing river of
sensations physical sensations associated with breathing
and if you lose touch with that because you're thinking a
lot then those thoughts are going to interfere with
seeing change those thoughts put you in a
world of holding on to a branch still being tied to the
dock relax the thinking mind and settle yourself into the canoe
of your body
where awareness is settled in your body
riding the river of change
all things are changing unless
we get caught up in
thoughts or we get caught in ideas and feeling of
self cross the river of change
when awareness is pulled into the world of
thinking the world of clinging holding
on then the awareness
cannot rest in the river of
change the changing
sensations the changing energies of the present
moment let go and let go so you can rest
float in the river of change
and then as we come to the end of this sitting perhaps relaxing a few moments
into whatever is shifting and changing in your direct experience
not chasing it or looking for it but allowing it
to move through
you allow it to show itself to you
we're opening and relaxing and [Music]
receiving change i i can
highlight how we get out of the river we get stuck in the
river when we get caught in thoughts
and a lot of preoccupation and thoughts clearly separates
us from a deeper
intimacy with a natural process of dharma
unfolding the
river carrying us
along as it grows and flows and opens up to greater and greater happiness and
peace may we appreciate how letting go of
preoccupations and attachments gives room for deeper
healthy process to unfold deeper peace
happiness and may we understand that this works interpersonally
too that we can bring kind and respectful attention to
others where they don't have to react to how we are don't have
to cling or resist or
want may it be that our way of being with
others helps them to relax helps what's the natural capacity
for peace that they have as a chance
to unfold may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you
so hello and welcome to this series on insight the kind of insight that we
emphasize in insight meditation and uh this is the end of the this
week's uh topic that covers the five different areas that we can call that
involve insight that we might define or describe as having insight into
something and the way that it unfolds is that um the way that this week has been
discussed is that um there is
um there is um uh that one way of understanding that
i just got distracted someone came here that uh that the un it unfolds kind of as
process there's an unfolding here just like samadei is an unfolding and this
one of the reasons to give this the whole series on samadei before insight is that we can understand better
appreciate better how the unfolding of insight the deepening of insight is a
form of samadei itself and some of the qualities and characteristics of samadei
come into play as we go along here and uh so the uh the first insight
from monday the personal insight is very valuable to have but from the point of
view of the samadei of insight it's settling personal issues enough that uh
we can give ourselves over to the process of meditation we don't have to be concerned about fixing something or
healing anything in ourselves because now we can kind of settle enough in
ourselves that we can kind of go in into this process and so as we go
deeper the uh uh then into it part of
this uh is to get quiet enough calm enough that we can see the distinction
between appearances and the recognition of them the mental knowing of them the
the uh simple way of saying it is the sense the sense experience we have which
belongs to direct experience and to um the names we have the concepts the
recognition we have for it so we tease those apart for the purpose of being
able to see even more clearly each thing so we don't have everything kind of
lumped together in one big general conceptual way and so then that allows
us to see conditionality and that's invaluable because then we see that it makes a
difference how we are that we do condition ourselves that if we get caught up in thoughts and hostility or
greed that has a effect on us that is not so beneficial if we let go and are
settled and open up more fully there in a kind supportive way that that has a
beneficial effect on us so conditionality helps us to see that how we engage is beneficial and a lot of it
has to do with appreciating how powerful it is meaningful it is to not be caught
not be uh tight around or resisting or uh having attitudes of aversion or
judgments or despair or all kinds of things that are added on top of our
experience and uh and then as we move on further then uh we start seeing uh much
more appreciation of how things are always changing and how uh the idea of
self doesn't have to be so u applied to it projected onto all
our experiences that they all are my experience or or uh they all have some
reference back to me and so there's a beginning to understand an understanding
of uh how changeable things are how things flow and are
impermanent and constant and how it's possible to be in that world without a
lot of uh self-p preoccupation self-consciousness and uh and self
doesn't have to be uh be defining everything in its own terms and that to
do so is unsatisfactory brings more suffering and so as we move along here with
insight um uh at some point we enter into the approach stage that we have
with samadei approaching into janna and um and so as we keep going here there's
a feeling of an onward leading mo movement this is good this is the right place to be and uh and some of the vanic
factors come into play there starts to be some joy and happiness in the mindfulness practice itself and the
clear seeing being there present for experience in this more direct way that
is so direct and so immediate it's much more of a of a of an observation a
seeing a sensing a receiving than sometimes it is when people practice mindfulness where the mindfulness uh
does involve kind of a higher order level of recognition now the recognition or the knowing is
really simple really uh immediate and and not a wider understanding that this
applies to all of life and um and we enter start entering into uh a very direct uh experience
experiential sensing feeling knowing observing of
how all the building blocks of all the concepts building blocks of sensations
that we have that they all um they're all coming and going they're in constant
they're constantly a flow of change of arising and passing and that's a classic
language is we enter into the stage of things just arising and passing and and
and in this stage we've kind of in this approach stage it enters into something
that's something like uh comparable to the first janna in that uh the mind is
not really going to wander off anymore it's not a lot of work to be present to
keep coming back keep coming back now uh it we're in the flow of the samadei
we're in we're in it and you might wander off a little bit but you're coming back
easily coming back easily just here it's like this massage of going away and
coming back and being here and rather than being absorbed in um in a samadei
in a in u like joy or something there might be joy there might be happiness
there might be many of the factors that happen in samadei but it's a very clear
that we're observing that we're present for the shifting and changing nature of the of
reality of reality of our direct experience of it and so now we're
entering into the world of of what classically is called the three characteristics and that is uh the big
emphasis the kind of the the the insight meditation for vipasana the capital i
insight is a deep seeing a deep experiencing a deep direct
sensing of the arising and passing of sensations the rising and passing of
thoughts the rising and passing of everything that we start just to see it comes and goes and comes and goes and
um and uh and so that's the the characteristic of uh all experiences
impermanent the second is that um in all these direct immediate experience of
sensations uh we cannot find a self uh sometimes it's called uh you know the
the characteristic of not self and the third is um duka and that there's uh uh
that there's some profound uh form of suffering of of uh uh
unsatisfactoriness uh in any movement of the mind to hold
on to resist to want anything to do with all these sensations that are moving
through so there's a higher sensitivity now in the modern terravada
it's called the character three characteristics in the time of the buddha these were called the three perceptions or the
three recognitions and um sya and uh these um and that makes a
huge difference because when it started becoming called characteristics then uh the three
characteristics uh there was a tendency to make into a kind of buddhist metaphysics philosophy that now we're
seeing the true characteristics of everything in the universe all things everything in the universe is
impermanent and constant everything is um is
um not self everything is suffering and that kind of univers
universalization of these three characteristics is not useful for deepening the practice and maybe not
even you know it's it's it's going in a different direction than the buddha really wanted us to go if we come back
and understand them as a three perceptions the three characteristics the focus is three three
recognitions the focus is not on the nature of what's out there but rather
the nature of how we perceive it so if i hold this bell and i tell you wow this
bell is impermanent and constant is con constantly shifting and changing and coming and going this bell is not self
this bell is suffering uh you'd probably think i was a little
crazy but uh what's inconstant is that
my perception of the bell turns out that yes the bell is has a certain constancy
but the mental activity of perceiving of recognizing the bell is a sh a shifting
and changing um flow of sand um and um
flow of river the idea that um this u this is my bell that's a mental concept
as well that's a mental perception and recognition seeing that idea of this is
my bell seeing it come and go and it rises out of conditions there's no self
that makes that thought that this is my bell it just thought that arises and so
there's no self in that thought exactly and there's no self that i'm projecting
now onto the bell and then there's the suffering when i say it's my my bell i want this bell i
should have it um so there can be we perceive the suffering in relationship
to it so there's these three very profound ways of perceiving or recognizing the
movements of the mind that take things as being permanent or constant take
things as me myself and mine that take things as um as these this is a source
of happiness if i just hold on to it and cling cling to it and rather than that
there's in this kind of samadei state almost as you go deeper into this almost
johnic state um so remember we're going to a deeper state this is where we start
uh perceiving uh in a deep deep way we observe in a deep way uh it's so
satisfying because we're in this nice state this onward leading state we see
that everything the flow of change the river of change everything that all
perception all sensing all acts of knowing all those
are shifting and changing and moving and coming and going whether or not there's
a bell out here which has some constancy uh that is besides the point uh the
world of freedom belongs to this world of of not making this into a permanent
thing not taking the perception of the mind and and making this mine not
suffering because i want to cling to it and want it um those the mind's
activities are in constant in a certain kind of way the
mind's individual activities is not self there's no self in those activities and
there's um and there's um and it's suffering to cling it's suffering you
can see the suffering of how we relate to it things if we look deeply into the
mind and so these are some but in this this uh uh fifth insight to really have
it as deep inside itself it is a kind of samadei deep samadei where we've cleared
the the veils of perception so that we can really see deeply into the mind and
see what the mind does that it make it projects permanence projects self and in
a kind of certain way not doesn't project but creates suffering in the deep samati then we
start seeing the opposite we see yes it's there's a we're in sensing the
inconstant nature of perception or recognition the inconstant nature
of the the notself nature of perception the not suff the we see that there's
suffering in in how we relate to it and how we can let go and this letting go
this not participating in this deep way allows for a deeper and deeper entering into a deeper deeper
samadei and uh my teacher in burma sometimes called called this vipasana janna
uh in this deeper way and so in understanding appreciating there's samadei here you might understand that
the thinking mind has gotten really quiet and the filters of concepts by
which we see is dropped away so these are the three these are the
five areas which insight becomes into play as we do this mindfulness practice
and uh for the next two weeks i'll be away on retreat and uh and i'll pick
this up again when i come back i think on the 16th of june and um and uh we'll
do a week on each of these three perceptions called three characteristics
in the modern world and um and uh appreciate kind of a deepening process
that that happens with each of these three um perceptions um these three
insights so thank you very much and i look forward to coming back in a couple of weeks