good morning good day everyone and welcome to
our inside meditation sitting
and this is the period of time where
the teachings are about insight the insight of insight meditation one of the
primary ones which is a kind of a deep
um insight into the changing nature of our experience into inconstancy
how things change how things disappear they arise
this is a kind of a universal human source for wisdom and deep understanding
of life and in a way the Buddhist tradition puts particular emphasis on it
that uh that um
uh it has tremendous value for the purposes of liberation of becoming free
and one of the reasons for that is that any ways in which we
interrupt the experience of change any ways in which we freeze our
experience or hold on to it or or raify it solidify it with how we think how we
perceive uh we add tension to our life and that
at first just might be a tension of trying to hold um the river back i mean try to get into
the river and stop the water from flowing is not going to be easy it's going to be frustrating
um and uh it might just be stressful it might end up into a major source of
suffering to be out of harmony out of attunement out of um
uh harmony with the changing nature of momentto-
moment experience and sometimes I think of it as a wind drag that we are uh have a big hands out
something out the window of a car and or something that's a big load on the back
of the car pickup truck and it's causing the wind is slowing the car down
or an anchor or some heavy object hanging over the back of a rowboat that
makes it much harder to row
so to pull in the wind drag to pull up the anchors to
untie the boat so we can flow with the the river
so it's poss but it's possible to know and feel and recognize that we have
stepped out of the river of change and uh and then put ourselves back and
it's as simple as returning to the breathing breathing itself represents
and is uh not only represents but uh can be uh kept at the center of this river
of change so to assume a meditation posture
and the paradox a little bit is that the stiller we are with our bodies the
stiller we are especially with our minds our inner life
the more we're attuned more we feel and experience change
the more we're caught in our thoughts the more busy the mind is
the more the mind tends to manufacture or interpret
that things are a particular way that they don't change
they'll always be this way or they'll never be different
so to sit quietly with a in a meditation posture that allows the
body to be still and quiet
in a way that feels nurturing
feels satisfying
and to gently close the eyes
and with the eyes closed to scan through your body
to see if there's some places where you can soften and relax
tensions of the shoulders
holdings of the belly
Tightness in the face around the lips
the jaw around the eyes
tension is one of those ways in which we all too easily
impute permanence or constancy or
tension all too easily
causes us to be out of touch with the changing nature of experience
and within this posture that you're meditating in
if your body is relatively still then chances are the biggest movement in
your body is a movement of breathing
and the movement of breathing has within it
change the biggest is breathing the change
between breathing in to breathing out between breathing out and breathing in
and the closest place to feel the change is in the sensations of breathing
you might be aware of two or three different sensations in the course of breathing in
sensations in your belly your chest nostrils
some of the sensations change in intensity the brief moments that they're present
and the sensations you're experiencing are also being sensed
there's a certain physical sensitivity that allows us to feel
sensations that allows us to recognize know
the experience in the body of breathing
as you exhale
soften relax the thinking mind
settling your awareness into the sensations of breathing
and have gentle quiet slow thoughts
thinking about the experience of breathing
not in the abstract but gentle thoughts about the direct
experience almost like a gentle instructions
stay there
what is this experience of breathing
let me feel it more carefully
or it might be very quiet words of in as you breathe in
out as you breathe out
it might almost be a nonverbal thinking
that keeps you closely connected
to the sensations of breathing in and breathing out
and as you feel the sensations of breathing see if you can
ride along with how they shift and change
almost like there's a river of change right there in your body as you breathe
the thinking mind quiet letting go of any thoughts except those
which which allow you to stay intimate connected
to the river of sensations
connected to your breathing
and when your mind wanders off in thought
notice how it takes you away from the sensations of change
out of the river
and how the s the thinking contributes to a world of ideas and
memories and plans
that is kind of a holding on kind of a solidifying in thought
that removes us from the changing sensations changing
nature of the present moment
and then notice whatever thoughts reactions
take you out of the river of change
pull you away from the changing nature of sensations direct experience
maybe some thoughts even feel like they solidify around ideas beliefs
plans and memories with a feeling like this is how it is
noticing the difference between staying close to the immediacy of change
moment after moment in your body
versus losing that intimacy to change
being caught up in thoughts
Noticing ways in which you tighten up
grasp hold tight contract around certain thoughts ideas
feelings that take you away
from The flow of changing sensations the river of change that's here and now
in direct experience
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
as you exhale soften the thinking mind
as you exhale
let the thinking mind open wide so the thoughts can empty out of the
mind think thoughts can float away
in favor of an openness and a spaciousness
of a quiet mind
as you exhale
to set your heart at ease
lifting the weight the pressure
the contractions around your heart center
so that the heart center can be softer calmer
and softening the belly
so the belly can be settling offer stability
a foundation for being here and now
and a way then to gaze upon the world kindly
to sit here softly gently and to consider
the world around you
the people in your life and what it's like to not get caught in
thoughts and judgments interpretations desires
but to be open to them in a gentle soft
flowing way wishing them well
so we see them through the lens of appreciation
care kindness instead of the ways in which we've
locked into interpretations and desires and ideas
about others may we through this practice
free people from our projections our interpretations our needs our
desires may we through this practice
offer people freedom from us
may we offer them wishes of well-being and happiness safety and peace
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free at least free
from our attachments our clings
our ways of holding on to how things should be
may we contribute to peace in this world
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this continuing series on the insights of insight
meditation and the topic currently is the First
insight insight into anicha anicha is the poly word often translated
as impermanence but in fact what it means is uh not
constant so inconstancy and the difference between those two
English words is impermanence is often inter interpreted that things will end
that things are not permanent because some point they'll stop being there
uh in constancy in contrast means that things are constantly changing they come
and they go that um uh days are not going to stop but uh individual days
stop and then the day comes back daytime comes and goes meals come and go
breathing comes and goes sleep comes and goes
all kinds of things in our life come and go and come and go and come and go breathing comes and goes comes and goes
comes and goes the heart beats uh ongoingly but each beat is an unc un
inconstant sensation in constant event a beat and it stops a beat and it stops
so it turns out that um if we don't imputee permanence if we don't get
caught up in our thoughts and ideas and have ideas this is how it's always going
to be this is how it is if we don't live in that world of concepts and ideas that
um it's much easier to experience how the present moment is always changing
always in constant and this fascinating difference between
the world of conception the world of ideas the world of plans the world of
stories um is that versus the world of direct
experience um is the difference between
um uh flowing down a river on a canoe in a
kayak versus sitting on the side of the shore and
fantasizing about how what a good kayaker I am i'm the best kayaker i'm a
great kayaker i'm the always be a good kayaker or I'm a terrible kayaker where
we lock in to an idea this is how things are and someone who's a good kayaker
will have a day they're not someone who's a terrible kayaker can
learn a skill and become better and there we don't have to have a fixed idea of how things are um I've had fixed
ideas of a friend maybe I felt hurt by someone who was angry and uh was holding
on to that anger seeing them through the lens of what happened a week ago
not realizing that they had changed uh it's something dramatic maybe very difficult that happened in their life in
the intervening days and uh I was still carrying my anger this is how this
person is and then I found out that they had a terrible loss and uh and as soon
as I hear that uh the the view I had before falls away and I'm ready to see
them now as they actually are i've seen people through the lens of my desires
where that desires was holding a fixed idea of who that person was and then
have those desires kind of soften relax or disappear as a lens of perception and
discovered that people are very different than the thought I had of how I the kind of desires or wishes I had
for them and so over and over and over again we can lock in to this is how
things are this is our interpretation that gives a kind of permanence a kind of constancy a kind of like solidity to
something that's inherently not solid it's always shifting and changing our
friends are always different from moment to moment minute to minute day to day our strangers are often different than
how we project ideas onto them bias prejudice all kinds of things that
we do are um are um
ways in which we solidify around ideas uh people spend a lot of time ruminating
thinking about themselves over and over again constantly tend to build up and
create fixed ideas of themselves often that are debilitating that can cause depression or anxiety or shame or all
kinds of things and um and this idea of fixating on ideas of self causes a lot of suffering
what we're learning to do in in mindfulness practice is to recognize
the difference between being locked in to ideas that give a sense of constancy
even permanence idea that I'll always be this way versus how things are in a
direct experience at a level that's deeper or more uh immediate than the
ideas the attachments we We have generally attachments
clings we have when we grasp onto something uh lends a sense of permanence at least
to the idea that we're grasping onto and this is what I need this is how it is
this is what's going on and in the doing that we've stepping out of the direct
flowing experience in the present moment of things always changing always changing
so as we sit in mindfulness meditation and settle in and especially you know we
f this this these talks are following the long series on samadei as we develop samadei and stability and centerness and
really find ourselves be able to rest here in the present moment in the direct experience not an easy thing to do
that's why samadei is really helpful to develop that capacity to be really right
here part of the value of That is to is is then to be able to rest in the
changing river of sensations experience thoughts feelings how it's all shifting
and changing much faster than our our interpretations our ideas of things
allow or admit or see and uh this is a very important insight
because what it allows is begins to show us the cost of attachment it begins to
show us how some of our suffering is born from some some kind of attitude
some kind of orientation towards permanence this is how things are this is how things need to be some kind of
permanence around holding on to an idea holding on to a memory holding on to a
plan or dream about the future that we're we're locked into something um and
even if it's a fantasy we're locked into and that fantasy is you know that we're
fantasy if we're kayaking or doing something wonderful there's something about being locked in that begins to
create a kind of sense of permanence in the knowing in the knower in the one who
is engaged any kind of clinging any kind of attachment is a form of stress that
gives us the wrong impression about uh what this world and life is about it
gives us a semblance of a fixed sense of self a fixed idea of
of desires a fixed idea of that tension or pressure um stress is kind of
something that's always built into reality into society that we um we have
to just go along with and many people don't see that how attached they are how
much they're clinging how much they've tightened up around ideas beliefs stories about themselves interpretations
judgments and the the vantage point that seeing
impermanence seeing the changing nature the inconstant nature of direct experience is it highlights how we get
caught it highlights how we're attached and it almost doesn't matter what we're
attached to uh we know we start seeing the cost we
see the tension we see the stress of holding on
that's a consequence of having of no longer being in the flow no longer being
in that river of change that things are always flowing and moving so that part of the insight of insight
meditation is the insight into how we suffer how we cling how we've lost
touch of something very immediate and nice here which we don't necessarily
think of as nice because the allure of thoughts the allure of promise of doing
things getting through our to-do list um fantasizing planning uh being caught up
in the world of activity can seem more promising more valuable than the simp
simple uh simplicity of being the simplicity of joy of happiness
contentment of just being here and so as we start settling into the
inconstant nature of breathing the flow of experience we start can see how we
leave that for solidity we leave that for attachment and that is invaluable to
see this is the beginning of a real wisdom in Buddhism to real ability to be
your own teacher to see what you're doing to see what is healthy for you to
do and what is unhealthy and the opportunity is to be able to drop into this world of direct
experience so that in a deep way our understanding
our interpret our understandings our insight our attitudes our motivations
our way of living in the world arises from someplace deep inside
that is quite capable of living in a rich even sophisticated way in this
world without any attachments at all that we can take care of ourselves we
can be creative we can be living with our with the conditions of the world
responding from a deep place inside that's part and parcel of this river of
change that we are just like a skilled kayaker
is completely wisely knowledgeably aware of the river the rapids the currents all
the ways in which to paddle and to shift the weight there's a tremendous amount
that goes into into being a kayaker but it all exists and flows from this
deeper place of constant change and being part of that change in a sophisticated way as soon as the person
gets locked in to these ideas they lose touch with the kayaking and they might
even lose touch of with the shifting nature of the river and they can you
know end up in trouble we stay safe safer
in the river of life if we don't get attached and part of the
function of this deep insight into inconstancy is to see how we get caught so as you go
through uh your day today start noticing how you get caught
notice how the cost of being caught notice what you lose touch with
notice how often it happens and then maybe at the end of the day or some
point in the day if there's a friend that you can talk about such things
maybe maybe a dharma friend you can call uh maybe talk about what you're learning
about the difference between being in the present moment in a full way and losing
that in some way through being caught in ideas feelings attitudes beliefs bias
become wise about attachment and you'll become a much better kayaker in this
world of this world that we live in thank you