morning folks Can you hear me am I
audible just need something in the chat if you can hear
me It's always a
question Great Sound is sounding Okay I'll wait till the top of the hour
to uh to begin It's lovely to see all the greetings in the
chat Many names I know and many names I I don't know
Okay So today is uh uh the second day of my week subbing
for Gil who's teaching a retreat at IRC and I'm very happy to be here with everyone this uh 700 a.m as we call it
since it's 7 a.m Pacific time uh the 7 a.m Sanga is just uh it's such a
delightful part of the whole IMC world you know it's come to be uh very
important you know in uh in our world our world our dharma
world so I'll carry on from uh from yesterday where I introduced the theme
of what is just defined uh in the sutas as the world the world which is that in
the world by which we perceive and conceive leave the world So these six sense spheres the
eyes and what is seen ears and sounds nose and what is smelled the tongue and
what is tasted the body and what is sensed tactally and the mind with all
its activities its mind objects And the relationship between
what comes to us through our physical senses all our interactions with the world that is and what we make of what
comes in the mental activity that arises conditioned on those uh six sense uh
sense senses on all that contact through those six senses That's the ground where we
find freedom It is our world and our freedom is found in that
world and so are the obstacles to that freedom And that's kind of what I'm focusing on this week The the sense
spaces in the the what arises in relation to the sense spaces that creates obstacles to clear seeing and
the insight that can arise as a result of clear seeing
So our experience of the whole world comes to us through these five physical senses and the mind and uh and of course
the mind is considered a sense in the in the Buddhist uh traditions There is no world outside of
what we sense You know that's it's maybe it's obvious but I I don't
think we really think of it that way And then uh the ma mind uh attempts to make
sense of it to create a concept of it many concepts of it all based on what
comes in through these physical senses the conditioned interactions of all of
these those make up our experience of the world of our
lives So there is a there is a suta in the the samuta nikaya one of the um
collections of discourses of the Buddha the connected discourses it's called the saba suta
which means the all the teaching on the all saba is all everything and the all
just like the world is according to uh the Buddha in the suta the six senses
and their objects and remember the the Buddha said that we can't reach the end of suffering
unless we reach the end of the world Just a slightly curious statement I
think I hope it'll be uh you know uh responded to in uh during this
week So my intention is to encourage inquiry to encourage investigation uh
into how we relate to each of these spheres of uh of our experience of life
And yesterday I spoke a bit about the first sense in this list the sense of
seeing sight and today the focus will be on on hearing Um but first let's
uh let's sit let's meditate So if
you'll take your uh useful upright meditation posture upright uh
metaphorically so even if you're lying down you can have that sense of uprightness in
the in the spine I think especially the kind of uh sense of dignity that can be
uh that can be felt when there is
uprightness along with ease along with letting go of any tension any kind of
muscular activity that isn't necessary in order to keep us
upright And as we usually do uh maybe a brief body scan
just touching with our awareness areas of uh of tension in the
body Breathing into them and then on the exhale just letting them ease up
We all have our own areas that that we habitually carry
tension Maybe in the face or throat shoulders the chest the gut belly
Just breathing into the any kind of tight places any kind of
places that feel constricted and letting them ease
up Might let your breath be a little bit deeper as you do this
really allow the sensations of breathing to uh to help with the easing the calming
of tensions in the
body For most of us the breath can have that can have that
effect calming settling
and letting your breathing be just happening as at its normal rhythm
whatever that happens to be right now
And letting your attention your awareness be with with the breathing for a little bit
And now just uh letting your uh letting your awareness be receptive to
sound Noticing the sounds that arise Sound of my voice
It sounds where you are wherever you are inside the building you're inside
Maybe sounds coming from
outside The sound of your own breathing If you can hear
that sounds coming from within the body other sounds besides the breathing
And just as uh we can see what is uh what's present um around us if our eyes
are opening and functioning well we can also hear if our ears are working
well working well enough maybe with the help of hearing aids
It's true for a lot of older
folks We don't need to reach out in order to hear It happens naturally when
a sound arises This
So as uh as sounds arise just notice them and let them be
here he heard And uh and also notice if the initial
hearing leads to an urge to uh actively
listen to uh to try to hear It's normal of
course especially if a sound is new or unusual
But if you find yourself leaning into into hearing trying to hear something
trying to identify what's making the sound or what the sound might
mean just notice the effect of that in uh in your body Notice if there's any tension that
arises sense of constriction tightness anywhere
And in your mind as well
And as much as possible just just let hearing happen without leaning
[Music] forward without the mind getting involved in conceiving
ideas about what you're hearing
Just rest in that way
Receptive awake
alert but not grasping at sound Grasping at meaning about sound
If you're aware of any uh any tension that's arising due to due to uh
attending to hearing some subtle way that uh that the
mind is um tightening up around uh trying to
here Really good to notice that And if you like it's uh it's fine
to let go of attending to hearing and just um rest with your usual way of
practicing with the breath or or other object or open awareness Just allowing whatever arises
to be known
But if you'd like to continue with just attending to sound as it
arises and noticing the effect the body and the
mind that can be really useful
You know I've heard that I've heard teachers say um I think I've heard Gail say it and
others as well that our attention when we're being mindful our attention is a
kind of love And I don't know if you feel that I
certainly feel it To give something attention is a kind of love
And we can take that uh that attention that love and maybe turn it outward
right now towards uh the world the big wide world beyond
our own world beyond our senses and our our mind states about
them the physical world out there and all the other beings and wish them well
Wish them well wherever they are in whatever state they're in May they be
safe May all beings be happy May all beings have as much health
as is possible to them May all beings have ease in their
lives May all beings be free
[Music]
So uh welcome
again and we'll continue this exploration of the of the sense spaces
and their objects There is
seen seeing and what is seen There's hearing and what is heard tasting and
what is tasted The rest of them you know between each of the sense organs and
what they sense there is a connection There is uh
something that uh that allows that connection to happen And that connection
can be pretty simple um or it can get quite complicated by
mental activity and that I'm focusing this week on the kind of mental activity
that makes it difficult uh to see with the clarity that's needed for insight to
arise You know in the in the text this kind of complication between the uh the seeing
and the seeing the hearing and the heard is called a feder fetter f
t a fetter that arises dependent on the seeing and what is seen on the hearing
and what is heard kind of unh wholesome hook that gets created between each sense
organ and its object that ties us down in a sense that keeps us
caught and feder feder is a kind of unusual word in our daily life but I
like it it has a lot of use in the in Buddhist world and translations of uh of
the word samojana is the word in in Pali and uh I like this word feder Gil uses
the translation not for this word recently not k n o t um which is also
really evocative of what's what's going on I think but I like this word feder
because uh I'm a birder I love birds and feeders
are what um what go on a hawk or falcon's foot in order to tie it to its
perch in falconry I'm definitely not a falconer like to watch the birds not not
hold them to their perches Um so it's a way a fetter is a
way of keeping the bird from flying free and that's what these fedters do to us
You know there's a list of 10 fedters that that's quoted often that are defined as uh the obstacles the main
obstacles to being liberated But I think uh what's really important to keep in mind is that a
feder is any mind state or like desire or ill will resentment pride envy
agitation just trying to make something happen any kind of a mental state or
activity that keeps us from being free that ties us down that keeps us looking
for stability looking for happiness in all the wrong places kind of in the big
picture When no fedters are operating on in us then we're free You know we're
liberated in a sense So these sense spheres are the are the
um the area where these feeders uh arise and the second of the sense
spheres is um the ear the hearing apparatus and the sounds that uh that
come to it And I think we're aware of how what we hear can give rise to
fetterss to knots to strong emotions that either keep us tied to the sounds
or that uh that uh make us push you know to get away from the sound
I recently very recently received a gift from a a Dharma friend a charming little
plastic monk who is sitting and holding a a mala of beads and hitting a a little
wooden gong a Zen style wooden gong and he runs on solar power He's right here
next to me a little visual aid
There he is eating his little gong And he's
uh uh because he runs on solar power uh he goes really fast on sunshiny days and
slower on cloudy days It's quite foggy and cloudy right now here And he's sitting on a pile of
dharma books that are right you know always right next to me next to a southacing window So he gets all the
sunlight you know that comes through that window And I notice that when the little
guy is going fast really hitting that gong at a rate of like eight or 10 beats
per second it's a little bit agitating to my mind I feel like the sound is
pushing me to go faster in whatever task I'm doing on my computer which is
usually where I'm sitting And that's not objectively true Of course this little
plastic guy is just responding to the amount of energy that the sun is
producing from the tiny little solar panel that's on the platform he's sitting
on But a fetter arises when my ears hear that sound It's a little bit aversive
the feeling A very subtle feeling of being pushed unfairly You know there
I've just added another layer blaming the monk for that and it's not a big deal of course
you know and of course and I have a lot of options to reduce the agitation I can
I can move the little guy out of the sunshine And I can also see if it's
possible to just hear the sound without assigning this meaning that arises out
of the aversive hook that has arisen to just rest in the hearing It's just a
ticking sound you know like a clock During the meditation it it
started out um relatively early in the morning here started out the little guy
was was uh tapping the the um the gong
quite slowly and then as it got brighter as the sky got brighter it went a little
bit faster and I was able during the meditation to just uh just hear it not
really listen in an active way and no uh no feder
arose but when it does you know the feder of aversion It arises in the mind
dependent on hearing the sound So it it arises sort of between the ear and the
sound that's being heard uh in a kind of metaphorical way And the mind gives
meaning to the feeling of aversion It assigns you know the intention of
pushing me to work faster to this innocent sound that the little plastic
monk is making And of course that's a very simple very simple
example but I think it it points um its ordinariness the very ordinariness of it
points to how easy it is for some kind of fetter to arise in dependence on what
we hear And there are sounds that have the potential to give rise to a lot more
discomfort and stress in the mind because of the associations we have with
them Um a siren you know a some kind of emergency vehicle or police vehicle
close by Someone screaming you know a person screaming a baby or a child or an
adult who's crying who's weeping natural sounds like thunder for
some of us whistling wind screech of brakes and the sound of a car skidding
hitting something Lots of in instances of hearing something where um some kind
of reactivity is immediately likely to pop up And sometimes it might be very
sensible You know if we're crossing a street and suddenly hear the screech of a car's brakes you know we don't need to
examine the feder that's arising in our minds We need to you know just look
around and see is there danger or is there danger for someone else if not for
me but there are also many times many times
when we hear a sound that gives rise to strong reactivity some form of grasping or
aversion And uh there is no pressing need to understand the source of the
sound or to take action There is instead just this hook the sound of a particular
person's voice Maybe now we hear it immediately We turn away from it maybe
turn off the radio We we heard the sound The feder arose and there we found
ourselves You know maybe chest constricted heartbeating faster mind
kind of darkened you know cons closed
There's a story that um Ajan Sha the very highly regarded Thai um master of
the of the last century monastic teacher teacher of many of our teachers he told
this story that he was staying in a a hut um outside a village in Thailand for
a period of intensive um meditation practice and the people in the village were having some kind of a a celebration
a festival And they had loudspeakers up around around the village in trees and whatnot
different high places and they were pumping out really loud music Thai pop
music And Ajan Cha reacted by just getting livid He stormed around his hut
he said asking himself how those disres disrespectful villagers could be so
thoughtless you know with no regard for this monastic who's trying to become
free free of suffering right outside the village It was an honor for the village
to have a meditating monk staying there and they you know they should so respect
etc etc etc is just going on and this kind of thinking he said he acknowledged
went on for a couple of days and then he said he had a sudden
recognition it's not the sound bothering me he thought I'm bothering the
sound it's me bothering the sound and his mind quieted the sound ceased to be
a problem the problem was the bothering that was in his mind the aversive
reaction the feder And on the other end of the
spectrum from aversion you know we might hear the sound the sound of a a
chocolate bar being unwrapped in the next room you know and suddenly there's
a strong desire for chocolate in the mind Some chocolate and we can just take a piece We can enjoy it and be done with
it But if we hadn't heard the sound would we have even thought about
chocolate now the sound was familiar and the mental associations that were already present in us gave rise to a
fetter maybe I want some And in both those cases you know
the mind can tend to blame the sound we heard for the feeling that arises
You know I can think it's the little monks hitting that gong that is bothering me or it's the fault of the
person who unwrapped the chocolate that now I want some But if we really look at what's
happening we can see that sound is just sound It's the reactivity that arises in
the mind that's the source of our irritation our hunger for chocolate
I'm seeing in the in the YouTube feed there's some uh visual distortion I
don't know if that's happening for others or if it's just me I hope uh it's not happening for you
So this is a sound going to I'm just know what I can do about that
actually Yeah intermittently losing sound Okay let me see what's happening
here Maybe uh I don't think I should stop the the
uh the feed That will be that could create a big
problem Yeah I can see that uh something is going on I'm just going
to have to I'm just going to have to continue I think because I don't know I don't I
don't know what the technical issue is here
I think it's okay Okay So so it's the reactivity that arises in
the mind That's the source of our irritation you know the source of our our hunger for chocolate And and that's
what the texts ask us to to do to recognize the feder that has arisen
um between the sense of hearing and the sound we've heard It's okay and to let
it go And how do we let it go well a
practice that can be helpful is to relax the mind moving from listening to simply
hearing letting the sound be sound instead of bothering the sound to use
Ajan Sha's expression
So yesterday I asked you to experiment with the difference between seeing and looking and uh and that's an exercise
that uh that we can do um uh any time you know to just notice the difference
in the mind in the body between these two ways of using the auditory sense And
I I asked you to do that a little bit in the uh in the meditation just to notice
when this urge towards uh towards listening um arises and what what is you
know what's driving that urge what's driving that urge
[Music]
did something happen when I rang the bell you
know was there a fed or a hook or m was it just a sound you know maybe a pleasant sound while it
lasted Just notice Just notice So today I just I want to encourage you to attend
to what arises when you hear different sounds during the day You know as you go through your life what's the mental
response is there reactivity is there some flavor of desire some flavor of
aversion i think each of us probably has a a vast library of sound memories that
hold connotations for us Some will condition the arising of joy
of love maybe of appreciation or gratitude beautiful qualities And with
some there might just be a hook you know something that isn't so lovely And it's
really good to see those because obstacles we don't see they continue to
drive us But once we do see those uh those uh we can eventually let go of
seeing them is the first step So thank you for your attention today Sorry about
any technical glitches that arose and I'll see you tomorrow tomorrow morning
Pacific time Have a good day