so good morning everyone from California and good day around the
world and uh big
welcome so one of the characteristics of many of our
minds is that we will
um not know it's so well and we kind of go onto a certain kind of business as
usual as we go about our life and we don't really pay attention to the quality of our mind how the mind is
working and the opportunity of meditation is to certainly learn about
the Mind learn about the different ways the mind can be the quality of the mind
and also to um uh to how to adjust the mind in a way
that is supportive for us and um and so in the topic of
samadi um the mind is becoming uh unified being
organized and um an organized mind and the mind will do that on its own if the
conditions are right if we're not distracted if we're not cut up in preoccupations the mind will begin begin
to come together and um and uh and uh and come into a kind of
an a settled unified organized matter
man manner where all the parts are kind of working together and so one of the steps towards
that then a step towards uh samadi is to orient the mind and Orient the mind is
different than focusing the mind uh focusing or concentrating mind is all
too easily interpreted as a laser focus on the control tower and we're kind of
kind of zeroing in almost like using our eyes to kind of stare something
down and um and often it uses maybe the front of the mind and to orient the mind is something
different uh it's to set the Direction uh a a sailor on a boat might
Orient the boat towards a lighthouse towards a
harbor and then but then be completely involved with the wind the waves the
currents the whole situation kind of open and available but with it but still
there's no the boat and the orientation is towards that Harbor going in
and so there's a way of orienting ourselves that is a gathering and a settling and a that comes almost from i'
like to just the back of the mind and um and that orientation then
allows for everything else to kind of begin joining and supporting that
orientation and so again with a with a sailboat once it's oriented we know where it's going we know where the
harbor is a lighthouse at the edge of the harbor perhaps then all the choices in sailing
are in support of heading in that direction and uh and there's many
different little pieces of choices but everything is for that purpose at that point um so I'll will guide you through
this idea of orienting the mind today is a beginning of unifying the mind in
somebody so to assume a uh posture where you organize
the posture you Orient the posture to a
wonderful balance between being
alert and being relaxed a posture that
promotes a heightened relaxed heightened attention
and promotes an alert body allowing to soften and
relax and even if you have a lot it's easy for you you know exactly what
posture to be in and you just plop into that posture you might slow
down and S way from side to
side forward and back to really begin to
find the balance almost as if each time you
meditate you rediscovering the appropriate posture
for
meditation gently closing the eyes
and if you have a settling spot for the beginning and end of each
breath starting there you might take a few long slow deep breaths
and relax as you exhale where the body can settle into
that settling Place deep within a grounding
place place within where you can feel rooted
here and then letting your breathing return to
normal and again with an ordinary
breath feeling the breathing arise from the grounding Place settling
place that place within where the in breath first sensations of in breath
begins and if there's more than one place the place maybe that's lowest most
grounded most settled within or the place that's most
comforting allowing receiving the inhale through your body
and relaxing the body on the
exhale kind of allowing all things to slide in towards that settling
point the grounding place
and then if you have this place some little area
where maybe where the breathing begins or where the breathing Sensations are
most nice nice to feel maybe it's just a small
area in the middle of it
all there's a long tradition finding that spot in the
belly maybe a couple inches below the belly
button an inch or so in
in from the
skin it could be a spot in the middle of the chest as the chest
moves it could be at the
nostrils it could be the whole breath body the whole way that the body expands
and contracts as you sit so it's a very broad Harbor big
opening or it could be a very small narrow opening in the harbor for the
boat and whatever it is whatever you feel
the breathing can be the home
base see now if you can feel or sense or
imagine being aware of that spot from the back of your
skull kind of we in the brain sits all the way to the
back a place we normally don't feel or sense or have much relationship
to often thinking and doing and
motivation might feel if it feel comes from anywhere in the brain it might feel like near the
front place where the eyes tense so the forehead scrunches up as we
focus but to kind of feel even if you don't feel anything just imagine
yourself sitting there at the back of that
skull and from there as you
exhale Orient yourself to the experience of
breathing this Skipper of a boat usually sailboats usually is in the back of the
boat looking forward towards the harbor
and as you exhale Orient
yourself
towards the center of your breathing
experience oh almost like there's a l a
light from the back of the skull
shining softly
gently onto the
breathing without any tension
on the inhale feeling the
rising the growing of the inhale in your
body and and as you exhale counting the
breath 1 to 10 but with every
count being oriented towards the
breathing there might be a way waves in the sea
that push the boat this way and that way but the harbor is always there
ahead on which to be
oriented every exhale with the
count sense or imagine or allow the awareness of
breathing to begin in the back of the
head where there is no tension
maybe in the back of the head there is no distracted
thoughts but there is awareness that is
oriented directed towards the exhale towards the
breathing
maybe like a Rudder of a boat that's at the back of the
boat for
as the inhale grows and
expands allow it to grow and expand into your awareness
almost as if the inhale as it
grows grows and touches the back of the
head so that when you exhale
there's an orientation of awareness all the way from the back of
the head towards the settling of the
exhale settling into the grounding
spot
e
for
for for
a soft orientation
but a clear orientation kind of a direction from the
back of the Mind back of the brain
skull that shines out down towards the breathing
kind of like a light a beam of light that attracts
welcomes all other things to join
it from the
sides so that on the exhale everything is settling relax
relaxing into the experience of the body
exhaling thoughts let go relax and slide into that
light quiting the
mind this orientation towards the settling
spot
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting do again let your awareness let the source
of how you know see with the Mind's
Eye let the place from which you Orient your attention to anything at
all let it Orient be oriented from all the the back of the head
or the back of your
body as a Radiance that's relaxed and open settles back
so that looking out upon the world is not done with
tension not done with wanting or resistance
aversion not done with a narrowing of the
focus but settling back to the back as if awareness
shines or begins from a relaxed
place where there's no tension in the
back and gaze Upon This World Imagine you're looking out across the
land your neighborhood your town or Province County
State looking out across the land for all all that is wonderful and difficult
in this world gazing upon
it from this soft relaxed place in the
back so awareness is not centered or doesn't begin in places of fear or
tension or wanting or even places of me myself and
mind gazing upon the
world and from there perhaps to Gaze on the world with kind
eyes with Good Will and well
wishing offering the world Well Good Will in the way You' wish all
that everyone would do what a world it would be if everyone wished each
other the best contributed to goodwi into this difficult
world and whatever way you wish everyone could do it may you do
it may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may the way and Way by which we Orient ourselves to to the
world provide some of this to those we encounter may all beings be happy
thank you
so hello for this uh second talk this week then
the 16th talk on samade and as I've often said samade is
a unification of Mind mind and body the Gathering to together more than a laser
focus and that unification of the mind has many different characteristics one is uh it's
inclusive the the idea that we don't settle the attention on something
in particular get absorbed in something but pushing things away there's a way in which there's a kind of feeling of
availability and openness that makes room to be inclusive of all
things and uh and that movement of inclusion receptivity um is a wonderful attitude
for receiving and including the primary uh subject of the samade so the
primary subject might be the breathing that's the standard which we're using for this uh sumati course and so this
inclusion this receptivity that in particular can be felt on the inhale and then there's a kind of
settling into it all settling into the body into the body breathing so that
it's a settling where we allow all things to settle into it almost like we're including everything without
focusing or on everything without thinking about everything or reacting to everything just on the edges everything
kind of settle and so um and so there's different aspects
of this unification so this inclusion is what I I talked about yesterday and
today the focus is this idea of orientation and um so if some of what
I'm talking about doesn't make sense to you it's okay maybe you could translate it in the way that does make sense to
you or you can just take it as being interesting and or not and um and just
kind of hang in there and as we kind of go through this especially for this week there might be different parts of this
week that speak to you um uh you know so today is this
orientation and that's a very different word than or idea I would hope than um
focusing or concentrating in a tight way and narrow way uh focusing is very much
associated with the eyes I think for some people and there's sometimes meditators engage their eyes um
unnecessarily in meditation if they're focusing looking trying to see their experience and they're can actually be
tension around the eyes because of that and so in a sense because of that tension that's kind of the the place
from which we're being oriented to do the awareness practice um um it might be that it's
more uh thinking uh knowing or even labeling the experience even counting
the experience it might engage someplace behind the the forehead or you know even
the forehe forehead can get a little tight um there might be a s a sense of there's a little voice or a little
Operating Center control tower that's doing the work um uh the mental work
that we have to do and uh and so again then the orientation the place from
which we're doing it might be behind the forehead and kind of in maybe cerebral cortex or
something and um sometimes it might be some other place where there's some tension or holding uh even if it's we
might be feeling kind of knowing or exper experiencing feeling the experience and so the orientation is
from the body itself and how it feels there might be the one who is
experiencing it the one who's enjoying it or or um UNC the one who's uncomfortable because of it and that the
one who's doing the awareness the one who's the experiencing or the one who's the victim the one who's the enjoyer
might reside some place in the body or someplace in a disembodied place that U
is kind of like the place from which the orientation is happening and one
opportunity is to find uh an or a place from from which we can get
oriented that that has no tension in it that maybe has no obvious association
with me myself in M um and so uh the
suggestion I've made was the back of the head kind of in the back of the skull uh
generally kind of the back of the brain the back near the back of the skull um
maybe there's an maybe if if someone has headache or something there might be some Sensations there but there's a
place there where where maybe there's not a lot of sensing neurons to really
sense and feel and so it's a little bit maybe free of all the associations of Me
Myself and mind free of the associations of doing a work and straining to make something
happen and um and you can say Well that's arbitrary it's made up to to find
a place like that in the back of the head to orient from um and maybe so but
that's not doesn't make it wrong that's mostly what we're doing the mind is doing anyways making up things making up
a place from which we're oriented it's arbitrary or it's kind of it's not really inherent in being aware that it
has a a a spot for from which to be oriented so if it's from the eyes or
forehead or something some other thing um uh we that that's made up too and so
we're using our capacity maybe for imagination to find a place from which
we can be oriented and um and some so one possibility is the back of the skull
and almost like there's a light there light of awareness um almost a light that's not a
light it's just kind of maybe Clarity or just a sense of directedness that um that uh is not
there's no tension or no grasping or pushing there exact exactly but there is
an intentness there is a sense of purpose that um that oh this is the
direction we're going and I myself love the idea of because I spend a lot of time on a sailboats on a sailboat going
towards back to the harbor you see the harbor and um but the boat is the waves
are pushing boats this way and that way the wind you have to adjust by the wind and you can't always actually be
directly focused on the Harbor there might be kind of going back and forth some but the harbor is all the always
the orientation always yes and the the the skipper of the boat can be quite
relaxed um doesn't really it's not troubled by the fact that we go a little bit to one side or the other side in the
waves but just because the orientation knows where they're going and just kind gently kind of stays keeps it on focus
and the mind is relaxed the awareness is relaxed softened moving in the direction and so
from the from the this this place in the back orienting ourselves oh this is the
direction and it's more like a kind of a wide field than a very tight
little one but it's orienting itself you know the harbor might be in the distance
it might be in the Horizon a very small little spot so there is a place that is
very teeny up ahead but there's an orientation that takes it in without getting tight and narrow and
focus and so the orientation with breathing is to find this orientation
towards the breathing that yes this and a and a kind of commitment and in wonderful soft
intentness a sense of purpose that this is what I'm doing now and if you feel
like other things are more important to think about imagine or feel or have emotions about uh with this
intentness or this kind of orientation towards the breathing uh it's um it's not to push
anything away but uh it's to allow it to
be there on the edges in the peripheral awareness so that you never forget about
the harbor you're going to the skipper might have all kinds of things going on
but uh it's always Focus there it's like driving a a car in the freeway you always know the direction you're going
ahead on the freeway uh even if you're talking and having a difficult conversation with someone in the car
you're always there there there so that's the orientation and then with that it allows
kind of a gathering a gathering of everything that supports that more like
it's almost like it's a the orientation is a slot SL maybe a big curved slide
and everything can slide in as we exhale and sliding down towards what I call the
settling spot or the Gathering Spot or the grounding spot which I find uh to be the very end
place where the last sensation of breathing occurs for me and that could be a different places depending where
you focus your body on the Torso but I do I do it right at the end of the out
re down in the belly and because it's the most grounding settling place inside
it allows everything kind of to feel settles there and then as I and that's
the small little spot of the harbor so everything is oriented towards and that little spot even if this feeling of
inhale grows and expands through the Torso it grows out of and continues
being rooted in that um that uh settling spot there and so what this is doing
hopefully is to create a a um
a welcoming or an appropriate or a wise
un way of orienting the attention towards something that's going to
develop a unification a gathering a wholeness a sense of of being kind of
really here and alive in the present moment without the uh too easily being
scattered and being fragmented by thoughts and concerns and feelings and
reactions we have um it's because we're on this wonderful we're doing this
wonderful thing we're in this boat heading towards the
harbor so don't get and that's what's important to do uh don't lose track of
that because you know may you know it's uh
you could get in trouble if you don't last thing you want to do is for it to get dark
before um you know you've reached the harbor so I hope that these analogies
and this way of talking um uh works for
enough of you that it's worthwhile and if it doesn't as I said um just kind of
follow along imagine always use your imagination in the sbody course
um don't try to understand all of it only logically or rationally or as a
technique of what to do but it's also the idea can just imagine it uh to some
way um and the imagination might give something on your inner system your
inner life something to orient yourself to something to to support you so that
you have an uh a uh maybe a better way of meditating
than if you just left your mind to its own devices
so so thank you very much and we'll continue with this uh theme of of
um of unification tomorrow