and welcome and here
we're middle of a series on samadi which is H samadi refers to a
state of being more than it does to a particular
practice practices can lead to this state
and so yesterday I went to uh have my teeth
cleaned and the hygienist uh took very nice care of me and got me comfortable
in the dentist chair and and uh and it's soon enough I would
closed my eyes and I opened and closed them as needed for her work but there
was something very uh wonderful about her care the way that she tended to me
and gently touched my my body to make it comfortable or
talk to me what she was doing and and uh and just that she was attending to me in
such a nice way and so as I was laying there my body started to feel relaxed
calm it started to have a tingling and warmth kind of through my body kind of a
nice warm contented feeling that spread through my
body and um I wouldn't say it was dramatic but it was quite Pleasant enough that part of the reason I closed
my eyes is just stay with that feeling that was going on and it was a feeling
of contentment nothing was needed uh just being just being alive was enough just being present here in
this uh situation and um and there certainly was
attention I put to my mouth my teeth to what was going on but it felt holistic
it felt like it I was not fixating attention on concerns about what she was
doing or to track every slightest little movement um I was there present in a
nice way but it was also there at the same time a diffuse attention a diffuse
presence through my body and this diffuse contentment of just lying there and uh nothing need to
happen so this is a state and uh as we come into
meditation um sometimes uh we're looking for a state of being a state of
Simplicity where which is there in a diffuse way to support us to provide a
kind of contentment or ease so that we're not thinking of meditation and
thinking about um somebody as a mental
exercise an exercise of somehow tightening up the attention the brain
the mind to really get to work now and focus on something um it's uh has a lot to do
about relaxing and letting go settling in and allowing some deeper sense of
maybe contentment sense of well-being sense of comfort sense of safety perhaps
to kind of course through us or vibrate or flow through us so that when we close
our eyes and metaphorically when we settle into the practice there's something there supporting us holding us
where in a sense just being alive is enough we don't have to do the
meditation practice we could offer uh ourselves to the practice we
can offer attention incl be inclusive of breathing the rhythm of breathing that
to could be the center of attention but um it's not like a uh a tight one it's a
settling stabilizing there in this field when I uh first started meditating
regularly twice a day in college uh twice a week I would go to a evening
sitting group in someone's uh house and I would bike there and after some months
of biking there I discovered that I started to to feel uh that as I biked
there as I approached the house that my body was already starting to feel kind
of this contented feeling this sense of gathering sense of being present sense of just being here is enough and so by
the time I sat down sitting down was a homecoming now here this is good that
could not happen if I sat down as if it was an assignment as if it was okay now
I have to get serious I about meditating and re in my mind and focus my mind and
all kinds of things so with that introduction perhaps uh there's
something that in your life your experience that is similar to this maybe
as a child uh there was some cozy place you would curl yourself up and be safe
and contented um that uh that maybe is a
reference point for a way of being a state state of being that
is the approach state for somebody it's it's it's the kind of
almost not doing anything um there's a not doing as we
allow something else to flow and open within us and there's a gentle doing
just a little bit more just just more enough more than nothing that keeps us
here so to assume a meditation
posture and for those of you who have done this often maybe just the posture is familiar
as [Music] home and maybe the care that you can
give to yourself to feel into your posture to see what small adjustments
you can make to make it more comfortable and more align
mind or maybe even it feels good that you're attending to yourself to your own
well-being and then with a posture of meditation that's right for
you to now simply check in just feel the familiarity of the
meditation posture see if there's anything just in the sitting here
now which is enough maybe you're still easily
distracted and cut up in thoughts but even so is there something about here and now in this
body that has a nice feeling to it a contentment a coming home
maybe you haven't noticed but maybe right now here and now in the place you're
in you're safe maybe you're warm
enough and with the eyes gently closed as a way that you're caring for
yourself doing something good you
gently without a lot of force taking some deeper
inhales and relaxing exhales
and then letting your breathing return to normal and now feel into your
body and how is it to be present in your body after those few big deeper breaths
and relaxing
if you allow your attention to be broad is there any
broad suus of feelings of well-being in
your body not
dramatic maybe they even coexist with whatever challenges you're
feeling but maybe there's a little s sense of calm now settling in
maybe a small amount of pleasure just being here in your
body maybe a
relief maybe a contentment a
comfort that is not located in any one place doesn't have a center in you maybe
but it's diffusive pervades some part of your
body and is there some way that it can feel
good to sit here without
meditating without doing anything except
maybe gently lovingly letting go of doing if you're thinking that's a
doing if you're trying to change something or Attain something that's a
doing not doing is there any feelings here and
now that just to be present just to be here is enough
not doing anything and allowing whatever arises in your
experience to come to
you to be to occur within some broad
State that's spacious or open contented
and then to be aware of breathing and is with breathing being in
the center of it all but not focusing on the
breath maybe almost as
if the sensations of breathing and awareness meet each
other they meet halfway
each receiving the
other almost like a warm sunlight
and you receiving each other as the sun warms you
up to experience the rhythm of
breathing where the sensations of breathing
have both a Clarity to themselves but also a diffuseness
as they are part of the wider field
state that has some pleasure
contentment maybe even some
happiness
e
for
e for
noticing if the if there's any broader state of being
that is Pleasant enjoyable nice comforting for
you maybe it's a bit of [Music]
calm some form of well-being
contentment and if there is such a wider State
however subtle it might
feel relax into it so that it's almost as if that state is doing the
meditation so the Mind rather than working at meditation
feels that it it's can relax into the
state almost as if the mind and the effort of the Mind joins the broader
state that spreads through your
body it is gently animated
by the rhythm of breathing in the
body
e
e e
e for
and as we come to to the end of this sitting taking some time
here to feel or sense whatever way that you've become
more comfortable or more
settled calmer
is there some way that some of you is little more contented just to be
present and is there any way that there is
some something in the mind the body the
heart that you could say has a is
Happy some form of well-being that feels settled and
contented or
calm that maybe is effusive through parts of your
body
that feels nice to surrender
to surrender into the feeling of
well-being that's more a state of being than something you're
doing what you do is surrender to it settle into
it open into whatever subtle or not so subtle sense
of well-being happiness is here
now or peace or spaciousness
and then if there's any way that you feel better now than you did at the
beginning of the meditation imagine that better imagine
that good feeling S A well-being is something you
can replicate and offer to
others imagine that you
could simply wish for others to feel it and it would spread into
them as it stays with
you that your own sense of well-being
is something that can spread out across the land radiate from you in all
directions so that your wish for other people's
well-being feels like a very satisfying important thing to do to wish people
well may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and as I go through the day today may I
remember I'm capable of well-being myself I'm capable of being
happy may I stay close to it so I can offer it to
[Music]
others thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this series on samadi delighted to be able to share
this topic in this slow way that we're doing it and uh we' been doing it now
for a few weeks and so as we're going deeper into it um please always remember
that it's good to start restart as a beginner whenever necessary
sometimes the art of meditation is to know when is it right time for that we
have to practice we have to apply ourselves in some way and when it's time to not apply ourselves but be more
receptive to be more allowing to um to in in a sense to rather than do doing
the practice uh when we are being practiced when rather than doing the
walking on walk through the airport here in San Francisco you are now stepping
onto the conveyor belt that carries you um horizontally through the
corridor and you can stop walking you're carry it along and um so it the the nature of our
practice changes over time and at some point and this is one of the nice things about practicing
regularly for some time is that some of the ways in which we are practice some
of the ways that things are familiar and a homecoming and and the good feeling of
I'm I'm back now in a place I'm really comfortable in that that begins to open
up a sense of deeper Comfort a deeper feeling of the practice is doing me
meditation is doing me rather than I'm responsible for every every single little thing that happens in
meditation and um and so to develop kind of a meditating meditator body which
means that it's such a familiar and comfortable and nice place to be that we
feel like we're it's doing Us in some way it's nice to settle into it and we can let go and relax and that takes a
while to develop and it's really worthwhile finding it and sometimes slowly over
time we begin to the body adjusts and changes and we find our
way and so at some point as we practice uh there comes a phase of practice when
we're before entering into this state of being called samadi that we're beginning
to approach it and classically it's called access concentration access Samar
I like to call it um approach the approach the approaching sumati stage
and uh this last summer I went back to um my hometown in Bergen
Norway and um being driven from the airport back into in into the middle of
town where it's such a you know home place for me uh something very cozy
began happening in my body and felt very contented and and satisfied and like
something like just being just being here was enough just being in this Mo as
I moved got closer and closer um something began to open inside something
began feeling uh confident comforted and home and safe something uh just
approaching it and uh in the course of the days I was there I would come and go out of the
center of town and and each time I came towards the center I remember having this feeling or going visiting the
places where I had lived growing up and just oh it felt so good to um to even
approach it be there and so this approaching approaching uh where We
Begin feeling that uh we're not necess we're not the only one practicing our body is
practicing we're being practiced there's a sense of a state of being that's a little bit seus and Broad that feels
like it's a uh it's inclusive it's unifying it's holding everything of who
we are uh in its broad uh kind of bubble
of pleasure well-being Delight confidence calm
contentment peace spaciousness I offer all these words not
because any single one of them is right but rather that this approaching this
feeling of rightness this feeling of of that it feels like real this is really
good to be here in such a way I don't have to keep practicing I'm being
practiced uh it's almost like um uh a state of being where just to be
alive is enough and so the idea that we're the ones in the control tower engineering
the practice making the practice work shifts begins shifting as something else
now begins to be suus pervasive through the body through parts of the body maybe
the Torso maybe the front of the chest maybe down the arms uh maybe in the face or in the hand
hands or uh some place in the body that starts kind of maybe vibrate maybe glow
maybe feel more open maybe parts of the body in a very contented way just feel
like they disappear like there's no resistance there's nothing almost nothing there because it just become so
peaceful in that part of the body and um and so some of this will
feel like just very nice pleasure some of it will feel like a joy
Delight that begins welding up some of it can feel like a very contented sense
of or satisfying feeling of happiness and
um that uh that we're just here and then what I talked about Monday this um uh
rhythm of applying attention and staying and resting and kind of settling again
and resting kind of like you know as I keep saying petting the cat and the pat purs
it's very nice and it's very comforting for the cat pet you're just doing this nice thing nice thing and it's almost
unselfconscious it's not trying to um provide the oneself or the cat with a
highest uh peak of human ecstasy and it just kind of just contented feeling
happy to be there so the same way with the the applying attention into the
middle of all this sense of wellbe with the breathing and the breathing is clear
enough it's kind of at the center of it but it's now begins to be feel F
feeling like this wider state is somehow the context of attention a Contex
context of awareness like awareness is Contin continuous with the state of
being as opposed to awareness uh being created and engineered from the
mind uh awareness becomes some maybe for sometimes becomes a diffusive or
diffusive feeling that it's more like a more like a diffusive feeling through the
body and um uh and maybe if you don't want to call it awareness that's okay
but it's kind of like the awar the feeling suus a feeling of well-being now
now pervades um our or influences or shapes
or or informs how we're aware how we're mindful how we're knowing the experience
we're knowing it now in a in an easy relaxed easygoing way and staying there
and um and and then so the art of meditation now samadi is to know how much effort to
make now when the mind is really distracted and really spinning out um
doing kind of a relaxed open peaceful calm awareness is not going to work we
want to practice the way with the amount of effort we put into practice uh is measured a little bit by
uh if we don't do it the alternative is worse so we have to do just enough that
it's a better than the alternative just enough to be present in an easy way way and then slowly things
settle in and we develop further and for further and as this we get into this
approach phase of practice um uh the amount of effort we have to make in some
ways diminishes there's less self there's less idea of attainment it's
almost like I don't doesn't matter if I go into samama it doesn't matter how
concentrated I get it doesn't matter if I attain anything or it what matter
matters is that just so good to lay there and be there in this contented way and um sometimes when I take a nap in
the afternoon uh I have I feel refreshed when I take a 15 20 minute nap but then
um sometimes I have no desire to get up from the bed uh I just feel so contented
and happy that just to be there and breathing and being alive feels like
it's enough it's good and there's no idea of attaining anything or proving
myself or having something something to show for myself or no idea of
nonattainment of getting away from anything just there so
um so to uh this approach St stage of
Fadi um is a uh is a time there come is it is when it comes to time when there
starts to be a shift between us practicing and being practicing us kind
of doing the focus and somehow feeling the awareness or the focus or the presence that we have is easy to do it's
almost like and there's some momentum happening something is holding us something is uh supporting us so that
practice is it feels more like it's being done from the inside out like
we're being carried now we're being supported now something is gathered something is unifying something is
holding it all so I apologize to offer all these
words BEC but I do that because no single word is going to work for
everyone and uh and some of this is very personal and so what I'm trying to offer
here is offer you a little bit of the map so that if there's better words for
you to describe how it is that um uh
uh then um please please go along with that but now we're at the approach
phase so um um so I hope that uh this
teaching uh even if it you don't exactly follow it or understand it um maybe it
brings you a kind of delight and confidence that this practice is good
and uh and it's good to be part of it knowing that there's a wonderful um Map There's a wonderful
territory there's a wonderful life to move into and be part of in this
practice of meditation so thank you