perfect so hello hello and welcome everyone to um the January 1st edition
of happy hour practicing together so
um yeah I wanted to invite us to practice with cultivating Goodwill meta
for ourselves and others and the world with leaning into our our presence and
intentionality um yeah for the year so that would be the theme of the guided
meditation today maybe I'll just leave it at that and introduce more as I lead
us so so with that let's um let's begin let's uh settle into
our meditation posture whether you're sitting in a chair if you need to move
to a position that's more comfortable actually just take a moment all of us and maybe lean left and right maybe
stretch your arms maybe leing forward and backward
really finding your center of gravity becoming embodied really feeling your
body before settling feeling the body any way that the body wants to be
felt perhaps rotating your your wrists your ankles yeah this body is alive this
body is Alive In This Moment and then take your time to settle really
take your time to settle into an upright posture if you're
sitting not a tight posture but allowing the back to be straight upright as if
you're being pulled up by an invisible string that effortlessly is pulling you
up vertebrae by vertebrae and the rest of your body can relax
relax relax relax offer its weight to the
Earth both grounded rooted into the Earth is the body
connected and uplifted at the same time holding these
dichotomies uplifted and grounded uplifted and grounded sounds
like a good theme for the new year uplifted rising up with our
aspiration our heart's aspiration lift it up lifting our heart
up as our body is connected rooted to the Earth stable present here
here I can nice heavy ballast settling us into the present
moment and relaxing and receiving the
breath breath moving through belly the chest
connecting the sense of rootedness of the body
body with the uplift of the heart the breath as the air
element lightness about it and yet moving through the body the Earth
element stable [Music] grounded steady steady steady
Letting Go thoughts and plans in this moment just receiving the
breath in breath out breath allowing it you allowing the receptivity to help
settle the heart and
mind
e
e e
i' like to invite you with each in
breath as the INB breath is received not focused on that's too
effortful when the INB breath ised relax the body and receive the in
breath see how that can shift your
experience receive the in breath however it shows
up the INB breath happens on its own deep shallow it doesn't
matter relaxing and receiving the in
breath not controlling not focusing but just receiving whatever is already here
however it presents
itself we receive the in
breath receiving the in breath however it is as a gift of
aliveness
present I'm alive I'm alive in this moment I have the chance to be alive and
receive this gift simply
receive not resisting the gift not doubting it not judging it not wanting
it to be otherwise it's like this right now
receiving this gift of the breath aliveness in this moment and with the out
breath offering the out breath wrapped with Good Will breathing out breathing
out your good wishes your kindness your friendliness
first first to this being who is you greeting yourself hello hello dear
being wishing you well wishing you
goodness wishing you
safety happiness
health and ease you can synchronize with each out
breath if you wish the wishes for
safety health or happiness actually second one second happiness
third one
Health fourth ease so the in breath receiving gift of
aliveness sense of presence and with the out breath
breathing out the wishes for Goodwill and if the forward wishes are too complicated just keep it simple wishing
yourself well may you be well may I be well
it feels too complicated at any point the receiving and giving lean into
whatever is simplest do whatever feels simplest and most nourishing most
friendly to
yourself
e e
powering this being goes you with goodwi with good wishes for this new
year on whose first day you are practicing you are planting seeds
wholesome seeds
it feels okay addressing yourself kindly I wish you well
dear I wish you goodness I wish you safety
happiness health and ease this year I wish you
well I wish you well may I be a friend to myself this
year I'd like to be a friend to myself kind
supportive may I be
kind to
myself may I be kind to myself this
Moment by inviting a to my heart right now whatever is
happening e
giving yourself a loving send off as you launch into this
year so way that some parents pack a lunchbox for their kids and send them
off in the morning where their care with their love their Goodwill you launch
yourself off in this moment with kindness good willll good
wishes care
can stay with yourself throughout the practice today
and if you wish now you have the option to bring someone
who's easy who's dear and easy could be a pet a child a friend benefactor
teacher so un easy into your heart space and wish them
well as if In This Moment present in this
moment if you're giving them a loving caring send off into the New Year wish
you well dear friend dear one may you be safe
happy
healthy and is right here wishing them well
preparing a lunchbox of care goodwi for them may you be
well lunchbox of Goodwill friendliness
without attachment to outcome of course of course we're simply planting seeds of
Goodwill cultivating friendliness care love in our own heart
no attachment preparing The Lunchbox
and setting it off letting it
go
e
e e
it feels okay staying where you are either with yourself or with an easy being or both
of you may both of us have ease and well-being
and if it feels okay you
can stay there or invite [Music]
someone for whom there's a tiny bit of challenge in your heart not the biggest
challenging person in your life not not go don't go
there just a little bit of challenge little bit of cloudiness in the Heart Is
it okay to wish them well and if it's not available come back to yourself or
easy being just gently stretching without getting out of
balance may you have goodness in the new
year you might need to keep them really far away in your mind's are
eye they're on an island and they have well-being and goodness but it's
possible perhaps they wish them
well
e
e e
for the last minutes it's possible to
expand wishing all beings all beings
everywhere goodness may all beings may all beings
everywhere have ease well-being happiness as much as
possible again not attach to the outcome knowing that it's not
possible that there are Joys there are sorrows in this world and yet wishing well for all
beings wishing well for all beings as much as possible may you all
be well all of us beings who are born and who die may all
of us have ease wellbeing goodness Happiness joy freedom
they all beings everywhere
including our ourselves may all beings be
well may all of us have conditions for goodness growth well-being
happiness and Awakening may all beings be happy may
all beings be free
everyone thank you so much for your practice joining on this first day of
the year makes me so happy to be practicing with you
oh so the Arc of our practice today the
guided meditation was the beginning I invited us to settle we always begin by settling
in the body settling arriving in the body a sense of body stable the Earth element
connected to the Earth and then the breath the air element the sense of uplift uplift in the heart and stability
in the body and uh and receiving the breath relaxing and
receiving not so much going out and for focusing trying to catch the breath and then I invited you with the in breath to
lean into receiving this gift of aliveness gift of presence so that we
become more embodied with the in breath and with the out breath I invited you to
breathe out this good willll s of you know the these wishes of Goodwill
as if your out breath is is um is showering you with with the wishes of
Goodwill and we start with ourselves wishing ourselves well as a way of cultivating friendliness meta Goodwill
and then we turned to someone who's hopefully easy um and then if it was available
invited you to open to someone who's just a little challenging wishing them well again in order to feel safe
sometimes you have to put them like way way way far away but can we still wish them well
and and oh and the metaphor that I invited you to bring in with both with yourself and with the dear being was
this metaphor of like launching yourself as if you were a child you you were your
own child you know the same way that parents pack up a lunch box and sent off their children into into the day with
their Goodwill like you're packing yourself lunch boxes suitcase of Goodwill go off to your one into the New
Year sweetheart may you have well-being May may you have ease just sense of this
embracing ourselves with Good Will these dear beings We Are Who suffer and and
have aspirations and resolutions and goodwi and challenges and all of that
and launching ourselves with Good Will into the ear and um and similarly for
our uh dear being and then as I mentioned switching to someone we have
some challenges with if that was possible accessible with without getting off kilter and then at the end opening
to all beings everywhere with cultivating our Good Will sharing our good wishes knowing that of
course happiness all the time is not possible for ourselves for our loved ones for for all beings so no attachment
to outcome but we do this practice to cultivate our own heart in friendliness
in meeting ourselves others uh with with good willll with kindness so that was
the arc so so the invitation for the small
groups uh breakout groups in the moment and and if you can stay I invite you to
stay it's sweet and auspicious to practice on the first day of the year with with
um yeah with Sana sharing your Goodwill sharing your good wishes for the new
year what are your aspirations for the new year year um if you feel comfortable
sharing them um I think it's quite sweet to be held Witness by another human
being who is on this path and is practicing um kindness Goodwill to share our um to
share our aspirations with them so so I I'll put the guidelines um in in chat
the guidelines for small groups is practicing meta mindfully listening and speaking really taking treating the
breakout as a continuation of the meditation embracing compassion noticing
if any resistance uh arises or discomfort internally externally and
meeting it with kindness compassion as long as you meet everything with kindness you're practicing stay on topic the topic
tonight the the um prompt and let's go in alphabetical order according to first
name the prompt is um what is your aspiration in the ways that you wish to
grow uh just a tiny bit maybe just one aspiration for yourself
in the new year um and if you like if you feel okay sharing please do that
that would be one round you can say pass no problem um or and you could the
second round perhaps you can share if you like something that came up in this guided meditation and it could be
anything um I fell asleep or I or I felt a little kindness towards this person
I've been having challenges with it wasn't as hard as I thought or maybe oh it was really hard it was harder than I
thought that's all good so staying on topic and taking turns briefly so each
person shares a little nugget and the next person then the next person comes back to you again you go around and
round avoiding cross talk interrupting giving another person advice um keeping
the space safe and kind so so as long as we're practicing
kindness um in the small groups they we're doing the practice right there's no right or wrong so so I'm creating the
breakout rooms now take care of yourselves take care of each other and really celebrate the the opportunity to
be with like-hearted people and and practicing with them opening the rooms
now here we go okay welcome back everyone everybody's
back the rooms are closed I see some Smiles it's always sweet to see that after you come back from the rooms so we
have uh some time now for any Reflections you like to share um I will open chat you can either
type it or you can raise your Zoom hand and you'll be given the floor what's
uh yeah what what came up what would you like to share for the benefit of of the
community I see Ola let's see Ola I'm going to ask you to unmute there you
go um I feel excited meeting new
people sweet yeah nice yeah thanks for
sharing this all this is this is a special Community welcome new and lovely people I
me yeah new and lovely people yeah that's a great advertisement for happy
hour new and lovely people come new come meet new and lovely people yeah we we
all hope you come back olola yeah sweet any other
Reflections today's practice on this January 1st
what's on your
heart sweet whenever you send me a direct message meditation with my
kitties helps me cultivate meta yay kitties are so helpful to pets yes yes
they're so cute and lovely yeah thank you for sharing this
oh and and I see actually Terren I just so you're sitting with your puppy there
oh my God my meta is just falling out of my heart I don't see all of you because of privacy um I wonder if the person
who's who has their kitties if I could if your kitties might be willing to come into the frame too it' be sweet to see
them oh yes sweet very
sweet thanks for sharing oh that's very just brings up a lot of metal oh oh very
sweet ah oh you say bunch of hands Fred you're
up thanks Nikki for for years I've um on January 1 I would sit down and formally
go through the previous year and uh look through my calendar and see what
it jogs in my memory and write it down and and um you know always there's
massive amounts of things that I've forgotten um so I was I had just begun doing that
before we sat down tonight but I I saw that uh I was looking at my intentions for the previous year for
2024 and you know they were full of the intentions were the sort of unsurprising
good things that you know we aim for here to live in kindness to uh to be of
service to to be more open to live in love and and I felt like
well yeah I kind of did that this year I I I worked at it and um and that was the
right direction and I you know I really credit um happy hour and practice and
the close examination of this with uh with close friends for whom it's important
too um and it's it's it's wonderful to actually see results and to um to
not presume anything to be accomplished no mission accomplished here but uh just
to be inclining in the way that I desire and to um to be able to be clear right
enough to see that there's there's some progress so thank you ah thank you so
much for sharing this friend I'm delighting I have so much mudita
vicarious Joy and Delight in the way that you're you're sharing your wise
reflection the practice of wise reflection which is an important part of
Buddhist practice which is really setting an intention as you did for pre previous
year setting the intention and then working at it throughout the and then at the end saying oh yes there was progress
these are the things that that happened and taking Delight both both in yourself
and sharing and allowing others to take Delight that yes it is possible because this is inspiring it's it's we Inspire
one another which is why Sana is so important and I'm so moved by by you
sharing by your practice report um incompasses the whole year and and and
as you shared a happy error and this community is a part of it yay thank you
Fred thank you so much for being a member a stal worth me stal worth member
of this community yeah heart oh hearts hearts hearts
yeah Denise Denise I see your hand
please True Confession I was really smiling when we left because I had been
watching Amy with the dog she's taking care of and if you want to see true
loving kindness going back and forth and absolute adoration
this dog the body language just everything just ah in heaven and you
know we talk about that easy to express that with a pet and when he's in the
right mood I can get that out of my cockail but sometimes it doesn't work quite as well as the
dog but he he will you sometimes he'll get up by me and yeah really it's a
really it's a special thing this one is is hilarious oh my God thank you for
pointing that out Den I'm seeing small square I'm seeing Amy and and the dog
she's taking here oh my God oh my God adorable Amy thank thanks so much for sharing thanks so much for pointing it's
just Mita right you're taking Delight in in Amy's love and care and back and forth oh my God I know we're all for
privacy reasons oh my God so cute oh my God licking you all over your face oh my
God oh this is this is meta right here we're
all practicing meta for you Amy right now and your talk this is so sweet oh thanks
Denise that's great Amy do you want to say anything now that you've been put on
the spot you don't have to I've um I'm watching him for a friend
and um it's it's he's amazing he cuddles like
crazy like I wake up and his head's like just gazing at me and he does he loves
just like to lean on me and cuddle it's like the wildest thing um but he's not
mine and talk about attachment I have to give him back it's like my heart perfect example
of meta without attachment right meta is unconditional I love you no matter what
knowing that I'm I'm going to give you back I just love you in this moment unconditionally per this is beautiful
Amy thank you thank you sweet sweet ah Diana I see
your hand please um during the
meditation uh when you were offering for us to um work with the person slightly
challenging um I did and this was a person who put and
circumstances put a great challenge over the Christmas holiday like even more than slightly so when I uh when I heard
that slightly challenging person the person automatically came to
mind automatically I had challenge except it wasn't there it had gone
poof the challenge had poofed or I don't have another word for
so I thought wait a minute what happened here so I don't know what point in time
but it had maybe there's a better word than
poof piffle I I I don't quite know but anyway I've been released how about we
released okay that's share so that's what I'm here for to learn these things
to experience them that was wonderful actually thank you thank you Diana thank
you for for sharing yeah what what came up for you in your practice and what a
beautiful surprise that was wow great wow that challenge that that tightness
in the heart uh that um it's been released through
through this practice Yeah I can wish this person well I can wish them well may they have a good year this year yeah
wow look at that who would have thought yay right
exactly beautiful yeah yeah
beautiful so dear ones we've come to the end of our uh January 1st practice
session together and I'm so absolutely delighted to be practicing with you thank you and I wanted to let you know
I'm going to be uh traveling going to be sitting a retreat and I'm going to be teaching a
retreat so I'm going to be in the gone for uh January I'll be back in February
so um of course happy hour continues or wonderful substitute teacher substitute
teachers who are going to continue um and uh yeah thank you for giving me the
the honor and privilege to to practice with you thank you this is just such a joy really such a joy for me thank you
all thank you for your practice thank you for your presence thank you for your cultivation May May the seeds we plant
together to cultivate our heart in goodness and kindness in in friendliness
towards ourselves towards others may it be a cause and condition for freedom of
all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone take good care I'm going to stop the
recording I'm going to stop YouTube m