he good morning folks my name is May Elliot and today we'll be studying the
third of the three characteristics uh known as anata or not
self and I want to begin uh by saying that not self- teachings can often be
perplexing for people um uh so please don't feel like you need to have a deep
understanding after today's session a 15minute daret doesn't really do it
justice um so it's okay if it doesn't quite land yet just you know allow not
self teachings to seep in over time so uh so one way uh to begin
exploring not self teachings uh is by noticing when selfing
is present and by that I mean uh noticing when we're feeling strongly
identified uh with some aspect of our experience and when we're not uh and we
even might think of selfing as on a spectrum um maybe on one end of the spectrum it can feel like there's a
really strong sense of self at times maybe there's a lot of identification a lot of defensiveness um
a really strong sense of I me or mine um or on the other end of the
spectrum um we can notice uh when it really feels like the sense of self is
um absent or or very thin maybe there's a lack of reactivity uh an absence of
defensiveness or possessiveness so typically uh When there's less selfing there's less
suffering so this can be an an interesting and very fruitful area of
Investigation so in our meditation today uh we'll be exploring two different aspects of our experience that we
typically identify with quite strongly um our body and our mind um and
specifically uh we'll be investigating our sense of identification with the body is there is there selfing occurring
in relationship to uh the body the physical Sensations um and then we'll when we
switch to looking at our thoughts um this is also an area where there's often a lot of identification thoughts can
really run the show so um so we'll we'll do a practice where we're we're noticing
seeing if we can notice when thoughts emerge uh sometimes being being able to see the arising of thoughts uh can help
us see that uh that they're less personal than we often think they are that you know we didn't put them there
or ask them to visit they're just kind of arising on their own based on conditions just um we could say selfless
phenomena coming and going um you know like a a thought can be like a bird
traveling through an empty sky so during the meditation today I'll
be offering some questions questions for investigation and uh you can allow these
questions to drop into your experience kind of like dropping a pebble in a pond
um you know just just dropping the pebble in dropping the question in and checking for
ripples um so that's one way to receive the the prompts um uh another is um that
I ask I might ask you some questions that invite you to investigate your own experience um and as you investigate
um you don't need to think about it to cognitively come up with an answer uh instead uh you're exploring your direct
experience uh and during any of this um if you discover there's identification
present there's a sense of you know selfing present there's sense of self um that's fine um that's great you're
seeing it um so remember that we're not trying to get rid of the sense of self
uh we're not trying to get rid of that sense of identification we're just wanting to bring our mindful attention to it just attending to it and sensing
what we find uh so remember um there are many
ways for insight uh into anata to be revealed uh this is just one way to
explore it one way to uh to deliberately investigate uh this Insight theme um but
there are many others uh so with all that said uh let's let's begin our
meditation so please uh find your meditation
posture connecting with uh what's happening for you
presently just feeling the body inviting relaxation
and connecting with some sense of okayness with the way things
are you have the capacity to allow things to
be and there might be some sense of contentment some sense of goodness in
realizing that we don't need to tamper with our experience that in our
meditation we can just allow
when you feel ready connecting with the breath or your other primary
anchor and allowing yourself to settle on the home base
to connect with the felt sense of
breathing we'll take some time now to collect and gather the
Mind allow ourselves to
settle
e
e e
we'll let go of the focus on the breath [Music]
now and widen the aperture of our awareness and of widening the spotlight
uh so we can see the whole body can take in the whole body at a
glance so we have a general sense of the body
and within it we might feel Sensations sparkling coming and
going tingling movement
and as you feel these different Sensations in different areas of the
body you might ask can I control these
Sensations just dropping the question in and letting it Ripple through
can I control these
Sensations and I control when this body sickens or ages
can I control when this body sickens or ages
the sensations that are presently arising and
changing did I create these
Sensations did I create these Sensations
there's a strong relationship between our sense of control and our sense of
identification can we see whether we're in charge of what happens in this body
is there any specific place in the body that the sense of self
resides and you might
investigate look for yourself is there a specific specific place in the body that the sense of self
resides where the sense of me I me and mine sense of
I a sense of me where does it reside
often people report that the strongest sense of self seems to reside behind the eyes
the top of the head in the
brain and yet if we investigate that area of the body the space behind the
eyes can we find a self there
being with whatever we find in a soft open
way not judging or
interpreting just
noticing when you're ready returning to the Breath Again settling and
stabilizing
e e
shift the attention now to the emergence of thoughts letting go of the
breath and instead imagining something like a blank
screen in the mind like a movie theater
screen and we're sitting on the edge of the mind watching this screen to see if
we can see see a thought emerge so see if you can notice the
first thought that arises on the screen after I finish this sentence
then letting go of any thinking connecting with a few breaths
again imagining this blank screen sitting on the edge of the mind
uh seeing if you can watch a thought arise see if you can notice the first
thought that appears on the screen after I finish this
sentence e
you might watch out for sneaky thoughts like wow there aren't any thoughts
coming or thoughts like uh I'm not very good at
this or this is
fascinating there's no need to stop these thoughts uh instead just know them as
thoughts not getting lost in the
content on your own time uh continuing this practice of bringing up the blank
screen and waiting for a thought arise maybe waiting to watch a few thoughts
arise before returning to the breath to stabilize and doing it
again it's often not easy to see thoughts so if this doesn't feel
available to you it's fine just to stay with a
breath if you're continuing to observe thoughts you might notice that some are
loud and clear While others might be faint barely
noticeable try to catch the very moment a thought
arises you might notice is the thought made of words or
pictures is it spoken and if so does it have a tone of
voice can you get to know uh what a thought is made
of
e
e e
when we see thoughts clearly as
thoughts over time we begin to devest them of their power over
us we have more agency to choose which thoughts we want to act on and which we
don't
rather than so strongly identifying with thoughts we can skillfully employ
them and let go of the
rest e
welcome welcome back again my name is May
Elliot and here we are continuing on our theme of the three
characteristics uh with today's focus on anata or not
self and while it can be relatively easy to see impermanence to see change um and
we can certainly sense what suffering is like uh so the first two
characteristics little more available teachings on not
self um maybe a little less except ible my hope is just to provide an
introduction if uh if this teaching doesn't make sense or doesn't quite land
um just let it wash over you and give it
time and I should also note that my my intention in sharing these teachings um
isn't to get you to believe there's no self um this isn't about you needing to
believe anything and I'm actually not even to here to tell you that there's no
self um in the sutas uh the Buddha was asked Point uh point blank is there a
self or no self and he actually refused to answer um he he wasn't interested in
getting hung up on philosophical views um in perpetuating beliefs um
instead not to teachings they point us to towards investigating what we
identify with as a means of reducing suffering so this term not self this
translation of a Nat not self um it can be used to investigate our
experience uh so for example um is this emotion who I really
am well uh okay this um this emotion it comes and goes so that's not self uh is
my career Who I Really Am is my my job title or my role well that
changes you know when I come home from work so that's not self uh is my physical appearance who I
am well that changes too I'm not in control of that uh so that's not self
either so all of these things change um so what we find is that we can't quite
put a finger on uh any fixed unchanging
core within us that we can call I me or mine so we can use anata teachings as a
means to explore uh what we identify with to see what we take as a self and
to invite us to to to look a little closer so our our standard view of
ourselves is that I am a specific individual that is in control of
experience and and this self persists through time in other words um uh the standard
view of of ourselves is that there's a continuous me moving through time and
space that's kind of like the given um however uh when we in when we
investigate the nature of self when we look a little closer uh we see there
isn't a solid permanent fixed thing that we can call me or M uh what we call our
s is much more amorphous than we typically when than we typically think
uh and much more difficult to pin down and when we see this uh when we see
this really clearly we can feel a lot more
free so when I talked uh when I talked about anicha a few days ago and I talked about
impermanence uh I shared that impermanence insight into impermanence is one of the inroads to the other two
insights it's one of the inroads uh in that it opens the door to seeing
unsatisfactoriness suffering and to seeing not self so I'd like to
extrapolate a bit on how on how impermanence uh helps us see not self um
namely uh this is because uh when we see in constancy when we see impermanence it
begins to erode our sense that there's a fixed self um it erodes that sense that
there's that you know continuous permanent me that moves through time and
space so instead um we humans were a little bit more like Rivers than a fixed
entity in other words uh we change and this change undermines that sense of of
permanent meanness um so so here's a a classic
analogy of a river um to help demonstrate what I
need so just like uh just like uh say the Mississippi River uh we humans we
have names and certain qualities right each River has its own unique nature um
you know some Rivers they're fast and clear other rivers are slow and murky uh
each River has a specific geographic location the banks of the river they
have some semblance of continuity uh but if we look a little closer um if
we kind of zoom in on the Mississippi River what we see is that it's just a constant flow there's actually nothing
fixed there that we can point to there's new water flowing through every millisecond so we humans uh are the same
we're like Rivers you know there's the the May Elliott River and the Gil fronal
River and the Taylor Swift River and the doly Lama River and conventionally uh
these names are useful and important designations right and not to
teachings I want to be clear that they're not uh they're not denying that there is something here there is
something here called May Elliot uh with memories and plans and fears and stories
and preferences and not to teachings aren't discounting this yes conventionally
speaking there's a me and a you uh and it's useful and necessary to distinguish
this um it's it's useful and necessary to be able to tell the difference between this being ourselves and other
beings you know we need to still be able to care for ourselves and our responsibilities you know if I if I go
to the ER with a broken leg and you're a doctor um please don't just stand there
thinking well there's no self so I guess I can't help like that's that's wrong
you um so um so on one hand we have these important skills and designations
and qualities and personalities and we're all unique um just how a river has its own
unique attributes but like a river there's nothing we can point to that's
fixed um the water in the river keeps flowing and flowing and flowing um as the philosopher um
heraclitus said I we can't step in the same river twice similarly for us we're just a flow of
changing experience um we could think of um uh the water flowing pastes being
like the mindstream the waterfall of thoughts emotions physical Sensations
always changing we're just a flow and we really begin to see this in meditation
we begin to see this constant flow we see there isn't a fixed core you know
there's no there's no little little person sitting in the control tower pressing buttons and pulling
levers um we're conditioned um we begin to see that uh
we're more of a process uh than a fixed entity uh so uh so what's the impact of
this why is it useful uh so as we begin to see that
there's no solid continuous me that persists Through Time
uh we become less concerned with promoting the self or defending the self
uh less concerned with praise and blame uh with reputation or criticism so
much energy goes into trying to be seen as competent and good and
likable um you we can still be good we can still show up in the world in a way
that we end up being likable um but not so much energy goes into trying to
perpetuate this self story for others um so as um as craving subsides selfing
subsides and that means that suffering Falls away so as we as we consider Nat
teachings um please remember we're not trying to
get rid of the self that would be that would be kind of like trying to extinguish a
right there's no need to try to get rid of something uh when there's nothing fixed there to begin with um you we we
don't have insight into not self through aversion to
self so uh so please don't weaponize anata teachings um and use them kind of
as a new reason to hate your humanness that's actually um not effective we
don't we don't get to not self through denying ourself or neglecting our needs or boundaries um we're not destroying
the self but instead we could say we're we are ennobling the self we're studying
the self and it's through that study of the self that we see through
it uh so we could say instead this is a practice about love about careful loving
attention so on one hand uh I care for this being called May
uh May Elliot and on the other hand when I look closer I see that this being is
ever changing and it's not fixed it's it flows like a river and this Insight
provides a lot of
freedom so uh having uh very lightly touched on insight into
anata I'd like to zoom back out uh to look at this week um this week's
teachings as a whole we talked about um we talked about
samadi concentration and how how samadi
uh stabilizes the mind how it helps to quiet the Blizzard of the mind so we can see clearly enough to see the three
characteristics um uh but I want to be clear that insight into the three
characteristics um it's not an end in itself but rather it facilitates letting
go um uh when we talk about letting go what we're letting go of is our greed
hatred and delusion the cesas the three poisons uh we're letting go of our craving our aversion our confusion um so
this form of Letting Go it doesn't mean we can't respond to suffering in ourselves or suffering in the world um
on the contrary when when greed aversion and delusion
subside qualities like love kindness compassion generosity uh they can emerge
in powerful transformative ways so the form of Letting Go that
we're practicing is one that relieves suffering and it actually makes more room for skillful compassionate response
it makes us more available to respond to harm and Injustice in the world
and and sometimes it's said that the most powerful way to be in service is
when we can get out of our own way so this is one way that uh seeing
through the self can provide so much more freedom uh not just for ourselves
but for others as well this is a a a short piece of a poem
by Mary Oliver uh to live in this world you must be able to do three
things to love what is Mortal to hold it against your bones
knowing your own life depends on it and when the time comes to Let It
Go to Let It
Go so uh if this possibility is inspiring for you the possibility of uh
deepening uh insight into the three characteristics of uh freedom from
suffering uh I have a practical suggestion for you uh and you may have already employed this suggestion in your
life um but I'd like to suggest that you consider silent Retreat
practice um so uh Insight can certainly occur in daily life and if you're
available to sit a a silent Meditation Retreat um it can be really fruitful for
depth of insight um so if you'd like to deepen in this way um if you want to
provide these the supportive conditions for insight um you might try a retreat
um Insight Retreat Center a sister Center to Insight Meditation Center is a
great place for this so uh if you're not already familiar you can check out
Insight Retreat center.org um there's many Retreats at that site um
uh on the drop- down menu on that page the residential Retreats menu uh you'll also see off-site Retreats Hidden Villa
Retreats um and often there's more availability for these Retreats um they don't fill up quite as quickly um so
there's lots of options um uh I'd be delighted to sit a retreat with you um
you're welcome to come sit with me I teach at Insight Retreat Center uh
Retreats at Spirit Rock and there's so many other centers you can sit at as as well uh IMS Insight Meditation Society
on the East Coast uh lots of options to pursue this if you want to um to explore
the three characteristics uh in this this deeper way um so thank you so much
for joining me this week um it's been lovely to be with you to support you in your practice um and may may the three
characteristics bloom in your own heart uh to support you in letting go to
support you in complete Freedom thank you so much for your kind attention take care