hello and welcome to this half an hour meditation and um building
on what we've been doing earlier this week I so I've beeno and welcome so I
I've been talking about um how we divide ourselves fragment
ourselves and we lose touch with the whole of Who We Are by the intent it of the desires we
fixate on or the aversions or also the ways in which
we latch on to identities this is who I am and um and all these uh uh gather
strength by the intensity of our thoughts our ideas our Concepts that we
have and it isn't that thoughts and concepts are wrong to have
what's important is to be able to see how we become divided how we become
fragmented through them lose touch with
ourselves and um and sometimes thinking puts us in touch sometimes we have
thoughts ideas concepts of maybe even Who We Are
that help us to Step Beyond limited Concepts into not just an idea of our wholeness
but a way of being in touch to feel to sense so that all our capacities for
awareness are in some ways operating at the same time a whole field of
attention and um so two things one is that it's not only important to see how
these Concepts divide us but also start getting a sense of the
intensity of the strength of them how much clinging or Force pressure
compulsion is behind them sometimes this is seen
by the thoughts carry us away into our preoccupations and maybe we come back to
the present to the breathing and then how quickly we get pulled back
and sometimes we get pulled back we feel the pull even before we've returned even
in the movement of returning there's the strength of the thoughts are
there the thoughts that unite us that bring us all together do not have that
intensity uh they don't they don't come with compulsion and pressure they're not
loud so in not being loud maybe we don't feel like we should or can or want to give
them much attention to allow things that we want to attend to but in the practice of
meditation it's the thoughts that are supportive that are non-compulsive that are quiet that are gentle that support
us here come back who say welcome into the fullness of who we are welcome
um be here to sense and feel all of
it open up there's a variety of things we can tell us so so thoughts can
support us to be here and now and this goes along with what I
talked about the first week of light awareness so there can be light
thoughts and then there can be kind of a light sense of awareness or or awareness
that has no weight and gentle and it's can be harder to stay
present for because of the strength of other preoccupations other
priorities but to develop a really healthy form of samade has a lot to do
with the slow and gradual art
of cultivating developing staying close
to a a gentle soft
light awareness a light gentle way of thinking
that supports that awareness come back be here here
now let's welcome the breathing back rather than forcefully jerking the Mind
back to the breath there can be a gentle thoughts and
attitude of let's invite the breathing back into awareness so the mind doesn't have to
move so I'll offer you some guidance on this light touch of awareness light
touch of thinking for this meditation so to assume a medit
meditation posture that's right for you
and right for you so that there is
a non-forceful alertness that may be arises out of the
body and sometimes that is helped by whatever posture you're in
to assume that posture with intention with a sense of knowing this
is the posture this is what I'm
doing a gentle intention an intention that maybe is
infused with self-care self-regard
wanting to do well for yourself through this
meditation and then to lower your gaze and if it can support relaxing
further closing your
eyes and then to
see if you can tune adjust your
thinking to have a light touch soft
quiet maybe the soft light kind of thinking that
conveys a kindness a friendly less a
care and giving yourself gentle instructions so you're starting to use
your thinking in a nice light welcoming
way giving yourself instructions like I often do at the beginning of a
sitting to breathe bre breathe deeply
relax do that for yourself
giving yourself instructions is a way in which you begin
helping yourself become whole undivided
maybe talking to yourself with a tone of
voice that is comfortable
settling for your mind and your heart
and then breathing normally
relaxing on the exhale maybe with extending the exhale
just a little bit longer than usual by letting go relaxing at the
end and relax into the settling
Point final point of where the last sensation of exhale occurs deep in your
body
follow the exhale to the end allowing yourself to settle into
that end and allowing the inhale to arise from that
grounding point that settling point
as if breathing inhale spreads from this single point where inhale
begins and with the exhale there's a return to that point
and don't uh Focus directly
or fixedly on this end of the exhale this point
settling point but do be aware of it kind of with
peripheral awareness
so the way of being with this settling place with breathing deep
inside grounding place as a light touch
and if the mind wanders off in thought notice how that you lose touch
with yourself and then and then give yourself gentle calm
instructions to Welcome Back Being in touch being connected
so how you instruct yourself is light and gentle and
kind slowly getting used to light kind
awareness it helps you stay in touch with the body your
experience
e
for
for for
e
as we continue see if you can find just the
right balance of not trying too hard to be
present and not wandering away from the
present maybe a little bit like being at the center point of a seesaw keeping
it
balanced relax attention on
breathing attentive not to wonderand
away
for for
and then as we come to the end of this meditation to see if there can be a
balance maybe balancing in the middle n
seesaw between being grounded in
yourself and turning your awareness out into the
world to the people that you'll encounter
today people known and people not known
strangers and to imagine staying at ease and
balanced present connected to
yourself while being aware of the world of others
inviting a kind attention inviting
Goodwill for both for your yourself and for
others standing here balance between these two with Good Will flowing in all
directions may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free and may it be that how I'm
aware as I go about my
day might contribute to Greater happiness and peace in this
world may all beings be
[Music]
well thank you
so hello and welcome to this now 10th talk on
samadi putting down the foundations for what is needed to really have a useful
form of concentration in meditation and
um the
um so we're learning how our minds work
how our thoughts our attention works so that we can use it in a useful
way to not understand ourselves and try to get concentrated sometimes doesn't work or
we override ourselves or the concentration comes with a lot of tension and
force and um one of the things I've been emphasizing this week is that the ways
in which our thinking the ways in which desire and aversions and the ways in
which identity how we identify ourselves can be uh divisive in
ourselves how it could create divisions fragmentations how it contributes to not
being fully in touch with ourselves sometimes even a disassociation or disconnection from
ourselves and because to try to develop somebody while being disconnected uh is going to be much
harder uh it's through being connected somebody is a gathering together it's a
collectedness everything collected together collectiveness of mind and body and so we have to kind of
understand how we do the opposite and then to understand how to use the mind
how to use the attention so that that attention doesn't further the division
the divide that attention actually begins to heal it so to use attention in a like a laser
focus in a fixed way in a determined way to to blast through something or blast
into concentration um uh that actually creates more
separation and so there's some kind of way of being relaxed and soft and
welcoming to have an attention that begins opening to the hole not forcing
ourselves into the present so I want to use an anal
ology that maybe points to something important that um if I find myself may
be afraid and the manifestation of that fear is that um I I hold my hands in
tight fists and uh and I just you know been
doing that for so long I never really open my hand if I'm going to pick something up I put it you know have to
hold my two fists together and grab it somehow and so all I'm thinking about is
you know all I know about my hand is it's fisted and I start being concerned
about am I fisted in the proper way and you know what's the right way to have a
fist is my thumb supposed to be inside or outside what do people think of my fist do I have a nice handsome fist or
is this something that's embarrassing as a human being to have this kind of fist maybe I'm supposed to uh tighten up
harder with a fist or maybe I'm supposed to I'm supposed to be a Buddhist so a good Buddhist has a relaxed fist easeful
fist all I know is Fist and then I come across some wise
teacher who tells me gil you might try relaxing your hand fully pry your fingers apart and let
your full hand relax and then I get disoriented but but
but but I'm I'm my fist that's who I am what am I going to there's no fist anymore the
fist disappeared what did you do to my fist and eventually I discover oh how
nice it is the absence of the Fist is really nice I haven't betrayed the fist
by by relaxing uh I've just stopped doing something
unnecessary and if I ever need to fist again I can do it I know how but it's so
nice not to have it so in the same way um the the ways in which we cling
the compulsions of the Mind the pressure and tightness and the force behind which we think want have AV verion uh it's
possible to feel the sensations of that and and uh sometimes when people have a
sense of I am uh just dness what they're
identifying is that fisted of the Mind the tightness in the center of our
thinking and thinking does not have to have any pressure associated with it thinking does not have to have any
tightness or um thinking doesn't have to be fisted
in any kind of way but if that's what we're used to and that's what we think thinking is it's inconceivable that we
would relax that thinking muscle and um and uh we feel like we
have to go along with it and this who I am after all and so the very Act of
identification holding on tightly to identities it isn't the identity that's necessarily the problem it's how we hold
on to it the compulsion the pressure behind it uh the thinking isn't
necessarily a problem it's the compulsion and pressure the clinging the force behind it and so what we can start
looking at is the underlying tension that's there in thinking and in
identifying ourselves having an identification with anything at all and it's possible to loosen the fist
to relax and something disappears when the just like the fist disappears
something disappears in the mind and if we think that what disappears is who we are it can be disoriented Ed
disorienting but what disappears is the tension is the pressure that same thing can exist with
how people focus their attention in meditation they associate meditation
with having this with the tension or the pressure that's in
focusing focusing on the breath I know I'm focusing breath because on the breath because there's a kind of a
gathering and tightening in the mind that it's like a like this little strain of looking at my breathing or some part
of my body and for some people that strain is
what keeps them present because otherwise the tendency of mind to wander off is so
strong what we're trying to do here is to find some other way of being present that does not
involve force does not involve any kind of strain and so we have to let go of
the strain and realize it's still possible be focused and we don't you you know uh in
a different way and that's a light way a soft way an open way and so the the
dedication the persistence is in staying open and relaxed staying available and
relaxed staying intimate and relaxed and so we work hard at being relaxed we work
hard at being at ease and of course you can't work hard
that way and strain the working hard is just kind of like a repetition coming back staying
close to in a gentle kind supportive way and so learning a whole different way of
using attention whole different way of thinking and a whole different way of
maybe even uh taking things some some aspects of who we are and identifying
this is who I am and this applies also to how we identify other people there can be force
and compulsion identifying other people as being somehow wrong you know I'm
right that's an identification and there can be a lot of strength behind that they're wrong it's the force and the
compulsion that that some get created that's not in the being right and wrong
it's the reification the solidification the separation the the prioritization of
a certain way of being prior prioritization of a fisted
mind where we lose lose something in that process a fisted hand loses the
Open Hand the fisted mind fisted mind loses an open
mind a tense mind loses an easeful
mind and so to begin experimenting in daily life in meditation with seeing can
you find a way to think talk to yourself have thoughts
that are light easeful that are thoughts about staying
present giving yourself gentle instructions not that you're you're going to do this
forever but if you're honest you might find that sometimes that's the better
alternative to how the to how the mind's wondering often different kinds of Thoughts by itself thoughts that maybe
are not so useful and it's a beginning of training preparing the Mind learning the
mind how to be friendly how to be easeful how to be light how to be uh
very comforting mind a mind that you want to stay close to by beginning to
talk to yourself in nice ways in gentle ways it's not so much what you say to
yourself but how you say it and that can begin translating to
having in a a form of present moment awareness that is
compelling because it's not compulsive it's compelling because it feels so com
so nice of course I want to be present of course I want to have an open hand
when it feels so nice to have it open of course I want to open to the sensations
of my body of course I want to open to the feelings I have not because the body
and feelings are necessarily comfortable or nice pleasant but it's so nice to
have that awareness that's light and useful and available and so in a sense if what we
if you want to identify yourself with something don't identify yourself with anything that has pressure or tension in
it identify with the awareness the thinking which has none that's easeful
and light Pleasant and may be friendly so I hope that what I'm saying
makes enough sense for you to experiment with this and to be patient as we move
it slowly into this world of samade where we're going is as I've told said
earlier here it's kind of like a sacred Temple and uh and it's kind of uh
amazing capacities of the mind uh that should be we should have a lot of respect for the higher reaches of samade
are astounding but uh we want to really create the good foundation for it and
that's I'm hoping we're doing and with the instructions for today I offer you those for for this
weekend that uh you find a nice easeful way of
thinking and find a way of meditation to nice easeful way of giving yourself
instructions so that you can ease yourself into a nice comfortable relaxed
awareness that's is able to stay welcoming the present
moment thank you