hello and welcome it's uh delightful to see the
names in the chat and recognize many of them and many of you so
hello and
um so Monday I said samade is simplicity
yesterday I said samadi is subtleness
settling and today I'd like to say that samadi is steadiness being steady with awareness
with the attention being steady not only in the present moment but being steady uh
in uh resting attention at a center
point so the settling Point may be the
Gathering point the the point within where the awareness can
feel um committed it can feel welcomed we're place within where
it's possible for the awareness to become absorbed or Be steady in the
Simplicity of the experience we're having and
um and so there's a variety of these centering
points Where We Gather ourselves and I think of them this centering points as
uh there might be more than one at any given one time even but I think of them
as um uh the center as like the center of a trampoline where if we sit at the
middle of a trampoline it's it um it bows it's it settles down bends down to
hold our weight and if we have uh as I used to have with my little kids a trampoline in
the backyard then all the little balls that they had in the trampoline would
all roll towards that Center and uh we didn't have to gather the balls they would if we sat stood in
the middle they would just roll down there so if we can find that uh we have
a place and the steadiness of staying on that place in for attention becomes that
kind of centering place where all the different desperate parts of who who we
are can begin to gather there together one of the things that's
helpful for developing somebody through being steady is if we're steady for example
and what I'm teaching is steady with breathing the rhythm of breathing in and
breathing out as it's experienced in the body and in particular in the
Torso and even more so in the area around the
belly uh the movements of the belly as we breathe but it could be the whole uh
torso the kind of expansive uh movements of the whole torso as we breathe in and the Gathering
Together the collecting coming back settling back on the exhale it's a variety of things that
there's the kind of the that center point where we're resting so that
everything can kind of roll towards it that as we're there
steady uh don't set up a war or a really strong conflict any conflict with a
thinking mind certainly there are of meditation is to learn how not to be caught in the
world of thought taking you away from the present but also you don't have to
think that you're supposed to push them away either there is an art to holding
steady on what you're being mindful of what you're focusing on and then letting
your thoughts recede to the background and if they can be in the background they can be
there kind of you can kind of know you're thinking but you don't have to be involved in it it's like
for maybe it's says you're having a nice
conversation maybe it's like you're having a nice conversations with a friend in a restaurant and uh there's
other people talking around you but uh you're not you know they're talking but
you're not listening to them you're staying focused on on your friend
so in this way you know that you're thinking but you're not focused on it you're focused on your friend the
breathing to feel it listen sense Be There Be steady be a steady friend to be
really present on breathing so to assume a meditation
posture and
sometimes I think of the posture of meditation that ones
that one that kind of frees up or opens up the front of the
Torso so it's easier to breathe the chest is not collapsed we're not
collapsed in such a way that the belly is kind of um crunched
up but rather there a feeling of being open in the and now kind of like an open
chest maybe the belly is open and expensive so that as you relax the
belly soften the belly the belly hangs
forward it's not pulled in
and maybe feeling the belly the soft belly as you breathe in
deeply feel the gentle expansion
pressure pushing outwards or downwards that happens in your belly as
you breathe in and how after a while with the in
breath Maybe
that expansion and pressure in the belly helps lift
up the rib cage and helps expand the
Torso around the ribs
and then discovering what it how you exhale how
the body exhales a long exhale is it first from the chest that
the contracts or the belly or both together
on the exhale relaxing and softening the whole
body and letting the breathing return to normal
and with a normal exhale
soften the body
and then to settle in and a simple
way to the experience of breathing maybe to a place within which
is the centering place the Gathering
Place maybe at the end of the exhale where something shifts and the
the inhale begins
and with if if you're with a friend who somehow is challenged by something and
needs support but the only support they need is just to know you're
there and you put your hand on the top of their back just keep your hand there
so they know they're being accompanied your hand stays there
steady in the same way the hand of awareness is placed
gently against the back of
breathing so it's not a frontal piercing of attention to the
breath a strain but coming from
behind and coming up and being there to feel and sense in a gentle
way to let the breathing know you're there for it
and then keeping the hand of
awareness with the exhale so you're accompanying the
exhale through the whole length of the exhale however short or long it might
be from the beginning to the end you don't lose lose
contact experimenting with a steadiness through
the whole length of the inhale
and then accompanying the exhale not pushing it
or needing demanding anything from it but keeping the hand of
attention there is in touch with a whole exhale from beginning
to end
and then both the inhale and the
exhale a steady attention to the whole
inhale followed by a steadiness with a whole exhale for
staying close to the Simplicity of awareness of breathing not making it a big deal or
project a Simplicity of attention that stays steady
intimate with the full experience of breathing
in breathing
out from time to time letting there be a settling of the whole body into the
breathing
and see if you can not be interested in your thinking you don't have to listen to it
or attend to it let it reive to the background is not important for these
moments of meditation
and instead to
trust being with breathing
trusting a steady attention
that stays with the whole length of the
inhale and the whole length of the
exhale over and over again
and if it's helpful you might be counting the
breath to keep you
there
e
e for
he and the more fully you
can fill awareness with
breathing the less room there is for
thinking
e
for
e for
and if there's any way it feels as if you're holding yourself back from the
breathing relax that holding so it might feel more like
you're entering into the experience of the body
breathing
for
e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to whatever degree you can appreciate
a steadiness of attention here with the
breathing with yourself with the
body with being aware
itself even if it's a challenge is there some way that you can
appreciate a continuity of awareness
the kind of continuity of awareness you would offer to a
friend if you're listening to them to their challenge that they're
describing and need to talk about a continuity of being present
so they know that you care through how you
listen and may it be that the way that we learn to attend and be present for
ourselves in meditation may it support us in our
ability to listen well to others
to attend to others so we can understand them better know them
better may it be that this practice that we do supports us in our ability
to be attuned be considerate be respectful of other
people so they feel that our respect through how we are aware of
them how we listen and may it be that how we listen
to the suffering World his
medicine to any feeling that people have that they're alone
unattended uncared for po may we live in such a
way that we contribute to all beings being cared
for being respected and listened
to may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all
beings be
free and may our ability to be present for
others contribute to their well-being and
freedom
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this series on samadi
and Monday I talked about some Sadi as simplicity
yesterday as somebody as settling subtleness and today as steadiness a
steady attention to the present moment a steady attention to the experience we're
having that we're really settling on and um and this idea of steady
attention is uh closely connected to the idea of
um of a continu it of attention continuity in the present
moment and um and uh the idea is to uh
hang out with the breath so we get absorbed so we get more engaged in it
and some people find this hard to do because they expect that somehow they'll find in the breathing something
wonderful like there's a key there or some pleasure there or some something profound there to be found if they keep
looking at the breathing the breathing is a solution and
um the um and uh the real kind of
um um uh warmth and beauty and Delight
of samadi is not F found in the object that we pay attention to but in the
subjective experience of being intimate or connected or steadied absorbed in the
experience we're having so we don't want to look for the solution in the
experience of breathing but uh there something happens in the interactivity
the interaction between us and breathing us and the object of
concentration uh in the the way in which we attend to it the steadiness the
subtleness the the simplicity and the continuity of
attention that um that is uh more continuous than the
continuity of being lost in thought and um so to kind of stay and
rest there so uh for one of the things that
can support this uh steadiness and continuity of
attention is the is the wise use of our
imagination sometimes if we if we have the ability to imagine in a nice way in
our own way uh that somehow that some form of imagination that brings us um
connected and inspired and kind of riding along with the with the breathing it can be easier to have the continuity
so I'll offer you some examples and uh the idea is that U you find and um if
you want to do this you find an example that works for you so uh uh something I
did in my early years of practice was imagining that uh my INB breaths and out
breaths were like the slow gentle um uh movements of the W wings of
a large bird breathing in and out with was the way the wings going up and down
and sometimes with the exhale if was it all extended it was like I was gliding
along in the wind and then I would lift it up again and let them go down and
there was something about this for me this imagery of being in the high high
sky and gently kind of the breathing being intimately connected to you know
associated with the wings flapping that um got me kind of really engaged the
continuity staying right there with it um another thing that I've done is
sometimes I've imagin and I've told this many story many times before but that um
it's a little bit I used to when I was a little kid I I loved going on a push scooter and uh and the way that a push
scooter would work is that I would you know with one foot kick the ground to
push the scooter forward and then I'd ride the momentum until momentum started
to slow and then now gently push again ride push and so with for The Med
meditation and breathing the inhale was like the push and the exhale was riding the
momentum uh and it just felt so good to ride that momentum to the end of the exhale and then I would would gently
push with the inhale and that imagery doing it that way kind of harnessed my
imagination to help me be present rather than the imagination taking me off to
some other lands and time and things that were going going on uh just like
the counting is taking thinking and using it for the purpose of being present so there can be the wise use of
imagination that brings you into the present more rather than taking you
away so the the the example I used in the medit this last meditation of
putting your gentle safe hand on the on someone's back or feeling someone there
for you holding you um maybe you're walking in an unsteady way in a place
that it's a little dangerous and someone's just there letting you know they're there to catch you you know if
you fall they they'll they'll take care of you and or something like that so if
that you know that might be nice like just right there it's related to an imagination I
used also many years ago when I was in college I took a massage class and the
teacher taught us to um um to when you're massaging someone never uh have
your hand uh always have one hand that's always connected to the other the person you're massaging so there's no
interruption to that and there's no surprise of being touched again if you get some massage oil to you know
to to use more of it for the massage and so
um and so you always have that contact so I found that a a nice imagery
sometimes of being with a breath in meditation never lose contact stay there
but for some people that's not the right image some people the bird flying is not the right image um another image I've
used because I've been doing this for 50 years so I've had a series of them uh another one that I've enjoyed sometimes
is thinking of the exhale is writing a slide and I'm just kind of writing going
down like a little kid going on the slide woo you know just writing the slide and that kind of just kept me
right there and it kind of made it kind of fun and and kind of you know like a being on a
slide so you might have your own imagery that might work for you and uh
I know some people have the image of breathing as being a big wheel and that
they just the sense of this wheel turning um helps them stay with the like
almost like the inhale is and exhale are the Turning of the wheel and
um and uh just that simple one keeps them connected and
involved um some people the imagination is not what's going to help them stay
steady and continuous with the breathing um and there might be some uh some
something interesting about the sensations of breathing or more more usefully something um Pleasant about it
some pleasure that's be found there and I've used the for example I find that I find generally exhale to me more
pleasant than the inhale sometimes it's been the opposite but uh to be sure to be there for the
whatever Pleasant or pleasure satisfactory Sensations are there if in
the cycle of breath just and then ride it feel it sense it and uh some people
uh find that they can get absorbed in breathing because they begin really tuning into wherever there's some sense
of pleasantness pleasure in breathing I've known some people who've adjusted
their breathing just a little bit um just so it can be a little bit more pleasant um more enjoyable sometimes
breathing a little bit slightly bigger breaths sometimes uh relaxing and uh the
the belly and softening somewhere in the body so some part of the cycle of breath is
pleasant and um and so rather than imagination to help be present it's the
uh the ability to tune into something that's Pleasant with the breathing and riding that pleasure allowing oneself to
feel the pleasure you're taking it in and um and all
along uh this idea of steadiness and continuity of attention with breathing
uh uh should be done without any strain without any expectation without
measuring how well we're doing so that of course we're going to wander off of
course the continuity is going to not be continuous and um and so uh
find a way to meditate so that the the loss of touch with the breathing the
loss of staying connected and steady is folded in as part of a healthy
meditation it's not a problem it's it's not an but rather just of course your
mind's going to do that and then find a relaxed way to begin again to come back
again to come back again and here also I used the imagination
uh and I I don't I don't think I it at first it was um a choice or something I thought about
it just something uh that uh an image that arose as I was doing the practice
and that was that I learned to become at some point in this practice I learned to have a friendly attitude to towards my
friend my to my friend to my breathing to my thinking I didn't set it up as a
tension or as a problem but then if I found myself uh wandering off in thought
I wouldn't tense up I wouldn't be critical I wouldn't see it as a problem but the image I had was that
there was a horse that had escaped the Corral and um and so the way to bring it
back was to ride another horse and ride right kind of ride up right next to it
so being being companions riding together and there go along with the horse that escaped for a little while
and then take a Big Arc around
180° so that uh to uh to come back to the Corral come back to where we're
supposed to be and um and so I that that imagery came up as I would notice I was
thinking and I would kind of go along with a little bit I wasn't going to immediately tense up or do something
about it just know I was thinking be accompany thinking a little bit and then
gently uh kind of has this idea okay come back let's go back let's make a big circle not a jerk back not uh you know
uh just a you turn around 180 degrees and just jerk back but just gentle long
curve and how long would that take maybe it took two or three seconds to do that
process and then when I came back to breathing that way um
uh it was I was much more settled than I was
before went you know when beginning of wondering off in thought and it was okay
here I am and then okay let's have continuity Let's Be steady here let's be
committed in a loving way or absorbed in just the Simplicity of this
simple settled and um and steady
here so I hope these ideas give you something to find for yourself that
supports you with this steadiness continuity of attention and then I thought that um uh
an announcement to make is that uh this Friday uh we would have a uh community
meeting for 7 a sa for those of you who can and I'll post a zoom link on imc's
what's new and and um in the IMC calendar and also Friday I'll post it on
the on uh here on YouTube and uh for the
chat and uh so then at 7:45 we'll switch over to uh zoom and we can have some
period of question answers some discussion we'll do a a breakout group so those of you can um you can all kind
of meet a few of the people who are part of this online s so thank you very much and I look
forward to being here again tomorrow morning