hello and welcome to our meditation and in this now multi-week
series on samadei that we are touching into the
topic of Janna and Janna is uh deep absorption it's not something that we
storm not something we assertively aggressively expect to experience
push ourselves to have it's a little bit like grace it's a little bit like um
gift that we receive that we set up the conditions for some deep letting go set
up the conditions for some deep settling steadiness that leaves us deeply
absorbed deeply engaged interested um
uh it kind of interests that it's almost enraptured in the simplicity of the
meditative experience and um so how we approach
sami how we orient ourselves towards it is very important and there is something
called the approach stage and part of the function of that stage is to uh reorient
us in a way where we're not selfish not greedy not
um be not feel like we're in charge it's up to us but orient ourselves with some
feeling of receptivity of of um gratitude gratefulness
uh of appreciating there's something more profound operating here than ourselves
as the agents of change meditative change and so some people find that the
reorientation uh at the beginning of meditation they
uh express their faith they evoke their faith some people have deep kind of
faith in dharma Buddha dharma sana they chant the refues for themselves
something that allows for shift what we what would be what is a little bit
um a um lost opportunity is if we just live our life
and then just slide into our meditation seat and just continue the mind stream and the momentum of our day just without
any other concern uh there is a way to somehow go through a little process of
reorientation this is not daily life as usual this is not the mental stream as usual that
we're going to connect to we are reorient reorienting
ourselves and one ritual for that reorientation is the care we give to our
posture that posture is not incidental it's not just to make a posture which is
only comfortable enough that not disturb our meditation because we're s it's cozy
and comfortable but to take care and time to
get into the posture um to make that a ritual
transition a ritual reorientation to now something
profound is going to might happen or we're going to make ourselves
available receptive ready
open in a way that maybe maybe our minds or hearts are not as we go about our
daily life so taking
a a comfortable but alert
posture so there's some degree small even small
degree that the posture evokes
attention a physical alertness a physical presence here at this time at
this place in this
body lining up the vertebrae of the
spine placing the hands in a way where the hands themselves the way the
arms are
provokes a certain kind of
attention
attentiveness and as part of this ritual reorientation to another way of being
than the usual one another set of values another way
of tending attending to this life of ours
part of that ritual is gently closing your
eyes gently relaxing the eyes the eyes don't have to work in
meditation they can relax
and and then take a few moments again part of this ritual transition
reorientation to feel your body in some broad global
way
kind of like if you step into from out the ordinary
life into a sacred
place that we enter maybe through a door through an opening a gate
not casually but we enter
it with all of who we are and so we
enter by feeling our body entering our
body and if it seems nice you can readjust your posture a little bit more
and then to begin orienting
yourselves on breathing without breathing deeper or
fuller slow the inhale so it just takes longer to
inhale slow the exhale but do so just short of being
uncomfortable so maybe just a moment or two
slower to do the ordinary amount of breathing
in slowing your breathing down
enough that you can feel the body's desire to breathe
and trusting how the body is breathing at
this moment not making anything a
problem and if you prefer you can go back to your usual speed of
breathing maybe now a little bit more conscious of breath breathing
and as you exhale to soften your
body softening the edges of your body
softening the thinking
mind softening in the heart
and maybe as a act of love or
faith or tenderness let there be a Small pause at
the end of the exhale very short but long enough for
there to be a feeling of care tenderness
love or faith in this process of meditation
where the short pause is like saying
hello to the deeper meditative process that
you're inner life is capable of
maybe more capable than your
mind's belief that is it is in charge
and in whatever way there's some
pleasure gladness wellbeing or
joy however small it might be in whatever way you feel it in your
body
orient yourself with that by orienting connecting your
breathing to the
well-being as if breathing breathes with or through the well-being
or as if the
well-being is what's providing the awareness of
breathing it's [Music]
well-being that tends to the breathing
if there is any gentleness
tenderness in a very simple
happiness contentment deep in your
body or tingling along the surface of your
skin a happiness that feels calm and
peaceful allow that
to mingle with the body breathing
Where part of you gets absorbed pulled
into the mingling
of well-being and breathing
part of you gets pulled into the rhythm of
breathing where there's a
massage where there is a
gentle care between breathing
An embodied feeling of contentment
happiness wellbeing however small that feeling is
If there's any way in which you're holding yourself apart away
from where breathing and well-being meet mingle
See if you can let go give up the holding back holding away
from release yourself into the breathing
allow yourself to slide into the embodied
experience of breathing breathing through and
with happiness contentment
and as we come to the end of this
sitting take a few moments to feel whatever degree of
well-being you feel in your body
any warmth glow
tingling any radiance or
pleasure associated with a simple happiness well-being
and as if that well-being is being held in check held
within a certain limitation in your body certain
area as you breathe in stretch the area wide
as you let go breathe out let that well-being be
unbounded let it release almost as a
balloon where a person releases the string the balloon can fly out across
the world let your well-being free
into the sky the space around
you imagining that your happiness and
well-being can be shared can touch the hearts of others
that your happiness is not just your
own we are living in this planet in kinship
with all other people all other beings and may it
be that what we know about happiness
well-being is experienced fully in us so we can share it with
others may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we know these three these four
things so we're in a better position to wish it for others
may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you
so welcome back to this ongoing series on samadei and we're now this week covering
the first Janna the first level of absorptive immersive
meditation and one of the
great aspects of this sta
uh stage of meditation this area of meditation is that we're allowed to give
ourselves over to being happy we're allowed the the ability to trust joy and
well-being it's okay to give ourselves to
it and one of the reason there's a number of reasons why it's okay more
than okay it's actually beneficial and very important part of the Buddhist path
one is that the happier you can be in a genuine peaceful meaningful
way the more you know that this is a possibility for others and the more you can support
others and see people's potential for well-being the more I think it inspires
care and love for others and perhaps also it's a gift we
bring others our happiness is a gift it's
also a gift to ourselves because there's something about a peaceful healthy
happiness that's embodied and present that helps the mind get organized helps
the mind get become whole or be be fully here be immersed in this
experience and what immersed means in part it means we're not distracted we're
not divided we're not fragmented we're not
caught in any attachments or clinging this full embodied happiness is is a
there's a movement in it to spread out through our whole being and bump up
against the places where we're restricted where we're tight where we're holding where we're afraid
and it's a loving happiness that can s gently kind of touch the places that are
hard for us hold them care for them um
accompany them so that we're not over identified with our challenges with our
pains our emotional ch difficulties we don't we don't overidentify it so
we're subtly reinforcing them or you know picking the scab in a sense but
we're loving them we're caring for them we're offering them something profound nourishment of attention and care that
comes in the form of well-being and trust and confidence and allows us then to
continue on the path of being settled so uh in the teachings of the Janna it's
quite common to provide a listing of what johnic factors are present in each
of the four Jas and um and there's a in the first genre there's five factors and then as
we go along into the deeper Jas um certain ones of these factors fall away
and so there's a shorter list then and Um and so sometimes the ways that these
genres are taught is that there's a kind of quantum steps of letting go of
deepening of releasing as we go through this and uh
and as what gets released is the what's more coarse what's more um uh has has
more energy or more activation to it and so that we we let go of those so that we
can drop into the more subtle factors that are are much more sublime and more
peaceful and so there's a movement from coarser to more refined from more
activator energetic to less and less to more and more peaceful and
quiet so some people emphasize uh these stages as being the four stages and so
the first second third and fourth Janna and so there can be definitely a feeling
of kind of kind of taking a big step a quantum kind of sudden dropping and going further
opening further um but it doesn't have to be that way and sometimes there's an
overemphasis and attachment and expectation and drive to go from one to
the other uh and if instead what we do is we don't
focus so much on the stages as being these these uh you know
you know um raified kind of states that we go into i find it sometimes much more
useful to just learn to recognize the primary factors that characterize the
deepening of practice and so these the uh these five first johnic factors are
useful to recognize so I'll go through them there is the uh the initial application of
attention there's a sustained attention it's means placing our
attention someplace and keeping there for a while then doing it again like a
massage or kneading dough and then there's u uh there's uh
joy and um I'll talk a little more about joy tomorrow because such an important part of the beginning stage here but
there's joy and rapture and then uh the the um the
fourth factor is uh happiness suka some people will call it bliss some people
will call it because it's kind of deeply embodied um some people call it even
pleasure but that doesn't quite give it justice because it's it's so sublime so
satisfying so such a contentment that comes with it that I prefer to use the word happiness
and then there's uh becoming one the unification the onepointedness that I
talked about yesterday so these the initial application of
attention the sustained attention joy happiness and becoming
one and um and uh uh so these are the
five that are at play and um and it's nice to recognize them the one that
seems most important at this stage is is you know they're kind of in in order
initially we need some kind of subtle way intentionality subtle continuation
of some gentle effort to stay present we're pretty much locked in we're pretty
much not going anywhere it feels like there's the mind's not going to wander off and there's no discursive thinking
it's very peaceful uh but there's still there needs to be a little bit of kind
of staying here stay here be here yes i
like the word yes yes with this in this needing of our attention into this
present moment um so it's very subtle very slight but it's going to stay here
stay here and um and uh there can start being
this joy and the joy in compared to happiness the joy is is said to be even
though it's can be a lot of manifestation of of uh joyful energies in the body tingling thrill
uh it um it uh is understood to be more of a mental activity it's a little bit
the mind is a little bit excited a little bit delighted like when I say yes this is good it's a little bit more that
yes than the mind than it is uh to be as uh deep
contentment that the mind is hardly involved it's almost like the body the the
um the breath is involved in in saying ah this exhale
ah the happiness is deep that deep place of ah so the joy is a little bit of like a
yes and um but whatever this is both of them are present so you don't have it's
not that important at the moment to distinguish them initially but the instruction the Buddha
gives when this joy and happiness arises from really being in the moment in the
flow of the present moment is to relax with it open with it let it pervade suse
and spread the Buddha uses a series of words like this spread through the body
and so there's a tendency in the body to the body to be through body and mind to
hold things in check to hold things in place there's tension in our body there's tension in our mind there's uh
attachment to what's happening there's many ways in which we bound things up to keep it limited and the opportunity here
uh is to soften the body soften the attention
open to a rep receptivi receptivity in the body and mind and as we as we do
this uh blowing on the fire as we do this kneading of the dough as we do this
Yes it's almost like sometimes I've thought of it as a as um ironing out the
wrinkles on a sheet of paper just kind of spreading it out spreading it out until the sheet is completely flat with
no wrinkles at all um sometimes it's just more like um a gentle heater that's
heating up from inside and spreading out in all directions some people like the image of
light there's a light that's spreading uh golden light that's spreading through
the body and beyond and some people are much more physically oriented it's actually the
phys physical sensations of that joy the physical warmth glow tingling vibration
of it that uh pleasure of it that begins to flow outwards and the pleasure is
actually quite useful as an object at this point um we're letting that
pleasure spread and spread and spread so it's not kept bounded it's almost like a
letting go around it or with it so so there's nothing holding it you know from
spreading out beyond beyond us beyond our edges of our
body and um and uh I prefer some people will just focus on the pleasure itself
like become one with that pleasure uh I prefer to um have that pleasure and the
breath be cerminous the pleas the pleasure the well-being the joy to be
intimately associated with the breathing almost like the pleasure the joy and the
breathing are holding hands or there's or they have become one and um and so
this wonderful the rhythm of breathing is what supports the spreading the
letting go the opening of that well-being through everywhere so this can't of course be
done too easily or just you know sit down plop down and do this
uh this becomes the the instruction when
we finally arrive in the present moment we feel oh now I'm really here this is
good i'm not and that you know as I've said number of times now don't expect that
often and um um what you'd expect often is that
you're always a beginner and that is incredibly profound to always be a beginner and be content to practice with
how you are at any given time but if you do practice regularly every day every day that
slowly the tendency to go into deeper meditation will become easier and easier
there'll still be ups and downs through the days and weeks depending what's happening in your in your life but you
you're predisposing yourself to be able to go further and further over time and
for this samadei series as I've said uh this is a time in the series where I
want to encourage you again to consider meditating more uh maybe twice a day I
mean one once with with this uh YouTube offering then maybe one time on your own
then uh or if you really needed to support would like to support you can listen to the guided meditation again a
second time but it really kind of make this more part of your
life and so as you go through your daily life today um look again for the look for the
pleasure look for the times of well-being for most people there's a lot
more pleasure a lot more things that are joyful that's that are available to us
than we avail ourselves of that we take time to experience
the weather it's springtime here in the northern hemisphere maybe maybe there's
delightful colors of green or flowers or new life being born or maybe
there's delightful animal running around that brings you a lot of pleasure you see
someone smiling whatever it might be the small pleasures of life take time to feel those and your
ability to let go and feel the small pleasures might support you to feel
those pleasures in meditation as well may you be happy thank you