okay so hello to everyone from around the world so nice to see all of
you let's go ahead and prepare for
meditation so settling in finding a
posture that will be comfortable for you for a half hour or
so I invite you to close the eyes if that works for you bring the
attention inward having a sense of connection and
intimacy with your own experience at this moment perhaps starting with the
body noticing your posture maybe you're in the sitting
posture or you could be standing or lying down
and just having an overall General sense of the body in the position that it's
in and then inviting finding some kind of balance and
ease in the posture so checking to see if you're using
a lot of muscles to hold yourself in this position and seeing if you could find a position that's quite balanced so
that there's not much need for muscles to hold you
up softening
inviting ease in some of the main places we carry
tension so maybe in the face the
jaw inviting ease through the
shoulders down into the chest and the belly
muscles of the low
back
softening and also finding a comfortable position for the arms and legs
and then connecting in to whatever degree of groundedness you feel from having
balanced and invited ease in the body is there a sense of stability or
settledness in the physical aspect of you
maybe sensing the natural Stillness of the body when it's
sitting and even if the body is uncomfortable in certain ways you know
those pains and aches and challenges that we have
there can still be a sense of groundedness and connectedness to what you're sitting on
to the
Earth body is fine as it is
and to start off today in the mind and the
Heart the invitation is to evoke or connect in with the quality of
sincerity so maybe locating the part of your heart that is really sincere about
meditation or about the spiritual life and offering that
part Center Stage offering it respect and
care this may be only a small part or it may be a tentative part of
you but the suggestion is to give it a a warm welcome
today acknowledging it yeah there is in my heart a a depth of
interest in this
practice even if the rest of my life is busy or sometimes directed in other ways
yeah there is a part though that's really really
sincere and maybe it's easy to contact
that and then releasing
the explicit connection to that an opening to experience
will gradually open so beginning again with the experience of the body noticing now the
body in the space that you're in sense of the room around you or maybe you're
outside sense of your actual location in space
and then also a sense of the bodily
Sensations inside that you're
experiencing the clearest one might be the breath coming in going out
the body contains Myriad
Sensations just letting those come forth be noticed
opening further to include explicitly noticing the
sounds where you are there's the sound of my voice and
there may also be sounds in the room sounds outside
people animals electronic equipment
heaters the things in our lives
we don't need to put a lot of effort into trying to hold all of these things
that I'm naming at once it's just that we open to the potential for each one allowing that
into the field of our awareness if such a thing should come in
a sound or a sensation of the
breath and in the same way gently opening further to include any emotions
that may be present or maybe a general mood in the
heart how are you feeling in general and also the shorter
term flickers of emotion that come through
maybe there's a moment of
joy and then a lingering sense of
sadness maybe you have a general mood of ease this morning or afternoon or
evening and then a flicker of
irritation just letting those experiences play on the screen of the
Mind along with any other Sensations or sounds and physical experiences that are
coming
and see now if you can include thoughts and
intentions in this Same Spirit as things that simply arise and
pass coming in going out
thoughts also are just movements of mind maybe they have a physical feeling
also phenomena experiences that come and go
and all of this is known by this quality of
awareness of
knowing kind of a heartful knowing that's
open to whatever experience arises and allows any experience also to
pass the whole gamut of what comes into the human mind
and noticing that as we open gently piece by piece it is possible to be with
all of this in a restful
way for
it's also a natural part of the human experience that the mind gets distracted
or caught up or contracted around something in
particular and in that case you could reinvoke that part of you
that that is sincere and touch that distraction with
the sincerity of caring for your meditation
your spiritual life just
see see if that softens the sense of caught
upness
for for
for
the
I
and as you continue to rest with the flow of experience and what awareness is
now naturally knowing you could see what kind of
meditation or what happens in your practice if you
allow the sincerity to have some space will the Mind settle in and pick
up the breath will it stay in open awareness
what is the Dharma want to do in you right
now
for
for for
e
for
and gently now
reconnecting with the sense of the body sitting
allowing your awareness to generally
sense position of the Body Sensations in the
body noticing what kinds of emotions or
thoughts are present
if any and perhaps sensing
into any space that you feel in the mind or the heart or the
body that which surrounds our experience or which provides the
background for experience to arise in noticing the contrast the experiences
and the
space often when we let the Dharma lead both of those aspects become
clearer sharper
and perhaps considering As you move out of the meditation the session today into
your regular life how would it be to let the Dharma
if that terminology makes sense take something of the
lead bringing our spiritual heart to
bear on just the ordinary activities could be the same type of
activities but done from the sense of practice or from the sense of walking
the path the benefits that would bring to our own
heart and also to others without our even having to talk
about our practice or the Dharma we would be expressing that
somehow there's a saying in the Dharma that
others are not so happy when I'm a Buddhist but they're very happy when I'm
a Buddha so carrying with
us our sense of the Dharma and the path for the benefit of for
[Music]
[Music] so I'd like to start today with a story
that was told to me by an older man probably in his
70s and he just showed up one day in a class that I was teaching I didn't know
him before and he said that 50 years ago roughly he
had experienced a profound spiritual opening that was so profound he couldn't
quite relate to it at the time and his response was just to go
back to his regular life to his career his family other things um but this experience that he
had had kept lingering in the back of his mind and sometimes he had made attempts
during his life to connect with spirituality but he hadn't really landed on anything that felt right for him and
so he had just um had just LED his life as as was
expected in the world and when he talked with me about it it was clear that his heart was
hurting in some way he had set aside something that was deeply meaningful to
him him for decades uh in order to live a more conventional
life and I wondered if he was bringing all of this to me because something in
his subconscious was sensing that maybe he didn't have much time left in this
life or at least you know not much time when he would have good enough
health so I felt like what the thing to do was was to strongly encourage him to
get serious about his spiritual seeking I think I even said something to the effect of hey you may not have much time
to resolve this yearning in your heart so go out and find what you need to find
and this is it and he didn't come back so um but I got
the sense something had landed so I hope he found what he was looking for even after a 50-year delay
and I open with this story which I know is kind of a powerful story uh in order
to say a couple of things directly first of all it's never too
late to get started um but second you do need to act on your heart's calling if you're
feeling such a thing so if you've had some kind of an opening or a yearning or
an intuition about the spiritual life if we have that but we don't give it any
space so if we keep living in the way that's expected by the people around us
and by the world then it will fade a bit it doesn't you know it's like a plant
that needs sunlight and space in order to grow and it can't do that if we don't
give it any space so you know the alternative to
that is to give your spiritual calling some space to take root and to grow and
to see what comes of that and I've noticed that people who prioritize their
heart's wishes deepest wishes may not always have an easy life but they tend
not to have any regrets either so we've made it to the last day
of this week about our spiritual direction that we might be thinking
about at the beginning of a new year and so maybe it's time to ask a
question what are you doing with your life it's an important question at any
stage of life actually and you know how can a person use this life well I think
that's a great question and I love it because it has so many answers there isn't just one way um but there maybe is
your way and so you know maybe one way to answer this question in a very
general way is to see our life as an act of walking a path you know to consider
ourselves to be a practitioner that's what I am I'm a bunch of other things too you know maybe
a parent a partner a worker a Community member a friend to VAR in various other
situations but at the heart of it all you know I'm a practitioner of some kind
so the theme this week of Letting Go and cultivation maybe culminates in these
Notions of a path and a practitioner and what is that for
us so I think even if we have a family and we're working and other things we
can still Orient our lives around the spiritual life and that makes a difference somehow that changes how
things unfold somehow
probably it's a distinct group of people in the world who see Life as a
practice there are some who do and some who don't and we wouldn't expect that everyone
would but I think the ones who do are somehow concerned with finding
Excellence with finding human flourishing and maybe with engaging
differently in the world than the more conventional way of being I've certainly found that you know
as a te teacher who connects with people who come to me about such things yeah I
do see that that there's this this group that are orienting around practice has
really good effects so but to engage in a life of practice if that's of interest
does mean making some choices and this is not just a Buddhist idea I think many spiritual teachers and
philosophers and guides and counselors have noted that some kind of discipline
or conscious engagement with our life is needed if we want to grow spiritually
you know what does it mean to be a practitioner so I wanted to suggest
today some uh qualities of a practitioner that
um that you may consider and consider what they look like in in your own case
because I think each one has um many different
manifestations and so the first one you know the First Quality that is shared by
people who consider their life to be walking a path I'm just going to use the blunt word which is I think they share
the quality of renunciation um recalling also that renunciation is the first of the three
wise intentions of the Eightfold Path that the Buddha named so what does that mean though it
it I think it's simply means that we're fueled by an internal calling so to to
practice we really do have to give up some things at the very least if you're going to sit for an hour a day that's an
hour that you don't do something else and you know we give up certain
things for the purpose of having a deeper and richer and Fuller life in various
areas so I don't know if pronunciation is the right word for that as it has
kind of connotations that are not so positive but I'm meaning it in a positive sense of uh letting go of what
is not supportive for this path that we're wanting to walk and so maybe there
are certain areas that we have to uh particularly look at in that case and
one of them is of course the material life that's maybe what we first think of with
renunciation but I don't think renunciation in this case means some
kind of restriction or narrowing or
um yeah cutting off but really more a real investigation of what is material
sufficiency in our life learning what is just enough so that we don't have extra
burdens on the Mind material things take up mental space and so if you're wanting
to use your mental space for service for for practice for meditation for retreat
for doing things that are meaningful um we don't want to have too many extra things that we're managing um but you do
need to have enough in order that life is uh comfortable enough secure enough
assured enough you have access to health and good food and all of that so this is
I think uh something that has to be done consciously so really looking at our material life to have the right amount
that frees us from fear and also from the need for overwork and over consuming
that can happen in our conventional culture so the material life is worth
examining in light of a spiritual life and then the second area is maybe of
renunciation is maybe seeing beyond the conventional
expectations so giving up con conventional views if you will um
so what is our relationship to what our society says we're supposed to be doing
you know get an education get a job get the right house have this or that keep up with the
neighbors Etc um it's okay to uh live a
life that looks conventional in certain ways but where are you coming from in
doing that you know is it um are we just buying into do everything that Society
tells us we should want and need and will make us happy or have you discovered in some way that those things
don't necessarily bring happiness that's what a lot of brings a lot of people to
the spiritual practice maybe they haven't quite articulated this but they're coming in the door because what
they were told would make them happy didn't actually fulfill that and the
Buddha picks right up on this in his teachings he's very direct about this and says yeah these things are not so
satisfying but it's okay you don't that doesn't mean depression and confusion
there's a there's this path that does bring actual satisfaction and actual
happiness and so we have to um again work in this area of how do we relate to
the messages that we hear every day and see every day uh and yet something is
calling us differently in our heart and there's I think a fair amount of work in being able to navigate that skillfully
gracefully uh keeping up the connections and relationships and factors of our
life that are needed this has always been true in whatever culture uh religion and spirituality has arisen in
so practitioners have to navigate that it can help to have a
teacher and then um maybe another large area another main quality of a
practitioner is what I like to call converting all problems to internal
problems and this is um this doesn't say that all problems are internal but one
quality of a practitioner is to look first inside to always try to find the
source of our suffering or struggle in our own relationship with experience
this will serve you very well in the long run if you're walking a path and being being a practitioner in life is to
first look at how we can change how we can shift that allows the Dharma space
to grow each of these areas are ways of creating space that lets the Dharma have
something to move into so that we're not covering it over like that man did for 50 years and not giving space for uh
something beautiful to grow so people with these qualities of
renunciation and of looking internally first I think have a certain depth and
strength that others can feel and interestingly what we discover when we
take on these qualities of practi of a practitioner is we discover softness
humility love compassion all sorts of things that um
come out of creating that space for the heart to grow so practitioners are moving toward
becoming both stronger and softer becoming freed from the compulsions of the heart that narrow us and bind us and
make us harder and also weaker so this gives us a general idea
of what letting go and cultivation can cover in their full breadth and you
might see if you've had specific New Year resolutions or intentions like
we've talked about this week how they might fit into these ideas of Letting Go
cultivation of material sufficiency of
um having an internal sense rather than just following societal conventions and
also uh bringing all of our problems into internal problems can we change
ourselves in some way so I want to read a quote from Steven Bachelor about creating a path
that I find very beautiful uh it's a couple paragraphs a little long but just just hang in there and and see how it
lands as we learn to play this complex instrument of Bones flesh nerves
impulses thoughts and feelings we trace a path that weaves its way like a
Channel Through the landscape of our experience it is Guided by an intuitive
yearning for what we value most deeply its space is the openness we are able to
tolerate within our hearts and Minds it is sustained by the networks of
friendship that Inspire us to keep going the path follows the Contours of
our life as one day turns into the next it is found amidst the most mundane of
circumstances as well as the most Sublime to create a path is to become
intimate with the space opening up within around and before us
this intimacy comes from the mindful awareness of what is unfolding in our
body feelings minds and worlds from moment to moment we get used to the
taste the feel the texture of the path it ceases to be something to which we
self-consciously Aspire and when we stray from it we feel its loss as an act
of self- betrayal so I really like this notion of the path
being something that's unfolding right here from connecting to
this experience here and now and creating space for the Dharma to move us
forward into the next moment it may be powerful and profound and it can be making coffee for
your family so um so returning to the foundational suta
from the dhap that we read at the beginning not engaging in what's
unskillful engaging in what is skillful and purifying one's mind this is the
teaching of the Buddhas so how does this look for you as we launch into
2025 it's your life and I think you won't regret um making it into a
spiritual path so my wish for all of us in 2025 is to give ample space to the
Dharma to let it grow and flower in whatever way it can in your life for the
benefit of you and everyone so thank you so much it's been a beautiful week be well