okay So welcome everybody Welcome from uh from foggy
Santa Barbara which is our typical spring uh summer weather here Typical
June weather We call it June gloom Hopefully it gets a little bit sunnier in July
there's a you know mental activity in the relationship to uh to seeing and
having perceptions about the weather just to be noticed
So today is the the last day of our week's exploration of what the Buddha described as making up the world the six
sense spheres uh these six pathways through which we meet all the experience
of our lives And I've been spending the week with you looking at these because
um our relationship with them is kind it's like the most basic way that we
create obstacles to the clear seeing that leads um to insight in our practice
and it's also the most basic way that we can let go of those obstacles Where do the obstacles arise
they arise in our minds The mind has a mind of course we know
has a really big job in in our life It's in charge of our relationship with all
the other physical senses with our relationship of what makes up our world
It's part of our world It interprets the world for us It guides how we interact
with all the situations and people that we come in contact with in our lives
Without it we could not uh uh function And we know this Of course that's
nothing new And we also know that the the mind's activity can get us in
trouble The kind of spinning out that the mind can do chewing on some old
grievance conceiving elaborate fantasies going down a rabbit hole of judgment and
blame sometimes of ourselves sometimes of others what is called papancha in the
texts probably a word familiar to many of you mental proliferation it's
probably the biggest source of duca the biggest source of suffering that we create for ourselves in our
lives so attending to the arising of an unhealthy attitude or of some kind of uh
habitual reactivity in the mind before it runs off into this proliferation this
flood of conceiving that can help us avoid so much dooka in our lives and
it's something we can learn to become more skilled at to to catch the beginning of the inclination to stop the
thinking train before its engine gets going You know how energy builds as we
start to think about something that has you know that has emotional impact for usually it really it builds and
builds So the path of practice in Buddhism could be you know could be characterized as gradually inclining the
mind in the direction that gets us out of that trouble the onward leading direction
toward what is beautiful toward what is wholesome skillful cusala and away from
what is the opposite of those and uh you know every situation in life is made up
of different kinds of of sense contact Remember it is that is our world
So attending to how the mind reacts to different kinds of situations It's a
it's a training in learning where the onward leading direction lies It helps
develop the the discernment and the energy we need in order to keep moving
in that direction So today I'm going to talk about um the last of the six senses Um
and I and I I want to bring the mental factor of vaydana into the into the mix
because vadena accompanies every moment of sense contact that is of course every
moment of life It plays a big part in the arising of feeders and it plays a
really big part in how feeders can be abandoned as well
So first before I get into that let's uh let's
meditate Taking your posture adjusting if if you need
to I need to adjust a little bit myself here
just to find that place of uh stability you know
balance And there can be ease and uh and alertness as well
and doing a little body scan if that's helpful to you Looking for those places where
there's
tension and just uh seeing if they can ease
up soften relax a little bit
Maybe using the breath to assist with that
And then letting the breath be the the center of your attention for for a
little while
Just being receptive to the sensations of of
breathing not reaching out for them grasping at
them We will breathe And the sensations that
accompany that breathing they will they will be there They can be known
Just simply Okay
Now if you're if you're feeling relatively settled like to invite you to
just open to uh to whatever is arising um in your
experience being receptive keeping that receptive uh
attitude noticing the arising of sensations of visual images of
[Music] sounds whatever is
arising Just being uh
receptive And and we know that
As we said thoughts will arise and emotions will
arise A sense of an experience being pleasant or unpleasant will
arise Forms of mental activity and we can be present to those
in a receptive way as well
And sometimes we will get caught I'll take hold of a thought or
image and and start to expand on
it And then we notice and we can let go if that's easy
And if you find that difficult you know attend to how the body
is when there is thinking with some kind of urgency some kind of uh a needy
quality driving it What are the effects you feel in the
body are they pleasant are they unpleasant
just invite a relaxed receptive awareness You know like sitting back and
watching the stream of sensations and and mental activity that
arise This is our world This interplay of physical senses and the
mind And every time we get caught in the mental
activity takes us away from being present We can recognize that and just
see if we can let it go Noticing the effect it has on our state
So what's what's going on in the body and what's going on in the
mind what's the effect of what's going on in the mind on the body
we can just simply know know that know each of those
things Now moving into evaluating
analyzing judging
It's all natural It's
arising The unfolding of our lives
Just see if you can know it simply with
easeful energy with with kind awareness
And everyone in the world
uh has some has these five physical senses in this mind to to work with
unless they're in some way injured in one of those
areas But this is the the way we all
um make our world could perceive and conceive our world all over everywhere
everyone
And those of us here we can take those uh those senses those the
abilities that are associated with those senses and we can use them in a way that
uh that brings some uh goodness into the world
that brings kindness and care
friendliness wisdom a little bit of
spaciousness And I hope we will do that so that we're adding a little bit
to the goodness in the world so that all beings
may be safe All beings may be
happy All beings may be healthy And all beings may have ease in
their lives And all beings everywhere may be
free
[Music]
Thank you for your practice Thank you for the practice all this
week and welcome again And uh today is the the last day
of this brief really brief investigation of the of the six sense spheres and the
and the fetterss that can arise in relation to them Anytime there's um sense contact
any kind of sense contact there's also some kind of mental processing of that
contact And what that mental activity begins
with is something that I think we're familiar with probably an immediate
simple response experiencing the contact as either pleasant unpleasant or
neither And that response is called vana in the Buddhist texts And I would
imagine you've heard many talks about this uh very simple basic and powerful
mental response which is happening constantly in every moment of sense
contact which we know in fact is every moment of our lives unless we're
unconscious So vadna is not a fetter but it is seen
as the trigger for all the mental activity that follows that often follows
sense contact you know which includes vets The word va is you know is most
often translated into English as feeling tone feeling tone the tone of a feeling
Another translation comes from psychology and also from chemistry Veilance you know positive negative or
neutral veilance And I I kind of like that one except that positive and
negative they kind of they seem to have a little judgment uh um connotations with them And and that's
not what's being pointed to with with va hedonic tone That's another translation
but seems a little bit opaque to me Gil has been using the word sensation
lately just pleasant or unpleasant Pleasant or painful
sensation And the word vena itself the poly word vena it comes from a root that
has meanings of both sensing and knowing Kind of maybe a merging of the two in a
way So sometimes instead of pleasant and
unpleasant the words used are pleasant and painful which are you know more literally accurate because the the poly
words for these two flavors of vadena are suka which which um you're probably
remembering from Gil's talks about um samadei can mean happy contented it has
a really delightful aspect to it and duka suffering stress stress discomfort
unease So suka and duka pleasant and unpleasant pleasant and painful And
there are lots of complex ideas about uh this
this reaction response Uh Bikubodi calls it an
affective factor that is in essence very simple And the reason for all the
different ways of defining and describing it is that simple though it is it's understood to have a lot of
power in driving our thinking and our behavior It's a kind of mental activity
and it acts as a bridge between the body and the mind
So conditioned on on sensing an experience as either pleasant or
unpleasant different mental states and mental activity will arise
We hear that often if an experience is um received as either as neither
pleasant nor unpleasant then the typical response will be boredom or zoning out
And pleasant vadena of course um commonly conditions mental activity in
the in the desire realm moving towards something and unpleasant or painful vena
conditions the mental activity in some flavor of the aversive
realm We don't have conscious control over vena It will arise It's it's
natural It will arise but we don't have to obey it And that's a really important
point That's a kind of pivotal point in our practice are practiced with feeders
are practiced with all the kinds of mental activity that
exist So in every instance of sense contact one of these ways uh of that the
contact is felt will arise immediately What feels like simultaneously to me with the contact
itself And if we aren't paying attention especially if the pleasantness or the
painfulness are are strong or intense that vena is likely to lead to some kind
of reactivity that is to a fetter to a knot and uh this sequence you know this
sequence is very famously laid out in the the teachings on the 12 steps of
dependent origination that that the very systematic description in the text of
how dooka arises in us The four middle
steps of the 12 in that cycle are the sense spheres sense contact vadena and
then some form of craving craving for or craving against we could say dependent
on the flavor of the of the vadena And vana is often described as the
weakest link in this chain of how uh duca arises If we notice
it and then just leave it be This is pleasant this is
unpleasant without elaborating we can stop craving and clinging in their
tracks The chain is broken and duca doesn't arise
So we can use va in the in the same way in practicing uh recognizing fetterss
When there's a sensation at one of the sense stores that we sense as pleasant we can know that this is
pleasant and it can be possible to go no further I take a piece of chocolate from
its wrapper I eat it savoring it and it's very pleasant I recognize this is
very pleasant And I stop right there before the desire for another uh piece
catches me and gets me eating I have avoided a feder arising And the same can
is you know is with unpleasant There's a kind of mental
reactivity happening We can abandon the fetter that has arisen We hear a dog barking close by Perhaps it's kind of
loud There's unpleasant vena And then we begin to feel some judgment
arising Oh they should keep that dog indoors That dog needs to be trained And
if we're paying attention right there we can notice okay there's a feder rising
There's some judgment There's some ill will Notice how it feels in the body maybe And right there I don't want to
move into that mind state I prefer to be at ease We abandon the feder
And the same is uh uh with what we experience as as
pleasant You know I can take that same piece of chocolate from the wrapper I eat it It's pleasant And then my hands
start to open the wrapper again and I feel the urgency of desire to have
another piece and I stop right there I recognize the feder and I abandon it Or
maybe maybe I have another piece and before I recognize the feather or before I'm willing to abandon
it So it's possible to notice the notice the vna and not go beyond there And it's
and it's and it's possible to just begin to feel the arising of uh of what is
really painful and to maybe stop it right there as
well And as we practice in this way you know hopefully we can let that pleasant
or unpleasant just be known and left right there And even after the feder is known you know after there is some
aversion or craving present we can recognize the feder that's arisen we can
stop right there not let it get the upper hand you know not let it tie us
down keep us stuck in desire or aversion Remember the teaching from the
Buddha on the gratification the danger and the escape Part of feeling the danger of the fetterss that arise is
feeling the dooka in the feder itself Craving aversion delusion denial These
are unpleasant mental states They're dooka Becoming more and more sensitive
to the duca that is inherent in craving or aversion You know then the the
painful vena these mental states uh becomes clearer It helps us to let go of
them So va like all mental activity is of
course conditioned on past experience It isn't inherent in the experience just
like the the mental activity of a feather is not inherent in the in the
contact in the sense contact really in a sense I've been talking about va in a way all all week
long the knots that arise the fed feathers that the Buddha described all
the varieties and relatives of craving or aversion or delusion that present
themselves in relation to sense contact They're conditioned by this even more
basic immediate sense of pleasant unpleasant or
neither They are conditioned And because they are conditioned they can
change Our mind and hearts are continually being reconditioned by our
lives as we live them Conditioned by everything that we come in contact with
Practicing the dharma is one of the conditions that we bring into our lives
And practicing the dharma conditions the mind in the direction of freedom of
beauty of deep sensitivity So that our minds and hearts are are moving in the
direction of freedom of insight of peace
The teachings on va in the in the discourse on the foundations of uh of
mindfulness satipana suta they distinguish between va that is worldly
and unworldly or worldly and spiritual or as the gil has recently translated
the words as surface and deep and vana in relation to deep
experience is that that's experienced with samadei with the cultivation of beautiful qualities of heart and mind
And pleasant vadna in this context it doesn't lead to craving It leads to appreciation to gratitude to meta And un
unpleasant vna in this context is more connected with the desire for liberation
kind of a you know a kind of painful longing for what is wholesome and
free and attending to this deeper vena It can really help guide our practice in
a beautiful direction Beautiful direction But that's a whole other topic
for another time Today I've only been speaking about vayna
um associated with sense contact the the worldly variety of
vena It's something to really pay attention to It's got a lot of power in
our uh in the activities of our of our mind So u very simple and uh a key place
to look So I hope this uh this week's topic
has been has been useful to you I've really enjoyed being with you all this week Remember the Buddha's words for it
is in this fathoml long body with its perceptions and mind that I describe the
world its origin its sessation and the practice leading to its sensation
These six sense spheres the physical organs of of sensation their objects and
the mind with all all its myriad activities our
world And by attending very carefully to what arises in this world noticing when
what arises taking us in the direction of just of becoming a slave to comfort
and pleasure or a slave to anger resentment judgments about ourselves and
others Noticing that how we relate to what's happening is what's holding us down
keeping us from being opening open spacious wise and
caring When we attend very carefully in this way uh we don't have to obey those
inclinations When we see what is arising in our minds when we are mindful we have
choices Until we see we really don't have a choice our old
conditioning way back to latent tendencies will uh choose for us But the
dharma gives us choices It shows us a healthier way of relating to what's oper
operating in us A healthy way of relating to what's happening on the
outside What's happening how we relate to it The dharma dharma practice dharma
practice moves us in the direction of what is kusula what is
skillful what is kalana what is beautiful what is wise what is conducive
to growth the dharma is onward leading my
favorite words in the in the dharma
teachings so I'll leave you with that And uh uh next week Kim Ellen will be be
with you and uh with all of us And uh I wish you uh I wish you a wise
relationship to uh all that is happening in your six sense spaces and much joy
coming out of that Thank you for being with me this week