so here we are with our second um I don't know is the word installment
that sounds kind of funny to say this word installment the
second day on this idea of poetry of practice can't believe I've done this
three other times but there's this way in which um poetry touches us in a
different way than just the more dactic teaching I like to do dactic teaching
I've done plenty of it but I also like to just use language maybe in a
different way because there's this way in which poems can be you might even say a
doorway to this another world where we're using ordinary words but their
arrangement of them kind of like evokes something a little bit different than
EXP exping this poetry is this arrangement of words that maybe includes
a rhythm maybe it uh points to maybe a possibility or some Wonder or some
openness which so much is about practice that can be a tremendous support for our
practice so with that is just a very short introduction I will lead us in a guided
meditation and I'll drop in a poem it'll be this same poem as yesterday because
as some of you know my little talking about the poem afterwards got all garbled due to the a mistake I made U
with the technology so just an invitation that when I drop
in the poem you don't have to figure it out you don't have to understand it you don't actually have to do anything have
to do anything maybe just allow it to touch you you and maybe it does and
maybe it doesn't and can that be okay okay so here we are with a guided
meditation taking a meditation
posture a big deep breath as a way to connect to the body connect to the
experience allowing yourself
to settle
in it can be with a big exhale can be a little bit of a letting
go
we're here in this moment this
location what would it mean to feel connected to the sitting surface you
find yourself on at this moment whatever that surface might be
cushion chair bed couch
floor feeling the pressure against the
body we're grounded and connected
there's a way that feeling connected to our sitting surface and serve as a
Bast so that we're not getting pushed around and lost in thoughts
can you be in a meditation posture and know that you're in a meditation
posture what is the experience of being in this posture Che
maybe a little bit of a body scan just noticing any obvious areas of
tension tightness
contraction they're welcome too you don't have to try to get rid of
them
around the eyes or the mouth common places to hold tension
the shoulders letting the shoulder blad
slide down the
back the chest
it to just soften and
open dearmour
itself and the belly
our beautiful
bellies bring in some appreciation perhaps and some ease
again feeling our contact with our sitting
surface feeling connected grounded we're here
then resting attention on the sensations of breathing
whether that's the movement of the chest or the belly or maybe the feeling of air
going in and out of the [Music] nose wherever feels
comfortable for you just resting attention there
what if meditation weren't a self-improvement
project instead was just an opportunity to land
here
e
e e
going to drop in a poem you don't have to figure it
out you don't have to understand it you don't have to appreciate
it you don't have to do
anything maybe it lands maybe it doesn't that's
okay maybe there are parts that Shimmer for
you maybe there
isn't this poem is prescription for the dis disillusioned by Rebecca Del
Rio same PA I read
yesterday prescription for the disillusioned by Rebecca Del
R come new to this day
remove the rigid Overcoat of experience the notion of
knowing the beliefs that cloud your vision leave behind the stories of your
life spit out the sour taste of unmet
expectation let the stale scent of what ifs wafted back into the swamp of your
useless fears arise
curious without the armor of certainty the plans and planned results
of the life you've imagined live the life that chooses
you new every breath every blink of your astonished
eyes e
read it again prescription for the
disillusioned by Rebecca Del Rio
come new to this day remove the rigid Overcoat of
experience the notion of knowing the beliefs that cloud your
vision leave behind the stories of your life spit out the sour taste of unmet
expectation let this stale scent of what if's sft back into the swamp of your
useless fears arrive
curious without the armor of certainty the plans and planned results
of the life you've imagined live the life that chooses
you new every breath every blink of your astonished
eyes
e e
and we allow the freshness
each moment to be
experienced
e
e e
for
[Music]
so I just ring the bell I don't know how that sounds for you
guys hopefully it's it was okay if you wanted to put something in the chat
that' be helpful for me to know if that way of ringing the bell works
s great okay great
okay so again I'll uh talk a little bit about
this poem and again for those of you who weren't here earlier I made a mistake last time that's why I sounded like
monks on speed I heard a number of different descriptions of it so um my my
apologies so I'll just say a few word of um a few words about
poetry that uh it allows language to touch touch us in a different
way and I would say so much about meditation practice is maybe like
opening up to different ways it's not our usual way of being in the world it's
not our usual way of maybe interacting or um feeling into our
experience and there's this way also like maybe the rhythms of poetry have this uh Beauty to it that maybe our
regular self speech or the speech that we do with uh
others is uh not um it's different I'm looking over this is
I'm looking over the chats to make sure that everything is okay yes okay here we
go okay so the poem for today prescription for the disillusioned the
same one as it was yesterday and I'll talk about it again differently
today I'll read it again prescription for the disillusioned
by Rebecca Del Rio come new to this
day remove the rigid Overcoat of experience the notion of knowing the
beliefs that cloud your vision leave behind the stories of your
life spit out the sour taste of unmet
expectation that the stale scent of what if sft back into the swamp of your
useless fears arrive
curious without the armor of certainty the plans and planned results
of the life you've imagined live the life that chooses you new every breath every blink of your
astonished eyes I think this poem is uh lovely and
it's a I would say a really good description of a meditation practice and I appreciate that titled prescription
for the disillusioned so what does it mean to be disillusioned often it means that we're
disappointed and perhaps something we had been looking forward to turns out to not be as good as what we were expecting
perhaps yesterday there was a daret that you were expecting to be able to be
comprehensible and it turned out to not be comprehensible and maybe there was this like a disillusion this
disappointment so there's this way which is a Perfectly Natural and normal thing to do in which we
imagine something about how we think something will go in the future I'd say
we probably do this for almost everything we imagine and then we're
laying that on top of our experience and then they don't match so we have what's actually happening then
we have our experience and they don't match and then there's this way in which
we feel disappointed and then we're trying to manipulate our experience so that it matches our
expectation kind of forgetting that our expectation is completely 100% imaginary
fabricated just collection of thoughts in the mind what's actually happening is
what meditation practice is pointing to and so when we notice this uh
occurring when our expectations aren't being met there's this way that we can
use it as an indicator or an encouragement to practice this
recognition that what is it that is causing these imaginary ideas about what
the future will be we could say it's our beliefs so that the underlying beliefs
the ones that we most likely are not aware of are influencing what we're
imagining what what's actually happening is what's actually happening we don't get to control that have you noticed but
we're trying to somehow control it by placing our expectations on top so what
are our expectations what's fueling them and part of that are our
beliefs so do we have beliefs that we should be comfortable at at all times do
we have a belief that the world owes us something or do we have a belief that
perhaps the world is uh an unsafe place or maybe we have this idea that um think
whatever our expectations are they should just be met dang
it so when we find ourselves disappointed it's an excellent occasion
to just gently inquire well what were the assumptions I was making what did I
think was going to happen again we don't have to make the the experience of
having expectations be wrong because that's natural and of course we're going to do it but what the practice is
pointing to the opportunity to just notice this difference between what's actually happening and our thoughts
about what's happening we will always be disillusioned as long as we're thinking
that our thoughts are what should be happening to practice is pointing to
just pay attention to what's actually happening and it could be as our poet
here is pointing to there's often some fear that's underneath that's fueling the underlying
belief maybe that's like underneath even the beliefs or maybe it's coloring or
coding our beliefs which is coloring and coding our expectations fear of being
alone fear of discomfort fear of feeling uncomfortable emotions
that maybe we feel are lurking just underneath the surface fear of
death fear of somebody close to us a loved one being harmed or death of them
or something there's so many different things that can be uh fueling our
expectations which lead to this disillusionment and then the title of
this poem is prescription for the disillusion so this idea of prescription we could say prescription
is a recommendation that's by someone who is deemed to be authoritative and
the Buddha was sometimes considered to be a great physician who was treating what ails us
what ails all of us Dua right Dua this
single word that stands for such a wide such a wide range of experiences from
just the mildly irritating to the tragic horrifying the single word covers this
wide uh range and we could say some people have said that the Buddha's
formable truth is uh a way in which this great physician uh taught the world and
was helping there specifically in Ancient India but for us today so could say the first Noble Truth is the
diagnosis the truth of Dua that there's dooka when our expectations about what
we want doesn't match what's actually happening and then the there was this uh
um the Buddha it talks about the cause of this suffering we could say it's clinging it's clinging to our expectations or thoughts about how
things should be how we want them to be how we imagine them to be the prognosis
is good there can be an end to suffering this is the third Noble Truth and then of course the fourth Noble Truth is the
Noble 84 path I won't go into all steps of this but many of you will know that
one of them of course is mindfulness one of these eight is
mindfulness we can summarize the no eight-fold path is uh practices we do in
the world CA ethical uh mental development mindfulness concentration
and wisdom View and intention so the fourth Noble Truth is
the treatment plan that uh this great physician if you will that the Buddha
provides for us this prescription is the Noble eight-fold Path which emphasizes
the importance of being present for what is actually
happening which very often might be disappointment with what's actually
happening can we just be with the disappointment can we be with the experence experience of being
disillusioned or disenfranchised or just
sad about what's happening maybe it's not what's
happening and instead our poet is pointing to live the life that chooses you can you be with what's actually
happening and recognizing what's actually happening maybe there's a little bit of anger I want it to be this
way dang it and it's not so can we engage with life as it
unfolds without feeling like we have to wrestle it into submission but uh
instead is there's this way can we meet what's arising including not wanting it
to arise that way this practice meets us where we are where we are often is feeling
disillusioned disappointed and then maybe you'll say I
was working with this home disillusioned prescription for the disillusion sometimes there's tremendous
happiness and joy too right I don't want to make it sound like there's always this disappointment so but I'm
responding to this poem so I'll read this poem one more time prescription for the disillusioned
by Rebecca Del Rio come new to this day remove the
rigid Overcoat of experience the notion of knowing the beliefs that cloud your
vision leave behind the stories of your life spit out the sour taste of unmet
expectation let this stale scent of what ifs weft back into this swamp of your
useless fears arrive curious without the armor of
certainty the plans and planned results of the life you've imagined
live the life that chooses you new every breath every blink of your
astonished eyes prescription for the disillusioned
by Rebecca Del Rio so thank you thank you for joining
me this morning on our poetry of practice the way that we're using some
poems to help bring maybe some freshness to our meditation practice so thank you
thank you