so uh I'm your very own Tanya Wiser and you know some of you I
definitely know and know me and some of you I don't so maybe I'll say a few words about myself
um I'm I am graduating next week from
the IMC IRC 4-year Dharma Teacher Training Program
yeah yeah woo it has been quite a journey and
um so I'm a student of Gil and Andreas really IMC baby this has been my place
of practice um since I don't know
the I don't know around 2008 or nine or something like that
and uh I'm a therapist and I say that because it tends to uh it tends to
permeate the flavor of my dharma i tend to bring up things that I have learned
as a therapist so just just to you know give you all a heads up
and I teach here on Thursday nights um if you're interested in connecting with
SA um the way I teach includes small practice groups people talking about the
the topic and connecting with each other and sharing practice and it's a lovely
way to build and create a sense of connection to the SA here i also teach
the queer SA here which is happens once a month online
so all right so my talk will be on uh my
fa my current teaching topic for Thursday nights which has to do with not
knowing not knowing and tonight or to this morning I'll weave in how not
knowing supports curiosity investigation and ultimately the freeing
of our hearts so I uh I have
[Music] um I have long found that
uh you know I've long been a student of duca studying duca suffering contraction
clinging the ways that um you know I suffer in my life I see
other people suffer I guess it makes sense I'm a therapist is kind of what I'm tuning
into and over time the more I've studied it the more I've recognized that um the
antidote or the opposite is love the sense of presence i don't mean love in a
romantic way i mean love in being available present
receptive letting the heart soften so this inspires me a lot i find
a lot of joy when I um connect even with
real difficult things and I can do so in a way that feels loving feels caring feels
like my heart isn't um trying to protect or control a
situation so I see um I I've been having a lot
actually delightful time practicing with this idea of not knowing a practice of not
knowing even during the sit this morning you know I would watch the
mind I have friends who came from the East Bay today and I was like is that them is that them don't
know you know just sort of letting you know watching how the mind starts
to want to build and collect information and and find out an answer and somehow
just dropping in this don't know sort of allows things to soften and
I I just find that there's just it's almost like this big
open bright light you know this sense of softening opening oh then what what what
is here it allows me to re-engage in the
moment i also think it's actually quite respectful to not
know you know it's respectful for me because truly every moment is different
every person is different we're all changing all all the time things are changing and kind of holding this idea
of not knowing kind of allows yourself to open up and see and be
surprised um be willing to meet and see people or things
differently it also helps me keep my mind fresh here now you know sort of
just on this cusp of you know what's happening now
i don't know if it happens for you but if I think I like if I'm going into
a meeting or I'm going into a situation I think I know what's going to happen
there's a maybe a bit of a wall or a bit of a um l you know sort of a lack of
openness that I experience a defensiveness or an
offensiveness you know and um and that definitely doesn't support
the heart in in softening or in my receiving what is in
front of me so it's respectful to others respectful to my
heart and it helps me stay
interested it's also incredibly important if we want to be curious if we
want to do one of the things the Buddhist said was incredibly important which is to investigate our experience
it's incred it's essential for us to be curious to be
investigative but maybe not in the the way that we might classically think of it as an analyzing
conceptualizing but more in a direct investigatory experiential kind of way
so you know for all of this mindfulness obviously is the foundation of our
practice we need to be mindful and present and
aware and mindfulness is critical if we want to live a life of nonharming
but if we're just mindful and we aren't engaging in the
other teachings of the Buddha it's not
enough it's not enough to just know to just be
aware we can be mindful and do all any kind of
thing when we're mindful in the way the Buddha taught we're actually attuning to
harm and lack of harm or homeless um wholesomeness and unh wholesomeness
suffering non-suffering wisdom
we need to understand and want to understand what's going on but not not
intellectually not conceptually more directly more understanding and seeing the processes
that are happening to seeing things like you know
the energies of greed hatred and delusion and how they operate to see how
things change in permanence and to recognize when we've got a strong
sense of a constructed self happening you know or a strong sense of other
constructed other happening that has to do like with thinking you know somebody
you've constructed this person how they
are so you know it's important to think about why are you practicing
Well you know I came actually I came to the practice because I was suffering a
lot and I wanted to stop suffering i didn't want to suffer so
much and so you know for a long time early in my practice it was just about
you know trying to suffer less in each moment and so my meditation for the you
know kind of a solid first year of great difficulty it might be that I spent five
minutes and all I did was say breathing in I calm the body breathing out I calm the mind you just trying to help
myself calm down and that's actually incredibly important because we need a
calm mind we need a relaxed body We need to
be more open and spacious for us to actually investigate in any meaningful
way so however long it takes us to do that in our sit or in our
lives that's beautiful and then there's more as things start to calm
down we can start to look at different things experience the dharma in a
different way
so I'm going to talk about um the Kalama Suta um it's a suta about how do we
discern what's true what's truth
the Kamas um were a group who uh who lived in a village that was maybe in a
throughway or you know through um a place a lot of people traveled and stopped at and including a lot of
different kinds of spiritual teachers so they
had an abundance of teachings but from all different
perspectives and so they started to maybe be a little bit
overwhelmed with all the ideas all the practices all the directions that they
were getting from all these different visiting teachers and so they had the Buddha come
and talk and their question was "How do we know what is true how do we know who
is right well to parallel to what maybe they were
experiencing you know if we step back and look our culture is feeding us all kinds of ideas and beliefs all the
time and these ideas and beliefs start to fill us up and when we start to believe them and
collect them we start to close ourselves off
and our culture encourages us to come to conclusions to have answers to know to
think you know and so we start collecting what we think of as
facts which are really just stories and we bundle them together with
some magic thread to create what we think is our truth the truth about this thing or that
thing or another thing this person or you know and some of us have a lot of
experience in certain realms of our life so we've seen hundreds of times that
maybe this leads to that leads to that so this is the conclusion or at least the mind tells us
so and so there's wisdom and that you know collecting information and ideas
and theories and and our experience but the way the mind weaves
things together it's kind of invisible to us and you
know really really there's often just just as you are each so
uniquely different from each other each situation ation each person
each moment of healing or each moment of suffering has its own
uniqueness and we don't know really how things are going to wind up we don't
know we do know it will change something will change
this morning in my inbox I got a beautiful poem super short it was super
perfect for me for this morning's talk by Rosemary Watah
Tramer and it's called One Clearing she
says "Every day I dismantle its nest the fear that wings darkly into my
thoughts." What every day read i'm rereading it every day I dismantle its
nest the fear that wings starkly into my thoughts
i really love that image of the nest and how we you know and that she's
dismantling these fears these thoughts these stories these
beliefs that are collecting creating sort of some sort of
a foundational place that we could sit in and rest on and look out from but in
the case of fear that's probably not so skillful not so helpful so I love that I think
about oh yeah yesterday I had this con you know idea about theory about what
this is doing and what that's doing and what's going to happen no let me just pull it all apart you know and let these
things sit individually and just sort of loosen it
all up again and we build these nests under the
illusion that we actually know and see what's going on we actually think we really
know but they're really stories we're weaving and so much of it is drawn upon
historical associative or you know sort of some way
or another fabricated information maybe misperception is the norm what if
we all understood misperception was the norm you know our perceptions our habits our
views our beliefs our histories all of this stuff you know they they all tend to reinforce
themselves and we tend to agree with our own
views and now you know there are lots of wars going on over
views lots of wars going on over views
there's this um Indian lay teacher um who's deceased now but in
um her name is Deepa Ma or
was she has this quote that I love the mind is all stories one after
another like nesting dolls you open one and another is inside
open that one and there's another story emerging when you get to the last
nesting doll the smallest one and open it inside of it is what it's empty
nothing's there and all around you are the empty shells of the stories of your
life isn't that great
she was a terra meditation master she really um had kids and
um I had a child die and her husband die and you know she lived in very poor
circumstances and she practiced she went off to do intensive retreat but most of her practice was in daily
life and in very difficult circumstances and so you know she she
she said mindfulness applied in every activity
speaking shopping ironing cooking caring for children she said the whole path of
mindfulness is this whatever you are doing be aware of it and she was called
the patron saint of householders
so to open ourselves up right to open these nesting dolls to dismantle our
nests it's really helpful to to not know and to be curious and to
investigate and it's not that we can exile ourselves from all of these ideas
and stories and beliefs there oh I wish I could I wish I could say I'm not going
to ingest this i wish I wish I could say that I could tell the mind not to remember
something it it doesn't work like that you know things just come in we get told all kinds of stories we watch movies we
watch TV shows you know we're conditioned by our parents and our teachers and all these things and so we
just we are we just need to know we're this big bundle of things that's ready to get all turned into nesting
dolls so we can't exile ourselves from this you know we just need to know
what's going on and be be curious and when we start to see the
mind gathering up all the data as much as possible don't
know don't know there's a neurologist um
neuroscientist who um I think her name was Lisa Barrett but I'm not sure if
that's correct but I read an article by her and she described you know the brain
is an organ right like any other organ in our body and she said it's our
prediction organ you know it's always predicting
it's taking all this stuff we have both willingly and and choicefully
inputed as well as unwilling have you know been inputed into us and it draws
on all of it and from that it makes kind of assumptions it predicts it's a great
thing until it's not so don't just believe your
thoughts test them investigate them and um so I'm this is bringing me
back to the Kalama Suta and what what the Buddha taught one of the beautiful things that the
Buddha taught in this suta in my view is you know these these practitioners are
asking how do we know what is true how do we know what is true
truth and the Buddha doesn't say go write a
thesis he doesn't say you know think and analyze and cognize and imagine and
evaluate and judge instead the Buddha teaches us how
to look directly at our experience and to use the measure of
suffering or the absence of suffering to help us determine that which is leading
toward what we or what he would call true dharma
in order to notice and be aware of whether something is causing you know
more suffering for us or others we have to be
embodied it's not something that you intellectually evaluate it's something that you recognize you experience you
sense you have to notice how you're being impacted you have to notice the quality
of your heart you have to notice if your mind is contracting and oh is there aversion in
my mind is there's this thread of not liking not wanting anger
hatred anxiety and fear are part of aversion fear because it's something we
don't want we're afraid of and you know with greed it's all
about trying to get or hold on to or control right it's all about wanting and
I was thinking about that this morning just from my lens of oh can I love or not because a lot of people are like
well but I'm attached i love I want this person i want this thing you know
but when I think about it if I'm really caught up in
wanting what does that feel like for me it's like ah you know I'm I'm really
focused on what I want to take in bring in you know keep and when I'm relating that
way I might know I love i might know I care but is the
heart really soft enough to open is this heart really
receptive i think it gets compromised
contracted in the effort and with delusion we're just all caught up in
like stories so if we're not really connected what's really going on we aren't really caring
and loving what's here you know we can't we're not really seeing what's
here all right back to the
Kamas so the Kamas were really confused they were really like you know
complaining and saying "This one says this and this one says that and how are we supposed to know and blah blah blah
blah blah." And the Buddha said something beautiful in the beginning maybe it has to do with a little bit
with not knowing and the Buddhist said you
know of course you are uncertain Kamas ah isn't that nice they're trying
to know and he's saying "Of course you're uncertain of course you don't know of
course you're in doubt there's reason when there's reason for doubt uncertainty is born." And so
this is the case ah I relaxed just imagining that
right of course and then the Buddha went on to say "Don't go by
reports legends tradition scripture logic conjecture inference
analogies agreement with your views probability or the thought this
contemplative is my teacher so the Buddha is even saying whoever their teacher is including him don't go by
just what I say and this is one of the things that I think that made Buddhism so accessible
to me was that I wasn't expected or required to just believe what I was
being taught that was really really important
for me to be able to really enter enter deeply into this
practice incredibly important for me
so you know we need to evaluate for
ourselves you know well let me come to the next thing
he says and I'll go back to that and then so he's laying the ground of course you don't know you don't know right it's
impossible to know with all these different things conflicting right and it's of course you you're doubting
and and uncomfortable and then he says don't just go by what's said or has been done
no matter who said it you know no matter how much evidence you have no ma no matter how predictable it seems and then
he says this when you yourself
know when you yourself know these things are bad these things are
blameable unskillful and unh wholesome so we're using we have old language here
but when you know this is not good this is not healthy
and he says 'Then these things are censored and and that they're censored by the wise undertaken and observed
these things lead to harm and ill will when they are hurting us when they are
hurting others abandon them when you yourself
know so the Buddha in this is one empowering each person right to engage
and reflect and he's also really
beautifully simplifying what we need to know
directly what we need to connect
with and you know not you know you suffer I suffer
right I suffer you suffer just like you I suffer right we all suffer but we are all of us because of our own
conditioning suffer slightly
uniquely so we need to study ourselves we need to notice you know
when we're in unhealthy mental and emotional territory
this is so beautiful for me this is beautiful and it's so
simple so you know one of his key teachings is that greed hatred and
delusion cause harm so we can just check in if there's
greed hatred and delusion and notice sometimes it's not clear maybe I need to
not like this or not want this or I want this but then okay is it causing harm is
it making me unwell is it making someone else unwell so for me I might give an example
of my child worrying about my child my adult child
is my worry while it's from the love of a
mama is my worry making me sick is it making me unwell is it contracting my
heart is it binding my mind is it turning my
stomach is it affecting my irritability
well if so it's probably leading to harm right it is i'm harming myself with
my abuse my ways that I'm holding
things so that tells me there's some way I'm looking at the situation or relating
it that I need to abandon there's some other way to hold
it or be with it that will allow my mind to relax and my heart to relax and my
body to be free the Buddha is telling us to know
the quality of our heart and our mind to use that as the reference point
for whether we want to pursue or abandon something
so after we come to this understanding for ourselves the Buddha
says "Know for yourself and listen to the wise."
When you know for yourselves and you can listen to the wise these things are skillful blameless
praised by sensible people and when you undertake them they lead to welfare and
happiness then you should acquire them and keep
them so the Buddha is not telling us to all be off in our own La La
Land right coming to our own completely own individual conclusions but rather to
also rely on those who are wise the teachings that are wise that have helped
us and you know our my relationship to various teachings change changes over
time too so you know it's also always wise to keep checking in about what
we're
referencing and he doesn't say you have to believe the wise ones absolutely
right but use this as another gauge to help yourself
so what we come to know and see is not just you know not just me and not just another not them not me but
both both self-nowledge and the knowledge of the
wise in another suta the Buddha um is teaching his son
Rahula about how to do this how do we how do we know whether what we're doing
is causing harm or not and it's not again it's not just
this intellectual analysis it's not a predictive thing but we might employ
those things but we don't rely solely upon them so he tells his son be anytime
time he's about to do something you know to take an action that might be significant to
reflect before you do it reflect is this causing harm to myself is it causing
harm to others or is it causing harm to both okay so before I you know go do
something important and say something important I want to reflect on these things and then the Buddha says "Okay
great." And then while you're doing it while it's happening reflect again have
mindfulness in the middle of it and reflect is this causing harm to me is it
causing harm to another or is it causing harm to both okay and so if it's not
Buddha says "Proce keep going." Great enjoy right
and afterwards so maybe you think it's not causing harm you go through it you still
don't think it's causing harm and afterwards you still pause and
reflect maybe many times after because sometimes we don't recognize the harm
until later and if it was all goodness it's
great to reflect and savor the goodness many many times many many
times asking the same
questions it's you know this is our dharma
compass our north star this is such a beautiful again
accessible thing to do which is to notice ah can I love am I present Am I
open receptive you know taking in being willing or am I contracted and
hurting and closed off am I
suffering i think it's something that you know I I know I reference a lot but
not enough you know I think that uh I I too
often overlook how I allow myself to suffer and I don't think I'm
alone and we need to look in all areas you know maybe we have we do work in our
our lives that's really meaningful and important work really helpful
work but if we aren't paying attention to how much we're trying to do or how
much pressure we're putting on ourselves or how much we're taking on we're letting ourselves suffer
probably most likely we need to notice it in all the
realms even if they're what we feel are completely wholesome realms we need to keep taking care of
ourselves be the guardians of our hearts pay attention to stress
early it'll help us make wiser decisions not to blindly just
accept our responsibilities our concerns as what is most
important so do you think you're paying close enough attention to your suffering to where
you're you know putting yourself in stress harm sway or harming others
is there some nest you're building a nest of fear stacking
dolls maybe pick one that you know you're constructing that you've been
building maybe bring it to mind maybe let yourself see the little
all the little tangled up pieces whether you like the nesting doll or the
nest all the things that are getting packed
together just take a moment to reflect on it and notice what you feel in your
body and what if what if you say don't
know don't know don't
know i don't know what if not
knowing releases the glue that binds it all together can you imagine
that letting the pieces soften
deconstructing your nest i'll read Rosemary's poem
again every day I dismantle its nest the fear that wings darkly into my
thoughts
every day I dismantle its nest the fear that wings darkly into my
[Music]
we have a couple of minutes i'm happy to take questions or if people want to come up I'm happy to talk to you after
afterwards so just is there a question or a comment anyone would like to share
ah Susan right behind you Martha
wow Tanya you're on fire oh um I really appreciate so much this
image of the nest um I'm like a very keen gardener and
every now and again after a windstorm it's not unusual to have a nest blown down and when you see a nest it's all
these little pieces of grass and feather
and somehow having this image of the little twig the little thing landing in
me and just gently let it go instead of this weaving
of the story line just so helpful thank you oh great Susan
thank you thank you
yeah anybody have a hard time imagining dismantling your
nest yeah maybe I'll teach you one of the
things that I do to help me it's actually comes out of uh my
practice with right effort so in my right hand I have the
nest that all that you were focusing on all that's sort of tangled up
[Music] together and
um you know all that that sort of contraction just let yourself feel it
and hold it
and then when you're ready in your left
hand there's not
knowing not knowing and opening relaxing into not
knowing just let the not knowing grow a bit
let it fill up your hand and the space around it just not knowing is huge it's
way bigger than the nest the knowing way
bigger and then when you're ready slide the not knowing under the
nest take your hands and put the right hand above the left hand the nest being
held by this huge amazing field of not knowing and let the nest rest let it be
held in that field don't try and get rid of the nest just hold it in the
beautiful expansiveness of not knowing let it be saturated by not
knowing let it rest in not
knowing it can be it can be that simple we just might have to do it every
day right effort right is you know one of the ways the Buddha
described it was in the time of the Buddha they didn't have nails so they used holes and
pegs to build things and so you know we're building
this nest so the Buddha would say when the peg is
rotten use a new good peg pound it in and replace the old one and then you
have the healthy rod in there holding things
together so what if not knowing can be that replacement thing holding things
together or allowing them to dissipate so maybe that'll help for those of you
who are having a hard time i hope it I hope it does thank you for your kind attention all right