so hello everyone and welcome
and I feel fortunate to be able to offer
uh you some of the share some of the
wonderfulness of uh this practice that I've been doing for so
long And one of the things that's quite wonderful
is developing the capacity to do next to nothing in
meditation So not try to attain anything or make something
happen except to be aware to be
present to be here And uh sometimes it's pretty clear in
meditation that the mind wants to be any anywhere but here Um way the distracting mind wanders
off in all kinds of directions and ways or it's clear that
the that the mind is aversive to here doesn't want to
be with what's happening here and now But to be able to be here with our
present moment experience and neither for or
against neither avoiding or you know a certain way you know
diving in to penetrate it or to but simply to be still
And as we're still to
notice or to be more simple simply to watch the unfolding of experience
And one of the purposes for samadei for developing concentration is to have the stability
to have the settleness uh to just stay here with the
experience and so much learning happens when you just sit and
watch An example that I heard many years ago is if a nature
photographer wants to take pictures on the vast plains of
Africa Uh to go running all over the plains looking for the animals makes it
difficult But if the person sits still quiet by the watering hole and
waits everything comes for the water All the animals
come So if we can sit sit still at the watering hole of the
dharma and watch the comingings and goings of sensations
experiences thoughts even feelings in a certain kind
of way And the heart of seeing the coming
and going kind of the key to it is to uh notice how the
perception the way we perceive the present moment is constantly
shifting Even if something on the surface seems like it's
constant it's not going away Like right now I can feel my hand on my
knee and you know as long as I rest my hand there that's sensations are going
to be there But if I really pay careful attention to those
sensations I can see how my perception of it shifts and changes to different parts of the
palm then to thinking about what I'm going to say here to all of you and then
looking at the screen and your names and the greetings and then back to my palm
and then it's my finger and then it's my thumb and then it's the
the you know the base of my palm and there was more pressure So the
perception changes all the time The idea of the hand on the knee is kind of
constant that kind of points to something's not changing So it gives the idea that there's constancy but this is
where if we can separate out the sensation from the concept of
it just the sensation just the perception so to be still and do nothing
more than to watch So we'll enter into that world
So to gently close your eyes
and and to enter into your
posture no matter what posture you're in can you adjust it a bit twist your body
sway side to side do something that gently opens your
chest maybe creates a little bit of alertness
in the back of your neck and the spine Maybe lifting
the back of the head up or tipping the chin
down Maybe there's ever so slight way that you
could accentuate the curve in the lower back or straighten the curve in lower
back Whichever way just ever so slightly that gives the lower back a feeling of
being more alert more
enlivened and feeling within a with a intentional
posture Feeling whatever sense of being enlivened you are in your
posture The sense of
living vitality Whatever degree is there Even if you're tired or feeling
weak to feel where in your body there's a sense of vitality
Even if you feel weak to have those sensations means you're
alive It's part of life coursing through
you and into that aliveness of your body your
posture in a way that's right for you nice for you Take a few long slow deep
breaths And as you exhale
settle into the grounding place deep in your
belly Deep with the weight of your belly your torso
settles The movement of breathing in and breathing out with the exhale
settles into a place of stillness deep within
Then to let your breathing return to
normal And as you exhale to soften relax your
body And to relax Exhale all the way to the end of the
exhale as a movement of settling into a
stillness A
settleness however brief it is
As you come to the end of the
exhale letting your thoughts thinking become
quieter letting your thoughts drift away Maybe letting them
go at the end of the exhale
And then feeling or imagining deep within there's a still
point
Stay close to that still point Do it Almost like it's
the quiet place within from
which you notice you watch all the change that
occurs Staying in the river of changing
sensations changing perceptions Even if something remains
and doesn't change stay
open Stay quiet and still observing what is
changing in your direct experience
No need to think about anything No need for thoughts to linger
anywhere Instead allow yourself to
watch the river of change The river of changing
perceptions
sensations how thinking and thoughts come and go
The way you can watch thinking if you don't get pulled into
the content just a phenomena of
thinking It's constantly shifting and changing with all the other changes
No need to think about anything Thinking about something is
doing something
Rest in the stillness from which you
can peacefully
observe all the change changing
perceptions Not even needing to identify what you're experiencing to even know what it is
Except that it's changing shifting appearing
disappearing flowing
And as we come to the end of the sitting
noticing to what degree any degree at
all you can find inside of you a way in which you're doing
nothing except watching the change changing
flow like a large boulder in a river where the current of the water
just flows by Be still and watch the flow the river of
change So that even your heart your heart
center is unstuck
Even so your capacity for a tender care
or kindness is part of the
flow part of the river of change A kind of love that's
actually stronger The less it's held in
check the more it flows and
openly and letting your goodwill flow outward into the world
Almost as if the more it flows outwards and spreads your heart just opens and opens
and opens outward into the
world and carried on the flow of your goodwill
Let there be the wishes May all beings be
happy May all beings be
safe May all beings be
peaceful May all beings be free
[Music]
Thank you
So hello and welcome to this series on
insight and um so today I'm talking about the fourth category of insight
that of the five different category major categories and um so the first is
personal insight that's unique to each individual The second is um insight into
way of seeing clearly that in any given moment there are two things There's
experience we have and the knowing of it the recognition of it And um so the
experience itself in the most fundamental basic way is the the way
it's experienced through the sense doors Um and um and so that sensing and
feeling and then knowing recognizing what that is Uh so that begins to tease things
apart that are often entangled and that tangle that we live
in of per what we call generally sometimes called perception is um there's a third element
that makes it really sticky or more a solid ball of knots is um the self who
perceives the self that's experiencing things So if I
um see a advertisement for the next greatest
revolutionary technological device and um and
[Music] uh and it just kind of appears on maybe
the screen and a commercial and that just comes and goes
And it's actually moving shifting changing scenery as they talk about this new device with great
ways And um but I immediately kind of lock in to the the
device and I'm the one who's hearing it I would like to have it If I could have
this device then I'll be the most tech advanced person on my block and I'll be
have a lot of people will admire me and it'll be really great And so there's
such a big knot of desires and ideas and ideas of self and the perceiver and what
the perceiver wants that's comes together almost simultaneous with seeing the device
hearing it being talked about And so the idea that simply seeing oh there's a
there's a new tech device I'm seeing it in front of me It's it's shifting and changing angles and it's my knowing of
it There's hearing the voice of the person saying talking about it There's
hearing and there's knowing that I'm hearing There's knowing there's sounds of speaking Um it's the the world gets
simplified can be simplified Uh so we're not caught up in the concepts the ideas the me that's
part of it where it all becomes one big tangle and uh and so to relax So part of
insight as we go deeper and deeper kind of like we're going deeper in the Janna
and we're deeper in deep concentrated states there's a stilling and a quieting and a simplifying of what the mind is
about and what we're doing and caught up in a calmer state and at some point uh
we don't not adding self and desires and wishes on top of our experience Each
thing is seen in its own pristine simplicity There's seeing the knowing of
seeing There's hearing knowing of hearing There is desire arises There's
knowing of desire There's a thought about how great this will be There's knowing there's a thought
arising And so now they're starting to feel and sense a freedom of allowing
each thing to be in this simple state like that That's not possible if it's all entangled together
As we as we start being that simple with the raw basic sense data coming in and just experiencing it it starts feeling
very satisfying to be present Um there's a kind of simple satisfaction joy It
feel there's an onward leading movement Yes this feels good This is where now
I'm connected And it's a little bit some of the qualities of samadeia coming into play as well which uh makes it feel
experientially like this is a good way to be This is now there's more freedom
here As it goes along we start seeing the third insight we talked about
yesterday that um the conditionality that uh there's a
sensation and that produces certain thoughts and maybe memories
uh memories arise and that produces sensations or tightening in the belly or softness in the heart area or something
There is we see the conditionality We see that when there's a loud sound outside something inside uh for a moment
just kind of cringes and I'm not the one who's trying to cringe It's I can't say
I do it I might say it's happening to me or it's happening with me but I don't
have to even say that I see the conditionality a loud sound and uh
muscles cringe muscles tighten and then they relax Um and so
it's cause and effect It's a condition and the effect of the condition that what arises from it And so we start
seeing that there's so much of this conditionality so much that that um things that occur that uh you can't
really take credit for it You can't really say it's me doing it Uh this
defines me because it's just just what happens There's a breeze against the cheek And you know the the sensations of
against the cheek um and knowing the sensation uh those are not me in some
kind of usual sense of my personality who think people think I am or who I
think I am uh I didn't make that happen that the sensations against my cheek um
it's just the conditions arise and there's sensation in the cheek and maybe there's a sense of pleasure with it and
um and pleasure just pleasure arising then there might be desire for more
pleasure and but the initial arising of that desire for more happened kind of
kind of not in any kind of way I can identify with it uh it just seems like
it's a desire floats up and it's almost like you say it's not me it's just a
desire and um and then I let you know it floats away if all those things are kind of
happening ing in a tangle then um then uh it's me wonderful
me having the pleasure of the breeze against my cheek It's me that wants to have more it's me you know just of
course it's me because it's all happening together in this big bundle of things and I don't see I don't see the
genesis of it where it arises out of something which is not my will not my I
have a desire without wanting the desire just seems to float up so when the mind is very quiet and
still in meditation it gets to be a fascinating world uh when we don't
identify with things we're kind of seeing the simplicity of different things arising the conditionality of it
and one of the things that begins to happen is the next the fourth kind of insight which is uh usually translated
into English as um comprehension and um maybe we can call
it understanding and this is a little this is somewhat conceptual but it
people don't usually don't think of it this way but sometimes people are actually coming to a conclusion
usion and that is uh you know to start seeing that there's so many simple
things that are occurring that are not being tied together uh sewn together the
Buddha talked about sewn together into some big bundle of things the
um uh the um and there's all these things are
occurring and because of conditions And there's no self in it There's no
self assertion no sense of self in it It's just like the breeze against a cheek Uh I didn't make that happen I
don't identify with that sensation there Those sensations define who I am In a
sense they have nothing to do with me except they're happening on my cheek I don't have to add anything build
anything I'm the you know build a story that I'm the best I have the best
sensations best the best breeze that anyone's ever had Ever I should really
get the Guinness World Book of Records to have such a wonderful sensation of a
breeze against my cheek I mean all that selfing doesn't go on And so to start
seeing that all this stuff rises and passes comes and goes without self And
then some people now understand wow there's a lot of experience here that I've identified with before And a lot of
this stuff is just happening without a sense of self without a self in in
um in uh without a self It just kind of phenomena arising It's a natural
phenomena that arises because conditions are such that this comes together to
make this arise And um and some people because the mind is pretty still Uh remember there's some
degree of samadei and concentration Um uh it feels good It feels true And
people start understanding wow there's a lot less self going on here than I
realized Um and some people say it's all not self It's all just conditions of
things coming together causes and conditions And some people will say that there is
no self There isn't they'll even say sometimes there is no will Uh because uh
will itself is just uh any kind of deci decisiveness decision is just something
that arises from other conditions There's no inherent self who's thinking it and planning it because in a very
deep state that you don't see that you just see this cause and conditions and effect or conditions and it's um what it
brings forth and so there's this comprehension and people will say wow and then they uh
there's no no self here at all and there's no self anywhere and what a great thing and there's freedom here and
so it they tend People tend to this this is comprehension This is a little bit like wow this is great I wish I want to
tell everyone about it and this means there wasn't a self in the past There wasn't any in the future
Wow And as in in correlary together with this there's no self in this experience
is the clear feeling that everything is arising and passing Everything is impermanent Nothing lasts
And um and if I just sit back and let the river flow all I see is
change And so then people come to make it So part of the stage of comprehension
is to make categorical statements to make broad categorical understandings
Wow Everything is impermanent Everything is changing Um the basic kind of
characteristic of reality is change and impermanence and not self and and um and
this is true everywhere in the world for every person all circumstances and so there's a kind of excitement or kind of
uh becoming philosophers kind of conceptualizing and thinking how wonderful this
is And for some people this is um uh because of their mind is so clear
and settled uh they almost feel like now I'm enlightened now I understand everything and this is fantastic and
it's like almost like a divine revelation for some people to come into this state but it's it's not the end of
the path and it's little bit of a detour in the sense that if people get caught
up in the conceptual aspects the generalization of it um now I know something true about reality itself and
becomes kind of a move into metaphysical philosophy to make these
broad claims and then now I have insight into the very nature of reality and um and so it can be exciting
it there's some truth to what we're experiencing and even thinking uh so it's important not to think it's just
pure delusion but um but the idea is to Keep
practicing This is the beginning of the practice opening up in new and important
ways And so so the stage of comprehension the stage of understanding
something that be is a more of a general understanding conceptual understanding
that's distinct from a deeper direct experience a deeper uh you know uh
non-conceptual experience And that's the the most important insight of the inside
meditation and that'll be what I'll talk about tomorrow So thank you very much