good morning everyone and
uh so this is um my first talk of the new year so happy New Year to all of you
and best wishes for the year and it's the custom for me for the
first talk of the year to be on the four noble truths these are a phenomenally
important and valuable uh template for insight for understanding
for wisdom for finding our way to a degree of
freedom and over these maybe more than 20 years now that I've been doing these
first talk of the year on the four noble truths um what how I've presented it has
changed over the years someone could go back and listen to all of them and track
the evolution of my thinking and my understanding of it over time and that speaks to how of um uh useful these are
for new understandings for New Perspectives for new ways of touching our heart in some important
way rather than taking the four noble truths as there's an orthodox true
understanding of it um it's this is very useful thing to engage in and explore
and apply in new ways and um I once sent an email to
bobot the famous translator of are these ancient texts a wonderful scholar and
asking about one particular way the Buddha taught the four noble truths and he replied not
that it was the true way of understanding them he explained oh that was a particular application
was being applied for a particular purpose so this idea so these four noble truths are wonderful things this
simplest way of saying them is just an outline really that
needs to be filled in um there is the truth actually the
they don't use the word this there they use the word this this
is the Noble Truth of suffering this is the Noble Truth of the
arising of suffering this is a noble truth of the
cessation and this is a noble truth of the path leading to the sensation of
suffering so immediately we realize that this is about suffering which for some people is a
really big word and not only to qualify as suffering it's like the big disasters
of life but uh sometimes uh it's been translated as stress stress and then we
can understand that it can apply to the smallest little things in life that are stress in fact it applies to
anything that uh degree of of stress
d-stress that um we might experience that it is possible and
reasonable to become free of to bring to an end and this is the good news of
Buddhism that suffering can come to an end Dua can come to an
end and um inherent in this teaching Central to all of Buddhism is the idea
that um of change things change Wonder way the other things
change and sometimes uh other people and myself maybe at times would have worded
this differently would have said Central to Buddhism is idea that everything
passes or everything's impermanent it won't be here all the time and that's
valuable as well to say but that also limits this understanding but if you
hear it as change that applies to Everything Everything Changes except for
platonic ideas maybe at least for
Plato and um so the uh uh that things
change and the idea is to find find our Peace by understanding something deep
about change and you hear that in the this wording of the Four Noble Truths the second truth is the
arising and this third Noble Truth is the ceasing the coming and going the
Buddha uses the word coming and going sometimes instead of change sometimes he uses appearing and
disappearing and uh sometimes inconstancy is used and sometimes the
word change things becoming different and um so there's this uh
wonderful account of a conversation that um
um a uh householder a man had with the
Buddha and um his name was
nakula the father of nakula and um he came to the Buddha and
paid his respects and then he said this I am
old venerable sir aged burdened with years advanced in
life come to the last stage Afflicted in body often
ill wow that's quite a statement now
remember this was 20 2500 years ago there was no
ER there was no pain medications there wasn't no blood
pressure medication heart medication there was no antibiotics there was no surgery for the
back for the hips for all the stuff I mean there's so much that happens in the
modern world that keeps us going kind of kind of tunes us up a little bit for a
while now because the march of change that the human body
is will change sometime when you're young if you're lucky you get stronger
and more capable and more skilled and if you're lucky enough to grow to be
old for most people change is not a welcome
thing and we spend people spend in this country a lot of money
fending off the effects of aging and um I think the time of the
Buddha they didn't have botox what they
had that was maybe better than Botox was
meditation so this is quite a remarkable statement this man is saying this is how it is for me and you can imagine in the
ancient world that yes being aged and old was you couldn't escape it and there
was no sense that you can go down to the local store and get some aspirin and some face cream and you know just kind
of shore it Shore things up for a while uh and so he's just saying this is
it's kind of a very clear things have changed for this man and he's clearly stating
it um I am old aged burdened with years advanced in
life come to the last agage Afflicted in body often ill he's not
complaining he's just saying this is what where I am and
um and he then he says uh I rarely get a chance to see the Buddha and hear his
teachings May the Buddha please teach me instruct me since this would lead to
my welfare and happiness for a long time so he's asking for teachings here
is my situation things have changed in this kind of way now please offer some
teachings and the Buddha replied so it is so it is this body is of your this
body of yours is Afflicted way down encumbered if anyone carrying around
this body were to claim to be healthy even for a moment what does that do to
other than foolishness that's a kind of straight strange statement and Powerful
statement
therefore you should train yourself thus you should practice this way you should
develop yourself and cultivate yourself in this way with the this Ori
a even though I am Afflicted in
body my mind will be unafflicted
this is how you should train yourself then the householder nakul
laita having delighted and rejoiced in The Bu in the Buddha statement Rose from
his seat and having paid homage to the Buddha uh went to visit the Buddhist disciple
venerable saruta and he said to Venable Buddha
this is what the Buddha told me he repeated the conversation and
um and he said to saruta it was the Ambrosia of such a
Dhat talk that the blessed one anointed me it's a very religious language but
you know that Dhat talks it was Ambrosia was very welcome he felt like he was given medicine some wonderful thing and
he was anointed he was blessed by it by the Buddha saying what did he say yes
the body can be afflicted but you train yourself so the mind is not
Afflicted when I was in Burma with uh my teacher upand
there was uh he was kind of a Stern Fierce General kind
of teacher he had very you know different teachers have very different personality in the same Monastery there
was a guy who was just the teacher who was just completely filled with love and you get in his presence and you you
could do no wrong with the pandita you could do everything
wrong and um but uh there was twice when
I was studying with him uh giving a talk his eyes sparkled and he kind of like
leaned forward and he said he said something like this he said as you age
the body just gets more and more worn out
decays and then he lean with sparkle and say but if your practice your mind gets
brighter and U and he was getting to be an old
man himself but as you could see like his theight and what's can happen so he had been training himself pretty much
his whole life this teacher of mine and that was his conclusion that the Mind
becomes brighter so um so then Sara said to the
the man didn't it occur to
you to question the Buddha further on how one is Afflicted in body
and Afflicted in mind and how one is Afflicted in body and not Afflicted in
mind that you got this great little teaching you didn't ask him how what to do with it how to practice with it and
so the um the man says to sarut well maybe you'll do it and he does so that
goes on from there and um and a lot of it has to do with
change the um how do we live with
change and and how is it we don't live with
change and that is one of the key insights and that's one of a lot to do with the four noble truths we
suffer when we lock on to something
and we're no longer living in the Stream the river of change we get we get preoccupied caught
in something this is how it is and uh and the way that theara
presents it to this man is when we take something in this universe in our
experience this is who I am if you take your appearance
in one way other your appearance defines who you are this is who I
am then when the appearances change you'll be distressed you'll
suffer if you have idea this is who I have to be and then you look in the
mirror and you're not what you were were once I've been surprised sometimes by
seeing people uh a big gap some years between seeing them
and I realized I was still carrying with me the image of them some years ago
sometimes it's with kids that are growing what and uh and sometimes of seeing
people who get older I'm sure people have done that with me because I'm getting
older and uh and one of the curious things about my own self-image that I've
seen over these decades um I do this to myself I'm usually a few years behind
with my self-image I kind of don't quite I kind of remember myself as you how I was some
years ago and still assume that's the way I am and um and it's I think it's
innocent enough I don't think I've suffered too much from that but this orientation to have an idea an image and
then lock onto it this is how it should be this is how it is so we can do that with appearance and we know in this
Society of ours a tremendous amount of suffering occurs because of how people
appear uh how they appear their skin color it's it's that difference that
distinction is deadly sometimes for people a lot of discrimination about uh
age there's people have told me repeatedly that because they're old
because they're old and short how much now they get overlooked people don't even see them anymore they tell me
and I stand in line at a store and someone comes along who's tall and young
and just kind of talks over them in the store clerk that ignores the person who was there first somehow they feel that
they become invisible their appearance and um and then there's
expectations of how we're supposed to look and how we want to present ourselves and this
changes so there's change in our appearance but that does not need to
afflict the mind and so how do we understand how we
how is the Mind becoming Afflicted around the changing of our appearance some of it has to do with how
we lock in we have lock into what it should be we have strong desires
expectations we have strong fears that we have to maintain it this way we have
we live in the world of ideas and Concepts and we're kind of oring
ourselves around these ideas of how it should be how we should be and what we expect it to be and the odd thing about
Concepts and ideas they can be platonic in the sense they can be kind of they don't change and their expectation that
things shouldn't change so there can be resistance there can be distress there could be fear all these kinds of things
start arising in the mind because our ch our appearances are
changing and it's not what we want or it is what we want and then we may be feel
happy for a while but it's a happiness that's dependent on that
appearance and then it passes away something happens and it's not there
anymore and um so how do we train
ourselves not to be afflicted in the mind when when there's
change in the body and um so part of it is understanding what is happening in the
mind and and being able to live with direct presence for the changing nature
of experience and that's one of the primary purposes of mindfulness
meditation is to place ourselves experientially
somatically in the field of change that's all that's what's
happening all the time things are changing all the time and um there's a song that was has
those lyrics I don't know if some of you old old enough to remember things are changing all the things are changing all
the time nothing known will be
mine everything changed that's why I made I made that
and U but nothing known nothing that you know will remain mine everything changes
everything so this identification this is me this is mine this is who I am I
have to be this kind of person this way and um and so we latch on we hold
on and um but what are these ideas Concepts that we latch on to how do we
step out of the river of change and
um so uh recently I had occasionally I have uh migraines and get nauseous and
this recently was relatively mild now it can go so I kind of continued my day but
um but the way that I uh I practice with it was to um place myself in my
body in the in the in the river of change my body the flow of change the
movements and everything and um and so when there was pain I would bring myself to the pain
and when I bring carefully to the pain that becomes more movement more change
makes it much more easy sometimes the pain goes away even it's or it's not no longer pain but then was I'm telling
telling you this is it became a wonderful vantage point to see how I started get how I got
Afflicted in the mind and how I got caught up in the idea oh this is
permanent this is this is may not permanent I knew it was going to be forever that way but this is not going
to change for the rest of the day I'm stuck this is terrible this is bad and I
could watch how that would happen as I as I could Swatch I could I could be
sitting and practicing with the river of change and this body and then if I kind
of got a little bit distracted my mind would go into my head
into my thoughts and as I go into the thoughts I would form this idea it
shouldn't be this way this is terrible this is you know should you
know you know I must have done something wrong what did I do and so there's this kind of these
thoughts where I could started locking into these thoughts these ideas I had a certain amount of fear
come up oh this is going get worse and it wasn't just fear that was coming but I would lock onto the fear oh no this
locking on this grabbing onto just kind of getting um that's where things got
rified things got solid ify and I was no longer in the river of
change I was in this idea or created idea of
permanence and um and then I could see oh look at that Gil you're having you're
lock locking on with the mind around something some idea some feelings some attitude some resistance something
that's what the mind is doing it's adding something to the situation wow
and then I'd relax go back into the river change and then it'll be okay for a while
until I wasn't doing that I kind of surfaced into my mind again and then had
a whole other vantage point to see what the mind is doing that gave birth to my
suffering around it and then I would come back in and open I kept opening up to the body that
was my practice open up to the change here be open to how things are flowing and moving and things were always
flowing and moving and um and it was fascinating also to see then also the to be open to
change and see that the thoughts were changing and so I would have the thought
that was something like this will be
forever but then I would watch it
this was very fleeting word will be just
fleeting and forever that word came to the end very
quickly it was just there like for a moment and it made a world of difference
to just see it as this word going through that um that rather than this is
going to be forever oh
forever forever forever which is you know is succumbing to it and getting caught in it and
locked into it and believing it it just for that moment it was
forever that because that was the what the word said but it wasn't forever the word wasn't forever the thoughts were
not forever the thoughts come and go as well recently also someone I was
presenting on something with a friend and and my friend said well I'm going to offer you my thoughts how I'm thinking
about this topic and then we'll hear about Gil what he thinks about this topic and and as soon as he said that um
I thought oh yeah I am thinking about it it was the topic and and I could watch
it was almost as if I could watch the thinking kind of in the air in front of
me like a river just passing by that had no weight no substance it was just a
changing flow of thoughts as opposed to sometimes I'm thinking about something and I'm like in
it I'm locked into it I'm concerned with it I'm curious about it I'm exploring it
and something about the mind has locked in something about the mind has zeroed
in and so that zeroing in locking in can
provide a sense of permanence a sense of constancy a sense that nothing is
changing but when my friend said what Gil's going to be thinking about it was just a
stream it was kind of like if you it to got watercolors and a brush and you were
going to paint a beautiful painting but the surface you were going to paint it on was a flowing
river imagine dipping your brush with watercolors to make a stroke in a
flowing river maybe you'd leave a trail of color in the but it would just kind
of be washing by and you couldn't really make the
picture it was like that's how I saw my thoughts go by the the changing nature
of thoughts wow so in that with that there was no
room for those thoughts to afflict the mind
the thoughts can afflict our mind not because of the thoughts but because how
we're involved in thoughts how we lock into them tense up react
resist uh you know have an emotional response to it and most emotional
responses are fine it's not the if we stay in the
river of change with emotions things are changing all the
time but if we react to the emotion I've had self-pity many years
ago I have this wonderful story for me of self-pity and I could and when I locked
into the self-pity it became clear that I suffered and my distress and suffering
grew but if I saw it as self-pity and kind of let go of it the suffering
disappeared and the physical pain that was associated with disappeared as well so
anger fear there's a way in which we get locked in we get caught in it and we
don't really see it or respect it or relate to it as part of the changing
nature of life and I've seen it works so much better to be with our my my emotional
life if I experiences this change constant change and then there's
much more room to allow it to be what it is anger
arises it's okay but it comes and it goes in and of
itself most Emotions Don't last more than a few seconds minute or two or something but what happens what keeps
them going is our feeding it our reacting to it our participation in
it but if we can really settle into the changing flow of emotions it's a coll
oscope of change and movement so so the for noble
truths are as as an honest
recognition that I'm suffering I'm I have stress
here as nakul told the Buddha in a clear
uncomplaining way I'm old and ill and
Afflicted just and now tell me a Dharma talk give me a Dharma talk and the
Buddha said yes it's true you are and we say that for ourselves yes it's true I'm
suffering and um and can you see the difference between
afflictions of the body and and non- affliction of the Mind Train yourself to
look at the Mind look what the mind is doing and so this the second and third Noble
Truth have a lot to do with seeing the change stepping out you know stepping
back into the river of change rather than being outside of it or caught in it or holding the bucket of the river and
saying I have the river and it's burden to carry this heavy bucket put the water
back in to the river and watch the rising and passing
watch the coming and going be in the
change and then they come this one they kind of
really the one of the most marvelous things about this teachings of the Four Noble Truths is the fourth Noble Truth
that if you can know the river of change and see the freedom from that the freedom from locking in feel the ease of
the mind or the spaciousness of the mind even a mind that has a migraine you can feel it this Freedom
there the psychological Freedom that uh in that
flow what is it like to be flowing in the current if everything is change
you're change you are the change in fact the Buddha said that the that at some point
in practice we enter the stream and when it was asked what is the Stream
um it's the EF path in you the stream is a way of living to to be in the flow of
of change completely without locking on without getting attached to anything or
resisting anything it makes us really wise and the eful path is a
manifestation of that wisdom if you're in the Stream of
change in this kind of way you're wise because you can see when you get caught
when you're trying to block the river stop don't move don't go when you try to
freeze it up when you resist it when you're holding on to things when you're taking
a bucket and holding on to that as um and um and that's that's a
tremendously wise thing to see look at that just like when I had the migraine I could see that difference and that made
a world a difference for me I was able to manage fine with it because I could see what the mind was doing and not give
into it and come back to the river of change to see what it's like to have the
mind unattached that's the first that's the first uh step of the eight-fold path to
be able to see that the Right View to see that operating if you're in the flow of that
River you see that if you have have ill will you're caught you see if you have
greed if you have hostility you're caught if and if you let go of that you
have this wonderful Delight of non ill will nonhostility which is often in
Buddhism is defined as kindness and
compassion you if you're really in if you are the change if you are the river
of change you see how lying and
stealing intentionally wanting to harm anyone takes you out of the river takes
you out of the change and you can see how that causes distress stress
suffering and so this wisdom of seeing that unethical Behavior
is actually a loss of something very profound some freedom and that's the middle steps of
the eful path and to see that when you're in the flow of the
river the the flow of change in us has freed up all kinds of beautiful and
healthy and wholesome qualities inside of us to flow Integrity that drive for
honesty for generosity for wisdom for patience for equinity there's all these
beautiful qualities that can flow when there isn't any resistance or
locking in or attachment and so and then to be mindful
of this and to be mindful of all this and to be settled in oneself in the
river of change these are the last three steps of the eful path so the eful path in this this
description is not exactly what you do is what you
become if you learn to relax and become the river of
change so it's not seeing change which is the beginning First Step but once you
see it then your Daya is to open and relax and become it and in that becoming
of it you become a wise person and you understand what it's like
not to be afflicted in mind you might be afflicted in body as you get older some
of you probably will be become older and as you
do maybe you know something now about not becoming Afflicted in your body in
your mind and that's the the premise of the
Four Noble Truths that it's possible to come to a place where the
mind is not afflicted believe it or
not so those are my thoughts for this year around the four noble truths and I
hope that they were meaningful for you in some way evocative in some way and
partly because today we have tea and we still have seven minutes that the Dharma
talk time uh if you're willing to stay for a few minutes and talk to someone near you say hello um be nice to greet
someone and welcome them to IMC and even if this is your first time at IMC you're
here and you can welcome the person you're hopefully you get you'll get welcome but you could also welcome them
and say hello and introduce yourself and if you want to say something about this talk anything was evocative or
interesting or or perplexing or in useful for you maybe uh share a little
bit what that was like and so if you it takes a few minutes and then I'll ring a bell and when it's time to stop for the
tea and everyone's welcome to stay or you can continue your conversations the one thing I ask is that when you look
around to talk to someone um look around maybe talk to two or three people little group of three just so no one's kind of
alone because everyone around you turned the other way we want everyone to be included to
look around make sure everyone around you is included somehow so please thank you