good morning good day good afternoon evening
um welcome back to the last of the series this week um so I'll begin with
um you know this is suta where the Buddha was teaching his son and one of
the uh aspects I want to I'll quote is um you develop meditation like
space just a space is not established anywhere in the same way when you're
developing meditation like space pleasant and unpleasant contacts
will not stay in charge of your mind one of the ways of thinking about
awareness is like a big open sky a big spacious sky and the objects that arise
in the mind are like birds or clouds floating by
rain falling thunder or lightning sometimes the sky is lit by
the sun sometimes by the moon or
stars so awareness can be thought of like the vast space in which all the objects of mind arise and pass
away appear and disappear the objects of mind as you know are the
sensations and sounds or thoughts and memories or
feelings emotions moods all our reactions to our
experience and they all appear and disappear in this vast space of
awareness everything we experience is constantly changing
it's constantly moving awareness isn't is undisturbed by
it all in in inside practice we give
careful attention to the details of our changing experience but we can also step back
from the details and pay attention to the spacious field in which they
occur between every changing object there is space and
stillness so let's
sit take a relaxed and alert
posture and gently close your
eyes might begin with a few deep breaths
and with each exhale relaxing a little bit more
deeply relaxing into your cushion or chair into the earth that supports you
allowing the breath to return to [Music] normal breathing
in breathing out as we breathe we can become aware of
the air outside of our body it's the same air inside of our
body we're breathing in and breathing out there's no
separation between inside and outside the same air that the bre trees
create the same air we're breathing
inside outside flowing back and
forth connected by breathing
we can become aware of a wider sense of feeling the whole
body as if the whole body is
breathing breathing in and breathing out
allowing the body to relax to
soften to open letting go of any ways it's bracing
itself it's
tensing allowing the body to relax calming anything that can be
relaxed the face the
shoulders any tensions in the back allowing the belly to be
soft arms and the
legs breathing in and breathing out as if the whole body is breathing
as you are aware of breathing with your peripheral awareness
you can become aware of the spaciousness that's all around
allowing yourself to just know it just letting it be while you breathe
with it thoughts might arise in the
space sensations emotions we can allow them to come and
go just breathing in and breathing out
allowing any movements of the mind to relax to
soften to settle down on their own no need to reach out to
them no need to push them away in the wider field of
awareness any of these movements can arise and pass away
the spacious mind has room for everything
whatever arises and passes can do so in this vast field of
awareness everything is flowing and changing
within a vast stillness
if the attention has drifted gently bring it back to the
present breathing in breathing out
resting in awareness
[Music]
so um I'll begin with um a cartoon I
saw um there's a school of fish swimming deep in the ocean and one of the fish
says "Are we there yet?" So in
um mindfulness practice we take a lot of care to get to know to understand our
thinking mind but that understanding is for a purpose the idea is to have freedom with
our thoughts however they are whether the mind's busy or if the mind is
exquisitly silent the Buddha said the dharma is good in
the beginning in the middle and in the
end in other words um it's good even if we spend most of the last meditation
distracted that awareness that brings us back is a moment of
freedom that awareness that sees the painfulness of the angry mind is a
moment of freedom the quote I read yesterday refers to
this taste of freedom this taste of
non-clinging just as this great ocean has one taste the taste of salt so also
this teaching and practice has one taste the taste of
liberation when we're mindful not clinging we get this taste of freedom
regularly a moment of mindfulness is not a moment of
clinging even if we're mindful of clinging that mindfulness is not
clinging so we can practice with that taste and experience that freedom
throughout the day these little moments these little tastes of
freedom and we can also live with the promise of freedom both a taste and a promise can
guide our lives we can have freedom with a busy
mind with restless thoughts freedom is there to be
found just one moment of not clinging not grasping it's there right there not
resisting it not pushing the moment away but attending to it with care allowing
it to flow the busy mind is not a
failure it's not a mistake it's there from the conditions
in our lives it takes only a moment to stop fighting
it to stop feeding it to just watch it do its thing until
it settles on its own
one of the classic teachings um uh one of the images for meditation
in the in Buddhism um is the image of a muddy
pond someone comes along and stirs up the bottom of the pond and all the mud
what needs to be done to have a clear pond is to leave the pond alone to allow
all the sediments to settle out the pond will become clear again all
by itself when we resist our experience
it's like stirring up the pond um Zen master Suzuki Roshi
said "When you meditate don't be bothered by your
thoughts they're just thoughts
so as we reflect on this
path this eight-fold path that the Buddha walked before us we can recognize
the forwardleading nature of this path to freedom it's a path we're going
somewhere we may be inspired by the idea of being free of greed hatred and
delusion or maybe the idea of the full blooming of our
hearts a heart that loves like the sun without
limits the idea of being at peace but also as we've been meditating
together this week moment by moment opening to our
experience we might also connect and this is um the title of one of Amma's
books uh and we might also connect with being nobody and going nowhere
and both of those are essential the forwardleading nature of the path and
being fully in the present moment in that moment being nobody going nowhere
there's a difference between having an aspiration to freedom an aspiration to free the heart
from the defilements and striving to get
there the difference between striving and aspiring is
suffering duka striving comes from the delusion
that what really counts is what's coming up and at this moment is somewhat not
enough lacking a bit not quite right it's what's coming up that's
good uh when I was in school I was regularly bored so I would
deeply contemplate the huge clock on the wall watching the seconds tick by just
waiting for the bell to ring once this boring class is over then I'll
be happy so to find myself at times echoing
that sentiment and meditation was an unwelcome
surprise i spent many of my much of my time during the years of education
striving to get to my real life once I graduated but once I began to work I couldn't wait
till the weekend i thought that's where my real life is but then I um during the
weekend I take a long drive to visit a friend and I'd often find myself leaning
forward and then voice would show up are we there yet are we there
yet striving has a contraction a tightness aspiration has a lightness of
heart we can climb a mountain with the aspiration of getting
to the top with a brightness of heart maybe inspired by the panorama we'll see when
we get there and on the way each step we take
can also be an arrival sensing the beauty around us
feeling our bodies walking on the trail sometimes we run into boulders on
the path that we need to climb over the boulders aren't wrong for being
there sometimes the path seems
easy and we're just enjoying the experience the sun on
us the beautiful sky the warmth and sometimes it's rough and
grally and awkward and sometimes it's deep and and
challenging and sometimes it's just easy downhill
sometimes the body aches the feet get tired but as we continue on the path we
don't leave our tired feet behind we bring all of who we are up the
mountain aching feet and
all but we can also climb that same mountain with a tide or grim
determination to get to the top to accomplish
it another checkbox of what we've done in our lives either way our body might show up
there but it's a very different experience we've climbed a very
different mountain with being nobody and going nowhere we
can be fully here if we're nobody we don't need to be
different in any way nothing has to change nothing has to happen this is the
taste of
freedom aspiration to freedom inspires us to keep choosing
what's wholesome to keep choosing the path even when it's
hard aspiration gladdens the heart if we're complacent or discouraged
the aspiration can lift the heart
and if we find ourselves striving remembering that we're being
nobody and going nowhere it can bring us back to
balance and in one way it's between these two seemingly opposite ideas that
the practice dances in its forwardleading way and going nowhere at
the same time
so thank you very much i've really appreciated um uh this
time with you and your beautiful comments and your
presence thank you