so good morning and welcome and
uh so for these weeks now idea is to slowly put together the
pieces the little steps to understand and to practice
samadi and um to give it's not really possible to in a
short time to give all the instructions that would really help understand the
elements of suadi practice and so to go through it really slowly and uh some of you might from
time to time be able to follow along uh closely to the instructions or
the guidance in one day and some of you won't and that's okay uh the idea is
take it in anyway and um don't uh uh um kind of
write it off because maybe you're agitated today uh or
something uh follow along the best you can maybe even with your imagination maybe even remembering a
time in your life where something like this was the case and uh so you have some it somehow
begins to register deeply so it's ready in meditation when it becomes relevant
for you so so today what I'm going to do is to say a few
words do a little guided kind of meditation to start us off and then do a
little exercise uh that involves opening the eyes and then closing the eyes again and
then getting started and so two things first that uh
the topic of pleasure last week was very important because we're using the simp
symptoms of of things going well in meditation the benefits of it as a kind
of as a as a funnel or as a helping us
gather and keep us in the practice and with time there's a direct feedback loop
between really being settled on an object of samade and and the strengthening of
those symptoms and um and uh whatever we're
doing with our mind and maybe our body whatever attitudes we have they'll have
a influence on the rest of us so if we spend a lot of time angry
there'll be symptoms of that in the body and chances are they're uncomfortable and those uncomfortable
Sensations then maybe subconsciously predispose us to feel
feel kind of unhappy about what's happening to us and so there's an uncons conscious subconscious kind of reaction
response feedback loop we get into we the anger makes us uncomfortable the discomfort makes us me more angry and so
it goes and often this kind of feedback loop goes
unrecognized in Sade we're using that feedback loop to feel the pleasure the
goodness of it just enough to stay focused and that uh the focus is not to
hold attention fixed mied but rather there's a gentle um the ancient text
talk about taking a nice soft cloth and putting against a brass Bowl putting it
there and then rubbing it cleaning it so these two steps placing there and then
gently rubbing it or a bird that's going to fly will flap its wings kind of
strongly to get up or is flying maybe but needs to kind of soar a little bit higher will flap its wings and then soar
flap its wings and soar and uh this is called um applied
and sustained attention that very gently there's a kind of returning to the breath staying
on it surfing on it stay sustaining attention there and then there'll be a
reapplying of that reapplication of attention we're not just holding our attention mention
there and uh but there's a relaxed soft kind of massage in a sense
touching kneading touching kneading touching petting touching petting that
we do and this is called in p vaka and vichara so these two things the feedback
loop and this kind of this application of attention and sustaining it where that massage is what
is part of what's keeping the the symptoms the pleasure the well-being uh
kind of moving it along and sustaining it so I'll do now we'll do the short
kind of settling meditation and then I will do an exercise with the eyes with
looking before we close our eyes again in order to do talk apply
this so to take a meditation posture
and for now gently close your
eyes and with your eyes closed take a few gently deeper breaths
not too deep comfortably deep and a comfortably long exhale
breathing in fully and on the exhale relaxing the
body and then letting your breathing return to
normal taking a few moments to feel your Global body the way your body
is grounded or settled in the seat that you're
on the surface that's receiving your body
weight and as you exhale gently release your body into the pool
of gravity
into being grounded in your seat
and then breathing normally relaxing on the exhale relaxing
the
face softening in the shoulders
softening the
belly and then centering yourself on the
breathing Maybe
allowing the weight of attention to settle into
the settling place the grounding place of your
breathing maybe at the end of the out breath the very beginning of the INB
breath
and then to do the exercise with the eyes
open your eyes and find a
spot that particular spot that's in front of you where that you can stare on that you
can hold your eyes on that spot
unwavering it's a very small spot and don't let your eyes leave that
spot hold your eyes still so it really stays
on the spot and we'll do that for about 15 seconds
and notice with your eyes fixed if there's any tension anywhere in your
body the shoulders the belly the eyes that comes with that kind of
fixing and now keeping your eyes open
look into space and let your eyes float in the eye
sockets and just kind of let your eyes roam around the room the place you're in
without any purpose without staring at anything just kind of almost like
tracing the outlines of things or floating around
maybe not even looking at things but almost as if you're not focused on any particular
thing but your eyes are roaming around as if you're following the track that
the trail of a fly flying around that flies flying very slowly and
relaxedly and your eyes just kind of gently do what they want to do no will
or no D no intention no directing your eyes just
let them float around the room
and now feel your eyes feel your face your body your
shoulders is this more relaxed for the eyes to be this way than it was to hold
them fixed on a spot and of course it' be different for
different people but a fair number of people find
that fixating fixing their eyes on something is more of a strain than
letting the eyes float and roam
around so the same thing with breathing if we try to fix our attention on
breathing it can become stressful but if we do something equivalent with attention as we did with
our eyes letting attention roam around with the
breathing it can be more relaxing so now still with your eyes
open find a relatively small spot not as small as
before some object that's that you can and maintain your focus on that object
so you're not roaming around with the whole room but in the
within the scope of this object let your eyes
roam looking at it seeing it so you see it with some
clarity but the eyes are also relaxedly floating around the object
and now closing your
eyes and let your awareness your attention settle on the breathing in out the
movements of the body breathing the sensations of breathing maybe coming and going from
your your centering spot for the
breathing in the same way let your attention be relaxed and
soft but follow Trace roam around within the sensations
of breathing
and then there's a settling or placing the attention
there again and resting there sustaining this free relaxed floating
attention so you feel and sense clearly the sensations are
breathing but there's a feeling of Freedom or ease in the
awareness and very gently there is a kind of a
reapplying awareness in the transition from breathing in to breathing
out from breathing out to breathing in so let there be a soft reapplying
reconnecting a connecting to the in breath when it begins connecting to the
out breath when it begins and then sustaining attention in
a soft relaxed way if the out INB breath is momentary
just let it be like a spark that appears in the night
sky if it's longer let it be like
a a wave or a river in which you gently
walk
flowing
by and if your attention Slips Away from breathing
see if you can avoid any judgments reactions to that
happened just see it as an opportunity to reapply
attention to put the cloth back on the edge of the bowl and then to rub
it to Flap the wings again and then to glide on the breath
and being careful not to try too hard this whole exercise
is just short of doing
nothing mostly
it's you're continually returning and opening awareness to the small area where
breathing
predominates maybe breathing is the
cloth and the movement of breathing is the cloth polishing your awareness
for for
sometimes wandering off into thought is a very small movement that takes you
very not very far
away and even if it a small moving away in
thought return reconnect to breathing in a relaxed soft
way almost like an act of
Love connecting and sustaining attention with
breathing for
and if there's any pleasure associated
with applying and sustaining connecting and staying with the
breathing allow that pleasure to be there
to remind you how good it is to
stay with the breathing with the relaxed soft
attention not fixating
attention almost as if it
roams in the particular are area where breathing Sensations
occur or the sensations of breathing roam around in
awareness at the center of being
aware
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting imagine your sit sitting on a
park bench a nice warm sunny
day gazing upon the
trees the birds the Gophers
squirrels with a relaxed gaze not fixating on
anything not staring but letting your eyes roam
be at ease
soft and there are people who come by but in this scenario you feel safe
and comfortable and nothing's asked of you and you allow your roaming eyes to
gently roam around with the people seeing them in a relax soft
way maybe there's no judgments no conclusions about people just soft
and gentle gazing upon the
world and as if this kind of gazing
is a vehicle to transmit our good will smile
gently smile on the people in your life smile thinking about the people and
strangers you might run into today gazing upon them with a relaxed
awareness and wish them well let your good will your goodness your
kindness travel into this relaxed awareness from you to
them as if you touch their hearts with a medicine of
kindness may all beings be
happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we all care with care for each other
with [Music]
[Music]
kindness thank
you so while I drink my water that might be nice helpful for me if
there were some comments about what it was like to do that exercise and that taught you something different about how
to be closely attentive to
breathing
e e
so thank you for those of you chatting about the exercise and
um I'll read U more of them after finished now so welcome to this next
talk on samadi and um and for this week uh we're
going to uh be looking at something that commonly in English is called access
concentration or access sombody though the the word
access uh never really quite s sat well with sits well with
me um the word in pachara um my understanding it it means
close something more closely to um uh approach
approaching Chara means to wander and to wander towards something and based on
that meditation we just did the idea that the that we attention has a little
bit quality of wandering soft roaming but it's roaming towards a particular
place it's moving towards something uh when I think of EX C
concentration I think of um like there's a door I have to go
through and uh and um but uh but I think
of approach then uh wandering towards approaching then I it's more of a kind
of a gentle movement like a like a river flowing that or I'm in the groove of
something and now I'm gliding along I'm in the slide sliding I'm approaching and
we're approaching a a shift that will happen when the samade kind of uh uh
Clicks in when the somadi kind of um uh becomes kind of a u uh envelops us or
begins to have a life of its own in a sense um uh when we we don't have to
make as much effort there's not so much dependent on us practicing but it's more that we're being practiced at some point
but we're approach roing this point where the shift begins to happen and um and there's a number of
things that begin coming together uh in this stage the stage called the
approach and um and one of them is that we get in the kind of in the in the
Rhythm or in the with a sense of ease with um uh these two uh factors of
samade which is connecting attention and sustaining attention
and um uh the awareness that places
attention and the awareness that stays there uh some people emphasize that
sometimes that involves a little bit of very rudimentary thought that the
thought is oh come back to the breathing and the thought that kind of kind of
begins to feel and sense what's going on know it more cck carefully oh that's a
smooth inhale that's a smooth out tail that's a a step by step inhale just
moves inhale goes up up up in kind of steps or that's smooth that's Pleasant
so it's not so conscious the thoughts but exactly they consciously done but there can be very simple uh kind of
thinking that keeps us in the flow of it and um and so um and the um the class
analogy that we'll review talk about again later is uh is
Akin uh to in the modern world uh mixing
uh water into flour to make dough where we start kneading the dough uh in order
to really spread uh the uh the Water Into the the moisture into the all the
uh the flower particles become moist and some way there's kind of a kneading and a full folding and and maybe it is like
folding folding bread and eaing bread and uh and if you were are very
relaxed and enjoy making bread enjoy eating bread it can be delightful uh
activity to just be kneading it and folding and kneading and folding um or or I associate sometimes
with um when I have uh received a massage and um and sometimes in certain
massages I like to breathe in the rhythm of the massuse kneading my muscles and
this uh breathing with uh the slow kneading of the different muscles um just feels like such a nice way of
flowing and being really present and connected to what's happening and uh so it's not a fixing
attention it's not steering at something and some people when they think of uh
concentration they feel like they have to kind of have this laser focus that's unwavering and um and that can create a
lot of strain but rather it's a very soft uh I like to think of it as um uh
just short of doing nothing just enough and different times of day different
times of situations that just enough uh is different how much effort we have to
make but uh but we're trying to make a very light effort so that some of the
the natural way in which awareness kind of roams and explores and moves around
an object happens just like with the eyes a relaxed eyes will roam around an
object to see it in different ways with very relaxed um uh movements not no not
staring at something if we want something from the object that we were looking at um then we stare and then
there could be a strain but if we just kind of want to know it in a relaxed way so the same thing with
um with uh feeling and senting um and it's uh some people it's
much more physical it's a fencing and feeling sometimes it's more of a
observing sometimes it's more of a knowing that goes on but it's really
right there with the breathing and what's nice about the rhythm of breathing people who for whom this works
is that the the rhythm of the breathing is little bit akin to the rhythm of um
connecting and sustaining attention connecting and sustaining attention stay right here stay right here and if that
can be done so it's almost like the the the the concentration that builds it
doesn't build from in sustaining but it builds in action in the activity of
connecting and sustaining connecting sustaining and the Art of this is to
know how to do that so that um it just feels like a natur for you the natural
Rhythm or easeful or or absorbing to do it and as I said sometimes if uh you can
almost use the inhale and exhale as the speed and rhythm of that massage so to
connect with the beginning of the inhale sustain it to the end connect to the beginning of exhale
sustain it to the end and um and uh and these two little activities connecting
sustaining give us just enough to do that it might be easier to stay focused
there um on the breathing in a relaxed absorbing way and there might be
thoughts but they kind of go to the periphery we don't have to be focused on them
and there at this point this stage in the meditation yes there will be thoughts that begin taking you away
that's normal that's completely at this stage the approach stage but uh but they don't take you very
far and now you can kind of watch and see the Mind beginning to go and because
you're in this rhythm of connecting and sustaining you see it the thinking beginning to go away and then you kind
of fold it back in fold thinking back into the activity of staying with a
breath rhythm with a breath some of you might find that it works better if you always can maintain
that very quiet counting uh very still soft count
because it gives a thinking mind something to do that keeps you focused rather than uh you know have thinking
mind Idol so it wanders off for some people uh uh rather than
counting there might be a single word like in out or even the word yes works
very well and uh I found the word yes to work really well when I'm also at the
same time become starting to become aware of the good influence that the
meditation has on the rest of me the pleasure that we talked about last week
and we start and the the pleasure becomes like the supporting actors or
the pleasure becomes the cheerleaders or the pleasure becomes the the encouragement you're doing well this is
good and um and uh and then you're um uh you know
it's almost like it's the pleasure is is teaching you oh this is a nice way of
doing it so for example M needing the bread uh if you're in a hurry and you
you know you can't really have to finish it quickly and and maybe there's people around you wanting your attention and
they're upset with you because you're not paying enough attention to them then you start needing it really fast and in
a stressful way and it doesn't feel good but if no one's there and you love doing
the bread you like the quiet and peace of the kitchen the lighting is coming in from the window just right and
everything is clean around you in the kitchen and and you don't have any any
press pressing responsibilities the moment and it just feels such a wonderful Delight to feel the texture
and the moisture and the and the movements of kneading the bread and
something inside of you kind of begins to relax and soften that says oh this is good almost like you don't want to stop
doing it uh even though you you're needing it Way Beyond what's really necessary it's just like such a nice
thing to do so uh whether you could follow all that in your own practice
um that is um um you know the IDE is all this is
supposed to if nothing else uh not be what you should do but it could be maybe
a a reference point to understand what you do do what works for you and what doesn't work for you so uh uh maybe some
of you will know clearly that um yeah counting doesn't work other people will
yes it works some people will say oh this thing about um this connecting and
sustaining I don't quite understand it I already have a good way of being with the breathing so I think I'll stay with
it for now so you're kind of finding your own way but I'm offering you all these
different elements and hopefully some of them will work for you support you in the process of becoming uh really
absorbed in the meditation practice absorbed in
such a way that the Mind thinking mind becomes quieter and Stiller and softer
and there's a feeling of well-being connected to meditation so may your connecting and
sustaining of attention May that movement be one that
uh can bring you Joy through the day that maybe throughout the day uh
there's a gentle massage of things you have to connect to and then sustain even
if it's as simple as connecting to a door handle and sustaining that connection until the doors open and um
may it be a a way of entering the present moment more fully so thank you