good evening welcome
welcome so tonight I want to talk a little bit um about
conflict and interestingly there's this way that conflict shows up in theas the
early Buddhist literature in that apparently there is some Heavenly
realm this is just like some little Side Story That's Just sprinkled in very
rarely but it's in there a few times in the suas this heavenly realm where the
gods and the Titans are always battling they're always in
conflict and this and the Gods in kind like in Buddhist cosmology they are just
disembodied beings they have no special powers they don't have special knowledge
or anything like this they're just like humans who happen to be
disembodied and Titans are I don't know what they are they are
other disembodied beings who are not gods and they are there's this conflict
between the gods and the Titans uh the poly word for Titan is Aura and some
people translate them as demons but uh they're not demonic so much as you'll
see so looking a little bit about these uh Gods and Titans interact and
specifically the king of the Gods and the king of the Titans interact we can learn a little bit about conflict about
uh how it was portrayed and how they um what the Buddha had to say about it and
you know what Jim I asked you to increase the volume but now can we decrease it just a tiny bit I can hear
that it's a little bit Lou yeah so is it possible that it could be just like in between there yeah so I'm not having to
throw my voice okay thank you
so maybe not surprisingly because there's yeah I'm sorry can it be just a
little bit tighter I feel bad as this but I'll lose my voice by the end of the evening if we don't do this okay I think
this will be good so Saka who is the king of the Gods
right they're always in this uh conflict with the Titans he asks the Buddha about
this and I'm paraphrasing a little bit he says to the Buddha when beings
including Gods humans and Titans all wish to live in
peace why are they perpetually embroiled in conflict and this is a question where we
could ask ourselves everybody wants to live in peace but why is there so much
conflict why is is there so much disagreement or violence and all these things that are happening and then the
in answer to this question the Buddha gives a discourse that um it begins by
saying this discourse like is tracing the cause of uh conflict and hostility
and uh the Buddha first says to Saka the co um why there is conflict is because
people have jealousy and stingy and that is we could say is wanting what
other people have or not wanting to share what you
have it's all about you know like mine I need more this kind of a feeling that uh
certainly we see a lot of that right in contemporary times too and soing that God is very happy to
finally learn this like oh okay okay great jealousy and stinginess is the source of conf
fantastic thank you I understand this and then Saka says but wait what's the
cause of jealousy and stinginess and then the Buddha says
um you know what I didn't write the whole list here but maybe I'll summarize this because the Buddha he's he points
to subtler and subtler things that are underg guarding each of these things and it gets all the way down to views
beliefs opinions this is the source of conflict and it gets expressed in so
many different ways there's this way in which clinging
to our views leads to conflict and some of you might be Pro protesting but of course
I'm clinging to My Views I'm right they're wrong of course you know
of course but there's this way in which we all know this that clinging like holding on
tightly to anything isn't the way to Greater Peace and Freedom whether it's a view or
whether it's uh well I guess views are probably the
strongest that we hold on to so tightly or maybe this wish to control
other people or you know there another way in which we hold on to things so not holding on to not clinging
to philosophies or doctrine or even teachings or including Buddhist
teachings right that's not to be held on to they can be a support and they can be
helpful but clinging to anything is not the way to the greatest
Freedom they can be held I've often find myself doing this like with open hands
as opposed to really holding on and part of the way that we can
recognize that the Buddha he's placing this emphasis on not clinging not holding on to not gripping our views is
he describes an awakened person somebody who has the most amount of Freedom
complete freedom and in this uh small little quote he says an awakened person is not
an enemy to any Doctrine seen heard or thought but not
forming opinions not shut down and not desirous they are wise ones who have
laid the burden down so the burden of trying to hold on like I'm right and
you're wrong I know things and you don't so it's not that they don't have
ideas and but and this word opinions here opinions are often like our views
that have implicit in them and here's how you're wrong and here's how you should fix it it's kind of like you know
this recommendation of a something that you should do so the Buddha is saying a completely
awakened person isn't one that's out there fighting with everybody who has different
teachings or has a different understanding instead they're helping other people to find more freedom
they're not spending time putting down everybody
else so this idea of to not engaging in disputes over beliefs and Views because
this recognition that uh when we get into disputes or conflicts about views
it just tends to lead to dogmatism it leads to like fundamentalism like people just dig in to their views when they're
kind of like see uh opposite ones we see this happening a lot in the
on the world stage or even in our um
Even in our personal lives we can see that oh just because somebody is has a
different view than our than we do then we just kind tend often to hold our views a little bit tighter maybe we feel
a little bit threatened by something that's completely different feel threatened of wait if they believe
something that I believe then that means I'm wrong so they can't be right because
implicit in that is I'm wrong so I must be right and they are wrong and then soon as you have this feeling like I'm
right then this US versus them Dynamic gets even uh created in even a stronger way and
and this can we just dig in in whatever way is necessary
or I heard this a story once that had a big impact on me I think it was from Sharon
solsburg uh she's a one of the elders in this tradition and she talks about um how she
found herself in this really big fight about with another Budd Buddhist
practitioner but a different Buddhist tradition than this one about what happens after death and their voices
were getting higher and higher and they were like fighting and arguing and then she realized what are we fighting
about we don't know we're not dead we don't actually know and yet there's this
big way that they both got kind of dug into their own beliefs and Views about
this because part of the truth I mean the truth is is that
we have this tendency to think that we know the truth based on our experience
of course of course but by Nature we have a limited
experience we don't have like all possible experiences so other people's views
often are coming from their experience and ours are coming from ours
so it does it's we often are setting up this Dynamic of like well My Views are
based on you know observation and thoughtfulness and intellect and those
their views are just you know idian syncratic and weird but it's just really all based on
people's experiences right nobody's making views just for the fun of it out of complete
nothing
so there's this way in which our unexamined opinions or assumptions or
beliefs we've just inherited them we have experiences but part of this
experien is the family we grew up in the culture we grew up in the society we
grew up in the society we're in now we're just kind of like uh adopting
these without necessarily looking at them or examining them and of course we are some ways that's how we Define
society and culture people have similar views that's okay of course we have them
the problem is the clinging and the insisting that we are right and everybody else is
wrong US versus them and with this practice something
that I appreciate so much it's like we don't have to turn off our critical intelligence and just adopt some
beliefs that is absolutely not what this practice is about what this tradition is about instead it's the opposite it's an
encouragement to investigate get
curious about what you hear as the teachings what you read about the
teachings and about yourself what are your views how how did you come to have them
are they helpful do they lead to more freedom or not and what I'm pointing to
is not the great like psychological archaological dig which is something a little bit different but just this uh
this openness this curiosity just like asking the question
where did these come from or what are my beliefs it's the asking of the question
that makes the difference because asking of the question just helps this recognition like oh yeah this is a
belief and there might be another belief possible if we don't ask that question that we just assume there's only one
belief the one that I have and it's the right one but just
asking helps create some space and some room for something else to a new idea or
maybe a new understanding or appreciation of people who have different beliefs different views
so when Saka asks the Buddha why why would everybody wants peace why is there
so much conflict the Buddha starts with something that's obvious and that we all experience like wanting more not wanting
to share and then when Saka has this conversation well what about that and
that and that they get down to views and beliefs this is a source of
conflict now I'd like to share another little story with uh Saka the king of the Gods and uh the king of the Titans
here's a another little story about conflict and in this uh The suas
Preserve this the Buddha is telling this story to the
monastics and there was this there was a battle
between the gods and the Titans and then the king of the Titans his name is
vti he goes to Saka the king of the Gods and says let's have a debate and let's
win over debate so this is after a battle maybe they said okay you know I'm tired of fighting maybe there's got to
be another way we can do this let's uh have a debate I'm paraphrasing here of course
and uh Saka the king of the God says okay so they assembled a panel of both
gods and Titans who they said would you know be able to determine who wins the
debate and then vti the king of the Titans he uh says to the king of the
Gods um why don't you go first and Saka
the king of the God says no you're the senior David you're the S senior here
why don't you go first it's a little bit of respect there and so V pitti the king of the
Titans he the this is the F his uh first uh statement and this is done in verse
so the English feels a little clunky sometimes but it's then in
verse fools who would vent anger even more if no one would keep wait here we
go fools would vent anger even more if no one would keep them in check hence
with drastic punishment the wise person restrains the fool
and the Titans applaud and the gods are silent for me I
just love this little bit of detail right we see this so much today right if you're on this team or that team or this
side of the aisle or that side of the aisle you're like all this you're just whatever you're yay and then uh this side is silent
right this was you know composed thousands of years ago and here we are still doing the same thing
so then um so the king of the Titans said that
and then um he said to the king of the Gods now you speak and the king of the Gods
says I think that this is the only way to put a stop to a
fool when you know that the other is upset be mindful and stay
calm and the gods applauded and the Titans were
silent and then uh the god of the Titans speaks next and he
says I see this fault Saka Saka writes the name of the king of the Gods I see
this fault Saka in just being patient when a fool thinks of you thus he puts
up with me out of fear the fool will chase you even more like a bull chasing someone who
flees so the king of the Titans is uh criticizing this whole idea of be
mindful and stay calm because he's saying well if you don't you know really punish them or hit them with Force
they're just they will assume that you are afraid and if they think that you are afraid they will go after you even
more and of course the Titans applauded when uh the king of the Titans said this
and then uh the king of the Gods replies let the fool think this if he
wishes that he puts up with me out of fear of goals culminating in one's own
good none better than patience is found I'll read that it's a little bit clunky
of goals culminating in one's own good
none better than patience is found this idea that patience really supports
one's own good one's benefit idea of patience and then he
continues when you get angry at an angry person you just make things worse when
you don't get angry at an angry person you win a battle hard to
win right I love this right if one person's angry and then another person's angry and they get angry again then
where's it going to end right you can't stop anger with more anger it's impossible it's just somebody it has to
stop somewhere or else there's just this resentment that just bruise and gets bigger and
bigger and here's Saka the king of the Gods is saying when
you when you don't get angry at an angry person you win a battle hard to
win otherwise right it just escalates escalates escalated and if you could just say you know what I'm just not
going to play that game I'm just not going to I'm just not going to engage and play that game with
you win a battle hard to win and then the king of the Gods
continues when you know that the other is angry you act for the good of both
yourself and the other if you're Mindful and stay calm so the king of the Gods he's also
saying that it's also beneficial not only for you to not get angry but it
helps them also and this is the greater good right
to support the person who is you are in conflict with and to support
yourself to not escalate instead to deescalate by simply being Mindful and
calm of course this is powerful it's not our natural impulse of
course and then this uh ends with the the um the panel of Judges that are
consisting of both gods and Titans said this the verses spoken by the king of
the Titans evoke punishment and violence that's how you get to arguments quarrels
and disputes the verses spoken by the king of Gods don't evoke punishment and
viol Ence that's how you stay free of arguments quarrels and
disputes you can imagine that uh all the gods clapped when they heard that and
the Titans uh were silent when this final ruling came
down this idea of being patient this idea of being Mindful and
calm in the face of conflict when meeting
somebody who's perhaps uh meeting you with
anger this is not something easy it's not something that's
straightforward and there's this way in which we can understand patience is this nonreactivity it's like
not acting on these uh impulses that aren't helpful that uh aren't supportive for us
so not raging and not blaming and not blaming themselves or not blaming um not
blaming others not blaming ourselves or not despairing or not making wild
stories but just to say wow okay so there's anger here and this is
uncomfortable I wish it weren't here maybe I don't even know what to do but
not escalating but said being mindful like recognizing this is very uncomfortable I
I wish it weren't like this chances are but is there a way that we can just
have hold our difficulties maybe in a spacious way instead of you know trying
to fix everything by as fast as possible by yelling or acting very quickly irrationally
perhaps be before we've had a chance to think things through is there a way that we can have
this more more openness and feels more peaceful and this recognition that yes this is difficult but I don't have to
fix it right this moment often we want to just to get out
of that feeling of discomfort and part of meditation practice this is not in the advertising
but part of meditation practice is to learn to hold discomfort because sometimes it's just
physically uncomfortable to be sitting still or sometimes we're meditating and
uncomfortable emotions come up or uncomfortable memories come up and as as
best we can to be able to hold them this is great practice for our daily life the
exact same thing right to discomfort arises and can we hold it so meditation
practice of course it's a allows some steadying of the mind but even if you're
having a very uncomfortable meditation session there's tremendous value tremendous
value in that so is there a way that we don't can
not lash out and maintain composure even when we're met with uh
somebody who is angry just instead maybe just take a deep breath feel our feet on the
ground and maybe even just doing that taking a deep breath and allowing that person to to see it maybe that's enough
that can uh bring things down maybe not
too don't underestimate how helpful it can be to feel your feet on the ground
often when there's conflict we don't have our wits with us necessarily that's instead we're feeling like oh wow what's
happening but feeling our feet on the ground is a way we can feel grounded and
uh maybe steady otherwise the thoughts are more likely to go out and spin and make some wild
stories so to have some patience when meeting some
conflict but I want to say a little bit about what patience isn't because it's
uh tempting when we hear about this okay have some non-reactivity to maybe think about it
in a certain way but patience isn't like this numbing resignation like
okay all right and there was this kind of like uh and we just kind of like
disconnect from our emotions disconnect from The Experience disconnect from what's Happening and there's this kind
of this okay well I'm just going to check out until this is over and then
maybe I'll check back in later maybe I won't so that's not patience that's
numbing resignation that's like just checking out is there way that we can stay
present feel our feet on the ground take a deep breath and feel the discomfort and not run away not check out I'm not
saying this is easy but there's a way that meditation practice really can support us in this
just this feeling discomfort and realizing okay it's not going to kill me I don't like it that's okay we don't
have to like everything it's
also patience is not gritting your teeth holding on and you know just
um maybe waiting for things to be over but with a lot of tension we could call
that waiting with aversion that's different than patience patience has this way of some
steadiness and allowing things to unfold so recognizing uncomfortableness
staying connected and allowing things to unfold how they're going to unfold
they'll unfold differently if we have some steadiness of course they will if we have some
calm patience also is not like being impervious to pressure it's not like
saying nope I'm going to stand here and not do anything no matter what that's just
stubbornness so instead uh patience is okay I'm feeling connected I know what's
happening I'm allowing things to unfold and it might become clear that it would be really wise to do this thing or that
other thing and then we do this thing or that other thing but we're not just
standing there not be uh not reacting as uh just out of principle and even though
it might be harmful to others or to ourselves to do that we're not doing it just for the sake of doing
it and patience the way that I'm describing it of course is not passivity this is work right to not check out not
run away but to stay present and this is a way that really we
can be with conflict is okay can I hold this and not masking or suppressing
what's happening maybe we flashes of anger come up maybe maybe flashes of
like why is this happening to me comes up but we're not acting unskillfully we're acknowledging our
experience and as best we can we're holding them spaciously with some
patience so that's one way to work with conflict is right this patience and
mindfulness and calmness and then the first story with suaka when he was asking the Buddha
about okay well why when everybody wants peace why is there so much conflict and the Buddha eventually got
down to well it's about views so this is a second way to work with
conflict is to have some awareness what are the views that we are holding on to
or that we are um maybe maybe just to Simply become
aware of our beliefs because most likely our views and beliefs they are not obvious to us
that's kind of the nature of views and beliefs that they are kind like buried underneath they're subtle and they are
have a giant impact on our life our actions but they're not obvious to
us and we may not even recognize them until there's a conflict and we realize
oh there's something here that's getting threatened what is it that feels threatened and this can be a way just
bring some curiosity to this this could be a way in which we can recognize oh
yeah I have this belief that things should be this way and they're not that way and they should be that way we might
have that belief and somehow just recognizing our
beliefs and naming them allows them to be held a little bit
less tightly I'm not saying we have to get rid of them I'm not saying we have to change them all but it's if we become
aware of them then we could start to see and recognize okay what's helpful what's not helpful what leads to more freedom
what leads to less Freedom can we bring curiosity and some
inquiry into our beliefs are like our inner life our views what are we holding on to is it
helpful maybe I also just want to add in here that beliefs are resistant to change they're not something that once
we see them they're going to be different or if we see things are like for example we might have a belief no
pain no gain I think this was a Nike slogan right for years ago but this idea that
you have to work hard and if you're not working hard nothing Good's going to happen I know I certainly had this
belief and uh I mean it worked until it didn't right until I the working hard
this idea that I had to work hard I realized oh actually this belie of
working heart I'm using this as a distraction from the rest of my life from my inner life and all these
difficulties my insisting that I have to work harder harder harder I just put all my attention and my energy there and was
ignoring everything else in my life my inner life my relationships these types of things I'm not saying you don't have
to work hard of course not but we might have a belief that uh nothing valuable
will happen unless we're doing that unless there's a lot of
striving and then there's a way in which we can dismiss things that are beautiful
uplifting easeful we might just be dismissing them when that might be exactly what's
needed in some ways all of us are so often I shouldn't say all of us many of
us are have this like this uh needs some nourishment like need some nourishment
of uh some ease and well-being and no pain no gain is uh can get in the
way get in the way of this so working with conflict we can
work we can learn from the king of the Gods the king of the Titans who uh have some conflict I guess
uh that's kind of what the Buddhist cosmology has and uh the Buddha is teachings about
well look at your views and have patience at your views and have patience
don't feel like you have to act so quickly and when I was thinking about
this I thought well looking at your views and have patience for me kind of felt like taking the high road right
this kind might be a way in which we might understand that uh in contemporary
teaching like oh this is what part of taking the high road means
and then I'll end with this last little story about the king of Gods and the
king of the titans the king of the Titans was really sick he was uh ill and
the king of the Gods went to him and uh offered to cure him you know I can cure
you I can make you say you're not sick anymore but I'd like you to teach me this magic
uh s's magic I don't know who SRA is some character teach me the magic of
sbur that's what the king of the Gods is saying and the king of the Titans said
no I'm not going to teach that to you because sbra used this magic and now
he's in purgatory and in hell I don't want you to have to go to hell so I'm
not going to teach it to you so there was some kindness there so here we are these two uh people that are two people
two beings that are in constant conflict and yet there was a way they had some
care and respect for one another
too so working with conflict with views and
patience maybe a little bit of respect in there to sprinkle some in that can't
hurt and with that I'll end and open it up to see if there's some comments or
questions thank you
so one of the aold path is Right View and I'm wondering Enlightenment like the
Buddha for example does he have the right views is it possible to have views that are actually
correct yeah thank you for bringing this up so right view some
the word right is not like the opposite of wrong in that setting it's more like
right in terms of like the correct tool the way that you would if you needed to
paint a wall you would use a paintbrush not a screwdriver kind of thing like that so your question is about does the
Buddha can you ask it again so in other words Enlightenment like a liberated being like the Buddha for example or who
who I'm sure the other ones but he he must have some sort of views
of some nature are they actually true correct I see I
see the actually I think the question is so is or the answer is whatever views
there are he's not holding on to them clinging to them so has we might say like well this
is his current understanding or this is this uh what seems to be true now
something like he's holding things that that way and then so there's just it's an absence of clinging so it's not maybe
that the views are I guess they are correct I don't
know next time I meet a Buddha I definitely will ask them though but isn't the Dharma of view is like a it's
a way of seeing right is could it be looked at as as a way of viewing the spiritual
path sure sure we could view the spiritual path like the Buddha talks
about this as a we're going to learn everything on this path so that we can better at winning debates with people
with other religious traditions and the Buddha would say no that's actually not a good reason why to learn this it's more to find more freedom or something
like that so is that helpful yeah great thank
you anybody else have a
I think it's I think I'll just offer more of a comment and then I'm reminded in your discussion of conflict a line
from the talmud which is uh a hero is someone who turns an enemy
into a friend and I could just see at the end of The Last
Story um some kindness turning to friendship between like the god of the Titans and uh Saka like this oh yeah
kindness coming first or even when uh was it Reagan when he met Gorbachev
there was a me he was like Hey if aliens were coming to attack your country would you let me know he's like oh yeah and
that was kind of star of a dialogue between the two of them that's just the comment thank you
nice nice thank you thank you
Conrad uh just a comment um so two actually one question then a
comment I know in Buddhism like the emphasis often is on Equanimity but I'm
wondering if patience I feel like it could hold an equal place but it's not
often talked about is that my understanding correct perception yeah so patients and this is a a good question
like how is it different than equinity and uh patients is part of the pyrames
which are these uh practices that are usually practiced not on the meditation cushion but out in daily life but
equinity is a little bit higher bar equinity is
um like patience would be more like okay this is really uncomfortable and I wish it weren't otherwise but uh I'm going to
stay here as best I can and be with it equinity was like oh wow look at that it's
uncomfortable and not with the sense of like oh and I really wish it weren't here what can I do to get to to
persevere through this so I quity is more like just noticing discomfort and as discomfort and not wanting to push it
away or get away from it uh and the second comment I was going
to make was especially when you talked about patients in terms of the when being in the
conflict um there's a quote in the taed Chang you've probably heard it already the Steven Mitchell version he says do
you have the patience to let the water settle and let the answer Rise by itself
here we go something like that there you go lots a good wisdom Diana there was a question on the
chat which is what what's the name of the suta so these are uh two different sutas
uh so the one with um uh where Saka asks the Buddha you
know what when everybody wants peace why is there conflict that's the Saka suta
that's a de 21 and then the other one where the uh
the king of the Titans and the king of the gods are in conflict and they're having this debate that's I doesn't have
a title necessarily I don't remember what the oh yes uh fine words it's
called and that is samut 115 so we go
any other
comments okay so may you have a if you I
was going to say may you have a conflict free but maybe you need to have conflict so then you can practice like what are
My Views have some patience may you have a wonderful evening thank you