so welcome again Welcome all of you I'm happy to be back with you again
sharing the dharma with all of you It uh just warms my heart to see um many
familiar names um uh over here on the uh chat and um and also just uh being aware
of how far and wide this um online sa extends Um it's very moving to
me Um so the focus this week will be on the various aspects of mindful
thinking Before we begin the meditation I want to share a few thoughts about
thinking You most of us like feeling calm and not having a lot of thoughts
running around the mind And because of that it's easy to judge thinking in
meditation as being undesirable But we all think it's
important not to place thinking outside of the meditation process
But what we want to do is encourage thoughts that are helpful to us and
discourage thoughts that are harmful to us Thinking can be a wonderful tool in
meditation We use thoughts to bring us back when we're distracted to remind us to relax the
body when we're tense to encourage ourselves to recognize the hindrances
when they arise We might use thoughts to guide ourselves to look deeper to explore to
investigate or just encourage ourselves to persevere But thinking like many tools
can also be used unskillfully such as habitually judging ourselves and others getting lost in
regrets in useless planning in worry in
rehearsing or judging or indulging in fantasies while
meditating But we can let thoughts be We don't need to get rid of them We just
don't need to pick them up and get lost in them When we're mindful of them
friendly with them we can let them come and go So let's sit
So take a comfortable but alert posture and gently close your eyes
Taking a few deep breaths And with each
exhale settling into the body relaxing any obvious tension or
holding
allowing the breath to return to [Music] normal You might get a global sense of
the body allowing the attention to meander freely throughout
the body relaxing any obvious tensions
And staying close to the body intimate with the body
sensations you can begin to notice the movements of the
breath allowing your attention to rest on the breath
Settling into the rhythm of the breath However it
is resting in this body in this breath
You might consider the mind as having a foreground and
background Placing the breath the body and the
foreground As long as thoughts remain in the background we can let them be
there They're not a problem Staying intimate with the body
breathing in and out We can allow everything else to be in the
background There's room for everything Nothing needs to be pushed away
We can be like a mountain rooted in this
body still
strong here The mind might wander
away but you can easily return and feel yourself
here rooted in this body in the
present And when thoughts arise they're just like clouds floating past the
mountain The mountain doesn't chase them It doesn't judge
them It doesn't try to hold on to them
thoughts can come in words in fragments of
sentences even whole sentences in
images stories or even just knowing
However thoughts are be alert to any strong pull or
compulsion that comes from
them If the thinking becomes prominent and it's in the foreground we can bring mindfulness to
it A kind curiosity an affectionate curiosity
How does it feel to be
thinking what's the tone of our inner
voice is it relaxed is it harsh
gentle if the tone is not friendly in any way see if you can encourage a
kinder attitude
How does it feel in the body to be thinking do we feel it anywhere in
particular if there's a lot of thinking sometimes we might feel like bees are buzzing in our heads
Is there location that seems to generate
it is there extra tension associated with
thinking can we relax into it
and if thoughts are no longer prominent just allow them to fade away
And if thoughts are very charged is there an emotion
underneath some form of aversion or anger or
fear or wanting or desire
if so you might shift the attention to see how those feel in the
body We can come out of the story and into the
body But if nothing is prominent you can allow the awareness to rest in the body
on the breath with an attitude of
friendliness Simply allowing any thoughts to come and go
If the mind has drifted gently bring it back to the
present moment to this breath to this body
to home
[Music]
my um first several years of meditation
practice even though I understood the basic teachings of mindfulness I'd even
set a few retreats it took me several years before I began to understand the
importance of being mindful of thinking Um there's a quote that paraphrases and
simplifies one of the Buddhist teachings With our thoughts we create
the world And all of us have experienced both wonderful worlds in our minds and
we've all had very painful word worlds in our minds Each one generated by our
thoughts And so even though I knew better I had a
really strong bias that meditation meant not thinking I could relate to the
breath Emotions seemed very rich Um even
mind states and moods but thinking seemed inferior to
me Uh but as my practice developed I began to realize wait a second thinking
is everywhere in my life it just permeates every day of my life Uh and
that this was really a natural human activity and we want to know life as it
is not as we want it to be And I began to learn to respect and eventually to
appreciate thinking in a very different way Um but the first thing we need to do
to befriend our thinking to is to get to know it to really um uh get close to it
not rejected Um you don't get to know anything you reject
Uh so the kinds of thinking we have come vary very very widely from the more
extensive thinking we use in daily life to the subtle thinking that arises that
might arise in the calm mind in meditation Um I'll start out with a
grosser more um uh coarser thinking Um
in daily life there are two kinds of thinking that easily can easily dominate the mind and that's discursive thinking
and focused thinking Now discursive thinking
um is a diffuse thinking without purpose When the mind just jumps from
one thing to another it might seem to meander gently or just jump radically Um
it's a very kind of um common kind of thinking in daily life Uh which also
shows up in meditation practice We often refer to it as the monkey mind where the
monkey just jumps from one branch to another one thought leaping to another
and often ending up miles away from where we started
Um focus thinking on the other hand is purposely focusing on a specific problem
uh a task or an idea I mean we use focused thinking in in paying attention
to the breath or directing the body um
directing muscles to relax in a systematic way We're focusing on it Um
in daily life you know we might be solving a problem decision making
um analyzing something studying learning anything
Uh for instance we might think should I sign up for a particular class uh should I go on this
trip or we might be considering um dharma ideas You know what does the Buddha say about
karma um or maybe we just figure out how to do something You know how do I fix my
car um but both discursive and focused
thinking can be done in a wholesome or helpful way or in an unhelpful
way With discursive thinking we can spend quite a bit of time dwelling on
what's wrong with our lives uh with ourselves with the world with other
people allowing the mind to jump from one thing to another compulsively worrying or
needless planning rehearsing
judging Sometimes we call this type of unhelpful discursive thought
rumination kind of a repetitive prolonged negative thinking about ourselves or
feelings past experiences that were upsetting over and over again trying to
solve something that can't be solved by thinking We can repeat a particular
theme and frequent rumination year after year
Rumination tends to add to our suffering It adds to negative moods It makes us
less effective in our lives And it doesn't resolve by
ruminating But discursive thought can also be quite wholesome It can let the mind meander in
a relaxed enjoyable way You know maybe daydreaming It can be an easy
subconscious mode that can foster creativity and actually helps integrate
our thinking Um many of us have had the experience of trying to solve a problem
you know using our focus thought and getting stuck you know just just stuck and going
for a walk and letting the mind just meander in a relaxed way And when we're
turning from the walk the solution shows up easily So it's this subconscious mode
that where the mind's at
ease And we can do the same thing with focus thinking We can do it in a way that's
relaxed and at ease or doing it in a way that's quite tense
Um for instance I used to write short stories and it was something I did that
was very relaxed and enjoyable I find myself wrapped with interest you know
many times the smile on my face But it took me years of mindfulness
practice to be able to do my taxes with a relaxed body and even an occasional
smile Um in meditation discursive thinking is usually not
helpful So we train the mind to prioritize the body sensations over the countless stories
the monkey mind can generate Discursive thinking in
meditation can be very very seductive Maybe some of you had a little bit of that today I don't
know It can be a form of entertainment You know some of the fantasies we go to
can be very very enjoyable Um gosh I've written books in
in in the middle of a retreat sometimes you know got so seduced by by a good
story Um but we can also get just as easily distracted with unpleasant
versions of discursive thinking with ruminating about worries about our lives
fears of the future regrets of the
past So the idea isn't to eliminate it in eliminate these kind of um coarser
types of thoughts uh but to do them in a wholesome way in a wholesome envir
mental environment Another kind of thinking that occurs in
both daily life and meditation is what can be called functional or practical thinking or I
like to call it present moment thinking Um in daily life for instance
um uh let's say we're cooking um we're cooking dinner you know and um the
thought the thought obviously enters you know well let's see what do I do next I need a lemon next I need to stir the
vegetables I need to set the timer um so whether or not those thoughts are
wholesome depends on the mood of the mind depends on the environment ment of
the mind We might be cooking in a rush and be very tense and worried about time
Where's that lemon um you know oh I want to stir you know it can be very
different quality to these thoughts Or we can be very very relaxed enjoying the process you know enjoying
the smell of the lemon um stirring those beautiful looking vegetables appreciating the fact that we
have a timer to set Um now in meditation functional thinking
might look like "Oh my knee hurts I'll shift my attention to it Pay more
careful attention." Or maybe um "My shoulders
are above my ears I'll relax them." Uh some of us have a narrator
that lives in the background It comments on the moment Oh that was a smooth
breath what's a little bit warm Now dysfunctional thinking about
the present moment can also be wholesome or it can trigger unhelpful
reactions Again depending on the environment of the mind In a tense mind we might get
reactive to the knee pain instead of uh exploring it with a curious curiosity an
affectionate curiosity What is this what's this pain like
uh or we might add judgment if her breath isn't to her liking or that was that breath was way too short and it was
a little rough and and it should be different and you know uh so this this
present moment thinking can be wholesome or unh
wholesome And the subtler form of thinking that occurs
um in meditation and and in daily life is the knowing and recognition that's
part of the realm of insight practice part of vaposa
One of the principles of mindfulness or vaposa practice is that we shift the
attention from focusing on the content of our thoughts to the process of
thinking to the activity of thinking to exploring what the
experience of thinking is actually like for us Knowing and recognition can be
wordless or it can be accompanied by brief thoughts For instance if you turn on the
light in a dark room suddenly you see all the objects of the room You recognize them You know they're there
You don't have to figure it out Oh let's see What is that um oh yeah it's got four legs It's it's a desk you know We
don't have to do that It just shows up We recognize it
So if during meditation we recognize that we're worrying about one thing after another we can shift the attention
to the body to any tens tensions in the body Maybe the forehead's contracted or
the shoulders are tight or the belly is contracted or we're holding our breath
So we we know those sensations Recognition is essential for
seeing the hindrances to meditation When aversion or desire take
us away from the moment when we're caught in afflictive emotional
patterns the pasta means seeing clearly This simple recognition of
what's present however it is whatever it is
When the discursive thinking is calmed we enter the world of knowing and
recognition We might recognize the different objects of mind that show up and many many physical
sensations that come and go the emotions that come and go the attitudes that show
up And we can choose to shift from the stories of the discursive mind in favor
of what we feel In short we drop the story and find
the feeling So um later in the week I'll
talk a little bit about reflective thinking Um a deeper kind of thinking
that can arise from the silence
So as you go through your day today you might periodically give some attention to how you're
thinking You might notice if you're thinking in a relaxed easy way or if the
thinking feels contracted or tense And if it does see if you can bring a kind attitude towards it
relaxing into it without rejecting it
So thank you for listening I'm looking forward to continuing
tomorrow Thank you