warm greetings and so I want to say that it's
raining here and there's a teaching that the Dharma is like the rain in the
forest and that when it rains in the forest the each all the different plants
small plants Big Trees each of them absorbs the the amount of water they
need for their life and so when the uh when hearing the Dharma reading the
Dharma being in the Dharma each of us will take in what we need or at at any
given time and uh to trust that so the topic is
um this week around samade is organized under the category
of pleasure and it involves a range of certainly Sensations like Pleasant
Sensations but also involves emotions of things like gladness and joy and
happiness and even more intense forms of
well-being and uh in the teachings of the Buddha uh the condition
for um concentration is some form of
Happiness to really get absorbed in samadi for samadi really to arise as we
meditate is um to have some M come some form of
Happiness the the condition for happiness is to have some form of Tranquility or being relaxed at
ease and the condition for relaxation is some
joy and the condition for Joy is to have gladness a
delight and uh and so these are called the the gladness
pentad gladness can lead to Joy Joy to tranquility tranquility to Happiness and
happiness to samadi and some people find this strange because the whole reason to practice
meditation um and maybe have somebody is to be able to feel some deep sense of
wellbeing and here it's reverse order well-being first and then somebody
and this gladness pentad is said to begin by being inspired by
something uh uh one of The Inspirations is mudita kind of a appreciative Joy
appreciating others people's maturity and development in the Dharma practice
to see people becoming Freer more more self more more more uh at ease more
peaceful more have more Integrity somehow become Freer in the process of
practicing um can be very inspiring and to be delighted in this rather than jealous or envious uh to be inspired so
that gladness arises and that gladness then as we practice can be there uh creating space for some joy and joy some
space to relax in a deep way tranquility and then to happiness another source of inspiration
that's classic Buddhism is in the three refuges in refuge and the primary Refuge
is the mindfulness practice itself to have experienced or to know or to Intuit
it that this the practice of mindfulness practice of being attentive and clear
and being here um is such a blessing is such a
significant way of uh coming to Refuge where Refuge means a deep sense of being
at home in this world home with oneself a deep sense of belonging in this
universe belonging to oneself and to feel glad for
that and um and there are a few other things that are mentioned that uh one of them is ethics to be inspired by our own
ethical life for some people that's very hard to imagine just because we are sometimes
the the most the greatest critic of ourselves is ourselves but if we see read what's
going on in the newspapers and kind of news of of how unethical people can be
maybe it's easier to understand that uh you are a wonderful alternative to that
and be inspired by that glad for that so to be
inspired to feel a certain pleasure the pleasure of gladness
so to assume a meditation
posture and for people who meditate a lot the posture can be
just a habit of sitting into but for people who have been
meditating a lot it's also that they know the goodness of the posture they know the goodness of being in
this space of meditation and just sitting down at it if we take
the time to appreciate it can be an inspiration wow this is
good and I know I've been delighted and happy to sit down to meditate even when
I was not happy I was agitated upset things were difficult for me but wow was
it good to sit in the middle of it to sit who is so much better than the
alternative even better than being being distracted from
it gently closing the eyes and start by not doing
anything not meditating and simply checking
in checking in with yourself in your body how it is and your mind and your
heart or your emotions without beginning to meditate
without being mindful without concentrating on anything just allow
yourself to be as you are and check
in how are you here and
now answering that question with what is present for
you and maybe just maybe
appreciating the Simplicity of just being present and checking
in this is how it is
and then beginning to Center yourself on the
breathing checking in maybe you're still not meditating but now check in how is
your
breathing what parts of the body are active as you breathe
what Sensations come into play as you
breathe this simp the simple experience of
breathing breathing in breathing out the sensations that come into
play is probably the same or almost the same as what the Buddha experienced when
he sat down to meditate with his
breathing in a certain way you are sharing within
experience that the Buddha had and which practitioners down Through
the Ages have had practitioners
who've gone into a samade of
breathing to mature
deeply and
then if you have some feeling for not meditating just sitting here quietly
being being the breathing as it
is almost like the next thing to doing
nothing a gentle quiet becoming attuned to breathing
becoming centered more in the
breathing so that the attention to breath has a light
quality a light
touch where the awareness of breathing doesn't carry much
baggage of judging the breath or oneself straining or pushing for
something to happen expecting
anything just a light touch of awareness with breathing as it
is and no noticing if there is a settling point a
grounding Point deep within where the first
sensations of inhale
begin if it's if that place is in the
belly maybe there's a ever so slight lifting up out of that grounding
point as the inhale
spreads with the expanding rib
cage and then returning to that settling
place with the exhale
and gently
lightly be aware of the whole length of the
inhale the whole length of the exhale with the tenderness or the care
maybe even the love that you might
have in gently petting a cat stroking across the
hair going with the ground brain of the hair not against
it the inhale is a gentle stroke through the whole length
of the inhale and so is the exhale
and if there's any pleasure
pleasantness in mindfulness of breathing maybe letting it be the purr
of the cat a contented
per enjoyment of what is good or Pleasant about awareness of
breathing
and then you might try to have a small smile on your lips just big enough to feel some
sensations of
pleasure around the mouth the cheeks maybe even up into the eyes
and if you do feel that
pleasure can you connect that to something you're inspired with in
relationship to the practice something that brings you a
gladness glad that you're here doing this
practice with a small
smile that gives embodiment to that Delight
with a light touch of awareness writing the whole inhale the whole
exhale maybe a small smile supports the
the pleasure and goodness of relaxing into
breathing relaxing with the
exhale letting go of thoughts as you
exhale as you settle into the grounding
place e
for
e
for e
appreciating the pleasure of a light touch of attention
on breathing
allowing yourself to feel whatever pleasure there is of
meditation a
pleasure which helps the Mind feel more at
ease that kind of ease that allows a thinking mind to be become quieter and
still and the pleasure of being present with the
breathing become
Central to our sense of being
here
for
e
e for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to again as we began to sit here without
meditating just allow yourself to
be and without any formal meditation
letting awareness of just
being have the lightest possible touch not trying to do
anything not trying to get any change
anything a lot the lightest touch on this present moment experience
of just
being maybe awareness is like a gentle
breeze moving over the the
landscape of you just being here
and then with awareness together with
imagination having your awareness that breeze of awareness the lightest of
touch bring into view the people of your
life people you might see this morning or
today and let them just be as you just be
and with the lightest Touch of awareness know
them as they
are without being for or against without wanting or not wanting
anything just allowing people to be themselves
and then to spread that breeze of awareness out across the
lands may be a difficult task but
possible to allow all things all people just to be as they
are not because you agree or disagree with them or not be independent of your
discernment and judgments as if letting everything just
be as they are with it in the lightest Touch of
awareness is medicine for the
world is medicine for yourself
and may you have the wish if you like to go into the world
today thinking of yourself as medicine for the
world medicine for what ails Us in this
world and to go into the world with the medicine of Good
Will the medicine of being able to see people as they
are without preferences without judgments so there might be a hope for
they can see themselves as they are in the Gaze of kindness gaze of
Goodwill that you offer may all
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and may each of us gaze upon the world
kindly May each of us contribute to the sum total of Good Will
and kindness that can exist on this
planet may all beings be happy
thank you
so hello and welcome to this um 23rd the 24th talk I
think 23rd talk on
samat and um and there this week the topic is the
pleasure of somebody and pleasure takes different forms at different times sometimes it
can feel like pure pleasure and um you know physical
pleasure and but it also can morph into the pleasure of delight the pleasure of
gladness the pleasure of Joy the pleasure of Happiness the pleasure of
Tranquility the pleasure of equinity the pleasure of release and
freedom and the pleasure of Refuge pleasure of
knowing we have a home that brings a certain degree of safety and Care
orientation meaning to this life of ours all kind of aspects of
refuge and so uh pleasure is an important part of Dharma practice and
maybe we can call it Dharma pleasure and in the teachings and
mindfulness the Buddha makes a distinction between two kinds of pleasure there's a pleasure that uh
comes from that can we can might want to call sensual pleasure if we uh
understand it to be that our senses are being stimulated by an external
source and um so if I eat a tasty food
that would be called sensual pleasure in The Taste because it comes from the food if um I stand in the warm sun on a cold
day and feel the pleasure of that that would be called sensual pleasure because it comes from outside and touches the
nerve endings and does something nice um if we're thinking about things
there's a way in which the thinking mind it's represents it's almost like
something outside of ourselves um I can have a fantasy about
something uh and the fantasy can bring a lot of pleasure and so what's it uh it's still
kind of on the outside the thinking sometimes certain kind of thinking uh is
on the surface and it kind of stimulates the surface pleasures of the mind um even though in in the and many
of us would think the mind is not part of the external world uh it's almost as
if certain kinds of surface thoughts our external World which are providing kind of an external stimulus to
things and uh there's not necessarily nothing wrong with that in any of this
but there is an an alternative which is uh pleasure which is not of the senses not of these the
sense doors that take in the external world but there is um uh the pleasure
that it kind of arises uh in a more diffuse way that
that swells up emerge arises inside uh for as no particular
external reason that comes for meditation and so it's a whole radically
different pleasure because it doesn't depend on the world doesn't depend on getting the world in shape getting
everything just perfect in the world and feeling content and happy with how the world is and how our external
relationships are and everything but it comes with a kind of coming into
harmony with ourselves and and a deep inner sense of of a of a sensing the
beingness of our life as that beingness comes into harmony as that beingness
comes into a kind of um um uh tenderness or wholeness or uh um
uh orientation and and that feels very meaningful for example in
meditation and uh and so there are Pleasures in meditation that um are certainly welling
up and I'm sure there's some sense some nerve endings that are being stimulated but that um it's not because
they're kind of like stimulated from the outside in but rather from the inside in
uh something a deep welding and inspiration and um there's also in that uh unpleasant
Sensations that are of the senses that that come from the outer outer world or
thinking about the outer World um uh or there's uh unpleasant
Sensations that can well up that um are not of the world exactly not of the
sense world but to come also come from when we feel something is profoundly out
of alignment in this world and so there's a feeling of things something is not
right but in meditation what we're uh beginning to give birth to and this is a language the
Buddha used the language of birth we're giving birth to a deep sense Wellspring
of pleasure Well Spring of well-being in meditation and uh and this sense of
well-being is closely connected to a number of things it's connected to Faith
or inspiration or confidence that yes that's represented I
think with a big yes I'm here this is good I I know this world I'm inspired by
it I have refuge in it so that we're more kind of inclined towards being
present here for our experience rather than being present continue to be in the
thinking mind that's maybe thinking about the external world has this external relationship to everything a
disconnect to everything uh even and and even if we're thinking about you know something that
we did yesterday and maybe we did something that was harmful and we feel regret now if we spend too much time in
the in the imagination of that event we're kind of removed for something deeper here so the idea is to come into
this deeper place and um and so meditation there could be
a sense of well-being a sense of being at home goodness here an inspiration
about what this is about to meditate so faith and there can be uh an wonderful
sense of yes to being present for it the
effort the energy of it but here um they look for how
to apply app oneself in meditation so the very application itself is
enjoyable so maybe it's a very light touch maybe it's uh with inspiration
it's just a delight sometimes we can put a lot of energy into meditation and it
just feels like a play almost or feels like Delight to do it so we and
sometimes we and we need to do very very little effort to get that the best
results from meditation so finding how can you enjoy um being focused how can you enjoy
being present with attention and then there's mindfulness and mindfulness brings Joy because it
brings safety mindfulness uh we see everything clearly enough that we learn
to not pick up not continue involvement with things which are harmful for
ourselves mindfulness creates the open space in which things can just be and
evolve and change and we can learn to trust delightfully trust that if we're
present things move towards health and maybe not directly but over
time and then there is um samadi beginning to feel absorbed
connected here um kind of like the joy of a cat
that's being that's being petted stroked being able to really C Center ourselves
here and and uh feel begin to feel more whole more settled more calm there's a
strong correlation with samadi with calmness so as we get calmer meditation
that's the pleasure that we start appreciating and then there's the more
subtle pleasure of wisdom of of being able to be happy that
we we can see clearly enough to find the path to find our way meditation is
onward leading samade is an onward leading path where we kind of not that
we're expecting something or trying to make something happen but it's kind of
like we can see feel
sense here's where the path opens up here's where the slide top of the slide
is that'll take us deep you know on that wonderful Dharma slide or here's a path in the forest
maybe it's not so easy to see at first and we're lost but then we start seeing traces of the path ah and the the light
of knowing it maybe after being lost in the wilderness there's a great joy and likeness and pleasure of finally having
seen the path so the function of wisdom is to help us find that path between so
we don't get caught in attachments expectations aversions desires but we
see the path of what's wholesome what's good what's healthy for us healthy way
of being present a supportive way of entering the world of
Som so there's many forms of pleasure of goodness of rightness of
wholeness and one of those uh words that uh of this pleasure that that uh comes
along with time is harmony that samade is entering into a state of being in
harmony all things harmonious here and now so
um so uh pleasure so part of what we're doing in
going into samadi developing suat is becoming a uh an expert or a a
SE or a uh a uh of pleasure within us
and so we can find that onward leading pleasure which is not there because of the world in any particular way or a
fantasy of the world is any particular way but something that's deeply connected the wellwells up from within
and um and where we discover that just to be alive is
wonderful just to the rest in our beingness without needing anything else
to happen is um is
um is very very meaningful and significant so the samade of pleasure so
today you might go around maybe with a smile on your face or maybe with the
lightest Touch of beingness to see if you can when you feel feel that there's a
different kind of pleasure that's not there because the world is providing
pleasure uh and maybe it's it's the wholeheartedness in which you wash the
dishes maybe it's the full embodiment as you walk walking down the street that
you're really there for the walk from the inside out than uh studying the world around
you may this day be a day of Deep
pleasure varied pleasure so that you learn more about this
world and then um I wasn't going to say anything about our fundraising today but
last night I talked about I talked with someone who uh used to work for save the
children has many friends who still work there and um an IMC member who's kind of
been our connection there and uh she said that many of her friends many of the people around the world who
are doing the good work of save their children uh their positions were funded
by the agency of International Development and so they lost their jobs and so um I think that our fundraising
drive to support save the children is even more important and meaningful now than it would have been even some weeks
ago and maybe it has even greater value to be able to support this wonderful
organization to continue their work at a time when the world really needs it so
um you can read more about our fundraising Drive in uh on imc's website
under what's new or there's a red banner on top of the website and um may this be
one of the ways that our wonderful um YouTube
Community um steps in to care for this world thank you