the invitation when you're ready is to settle in
Settle into a posture that allows you to be present with whatever the internal and external
weather is
today Maybe taking a couple of longer slower deeper breaths
and noticing whatever um emotional tone or mood you're bringing in with
you For me there's a little bit of a flurry from having done a bunch of tech
stuff and watching the mind
settle watching the sediment of thought settle into the
body And a tuning attuning to your
breath your body Perhaps the sound in the
room the sound of my voice
allowing the body to
relax and the attention to go
inwards and down
Notice Okay If there are thoughts emotions
sensations and allowing them to be there with
simplicity keeping mindful awareness in the forefront
tuning
resting and the flow inward and outward to the breath
Noticing appreciating the return or continuation of mindful awareness
Acknowledging simply whatever
arises noticing it persists changes for a
while Perhaps into something
else or into moments of soothing silence
from time to time
Noticing what is in awareness and noticing
[Music] how you are with awareness What's this moment
like just allowing the system to respond with interest
As the attention gathers itself collects itself
here relaxing ing into the rhythm of
breath The texture of sound sensation
Riding the
moment with
simplicity
ease Noticing and softening into what's obvious
Noticing and tuning into any
softening presence [Music]
relaxation in the body
Noticing and tuning into any ease or
contentment Simple awareness in the heart and mind
and appreciating
that Savoring
it And from that place turning your gaze outwards
to the others your life touches directly and
indirectly with an internal gesture of generosity care
kindness offering the wish that they may be safe
Happy
healthy May they be peaceful at
ease and free
and offering the determination the
wish that our practice here together may be part of the
growth of peace love and liberation in the
world May all beings be free
[Music]
Thank you for the sincerity of your practice
So good morning friends Good
morning Really appreciate being able to practice together It's a rainy cool morning here in Santa
Cruz and um we appreciate the value and value
this sa So um like to introduce the theme for
this week which is inspirations for insight So a kind of a series of stories
and anecdotes um some myths from the Buddhist time
anecdotes from my own life that are a bit in honor of Vesak a
Buddhist holiday that happened on Sunday the early tradition celebration of the
Buddhist birth death and enlightenment Just a moment
So these um these stories once I'm able to talk over the um garbage collection
these stories are um also that they've been told for
centuries millennia to um evoke beneficial qualities of
heart and mind to inspire the heart and mind and mindsets attitudes conducive to
insight liberation to strengthening practice And one such mindset is
interest So as these stories unfold over the week I want to invite you to get
interested and allow your own meanings to emerge from them as
well So when I talk about insight it can be insight with a little eye which is um
an insight to your own conditioning insight into the universal truths that the Buddha taught about
human subjective experience just overall
And then there is the capital I
insight which is a deeper knowing into the commonality of human subjective
experience The truth that the Buddha taught as being relating to all
people all human experience everywhere And both kinds of insight help to free
the mind and heart in different ways They both can be very powerful So that's what where we're
going this week And um the first story is one that many of you are familiar
with So it is kind of the in a sense the origin story of the Buddha's
teachings And I'll give a brief version here The Buddha was raised as a prince
Um his father had determined that he should succeed him in leading their
kingdom and um he was offered a life of luxury of opulence of every possible
sensual desire and was protected from the suffering of life and groomed to take
power And part of this may be because um the Buddha when he was born two very
consequential things happened his mother died in childbirth So he was raised by a very loving stepmother And the other
thing was that there was a seer who had said he would either become a great king or a great spiritual teacher And his
father had a definite preference for the king
So there he was protected from any
possible blip in his life Even the beautiful flowers in the garden were deadheaded the the blooms were removed
before they could fade But as he got older as a young man curiosity interest
motivated him to sneak out of the castle with his friend the charioteer And he
discovered the messengers of old age sickness and death which shook him to
the core He hadn't seen these things
and they affected him deeply and he conceived of the idea of wanting to
discover another way wanting a different way to penetrate through and release
himself from life suffering And then on one of those trips he saw a wandering
sadua sage peaceful graceful walking through all of
the chaos of the marketplace And he left
home And there are many discourses where he talks about this um
what he left behind and talks about the
benefit the um appeal the virtue of a
life of the kind of simplicity that he was leading He let go of all that status
and wealth and became a wandering aesthetic It was the beginning of his own hero's journey And it also
[Music] became the inspiration for generations of practitioners to
embrace simplicity So most of you have heard
this story I'm sure And um many people over the centuries have found it
resonates with them in part because many of us come to the path of practice
because of something that's not right a wish for something deeper some kind of
suffering or disease In the story the Buddha
literally lets go a preoccupation with status wealth sensual pleasure
But this could also be considered a metaphor an instruction And he uses it
this way in some of his teachings in the kind of simplicity of mind that is
helpful to deeper joy freedom helpful to spiritual
cultivation One of those areas of simplicity is letting go letting go of a
preoccupation with status or at least not taking it quite so
personally Another version of this is not giving energy to comparing mind or
FOMO but instead turning towards this this moment as best we can
There's also a level of simplicity of releasing concern Releasing concern with what I'm
going to get out of this meditation session this retreat this
practice this teacher even In other words it's a shift of
interest It's a shift of interest
in getting interested in how we relate to various forms of
insecurities even cravings in our own minds and hearts and
relating to them more simply as what's happening now rather than as commands
real needs or even um distractions verdicts on
me So turning interest to the simplicity of the
moment Turning that interest to the simplicity of the moment helps to support
contentment which is an underrated and very important quality in deepening
practice and in discovering insight So I speak from personal
experience As a young person a young adult an adolescent I was very discontented Always reaching out
reaching out wanting more wanting wanting wanting Happiness was out there
not in here It's so common Now there's even the
simile of monkey mind which is the mind grabbing on to the next thing and the
next thing Another practitioner I know called
her mind a mongoose mind looking at the shiny next thing to pay attention to to
grab onto to look for
happiness instead moments of
contentment And there were many in my younger life that I ignored or um forgot
about didn't kind of appreciate in this relentless pursuit It wasn't until
encountering a major health challenge that I started to learn how to turn
towards my own body heart and mind and relax be
with find contentment in the simple absence of reaching out in the simple
absence of a moment of discomfort a simple moment of being
present no matter how [Applause]
fleeting So eventually even in the midst of health challenge I started to feel this simple
happiness that I'd never felt before It was the happiness of
presence of being here now Many of you have experienced this It
was humbling for me that that simple presence later got disturbed as I got more into meditation with then the habit
of wanting projecting itself into the
practice But that wasn't a mistake Habits of aversion habits of
wanting showing up in the practice are these amazing opportunities to discover the habits of our own minds the
tendency of our own hearts and start to release them Let them go
Cultivate a clearer
way a simpler way a more content way
One of the ways of doing this is to notice and
appreciate savor moments of contentment and ease now rather than setting them
aside to look for a greater moment or a contentment later And another is to notice notice
the frame of mind whatever it is like the glasses
that you're wearing Notice how it filters
experience Am I wearing rosecolored glasses or duca colored
glasses checking out what is the general mood or
attitude internal posture stance of relationship to the moment
It's worth appreciating this because then sometimes we can drop into a moment of
clarity Notice what's already here Allow it Be content with it Rest in
it And it's worth appreciating because contentment supports
non-distraction Contentment supports presence Contentment supports the
capacity to see clearly without clinging or craving It has a flavor of the peace of
the freed liberated mind It's almost like a continuum towards it So it in
itself is onward leading and it's a condition for that
simplicity The Buddha praised both likening a
practitioner with these qualities as being free with nothing carried except
the wings like wings of a bird And that simplicity is supported by
contentment and supports contentment simplicity of lifestyle that supports
making time for practice The Buddha's going forth his
letting go of everything is one example of this as our contemporary and ancient monastics
Many people though in the midst of our rich and full and busy lives find a much more harmonious
relationship with the heart by just simplifying
activities And there's simplicity in how we relate to our own hearts and
minds which supports a wholesome relationship with whatever is there The capacity to simply turn towards to be
with Simplicity supports clear seeing clarity
and simplicity supports insight
So how do you support the inner rising growth of
simplicity well to some extent simplicity is an acquired taste
Maybe notice how you've acquired it in your own life and where it's not there
or complication is there Notice how it
tends to release the most unhelpful proliferation of mind if we just step
back with it If we just step back with it allow it to be simply okay It's
complicated Just complicated not a
problem Can go to your senses Drop into the senses of the
moment Sensory gateways to awareness
and trusting that each moment of mindful awareness noticed as such invites the
next moment of awareness That quality of awareness
itself is free of complication It's like a You can
ask yourself "What's this moment like what's obvious here
it cuts through to something direct a direct
simpler way of knowing that is in the direction of ease
satisfaction simplicity of freedom
So in the next 24 hours should you choose to accept it your homework
assignment is to notice what wholesome qualities of heart
and mind this talk the story at the beginning may have evoked in you and to
perhaps notice when there are moments of simplicity and ease and when there are not in your life
Notice the difference Would love to hear or see in the chat what you
discover So thank you for your attention and your practice