good morning and welcome to our meditation And
uh one of the differences between mindfulness and
insight is that mindfulness is the use of attention that uh prepares the ground to
have insight to have a deep seeing and uh or true seeing seeing truly or
actually how things are And
um and so as we sit today in mindfulness
meditation the role of samadei is to be able to sit in the
middle of uh all our capacities for
attention and have them unified in some kind of wonderful way working together
So attentional capacities we have are recognition a cognitive knowing of
what's happening And this cognitive knowing may or may not be verbal It might be kind of a nonverbal
knowing It might also be a kind of visual knowing Some people are visual
thinkers Another attentional faculty is our capacity to sense and to feel with our
senses And in Buddhism the the idea of sense
experience just like it it includes seeing hearing smelling tasting and the
tactile which is whatever sensations there are that are born through the body
There's a kind of sense door that uh very simply in the simplest possible way
uh knows or senses that we're thinking And I use both words knowing
and sensing thinking because thinking sometimes is more than just words and
ideas or images It's also the the you can feel the physicality sometimes of
thinking the tension or the pressure the contraction that comes along with
it Another attentional capacity is to settle back and observe
experience And this is to perceive without being in any kind of
way entangled with experience allowing things to be just as they are and not so intimate as feeling
sensing the experience and not so not so cognitive as an act of recognition But
it's it's observing without recognizing what something is
but observing how it moves and changes and comes and goes and shifts and
oscillates and vibrates and like you would sit and observe um a
river and you don't know the name of the river but uh you just you don't even the
idea it's a river even falls away Just watching the flow the current or the
waves washing against the shore or the a fire on a you know in a dark night the
outdoor bonfire And
uh and then to bring all these together in samadei is to
sit in the general sense of just being
present here All of ourselves included So to
begin very simply is to assume a meditation
posture A posture that for you supports attention
presence to the experience of the present moment
And to notice as you sit with your
body by what means
are you aware of your body in what way are you aware of your
body that's different than thinking about it or trying to analyze the
question analyze the topic of trying to figure out with your mind Nothing to figure
out rather when you're not
thinking In what way are you aware of having a
body in the meditation posture
is it a knowing recognition cognitive
recognition Is it a sensing sensations the
body maybe is maybe a broad glow or vibration through the body A diffuse
feeling of softness through the
body or particular sensations of
contact places the body touches Maybe where the body touches
itself the hands on them touching each other or on the thighs
And as you're aware of your
body allow the awareness to go through your body
wherever the awareness wants or wherever the body seems to
invite awareness So you're not directing the
awareness but rather you're following the
awareness where it goes in the
body Maybe you're following whatever
the body seems to call on for you to be at
with Sometimes it's a knowing sometimes it's sensing and
feeling having your awareness
follow and not direct not
letting the directing and actively doing
mind at
rest So you aren't taking the lead but you're allowing awareness
to join with the
body If you're aware of tension in your
body it's okay
See how simple the awareness can
be And if it's easy enough if you feel like it's the wish
the body has allow for the body to relax
If the body seems to invite you to relax or calm the
body then go ahead and allow for a calming
softening through your body
Where your body you seem to be most aware of the
body where is it easiest
for awareness to rest in the body
And then within the body as part of the body become aware of breathing
Knowing breathing in a simple relaxed
way Knowing breathing in as breathing in breathing out as breathing
out Or perhaps sensing the sensations that come into play as you
breathe
Awareness can follow the sensations of breathing as they appear
And the knowing mind can from time to time know
recognize some of those sensations of
breathing We're knowing the sensations is meant to support
Staying close to the sensations of breathing
And as you exhale letting go of your
thoughts relaxing the thinking
mind and letting go into the body breathing
thing Yeah
To know to feel and sense to be
aware continuously
enough that we find ourselves
settled here in present moment
experience The mind is steadied
thinking has become stiller and quieter
And then at some
point the capacity to simply observe
experience in the present
moment like waves endlessly washing up on the
shore A river
flowing Simply
knowing the movement the appearing and disappearing of
things without needing to know what they are
or to feel what they
are Nothing to figure out nothing to
fix nothing to accomplish
But to settle back with an overview that
observes the river of sensations the river of thoughts and
feelings as they flow through
Being careful to not getting stuck anywhere
Just watching the change
And as we come to the end of this
sitting to notice
again what you're aware of without any particular effort to be
aware except to be awake to be
here and how are you
aware is it there simple knowing recognizing
A simple
sensing a simple
observing or is there some kind of indistinct general sense of being
aware that doesn't quite fit any of those three categories
maybe because it's a natural blending of all
three that keeps you right here
And then to expand your here outward into your room the building
you're in the place location you're
in to expand your awareness outwards into the world
Considering how today you can live in
a generous way to the people you'll encounter to the world
itself How is it that the practice of meditation
awareness can lead you to benefit this world even in the
simplest ways may it be that the benefit from our
individual practice our collective practice
together translate to bringing welfare and happiness to this
world May all beings be happy May all
beings be safe May all
beings be peaceful May all
beings be free
[Music]
Thank you
So hello and welcome to this third talk um introducing the topic of
insight and today I'd like to uh discuss the difference between mindfulness and
insight mindfulness and vipasa the word vipasana
is uh what we translate at IMC as
insight and uh some um people who practice mindfulness don't
uh don't translate vipasa they use it they just use the poly word to describe
the technique of practice that they do practicing vipasa and u sometimes in our tradition
in using the word insight we say we're practicing insight side
meditation But uh originally in back in ancient Buddha Buddhism the word
vipasana did not refer to a practice It
referred to the results of the practice the way in which the practice led uh
practitioners uh to be able to see deeply into their
experience and um and that deep seeing
uh is uh uh is the insight that we see The insight we come to understand the
liberating um uh perspective orientation
understanding seeing per perception that uh comes into play uh in a way that
brings uh uh this liberation from suffering And um so uh mindfulness
practice is not the same as insight but it's mindfulness practice that leads to
the insight creates the conditions by which we're present enough and clear enough in our awareness perception to be
able to see clearly So this word vipasana I often uh
as I have on Monday um uh kind of described its meaning as being clear
seeing where the v the prefix vi is a uh
emp just a prefix of emphasis So it's emphasize it emphasizes seeing how we
see or strong seeing So it becomes clear seeing But the V can also uh be a prefix
that distinguishes things uh and uh that divides things And so another way of
understanding vipasana is that it's uh um uh distinctive seeing
or distinguishing seeing Uh it's uh it's a uh seeing with seeing the the the
clear distinctions of things the seeing the with seeing with clarity so that we
see the particularities of what's actually happening
Um and uh and so it's again the emphasis is on what is seen in a sense not the
act of seeing So mindfulness is a practice that leads to that In classic Buddhism
mindfulness is not an end to itself but a means to something And um and so how is
mindfulness practiced in the teachings of the Buddha there are a number of
attentional faculties that are engaged that we can call mindfulness practice
leading to a very strong established sense of awareness
And uh and so uh there's a we have a lot of attentional faculties and all of them
are awakened and and and uh and brought together in order to be established in
the present moment clearly enough in order to see distinctly And
um so there's knowing uh the simple recognition of experience
There is sensing or feeling experience experiencing it experientially
uh through the body And then there is something called uh
sajana which is uh often translated into as to English as clear recognition or
clear understanding And this is the uh I think the form of
practice that's most often taught in uh in what's called secular mindfulness and
sometimes in uh the Buddhist insight meditation tradition as well because
it's it's uh it's knowing it's recognizing but more than just a raw
simple recognition of what's there It's recognizing in a particular way So it
said recognize So it comes comes along with a greater understanding
uh perspective orientation So it's a um
uh knowing in uh without judgment
knowing um with kindness with friendliness uh knowing with spaciousness and
openness It's it's uh it's a un some kind of understanding of what we're what
we are seeing or knowing or feeling the context of it the the value of it and in
Buddhism this clear understanding of things uh is a very important form of uh
part of mindfulness training because as we understand uh in some simple way uh
the experience we it and guide us more deeply into our experience And one of
the very clear distinctions for clear comprehension clear understanding is to understand whether what we're doing
what's going on mental activity the practices we're doing is helpful or not
helpful Is it wholesome is it nourishing or is it not uh is it onward leading to
greater stability greater presence being more rooted here in the present moment
or is it not and uh so we're we're monitoring
ourselves a little bit as we practice so we can adjust how we are adjust how
we're practicing so that uh we begin enjoying it more It's not a strain It's
not hard work Uh but we're learning the art of being present in a supportive
um way that uh welcomes attention welcomes us to be We want to be present
And so uh clear comprehension of what's happening in the present moment uh is an
an aspect of mindfulness practice So there's knowing there's
sensing there's uh clear comprehension Uh and then the last one that's
mentioned in the Buddhist teachings on mindfulness practice is to um or two
kind of things is to when we're sensing to feel the whole body and as we are um
feeling it to relax the tensions and the holdings in the body So there is emphasis on calming the body as we
meditate So that's a that's a kind of a handful of things to hold together But
uh in practicing these in an easygoing relaxed way uh then what we're looking
for is uh coming into a place where awareness attention is
now stabilized established um at ease resting here in the present
moment in our direct experience And um and uh and that takes a while Well it
takes a while for the thinking mind to calm down It takes a while to understand and see the dynamics of the what's
happening within us to be able to settle and relax and to uh be rooted here in
the present moment And for people who practice samadei uh that's uh meant to be a great
support for this uh uh stabilizing attention in the present moment And so
at some point when it's stable being present being aware is not work It's
just kind of almost as if it's just an how we are And so as we just are then
the uh the next attentional faculty we have ability to be aware comes into play
And this is what the Buddha calls observing auasana It has the same word as in
vassana And the prefix anu means toward something to si settle back and just be
able to observe And the observing of experience
uh has some wonderful qualities And sometimes when people teach mindfulness uh this is this is what they're
emphasizing And this is uh to um observing is a little bit the mind is
quieter than it would be if there's simple knowing of the experience
Um there doesn't have to be a knowing and observing Uh and it and um uh and
then uh it's not as intimate It's not connected when we're
sensing Sensations and s and the sensing the act of sensing are one and the same
They can't really be separated A moment of sensing comes with sensation
sensations we have come with the sensing of the sensations If there's no sensing
of the sensations are there sensations at all and um and uh if there's no one in
the forest and tree falls is there a sound and so um and so observing is little bit
removed but not so removed that it's detached or or distant or aloof
um observing So there's a kind of wonderful delight wonderful ease
wonderful maybe a kind of intimacy that or kind of belonging or presence that's
comparable to uh resting on the beach maybe maybe for hours and just being
absorbed and watching the waves wash up on the shore and wash back coming and going Um there's something about the
mind that watching very simple motion and the shifts and the changes
that relaxes and settles the mind and watching a river flow can do that
Watching a f a fire um uh moving you know just in the fireplace or outdoors
Uh people can watch it for a long time just watching it and watching it Sometimes just being outdoors in in the
natural world and uh maybe at ease in a bench in a park and just gazing at the
leaves the greenery the scenery Uh uh there's something about just watching
and seeing the kids play in the park or watching that we're not necessarily
actively recognizing every little thing We're not actually touching anything but
there's something about observing it can be very very satisfying It's like everything is uh um um nothing needs to
happen nothing needs to be done nothing needs to be fixed just to observe So these are the attentional
faculties that are considered part of mindfulness practice recognition knowing sensing feeling
um clear comprehension a little higher order level of understanding that helps
us to relax and be simpler and present for our experience in a useful way Uh
relaxing um to some degree and uh observing And
when those uh are supported by samadei it's a lot easier for all those uh to
keep us here rooted in the present moment in a fully way where all our
attentional faculties are kind of awake and present Samadei not only brings us
in samadei well practiced not only supports us to be here but supports us
to um to uh be here with uh uh with all these attentional faculties operating
kind of naturally maybe in in coordinated in some kind of holistic way
that lends itself to a generalized feeling of being aware a field of awareness that's a
combination of all these things operating together and then
uh the mind our heart is ready for insight uh uh the what what we see in
our experience So that'll be coming up So um mindfulness practice is a practice
that leads to insight Mindfulness practice supported by samadei
uh helps that capacity for insight to come alive in a full
way So thank you uh and uh so I look
forward to continue tomorrow