so everyone welcome as we start to settle in
to our morning afternoon evening meditation together
the invitation is to consider in your heart or if it feels right to share
aloud or in writing what if anything you noticed about
motion conveyance air movement
in your practice the winds of change in your practice
and as you consider that beginning to settle into
whatever posture expresses supports your meditation practice best this morning
taking a moment perhaps to look around your room or your space
and especially noticing the spaces between or around objects
between you and the screen or between you and whatever is in front of you
noticing what artists call negative space the space around the space between
and then perhaps taking a couple of longer more intentional breaths
allowing your attention to go inside
and notice how you perceive the space around you
with your eyes closed
noticing sound and silence
perhaps an intuitive sense of the largeness or smallness
of whatever kind of environment you're in in this moment
then allowing the breathing to be natural
however it is today
noticing breath
moving in to your body through the space of your nostrils or mouth
that sense of expansion or rising this breath enters in the lungs
the diaphragm moves the abdomen moves
perhaps allowing the shoulders to roll move up and down a couple of times
to allow more relaxation in your core
inviting the eyes to soften in their sockets
the tongue to relax in your mouth
perhaps noticing if there's a way of holding your head that allows just a
little bit more space between the vertebrae in the back of the neck a
little bit more relaxation
allowing the heart the mind the attention to attune to this moment
the warmth and cool on your skin
the weight of this body held to the Earth
no sense of moisture or dryness in your mouth or nose
the tuning to any sense of spaciousness within
perhaps that little pause between breaths
or a feeling of softening in
softening and releasing into this moment
allowing any mental or emotional activity just to be there in the periphery
and noticing these sense
of healthy distance space from any thoughts
emotions space between
any mental activity and resting
allowing Present moment experience to flow through
unimpeded
inviting more ease relaxation
into this moment
allowing the body to soften
into the surroundings
and if it feels right sensing into
perhaps imagining
the vast sky above you wherever you are
far above or just above
sense of wide open space
letting the heart relax into that wide open space
the mind the body to open to it
and allowing wishes of goodwill friendliness meta
to flow out born on into
this open space flowing out boundlessly
wishing that others be safe
happy healthy
that they be peaceful at ease and free
in whatever words or wordless reverberations
like sunlight through unimpeded space
go outwards all directions
towards whomever or whatever occupies
that open space within and around your heart
and as this meditation draws to a close
considering how our practice here together your
practice might be of benefit in your own mind and
heart and life and how that benefit might radiate out
to benefit all of the lives we touch and all of the lives they touch
outwards and outwards
may all beings be safe peaceful
and free and may our practice here together be a cause and condition for greater
love liberation and peace in the world
[Music]
thank you for your practice
so friends we have reached the fifth of five days exploring the
five elements which is a contemplation and meditation practice
in the ancient teachings of the Buddha a practice that can support insight
reveal insight
so today well this week we've covered earth water
fire air or wind and today we're covering space
so the space element
um is the topic and the translation element for the word datu really kind of
completely breaks down here a better translation could be quality or even
potential or potentiality in our direct experience
space around and in our bodies can be quite
evident the space around or between objects
the space out up in the sky especially the night sky and the space within our bodies our
ears mouth nostrils other orififices the space within the diaphragm or lungs
but often in the ancient tradition especially in the commentaries space is
considered to be more of a mental quality or shifts in perception
so what do I mean by this well here's a couple of the ways quality of
space might show up in the experience of meditation
externally many people find it easy to tune into the space of vastness or
closeness even with their eyes closed through noticing the quality of sound
sound and silence or verberation can make it very clear whether we're in
a smaller space kind of cozy or in a vast cathedral or out in the open
outside even with the eyes closed there can be a sense of the amount of light and where
the light is coming from that might give the sense of a sky
and then sometimes when we're fortunate there's an inward sense of spaciousness
in the heart in our perceptions and even in our bodies remember some people after
a retreat feel like they've lost weight within their bodies like it lost a
density or contraction and there's more of a sense of spaciousness almost like it's between yourselves
or at other times there might be a sense of density contraction
and while these are all perceptual qualities it's echo echoes physics right
we are on a quantum level mostly space our atoms are 99.999%
empty without space we'd be really tiny and very very heavy
i find it fascinating that in a simile back in the Buddha's time the bronze age
ancient India the Buddha conveys a similar notion
he uses the simile of the form of this body being like a lump of foam
like a lump of foam there's an emptiness there and more practically another
simile used and I'm quoting here friends just as when a space is enclosed
by timber and creepers grass and clay it comes to be termed just house
so too when a space is enclosed by bones and senue flesh and skin
it comes to be termed just body
so that simile reveals an ancientness of the construction of homes in ancient
India the um simplicity of it it also both of these simileies allude to the
insight of a nata not self the emptiness
that can be directly perceived through insight that is within
linking internal and external perceptions of space can be awe
inspiring and very practical and helpful in settling the mind
simply looking out at the night sky the space around the stars the space between
the stars the space around the moon if you're out in the country especially
where you can see clearly there's this vastness
wow a sense of healthy humility and
smallness in the larger vastness of things
and then on a practical level the space around
and the space between things whether they be the palm trees I'm looking at outside my window right
now or buildings or plants that begins to attune and settle the
mind and nervous system if we do it for at least a while this works inside a
room by simply looking at the empty spaces where the corners are or the space between furniture
and a solid minute or two or three of that actually
settles the nervous system it settles reactivity and if you do it right before meditation
it can help our minds attend to the space between
thoughts the space within can try it right now
closing your eyes and feeling into
the space that weaves through interpenetrates
your body
so for some on retreat in certain states the perception of this
internal space becomes vast even infinite
this is a base of perception which is related to the jas that Gil talked about
earlier this year the immaterial jas they're sometimes called
and that can be a powerful experience not necessary for awakening or insight
and powerful nonetheless the Buddha advised his son Rahula to
make his meditation like each of the elements including like space
he asks says "Son if you make your meditation
like space agreeable and disagreeable contacts
contacts meaning any sensory data any sensory contact
will not invade your mind and heart and remain
because nothing sticks to space right
the Buddha also in a more daily life context which is still quite relevant
today teaches practitioners to imagine space if they're hearing harsh divisive
unpleasant or even hostile speech
the technique he offers is to imagine those words landing in space that they
need to have no impact no impact
and as part of the same teaching the Buddha then asks practitioners to
imagine space boundless vast space as a
way of cultivating boundless meta goodwill friendliness
this is even um echoed in the very common chant about meta and the other
immeasurables Brahma Biharas where the chant is something like
outwards and unbounded freed from hatred and hostility with
goodwill with friendliness with kindness outwards and unbounded
There's an unbinding that happens in internal reactivity
when the heart begins to open to meta when the heart begins to
open to spaciousness even without any conscious kindness being cultivated
kindness tends to be a more natural response when we're
spacious you've probably noticed
so space as element space as quality
space as inspiration space as a perceptual
way of relating to your body your meditation your heart and mind
it's the fifth of the five qualities five elements we've explored this week and to recap
we've explored the potentialities the qualities from kind of an inspiration point of
view as well as a more direct experience in meditation
of earth heaviness or lightness
hardness or softness smoothness or roughness of water
fluidity wetness or dryness the sense of motion
sense of capacity of motion malleability fire warmth and cool
the warmth of compassion the heat of determination the coolness
of equinimity and air
even more related to motion where breath becomes air internal and
external all of these qualities teach us our inseparability from nature
our fundamental belonging with everything
attuning to these can support insight into inconstancy ana
they can ground the meditation in broader and deeper connection with felt experience and cultivate more
malleability of mind fluidity of perceptions
these contemplations can support letting go of a flare of reactivity
and support a healthy warmth or coolness of the heart depending on the situation
it can open us to mindfulness of motion and
more ways of skillfully navigating more balanced to navigate the dooka
of life's storms and the eight worldly winds and finally
these practices can reveal inner spaciousness they can support an absence of fixated
self- concern and that's an absence into which an abundance of presence can flow
i'll close with another poem by Rosemary Watah Traor
it's entitled it's like this
it's like this the sun itself is constantly moving through space
wherever and whatever that is yet it never leaves us
add this to the list of marbles like how a glass of water was once a
cloud like how love can grow in us despite despair
despite fear given such gifts one must wonder how it
is our arms aren't constantly raised in spontaneous praise for life
i know and you know why sometimes our hands stay down
but now standing still together even as we're spinning and racing through space
even if it's only a whisper when faced with the truth that great forces hold
our lives in place it feels right to say "Thank you
thank you." Eyes lifting heart trembling
the improbable earth so solid beneath our feet
so thank you for your kind attention and thank you for your practice
i have two short announcements one is that if you would like to deepen
your practice and spend more time with myself or with other wonderful teachers
Gil Paul others um there are opportunities to be part of the Buddhist
chapency training either in person with him or online with me applications are
now open and there's also the opportunity to sit potentially a retreat with me upcoming
in August so both of those will be in the chat thank you it's been wonderful
to be with you this week