so welcome uh welcome folks um happy New Year to
you it's good to uh good to be together good to
practice so um one of the uh sa members
sent me sent me this uh yesterday uh from James Baldwin
um he wrote um if it hurts you that's not what's important everybody's
hurt what is important what Corrals you what bull whips you what drives you
torments you said you must find some way of using this to connect you with
everyone else alive this is all you have to do it with
you must understand that your pain is Trivial except in so far as you can use
it to connect with other people's pain and in so far as you can do that with
your pain you can be released from it and then hopefully it works the other way around
too in so far as I can tell you what it is to suffer perhaps I can help you to
suffer less then you make oh 15 years later several
thousand drinks later two or three divorces God knows how many broken
friendships and an exile of one kind or another some kind of
breakthrough which is your first articulation of who you are that is to say your first
articulation of who you suspect we all
are this is um what um the way our pain becomes
valuable more than trivial and pain is um sitting is not uh
merely about that but it is about that
so let us um let us sit and practice and uh feel our bodies
and find a way to uh our pain into
goodness for
and just know yourself as a
sensory system
what we call our life will only ever
be sensory
experience and so we breathe
relax so as to sense more of what's
here to begin saturating oh awareness with
uh sense
experience
e e
as you breathe see where your breath reaches and where it doesn't
without
straining see if you can breathe in a way that
unifies the whole field of your
body that doesn't privilege the front of your body over the back
or your torso over your
toes sensing the impact of your body breathing across
the whole
body
e e
perhaps you gently rest the inner
gaze one spot the blank uh mental
green our discurs of thinking usually needs a kind of
accompanying
imagery and sometimes our eyes [Music] move so we just rest in a kind of
simple relaxed way
so we breathe and feel our body unifying the field of
sensation
e
e e
whatever um pain might be in your
life where invited to to use that
connect us to
others to see it nature as not self
to depersonalize Sam
Sara
e e
we begin to articulate uh
who who Baldwin says you supect we all
are
and the compassion can get
very vast very
quickly and don't worry about the detail
tells how to implement this intention or that
intention the suspicion that uh compassion can't scale all the
way the sense of paralysis in the face
of the endlessness of of suffering don't let any of
that close your
heart can work out the details another time but right now
we honor what's
shared we use our pain to connect us
deeply to others
e
e e
it's almost like uh our our breathing conveys the
love to uh all the parts of our own
body radiating outwards
just the Deep honoring of the condition of sentience
that we can be at EAS and we can suffer
how completely this is shared across space and
time all beings it's always been like this
in that love uh fear and all the
rest sort of just
melts
e
e e
knowing how deeply Our Lives intertwine
I undertake the training precept to protect
life
e e
[Music]
e
okay so from uh from uh
tolto and AAR famous line all um all happy
families are alike but each unhappy family is unhappy
in its own way and in the Buddhist
tradition unhappiness maybe we say duk
suffering is charted quite meticulously the varieties of suffering
the three species of suffering
the um four types of of clinging the
hindrances the feathers the the the subtle Fe the OA cesas the subtle
feathers attachment to light a million ways to suffer the fever
dream of thirst that is gr and the the heart on fire of
hate the uh foggy bewildered
indecisiveness of delusion all these different ways of U
that we can suffer that we do
suffer But ultimately I I might might say it's the
reverse of Tolstoy suffering is suffering clinging is all
of the same piece it's the expression of
Freedom that is highly varied there's more you could say of our
personality in our freedom than there is in our
suffering your spontaneity and aliveness and and we could say
uniqueness is found not in your suffering but in your
freedom and everyone who suffers uh a lot reminds me of everyone
else who suffers but everyone who is
free they seem free in their own distinctive
way and my pain you know it almost feels like oh
that's my brand you know that's so intimately me it's not
self same old story actually locks up
our uniqueness Ben Lerner said uh nothing's
a cliche when you're living it nothing's a cliche when you're living
it and that says something important about suffering the kind of felt
distinctiveness of it part of what Baldwin was trying to explode in that
passage I shared but yeah the felt distinctiveness
of our suffering suffering feels so uniquely ours
so particular it could never be a cliche my heartache could never be a
cliche no no and we're so alone in it that's kind
of the Hallmark of suffering in a way is sense of disconnection the sense of the
absence of empathic connection with oneself and we're divorced from others
and divorced from the sense of the shared human predicament it feels unique our pain
feels unique but it's not there's more of our particularity in
our in our freedom than there is in are
suffering when I um when I meet people on the
path um you know in a retreat or talking
in some context I try to attune um to the particularity of their
heart the kind of shape of their heart mind and
uh you know was sort of yeah trying to use the Carl I think Carl Rogers
language to inhabit the world of the other as if it
were your own without losing the as if condition as if it were your own without
losing the as if condition and that empathic
Attunement sensing into the suffering it always maybe not always but
it almost always feels familiar kind of
familiar even if our lives have been very different even if one of our
experiences of suffering may be less intense more intense there's
some access some sense of uh sharing in
the pain it feels familiar but
um it's your freedom that I find startling and
novel and it's very lovely to
um follow along in the lives of practitioners and um witness the kind of
growing freedom to follow along maybe over period of many
years and it's uh lovely and inspiring
because I'm often detecting some flavor of freedom
in you that I don't have that feels new
novel to me and it's a delight to to become the
student you might not even know when it's happening for me but it
is there is this Noble truth about the cessation of suffering the complete
fading away and cessation of this craving to abandonment and
relinquishment getting free and becoming independent of of it
and we notice that the uh the budha speaks much more about what we're freed
from than how Freedom
manifests right the Buddha speaks much more about being freed from greed ha and delusion but what does that look like
would that be like a super chill unemotional person would
what what would that what would one's ethical life look like that's freed from
greet and delusion would they be awkward or funny
or what what what would you look like
freed some of these species of pain freed up of some of your
Neurosis we talk about no self and not uh but um other Traditions talk about
true self and I don't know if this is reasonable
but um maybe we can say that
um suffering involves the false self in some
way the alienation and
performative negotiation of a role the melodrama
of suffering me as the protagonist center of it
all the psychoanalyst um winot uh Associates the the true self
with the spontaneous
gesture and it's our spontaneous gesture that feels distinctive
that feels um uniquely ours everything else somehow feels like some weird dress
rehearsal our suffering feels um
performative and it's only in our freedom that we actually express ourself
at a deeper level a freedom in other words frees you
up to be yourself to express your particularity your aliveness the
spontaneousness spontaneity right and so as we become more free as
we begin to shed at least in moments some of the greed ha
delusion um our personality
uh is does not undergo some radical transformation but it's freed up of some
of its compulsivity the personality can
can be a kind of um yeah an appendage of the the Neurosis
it's like performative leakiness
and we start to let go and what's left in the let the kind of wake of letting
go is um is your own spontaneity your
particular goodness your quirkiness your
unselfconscious particularity and that
what's
distinctive the uh Buddhist
um teacher therapist um Bruce Tiff
um said something like um I treat every
patient as if they're already enlightened just pretending not to
be it's very um sort of touched by that
and reflecting on that treat all PE patients you know as if
they're already enlightened just pretending not to be you know and
um yeah how do we attune to the dimensions of freedom in
ourselves in others how do we actually sense the the particularity the
uniqueness of the other that is offered by the portal of their own
freedom and um and how do we as we practice as
we uh Grow Let Go how how is it that we
become more uh uniquely
ourselves so I offer this for your consideration and
uh please uh pick up whatever is useful
okay so thank you and
uh yeah welcome to uh 2025 happy to be living together with you
s um yeah may we uh may we be
well okay folks