So hello everyone and welcome
and here to the meditation that's uh
part of a longer series uh that sets the context for today and part of the more
recent context is a you want is a um
deeper engagement deeper reflection exploration deeper her uh uh
discovery of wise ways of practicing with suffering, with stress, with
destress, uh with the emotional tensions that we
carry through our days. And um
and there's a number of purposes for this. One is so that uh we can discover uh
profound satisfying healthy happiness
that um can be an alternative to suffering and also can be a partner to certain forms
of suffering that we have. Suffering is not a mistake to have to experience. Um,
there's all kinds of emotional pains that come with being human, but there's
also what we add. And it's the the what we add
unnecessarily that is a big part of what we're
uh kind of working with in Buddhism. So what I'd like to suggest that one of
the important areas of practice
is uh my the opportunities with mindfulness practice
is to be able to
um suffer without making anything of it.
to to feel our emotional distress, emotional pain, to feel our physical
pain, to feel the challenges we have. And of course, there are times we should
adjust and change and fix certain things. But when we come to meditation,
one of the great opportunities here is to discover a kind of freedom that comes
when we don't have to do anything about it. We can
just sit and not add any second arrows.
So the so just to sit
and not make anything up in relationship to the suffering to let it just be
suffering and not be for or against it not
interpret it not have an attitude even towards it that
it's undesirable or not try to protect it just a radical leaving it alone,
not making anything of it, not
imagining a future with it where it's going. Just radical simplicity.
Let it just be suffering and um just be sadness, just be
anger, just be disappointment, just be
hurt, just be. And one way that uh it's been meaningful
for me to think about this is that um when we're suffering,
be a suffering Buddha. When we're sad, be a sad Buddha.
when we're discouraged, be a discouraged Buddha.
And what that kind of language does, that kind of image does for me is it
allows me just to pull back. Let it be. Don't do anything with it. Don't see
anything as a problem. Don't see suffering as a problem. Don't even see suffering as an
opportunity to find happiness. Just let it be. Don't make anything up out of it.
So to assume a meditation posture
and if you've been meditating for some time
maybe you can feel the familiarity of the posture that you assume.
Maybe it's even a homecoming. Ah, here I am.
My body in a familiar posture of meditation.
Maybe the body now becoming the meditation center, the meditation
hall, the temple.
Feeling the familiarity, feeling the goodness.
And also feeling the tensions, the holding
the parts of the body that are activated with emotions, energy, tensions.
and to gently
breathe more fully and as a statement
as in kind of a claim to presence here Now
as you exhale
a relaxing that is a definitive
reminder statement act of being here No.
letting your breathing return to normal. And as you exhale,
relax, soften, put your body at ease.
As you exhale, to whatever degree you can,
set your mind at ease, easing up the tensions, the tightness.
The pressure in the mind.
As you exhale, ease up
in your heart area with your emotional feelings,
sensations.
Be easy
with how you're feeling emotionally.
easing up.
And then becoming aware of how the body, your body experiences
breathing, the movements of breathing.
The alternating sensations of breathing in and breathing out.
And then ease into your breathing almost like your awareness.
You can enter into the phys physicality of the body
breathing.
As you get to the end of the exhale,
let go. Settle in
for a moment. Let there be a grounding deep in your body at the end of the
exhale where you allow yourself to let go of
everything else, past and futures.
thoughts, beliefs.
Try to make anything happen except grounding deep in the body with the
exhale.
And the inhale arising from this grounding spot.
And if you find yourself thinking, take a moment
to see if you can recognize
that you don't need to be thinking what you're thinking
unless it's about the meditation on breathing itself in a simple way
remembering to do it.
Nothing else at this moment
requires thinking
When the mind thinks things, it's often making things up,
constructing ideas, stories, conversations,
judgments, commentary.
It's possible to feel the pressure to do this.
A kind of subtle pressure
of believing this is important to do.
A certain desire clinging
at the end of the exhale. Let it all go
and find a rest deep within in the body. The resting
spot, grounding spot.
A rest below the agitation of thinking.
And if you're thinking if you're if you're suffering
in any kind of way, distressed,
troubled, uncomfortable emotionally with anything.
Notice if that suffering
arises out of how you're thinking.
Notice how the suffering feels in your body.
Notice if your suffering affects how your breathing
and maybe the suffering is even very mild stress.
And as you know it, as you feel it,
leave it alone.
Not making anything up. Not building any conclusions.
Not adding the ideas, the judgments of thinking on
top of it without interpreting it. Just let it be.
Let let it leave it alone
with the exception of maybe breathing with it.
We're dropping down to the grounding spot deep within the breathing
below the suffering and radically
unconditionally leaving your suffering alone.
Nothing to do about it, nothing to fix,
no conclusions about oneself.
It can be so simple that all that's left of suffering
are the immediate sensations associated with it.
Thinking not needed.
And then
as we come to the end of this sitting,
what might you have learned? learned. What could you learn
here and now about leaving suffering alone?
Not making anything uh making making anything of it.
Not making up anything about it.
Suffering is suffering in and of itself. It's bad enough.
Don't add anything. Don't make anything of it.
And can you find in that simplicity, leaving it alone,
some freedom,
maybe breathing room with the suffering.
Maybe a sense of ease or peace
that's deeper within you or which surrounds everything.
can
not making up anything, not trying to do anything,
give you a sense of ease
that can exist. this together withever with whatever stress
duka that you have
and then holding this ease and unease together.
May we appreciate or understand
that others have duka, others have unease,
suffering, and they have the capacity
to have ease, to find freedom.
And may our own suffering help us to have a greater compassion,
patience, love
for others.
And may our own freedom from suffering, our own ease,
be the source of good will, well-wishing for those we're with.
May with whatever ease, well-being we have,
may we live with good will. May all beings
be happy. May all beings
be safe. May all beings be peaceful.
May all beings be free.
[Music]
Thank you.
So hello and welcome to this continuing series on insight
and for these days it's uh having insight having a deep understanding recognition
about uh suffering. A big word and uh sometimes alternative
word that I like is unease. And then when I was younger, I was aware
of some writers who wanted to uh translate it as disease with a hyphen
between the dis and the ease. that somehow there's a deep unease. And
the value the value of this emphasis on uneasiness is that uh it maybe a little bit easier
to understand the broad kind of um
u terrain broad range of what Buddhism refers to as duka. There can be an
uneasiness with just the mildest little thing and they can be quite big and
large. And um and so one of the really
important teachings that we teach and I taught about it yesterday
here at IMC and taught it here on YouTube is that um the idea of the two
arrows that uh if a person is uh injured by an
arrow that's shot at them that's painful. There's no
doubt about it. A second arrow is uh shot at the person, it's even more
painful. And the idea in from the Buddha about these arrow, the simile of the arrows is
that the first arrow uh is just what life
brings us. Uh we get sick, we get injured, we get
old, we we die. Uh there's loss. Uh, we break a cup,
falls on the floor, and it breaks. Uh, maybe we didn't even drop it. It was just somehow the the cat pushed it over
the edge of the table or or there's an earthquake and and um a precious
family heirloom falls and shatters. And there's all kinds of things. The first arrow is what life brings us. And
um and we have sometimes very little control over um these first arrows.
Maybe we try the best we can sometimes to prevent
the difficulties, challenges, things break, but um
the first arrow is just what comes and we're not responsible for it. And um and the second arrow is the one
that we add to the situation and that's when we make things up. We we
interpret it. We uh judge it. We
uh dream up scenarios of frightening futures about because of this this will
happen now and that'll be terrible. We uh cling to uh how we want things to
be or how they should be or how they shouldn't be. Um it's bad enough to have the cat knock
the precious teacup on the floor and um but don't make it worse.
uh the second arrows that we add. Uh we might not be happy with what's happening
on a the political level and uh maybe politicians are spreading fear and hate
and anger and then we get uh afra afraid and angry ourselves. And so in a certain
kind of way the first arrow is what the politicians do. The second error is what we add to it and add to it to the world
but also add it to ourselves. And in some ways it's very sad that um how much
added suffering we add to ourselves um when the first is bad enough
and uh when for example politicians are filled with as is commonly done to get
elected is to spread fear and anger uh and uh and then we do the same. We're
just adding to the accumulation of this kind of terrible kind of way, ugly kind
of way of being in the world. And uh we're not the solution. We're just making the problem worse and worse. And
so it's very hard to imagine leaving things alone. Like it's okay to do that. Not to add to
suffering, not to add second arrows. Of course, we have to do something. We have to fight the good cause.
Meditation is a very special place. It's a place where we step out of the ordinary world.
It's like kind of like the old days going to the library. And you go to the library and it's a quiet place. It's
kind of a sanctuary. It's kind of a peaceful place. People leave you leave you alone for the most part there.
People are quiet. Maybe some people are talking softly, but it's it's a kind of
its own unique place. and we go into the library and and we kind of participate
in the in the culture of the library. Meditation is like going to some place
like that where there's a different culture, there's a different understanding, different possibility.
And one of those is a place to learn not to fix things, not to judge things,
not to make up any stories about things, interpretations, not to live in the future and pasts
about things, not to uh tell stories about it.
And um and um but rather to leave things radically alone. Just let each thing be
itself. And what that means is we're not adding second arrows, third arrows, fourth
arrows. Uh and sometimes these arrows that we build uh we throw we we we are
second third arrows we're doing become the foundation stones for building
bigger and bigger um buildings of suffering, buildings of stories and
and interpretations of life and ourselves and our identity.
And when when uh our world, our self, our relationships to others built on all
these accumulated arrows that are that are landing on top of each other,
they're not very safe. They're not stable. Um they'll blow over, they'll
fall over. When they get tall enough, they will definitely collapse.
And um so uh so this idea of meditation
being its own domain to leave things alone. Just breathe with things. Just
know it. Know it. Don't construct it. Know it. Don't add
to it. Don't make it worse. and find some ease in the knowing of oh
wait there's stress there's pain there's unease here let's just know it in the
simplest possible way let's just feel it in the simplest possible way let's be
careful we don't add to it with stories don't make anything about make up anything about it don't make anything of
it and one of the fascinating things to discover from doing this or trying to do
it, doing it to some degree, even a m small degree is we at some point we
start recognizing um how the source of some of our
suffering, the immediate source, the kind of experiential source, the place where the
tension arises, the unease arises is not from the events in the world, but rather
from the way we think about it. So the cat knocks over the cup
and uh in and of itself that doesn't have to do anything in the mind. But then the mind immed immediately
uh narrows and focuses on oh that was a gift from my best friend and my best
friend will feel like I've you know will be upset with me because that cup is now
broken and maybe my friend will think I was disrespectful and we'll think that
I'm a careless person and and we can and but if you're watching all this you can
feel how much suffering tension unease is it rising in the wake of these
thoughts that we have. And then at some point we can also see
that our unease is the very source for more of this kind of making up thoughts.
And at some point the unease the tension that we carry and within us becomes like
um the toothpaste without the lid toothpaste uh tube that
if we keep pressing it the toothpaste will just keep coming keep coming keep coming brushing it away but as long as
the tension is there the pressure is there it'll keep pouring out the the thinking will just keep pouring out
stories will keep make because of the tension we have here on the mind.
So to learn to leave things alone to leave our suffering alone is a
dramatic step of of uh learning a radical different way is not adding more
arrows. And even if you have 10 arrows being fired at once, rapid fired arrows,
we can learn not to do the 11th. Don't add one more.
Just let it be. And at some point in this practice of the dharma,
it's almost necessary to learn the art
to leave suffering alone. If we've have a whole series of madeup
suffering, madeup reactivity that we live under, um, at some point we need to
learn to stop at the 30th generation of arrows.
And this stopping means that at some point we have to be
willing to be at ease with suffering. At some point, we have to learn to just,
okay, now there's a different way. There's a different culture. There's now I'm in the library. And now, let me just
be here without making anything up with that, without talking loudly about it,
without yelling. Now, let let me learn how not to how to
suffer without adding an arrow.
Let me learn how to suffer without
having thoughts, ideas, reactions that just adds more and more.
And the marvelous thing that can happen is when we learn that stopping, learning to stop and just let suffering be very
simple, not making anything of it. Then the edifice of tension, the edifice
of all these arrows begins to collapse, begins to fall away, begins to relax.
But if we have think we always have to react, always have to do something with it, always make something of it, always
define ourselves, always see what our our problems as reflecting back on who
me who I am, then that just gets perpetuated more and more and more.
So whether it's the second generation, the hundth generation of arrows that
you've been slinging at yourself over a lifetime.
At some point, just stop.
Stop and look better. Stop and see more clearly
what is there. And one of the things to clearly see
is the stopping is the not adding and in doing that finding your ease.
Ease on the path to freedom. So thank you.